<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFD9A2B1AFFE546939A7ACEF3E1BC6557" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5227 IH: Chinese Electronics Defense Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5227</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the Department of Defense from acquiring computers or printers manufactured by or from entities controlled by the Government of the People’s Republic of China, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFDC7A45AB20A45AD8AEBFA0C9781CEC7" style="OLC"><section id="HE042936917824AAE9E177EAA3FA9CEDD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Chinese Electronics Defense Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H465EEC736B1F43788DE1ABB276BF5C2D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on computers or printers acquisitions involving entities owned or controlled by china</header><subsection id="H4266CD94EC304696B38BCE0D5956A04C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense may not acquire any computer or printer if the manufacturer, bidder, or offeror is a covered Chinese entity.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA31594C4A9FF45D4AB1C49E0F61839BB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>This section shall apply only with respect to contracts or other agreements entered into, renewed, or extended after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2D86D6D19174478E8FECE3E178E0A566"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB639A685CB3040D39BEF976BA9396862"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered Chinese entity</header><text>The term <term>covered Chinese entity</term> means an entity that the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Director of the National Intelligence or the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, determines to be an entity owned, controlled, directed, or subcontracted by, affiliated with, or otherwise connected to, the Government of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40EDE86E91834F2FBC47DC5D89FD5D52"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Manufacturer</header><text>The term <term>manufacturer</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H21962F23218D43698E24AD4ABAA339ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the entity that transforms raw materials, miscellaneous parts, or components into the end item;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8765C13B914484B84AB8FEABB0723DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any entity that subcontracts with the entity described in subparagraph (A) for the entity described in such subparagraph to transform raw materials, miscellaneous parts, or components into the end item;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15F0D6F058644D9FBC3D80A771181C18"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any entity that otherwise directs the entity described in subparagraph (A) to transform raw materials, miscellaneous parts, or components into the end item; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H210CEF11A6A342B887A752C106DF5FED"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any parent company, subsidiary, or affiliate of the entity described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

