<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCBE7E5AA8BBE4A908E4FAA512A1E2610" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4636 IH: Wireless Electric Vehicle Charging Grant Program Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4636</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230713">July 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Transportation to establish a Wireless Electric Vehicle Charging Grant Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA267A7D289A44C3C96A25BB8E8B80FBC" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H99D2A5B73CA5454A8D6F8F89D69F2515" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Wireless Electric Vehicle Charging Grant Program Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4B3506CAF2144AFD813E3F7143318327"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H663EA17C66A540449B083E4E05382B3D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Electric vehicles are crucial to cutting greenhouse gas emissions, reducing reliance on fossil fuels, strengthening United States economic and national security, and combating the climate crisis. As of 2019, the transportation sector accounts for 29 percent of all greenhouse gas emissions, which is the most of any sector.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1054E9C7C1EF458DB53D94810C83E524"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Increasing the adoption of electric vehicles will reduce pollution and increase air quality for communities located near roads with high traffic density or high-volume routes.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A5F21B91F754B69AF4F87F5A2C2FD59"><enum>(3)</enum><text>As the automotive industry shifts towards electric vehicles, investing in new electric vehicle technologies will be crucial to enhancing America’s competitiveness, creating jobs, and ensuring continued economic growth.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H65ECDDBD2885412BAD3F13EE62368C82"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Range anxiety is one of the chief barriers to electric vehicle adoption. If deployed strategically, wireless electric vehicle charging could help by providing drivers convenient opportunities to charge and extend the range of electric vehicles.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1F5F3F5D44FB45F8BAA857EE21E4954D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Wireless charging technologies could be invaluable for electric transit buses, trucking, fleet vehicles, and autonomous electric vehicles, allowing for convenient and hands-free charging, while also lowering costs, as effective wireless charging would reduce the need for larger and heavier batteries.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H26EA49BD4B3647BD8B5254F514E9A72E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Wireless and dynamic charging can also reduce pressure on the grid, allowing vehicles to charge through space and time, shaving peak demand and reducing the need to build massive charging capacity at any given location to meet growing electric vehicle charging demand.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA21DC3022CB4E5C89D1E1BABB5F2C65"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Wireless can enhance electrification of fleets, including medium and heavy-duty vehicles, helping them meet operational needs that cannot be met solely by traditional charging systems.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7BF8929EB44B44B999FFFB8257BD62CC"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Wireless electric vehicle charging has the potential to make electric vehicles more accessible and allow all people of the United States, regardless of physical ability, to enjoy the benefits of electric vehicles.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2993EA9A9E7B4E889303499B0E90C101"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is critical to establish a resilient and robust domestic supply chain for all electric vehicle charging infrastructure. With strong Buy America requirements, federally funded programs can incentivize companies to build facilities in the United States, creating good paying jobs and economic growth for communities.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H09AC2F078B9540758FD675537D9BC9E3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of Wireless Electric Vehicle Charging Grant Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation shall establish a program, in coordination with the Department of Energy, to award grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities for projects to construct, install, or improve existing wireless charging infrastructure and technology for electric vehicles, including performance, safety, electromagnetic compatibility, interoperability, development, and testing of wireless charging. The program shall be known as the Wireless Electric Vehicle Charging Grant Program (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>).</text></section> 
<section id="H4479D1998FE7459DA66F4A79011158DC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duties of Secretary</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In carrying out the Program, the Secretary—</text> <paragraph id="H9E7B865F2F2A4C41BFCA8D08D6F73905"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may award grants for projects described in section 3, including for wireless charging located along roads, in parking lots, airports, and at coastal and inland ports;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H33F11F7D6DC4438FA436CD1BEAEDA3E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall ensure that recipients of the grants focus on the wireless charging of 1 or more of—</text> <subparagraph id="H811D8D95633F4E8297F32DB14A058AF0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>light-, medium-, and heavy-duty vehicles;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB74B1DCD040A4BAFAA5B2D7534E7377C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fleet vehicles, including the Federal vehicle fleets; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H288923B8F55740ADBD1E2172E6613A9A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>public transit;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2EAD60F462394EE89078694F8BFF533B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall publish an annual progress report to the relevant committees of the House of Representatives and the Senate that includes—</text> <subparagraph id="H6C399A022A9F4CD6A080DDE70ABBB693"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of recipients of grants, amount disbursed, and reasons for the selection of projects;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDB45A54649754698B21171E120E3FD6C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the progress of each pilot project funded under the Program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H35C2A13F4D75421ABB3827D887C434C0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>successes, failures, and safety of the technologies funded under the Program;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H50C29AA7F0B54034A74A881EDB5F7DDF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommendations for future funding, best practices, and policies relating to wireless electric vehicle charging;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD4FEA6DF4CDD46A1850C1D95C9D54385"><enum>(E)</enum><text>workforce impacts of each project;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H456D28CFC10D433D89E9820789FEB7CD"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> the environmental impact of each project, such as the amount of fuel saved from the project, predicted emissions savings, changes in air quality, and any other environmental information deemed necessary by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA165BE5A3A8D47F6AB85E900D66C94EF"><enum>(G)</enum><text>any other information the Secretary considers necessary; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED7F201AA4964C7CB5AECB4ED469A116"><enum>(4)</enum><text>may provide technical assistance, as determined appropriate by the Secretary to eligible entities with respect to activities described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H6B1DC52940C74FC1A15F1527D5D6FC06"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grant recipients</header> <subsection id="HAFC4BF1C2AB04A7C8E2D0EB18E94C3E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible for a grant or technical assistance under the Program, an entity shall be, or be partnered with, any of the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H39C164BC8DE747A9B9391FC388A45AFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State, local, Tribal, or territorial government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4DA0061B5A944C9B896AF570C1A54B21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A Metropolitan Planning Organization.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8C6094E4CC4A40A2A0DAF969751F6E73"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A special purpose district or public authority with a transportation function.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8EE9AE610C1D4FB5AC02ED0CD7FEECE0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A transit agency.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9E324E1334ED44F6AFA285CA9B18515E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Geographic diversity</header><text>In selecting eligible entities to receive grants under the Program, the Secretary shall prioritize geographical diversity.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE9F80D8111424186A1DD7D702661760D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional grant amounts</header><text>An eligible entity may receive a grant from a State, local, Tribal, or territorial government to carry out similar activities as the activities funded under the Program. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBE41F2B8F5994FF0A38CFC5935E48988"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Workforce development and training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligible entities may use a portion of their grant to cover costs associated with training workers to construct, install, maintain, or operate the projects.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF8C6BAF6EC9441A7801803D0823757DB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Community engagement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligible entities may use a portion of their grant to cover costs associated with engaging the communities and affected workers, such as drivers, on the planning and design of the project and educating the public on the project.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD57CB4326AEA4B849837AEB34F92A506"><enum>6.</enum><header>Cost share</header> 
<subsection id="H79FA8C03B7E649AAA9E8A8AC5EFB7E87"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal share of a grant awarded under the Program may not exceed 80 percent of total cost of the project.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB8E424C288ED4A409B5C628947495D21"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Maximum grant amount</header><text>The amount of a grant awarded to an eligible entity under the Program may not exceed $25,000,000.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HA8DEBF2E02E747DC913E0C3774315380"><enum>7.</enum><header>Program requirements</header> 
<subsection id="HA829CD2AA6434CA588E1F92DA0390296"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding the grants under the Program, the Secretary shall prioritize projects that—</text> <paragraph id="H132A30AADB1B405DA835A7DD751EBB78"><enum>(1)</enum><text>focus on non-disruptive designs that are compatible with existing infrastructure and beneficial to the public, including for low income, underserved, or disadvantaged communities;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5BAFB4C32B06456AB913628A553C029D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>focus on cost-effective, energy-efficient, and environmentally sustainable technologies for public use;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF9CE32A530344C997261D0FB99A189F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">focus on compatibility with the entire range of electric vehicles and with, if determined appropriate by the Secretary, developing and evolving universal wireless charging standards;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H226DD0487BE84B3DA5D4B22AA3EE28DC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>focus on safe designs that are compatible with frequent use in a variety of weather conditions and road maintenance activities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H96342C0E5CA1470A949BDD4DE2572AB8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>are carried out by entities that emphasize diversity, equity, and inclusion in the eligible entity’s workforce and business practices;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD92B4A43FE9D4CFF9B920FD6A5A04F9E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are likely to leverage Federal investment by encouraging non-Federal contributions to the project, including projects from public-private partnerships; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21D5862AD2B34E95886104943CE7F7EE"><enum>(7)</enum><text>have State, local, Tribal, or territorial government support;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H288FF5AFC2524A28B7BD4C90E6F7CAE9"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have an outreach strategy to inform and educate the public on project benefits and uses before, during, and after the construction of the projects;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB3105A6C7350450EA257F0809F43BB51"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have an inclusive plan to engage and ensure that the surrounding communities and impacted workers, such as the drivers of the vehicles, are included in the planning and design process;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H04622E22E7FB4769A3949C10E726E829"><enum>(10)</enum><text>focus on interoperability development and testing;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HADE8458DA260472F92AC110151467093"><enum>(11)</enum><text>focus on fleets, including medium and heavy-duty vehicles, which through transitioning to electric can have a significant impact on reducing fuel consumption and CO2 emissions; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H826A14DB48FA41B6973B1BB5CEA2010F"><enum>(12)</enum><text>help improve the life of the vehicle’s battery.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H79CBB3873EE241BE94C01C1B5B0F9638"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Wage rate requirement</header><text>The Secretary shall require that each recipient of a grant under the Program provides reasonable assurances that all laborers and mechanics employed to carry out the projects for which the assistance is provided, including laborers and mechanics employed by contractors or subcontractors, will be paid wages at rates not less than those for similar work in the locality as determined by the Secretary of Labor in accordance with subchapter IV of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Davis-Bacon Act</quote>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7DCAB73036E9499ABD4EC42C38DFFC4D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Neutrality toward organized labor</header><text>The recipient of grants under the Program shall have, and ensure that all employed by contractors and subcontractors of the covered entity with respect to the covered activities have—</text> <paragraph id="H3012F7D87C9A435CAAD6FAF87AF43793"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an explicit policy of neutrality with regard to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4D8CC00F1D7D4D2EBEC1FAA37B581CE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>labor organizing for the employees engaged in the covered activities; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC790F244A04E40C598886C6C6521BA29"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such employees’ choice to form and join labor organizations; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4B17294D27CF4239B170987BC261627A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>policies that require—</text> <subparagraph id="HD589C90238334A0296E45D784B7ACF5E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the posting and maintenance of notices in the workplace to such employees of their rights under the National Labor Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/151">29 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE3FEA7A7567045D3B24ED4BEECE73972"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that such employees are, at the beginning of their employment, provided notice and information regarding the employees’ rights under such Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAC433FD830954923A71029B12AD4B587"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Buy America</header> <paragraph id="H056DD98DA5A547418B0EBE368AFAF6FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), recipients of grants under the Program shall comply with the requirements described in section 5323(j) of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H411B568882ED4B4887CAA73FE6791B7E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may provide any waiver to the requirements described in paragraph (1) in the same manner and to the same extent as the Secretary of Transportation may provide a waiver under section 5323(j)(2) of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H319DE0587AE1440BB512BCBF894CF96C"><enum>8.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H0F07B82933FD4858A537215EF14C7C21"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Electric vehicle</header><text>The term <quote>electric vehicle</quote> means a zero-emission vehicle powered by an electric battery and train.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB22FF4D9CA214F17AF24D790592FE7EF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of title 23, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30CA9D8B3B664B0E8C7D3B3105A04902"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Wireless charging</header><text>The term <quote>wireless charging</quote> means the charging of a battery by inductive charging or by any means in which a battery is charged without a wire, or plug-in wire, connecting the power source and battery.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HE07135CFDD574D15822B69DAF3EDF912"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated $250,000,000 to carry out this Act, to remain available until expended.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

