<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H50218479961F44D4841684B421C8BFD1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6298 IH: Stop Shackling and Detaining Pregnant Women Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6298</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231108">November 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To safeguard the humane treatment of pregnant women by ensuring the presumption of release and prohibiting shackling, restraining, and other inhumane treatment of pregnant detained noncitizens, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9F3BA6DC72B74474BD9B6B6611142CFF" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HD8C8AC59CD724483A8A29F7E3A03F970"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Shackling and Detaining Pregnant Women Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H531AB548EF324A09B556D4FF1E2629ED"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitation on detention of pregnant women and mothers of newborns</header><subsection id="H41EE9BCE7DAA4521AFB54E1228F26C75"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presumption of release</header><paragraph id="HB2C2D64EEEC04E75BDB11AA2A3C1AA2E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Secretary—</text><subparagraph id="H0220A45A0F6F46DEB6F3051E9EDAB551"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall not detain an individual under any provision of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>) who is known to be pregnant, lactating, or postpartum, pending a decision with respect to whether the individual is to be removed from the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09FDD51252954917863B5011AD6F0E20"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall immediately release any detained noncitizen found to be pregnant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A880297B5184BA0A0043BAE4B387D3E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>The Secretary may detain pursuant to the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>) an individual who is known to be pregnant, lactating, or postpartum—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE0F4FEC9F274BF3BED3FC01FF7EC075"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">under extraordinary circumstances in which the Secretary makes an individualized determination that credible, reasonable grounds exist to believe that the individual presents an immediate and serious threat of hurting themselves or others; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2D114CB8CC564717AB40161B06744F2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such detention is the least restrictive means available to mitigate such threat.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2D96AFCCC2B478DA2192D9DE64CF91F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Removal</header><text>In a case in which detention is the least restrictive means of effectuating the removal from the United States of a pregnant individual subject to a final order of deportation or removal, the Secretary may, solely for the purpose of such deportation or removal, detain the pregnant individual for a period that is—</text><subparagraph id="HADECC28CA7EB4A80845DA8A1EF42CD30"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the shortest possible period immediately preceding the deportation or removal of the individual from the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H529C129B81854D608707CEB8AD0485DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not more than 5 days.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H741740194D3D402BAE9451073EA28EA5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Biweekly review required</header><paragraph id="HFEF14679850C49C0BFF12586903DBFD2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to a noncitizen detained under paragraph (2) of subsection (a), not less frequently than every 14 days, the Secretary shall conduct an individualized review to determine whether the detained noncitizen continues to be subject to detention under that paragraph.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3730E1FC17AE4296A2DD3EE9C5948C7C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Release</header><text>In the case of a determination under paragraph (1) that a pregnant noncitizen is no longer subject to detention under subsection (a)(2), not later than 24 hours after the Secretary makes the determination, the Secretary shall release the noncitizen.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA63234EFD11B42AE9CFF73CAA1D8DDC0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Humane treatment of pregnant detained noncitizens while in detention and custody</header><subsection id="H079008AD0020451DBD3C8316C329A7E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on restraint of pregnant detained noncitizens</header><paragraph id="H8E77684F61EB414892769F794B4574F0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), restraints shall not be used on a noncitizen in the physical custody of the Department of Homeland Security who is known to be—</text><subparagraph id="H12BB8B3204834392A2123402359FEFB5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>pregnant, including during—</text><clause id="H12510CE911CC488FA337613641807D50"><enum>(i)</enum><text>labor;</text></clause><clause id="HD9FE75D0E64B42C1B969EC375E314CC5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>transport to a medical facility or birthing center; or</text></clause><clause id="H79923D860BB44BEAB6E34D06C0289243"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>delivery;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6E623B8D01D49F59853B5C9AE39EAF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>lactating; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EC0689AD4624E5FAB4A55BDE436D2A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>postpartum.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE244A27E841450F8EDC320C9DC94B13"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><subparagraph id="H74E91BA343D1476887AA70756444D466"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), subject to subparagraph (B), use of a restraint on a detained noncitizen described in paragraph (1) may be permitted only in an extraordinary circumstance, except in the case of a medical contraindication, in which the facility administrator has ordered the use of the restraint after making an individualized determination that—</text><clause id="H29518929E43C464880E31509E6FA4E4B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>credible, reasonable grounds exist to believe the detained noncitizen presents an immediate and serious threat of hurting themselves, staff, or others; or</text></clause><clause id="HA86E3D1E6BBC4EBB981ACE4C67981B2A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reasonable grounds exist to believe the detained noncitizen presents an immediate and credible risk of escape that cannot be reasonably minimized through any other method.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79E6E77754614BAF92C3F4C8BAEE226D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement for least restrictive restraints</header><text>In the rare event of an extraordinary circumstance described in subparagraph (A), only the least restrictive restraint necessary shall be used, except that—</text><clause id="H39B557BC09074808965374DFCBDBC3A4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>if a doctor, nurse, or other health professional treating a detained noncitizen requests that a restraint not be used, the detention officer accompanying the detained noncitizen shall immediately remove any restraint; and</text></clause><clause id="H099F08C52DE7470EAA61374C026767C3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>under no circumstance shall—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA98AB34B1CE41D599EDFE96800C0F07"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a leg, waist, or 4-point restraint be used;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB27B743FFBBD4F5AAC15AD274072E6CA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a wrist restraint be used to bind the hands of such a detained noncitizen behind the back of the detained noncitizen or to another individual; </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE19691B6135A4EF89C76AFFC960BBED0"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a detained noncitizen be restrained in a face-down position or on their back; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H26D464738FB24902929F62FCBB8A93B0"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>any restraint be used on any detained noncitizen who is in labor or delivering.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9D9070636BC4AAFAD42B4BE55D248C0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Record of extraordinary circumstances</header><subparagraph id="HE20EDE540A4B4DC6A8022358E13F3067"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>If a restraint is used on a detained noncitizen pursuant to paragraph (2)(A), not later than 5 days after the date on which the restraint was used, the facility administrator shall—</text><clause id="HBF6A730766724707957154C5EA9CAB48"><enum>(i)</enum><text>record in writing the finding that describes the medical purpose or extraordinary circumstance that dictated the use of the restraint; and</text></clause><clause id="H42AD226B859142229C17CF9781B80C0D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>submit the finding to the Director.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CBB907729AE400098CA7F58433B5EF3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Retention</header><clause id="HEE4F92C7984F4028B65C7A8BF2BE808A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Facility</header><text>With respect to a written finding under subparagraph (A)(i), the facility administrator shall—</text><subclause id="H9926A7E44BD640F7B0053A481B507815"><enum>(I)</enum><text>keep the finding on file at the applicable facility for not less than 5 years after the date on which the restraint was used; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0F881A43AE634DC19946915528E1FCF2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>make a copy of the finding available for public inspection on request, only after making appropriate redactions so as to protect personally identifiable information.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE3342A622FFD44D0B79B49C2832D1029"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Immigration and Customs Enforcement</header><text>With respect to a written finding submitted to the Director under subparagraph (A)(ii), the Director shall maintain the written finding and make the finding available for public inspection only after making appropriate redactions so as to protect personally identifiable information.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD092B795A304C928F3F631931B1FE72"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on presence of nonmedical staff</header><paragraph id="H9F32A3C95947491EB7914D3160355E71"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), nonmedical staff shall not be present in the room during a pelvic exam, labor, delivery, or treatment of any other symptom relating to a pregnancy of a detained noncitizen, unless specifically requested by medical personnel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA169F8B3A6884AD7968C7D60FE59E4F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>If the presence of nonmedical staff is requested by medical personnel, the nonmedical staff shall—</text><subparagraph id="HCFCBD5B28114419C877A7A6FD8F403AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be of the detained noncitizen’s gender of choice, if practicable; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43BFC485D71B44F6B37C6E601D8C0B14"><enum>(B)</enum><text>remain at a reasonable distance from the detained noncitizen and face toward the detained noncitizen’s head to protect the privacy of the detained noncitizen.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2219786FF024B9B92789009100D5E75"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of restraints</header><text>If a restraint is used on a detained noncitizen pursuant to subsection (a)(2)(A), an employee of the Department of Homeland Security shall remain immediately outside the room at all times so that the employee may promptly remove the restraint if requested by medical personnel, as required by subsection (a)(2)(B)(i).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEC641491FBEA49A696128E1A7144B632"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Access to services</header><paragraph id="H4F2F51AF2AC2401698C48C06F3ACF627" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement custody</header><text>A pregnant detained noncitizen in the custody of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement shall have access to health care services, including comprehensive services relating to reproductive health care and pregnancy, including—</text><subparagraph id="H758155D0B84B4A1C836EE51C3170190C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>routine or specialized prenatal care;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A4D1A879C184471AE5AA0DAF406C11A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>comprehensive counseling and assistance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E0D32A2844B44DD9780ACC4D007387F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>postpartum physical and mental health care, including substance use disorder treatment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E3B325EFDF34566B7E09751C0291658" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>lactation services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H925EDBD6CA4C44EE870EF170B06F2459" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>abortion services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8543D1CB4AC457194C279E25796D8B4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>U.S. Customs and Border Protection custody</header><text>The Commissioner shall ensure that minimum standards of care are met for pregnant detained noncitizens in the custody of U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0BD6BE577ADD4807B20CD1B1ECD4FF46"><enum>4.</enum><header>Notice of rights and training</header><subsection id="H66E33607065A47DC86F8C5421FC9388F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notice of detained noncitizen rights</header><text>The Secretary shall provide to each detained noncitizen, in the detained noncitizen’s native language, notice of the detained noncitizen’s rights under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H04E3226323B94E4481C082116E61EAFE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Training for DHS employees</header><text>At the time of hiring, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall provide training on the requirements of this Act to each employee of the Department of Homeland Security who has a role in the detention or care of a pregnant detained noncitizen or a postpartum parent of a newborn detained under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="HB13516FED7094513A70389729C06C6E6"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reporting; rulemaking</header><subsection id="HB97E24AC56BE48A49D4BFC3A4E74E855"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H22515A7A42BB4BECBA840267E2E10A71"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports by facility administrators</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the end of each quarter fiscal year, the facility administrator of each facility that detained a pregnant noncitizen during the quarter shall submit to the Secretary a written report that includes, with respect to the facility during the quarter, the following:</text><subparagraph id="H47603ED90240458A89D22717686A9B2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An account of every instance of the use of a restraint on a pregnant detained noncitizen during pregnancy, labor, or postpartum recovery, including the type of restraint, the justification for the use of such restraint, and the name of the facility administrator who made the individualized determination under section 3(a)(2)(A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC79ADBE1B82C4B10B6EDB0DD2EFCDB1E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The number of pregnant noncitizens held at the facility.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H781EFFD0B9BD4319A88389EF14FDD256"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The average length of detention of pregnant noncitizens.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13DC2CF741E746CE9C694B045FC42A9D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The number of pregnant noncitizens detained longer than 15 days.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA50D408690CF46AEB2FB0B1A00304D3F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The number of pregnant noncitizens detained longer than 30 days.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4D09A64F26684572A44184555EC51A2B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The number of pregnant noncitizens who gave birth while detained, and a description of the outcomes of such pregnancies, including any pregnancy that resulted in a live birth, stillbirth, miscarriage, abortion, ectopic pregnancy, maternal death, neonatal death, or preterm birth.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC49574C4F30F4219BD3D29249A9F7DC6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Audit and reports by Secretary</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the end of each fiscal year, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H52D48410883B4BF8A7DCD254E34A5629"><enum>(A)</enum><text>complete an audit of the information submitted under subparagraphs (B) through (E) of paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E39B880313E414A810A3C5ECFA6BCE1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report that includes all information submitted under paragraph (1), disaggregated by facility; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6E18DDA9D3D47A4893E0E95FF74E50F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>issue regulations in accordance with national standards regarding minimum standards facilities should provide.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9579F713E2594C53BA26EAD83AAF75BB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Privacy</header><text>A report submitted under this subsection shall not contain the individually identifying information of any detained noncitizen.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46352402A780423CA294D574CE03527D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public inspection</header><subparagraph id="HA0CB10B2A82E4037B4810D183917C5E9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), a report submitted under this subsection shall be made available for public inspection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B8B901D090F46FF88DDD1E0EC796831"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Facility administrator</header><text>A report submitted under this subsection that is made available for public inspection shall not contain the name of the facility administrator otherwise included under paragraph (1)(A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAA28970D374C4DF39CA9EEE4893E63B5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>The Secretary shall adopt regulations or policies to carry out this Act at each facility.</text></subsection></section><section id="H9A19FA9A83F74427900DBE238142A17C"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H953FDEF13EC9461EA7D93BAF57240180"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of congress</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H80F4626AA7B943B1ABE4F0E2CC8DC09E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55A382A6319B4F7BA4F52009AC980F5B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A66DD0F158F4C39ABDE9E1EAE38D0AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commissioner</header><text>The term <term>Commissioner</term> means the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2A20FFD2E8A4F488E4B261F0E1533E7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Detained noncitizen</header><text>The term <term>detained noncitizen</term> includes any adult or juvenile individual detained by any Federal, State, or local law enforcement agency (including under contract or agreement with such agency) under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H392381B66FFE4DECBEAD4DADA0311970"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Detention officer</header><text>The term <term>detention officer</term> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H983C48B5B101417EA7C79B7F05FBD967"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">works at a facility, including an individual who works at a facility pursuant to a contract or subcontract; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H032AAB03FB83402DA96C252D9B711211"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">performs duties relating to the security, custody, or transport of individuals in custody.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E28F941FE4C472CA9A58B96D796EB22"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD696D2DA9ACB4970AE0EBC929442F695"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Facility</header><text>The term <term>facility</term> means a Federal, State, or local government facility, or a privately owned and operated facility, that is used, in whole or in part, to hold individuals under the authority of the Secretary of Homeland Security, including a facility that—</text><subparagraph id="HB232E9019AC34C6D8D72D8FF05F44868"><enum>(A)</enum><text>holds such individuals under a contract or agreement with the Director or the Commissioner; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA5F618682004A7E9CFEBC6CEA0A6336"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is used, in whole or in part, to hold individuals pursuant to an immigration detainer or similar request.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H684DB2AC1CEC43058536CDED2AF9B59A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Facility administrator</header><text>The term <term>facility administrator</term> means the official responsible for oversight of a facility, or the designee of such official.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7316DB6AB9754832805C2908554DFDDE"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Postpartum</header><text>The term <term>postpartum</term> means the 1-year period, or longer, as determined by the licensed health care provider of the individual concerned, following delivery, including the entire period during which the individual is in a medical facility, birthing center, or infirmary after birth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDACEB6C9BCD64C72A058F2F60593C9AE"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Restraint</header><text>The term <term>restraint</term>—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDD3609C14DE94CFF92E36A260766A31C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means any physical restraint or mechanical device used to control the movement of the body or limbs of a detained noncitizen’s body, including—</text><clause id="H460EA1F647264130BF43F075BFEA9C36"><enum>(i)</enum><text>flex cuffs;</text></clause><clause id="H88FD550D7165493EB9D801F6D6BC0C12"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>soft restraints;</text></clause><clause id="H8FB068D71631476EBEF919F93916FE9C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>hard metal handcuffs;</text></clause><clause id="H6E32812551C445E4B8B4DA42FCEAC82E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a black box;</text></clause><clause id="H6AAD921BF3BF446B888D1889680DCD24"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Chubb cuffs;</text></clause><clause id="H6F9535F8C6ED45C8B01A93863B56AA9A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>leg irons;</text></clause><clause id="H32580A00AFB345BE8A6063A1D66B9578"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>belly chains;</text></clause><clause id="H7C3413170ED2427AA600B29A14C30C26"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>a security (tether) chain;</text></clause><clause id="H0E7C232744084AC99903FFE5988A7B26"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>a convex shield; and</text></clause><clause id="H17F294D1975A4B08B945D01DFE2F6B9B"><enum>(x)</enum><text>any other type of shackles; and </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCA36FBF13BC941D290EA39A1483C7909"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include medical restraints.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H82CCF1E84A52406EB50C819C84FE3EDC"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

