<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H64701B2D7E5C4EB491D52F3285B84FC0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6248 IH: Think Differently Transportation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6248</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231106">November 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. Gonz&#225;lez-Col&#243;n</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require Amtrak to report to Congress information on Amtrak compliance with the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 with respect to trains and stations.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2724A237E0B343D5BBE4DEEB3F1A9085" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0173C67919F14264A11C0E033606C679" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Think Differently Transportation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA4E1871CBC5D41799254A9EF499A68D9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on Amtrak ADA compliance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 24315(b)(1) of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H50C6A5D43DE6475BB310E03CA540CCBA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B) by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H533BA1F9520B4C2BBB4E053CD8BD1E8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C) by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H24FAAB467D9D45978295B2BB3CD6F91C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEF89D82546AF45E685EDCF4874109608" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="HF59D90C4BC11468AA980C95071766E3D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall include an action plan for bringing Amtrak rail cars and Amtrak-served stations that are not in compliance with the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>) into compliance with such Act as required by the settlement agreement entered into in 2020 between Amtrak and the Department of Justice, as applicable; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB2F6C26CF4BB4D96AB3AE9943FB9A640"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall include a status report on—</text> <clause id="H3B3DE91D79184893924F614BD8D406E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Amtrak-served stations for which Amtrak is solely responsible for compliance with such Act based on an assessment carried out by Amtrak, including a timeline for any required compliance with such Act consistent with the terms of the agreement described in subparagraph (D); </text></clause> 
<clause id="H88F8353E5CC546C68C70A89D371B83A5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amtrak-served stations for which Amtrak has a shared responsibility for compliance with such Act based on an assessment carried out by Amtrak, including a timeline for any required compliance with such Act for the portions of the station for which Amtrak is the responsible party consistent with the terms of the agreement described in subparagraph (D), and who is responsible for compliance with such Act for the other portions of the Amtrak-served station where Amtrak is not the responsible party and the timeline for compliance where Amtrak is not the responsible party; and</text></clause> <clause id="H3987A1550A824DD797B2F235CFFDB86F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the status of compliance with such Act for all Amtrak-served stations for which Amtrak is not the responsible party, nor is responsible for a portion of the station, and the entity or entities that have responsibility for compliance with such Act, based on an assessment carried out by Amtrak.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

