<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFA4EB88DA0D9480FBD599580AE617A25" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5052 IH: Rural Outdoor Investment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5052</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 to provide grants for outdoor recreation projects to spur economic development, with a focus on rural communities, and to provide training for rural communities on funding opportunities for outdoor recreation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2DBF2C15C3214E3C9DD417164308D6F7" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H20F90A38BD89490985A3CD8F3D9B8DA1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Outdoor Investment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HBF8689FDC1C246848C3A12755041E64D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Outdoor recreation grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title II of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 is amended by inserting after section 207 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3147">42 U.S.C. 3147</external-xref>) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17E57EB563504F939C29446F6501FFA1">
<section id="HEBDCF91FB4004CAC811B7E519968B320"><enum>208.</enum><header>Outdoor recreation grants</header>
<subsection id="H6577C4109D3C493F93156A173446B2CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of outdoor recreation</header><text>In this section, the term <term>outdoor recreation</term> means all recreational activities undertaken for pleasure that—</text> <paragraph id="H3DC91B8CEDE64B1D9739BC1C69828627"><enum>(1)</enum><text>generally involve some level of intentional physical exertion; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDCA3A8BE0FDF48B9869E6CB59A404E0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>occur in nature-based environments outdoors. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4A609CC07E16407D8D43D52EE436AAB2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall make grants to eligible recipients for outdoor recreation projects to spur economic development, with a focus on rural communities.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HFBBF66DDFAA242C7ACD2A8FD999F3BA8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028—</text> <paragraph id="HF8D4C1B3504848C196F5ED45389E1771"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$30,000,000 for grants under section 201 for outdoor recreation projects to spur economic development, with a focus on rural communities;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9ED09E36B48645EC8BC4534DF6C2E3DF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$5,000,000 for grants under section 203 for outdoor recreation projects to spur economic development, with a focus on rural communities; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF4BD9A11386442FDAB68BD92A32A3514"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$2,500,000 for grants under section 207 for outdoor recreation projects to spur economic development, with a focus on rural communities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H654BD1B530A146B18B22CECCC6465F41"><enum>3.</enum><header>Training for rural funding opportunities for outdoor recreation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Beginning not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development, in consultation with the Administrator of the Small Business Administration and the Secretary of Agriculture, shall develop a partnership agreement—</text> <paragraph id="H2822AA0CBA824F2EAC16459142035654"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to provide for the development of—</text>
<subparagraph id="H474DF4B726214877A7C975BFAEC0EB97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>basic training, including in-person or modular training sessions, for small business concerns (as defined in section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>)) and rural communities relating to existing funding opportunities for outdoor recreation, including funding opportunities for—</text> <clause id="H9E8ABC3291FD48688C12DD3EB312487E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>business development;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD3CC029793E344DA9ABBE3BB67BD9CB7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>community planning; </text></clause> <clause id="H0D5CE143D9B84BD7B2039C8CDB8413D6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>infrastructure investment; </text></clause>
<clause id="H600DE583AE144E598DA3DBDB53515690"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>community capacity building; and</text></clause> <clause id="H10EA188488B34989BD73F3CD9811DC9D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>marketing and communications;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA4ADAC87701C4999A79A0A3F41EDDFC2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>informational materials relating to existing funding opportunities described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4550E757D6384E6A93EB1647D5C7EC2B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>opportunities to coordinate among Federal departments and agencies to share the basic training and informational materials developed under subparagraphs (A) and (B) with those departments and agencies and relevant nongovernmental organizations;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCCBCBE906B164CCE8E2AEBF06C88E8AB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to provide the basic training and informational materials developed under paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H08F7496E31244DB6BDE529546815DBCD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>through electronic formats, including internet-based webinars; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H77B969D4EC5E43EFB1A64C91706D482E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at physical locations, including offices of the rural development mission area; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H428FD19A2488463F981D70FC3F89E9F2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to make the basic training and informational materials developed under paragraph (1) available to rural business development entities that partner with programs of the rural development mission area, including institutions of higher education, nonprofit organizations, business incubators, and business accelerators.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HA8EF1429B2A74C70A4CAB43AFC56E1D2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Recreation economy for rural communities</header>
<subsection id="H72CCDBEF309247C295199F921A287998"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of program</header><text>In this section, the term <term>program</term> means the Recreation Economy for Rural Communities planning assistance program sponsored by the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Under Secretary for Rural Development, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCAE9DBD82D374CA4B8F849799B1A0EAC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text>To build on the program, the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Under Secretary for Rural Development, in partnership with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency and the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, shall develop partnerships to connect the program to—</text>
<paragraph id="HA1485CEC5997454CB4891390466895AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Economic Development Administration and the Small Business Administration; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H36F098DDBB7D4AEA824E40BAE160FD89"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the basic training and informational materials described in section 3.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HADD67742CD5D4726A962BE982D36EA41"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Under Secretary for Rural Development, in partnership with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency and the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, shall carry out a competitive grant program to assist entities otherwise eligible to receive assistance under the program in carrying out an action plan developed under the program.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6BBE70EB3654462AA758F5741EB364B3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation</header> <paragraph id="H163D2618EEAC4AF0AD38685C0676A1EF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On request of a regional commission described in paragraph (2), the entities carrying out the program shall consult with the requesting regional commission in carrying out the program. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCF44D01E04C7472795E667399BCD7E4E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regional commissions described</header><text>A regional commission referred to in paragraph (1) is any of the following: </text> <subparagraph id="HEB568F5549BF4C9D87BFF41C14DC93C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Appalachian Regional Commission established by section 14301(a) of title 40, United States Code.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H44A8D544BD8B4E28A712491A29405547"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Delta Regional Authority established under subtitle F of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2009aa">7 U.S.C. 2009aa et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA5425A5CA12E4122A681FFEC7537EC2F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Denali Commission established under the Denali Commission Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3121">42 U.S.C. 3121</external-xref> note; title III of division C of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/277">Public Law 105–277</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1FC4F2797CDB46FB932B3293C6539A4E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Northern Border Regional Commission established by section 15301(a)(3) of title 40, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H80531B37C87B4B08AA54C6981511F0B3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Northern Great Plains Regional Authority established under subtitle G of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2009bb">7 U.S.C. 2009bb et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H80F1B6671DF14C94AFC7898C2FF13AF1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Southeast Crescent Regional Commission established by section 15301(a)(1) of title 40, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7AC900736F92474AB3F3102D448A427F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Southwest Border Regional Commission established by section 15301(a)(2) of title 40, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6248DA2D099A42558D85E001D9873C4E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header>
<paragraph id="H3DF41983FA6949BAB52341F226DC7D4A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out the program $12,500,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD01860A3DAAA4121B0DC64CF38270B01"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>Beginning with fiscal year 2025, of the funds made available under paragraph (1) for each fiscal year, not less than 50 percent shall be used to carry out the grant program under subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

