<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H90E2976327314EAB8F98DFFFF31D657E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5512 RH: Russia and Belarus Financial Sanctions Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 255</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5512</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–316, Part I]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</cosponsor> and <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HBA00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on September 14, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require United States financial institutions to ensure entities and persons owned or controlled by the institution comply with financial sanctions on the Russian Federation and the Republic of Belarus to the same extent as the institution itself, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HBA00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H540F08CB72084C8AAC1041733DC10F52"><section id="H302717717EE74B6B80A915C2B9077CFA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Russia and Belarus Financial Sanctions Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBCC688BB480849FD8AB5782EB866DF9D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirements</header><subsection id="H552A4BBF47CC49C0817EBF2A36ED3F59"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A United States financial institution shall take all actions necessary and available to cause any entity or person owned or controlled by the institution to comply with any provision of law described in subsection (b) to the same extent as required of a United States financial institution.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBEA86187D0C843D4A697F150B0F426A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provision of law described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A provision of law described in this subsection is any prohibition or limitation described in a sanctions-related statute, regulation, or order applicable to a United States financial institution concerning the Russian Federation or the Republic of Belarus, involving—</text><paragraph id="HDCC11A32EB56421A8F3F2C1860EE2E76"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the conduct of transactions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H430A960985E4468B8103F4C60DEBF768"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the acceptance of deposits;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H320F8A48FB9147C2A962256836804213"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the making, granting, transferring, holding, or brokering of loans or credits;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E714AE0F38E4BDA95EA1C218E45797E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the purchasing or selling of foreign exchange, securities, commodity futures, or options;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E518F340078450390C76CC641934E09"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the procuring of purchasers and sellers described under paragraph (4) as principal or agent; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99D8B6BE687646F39E982F03B8006A2C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any other good or service provided by a United States financial institution.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0BC22787BE484C418A837B6324C5963D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>A United States financial institution that violates subsection (a) shall be subject to the penalties described in the applicable statute, regulation, or order applicable to a United States financial institution.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0CE46AC0A42B41A8AB93D4E4FF7CBE8D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>United States financial institution defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>United States financial institution</quote> means any U.S. entity (including its foreign branches) that is engaged in the business of accepting deposits, making, granting, transferring, holding, or brokering loans or credits, or purchasing or selling foreign exchange, securities, futures or options, or procuring purchasers and sellers thereof, as principal or agent. It includes depository institutions, banks, savings banks, money services businesses, operators of credit card systems, trust companies, insurance companies, securities brokers and dealers, futures and options brokers and dealers, forward contract and foreign exchange merchants, securities and commodities exchanges, clearing corporations, investment companies, employee benefit plans, dealers in precious metals, stones, or jewels, and U.S. holding companies, U.S. affiliates, or U.S. subsidiaries of any of the foregoing. This term includes those branches, offices, and agencies of foreign financial institutions that are located in the United States, but not such institutions’ foreign branches, offices, or agencies.</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HBA00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

