<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2DAA52BCD16A4D1A929956EAADED3D98" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5570 IH: United States Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5570</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230919">September 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish and implement a multi-year Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Strategy to reduce the negative environmental and social impacts of illicit gold mining in the Western Hemisphere, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFEA6AC731A8944C5A3343C6FAC8EB555" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H0DAC2897709E4CE88B3D61EE16B28202"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD578FF47020044DAB8CE47F04524EC8C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="HB6D5E39B84E34F0EACF71B0563176C6C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The illicit mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold in the Western Hemisphere—</text><subparagraph id="H09C3888C4CF640E49D0A37DC4B7D6910"><enum>(A)</enum><text>negatively affects the region’s economic and social dynamics;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF57B761C5AA04679836E204299AB9478"><enum>(B)</enum><text>strengthens transnational criminal organizations and other international illicit actors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31EFB993921947EFBAC0731D66969344"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perpetuates human rights abuses and land occupation against indigenous communities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29ED33FF8EE44FBEAF76F1AD35675109"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">can cause significant environmental destruction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F72575FC32C46DCB5BC40DFE0790A19"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A lack of economic opportunities, corruption, and the weak rule of law promote illicit activities, such as illicit gold mining, which increases the vulnerability of individuals in mining areas, including indigenous communities, who have been subjected to trafficking in persons, other human rights abuses, and population displacement in relation to mining activity, particularly in the artisanal and small-scale mining sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA770D4A5A994665848525EA7BB7D20E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Illicit gold mining in Latin America often involves and benefits transnational criminal organizations, drug trafficking organizations, terrorist groups, and other illegal armed groups that extort miners and enter into illicit partnerships with them in order to gain revenue from the illicit activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10EB485A57A248169B21BAF10BBA1EA3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Illicit gold supply chains are international in nature and frequently involve—</text><subparagraph id="H426B0501B8E341558466FD6207707535"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the smuggling of gold and supplies, such as mercury;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H775C9816F1C1488F87C711DA46ED83F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>trade-based money laundering; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A8CA8CD62774D2DB481AB2BDD8D6BF6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>other cross-border flows of illicit assets.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4C487680ADD43CCAAF7117CE86E50D6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In Latin America, mineral traders and exporters, local processors, and shell companies linked to transnational criminal networks and illegally armed groups all play a key role in the trafficking, laundering, and commercialization of illicit gold from the region.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA07F61065313424DBC94A7FD74166B7C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>According to a report on illegally mined Gold in Latin America by the Global Initiative Against Transnational Organized Crime—</text><subparagraph id="HC772D162CE9848B682B14CDEFE310838"><enum>(A)</enum><text>more than 70 percent of the gold mined in several Latin American countries, such as Colombia, Ecuador, and Peru, is mined through illicit means; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE57DABFD74042148CDC7AB806D4CD86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>about 80 percent of the gold mined in Venezuela is mined through illicit means and a large percentage of such gold is sold—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H71F1226998514A51B47ABC47AB787D29"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to Mibiturven, a joint venture operated by the Maduro regime composed of Minerven, a gold processor that has been designated by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury, pursuant to Executive Order 13850 (relating to blocking property of additional persons contributing to the situation in Venezuela), and Marilyns Proje Yatirim, S.A., a Turkish company; or</text></clause><clause id="H3F67CDDA994E44F09633815E3868B239"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>through other trafficking and commercialization networks from which the Maduro regime benefits financially.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0446738178D64C178D832C8B550A3BCB"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Illegal armed groups and foreign terrorist organizations, such as the Ejército de Liberación Nacional (National Liberation Army—ELN), work with transnational criminal organizations in Venezuela that participate in the illicit mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98DC6CF5AD404BBD87A1D491D2A1DCF1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Transnational criminal organizations based in Venezuela, such as El Tren de Aragua, have expanded their role in the illicit mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold to increase their criminal profits.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA55950DD7C5A4BB888D6445D9A9D2792"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Nicaragua’s gold exports during 2021 were valued at an estimated $989,000,000 in value, of which</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5C222BA57480439198EE4AEEE6BD84ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">gold valued at an estimated $898,000,000 was shipped to the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HACCD74A503FA4CA68C6E5928C7B3D9B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">gold valued at an estimated $48,700,000 was shipped to Switzerland;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE42BFC3B1CB541F48DC6893CEC5B3789"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">gold valued at an estimated $39,000,000 was shipped to the United Arab Emirates; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H93A35C81508446B68E6381FECC85AA41"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">gold valued at an estimated $3,620,000 was shipped to Austria.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HCDF7160F29084BF48F2ABC19E0F31647"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HA6F02277F4A24458AF8A99684E038CFC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4AF302579FB94B03AD29D309706B1546"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4F24911651A14D9CAF65E4F4B4FEE99C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</committee-name>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC796268FDE424B7FA32B758471CC31AF"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</committee-name></text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H62898FDE7EF74C25BA56C9777F636F23"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives</committee-name><committee-name committee-id="">.</committee-name></text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0AF053EECDE435DB388EAF5C0FF86BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Artisanal and small-scale mining; ASM</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>artisanal and small-scale mining</term> and <term>ASM</term> refer to a form of mining common in the developing world that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE71E0806579A4B2DA6C14BCB46B9BF7B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ranges from employing rudimentary, simple, and low-cost extractive technologies and manual labor-intensive techniques to being highly mechanized, using large earth-moving equipment and high through-put processing centers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H415875123DD34144984C886DC1E38B52"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is frequently subject to limited regulation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H729F9C31B91847CDBAB1917F8115B868"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">often features harsh and dangerous working conditions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE3319A251BEA44AA9B64BB01E2091420"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Illicit actors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>illicit actors</term> includes—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4514B8911E9D4A4B968491A9A8851A69"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any person included on any list of—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF96A74D227B348998A6984133260AEE7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">United States-designated foreign terrorist organizations;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7BC18E3CCF3A42E7B07FE7EB2A4DBE20"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specially designated global terrorists (as defined in section 594.310 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H18CE03B8E96648BBB992584A7AA5EE10"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">significant foreign narcotics traffickers (as defined in section 808 of the Foreign Narcotics Kingpin Designation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1907">21 U.S.C. 1907</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2045341373EC449B9C7112552D0BAC6B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">blocked persons, as maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B7B831EB7E746BD97A646F83640BA79"><enum>(B)</enum><text>drug trafficking organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA644793CAE4E446080EEAE35D532AC3C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Key stakeholders</header><text>The term <term>key stakeholders</term> means private sector organizations, industry representatives, and civil society groups that represent communities in areas affected by illicit mining and trafficking of gold, including indigenous groups, that are committed to the implementation of the Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Strategy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13BA73DA705D43D19F83D6FABE607DD8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Legal gold and mining partnership strategy; strategy</header><text>The terms <term>Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Strategy</term> and <term>Strategy</term> mean the strategy developed pursuant to section 4.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B56D3662A7B4B05A8E73C17F9045E3A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Relevant federal departments and agencies</header><text>The term <term>relevant Federal departments and agencies</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H1B362C46B755406CB34D04E1FD474E48"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Department of State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE061D652AF99441CBB96AF622D7B27A9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Department of the Treasury;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA32C86D241F84F9489D039B279A6131B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Department of Homeland Security, including U.S. Customs and Border Protection and U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21BDB810A45849E0AC9BE277C78F596A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Department of Justice, including the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Drug Enforcement Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B54E488974E48D3BD65BDBD209B7C9F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Department of the Interior;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47528A00173D40F68AF0422737F67AFF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the United States Agency for International Development; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AAF7EB828414575941896CDA6796318"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other Federal agencies designated by the President.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HCA6677F594804C4CAB3FED34B3063520"><enum>4.</enum><header>Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Strategy</header><subsection id="H230474EA9D4B4B82B83C10B22E790394"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Strategy required</header><text>The Secretary of State, in coordination with the heads of relevant Federal departments and agencies, shall develop a comprehensive, multi-year strategy, which shall be known as the Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Strategy (referred to in this section as the <quote>Strategy</quote>), to combat illicit gold mining in the Western Hemisphere.</text></subsection><subsection id="H542354FD197E4EC8B44095975DAEE802"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The Strategy shall include policies, programs, and initiatives—</text><paragraph id="H0186A0F6275A43F9A3FFF5F52F2A982E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to interrupt the linkages between ASM and illicit actors that profit from ASM in the Western Hemisphere;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC81A93E757ED4DA696EB4D228D31E76D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to deter ASM in protected indigenous land and environmentally protected areas, such as national parks and conservation zones, to prevent mining-related contamination of ancestral indigenous land and critical natural resources, such as water resources, soil, tropical forests, and other flora and fauna, and aerosol contamination linked to detrimental health impacts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9486B90EC79E4FC89FB7032E0F1621F9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to counter the financing and enrichment of actors involved in the illicit mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold, and the abetting of their activities by—</text><subparagraph id="HB91F9505E32745839CE47E39BE9559D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promoting the exercise of due diligence and the use of responsible sourcing methods in the purchase and trade of ASM;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D4AA9E5981E4BE290074531DA680346"><enum>(B)</enum><text>preventing and prohibiting foreign persons who control commodity trading chains linked to illicit actors from enjoying the benefits of access to the territory, markets or financial system of the United States, and halting any such ongoing activity by such foreign persons;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H550F855823DB47C88199475A18873A36"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">combating related impunity afforded to illicit actors by building the capacity of investigative and anti-corruption offices and addressing corruption in government institutions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9759C4C7882487CA4B86A2598721C4B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>supporting the capacity of financial intelligence units, customs agencies, and other government institutions focused on anti-money laundering initiatives and combating the financing of criminal activities and terrorism to exercise oversight consistent with the threats posed by illicit gold mining;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1442C03770CE4DADA1B81A7589F4F626"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to build the capacity of foreign civilian law enforcement institutions in the Western Hemisphere to effectively counter—</text><subparagraph id="HCD1FB159D6A54496BF3546C142B9E669"><enum>(A)</enum><text>linkages between illicit gold mining, illicit actors, money laundering, and other financial crimes, including trade-based money laundering;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4FEE65A375384BA9AFEFCD13DFA8C5EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>linkages between illicit gold mining, illicit actors, trafficking in persons, and forced or coerced labor, including sex work and child labor;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E73010B63154A5B971F2B5535E35B6A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the cross-border trafficking of illicit gold, and the mercury, cyanide, explosives, and other hazardous materials used in illicit gold mining; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7950BBAA35B240C9B64B7DCEF67EF231"><enum>(D)</enum><text>surveillance and investigation of illicit and related activities that are related to or are indicators of illicit gold mining activities;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FB27BA74CE34C5F8F68B239DD92B333"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to ensure the successful implementation of the existing Memoranda of Understanding signed with the Governments of Peru and of Colombia in 2017 and 2018, respectively, to expand bilateral cooperation to combat illicit gold mining;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H323E94E4382842A0BED8FF7A76B068C7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to work with governments in the Western Hemisphere, bolster the effectiveness of anti-money laundering efforts to combat the financing of illicit actors in Latin America and the Caribbean and counter the laundering of proceeds related to illicit gold mining by—</text><subparagraph id="HA8D703F2B27A44B3B8484A99FC13C9B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>fostering international and regional cooperation and facilitating intelligence sharing, as appropriate, to identify and disrupt financial flows related to the illicit gold mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold and other minerals and illicit metals; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DAA80F6604A409392CCFE47C1FFFCC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>supporting the formulation of strategies to ensure the compliance of reporting institutions involved in the mining sector and to promote transparency in mining-sector transactions;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B6BCB730B7D4098A27D9E59EF5A9CD6"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to support foreign government efforts—</text><subparagraph id="HD2FBE4A6D98C4B668DF60A94FF124C02"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to increase regulations of the ASM sector;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DF0F18E19E14FC28E00285351DF68DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to facilitate licensing and formalization processes for ASM miners;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99825E61A34C4EB18EF2C37ACA116D86"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to create and implement environmental safeguards to reduce the negative environmental impact of mining on sensitive ecosystems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBB120AC83DC40C0BCDC7F8B885F1BA7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to develop mechanisms to support regulated artisanal mining as a job growth area;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H08AFFD89AC7E4D348B002E23B84E015E"><enum>(8)</enum><text>to engage the mining industry to encourage the building of technical expertise in best practices, environmental safeguards, and access to new technologies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68519251C36E4DF6A03127CF63C5CC41"><enum>(9)</enum><text>to support the establishment of gold commodity supply chain due diligence, responsible sourcing, tracing and tracking capacities, and standards-compliant commodity certification systems in countries in Latin America and the Caribbean, including efforts recommended in the OECD Due Diligence Guidance for Responsible Supply Chains of Minerals from Conflict-Affected and High Risk Areas, Third Edition (2016);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H961005485C2142878FF1407B5A6BCB31"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to engage with civil society, including the indigenous communities that are directly impacted, to reduce the negative environmental impacts of ASM, particularly—</text><subparagraph id="H778288A549084DA9AD3CE9F0FD8C1EA8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of mercury in preliminary refining and in extracting gold;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5239F5CDDA2948DD8A7A3695D09A5C12"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the destruction of tropical forests;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08720AEFEEDE4AF78DA294BDD43970B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the construction of illegal and unregulated dams and the resulting valley floods;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FC6EB151FE64C08AF2CF2F9DAD8C9DA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the pollution of water resources and soil; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H255FA1B5165D4B678952D2E802581C0F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the release of dust, which can contain toxic chemicals and heavy metals that can cause severe health problems;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2FA66EEF0614E9BBA14F9C1ACF670E9"><enum>(11)</enum><text>to aid and encourage ASM miners—</text><subparagraph id="H43144729D9594FAAA01A5A9A86E88C53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to formalize their business activities, including through skills training, technical and business assistance, and access to financing, loans, and credit;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A7907BD4ACB4A55BC37B6414991EEEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to utilize environmentally safe and sustainable mining practices, including by scaling up the use of mercury-free gold refining and extracting technologies, and mining methods and technologies that do not result in deforestation, forest destruction, air pollution, water and soil-contamination, and other negative environmental impacts associated with ASM;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC7AD826E74A48F3B29A50BA2C6E4974"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to reduce the costs associated with formalization and compliance with mining regulations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AFE4E337AD34A18B9AB04C3C8638F4E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to fully break away from the influence of illicit actors who leverage the control of territory and use violence to extort miners and push them into illicit arrangements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H534AF434841A43D1B585EBC0E72BF899"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to adopt and utilize environmentally safe and sustainable mining practices, including—</text><clause id="HBD056C8966C54A7096DF679F57897347"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">mercury-free gold refining and extracting technologies; and</text></clause><clause id="H803CAEE7F89547229888EB833946EE58"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>extractive techniques that do not result in—</text><subclause id="H4DA1E864736849C4AAAC6F69FC65BB29"><enum>(I)</enum><text>forest clearance and water contamination; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H82A9B2D9AEC246F7BA7AB1D26D049154"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the release of dust or uncontrolled tailings containing toxic chemicals;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C85E3B0823146E8BFE5FA7BB002F107"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to pursue alternative livelihoods outside the mining sector; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82091826ACD34DBCA2578D91BE273BBF"><enum>(G)</enum><text>to fully access public social services in ASM-dependent communities;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D0F3FC22FDC4FE288165F004B57321A"><enum>(12)</enum><text>to support and encourage socioeconomic development programs, law enforcement capacity-building programs, and support for relevant international initiatives, including by providing assistance to achieve such ends by implementing the Strategy;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67CFFB3EC2C2484AB322D26B2A0023C9"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to interrupt the illicit gold trade in Nicaragua, including through the use of United States punitive measures against the government led by President Daniel Ortega and Vice-President Rosario Murillo and their collaborators pursuant to Executive Order 14088 (relating to taking additional steps to address the national emergency with respect to the situation in Nicaragua), which was issued on October 24, 2022;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEC60BA056DC415880DEC26365E04A81"><enum>(14)</enum><text>to assist local journalists with investigations of illicit mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold and its supplies in the Western Hemisphere; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6078B9CC3CAE4A66AC3919722B407210"><enum>(15)</enum><text>to promote responsible sourcing and due diligence at all levels of gold supply chains.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEC3B2FB93F954247AE2EF68DEEBFF09A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Challenges assessed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Strategy shall include an assessment of the challenges posed by, and policy recommendations to address—</text><paragraph id="HAB0644048DE0447584AECCB2994D4324"><enum>(1)</enum><text>linkages between ASM sector production and trade, particularly relating to gold, to the activities of illicit actors, including linkages that help to finance or enrich such illicit actors or abet their activities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13C899CD4D2040B984C2694A2BC7EC6C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>linkages between illicit or grey market trade, and markets in gold and other metals or minerals and legal trade and commerce in such commodities, notably with respect to activities that abet the entry of such commodities into legal commerce, including—</text><subparagraph id="HE7EAB9B657FA4C14BD7343A6195D9D96"><enum>(A)</enum><text>illicit cross-border trafficking, including with respect to goods, persons and illegal narcotics;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8733656062A04FAA87753997FA4CFFB8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>money-laundering;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H764D1791F10746B99AD582D383518E2A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the financing of illicit actors or their activities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07EB15CA7F1745E6931E17EEDE96EA56"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the extralegal entry into the United States of—</text><clause id="H8D95E53E589146C4AB0AE2EF5BD7318E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>metals or minerals, whether of legal foreign origin or not; and</text></clause><clause id="H03F93BC19CC84BED86761C61870F4DE3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the proceeds of such metals or minerals;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BE30680C7564628AC00D7AFAFD30616"><enum>(3)</enum><text>linkages between the illicit mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold, diamonds, and precious metals and stones, and the financial and political activities of the regime of Nicolás Maduro of Venezuela;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACE354A7AC6340B8A2284C55066E7192"><enum>(4)</enum><text>factors that—</text><subparagraph id="H749B04E723824C92ACE7B816337E1FD8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>produce linkages between ASM miners and illicit actors, prompting some ASM miners to utilize mining practices that are environmentally damaging and unsustainable, notably mining or related ore processing practices that—</text><clause id="H0AC2354E218846A49B73AD259831B37C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>involve the use of elemental mercury; or</text></clause><clause id="HBECA7248D2DE4558A715A188510EA26C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>result in labor, health, environmental, and safety code infractions and workplace hazards; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7265F06E55C4E76BA2B4D626D9099A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>lead some ASM miners to operate in the extralegal or poorly regulated informal sector, and often prevent such miners from improving the socioeconomic status of themselves and their families and communities, or hinder their ability to formalize their operations, enhance their technical and business capacities, and access finance of fair market prices for their output;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F70EEB15D8F480F82703233B240870E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>mining-related trafficking in persons and forced or coerced labor, including sex work and child labor; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8828207BAA014EE9A13CC816C6134484"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the use of elemental mercury and cyanide in ASM operations, including the technical aims and scope of such usage and its impact on human health and the environment, including flora, fauna, water resources, soil, and air quality.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H27BFE1DF42D44836832EE600D06EA49A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Foreign assistance</header><text>The Strategy shall describe—</text><paragraph id="HFEBE182BA83E46F0BA7A1AF12E75238B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>existing foreign assistance programs that address elements of the Strategy; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DF853D9EED64EF496DA00D306895212"><enum>(2)</enum><text>additional foreign assistance resources needed to fully implement the Strategy.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H376D66AF2C7D4BFFA4A840D168613C27"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall submit the Strategy to the appropriate congressional committees.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3A1E4C54D6524630A8FBAEAF8A67EFAC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 180 days after submission of the Strategy, and semiannually thereafter for the following 3 years, the Secretary of State, or the Secretary’s designee, shall provide a briefing to the appropriate congressional committees regarding the implementation of the strategy, including efforts to leverage international support and develop a public-private partnership to build responsible gold value chains with other governments.</text></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H49D6E2C3D2434F2085395CC5D9D5620F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Classified briefing on illicit gold mining in Venezuela and Nicaragua</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, or the Secretary’s designee, in coordination with the Director of National Intelligence, shall provide a classified briefing to the appropriate congressional committees, the <committee-name committee-id="">Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate</committee-name>, and the <committee-name committee-id="">Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives</committee-name> that describes—</text><paragraph id="H7AEB35D58D2B436F9C1E6CD28A234A35"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the activities related to illicit gold mining, including the illicit mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold—</text><subparagraph id="H5B3226AD81A44187A99D52EC475DC5F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>inside Venezuelan territory carried out by illicit actors, including defectors from the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia (FARC) and members of the National Liberation Army (ELN); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB5AAC4249A0457C9102F7D6733C1BF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">inside Nicaragua carried out by state-owned mining companies such as Empresa Nicaraguense de Minas (ENIMINAS);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H75F34DA8B881442E80FB02DC2E0F7C9F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Venezuela’s illicit gold trade with foreign governments, including the Government of the Republic of Turkey and the Government of the Islamic Republic of Iran; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDB0E2127F8C4CFB93EECF132BD60422"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nicaragua’s illicit gold trade with foreign governments, including the Venezuelan regime and the Government of Russia.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H77622203813241C798E016B3E9A3CAD0"><enum>6.</enum><header>Investigation of the illicit gold trade in Venezuela</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of the Treasury, the Attorney General, and allied and partner governments in the Western Hemisphere, shall seek to—</text><paragraph id="H0E1B3F712445461DB4399D7CC7F6AE84"><enum>(1)</enum><text>lead a coordinated international effort to carry out financial investigations to identify and track assets taken from the people and institutions in Venezuela that are linked to money laundering and illicit activities, including mining-related activities, by sharing financial investigations intelligence, as appropriate and as permitted by law; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC2C66EA64724733BE78E4E7FC08CAEE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide technical assistance to help eligible governments in Latin America establish legislative and regulatory frameworks that bolster legal mechanisms to disrupt illicit mining, including by supporting the capacity to impose and effectively implement targeted sanctions on—</text><subparagraph id="H90D01F5877BB41B28F9005AE44002599"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">officials of the Maduro regime or any successor thereof not installed through free or fair elections who are directly engaged in the illicit mining, trafficking, and commercialization of gold; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE3EF33D2206E463A87870E10827BDAFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>foreign persons engaged in the laundering of illicit gold assets linked to designated terrorist and drug trafficking organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H6F24913CE40E4046889C2D8D60B0D645"><enum>7.</enum><header>Leveraging international support</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In implementing the Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Strategy pursuant to section 4, the President should direct United States representatives accredited to relevant multilateral institutions and development banks and United States ambassadors in the Western Hemisphere to use the influence of the United States to foster international cooperation to achieve the objectives of this Act, including—</text><paragraph id="H554A72CED875492FA6A847A459246378"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">marshaling resources and political support; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87F03AEA2FF2469C92ECA859FADD98F8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encouraging the development of policies and consultation with key stakeholders to accomplish such objectives and provisions.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD1ED71A4AA594C79BDCA0FAF2FE2DF0F"><enum>8.</enum><header>Public-private partnership to build responsible gold value chains</header><subsection id="H09B23D812C264444BAB9580E5A27E5B4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development (referred to in this section as the <quote>Administrator</quote>), in coordination with the Governments of Colombia, of Ecuador, and of Peru, and with other democratically elected governments in the region, shall consult with the Government of Switzerland regarding best practices developed through the Swiss Better Gold Initiative, a public-private partnership that aims to improve transparency and traceability in the international gold trade.</text></subsection><subsection id="H081D8ECC54A64A378156C143072EBF47"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall coordinate with the Governments of Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, and other democratically elected governments in the region determined by the Administrator to establish a public-private partnership to advance the best practices identified in subsection (a), including supporting programming in participating countries that will—</text><paragraph id="H7F8DC9577AF7490CBAEA52D9061EBB1B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support formalization and compliance with appropriate environmental and labor standards in ASM gold mining;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE34D61DF53184B4081E8C023084A5F46"><enum>(2)</enum><text>increase access to financing for ASM gold miners who are taking significant steps to formalize their operations and comply with labor and environmental standards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5E01DCA6F544B5B8C58887AA3DC4CC5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>enhance the traceability and support the establishment of a certification process for ASM gold;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34F875BC802C46F4A1EEA09D2E10C890"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support a public relations campaign to promote responsibly-sourced gold;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F7BB5F56A544C429BB7D20338711125"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include representatives of local civil society and indigenous communities to work towards soliciting the free and informed consent of those living on lands with mining potential;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22E776124F164FA083C5DE13958CFAC0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>facilitate contact between vendors of responsibly-sourced gold and United States companies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D207690C7254F49A75047D4AD03524D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>promote policies and practices in participating countries that are conducive to the formalization of ASM gold mining and promoting adherence of ASM to internationally-recognized best practices and standards.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0280DBCB13444CEDBC8F7F9495B37A47"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Meeting</header><text>The Secretary of State or the Administrator, without delegation and in coordination with the governments of participating countries, should—</text><paragraph id="HF637F386B5BC45DAB5CF724BF5B0D11A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>host a meeting with senior representatives of the private sector and international governmental and nongovernmental partners; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA2E96A56292419083EEBE55045D9B62"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make commitments to improve due diligence and increase the responsible sourcing of gold.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD0997485A20845E382B135718B91AC16"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Department of State $10,000,000 to implement the Legal Gold and Mining Partnership Strategy developed pursuant to section 4.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

