<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H23DE662212804606AC5C06F5D73FE576" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>111 HR 2734 IH: Ocean Acidification Research Partnerships Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2734</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for ocean acidification collaborative research grant opportunities.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1355626406E14A77957FACE553E9FF6A" style="OLC"><section id="HD6B05BAD0E69421886C9052C13C991A8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ocean Acidification Research Partnerships Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC3E98A74DC314BFE93B15BC5568E1575" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ocean acidification collaborative research grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Federal Ocean Acidification Research and Monitoring Act of 2009 (enacted as subtitle D of part II of title XII of the Omnibus Public Land Management Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/3701">33 U.S.C. 3701 et seq.</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/11">Public Law 111–11</external-xref>)) is amended by inserting after section 12406 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/3705">33 U.S.C. 3705</external-xref>) the following new section:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEE5556510C254FE493F0ED15D6F11ADA" style="OLC"><section id="H207AF0340B1145128693E66B37ADA4D5"><enum>12406A.</enum><header>Ocean acidification collaborative research grants</header><subsection id="HE04D0CA9481F4A31B3A07EBE182798C5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA9D67D1E2CFE4961A7F51BDAF65E193E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Academic community</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>academic community</term> includes faculty and other representatives of institutions of higher education and other schools, researchers, scientists, and natural resource managers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F5C704044E94EE596A5101CF65BC186"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Seafood industry</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>seafood industry</term> includes shellfish growers, shellfish harvesters, commercial fishermen, recreational fishermen, other members of the seafood harvesting or supply chain, and organizations representing any of such groups.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6436E60E907C443EA1792E24E10AEAB0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Secretary shall provide grants for collaborative research projects on ocean acidification developed and conducted through partnerships between the seafood industry and the academic community.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBA85F7BF852146059AE921C6C59C64DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Criteria for approval</header><text>The Secretary may not provide a grant for a project under this section unless the project is—</text><paragraph id="HD6B951F2FBFA48DCBAD91715DB868E44"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consistent with the themes identified under the strategic research plan developed by the Subcommittee under section 12405; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EA19F4CB3744382AA06B78F0C1B3F5D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>designed to—</text><subparagraph id="H1675BCD0396D41089CFEEE7C19397F84"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop and support partnerships, communications, and shared understanding between the seafood industry and the academic community;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E6F96C3140845B5B8D8F958E9116FAB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include the seafood industry in research on ocean acidification;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7020178A730C4FB69D90D2A1C46C13BD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>deliver research, monitoring, or adaptation results which will benefit both the seafood industry and the academic community;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H903C2B3352F6477A98D85294331283CF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>incorporate into the research agenda the expertise of both the seafood industry, including their unique understanding of the natural environment, and the academic community;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74CF9CAB433A4F3FBF72299DEE4E1319"><enum>(E)</enum><text>promote better understanding of seafood industry research questions and priorities within the academic community;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D0167B0915A4A728B19F4D96FF6BBBB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>promote wider understanding of ocean acidification among the academic community, the seafood industry, and other stakeholders as appropriate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BB16557F20844E0A1996A57A12F5351"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include appropriately balanced support from both the seafood industry and the academic community.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H077AE7EE483948C282F609BA7555ACE6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary shall prioritize funding under this section to projects which—</text><paragraph id="H9F1CE4936D3F475781C6D0BCCF684F3F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>address ecosystems and communities vulnerable to the impacts of ocean acidification;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB83867D24CB4C1ABA456FFF92414D65"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrate support from local stakeholders, such as representatives of States or other governmental jurisdictions, community organizations, tribes, or educational institutions, as appropriate, located within the region in which the project will be undertaken; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E02469C51524FC1885EE399ADF8F65F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>utilize seafood industry assets as research and monitoring platforms.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE9A10307ECF44DFF9BD92C49CC250D20"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Implementation guidelines</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary, in collaboration with the Subcommittee, shall issue implementation guidelines under this section, including criteria and priorities for grants. Those guidelines shall be developed in consultation, as appropriate, with the following:</text><paragraph id="HC10F289275CA4E398E0A711022BE3A11"><enum>(1)</enum><text>State, regional, and local decisionmakers with ocean acidification experience.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A508C8D6F6A4651BE1BBFCEB3BB4A34"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The seafood industry and other marine-dependent industries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F2A6E2552A2467B9EC49804144F9475"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Formal and informal educators, including both those within academia and those who are not.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71309ECCF5B44718ABE63D99341551BD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Tribes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45E33B4DD75142B5AFAFF7ECBC06D2A3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Nongovernmental organizations involved in ocean acidification research, prevention, or adaptation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H011202787FC24FD8BBBC123CBD2FEDA5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any other appropriate community stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H21D7E9CEC8BA49B9B6DB0F8C9CD8F9ED"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Contents of proposals</header><text>Each proposal for a grant under this section shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H39B00046091C4000BEC47BBB71039D38"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the qualifications of the individuals or entities who will conduct the project.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7477721142B48DAA643AA393FB49080"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A plan for ensuring full participation and engagement of both industry and academic community participants, including a description of how each partner will contribute expertise to the project in terms of design, execution, and interpretation of results.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD386F3B934884465A41D96EC7BF7CBE6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A plan for the dissemination of the results of the research project, which may include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H57E7AD980D6E4D599EBEE3FCE42DCAB0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Educational programs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE555813C2FA54BAAA8832C3D314B0092"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Presentations to members of the seafood industry, the academic community, and community stakeholders.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3D2E8983B6E4A66A8327FEECA5614B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Scientific publication.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF314883E8F6F4BA5A5B82725874BC64C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Delivery to appropriate representatives of States or other government jurisdictions who would use the information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4674C2D11A2B42FCAE853CEF047CE9F6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of how the project is consistent with the program elements described in section 12405(c).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28291A1BCAE445A4AEC329B18CB67CF7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any other information the Secretary considers necessary for evaluating the eligibility of the project for funding under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0DC47563B6104FEA9577E51E849BA445"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Alternative participants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may make a grant under this section to a partnership in which a marine-dependent industry is substituted for the seafood industry if the proposed project serves the purposes of this section. In such a case, the participation and interests of that marine-dependent industry shall be substituted for those of the seafood industry in applying the requirements of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6FC3199E5A514366AC35E389882ABBC3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Project reporting</header><text>Each grantee under this section shall provide periodic reports as required by the Secretary. Each such report shall include all information required by the Secretary for evaluating the progress and success of the project.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8672133A92644AD9B38A943E89F7B7D4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Matching requirements</header><paragraph id="H1C53BFE359BC4C65B984A2620561369F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the total amount of Federal funding for a collaborative research project supported under this section may not exceed 85 percent of the total cost of such project. For purposes of this paragraph, the non-Federal share of project costs may be provided by in-kind contributions and other noncash support.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC9F46BDAD9B43BA8CDEC2A0B9AB9AC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive all or part of the matching requirement under paragraph (1) if the Secretary determines that no reasonable means are available through which applicants can meet the matching requirement and the probable benefit of such project outweighs the public interest in such matching requirement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H376873AC55134EB1A6B62FDD93E72A29"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary for carrying out this section $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

