<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Received-in-Senate" dms-id="H8AE1809B9A934EED903EBE0A8FA72406" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 542 : Elizabeth Dole Home- and Community-Based Services for Veterans and Caregivers Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>H. R. 542</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20231206">December 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received</action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to improve certain programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs for home- and community-based services for veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEF17EC048FCA4BC3993049C0EF122F06" style="OLC"><pagebreak></pagebreak><section id="HCE8E0B831D9F43B58493A89370F0DE27" section-type="section-one" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H6C923EAC43D644D687FA03605336D6F4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Elizabeth Dole Home- and Community-Based Services for Veterans and Caregivers Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Elizabeth Dole Home Care Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H9D2855019D42498BBD4FD92CE47A8F2F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HCE8E0B831D9F43B58493A89370F0DE27" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5EF8932A577D42E59D203353191944A3" level="section">Sec. 2. Increase of expenditure cap for noninstitutional care alternatives to nursing home care.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA839C7314E2F45CD8EDC4D508F628F2F" level="section">Sec. 3. Coordination with Program of All-Inclusive Care for the Elderly.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF7343D3869F1498CB1AF8659825DFAF1" level="section">Sec. 4. Home- and community-based services: programs.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H948DE8D2CD374AB28114679AB5348208" level="section">Sec. 5. Coordination with assistance and support services for caregivers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3B8C1F4FF4F94FD2BF4EE81CB99A0E10" level="section">Sec. 6. Development of centralized website for program information.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H69296066C5D44378AEA914E0D035C89D" level="section">Sec. 7. Improvements relating to Homemaker and Home Health Aide program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H36DB56F1F4EC4877BC118553BF60E227" level="section">Sec. 8. Reviews and other improvements relating to home- and community-based services.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0ADA058375904C98B19262682CA488DF" level="section">Sec. 9. Modification of certain housing loan fees.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBDB25FD2988542699E2EB30283E25D45" level="section">Sec. 10. Definitions.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="H5EF8932A577D42E59D203353191944A3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increase of expenditure cap for noninstitutional care alternatives to nursing home care</header><subsection id="H1A9F6848836D4DDFA82A3785F0D3AB65"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Increase of expenditure cap</header><text>Section 1720C(d) of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HCBCCAA59731043D6B674CA5180B246CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The total cost</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="USC"><enum-in-header>(1)</enum-in-header></header-in-text> Except as provided in paragraph (2), the total cost</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4418BD039AA49C493EDC4C9ACD630B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>65 percent</quote> and inserting <quote>100 percent</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60F9FCB5B4D44615B1C8FFBFE8318625"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H2A920D3EEF444E24BF9987D412D9CD55" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H29EE7CD12C594BCBA7D26051431ED44C" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H24503580122744DCA63BE21A7BAD5424"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The total cost of providing services or in-kind assistance in the case of any veteran described in subparagraph (B) for any fiscal year under the program may exceed 100 percent of the cost that would otherwise have been incurred as specified in paragraph (1) if the Secretary determines, based on a consideration of clinical need, geographic market factors, and such other matters as the Secretary may prescribe through regulation, that such higher total cost is in the best interest of the veteran.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF40378E2D8E4234A2260CD775FAEB03" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A veteran described in this subparagraph is a veteran with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, a spinal cord injury, or a condition the Secretary determines to be similar to such conditions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65F2929C009F4FA495438823927766BA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to fiscal years beginning on or after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section><section id="HA839C7314E2F45CD8EDC4D508F628F2F" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Coordination with Program of All-Inclusive Care for the Elderly</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1720C of title 38, United States Code, as amended by <internal-xref idref="HEF17EC048FCA4BC3993049C0EF122F06" legis-path="1.">section 2</internal-xref>, is further amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HF31669C5B968483086FA732805ED3FCB" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H036CB46B49E443CEAB58A885F15C0D3D" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In furnishing services to a veteran under the program conducted pursuant to subsection (a), if a medical center of the Department through which such program is administered is located in a geographic area in which services are available to the veteran under a PACE program (as such term is defined in sections 1894(a)(2) and 1934(a)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395eee">42 U.S.C. 1395eee(a)(2)</external-xref>; 1396u–4(a)(2))), the Secretary shall seek to enter into an agreement with the PACE program operating in that area for the furnishing of such services.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HF7343D3869F1498CB1AF8659825DFAF1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Home- and community-based services: programs</header><subsection id="HC1D47E31DE2A4FDEBEF6901B5AFE6CEF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/17">Chapter 17</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1720J">section 1720J</external-xref> the following new section (and conforming the table of sections at the beginning of such chapter accordingly):</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HAFFA7CCE06B543FC8841007607426976" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HFCBEF68105B3477BB8D61165CBAED20D"><enum>1720K.</enum><header>Home- and community-based services: programs</header><subsection id="H45B9831C711B4B4E9954D0B3B4C516FF" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In furnishing noninstitutional alternatives to nursing home care pursuant to the authority of section 1720C of this title (or any other authority under this chapter or other provision of law administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs), the Secretary shall carry out each of the programs specified in this section in accordance with such relevant authorities except as otherwise provided in this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H86383641C1A548FA97258936DA47A231"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Veteran-Directed Care program</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H16D101A27CEA4E9185CAC0A52C69BFBF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in collaboration with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall carry out a program to be known as the <quote>Veteran-Directed Care program</quote>. Under such program, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs may enter into agreements with the providers described in paragraph (2) to provide to eligible veterans funds, to the extent practicable, to obtain such in-home care services and related items as may be determined appropriate by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and selected by the veteran, including through the veteran hiring individuals to provide such services and items or directly purchasing such services and items.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28A07C2DA4DE4BFCACDEA66AC113F30A" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The providers described in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="H28D6E3D7199842A1861123443CD671D8" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An Aging and Disability Resource Center, an area agency on aging, or a State agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64263011033A4676BCF2DB02C12C2F01" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A center for independent living.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBADC2A62F24B4998B011FA7127D73F2A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An Indian tribe or tribal organization receiving assistance under title VI of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3057">42 U.S.C. 3057 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0D5EF7EF19643ADBE9FAAA8D9A845DB" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the Veteran-Directed Care program, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall—</text><subparagraph id="H8EF6A1B555364A4DA2280BB575BFE447" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>administer such program through each medical center of the Department of Veterans Affairs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCBE340BF33D49709E9B8FB4212B5729" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">seek to ensure the availability of such program in American Samoa, Guam, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands of the United States, and any other territory or possession of the United States, to the extent practicable; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66EECDA6800A4380BBC14A648B97B021" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>seek to ensure the availability of such program for eligible veterans who are Native American veterans receiving care and services furnished by the Indian Health Service, a tribal health program, an Urban Indian organization, or (in the case of a Native Hawaiian veteran) a Native Hawaiian health care system, to the extent practicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H68E41DF436644EF69A8F74A994944E03" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a veteran participating in the Veteran-Directed Care program is catastrophically disabled, the veteran may continue to use funds under the program during a period of hospitalization in the same manner that the veteran would be authorized to use such funds under the program if the veteran were not hospitalized.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAF6370A0EC36474FB3927E9CB444D8EA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Homemaker and Home Health Aide program</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA8911FF9BA294F2082BB05E49A79F638"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a program to be known as the <quote>Homemaker and Home Health Aide program</quote> under which the Secretary may enter into agreements with home health agencies to provide to eligible veterans such home health aide services as may be determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6533428AEB6C4D72A2D468ECB2827A68" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the Homemaker and Home Health Aide program, the Secretary shall, to the extent practicable, ensure the availability of such program—</text><subparagraph id="HD08A267571A848C7A1702A99DB00A932"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the locations specified in subparagraph (B) of subsection (b)(3); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13DBAEE64C6B4137A6F72242E725A428"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the veteran populations specified in subparagraph (C) of such subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B96AA1FD153418FA89A02149EC16CA5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Home-Based Primary Care program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a program to be known as the <quote>Home-Based Primary Care program</quote> under which the Secretary may furnish to eligible veterans in-home health care, the provision of which is overseen by a provider of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H887BE8B59183481FBA1BD3F7E4742084"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Purchased Skilled Home Care program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a program to be known as the <quote>Purchased Skilled Home Care program</quote> under which the Secretary may furnish to eligible veterans such in-home care services as may be determined appropriate and selected by the Secretary for the veteran.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA50A0AF3ED1947BB9307E90C4D419D2F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Caregiver support</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HCED87D6C6F584F38A2CD1AB399032982"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a resident eligible caregiver of a veteran participating in a program under this section, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HB5F8AD70ED2A4561B8A3419ECA8BE488" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the veteran meets the requirements of a covered veteran under section 1720G(b) of this title, provide to such caregiver the option of enrolling in the program of general caregiver support services under such section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86D5E3DCABAD43D3B464FD22B8AA6EA2" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide to such caregiver covered respite care of not less than 30 days annually; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F43E5F9F83048C5919A6B711DE5DEE6" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>conduct on an annual basis (and, to the extent practicable, in connection with in-person services provided under the program in which the veteran is participating), a wellness contact of such caregiver.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB94F2DDAD0E4738BA3259D3C26023EC" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Covered respite care provided to a resident eligible caregiver of a veteran under paragraph (1) may exceed 30 days annually if such extension is requested by the resident eligible caregiver or veteran and determined medically appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD37F68F69FEB4D69AA9A43F82C43C22B" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to limit the authority of the Secretary to carry out programs providing home- and community-based services under any other provision of law.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDC26EAC7A6024A92821FF806FDF11C91"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H3BF943607E8247A5AF551030067BA068"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>Aging and Disability Resource Center</term>, <term>area agency on aging</term>, and <term>State agency</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 102 of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3002">42 U.S.C. 3002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE2E0F4B6A1C46409C8479235E47007B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>caregiver</term> and <term>family caregiver</term>, with respect to a veteran, have the meanings given those terms, respectively, under subsection (e) of section 1720G of this title with respect to an eligible veteran under subsection (a) of such section or a covered veteran under subsection (b) of such section, as the case may be.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00E5579551BA4963A439E5FDB07D40CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>center for independent living</term> has the meaning given that term in section 702 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/796a">29 U.S.C. 796a</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H091144D22185415FB9AFFFEE660D18AA"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered respite care</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1720G(d) of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC12C823B8AC4575984BB6BF1EC3A092" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The term <term>eligible veteran</term> means any veteran—</text><subparagraph id="H071504A1D2B64915AEEDA856CE24C659" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for whom the Secretary determines participation in a specific program under this section is medically necessary to promote, preserve, or restore the health of the veteran; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35D124B9D4904B6E9784618FBC308483" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who absent such participation would be at increased risk for hospitalization, placement in a nursing home, or emergency room care.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B37DB6E68A54D84A7E0FDD1A4E682D3" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>home health aide</term> means an individual employed by a home health agency to provide in-home care services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7705FDF26E27446B829792BEDA31ADD7" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The term <term>in-home care service</term> means any service, including a personal care service, provided to enable the recipient of such service to live at home.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE78369F540D24A01BE9A3375D9429275"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>Indian tribe</term> and <term>tribal organization</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79D40ED156B84331A338E4E91843F2F3" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The terms <term>Native American</term> and <term>Native American veteran</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 3765 of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21A7087A62E94FB2902ACE8B97C630FC" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>Native Hawaiian</term> and <term>Native Hawaiian health care system</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 12 of the Native Hawaiian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11711">42 U.S.C. 11711</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9614AB06BCB424BA31C5F3EBF9B4127" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>tribal health programs</term> and <term>Urban Indian organizations</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1603">25 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AB7C7E467084391901B98F572DF5042" commented="no"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The term <term>resident eligible caregiver</term> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="H7100475ED1FF47409EEB615A356051A3" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a caregiver, or a family caregiver, of a veteran and resides with that veteran; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0FDDD079907C4A678F85F70EB8FEF287" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has not entered into a contract, agreement, or other arrangement for such individual to act as a caregiver for that veteran unless such individual is a family member of the veteran or is furnishing caregiver services through a medical foster home.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H64356EE7093846EDBC30D0483DFF9D50"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline for improved administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall ensure that the Veteran-Directed Care program and the Homemaker and Home Health Aide program are administered through each medical center of the Department of Veterans Affairs in accordance with section 1720K of title 38, United States Code (as added by subsection (a)), by not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H948DE8D2CD374AB28114679AB5348208" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>5.</enum><header>Coordination with assistance and support services for caregivers</header><subsection id="H92E8CBD6501744108EFEEDF0A5536B53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Coordination with Program of Comprehensive Assistance for Family Caregivers</header><paragraph id="HA954A26327D34CC8AEC26B9A22289089"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>Section 1720G(a) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HCF40C4C99C8B411AAA0109FE8D62211C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H35BDC35F561643B39987A9ECD0F99DB0" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD521EC84CB7F4857966A78B4172BA685"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a veteran or caregiver who seeks services under this subsection and is denied such services, or a veteran or the family caregiver of a veteran who is discharged from the program under this subsection, the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="HBCCCF081F538412C850B194558D27ECB" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the veteran meets the requirements of a covered veteran under subsection (b), provide to such caregiver the option of enrolling in the program of general caregiver support services under such subsection;</text></clause><clause id="H7387318B45F04532BD2D938DEA62E582" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assess the veteran or caregiver for participation in any other available program of the Department for home- and community-based services (including the programs specified in section 1720K of this title) for which the veteran or caregiver may be eligible and, with respect to the veteran, store (and make accessible to the veteran) the results of such assessment in the electronic medical record of the veteran; and</text></clause><clause id="HC4FF73792FDA4BB4A2AF76FA0F06FCC6" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provide to the veteran or caregiver written information on any such program identified pursuant to the assessment under clause (ii), including information about facilities, eligibility requirements, and relevant contact information for each such program.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72B70A750E0D46D08B60DA090DCC7981" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each veteran or family caregiver who is discharged from the program under this subsection, a caregiver support coordinator shall provide for a smooth and personalized transition from such program to an appropriate program of the Department for home- and community-based services (including the programs specified in section 1720K of this title), including by integrating caregiver support across programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H9190CEE62F8742998A3780BA0ECC4FE9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by paragraph (1) shall apply with respect to denials and discharges occurring on or after the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0788160BFCD74E6CA8F93E8998F4F385"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header><text>Section 1720G(d) of such title is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H92AF3AAC6DF34C02A7B21A8B149EC098"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or a covered veteran</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>, a veteran denied or discharged as specified in paragraph (14) of such subsection, or a covered veteran</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H921DFDC12A5340C09753C57EB58E5846"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>under subsection (a), means</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>under subsection (a) or a veteran denied or discharged as specified in paragraph (14) of such subsection, means</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H41618D9A9B30405F8A44C56017CB5CE6" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conformity of respite care across programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1720G of title 38, United States Code, as amended by subsection (a)(3), is further amended—</text><paragraph id="HB6F4856F5ED94C0BA1073072E42634CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(3)—</text><subparagraph id="HA15D3367DD234702A0767E00C7B22708"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (A)(ii)(III) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H4B0056FE1F3245D2AC09ABE38B1414AC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subclause id="HB0A96538AB004C5DACF6EB91EB35E053" indent="up2"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">covered respite care of not less than 30 days annually;</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCFDD189FC80A44978B62CC8D2FC3773C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B) and redesignating subparagraphs (C) and (D) as subparagraphs (B) through (C), respectively; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H61802AC663304304AC697165EA8BDCA4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by amending subsection (b)(3)(A)(iii) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H8B9DF57CE9154D338734C0CCCC2C8587" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H0655CA8D65AD449EB09BF0B9968D7E43" indent="up2" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Covered respite care of not less than 30 days annually.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H9ED52A5EC22148AE846367037B9FCAE3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="H8D713F76E8414959AD2DCC01C3C664A7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (2) through (4) as paragraphs (3) through (5), respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H971549EAEF7948A68365806C62548345"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H2AE4F0754F384F62BACE2C33D0189719" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H9991F0E8D1F941E5BBCBB8D923AA94C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered respite care</term> means, with respect to a caregiver of a veteran, respite care under section 1720B of this title that—</text><subparagraph id="H6E271448645F4ED789D8B42AE89AA250"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is medically and age appropriate for the veteran (including 24-hour per day care of the veteran commensurate with the care provided by the caregiver); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9744B994854C46D29563A77430997B22"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes in-home care.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H56CE9E5A66B446CBA893214ACE6EEB9B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Review relating to caregiver contact</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct a review of the capacity of the Department to establish a streamlined system for contacting all caregivers enrolled in the program of general caregiver support services under section 1720G(b) of title 38, United States Code, to provide to such caregivers program updates and alerts relating to emerging services for which such caregivers may be eligible.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3B8C1F4FF4F94FD2BF4EE81CB99A0E10" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Development of centralized website for program information</header><subsection id="H63BBA77A8BC441CFA4C8A3F9CDCE9801" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Centralized website</header><text>The Secretary shall develop and maintain a centralized and publically accessible internet website of the Department as a clearinghouse for information and resources relating to covered programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC66E1617733C4C2891AFE7E7A0E33315" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The website under subsection (a) shall contain the following:</text><paragraph id="HAB32B42300BF4DCFA36590932F72F36A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of each covered program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AAE28B6242E452F92B720EB838859AE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An informational assessment tool that—</text><subparagraph id="H9B1975EB75FD4943B88299F0472F8E9D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>explains the administrative eligibility, if applicable, of a veteran, or a caregiver of a veteran, for any covered program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA20ACA59B9B4528A360F7604226EF16" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides information, as a result of such explanation, on any covered program for which the veteran or caregiver (as the case may be) may be eligible.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H63FAE6943FF34CFEA2B184FC7585468A" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A list of required procedures for the directors of the medical facilities of the Department to follow in determining the eligibility and suitability of veterans for participation in a covered program, including procedures applicable to instances in which the resource constraints of a facility (or of a community in which a facility is located) may result in the inability to address the health needs of a veteran under a covered program in a timely manner.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD5D8E0576EB426BB7B96A079FFE2B14" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure the website under subsection (a) is updated on a periodic basis.</text></subsection></section><section id="H69296066C5D44378AEA914E0D035C89D"><enum>7.</enum><header>Improvements relating to Homemaker and Home Health Aide program</header><subsection id="HEF7734CA284249AEA10398DFB1E4A7E9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program for communities with shortage of home health aides</header><paragraph id="H6BCB7C6F71DD473286ADDD4E3EF85522"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall carry out a three-year pilot program under which the Secretary shall provide homemaker and home health aide services to veterans who reside in communities with a shortage of home health aides.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07ECEF46F7DD4998AEB1ED4E641D5309"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Locations</header><text>The Secretary shall select not fewer than five geographic locations in which the Secretary determines there is a shortage of home health aides at which to carry out the pilot program under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB026631C2D4645EA99817085DD14685F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Nursing assistants</header><subparagraph id="H49365F5CD46D4C349D699982CFF1AE6F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the pilot program under paragraph (1), the Secretary may hire nursing assistants as new employees of the Department of Veterans Affairs, or reassign nursing assistants who are existing employees of the Department, to provide to veterans in-home care services (including basic tasks authorized by the State certification of the nursing assistant) under the pilot program, in lieu of or in addition to the provision of such services through non-Department home health aides.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0913115F5D64093B99E9A5B2ADE4A27"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Relationship to Home-Based Primary Care program</header><text>Nursing assistants hired or reassigned under subparagraph (A) may provide services to a veteran under the pilot program under paragraph (1) while serving as part of a health care team for the veteran under the Home-Based Primary Care program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B838577DFD3436292D5F700A6054CF7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date on which the Secretary determines the pilot program under paragraph (1) has terminated, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report on the result of the pilot program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBE4422C5DF5B45C0A530E220447D1C78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report on use of funds</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report containing, with respect to the period beginning in fiscal year 2012 and ending in fiscal year 2023, the following:</text><paragraph id="HAAB5C0FD8F9043BD89F565C2544AA9EB" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An identification of the amount of funds that were included in a budget of the Department of Veterans Affairs during such period for the provision of in-home care to veterans under the Homemaker and Home Health Aide program but were not expended for such provision, disaggregated by medical center of the Department for which such unexpended funds were budgeted (if such disaggregation is possible).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H803AE6D0268B46DBAFFF8A75C0FDEA1A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable, an identification of the number of veterans for whom, during such period, the hours during which a home health aide was authorized to provide services to the veteran under the Homemaker and Home Health Aide program were reduced for a reason other than a change in the health care needs of the veteran, and a detailed description of the reasons why any such reductions may have occurred.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H22554F87AADE4742B6596D382195F42B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Updated guidance on program</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue updated guidance for the Homemaker and Home Health Aide program. Such updated guidance shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H09330320BFD943768930B1AB3DF4F0BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A process for the transition of veterans from the Homemaker and Home Health Aide program to other covered programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA137051E714A4DE3BDD5968D3805CCFA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement for the directors of the medical facilities of the Department to complete such process whenever a veteran with care needs has been denied services from home health agencies under the Homemaker and Home Health Aide program as a result of the clinical needs or behavioral issues of the veteran.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H36DB56F1F4EC4877BC118553BF60E227"><enum>8.</enum><header>Reviews and other improvements relating to home- and community-based services</header><subsection id="HFE0F95CFEC834099976C4859ACC870CA" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Office of Geriatric and Extended Care</header><paragraph id="H4DCC620521204B468E30C9D72B87B1B6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review of programs</header><text>The Under Secretary for Health of the Department of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a review of each program administered through the Office of Geriatric and Extended Care of the Department, or successor office, to—</text><subparagraph id="H0D886411323A43648CA506C52A401968" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure consistency in program management;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7180467B08E342D6BCD61F63A4E5CEDD" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>eliminate service gaps at the medical center level; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32E56B1A3BDB4A6A87769BD0EC3C939A" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure the availability of, and the access by veterans to, home- and community-based services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H05CC9AEFA86E44D980D8AEC5851EA669"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assessment of staffing needs</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct an assessment of the staffing needs of the Office of Geriatric and Extended Care of the Department of Veterans Affairs, or successor office.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EA7E9875FA646E1B5A3DFD98A3B5F42" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Goals for geographic alignment of care</header><subparagraph id="H1145D19D27494A95B98E3BA85EB35357"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment of goals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Geriatric and Extended Care, or successor office, shall establish quantitative goals to enable aging or disabled veterans who are not located near medical centers of the Department to access extended care services (including by improving access to home- and community-based services for such veterans).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D430F718D0F44BAB6ED58EAD7A73586"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation timeline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each goal established under subparagraph (A) shall include a timeline for the implementation of the goal at each medical center of the Department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BA9F3F1BD5C4B51AACD5BA7C19165CB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Goals for in-home specialty care</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Geriatric and Extended Care, or successor office, shall establish quantitative goals to address the specialty care needs of veterans through in-home care, including by ensuring the education of home health aides and caregivers of veterans in the following areas:</text><subparagraph id="HCE96D4F905E2436AA937207DDED72E89"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Dementia care.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD4FA071075D4D48B3013463D2845EF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Care for spinal cord injuries and diseases.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5191CE7B13984DAD91BDD6A72ABF3B38"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Ventilator care.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC465FA8694884DCE9E78B3ABA8F5984B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Other speciality care areas as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF7269606D8D42A3AAFCFD7B9E284DCD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report containing the findings of the review under paragraph (1), the results of the assessment under paragraph (2), and the goals established under paragraphs (3) and (4).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7319E06C7EE44034BBA2238A3BB88EC5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Review of incentives and efforts relating to home- and community-Based services</header><paragraph id="H0913F957117D4459AEA4CF6DF9AF6E2C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a review of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H60A185C6DC47426795C011470479776A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The financial and organizational incentives for the directors of medical centers of the Department to establish or expand covered programs at such medical centers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17D6B9F1EAAB403BA3B0F4DD88395B44"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any incentives for such directors to provide to veterans home- and community-based services in lieu of institutional care.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AA0ABA268DB4152852AB6AC6CED1390" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The efforts taken by the Secretary to enhance spending of the Department for extended care by shifting the balance of such spending from institutional care to home- and community-based services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38DC0362FE07470F82BEEA1934FD6E25"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The plan of the Under Secretary for Health of the Department to accelerate efforts to enhance spending as specified in subparagraph (C), to match the progress of similar efforts taken by the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services with respect to spending of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services for extended care.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4982E3AEECA64C849B42AD9FCA6B1DA9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report on the findings of the review under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB1AEB21F4C3B483FACD19EAD6284CDA6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Review of respite care services</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a review of the use, availability, and effectiveness, of the respite care services furnished by the Secretary under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/17">chapter 17</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBF2C25D77D0F450AAA8380753F6938CD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Collaboration To improve home- and community-Based services</header><paragraph id="H7B8D4692C6A6422F900B87B333E891BE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report on expansion of certain mental health services</header><subparagraph id="HF4FA45C1624E49F882BEBAE5E2E6662B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in collaboration with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report containing recommendations for the expansion of mental health services and related support to the caregivers of veterans.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C9704E86594405CA0227EDA8999C362" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Matters included</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report under subparagraph (A) shall include an assessment of the feasibility and advisability of authorizing access to Vet Centers by—</text><clause id="H1680C97D064A49FA894D8EDEF4212B10" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>family caregivers enrolled in a program under section 1720G of title 38, United States Code; and</text></clause><clause id="H0ABE1EFD5DA540B28BCCA2CE6152464D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>family caregivers of veterans participating in a program specified in section 1720K of such title, as added by <internal-xref idref="HF7343D3869F1498CB1AF8659825DFAF1" legis-path="5.">section 4</internal-xref>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF5A5391C9FB435BB4380DFB5F451C42"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><subparagraph id="HF4273F33D5C74E8982E0BA85243590A8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Development</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall develop recommendations as follows:</text><clause id="H398CB5E060014E769D0D2CF4467BBAE4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to home- and community-based services for veterans, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall develop recommendations regarding new services (in addition to those furnished as of the date of the enactment of this Act) in collaboration with the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></clause><clause id="H86A1C3057FFB493DB4DC4E02EBA070A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to the national shortage of home health aides, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall develop recommendations regarding methods to address such shortage in collaboration with the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of Labor.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H672A31066CEF44D5A1C1E0A35678AA0E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report containing the recommendations developed under subparagraph (A) and an identification of any changes in existing law or new statutory authority necessary to implement the recommendations, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8753FB392B844812808571668BB20B63"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Consultation with Secretary of Labor</header><text>In carrying out this paragraph, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall consult with the Secretary of Labor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H18756BCA21824C2E80B107296AF16035" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Feedback and recommendations on caregiver support</header><subparagraph id="HFBF609FEA94448889BCB0F10BB59477D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Feedback and recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall solicit from the entities described in subparagraph (B) feedback and recommendations regarding opportunities for the Secretary to enhance home- and community-based services for veterans and the caregivers of veterans, including through the potential provision by the entity of care and respite services to veterans and caregivers who may not be eligible for any program under section 1720G of title 38, United States Code, or section 1720K of such title (as added by <internal-xref idref="HF7343D3869F1498CB1AF8659825DFAF1" legis-path="4.">section 4</internal-xref>), but have a need for assistance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H040401C3D0054F4997DAA53D6A919C60" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The entities described in this subparagraph are veterans service organizations and nonprofit organizations with a focus on caregiver support (as determined by the Secretary).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H181CE72578F949B6803B599F2A74AE68"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Collaboration for Native American veterans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall collaborate with the Director of the Indian Health Service and representatives from tribal health programs and Urban Indian organizations to ensure the availability of home- and community-based services for Native American veterans, including Native American veterans receiving health care and medical services under multiple health care systems.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0ADA058375904C98B19262682CA488DF"><enum>9.</enum><header>Modification of certain housing loan fees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The loan fee table in section 3729(b)(2) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>November 15, 2031</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>February 4, 2032</quote>.</text></section><section id="HBDB25FD2988542699E2EB30283E25D45"><enum>10.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H4A3F914AD6EA4CAFB0AD435C4B05D934" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The terms <term>caregiver</term> and <term>family caregiver</term> have the meanings given those terms under section 1720K(h) of title 38, United States Code (as added by <internal-xref idref="H948DE8D2CD374AB28114679AB5348208" legis-path="5.">section 4</internal-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD225383802443E3859D463B77F6F69F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>covered program</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H2694AB2ABA764659B2B6C3A971D5E6CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means any program of the Department of Veterans Affairs for home- and community-based services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BF3F6CF842D4494A7ADE5D34547BE20"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes the programs specified in section 1720K of title 38, United States Code (as added by <internal-xref idref="HF7343D3869F1498CB1AF8659825DFAF1" legis-path="4.">section 4</internal-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDEBF2175DF048EDBDD6D3ECA1FE988A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>home- and community-based services</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H1E331D8ECDA144C490BD0892E671B218"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means the services referred to in section 1701(6)(E) of title 38, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD42E32140A624D1284F5F5FCA093FADA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes services furnished under a program specified in section 1720K of such title (as added by <internal-xref idref="HF7343D3869F1498CB1AF8659825DFAF1" legis-path="4.">section 4</internal-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BB98EA4C1A54D128FE7B54FDC2B0562"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>Home-Based Primary Care program</term>, <term>Homemaker and Home Health Aide program</term>, and <term>Veteran-Directed Care program</term> mean the programs of the Department of Veterans Affairs specified in subsection (d), (c), and (b) of such section 1720K, respectively.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D120D369D4547F39FE7F2F5F4CBB574"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>home health aide</term>, <term>Native American</term>, <term>Native American veteran</term>, <term>tribal health programs</term>, and <term>Urban Indian organizations</term> have the meanings given those terms in subsection (h) of such section 1720K.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC568039F387483EB3D69D511180FE5E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Vet Center</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1712A(h) of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC6DAC58EA7F438D8316AA9D59BA98C7"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>veterans service organization</term> means any organization recognized by the Secretary under section 5902 of such title. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20231205" legis-day="20231205" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives December 5, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Kevin F. McCumber,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation></bill> 

