<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H66A6DCB8E2764904A69E3B6F7E07A5A7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6797 IH: Restoring U.S. Leadership in International Organizations Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6797</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for enhanced United States leadership at international organizations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD5E8CBE5BE7A4BADA6339E9FB4B345A6" style="OLC"><section id="HCC45E11FF8314EBAB946B015BADAC06A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restoring U.S. Leadership in International Organizations Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2CA99C2DF136477D8B0FC1C75DC0699F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Promoting service at international organizations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 603(b) of the Foreign Service Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/4003">22 U.S.C. 4003</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF44269073A044470A113F0EE645151F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>or</quote> after the semi-colon at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFF3390F4F0940F38166E6D736626124"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (4) as paragraph (5); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17D3F8D6F72748E890CD122807E2E725"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (3) the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block id="H653E60D807A24A2FBE1B459F166B2151" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HE40D1593F56F4A0EA2BD4243F68D816B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>experience serving at an international organization, multilateral institution, or engaging in multinational negotiations; or</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HD6A4E2A710AD4C0BB381053B856045C4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States that—</text><paragraph id="HDE7990527E8E447CB02E26244AEB8740"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Special Representative of the United States to the United Nations serves as a standing member of the cabinet;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DC59D9B22D24BF4B14D10FA3E152AE2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assessed dues to multilateral organizations be paid in full in a timely fashion;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H273BCDC1E2C44D96970B43FE8BC8F4ED"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Federal agencies utilize all the authorities under section 3343 of title 5, United States Code, or subpart C of part 352 of title 5, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations) to detail or transfer employees to relevant international organizations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACD3A3D865884A92A9C0DAD9942B50C8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>that the Secretary of State shall assist the Department of State and other Federal agencies in carrying out paragraph (3) to the fullest extent.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H05775085871E414CBE89C840C71FA0EA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reporting on details and transfers to international organizations</header><subsection id="HBAC347D8148F4438AB86188C26974BE2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the heads of other Federal departments and agencies as appropriate, shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the total number of Federal employees detailed or transferred to an international organization during the immediately preceding 12-month period. The first such report shall include a strategy for increasing the number of Federal employees who are so detailed or transferred to such an international organization.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC84CB1623EAC464F9F01AD47C1AB613D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>Each report required under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HDFB785B2E97F47F29155BEB686FFBA58"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of Federal employees detailed or transferred during the applicable 12-month period to an international organization under section 3343 of title 5, United States Code, or subpart C of part 352 of title 5, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations), disaggregated by—</text><subparagraph id="HB49702EAD4DB4E629F94F3A1AD77A019"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an identification of the Federal agency from which such employees were so detailed or transferred; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1639E7FCCD147D5BF4CBDF183FB25D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an identification of the international organizations to and from which such employees have been so detailed or transferred.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H19AE5F27535E4D318207573C17BCEDC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A list of international organizations to and from which a Federal agency previously so detailed or transferred Federal employees.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H88938E28BC4D4192AA4945F2C157E464"><enum>5.</enum><header>Training for international organizations</header><subsection id="HCA50BCA7514A4520A228983FD1613E38"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Training programs</header><text>Section 708 of the Foreign Service Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/4028">22 U.S.C. 4028</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="HAAECF70301A349C197FC53B65AE97BDF" style="OLC"><subsection id="H4E7F59D5399144E7A216485B139F5D02"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Training in multilateral diplomacy</header><paragraph id="H2EEA111B4AC84A7CAE432883A94D0F37"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State, with the assistance of other relevant officials, shall establish a series of training courses on—</text><subparagraph id="HAA0939DF63F7438A8C753E7FAFCA1549"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the conduct of diplomacy at international organizations and other multilateral institutions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1616FF2E9F9D4AC8B51D6862F8EDF0E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>broad-based multilateral negotiations of international instruments.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AED492503884D63ADF5970964F2D243"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Required training</header><text>Members of the Service, including appropriate chiefs of mission and other officers who are assigned to United States missions representing the United States to international organizations and other multilateral institutions or who are assigned in Washington, DC, to positions that have as their primary responsibility formulation of policy toward such organizations and institutions, or toward participation in broad-based multilateral negotiations of international instruments, shall receive specialized training in the areas described in paragraph (1) prior to beginning service for such assignment or, if receiving such training at such time is not practical, within the first year of beginning such assignment.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H3A79A4AAB9E44938A854DA6A5880EE83"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Training for department employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State shall ensure that employees of the Department of State who are assigned to positions described in paragraph (2) of subsection (e) of section 708 of the Foreign Service Act of 1980 (as added by subsection (a) of this section), including members of the civil service or general service, or who are detailed or transferred to international organizations or other multilateral institutions for a period of at least one year, receive training described in such subsection (e) and participate in other such courses or trainings as the Secretary may recommend to build or augment identifiable skills that would be useful for such employees representing United States interests at such organizations and institutions.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

