<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4B0D5DF7DB9444C9B5C044CA6A9C3AC6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5753 IH: To reactivate and repurpose canceling funds to deter the Chinese Communist Party before such funds are extracted from the Department of Defense on October 1, 2023.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5753</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230927">September 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Appropriations</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reactivate and repurpose canceling funds to deter the Chinese Communist Party before such funds are extracted from the Department of Defense on October 1, 2023.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H64D645E2379A42E29DA897DC17E00E32" style="OLC"><section id="H7CE4F838E91742439311E3B908865CE5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Funding Indo-Pacific Readiness and Enhancing Stockpiles Fund to deter the Chinese Communist Party</header><subsection id="H5D8096721B844196B1BDB4CEAF6B5CFA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Treasury a fund to be known as the <quote>Funding Indo-Pacific Readiness and Enhancing Stockpiles Fund</quote> or the <quote>FIRES</quote> Fund (hereafter in this section referred to as the <quote>Fund</quote>). There shall be deposited into the Fund amounts transferred under subsection (c), which shall be used only for the purposes specified in subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="H024E312A9C1E4533AEBEE75B3C8FCFDA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Control of the Fund</header><text>The Fund shall be under the control of the Secretary of Defense acting in consultation with the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3430E3FA3E19433F856F02BB5D5F35D5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Transfer of expired amounts</header><paragraph id="H6758E34FDD4A4439999AC4DD88C6EE3E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary of Defense shall transfer into the Fund any amounts previously appropriated for to the Department of Defense for procurement; research, development, test, and evaluation; operation and maintenance; or military personnel that are unobligated on the last day of the fifth fiscal year after the period of availability for obligation of such amounts ends pursuant to section 1552 of title 31, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE9CA398DB644543B3EF7D3225CDA11A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of certain unobligated funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out paragraph (1), the Secretary of Defense may elect to use all or a portion of unobligated amounts previously appropriated for military personnel or operation and maintenance—</text><subparagraph id="H23569A1122C74EB597D0E9D42B2E97C4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for transfers to the Foreign Currency Fluctuations Account in accordance with section 2779(d) of title 10, United States Code; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H347AB7176A304476B8A57A2995327EA8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for transfers to the Fund.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H12C574C2E52648F5A8BA6FB959DADDE8" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of Funds</header><text>Subject to subsections (e) through (h), monies deposited into the Fund shall be available, without fiscal year limitation, for expenditure. Funds deposited into the account as designated in subsection (c) of this section shall be made available, without fiscal year limitation, for expenditures only for advancing the following purposes:</text><paragraph id="H9E5EF262F61C4BB88D8C7D43EB23DB35" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The production of munitions, the expansion of munitions production capacity, and the construction of facilities for the production, storage, and transport of munitions, including government-owned munitions facilities specializing in solid rocket motor production, prioritizing weapons platforms identified in the reports submitted under section 1251(d)(1) of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/113">10 U.S.C. 113</external-xref> note), in concurrence with the Commander of the United States Indo-Pacific Command.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7453B04D2454C14AB083FC579694AA9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Shipbuilding and conversion, associated facilities, and programs in support of section 1025 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/7291">10 U.S.C. 7291</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F3D0E616B7841D1B56F9AE0C62D5A78" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Within the Indo-Pacific Theater, expeditionary air base infrastructure, forward arming and refueling sites, facilities enabling the pre-positioning of military stocks and logistics capabilities, and installations to support Navy vessel mobility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0394FEC6FEFE445FA17B3F394BE2C4BA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text>Not less than 10 percent of amounts deposited into the Fund shall be used for loans or grants to, or contracts with nontraditional defense contractors and small- and medium-sized businesses.</text></subsection><subsection id="H00E3934F4EFE43FDAF5C500FC8FBAF95"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Contract authorities</header><text>To carry out the purposes of this section, the Secretary may, in addition to any other authorities provided under law—</text><paragraph id="H78A255B3C82F4C37A6A4E8BE66755074"><enum>(1)</enum><text>use other transactional authorities described in sections 4021 and 4022 of title 10, United States Code; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDE31F81AC5146CB82CD96A1253ED608"><enum>(2)</enum><text>enter into multiyear contracts in accordance with section 3501 of such title.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H347072A5CC8D4CB68BCF88B074C8F973" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Congressional notice and approval of contracts</header><text>No contract may be entered into using amounts in the Fund until—</text><paragraph id="HEC46EC0792D14113A4554D3DA9A03F1A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Defense submits to the congressional defense committees written notice of the intent to enter into such contract; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9410FF3DE8D641718851FC860FE687C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a period of 15 days has elapsed following the date of the submittal of such notice.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H91ADC512A4D94DC2A25865A494204F43"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Return of expired amounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any amounts transferred to the Fund under subsection (c) that are unobligated on the date that is 10 years after the date of such transfer shall be returned to the general fund of the Treasury.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9C3DF1B6FB8D41E1941A6D001D8F3C9C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H4E21C65000AA457AA888326C5B455AA4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports on transfers and expenditures</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the first transfer of amounts to the Fund under subsection (c), and not less frequently than once every 180 days thereafter, the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report on expenditures made from the Fund. Each report shall identify—</text><subparagraph id="H39C4EBA299F64070A5838ABD97875B75"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount and source of any appropriations transferred to the Fund under subsection (c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE87DC09CFAD04F3CAA1BD05114F38FF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the specific expenditures for which such amounts were used after such transfer; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08C212152DA342659FC84BA52DDB2765"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the balance of funds remaining in the Fund.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF27755F2CFAE44FBABEE7E2BE6267231"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports on expired amounts</header><text>On a quarterly basis, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report identifying any amounts described in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="HE8265759C7F04749ADF56E494A7DD8A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that are available and have not yet been transferred to the Fund; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72F249DB25F04CD7A0E0E471FBFB7560"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that are expected to become available for transfer to the fund, regardless of when such availability is expected to occur.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD75ADFAE84444A79B9666236B29CFAD2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>GAO review and verification</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the submittal of each report described in paragraphs (1) and (2), the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text><subparagraph id="HE960F7C799EF47A9972B1F920F162157"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review and verify the information contained the report; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B0166C2BA3147278C7F138FE0B2DEAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit to the congressional defense committees a report on the results of such review and verification.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1EE61C83069F403EA84B512CF64045DF"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Congressional defense committees defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>congressional defense committees</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

