<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5B28B2EB2AF146A3BE67C4CF58865BD0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6367 IH: Armed Conflict Migration Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6367</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231113">November 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Treasury to instruct the United States Executive Director at each international financial institution to use the voice, vote, and influence of the United States to provide financial assistance to countries that receive an influx of civilian, non-combatant displaced persons stemming from the armed conflict that has resulted from Hamas’s October 2023 terrorism in Israel, to be used for humanitarian aid for the displaced persons.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEB7FA5F41E134953BE23D114F334BACF" style="OLC"><section id="H9EC50628F29A4E169439F833A71415B9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Armed Conflict Migration Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H37891ADEDCC34CF2A17A15753169FB14"><enum>2.</enum><header>United States advocacy in the international financial institutions for financial assistance for countries that receive an influx of displaced persons stemming from the armed conflict that has resulted from Hamas’s October <enum-in-header>2023</enum-in-header> terrorism in Israel, to be used for humanitarian aid for the displaced persons</header><subsection id="H094FE93F7D074AA49CA32B1364C437CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall instruct the United States Executive Director at each international financial institution (as defined in section 1701(c)(2) of the International Financial Institutions Act) to use the voice, vote, and influence of the United States to support the provision of financial assistance to countries that receive an influx of civilian, non-combatant displaced persons stemming from the armed conflict that has resulted from Hamas’s October 2023 terrorism in Israel, to be used for humanitarian aid for the displaced persons.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3B118C7532C94ED7AD55190B63036A2E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>This section shall cease to have any force or effect on the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="H0484C323C31C468584F982BA241CA6CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date that is 7 years after the date of enactment of this section;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3952AC6A679849589CA5BD80540E95C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which the Secretary of the Treasury certifies to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate that the requirement under subsection (a) is not in the national interest of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02E1D4776EA34E8BB8C86E47B2D87217"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the date on which the Secretary of the Treasury certifies to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate that the armed conflict that has resulted from Hamas’s October 2023 terrorism in Israel has ceased to be a cause of an influx of civilian, non-combatant displaced persons to other countries.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

