<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF83BBBC992E9441FBE7D440582F591E0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4049 IH: Access and Dignity for All People Who Travel Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4049</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide seating accommodations for qualified individuals with disabilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2BDBEE92EE504D3F8F67D257602DF63C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE631C7A5301D47CABFA6A56DA4E33907" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title<editorial></editorial></header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Access and Dignity for All People Who Travel Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAAD0AAE808BF4F05A3B23102A8420068" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the following definitions apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="H85DECA1F9C404DB39A9048B47BB6D23F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Air carrier</header><text>The term <quote>air carrier</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 40102 of title 49, United States Code. </text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H510BD7201A5B486CA91A4AA140D42A4C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of congress</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate committees of Congress</quote> means the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5940D175009D46E89347A3358243F022"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign air carrier</header><text>The term <quote>foreign air carrier</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 40102 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H40F884775CF54065A5DA1AE2A67D74DF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Qualified individual with a disability</header><text>The term <quote>qualified individual with a disability</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 382.3 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H67B8915C306645B5B31A64948F7FC179"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB5907961C1B4B1CA210116D37F9D342"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Service animal</header><text>The term <quote>service animal</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 382.3 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H75401E6BFD4D4DEC950B8F4EA88570C1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Seating accommodations for qualified individuals with disabilities</header> 
<subsection id="H061FE3972B7D48E2AFD0235CADF5F82A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<paragraph id="HAD4C2F925AB8445BBAFB55BC779A8938"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advanced notice of proposed rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall issue an advanced notice of proposed rulemaking regarding seating accommodations for any qualified individual with a disability.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8654A45403A54E24B91C5DC2116A65D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice of proposed rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the advanced notice of proposed rulemaking under paragraph (1) is completed, the Secretary shall issue a notice of proposed rulemaking regarding seating accommodations for any qualified individual with a disability.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA12F4E5BD75C41E08A8319FECA757BDB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Final rule</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the notice of proposed rulemaking under paragraph (2) is completed, the Secretary shall issue a final rule regarding seating accommodations for any qualified individual with a disability.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7C550CE87AB242EE9F0EE24C0BBEEABF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In carrying out any rulemaking under subsection (a), the Secretary shall consider the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE9ADA0E1232444A4839E2B532DD1A826"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The scope and anticipated number of qualified individuals with a disability who—</text> <subparagraph id="H72A57CD7B9E344BE8A9693CD5DED9E51"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may need to be seated with a companion to receive assistance during a flight; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H67F38BF27D134CC08A2FE5723136C47E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>should be afforded bulkhead seats or other seating considerations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE35A297D2A64165ADB7240CCA5A2E77"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The types of disabilities that may need seating accommodations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H696FE23CAA03495782F99A26DEF25C8F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Whether such qualified individuals with a disability are unable to obtain, or have difficulty obtaining, such a seat.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BB2790168B4486C8FB14C7B29B2B60B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The scope and anticipated number of individuals assisting a qualified individual with a disability who should be afforded an adjoining seat pursuant to section 382.81 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H144AD236D9C449FA88C0A0A97A5284B5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any notification given to qualified individuals with a disability regarding available seating accommodations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC71BF1276B0A4D5281C7C6B49A154DCE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any method that is adequate to identify fraudulent claims for seating accommodations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H939C817C2A9846AC9396671D2C2FD3C1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other information determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H7971B166409C454FA0A3E38ABA6109D1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Known service animal user travel pilot program</header> <subsection id="HA0037D3F59E34775AAA143A3BB9F40EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program</header> <paragraph id="HE2116F668A49437CBDBB19242743CAB0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <subparagraph id="HBD34398B8C514365A341C2453ACCD6F8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a pilot program to allow approved program participants as known service animal users for the purpose of exemption from the documentation requirements under part 382 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, with respect to air travel with a service animal.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H140C4373A2064A60BF6F32945BCB6B87"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The pilot program established under subparagraph (A) shall—</text> <clause id="HBB45CC4193304A85902A70A8EE97FAAC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be optional;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF3CC6898250E4B2CB24941BCE826EDF0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide to applicants assistance, including over-the-phone assistance, throughout the application process for the program;</text></clause> <clause id="H87787C8D22F34988B83FA8642F6FD0ED"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with respect to any web-based components of the pilot program, meet or exceed the standards described in section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794d">29 U.S.C. 794d</external-xref>) and the regulations implementing that Act as set forth in part 1194 of title 36, Code of Federal Regulations; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2842B4713E2A4F51B4B454347B8779CA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>exempt participants of the pilot program from any documentation requirements under part 382 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE2439D4E2F424F1B90F0EB13F9C5D064"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In establishing the pilot program under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consult with—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE63A72D4C37B4CB7A9A62AFE23C4F98B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disability advocacy entities, including nonprofit organizations focused on ensuring that individuals with disabilities are able to live and participate in their communities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H10052FAB3B7048F8AB7E8D9CBB51227C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>air carriers and foreign air carriers;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB7410F769645442890A0107E3515B021"><enum>(C)</enum><text>accredited service animal training programs and authorized registrars, such as the International Guide Dog Federation, Assistance Dogs International, and other similar organizations and foreign and domestic governmental registrars of service animals;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3CE1A33AF8684227A7F3BE0DA8D5A5C9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other relevant departments or agencies of the Federal Government; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7E9600611179434EAAFFAB333622B81C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>other entities determined to be appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBB51122527414A4697466037097569B7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to participate in the pilot program under this subsection, an individual shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF2714061C32E4AEA98BB465019F9FF38"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be a qualified individual with a disability;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H56B5DDA0B54D42ED85640587EEE66C3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>require the use of a service animal because of a disability; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF60F9D6495814CD9BB5892F3D686FE42"><enum>(C)</enum><text>submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE301E20D6EA04EF5B317CF56005F3B77"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>The Secretary may award a grant or enter into a contract or cooperative agreement in order to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0FBC06E4A3174B62898EEF9C55196718"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Nominal fee</header><text>The Secretary may require an applicant to pay a nominal fee (not to exceed $25) to participate in the pilot program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4C719F8AC93F4CE7A3BD53F719184751"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Reports to congress</header> <subparagraph id="H206E249808E2496FB16F00AA50CB9D7C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Planning report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a publicly available report describing the implementation plan for the pilot program under this subsection.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H49979E03ABFF4192B9269E0A27CF72B6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the establishment of the pilot program under this subsection, and annually thereafter until the date described in paragraph (7), the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a publicly available report on the progress of the pilot program.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H052EAAB6FFF649A386AE468BC551D943"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a publicly available final report that includes recommendations for the establishment and implementation of a permanent known service animal user travel program for the Federal Government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5F70B6C003F6477DA9984CF7830B3750"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The pilot program shall terminate on the date that is 5 years after the date of enactment of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H404E54AD40B542AB89E66BDDAA93BFD1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Accredited service animal training programs and authorized registrars</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall publish on the website of the Department of Transportation and maintain a list of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H88CFD72C7D304D3DA70FF7BCD0D49734"><enum>(1)</enum><text>accredited programs that train service animals; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H06A91AED4E29466EA60A8632F4B691BA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>authorized registrars that evaluate service animals.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB06BE4C8FD224BEB8C6CB33733F9C753"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to congress on service animal requests</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on requests for air travel with service animals, including—</text> <paragraph id="H39EE06E4C0564FBFB39B1E788050E821"><enum>(1)</enum><text>during the reporting period, how many requests to board an aircraft with a service animal were made; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H00B1C82E61A74A18B29B6BE01128F6C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number and percentage of such requests, categorized by type of request, that were reported by air carriers or foreign air carriers as—</text> <subparagraph id="H95FD06EC052948AF85D83BFA45790D0E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>granted;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD2176C21E9AB40F6B19850A6E29D9E4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>denied; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7B56EE80668D49FA8070BE87A8690CBD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>fraudulent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3CDCFAEAA75040348C037CF9487AC702"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Training</header> 
<paragraph id="HB062DDE6B6EC479C889502D00CCFAD7C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall, in consultation with the Air Carrier Access Act Advisory Committee, issue guidance regarding improvements to training for airline personnel (including contractors) in recognizing when a qualified individual with a disability is traveling with a service animal.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAEE1F2984FAD4662802A53CC7148394A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The guidance issued under paragraph (1) shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEA42096F43164E2CB60E2B999F96B2F1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>take into account respectful engagement with and assistance for individuals with a wide range of visible and non-visible disabilities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF83D7A44EE304C91B717AB1BE0B538AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide information on—</text> 
<clause id="H89D34F6D732048B6A266733B96F14317"><enum>(i)</enum><text>service animal behavior and whether the service animal is appropriately harnessed, leashed, or otherwise tethered; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA606407C7F624D0C8C386DFA51413DA0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the various types of service animals, such as guide dogs, hearing or signal dogs, psychiatric service dogs, sensory or social signal dogs, and seizure response dogs; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE781CB66921D475DA29A8B83BDA05353"><enum>(C)</enum><text>outline the rights and responsibilities of the handler of the service animal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

