<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6A43AEC3436A4E0F9106F8DA9196B84B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6331 IH: Delivering Optimally Urgent Labor Access for Veterans Affairs Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6331</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. Gonz&#225;lez-Col&#243;n</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to establish a pilot program to furnish doula services to veterans.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H632F08EDBA224C8B84CFB9E048E8D6DE" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H411D8452D0C04D6BB950E46BB81C5BD0"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Delivering Optimally Urgent Labor Access for Veterans Affairs Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>DOULA for VA Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0FB4228B3AAA43C99B7324825B21CD6E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program on doula support for veterans</header> <subsection id="H08EB3E0EA1DD40B6ABC218BE1048654B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HBFE7F47F60B4440DB2C518ECDFC059FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>There are approximately 2,300,000 women within the veteran population in the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H980F99782E17409DA5E0023011B6762D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The number of women veterans using services from the Veterans Health Administration has increased by 28.8 percent from 423,642 in 2014 to 545,670 in 2019.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD4150198B24A44369DF4EAB65577571A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>During the period of 2010 through 2015, the use of maternity services from the Veterans Health Administration increased by 44 percent.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B3E2AFFCEAB4F2D8CBF8257F40DA2A1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Although prenatal care and delivery is not provided in facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs, pregnant women seeking care from the Department for other conditions may also need emergency care and require coordination of services through the Veterans Community Care Program under section 1703 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H43945DD9CA8747D4998A2A96FF8C9B4A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The number of unique women veteran patients with an obstetric delivery paid for by the Department increased by 1,778 percent from 200 deliveries in 2000 to 3,756 deliveries in 2015.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBD2AB0FAB08F4F5ABF44473AF65F83F9"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The number of women age 35 years or older with an obstetric delivery paid for by the Department increased 16-fold from fiscal year 2000 to fiscal year 2015.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9AFD277DEC954B49B8B264D9DCAF650E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A study in 2010 found that veterans returning from Operation Enduring Freedom and Operation Iraqi Freedom who experienced pregnancy were twice as likely to have a diagnosis of depression, anxiety, posttraumatic stress disorder, bipolar disorder, or schizophrenia as those who had not experienced a pregnancy. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3D2D521715E44D338EC0D8D72F067BFE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The number of women veterans of reproductive age seeking care from the Veterans Health Administration continues to grow (more than 185,000 as of fiscal year 2015).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC156BD4FC756411885ED42C50B7CED02"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program</header> 
<paragraph id="HB8F3028220B44C85A7E4D13C6B9C7E51"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish a pilot program to furnish doula services to covered veterans through eligible entities by expanding the Whole Health model of the Department of Veterans Affairs, or successor model, to measure the impact that doula support services have on birth and mental health outcomes of pregnant veterans (in this section referred to as the <quote>pilot program</quote>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB2AD996E03E4B71B2DA537A7F6BF825"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text>In carrying out the pilot program, the Secretary shall consider all types of doulas, including traditional and community-based doulas.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H13816C2CA54B4BFC9614903D802AF8EE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In designing and implementing the pilot program, the Secretary shall consult with stakeholders, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H4F45A0E600214E6D8F9E38C513E2C96D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>organizations representing veterans, including veterans that are disproportionately impacted by poor maternal health outcomes;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H18A014D9133645D7801C05A9F518E1CA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>community-based health care professionals, including doulas, and other stakeholders; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDC24E972A46C47E8ADE2A844AF10FA61"><enum>(C)</enum><text>experts in promoting health equity and combating racial bias in health care settings. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H53FAD961087144AAA6C4C68ABB108E87"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Goals</header><text>The goals of the pilot program are the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HD3C6ADEB724049038955E4047C639868"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To improve—</text> 
<clause id="HA9372BE474D6457CB75F1BB8B779A577"><enum>(i)</enum><text>maternal, mental health, and infant care outcomes;</text></clause> <clause id="H351CBF4497CF4D05B6371191EC994506"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>integration of doula support services into the Whole Health model of the Department, or successor model; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB805B50392B4DB1A16A05495B31F02E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the experience of women receiving maternity care from the Department, including by increasing the ability of a woman to develop and follow her own birthing plan.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0DC463B8D8CD4CA599691316A5C6604B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To reengage veterans with the Department after giving birth.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H90B9B98A395B4B4E85ECDF86637DD4BF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Locations</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out the pilot program in—</text> <paragraph id="HC2BF67CF1AED4E428EB1ECB0B8B95016"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the three Veterans Integrated Service Networks of the Department that have the highest percentage of female veterans enrolled in the patient enrollment system of the Department established and operated under section 1705(a) of title 38, United States Code, compared to the total number of enrolled veterans in such Network;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE61CFE0C7B88495B9879FCFFD6549A7B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the three Veterans Integrated Service Networks that have the lowest percentage of female veterans enrolled in the patient enrollment system compared to the total number of enrolled veterans in such Network; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCE670CC567974085BF408618C3CC2834" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>at least one Veterans Integrated Services Network—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0BC321CFEE1A4A4E88591163D144DB1F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">located in or serving a Frontier State (as defined in section 1886(d)(3)(E)(iii)(II) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww(d)(3)(E)(iii)(II)</external-xref>)) where more than <fraction>1/3</fraction> of the population lives in frontier land; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5AFF9A129F1B4067BE59AF12DD0399FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serving populations experiencing higher average risk and prevalence for maternal mental health disorders, including American Indian or Alaska Native veterans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC21A601D43FC47BBB97E46383A68D4CD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Open participation</header><text>The Secretary shall allow any eligible entity or covered veteran interested in participating in the pilot program to participate in the pilot program. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H4E41DB3183E8428B95066001B61278E5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Services provided</header> <paragraph id="HB615B817AF02434CA72D7863A16CCFE0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Under the pilot program, a covered veteran shall receive not more than 10 sessions of care from a doula under the Whole Health model of the Department, or successor model, under which a doula works as an advocate for the veteran alongside the medical team for the veteran.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H07BE65B255654587878E03EE81D32F29"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sessions</header><text>Sessions covered under paragraph (1) shall be as follows:</text> <subparagraph id="H980668F6A95E40308C0EB99018C076F1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Three or four sessions before labor and delivery.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8C89F71537244AF5B593884C9CCF35A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>One session during labor and delivery.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H076B7529E54C4EFC803BA8D237652C68"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Three or four sessions after post-partum, which may be conducted via the mobile application for VA Video Connect. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB6ECE512890B4CD4A77C27EFCBA51720"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Administration of pilot program</header> 
<paragraph id="HB9E7989B51964AE5BDC1CDCC0E386072"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of Women’s Health of the Department of Veterans Affairs, or successor office (in this section referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>), shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HB2996708CAD249A98301440F3ADD3680"><enum>(A)</enum><text>coordinate services and activities under the pilot program;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA5B5B86E4A0341A1912083A971D8F7AB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>oversee the administration of the pilot program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8C8EAA53CAEF4D489D2965B859D365BD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>conduct onsite assessments of medical facilities of the Department that are participating in the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD5D74E4EE3AC445AB96D04FBA52D08F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidelines for veteran-specific care</header><text>The Office shall establish guidelines under the pilot program for training doulas on military sexual trauma and post traumatic stress disorder. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD6F248418C4440FC87BBDDF42D117934"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Amounts for care</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office may recommend to the Secretary appropriate payment amounts for care and services provided under the pilot program, which shall not exceed $3,500 per doula per veteran. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5CA409EB2148482EB5FAC7EDD4EECFB3"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Doula Service Coordinator</header> 
<paragraph id="HB545A8FC54AE4C22A99DF7211C2D9EEE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in consultation with the Office, shall establish a Doula Service Coordinator within the functions of the Maternity Care Coordinator at each medical facility of the Department that is participating in the pilot program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0FBB028A686949399911B9891355F92C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>A Doula Service Coordinator established under paragraph (1) at a medical facility shall be responsible for—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBE1453EFFED44CEB9653D165A1DDC71D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>working with eligible entities, doulas, and covered veterans participating in the pilot program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA5E20BF5DC4D46568FF00A9BB8BC12B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>managing payment between eligible entities and the Department under the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE36F7C652C974351B337D5A651E67007"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Tracking of information</header><text>A doula providing services under the pilot program shall report to the applicable Doula Service Coordinator after each session conducted under the pilot program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H865791E96F994D11906A8E97736F45F5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Coordination with women's program manager</header><text>A Doula Service Coordinator for a medical facility of the Department shall coordinate with the women's program manager for that facility in carrying out the duties of the Doula Service Coordinator under the pilot program.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDD1CED23937641C7AE8B98287B8B6BF5"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Term of pilot program</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct the pilot program for a period of five years.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB08B43601F0048B38D0E1E0AAAD3D42D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a process to provide technical assistance to eligible entities and doulas participating in the pilot program.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3DBA986D3BF34F318A549F79122F86F8"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="HC778098A558D4225902A931A87C2D5C6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for each year in which the pilot program is carried out, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the pilot program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1FA6454E6134791B6F1DF647121971D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>As part of the final report submitted under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall include recommendations on whether the model studied in the pilot program should be continued or more widely adopted by the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8A598ECB8A37488D84B6110A80547435"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary, for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029, such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H60C72B35815A46E5B11DC2CDC3CD588F"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6DFCC8BA70C74ACA9E2201D186B5DE2D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered veteran</header><text>The term <term>covered veteran</term> means a pregnant veteran or a formerly pregnant veteran (with respect to sessions post-partum) who is enrolled in the patient enrollment system of the Department of Veterans Affairs established and operated under section 1705(a) of title 38, United States Code. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3578200D753543FBBD4EBE2A18FFCA64"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity that provides medically accurate, comprehensive maternity services to covered veterans under the laws administered by the Secretary, including under the Veterans Community Care Program under section 1703 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEB5B3088713847DD8F1E788102DFBF24"><enum>(3)</enum><header>VA Video Connect</header><text>The term <term>VA Video Connect</term> means the program of the Department of Veterans Affairs to connect veterans with their health care team from anywhere, using encryption to ensure a secure and private session. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

