<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H82B513C508344F03BE002C151D367AF3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2661 IH: Project Safe Childhood Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2661</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230417">April 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="H001095">Mr. Hunt</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reauthorize and update the Project Safe Childhood program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB6CA228CAF2F4DC8883E4EACB3689A3D" style="OLC"><section id="H468C7C6DB0B54DA6B23685F3BDE77317" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Project Safe Childhood Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H67CC821C2BDD4A89B36062EB06013323"><enum>2.</enum><header>Project Safe Childhood modernization</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 143 of the Adam Walsh Child Protection and Safety Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20942">34 U.S.C. 20942</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H159B4D0511DF415DB345BDBB09C90605"><section id="HD4D9B2BACFB94A68A3F1C35F5093A984"><enum>143.</enum><header>Project Safe Childhood</header><subsection id="H182934E1E3D1458DB885BBBB8341CB1D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H13AA2E9157AD4880A60281818BC87BCF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Child sexual abuse material</header><text>The term <term>child sexual abuse material</term> has the meaning given the term <term>child pornography</term> in section 2256 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H081AA624E1384C7AB0BFE31BA1F39196"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Child sexual exploitation offense</header><text>The term <term>child sexual exploitation offense</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H1D81ED61E6F44EC5AA94524E70D4EA65"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H316445910DD141E8A07196AFC3EB2C1D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an offense involving a minor under section 1591 or <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/117">chapter 117</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code;</text></clause><clause id="HCE18627C366E4D46B1F87D435EC6EA5A" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an offense under subsection (a), (b), or (c) of section 2251 of title 18, United States Code;</text></clause><clause id="H17A1B91845F24A91BF1410FDA5292538" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an offense under section 2251A or 2252A(g) of title 18, United States Code; or</text></clause><clause id="HBDD5944EB1D245FEA2B9FFFE28238000" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any attempt or conspiracy to commit an offense described in clause (i) or (ii); or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66125DBB23FA4A58B2BC525597CBA3B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an offense involving a minor under a State or Tribal statute that is similar to a provision described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4CED8399DE545429C4E5BCE9B8558C0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Circle of trust offender</header><text>The term <term>circle of trust offender</term> means an offender who is related to, or in a position of trust, authority, or supervisory control with respect to, a child.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H597D320CBD6E4C138077B0166A378C12"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Computer</header><text>The term <term>computer</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1030 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA8F87CCDD404C9CB1F903093718DB5A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Contact sexual offense</header><text>The term <term>contact sexual offense</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HC0AA336A51744154972459F445E6B491"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an offense involving a minor under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/109A">chapter 109A</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, or any attempt or conspiracy to commit such an offense; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C2972BA432A43FE9545C3C55B4B2768"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an offense involving a minor under a State or Tribal statute that is similar to a provision described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C73431EC0B34ED5963FC716C4EB4B6A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Dual offender</header><text>The term <term>dual offender</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H4E81BC397FD9400583C77DCDB1F5F3DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a person who commits—</text><clause id="H4F2D558887994DACB8C8CE7473642348"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a technology-facilitated child sexual exploitation offense or an offense involving child sexual abuse material; and</text></clause><clause id="HD69D07FF46D3432EBB961DECFAD06DA0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a contact sexual offense; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H046C75FDE5D94125B53F3E0CE73B57A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>without regard to whether the offenses described in clauses (i) and (ii) of subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H146D8516E9AA4070BF602A8ABDBE7F8C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are committed as part of the same course of conduct; or</text></clause><clause id="HAF9643299C3748DBB1A8D7B8BB203C30"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>involve the same victim.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF97A2E950BCB4416BFCF8367233FB7CF"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Facilitator</header><text>The term <term>facilitator</term> means an individual who facilitates the commission by another individual of—</text><subparagraph id="H7F0F19BE86F843908AA004AA41367567"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a technology-facilitated child sexual exploitation offense or an offense involving child sexual abuse material; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1ACFEF4142D3496AA44D0B573539220F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a contact sexual offense.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H814635FFB9F243D6B7195E7EB0271975"><enum>(8)</enum><header>ICAC affiliate partner</header><text>The term <term>ICAC affiliate partner</term> means a law enforcement agency that has entered into a formal operating agreement with the ICAC Task Force Program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBE6040710054EEDAF37A81F9F2945A7"><enum>(9)</enum><header>ICAC task force</header><text>The term <term>ICAC task force</term> means a task force that is part of the ICAC Task Force Program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE826624C945489FA613D4F48CA98764"><enum>(10)</enum><header>ICAC Task Force Program</header><text>The term <term>ICAC Task Force Program</term> means the National Internet Crimes Against Children Task Force Program established under section 102 of the PROTECT Our Children Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/21112">34 U.S.C. 21112</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F85C978B02E43B7AB15F493237AA11C"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Offense involving child sexual abuse material</header><text>The term <term>offense involving child sexual abuse material</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H9EFF748D85724F99B303070F9D17EB3C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an offense under section 2251(d), section 2252, or paragraphs (1) through (6) of section 2252A(a) of title 18, United States Code, or any attempt or conspiracy to commit such an offense; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA66F83B424594E678D95DA969067C760"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an offense under a State or Tribal statute that is similar to a provision described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFC11C4B5AAC44ABB9B32CF9E7B986CA"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Serious offender</header><text>The term <term>serious offender</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H9D929BC5C3464DFE9D60618E9DF825F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an offender who has committed a contact sexual offense or child sexual exploitation offense;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H535171C4F2FD4C26B6E89F3BD01CBD5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a dual offender, circle of trust offender, or facilitator; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA5E6FEE1FBB41F48E4F7CDA07F0560F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an offender with a prior conviction for a contact sexual offense, a child sexual exploitation offense, or an offense involving child sexual abuse material.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0FA9B7E01DB4303932DD94612B7CFCF"><enum>(13)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means a State of the United States, the District of Columbia, and any commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0685B498F94841B28A8538E3818CCEEC"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Technology-facilitated</header><text>The term <term>technology-facilitated</term>, with respect to an offense, means an offense that is committed through the use of a computer, even if the use of a computer is not an element of the offense.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H85431DDD59754A84A3EF23595313A9AC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of program</header><text>The Attorney General shall create and maintain a nationwide initiative to align Federal, State, and local entities to combat the growing epidemic of online child sexual exploitation and abuse, to be known as the <quote>Project Safe Childhood program</quote>, in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H27DD97F5BECD41FEA6F1B0B35BC3C037"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>The Attorney General, in coordination with the Child Exploitation and Obscenity Section of the Criminal Division of the Department of Justice and the Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention of the Department of Justice, and in consultation with training and technical assistance providers under the ICAC Task Force Program who are funded by the Attorney General and with appropriate nongovernmental organizations, shall—</text><paragraph id="H2D8BB5841FC749BDBB0CB9A8C79E49BB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop best practices to adopt a balanced approach to the investigation of suspect leads involving contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, and offenses involving child sexual abuse material, and the prosecution of those offenses, prioritizing when feasible the identification of a child victim or a serious offender, which approach shall incorporate the use of—</text><subparagraph id="HBB5878C1639C42E7AE59A7CE2628725D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>proactively generated leads, including leads generated by current and emerging technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44DAA05785614DA684F910026E4CD0F3" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in-district investigative referrals; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA12272F8D43246D8B6FC3FBC68A58137"><enum>(C)</enum><text>CyberTipline reports from the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3303F6B0C274DCFAF7F124F0E491D3D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop best practices to be used by each United States Attorney and ICAC task force to assess the likelihood that an individual could be a serious offender or that a child victim may be identified;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA92CF2F324F40FA91673615228AE740"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop and implement a tracking and communication system for Federal, State, and local law enforcement agencies and prosecutor’s offices to report successful cases of victim identification and child rescue to the Department of Justice and the public; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC94D7C8BAFF42E0BD92756E4256B241"><enum>(4)</enum><text>encourage the submission of all lawfully seized visual depictions to the Child Victim Identification Program of the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2915732952B94C8BA2CC58A9DF91F2A7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>Except as authorized under subsection (e), funds authorized under this section may only be used for the following 4 purposes:</text><paragraph id="H4AAB5B30E9AE4AD193290E25F2EABCFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Integrated Federal, State, and local efforts to investigate and prosecute contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, and offenses involving child sexual abuse material, including—</text><subparagraph id="HA049F6A6B77544C7A1741B9D4010CE20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the partnership by each United States Attorney with each Internet Crimes Against Children Task Force within the district of such attorney;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02F20A9C75434FD88CF8F30DF9938067"><enum>(B)</enum><text>training of Federal, State, and local law enforcement officers and prosecutors through—</text><clause id="H0C4922AE2BE44A1686E9C9462517F5E8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>programs facilitated by the ICAC Task Force Program;</text></clause><clause id="H286301CB38D04096AD986C80D819E351"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ICAC training programs supported by the Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention of the Department of Justice;</text></clause><clause id="H850C8DEDEF434DD3A50575C142905BBD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>programs facilitated by appropriate nongovernmental organizations with subject matter expertise, technical skill, or technological tools to assist in the identification of and response to serious offenders, contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, or offenses involving child sexual abuse material; and</text></clause><clause id="H352477577EF64A77871EF35BEB07AA5D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any other program that provides training—</text><subclause id="HA504851CCC964840A76CA4E9547F7597"><enum>(I)</enum><text>on the investigation and identification of serious offenders or victims of contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, or offenses involving child sexual abuse material; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H92AE1CEB1DEE423497C019A745855147"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that specifically addresses the use of existing and emerging technologies to commit or facilitate contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, or offenses involving child sexual abuse material;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9568A0DF6D504D52B9169242747EBC90"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the development by each United States Attorney of a district-specific strategic plan to coordinate with State and local law enforcement agencies and prosecutor’s offices, including ICAC task forces and their ICAC affiliate partners, on the investigation of suspect leads involving serious offenders, contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, and offenses involving child sexual abuse material, and the prosecution of those offenders and offenses, which plan—</text><clause id="HD75DAA9AB1434DE39836474BFDDD8C51"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall include—</text><subclause id="H4707648F577B4C5C8A769B9C07B551D8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the use of the best practices developed under paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (c);</text></subclause><subclause id="H19B6D049048240AC89124B88F6BB4D09"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the development of plans and protocols to target and rapidly investigate cases involving potential serious offenders or the identification and rescue of a victim of a contact sexual offense, a child sexual exploitation offense, or an offense involving child sexual abuse material; </text></subclause><subclause id="HCD4424539BDB4AD6AAE1B0EEDBF81653"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the use of training and technical assistance programs to incorporate victim-centered, trauma-informed practices in cases involving victims of contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, and offenses involving child sexual abuse material, which may include the use of child protective services, children’s advocacy centers, victim support specialists, or other supportive services;</text></subclause><subclause id="H64BBE4C9B203466AAA480AB5DA626251"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the development of plans to track, report, and clearly communicate successful cases of victim identification and child rescue to the Department of Justice and the public;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC6DCCE9538764FF282429786C281ADC6"><enum>(V)</enum><text>an analysis of the investigative and forensic capacity of law enforcement agencies and prosecutor’s offices within the district, and goals for improving capacity and effectiveness;</text></subclause><subclause id="H7F6A171293CB401DAF7F24B10208E44B"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>a written policy describing the criteria for referrals for prosecution from Federal, State, or local law enforcement agencies, particularly when the investigation may involve a potential serious offender or the identification or rescue of a child victim;</text></subclause><subclause id="H939A2194B8914C6EA167BC7D54353688"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>plans and budgets for training of relevant personnel on contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, and offenses involving child sexual abuse material;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD6CE92CF924944B5A5A0BC7CDB1B9639"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>plans for coordination and cooperation with State, local, and Tribal law enforcement agencies and prosecutorial offices; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HAA25DD3BF245407C8F2794681167A360"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>evidence-based programs that educate the public about and increase awareness of such offenses; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H368E63E633F2486B9D49B59163BC129E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall be developed in consultation, as appropriate, with—</text><subclause id="HB7E84DF8849F4EE8B91C23AB5302394E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the local ICAC task force;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC57C32846B1B484AB2A54757C656CD5F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the United States Marshals Service Sex Offender Targeting Center;</text></subclause><subclause id="H8B66B075CD8244A98C0DC2A41743E88A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>training and technical assistance providers under the ICAC Task Force Program who are funded by the Attorney General;</text></subclause><subclause id="H7BD57DA6A1F448909ABF1121623ECD2E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>nongovernmental organizations with subject matter expertise, technical skill, or technological tools to assist in the identification of and response to contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, or offenses involving child sexual abuse material;</text></subclause><subclause id="H71F20D78AEB5400983F05CA2443E341F"><enum>(V)</enum><text>any relevant component of Homeland Security Investigations;</text></subclause><subclause id="H24103BF69F0F46CE95DF9A43418DA81D"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>any relevant component of the Federal Bureau of Investigation;</text></subclause><subclause id="HAD4BECD9E57244FA80095366CEE3EC9F"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>the Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention of the Department of Justice;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD1E3A7F9DB184A15AB696B8D72F4BBDD"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>the Child Exploitation and Obscenity Section of the Criminal Division of the Department of Justice;</text></subclause><subclause id="H415D7C6304A641449FA7896A481712B9"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>the United States Postal Inspection Service;</text></subclause><subclause id="H339AF56B3D36496D8375A2AD75EAC2D6"><enum>(X)</enum><text>the United States Secret Service; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H8376EF725399483FB7CA104A36825844"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>each military criminal investigation organization of the Department of Defense; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70B22C33F7E94600A0A2C2622347D3A5" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a quadrennial assessment by each United States Attorney of the investigations within the district of such attorney of contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, and offenses involving child sexual abuse material—</text><clause commented="no" id="HC199DE1646C24E25BBF4F59813281304"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with consideration of—</text><subclause commented="no" id="H03189DC41E6645DE82933DDA7E4671F9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the variety of sources for leads;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HF25AF00849574A21A88053CD25AF0EF5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the proportion of work involving proactive or undercover law enforcement investigations;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H00DA469ACEC447A0A2833483A6E42747"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the number of serious offenders identified and prosecuted; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H0847FF52F95E429582F5B65C2140BF73"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the number of children identified or rescued; and</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HC3AC48BC0FE1403AAFDF31835B5B311A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>information from which may be used by the United States Attorney, as appropriate, to revise the plan described in subparagraph (C).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H15A9485B5C104D7DB73EA74A1BCC344E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Major case coordination by the Department of Justice (or other Federal agencies as appropriate), including specific cooperation, as appropriate, with—</text><subparagraph id="H0E08FFA2E7804922A1C5E34D76BDCDE3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Child Exploitation and Obscenity Section of the Criminal Division of the Department of Justice;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3C3F613888742A1B8BAD73EDC827E9E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any relevant component of Homeland Security Investigations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B7CE083BC424CBE99579790FBD86620"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any relevant component of the Federal Bureau of Investigation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA35C530DEA8457D9B5094BF0EC19FC3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the ICAC task forces and ICAC affiliate partners;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H622E55430F8F4B18A90EEC734BA5DAA5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the United States Marshals Service, including the Sex Offender Targeting Center;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD64E8ED368B94E62B5AC08854023C203"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the United States Postal Inspection Service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF72CD20BCA714BE691D74A0A8D57CB29"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the United States Secret Service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AEC07351BB44E17982814C95517BCAA"><enum>(H)</enum><text>each Military Criminal Investigation Organization of the Department of Defense; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1708C033B6E249A0902E2AC7C6FC9334"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any task forces established in connection with the Project Safe Childhood program set forth under subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3D6B8A402004708B7A3B00ED9FD7697"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Increased Federal involvement in, and commitment to, the prevention and prosecution of technology-facilitated child sexual exploitation offenses or offenses involving child sexual abuse material by—</text><subparagraph id="H28EC7D17A1FA4F4F8D2F00A730B63F93"><enum>(A)</enum><text>using technology to identify victims and serious offenders;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3564AD03CAD3482A90E3B5B9CACBCF20"><enum>(B)</enum><text>developing processes and tools to identify victims and offenders; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB510F9676BC48BCBB12AB2B53868E83"><enum>(C)</enum><text>taking measures to improve information sharing among Federal law enforcement agencies, including for the purposes of implementing the plans and protocols described in paragraph (1)(C)(i)(II) to identify and rescue—</text><clause id="HF4AD1B2A45074DD7ACD4CF5D869D1F24"><enum>(i)</enum><text>victims of contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, and offenses involving child sexual abuse material; or</text></clause><clause id="H781153B524F34653B77E155083392271"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>victims of serious offenders.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E70713C3FD94723AB71CACCB630154F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The establishment, development, and implementation of a nationally coordinated <quote>Safer Internet Day</quote> every year developed in collaboration with the Department of Education, national and local internet safety organizations, parent organizations, social media companies, and schools to provide—</text><subparagraph id="H36BED512FE1B4185A61E2349EF9F4AFE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>national public awareness and evidence-based educational programs about the threats posed by circle of trust offenders and the threat of contact sexual offenses, child sexual exploitation offenses, or offenses involving child sexual abuse material, and the use of technology to facilitate those offenses;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC1A2EA9087F44DAA7947411EBF0D45D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>information to parents and children about how to avoid or prevent technology-facilitated child sexual exploitation offenses; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE07C1E2CD91B47EF9B39EDDD20EF68A0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>information about how to report possible technology-facilitated child sexual exploitation offenses or offenses involving child sexual abuse material through—</text><clause id="HB15628E18CC3496D941AEDFFF80F4A00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children;</text></clause><clause id="H6DEE5B0E8A95462A92D7A5DB4FAC4947"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the ICAC Task Force Program; and</text></clause><clause id="HCDE83A0FCA89425D94101B8F5802A753"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any other program that—</text><subclause id="H3288434898F847A39E9BA06B0A853E42"><enum>(I)</enum><text>raises national awareness about the threat of technology-facilitated child sexual exploitation offenses or offenses involving child sexual abuse material; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3761FEC0BD6B48B1B616353B1FD1AB46"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provides information to parents and children seeking to report possible violations of technology-facilitated child sexual exploitation offenses or offenses involving child sexual abuse material.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H22A3EF8D65F84107A42256F168A7A1BF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Expansion of Project Safe Childhood</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (d), funds authorized under this section may be also be used for the following purposes:</text><paragraph id="H4CCFD1411105401082DD4ACC684E018D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The addition of not less than 20 Assistant United States Attorneys at the Department of Justice, relative to the number of such positions as of the day before the date of enactment of the <short-title>Project Safe Childhood Act</short-title>, who shall be—</text><subparagraph id="HCBCF67D0361F4C418789480B820D447D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>dedicated to the prosecution of cases in connection with the Project Safe Childhood program set forth under subsection (b); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3006F4100DB44AFCB89DC5890C57CE4A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>responsible for assisting and coordinating the plans and protocols of each district under subsection (d)(1)(C)(i)(II).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H54E841ADAB234860935C3A6A2280D340"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Such other additional and related purposes as the Attorney General determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE23E53BDE85E4B339161EAE026F42670"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="HCCBAB01DEADA436F9F925C7D11D2E9AC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purpose of carrying out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated—</text><subparagraph id="HE06089CA33A140DB9AD328C6D9AE291D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for the activities described under paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (d), $28,550,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2028;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE2B8BB6BB8C4D4FAAEB4284C768448A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for the activities described under subsection (d)(4), $4,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2028; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9262238BCAB448DFA63E014F97711230"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for the activities described under subsection (e), $29,100,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2028.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0999C2C3C4D64C6B862D921004B1C1DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Amounts made available to State and local agencies, programs, and services under this section shall supplement, and not supplant, other Federal, State, or local funds made available for those agencies, programs, and services.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HA08259F20EE4476984B51C685DFF0B8E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Technical clarifications</header><subsection id="H7F351BDAB14340EC8FCCED028FA1D625"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H501A07B316794A7DB11794F3D9CADF58"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 1201—</text><subparagraph id="H65EF675705064BF79FA5B4A4F9AA79F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>obtains by defrauding or deceiving any person,</quote> after <quote>abducts,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C77D41B54784B22A98EA4C79399B5AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (g), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF0E07E8DCBE547B0A0C419565F09E4FC"><paragraph id="H2A8B284E9ED64CDDB008FC5DA0AF398E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Defense</header><text>For an offense described in this subsection involving a victim who has not attained the age of 16 years, it is not a defense that the victim consented to the offender’s conduct unless the offender can establish by a preponderance of the evidence that the offender reasonably believed that the victim had attained the age of 16 years.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H885A897D667843DB9AE5E37630360008"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in chapter 109A—</text><subparagraph id="H2F8E491C948147F5B0C334A2D5C310AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 2241—</text><clause id="HB0C02DB88481406EBB65EE548761186B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subclause id="H8112E5B194654DCDB15D08F2FC2D3214"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><item id="HBE115E3298FE432EB69B0EE8B4A18FE7"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></item><item id="H88B5F527F83C4E538911640AC024F8FC"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>a sexual act with</quote>; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H8573DCCEA31C4A4A852D578500D414A5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B)—</text><item id="H5ABFD8CC7B4745AE8D5060507D6F200E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></item><item id="H00BCE279EB3145758E73A2218F763CF8"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>a sexual act with</quote>;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H917B3E118F434149A72151FA79619375"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subclause id="H019112CD94434419BA8D95DF11F26D53"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>crosses a State line</quote> and inserting <quote>travels in interstate or foreign commerce</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5E1CAC85376645FE962D78F10A2EF8A0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or cause</quote> after <quote>engage in</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H0804B7FD0CD6492D8594FC742053434C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>a sexual act with</quote> each place it appears;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD6EB21B95AA41EC98842C00F99B7BE9"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>subsections (a) and (b) with</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA3F3D6F3CC9C4C46B9ED4D0F9BFA8179"><enum>(V)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote> each place it appears; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H03DF6890E55A4334B7B333B6C0A42AEA"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causing</quote> after <quote>so engaging</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H5E4D58D543F94C9886E0F26CB2E633E2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (d), by inserting <quote>or being caused to engage in</quote> after <quote>engaging in</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA51C07A62DA74C10816AFBE2B3CE0870"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 2242—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H482199541ED1416EB1D96397133C35DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="HB96219CDA1B24488BEF80E924A119E5C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HC25E00B8DE5F4673BE1CFD48C9E3F053"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>a sexual act with</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6E49FAA6AEC4EEB9244D95D97262E6D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><subclause id="H4A2DD928AB87406891427344709C1DE0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H5476763DF59449759B9A058B7A40BA28" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>a sexual act with</quote>;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9801FEBEF92449C9A7510623F062AEA8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 2243—</text><clause id="H448F2D725B5C4FCEACF6D86DE891C5E5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subclause id="H1E090E7C116E4491AAA57FF96CEE9072"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text><item id="HDD76861B5A174FF59112781413B34F44"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></item><item id="H07C8F9E1D4AD4F3B9E2B71D31521536D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>a sexual act with</quote>; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H546FA9A3781B410F8984AA0222A2BF79"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>or causing</quote> after <quote>so engaging</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HAC7F9795C74445788CD8AFDDD11C64F0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subclause id="HEA272E37845B4EA8B954079F8B38DAA6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text><item id="H08D8289835D545EE97E06CB7AE6BAEBF"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></item><item id="HD6FDF227837B4470849A24E18701334B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>a sexual act with</quote>; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H1FD04DF9D38E4036B8E277D86731859D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>or causing</quote> after <quote>so engaging</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HC7E6C5E046314ED786A87CFE7E2968E6" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H124B88ED719242579B3FCEF9B27FC0FB"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H426DA840BDC84F5E82C97CC993C3D6E5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>a sexual act with</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H6447B9E98B7646A7974A5D8C1E56C0C6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subsection (e)—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE3463CAC17FA4D4083ADCBCA03D8C63E"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>or being caused to engage in</quote> after <quote>engaging in</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H79AB48409B8E469CB5C6F0C9886EE99A"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>between the persons so engaging</quote> and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H853DDA4FE3044787A7C2C4DE3690031E"><text>between—</text><subparagraph id="H25303E217E5A4988BC536550958B7FE3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the defendant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H766C488DD264476587583DC0329F3639"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the person—</text><clause id="H7E8FA2CF2670484689D18FDC13B53A3F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with whom the defendant engaged in a sexual act; or</text></clause><clause id="H9A7E171C1FA24A7AAED4EC71D69EFA25"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whom the defendant caused to engage in a sexual act</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53609DFD7FD34C3EAF2ECA9EE6502F44"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in section 2244(b)—</text><clause id="H86BEEDC43F064AD49F6F1F21D0F6F1BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H19838633DD62416C8B2E7210E1CC96EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>sexual contact with</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF50D406EF9DD405FA15E34BD17B97FFB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 2423(f)(1)—</text><subparagraph id="HE42C66A7CC914027830CF560E44E61A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>a sexual act (as defined in section 2246) with</quote> and inserting <quote>any conduct involving</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05F72FDFC50D4B6D854EB5F23DEF51AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>sexual act occurred</quote> and inserting <quote>conduct occurred</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBCA71AE411204B2D8D820D1595DC59E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment to section 2241(c) of title 18, United States Code, made by subsection (a)(2)(A)(ii)(I) of this section shall apply to conduct that occurred before, on, or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF6FBBF85149B4F0D83DA5A9AF5E3E863"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sexual exploitation and other abuse of children</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title 18 of the United States Code is amended—</text><paragraph id="H187674BFFA0140D099972F795218AF56"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 1466A—</text><subparagraph id="H2BFD78053C5049049C43E3A776DA2BAB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)(A), by inserting <quote>, or includes a minor in such visual depiction of any adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct</quote> after <quote>sexually explicit conduct</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D13BC0F963B469BB4D91E3EDECBDF9A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1)(A), by inserting <quote>, or includes a minor in such visual depiction of any adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct</quote> after <quote>sexually explicit conduct</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43E40B503B664897872490137C19EA0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in chapter 109A—</text><subparagraph id="HFAF368EAAE024DD0A3786C719B60E705"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 2244—</text><clause id="H15018BCCEC604A9B97BFEE2CB09BC5B4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subclause id="HF462B814435A4A5797E052B465798A1C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) through (5) as subparagraphs (A) through (E), respectively, and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text></subclause><subclause id="H345684828ADF4F76B3FBED415AFEE28E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Whoever</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD02186AACE2542BA91C8191B4D5E10C8"><paragraph id="H201E48DD671F400B9EB4321F12B28037"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Whoever</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause><subclause id="HE507859DCFA74EEB9C2A5A407E82E0E9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), as so designated—</text><item id="HE037C5513AEA4BC8987231F7DC0EE557"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>if so to do</quote> and inserting <quote>if to do so</quote>;</text></item><item id="HD16323C02F394D9994792A1D41E5C555"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>ten</quote> and inserting <quote>10</quote>;</text></item><item id="H91F7B8D41DF2493A99BE16D460F6FFB0"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>three</quote> and inserting <quote>10’</quote>;</text></item><item id="H87EF582A11FF4E0DA7B8D8E02F4723EB"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>two</quote> and inserting <quote>5</quote>; and</text></item><item id="HFFA69CBDEFCA4327B51B58E1BF6AB3E0"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>two</quote> and inserting <quote>5</quote>; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H6876125E922040FEA2D2BA9CAA0C9FE2"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H93A4AFBF338843039D1AA63394B819A5"><paragraph id="H009FE700C52D4EF99DE215AC0156E3D7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Attempt</header><text>Whoever attempts to commit an offense under paragraph (1) shall be subject to the same penalty as for a completed offense.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="HCF8874F56D4042649D86C4E193C988DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subclause id="HAD20F74E621D4584A0BF49A8C35F6E74"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or causes</quote> after <quote>engages in</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H0C38AD3C5A5941838E984874F9E83C2F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or by</quote> after <quote>sexual contact with</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H3267783F2FBD4D2EB5FE5AC1F131EC9F"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or attempts to do so,</quote> after <quote>other person’s permission</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H29079A54B3A74D14ACFFA4D0ABD9DCAB"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by striking <quote>two</quote> and inserting <quote>2</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HA900ACD9BD9E49F7B1CC19F3472B03D6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>If the sexual contact that violates this section (other than subsection (a)(5)) is with an individual</quote> and inserting <quote>If the sexual contact or attempted sexual contact that a person engages in or causes in violation of this section (other than subsection (a)(1)(E)) is with or by an individual</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF43D9DAB3DAF4C37836F93B3B4764D2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 2246(2), by inserting after <quote>16 years</quote> the following: <quote>, or of any person by a person who has not attained the age of 16 years,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC22C0435F73E4DC8BBB7B4F775449A68"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in chapter 110—</text><subparagraph id="H013F9B0391AA481CAE5C01D3B9C1109D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 2251—</text><clause id="H498471EC2003432B997DD347770866A0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking subsections (a) and (b) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F20756753A444738A1580BE247F4627"><subsection id="H0D6D6D26B6534E23BE6C2470252FCC8D" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Any person who, in a circumstance described in subsection (f), engages in any of the following conduct shall be punished as provided under subsection (e):</text><paragraph id="HC718DBCC00EA4ECB9C20A05F701815DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Employs, uses, persuades, induces, entices, or coerces a minor to engage in any sexually explicit conduct for the purpose of producing any visual depiction of such conduct or transmitting a live visual depiction of such conduct.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13B303DE3F5E463F9ABAE12C564944B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Employs, uses, persuades, induces, entices, or coerces a minor to engage in any sexually explicit conduct and in the course thereof, knowingly produces or causes to be produced any visual depiction of such conduct, or transmits or causes to be transmitted a live visual depiction of such conduct.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10C4D627D615498CBB93458D3BA8D2DA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Engages in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor for the purpose of producing any visual depiction of such conduct or transmitting a live visual depiction of such conduct, intending that the minor be included in such visual depiction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H94A37FAE9B8F4CB48E8386ECE307D9C6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Engages in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor and in the course thereof, knowingly produces or causes to be produced any visual depiction of such conduct, or transmits or causes to be transmitted a live visual depiction of such conduct, intentionally including the minor in such visual depiction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20A47E946CBF41C49316C58DA46E64A6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Has a minor assist any other person to engage in any sexually explicit conduct during the commission of an offense set forth in paragraphs (1) through (4) of this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB67A87AE681E4046978B62E7262326AD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Transports any minor in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce with the intent that such minor be used in the production or live transmission of any visual depiction of a minor engaged in any sexually explicit conduct.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5E1947DA39ED4C4B879270631902B908"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Any parent, legal guardian, or person who has custody or control of a minor and, in a circumstance described in subsection (f), engages in any of the following conduct shall be punished as provided under subsection (e):</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H191762F1BBAA4955B3B45389741EB966"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Knowingly permits such minor to engage in, or to assist any other person to engage in, sexually explicit conduct—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB8A17B59DFEF46EBB0B9A7C71BAD944C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the purpose of producing any visual depiction of such conduct or transmitting a live visual depiction of such conduct; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H031302A7E6B84784A6FF4D86C2906DCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowing that any visual depiction of such conduct will be produced or transmitted.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H45B2C57D95F14CBF969D291B0ADDA335"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Knowingly permits an adult to engage in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of the minor—</text><subparagraph id="HDF9E484235F5419CB9677A2F2FA18712"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for the purpose of producing any visual depiction of such conduct or transmitting a live visual depiction of such conduct, intending that the minor be included in such visual depiction; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H610CF0E660654448BBA4E2F26CF6ACB1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>knowing that any visual depiction of such conduct will be produced or transmitted, intentionally including the minor in such visual depiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="HE7ECDB3C2685447B84CD24600FECA9E6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subclause id="HC3EA5950C6EF46F9A4F55D46C27B0B0D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><item id="H7719B75B2D9041BDBB6509FE9D072CF5"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by striking <quote>employs, uses, persuades, induces, entices, or coerces any minor to engage in, or who has a minor assist any other person to engage in, any sexually explicit conduct</quote> and inserting <quote>engages in any of the conduct described in paragraphs (1) through (5) of subsection (a)</quote>; and</text></item><item id="HD0C1808D34204DE48D2D016F6649DBE1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by striking <quote>for the purpose of producing any visual depiction of such conduct,</quote>; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H7927A5637DC145C5876FCA0777301C82"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><item id="H8F3D2650E5FE4B1F9DD004A76D49F5F2"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or transmitted</quote> after <quote>transported</quote>; and</text></item><item id="HDD22297C5F5B421191EAF4054C2A7FF0"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B) by inserting <quote>or transmits</quote> after <quote>transports</quote>;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H7003E7F8763A4FD2ABCAF1333F8B1837"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(1), by striking subparagraph (A) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H049D53BD049A41188A9D10D30094808E"><subparagraph id="H7D531CEC62F747D7907F5137A8D73CC2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to receive, exchange, buy, produce, display, distribute, or reproduce, any visual depiction, if—</text><clause id="H09E92A3894284767B3DB8B7A4923A9E9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the production of such visual depiction involves the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct and such visual depiction is of such conduct; or</text></clause><clause id="H79F49ED2E1134C7BA37899D8296A20AC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the production of such visual depiction involves an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor, such visual depiction is of such conduct, and the minor is intentionally included in the visual depiction; or</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="HB6780F19EAF54BA4BD181AC254901859"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H56A197AD92874D0687355A4770C9CEDB"><subsection id="H71C21DBA14AB45548AFF87292D546221"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Circumstances</header><text>The circumstance referred to in subsections (a) and (b) is that—</text><paragraph id="H164CBFB6966041F49C9492831F160DBC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the person knows or has reason to know that the visual depiction will be—</text><subparagraph id="H3DF5B11AB4E441CCB582FA839DCBBE2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transported or transmitted using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED0BB816C70547648A17242259D6EA2A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>transported or transmitted in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92F74A2177074017BF175EFFA2B94D87"><enum>(C)</enum><text>mailed;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H31A2747E36BA4FD7B46D0AC87B7F3D94"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the visual depiction was produced or transmitted using materials that have been—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32689E28DB9849678D3D0F7C7CCE4C73"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">mailed; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA3E20199E5D84A048BDD8FE6401CFB0C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shipped or transported in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce by any means, including by computer;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H251E6190189D47B4BF4F36691F608FF9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the visual depiction has actually been—</text><subparagraph id="H6D07C273C69B41CC97E67D038DB8223A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transported or transmitted using any means or facility of interstate or foreign commerce;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B41561FF0B848FFBBCAD8F836015B68"><enum>(B)</enum><text>transported or transmitted in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C0C00FF604341A69E099A06F8296A65"><enum>(C)</enum><text>mailed; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DCEC2F89FFA42198D9E6EA8BD0A2074"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any part of the offense occurred in a territory or possession of the United States or within the special maritime and territorial jurisdiction of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF6932AD8B004A5AAA27ECF47997A9CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 2251A—</text><clause id="H1112273E2D1D4519B849D906308DC6F4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subclause id="H4F695B5FAD414F5687A6BD980FDBE514"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>or control</quote> after <quote>transfer custody</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB94118EAD14542EA881CA637DCB7C81C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (1) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBBF4355F0B4540D2B83614A199C14750"><paragraph id="H6D1C27D87CEC41B58E032F063B630D81"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with knowledge that, as a consequence of the sale or transfer, the minor will be—</text><subparagraph id="H36624367D2C54E0E80BAFEC50C6FF3C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>portrayed in any visual depiction engaging in, or assisting another person to engage in, sexually explicit conduct; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45C2134D949743E3ABE99E05465C3608"><enum>(B)</enum><text>intentionally included in any visual depiction of an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of the minor; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause><subclause id="HC9AF24488D9B48648B87A6E6CAAACE15"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><item id="HFD410CC9596E4CD18729D30CB6001CBE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>either</quote>;</text></item><item id="H6814F54DC4B74A9CB05CF0D952852769"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></item><item id="HCC71996CEBFA45A0918A5455038BBA6F"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by adding <quote>or</quote> at the end; and</text></item><item id="HDCA04A0068264330ACECC329FD26B12D"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (B) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H913CD93112C7411BB671B652F389AD83"><subparagraph id="HD2706B6EDBD94C8DBF67B060EBB536CA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the intentional inclusion of the minor in any visual depiction of an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of the minor;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></item></subclause></clause><clause id="HC8E8327978E745289A7D54BD6191685C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subclause id="H5C37A702C96E40A2A58CC97428102D10"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (1) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA308E953E2B64FB4BBE3F6CED61D46DD"><paragraph id="H7891DD25E2B341A499B39BF392A8FFB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with knowledge that, as a consequence of the purchase or obtaining of custody or control, the minor will be—</text><subparagraph id="HB707CC8EE7674A8F8BD2607301F4A0BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>portrayed in any visual depiction engaging in, or assisting another person to engage in, sexually explicit conduct; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3773C0DA73394C749250ED491579B8CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>intentionally included in any visual depiction of an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of the minor; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause><subclause id="H5C84DAB0512C45E9AE408B90F0AAAA56"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><item id="H592211C1A358419D9904278A688E3256"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>either</quote>;</text></item><item id="HFE677E75D8534EC8B5D53C7CC384816F"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></item><item id="H0E25AC50E6274FF3949B1E0051F0A82C"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by adding <quote>or</quote> at the end; and</text></item><item id="H0FDD3967E88A4AD7AC6E1C22C53B1791"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (B) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D1FB125F5E74F1889ED63F857CE0AFF"><subparagraph id="HC9480610EB254F33987008BB77BE1312"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the intentional inclusion of the minor in any visual depiction of an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of the minor;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD730495CB03D4230A9CD672C179B1A08"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 2252(a)—</text><clause id="HCB852BFFB4434FDC836E15992E3B0FC8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking subparagraphs (A) and (B) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4B6A6529F36440BA58778233044015D"><subparagraph id="HCD5FDE38635E46658146B2B92BA40633"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the producing of such visual depiction involves the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct and such visual depiction is of such conduct; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AC796B0648C488B9DD9FF609355E989"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the producing of such visual depiction involves an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor, such visual depiction is of such conduct, and the minor is intentionally included in the visual depiction;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H8ACD40C1F7FF4A6CA818F7805A7B6866"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking subparagraphs (A) and (B) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1494995BDF2A4F6087E513E01A5D279F"><subparagraph id="HF609537DC8244FD98E7896EECBD82DAA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the producing of such visual depiction involves the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct and such visual depiction is of such conduct; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CA40BC7A7F6420EB7AE3055C1D99ACD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the producing of such visual depiction involves an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor, such visual depiction is of such conduct, and the minor is intentionally included in the visual depiction;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="HA68D985DAC444EC48B02CDFFB55BB418"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(B), by striking clauses (i) and (ii) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC950AD4489F04848947AB89994053041"><clause id="HEB6B59E9FBD542B683E9EC5B5ADC5BC2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the producing of such visual depiction involves the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct and such visual depiction is of such conduct; or</text></clause><clause id="H1EE2B1598CFD45EB8F5C51328BAA3FB7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the producing of such visual depiction involves an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor, such visual depiction is of such conduct, and the minor is intentionally included in the visual depiction;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H8EB4BEDEBCB5499F998E86F7E99CC8F6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)(B), by striking clauses (i) and (ii) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF6FFDED159064741AF7A07736EF4C7CC"><clause id="H8962CBF4E9A5477D87926222BEC23DAC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the producing of such visual depiction involves the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct and such visual depiction is of such conduct; or</text></clause><clause id="HE608162701EA45569177296FBEDC6227"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the producing of such visual depiction involves an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor, such visual depiction is of such conduct, and the minor is intentionally included in the visual depiction;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H91AE1F60665B48F69491885DCB558979"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in section 2256—</text><clause id="H58E46D4A66AC4E51A5F6E0D93B832D91"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (8)—</text><subclause id="H4DE10FEB122A4E79B7F8B51633A5D2AB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (A) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF92D3D8953B4140ADDDCBE2BBA52904"><subparagraph id="HA4607E235E1C4F6FB0D9642CA76565FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the production of such visual depiction involves—</text><clause id="HDB08EB3BA2DF475D9B32BFF6B16BC286"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct; or</text></clause><clause id="HC4FD4CA4508B49BE9BB18B8E4B3DE55D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor and the intentional inclusion of the minor in the visual depiction;</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause><subclause id="HBB3BA7481CF4425FA390A82787618A53"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by inserting after <quote>sexually explicit conduct</quote> the following: <quote>or that of a minor intentionally included in such visual depiction of an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H532197CA4D5A4E1CA3C9BCF9EBBEC7CF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by inserting after <quote>sexually explicit conduct.</quote> the following: <quote>or is intentionally included in such visual depiction of an adult engaging in sexually explicit conduct</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB31636ADC8074FBCB4CA89347898E6E2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon;</text></clause><clause id="HEFC782DD4EC14F0DA1C08A856D6B2CD1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in paragraph (10), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="HF4089D5B298A4BA38E357A7C2DB766AF" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in paragraph (11), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H7F48B8571CC446E8BE70966A8E7F7E0F" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98FB9AEEC0C04B279C27BEEF8A6E7847"><paragraph id="H620EFC0FD33B4618A0792AED4DBE66C1"><enum>(12)</enum><text>the terms <term>uses any minor to engage in</term>, <term>the use of a minor engaging in</term>, and <term>in the presence of a minor</term> do not require—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H83384E0F7F684F3E941B5D5335EA30A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the minor to be aware of, or to be capable of appraising the nature of, the sexually explicit conduct; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3D6B40D641EA4CF1B357B144EEDF9B6C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any direct engagement or active participation by the minor in the sexually explicit conduct.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B1B4DEB503D4A22BE8DBD8A28135A93"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in section 2260—</text><clause id="H9ED41CB4BC314E0C88381145611BC4CF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking subsection (a) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A536FAB6EB24552B1EF31D2A863B6A2"><subsection id="H4FE7BD18D7DD4C73B0F150D4450A0F74"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use of minor</header><text>A person who, outside the United States, engages in any of the following conduct, intending that the visual depiction will be imported or transmitted into the United States or into waters within 12 miles of the coast of the United States, shall be punished as provided in subsection (c):</text><paragraph id="HC35F2C823C96414D92D0B280CCEEBBBE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Employs, uses, persuades, induces, entices, or coerces a minor to engage in any sexually explicit conduct for the purpose of producing any visual depiction of such conduct or transmitting a live visual depiction of such conduct.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H387BE17743F7448DB884C4B9A9AA439D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Employs, uses, persuades, induces, entices, or coerces a minor to engage in any sexually explicit conduct and in the course thereof, knowingly produces or causes to be produced any visual depiction of such conduct, or transmits or causes to be transmitted a live visual depiction of such conduct.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05922D2D50084496B8E652A8F5AA46B4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Engages in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor for the purpose of producing any visual depiction of such conduct or transmitting a live visual depiction of such conduct, intending that the minor be included in such visual depiction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H111A3DCC5FBB40A3A7F08C78F313296E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Engages in sexually explicit conduct in the presence of a minor and in the course thereof, knowingly produces or causes to be produced any visual depiction of such conduct, or transmits or causes to be transmitted a live visual depiction of such conduct, intentionally including the minor in such visual depiction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H93D4530E2C7C4143878E14D2F5D00D89"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Has a minor assist any other person to engage in any sexually explicit conduct during the commission of an offense set forth in paragraphs (1) through (4) of this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H94C30063BFD04121916A742F7502F2EC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Transports any minor in or affecting foreign commerce with the intent that such minor be used in the production or live transmission of any visual depiction of a minor engaged in any sexually explicit conduct.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H8DABF9F311914DFABB6CB015A8AE9E36"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>visual depiction of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct (if the production of the visual depiction involved the use of a minor engaging in sexually explicit conduct), intending that the visual depiction</quote> and inserting <quote>child pornography (as defined in section 2256(8)(A)), intending that the child pornography</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

