<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H977CA44EA92E466DAF721785581259A6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2376 IH: To amend the Indian Health Care Improvement Act and title 5 of the United States Code to facilitate participation in Federal benefits programs, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2376</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230329">March 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Indian Health Care Improvement Act and title 5 of the United States Code to facilitate participation in Federal benefits programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF9467513FCDF40F5AAE95915CF581754" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H08D2E6A6CA654D598B635DF6C0055A37" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Amendments to Indian Health Care Improvement Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 409 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1647b">25 U.S.C. 1647b</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HF92DFDF5B9CA4A31886A50DF3619342B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or an urban Indian organization carrying out programs under title V of this Act</quote> and inserting <quote>, an urban Indian organization carrying out programs under title V of this Act, or a Tribal College or University as defined in section 316(b)(3) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059c">20 U.S.C. 1059c(b)(3)</external-xref>),</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H89E0614FA3BC49998AFF1BAE2FC6D552"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or urban Indian organization, under chapter 89</quote> and inserting <quote>, urban Indian organization, or Tribal College or University, under chapter 89</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE5B07C0596354EB5927ABF0F1867366E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or urban Indian organization, are currently deposited</quote> and inserting <quote>, urban Indian organization, or Tribal College or University, are currently deposited</quote> ; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H77021D0957564DC9B406ED53B4202007"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>In addition, employees of such Indian tribe, tribal organization, urban Indian organization, or Tribal College or University shall be entitled to purchase coverage, rights, and benefits under chapters 89A and 89B of such title if the Indian tribe, tribal organization, urban Indian organization, or Tribal College or University determines that the employee is eligible, and the necessary employee deductions or direct payment for the coverage, rights, and benefits for the period of employment with such Indian tribe or tribal organization, urban Indian organization, or Tribal College or University are currently deposited in accordance with requirements under such chapters.</quote></text></paragraph></section> <section id="H440CCB6622294FE2919ADEF9533479D5" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Tribal Insurance Administrative Account</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8909 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HB90F848508F6453191FBC4C63D7186DF" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="HD138B5E661434347AF0B1C99228054CD"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Tribal Insurance Administrative Account</header>
<paragraph id="H2CFA2D0C44CC4F27B3D50F574B305C83"><enum>(1)</enum>
<subparagraph id="H0462704F7D1642639EE121E2B68FC6BE" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Fund a Tribal Insurance Administrative Account (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Account)</quote>. The administrative fee charged to each tribal employer that purchases coverage, rights, and benefits for its employees under section 409 of the Indian Health Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1647b">25 U.S.C. 1647b</external-xref>) shall be collected by the Office of Personnel Management, or other entity as authorized by the Director of the Office, for the administration of the Tribal FEHB Program. All such fees collected shall be paid into the Account.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD19149826802417ABDFA22E4AB034743" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The administrative fee under subparagraph (A) shall be determined annually by the Office and shall be charged in addition to any premium for each enrollment of a tribal employee. The administrative fee—</text>
<clause id="H9B20A30A7FDC4B97848A9A586FF06E33"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be a percentage, as determined by the Office, of the weighted average monthly premium calculated with consideration to all plans and options and the total number of enrollees enrolled in all plans and options; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBA0FEE3A08F146E6B81D6C0DA2C5E8E9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not exceed 3 percent of the applicable average monthly premium.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8654D14CAEB240018A007A7E948733EA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Account shall be available to the Office, without fiscal year limitation, for reasonable expenses incurred by the Office for the administration of the Tribal FEHB Program.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

