<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H82A3488FA02E4AEDA102D96B46139F16" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2469 IH: Toxic Exposure Education for Servicemembers Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2469</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230403">April 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish an outreach program to inform members of the Armed Forces, assigned to work near burn pits, of the risks of toxic exposure, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA397B1F05EC64812938D89135BAD55AE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB2371251389D4B61B8049A92E65304FB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Toxic Exposure Education for Servicemembers Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HEA9823C1EE2B43A6BDAC65C9056DF0F5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Outreach to members of the Armed Forces regarding possible toxic exposure</header> <subsection id="HB2E7CD16D48046D69BFF67A3334A1B2A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall establish—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF655D57113A141EEA4A97E4CDEA99961"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a new risk assessment for toxic exposure for members of the Armed Forces assigned to work near burn pits; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCEE2D6271B194ABFAF6B29AB6F775AB4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an outreach program to inform such members regarding such toxic exposure. Such program shall include information regarding benefits and support programs furnished by the Secretary (including eligibility requirements and timelines) regarding toxic exposure.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H58BC40EBEFC84AF6BCBAECA6B33A9CD0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Promotion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall promote the program to members described in subsection (a) by direct mail, email, text messaging, and social media.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H490198C1992640769746E17937BBE827"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall publish on a website of the Department of Defense a list of resources furnished by the Secretary for—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD41998B67CED483B999EA88103240078"><enum>(1)</enum><text>members and veterans who experienced toxic exposure in the course of serving as a member of the Armed Forces;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H976A0F29A7864ACAAEF6287324A3585F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>dependents and caregivers of such members and veterans; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H92FE6F5C6A11404AB4527C1472F43B01"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">survivors of such members and veterans who receive death benefits under laws administered by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H50BF44BA170442929F4F8A0842A16F3A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Toxic exposure defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>toxic exposure</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

