<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C40E8C552E0466780E82ECD0FFFCE8A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1367 IH: Water System Threat Preparedness and Resilience Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1367</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a program to increase drinking water and wastewater system threat preparedness and resilience, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H115DF0E639184084B7EA87CB2BDE4F1F" style="OLC"><section id="HA048DD76D91140CD8D41A1B1A46AFEE5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Water System Threat Preparedness and Resilience Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA5105B88B5794A64BE0006CE7A927C48"><enum>2.</enum><header>Program establishment</header><subsection id="H072859F8AB4F48CB8DB7640C3818B03C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HBB683D5EE12C44C589823301D9A8FF95"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community water system</header><text>The term <term>community water system</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1401 of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300f">42 U.S.C. 300f</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C30F72CD4B647CD8F79C2A6E5922660"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Natural hazard</header><text>The term <term>natural hazard</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1433(h) of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300i-2">42 U.S.C. 300i–2(h)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9ED0A95FADC443D81138BF2C2101E99"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Treatment works</header><text>The term <term>treatment works</term> has the meaning given the term in section 212 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1292">33 U.S.C. 1292</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44F548AA44D246E298E642B3AC445B40"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Water Information Sharing and Analysis Center</header><text>The term <term>Water Information Sharing and Analysis Center</term> means the Information Sharing and Analysis Center referenced in section 1435(d) of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300i-4">42 U.S.C. 300i–4(d)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HECADD1F16C024A8DBC262973B7EAF944"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency shall develop and carry out a program—</text><paragraph id="H74F9CB5F0DDA42F1B66667359C211DCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to encourage, support, and maintain the participation of community water systems, treatment works, and other appropriate entities in the Water Information Sharing and Analysis Center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31DAF98593E24293BFE8AA0F02861083"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to offset costs incurred by community water systems and treatment works that are necessary to maintain or initiate membership in the Water Information Sharing and Analysis Center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3165FE83831E43C89B42391724F18745"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to expand the cooperation and coordination of the Environmental Protection Agency with the Water Information Sharing and Analysis Center with respect to incident data collection and analysis of water sector-related threats; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD792456F043140879E4030EC9F6A6EA7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to enhance the tools, resources, and materials of the Water Information Sharing and Analysis Center for—</text><subparagraph id="HB27F24D40CAF4B009D6D20B4F0279A76"><enum>(A)</enum><text>monitoring the status of the water sector; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD15A02F5C0004E7B9178B1A6905D3947"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enhancing the preparedness of community water systems and publicly owned treatment works to identify, protect against, detect, respond to, and recover from malevolent acts (within the meaning of section 1433 of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300i-2">42 U.S.C. 300i–2</external-xref>)) or natural hazards.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7EA0C46EE2A641D0B3687D7988E81B51"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 and 2025, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

