<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7F2A3746607D460D99A57502E7AC4FDD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6752 IH: To require prompt reporting of any incident in which the Armed Forces are involved in an attack or hostilities, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6752</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require prompt reporting of any incident in which the Armed Forces are involved in an attack or hostilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDC3F775E3FA44DFA82A2A8A846B40111" style="OLC"><section id="H88907499D85C4478A997D9B1DCE00880" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Report on Hostilities Involving United States Armed Forces</header><subsection id="H4E6752AA1A67489CB2F606814037038C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 48 hours after any incident in which the United States Armed Forces are involved in an attack or hostilities, whether in an offensive or defensive capacity, the President shall transmit to the congressional defense committees, the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate, and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the incident, unless the President—</text><paragraph id="H12472FBCBA9E47F3A80B1E5283E19368"><enum>(1)</enum><text>otherwise reports the incident within 48 hours pursuant to section 4 of the War Powers Resolution (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1543">50 U.S.C. 1543</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC9726DCCB244ADE926BE9FF2434E652"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has determined prior to the incident, and so reported pursuant to section 1264 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1549">50 U.S.C. 1549</external-xref>), that the United States Armed Forces involved in the incident would be operating under specific statutory authorization within the meaning of section 5(b) of the War Powers Resolution (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1544">50 U.S.C. 1544(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A17C3EEE9E743B8B66400F77E80F623"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>Each report required by subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="HDB7E360A5908481882DCFB86FC00DD87"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the authority or authorities under which the United States Armed Forces were operating when the incident occurred;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D9CE40C3EDA4A06842FE8315593C07F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date, location, and duration of the incident and the other parties involved;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9DDE5AC73E44D139E6C121997FF907A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of the United States Armed Forces involved in the incident and the mission of such Armed Forces;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95E143F86AF14B618750438D8C0F9108"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the numbers of any combatant casualties and civilian casualties that occurred as a result of the incident; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32515AC67AE04DE98951A583930BCB00"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any other information the President determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

