<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1C64ABDF1E7049648219A79D18A203F0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3693 IH: Migrant Relocation Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3693</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000600">Mr. Langworthy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require advance consultation with State and local officials and monthly reports to Congress regarding the resettlement, transportation, and relocation of aliens in the United States.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFCF210BAE02E47A5837A807C44C0E3EA" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H78AB132321F34EB49EB174FE2E239B37" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Migrant Relocation Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H05B48C042F5241F4B722FDF64CEBDB5A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Advance consultation with State and local officials and monthly reports to Congress regarding the resettlement, transportation, and relocation of aliens in the United States</header> <subsection id="H9722264A8657407CA724348305D80C11"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Consultation requirement</header><text>Not later than 3 business days before any resettlement, transportation, or relocation of non-detained aliens in the United States that is directed, administered, or funded by the Federal Government, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in the case of minors) or the Secretary of Homeland Security (in the case of adults), as appropriate, shall consult with the governors and municipal chief executives of the directly affected States and local jurisdictions regarding the proposed resettlement, transportation, or relocation.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H07EC2C4BF7054609AF99F22E8F95D920"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports required</header><text>Not later than 7 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and monthly thereafter, the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with other appropriate Federal officials, shall—</text> <paragraph id="H28B4C7651B124A1C82F7E0E03FDBF8DC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit a State-specific report regarding the resettlement, transportation, or relocation of non-detained aliens in the United States during the previous month that was directed, administered, or funded by the Federal Government or that involved aliens subject to the U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement’s Alternatives to Detention program that contains the information described in subsection (c) to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H24280830A8064C26A2F25037A3C8DC1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD4C94C50D48643BEBE42C7429A70F759"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H50AFA4D4AF104255BB0937654E07167A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Governor of each of the affected States; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23F73CB14FB74C1788D6B88FCCFA5080"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make the report described in paragraph (1) available on a publicly accessible website.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H905E82EDDD1D449CAACE63F339FD5C83"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each report under subsection (b) shall contain, with respect to each State—</text> <paragraph id="H390FD9E6B1834FE7A4C7B5CD2CD97AA2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of aliens resettled, transported, or relocated during the previous month and the current calendar year, disaggregated by—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1EE1656EA29C47E894F764F251A3B8B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the numbers of single adults, members of family units, and minors;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB778747CF75948B690DAEA1CC79BA091"><enum>(B)</enum><text>age;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HABA3C5A15B4C44768B00FF0FD6ADBC36"><enum>(C)</enum><text>sex; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H166A7E111638476EB7AF219CD57BFE76"><enum>(D)</enum><text>country of origin;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H82F3E7EB68524E0094C6E608E4546E12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the methods used to determine the ages of such aliens;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF8FA92A280343858E7E8F74E7E51F8E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the methods used to verify the familial status of such aliens;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF02AEABB67B24DBEA6CCD9CF3C3C2D87"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the types of settings in which such aliens are being resettled, transported, or relocated, which may be aggregated by the general type of setting;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6EEDD322D83A4B42AAE1126438492253"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a summary of the educational or occupational resources or assistance provided to such aliens;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0A88C5F4C2D4C09867885E142DBC195"><enum>(6)</enum><text>whether such aliens are granted permits to work and how any such aliens without a work permit will financially support themselves;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H09349D08AB1D4A5D8B78464E80DF3C2A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the amounts and types of Federal resources spent on alien resettlement, transportation, or relocation;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3C5562C3FA964FC1A366CC94D4BF3EF8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>whether the aliens are being resettled, transported, or relocated on a temporary or permanent basis, disaggregated by—</text> <subparagraph id="H77F378E4E35F46168A75FC695263B667"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the numbers of single adults, members of family units, and minors;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3ADDD828605148D89F6D00D7F04F31E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>age;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H036413E0CA534B9788F5E3F3341CF2B7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>sex; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9137A542996A4EF3A47AE204B66AE13E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>country of origin; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49FD7555F3284AA5875B8CCD349F414B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the types of security screenings performed with respect to such aliens.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

