<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4A57EBC19560497AA58C25A755F881C1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 271 IH: Restoring Normalcy in America Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 271</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230111">January 11, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000298">Mr. Estes</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide for greater accountability with respect to Federal activities and expenditures relating to COVID–19, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE9E288AB4B554DC88EF511AE4AC05B63" style="OLC">
<section id="HBC6D24C4445A4387A16A955731244058" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restoring Normalcy in America Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD1BD983664A84B04AF8D8C27E25C5E0A"><enum>2.</enum><header>HHS COVID–19 study</header> <subsection id="H743130FE994C4A72B5F2D0D33B6FD068"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall conduct a study on—</text>
<paragraph id="H72F3B82E4AD047FCA0D641D0CF5F9913"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the effectiveness of vaccines licensed under section 351 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>) or authorized for emergency use under section 564 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360bbb-3">21 U.S.C. 360bbb–3</external-xref>) in providing immunization against COVID–19 (including any additional doses of such a vaccine to be administered after the primary series of doses);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H95859380F44746E694CDB251AE9DC4B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effectiveness of treatments approved under section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref>), licensed under section 351 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>), or authorized for emergency use under section 564 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360bbb-3">21 U.S.C. 360bbb–3</external-xref>) to treat COVID–19;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H02910CBBAAF94D5EBB33A0334C749435"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the rate of transmission of SARS–CoV–2 throughout the United States, beginning on the first day of the emergency period (as defined in section 1135(g)(1)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-5">42 U.S.C. 1320b–5(g)(1)(B)</external-xref>));</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDAC4E977AA4641E3B4EE0B53346AEDED"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the level of preparedness of the United States for future pandemics; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H482EB33C1474405AAA582D6DDDC47359"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the cause and origins of the COVID–19 pandemic.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1428812667A94DDDA5D283904DA3AD18"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress a report on the findings of the study conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H75F7F5D7025C4E2F98C7FC8A4174E1E6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Of the amounts made available to the Secretary of Health and Human Services in appropriations Acts that remain unobligated as of the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary may use not more than 3 percent of such funds to carry out this section. </text></subsection></section> <section id="HBD3B9AC136EF40168217D98CE4DA10CD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Termination of emergency use authority for COVID–19 prevention and treatment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, may not authorize under section 564 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360bbb-3">21 U.S.C. 360bbb–3</external-xref>) for emergency use any drug, biological product, or device for use in the prevention or treatment of COVID–19.</text></section>
<section id="H43E58D6B67DE4436825B27E1FF48EDEB"><enum>4.</enum><header>COVID–19 funding audit</header>
<subsection id="HF0D08333F3EB4761AE95C7DC7F4131E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct an audit of all Federal funding made available to the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, and the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention for programs and activities relating to COVID–19. Such audit shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H4EF58E24E79F4EFC9FD3DA890995E12C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an accounting of the amount of such funds that have been obligated or expended, disaggregated by agency and activity; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFF75F605DA7346A98AE94D481A58FE1F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an accounting of any such funds that remain unobligated and available for rescission.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEEC7AE7D98944A11B36B08E7FF0CED24"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Congress a report on the findings of the audit conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H54791693551E49B1822F45C05E9405F3" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header>Unlawful employment practice under title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 for failure to offer re-employment to employees discharged for failure to receive a vaccination against COVID–19</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of section 703(a) of title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2003-2">42 U.S.C. 2003–2(a)</external-xref>), it shall be an unlawful employment practice for an employer to fail to give on request full consideration for, and to offer a position at the pay and level equal to the applicable pre-discharge pay and level, of employment to an individual previously discharged from employment by such employer based on such individual’s failure to receive a vaccination against COVID–19.</text></section> <section id="H4251A87CF3FF46AA89D740C002DB2F31"><enum>6.</enum><header>COVID–19 vaccination status and places of public accommodation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title II of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000a">42 U.S.C. 2000a et seq.</external-xref>) is amended as follows:</text>
<paragraph id="HD8249BDA9185478BB72A3749DF6B2EAA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In section 201, by inserting after <quote>on the ground of race, color, religion,</quote> the following: <quote>failure to receive a vaccination against COVID–19,</quote>. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF946B8A9BF674CE5928A1FDE23B77A14"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In section 202, by inserting after <quote>on the ground of race, color, religion,</quote> the following: <quote>failure to receive a vaccination against COVID–19,</quote>.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HCC4DA1F2B5D343C184B7518B0F0FD48C"><enum>7.</enum><header>COVID–19 vaccination status and Federally assisted programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 601 of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000d">42 U.S.C. 2000d</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>failure to receive a vaccination against COVID–19,</quote> before <quote>race, color,</quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3D3E9C1CFF9246A3AD75EE6F11DA5D5F"><enum>8.</enum><header>COVID–19 vaccination status and employment</header> <subsection id="HFDB525E349B842A38BAD90CC9D28FDA7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reinstatement of members of the Armed Forces involuntarily separated for refusing To receive a vaccination against COVID–19</header> <paragraph id="H530AD797931E49D9B29592D0E5200745"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reinstatement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the request of a covered individual, the Secretary concerned shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H14E79F82238A410290632E3304B952CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reinstate the covered individual as a member of the Armed Force concerned, in the same rank and grade the covered individual held at the time of separation from the Armed Force concerned; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF306F5AF06744FF4950F9C23CEEB74CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expunge from the military service record of the covered individual any reference to adverse action against the covered individual solely on the basis of the refusal of the covered individual to receive a vaccination against COVID–19.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA3F885A8877244E3B45F62B9AD71D2B1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <subparagraph id="H1E30971F9DDE4CC0A2889AB5BFE9198D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>adverse action</term> includes involuntary separation, demotion, and discipline.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF7E2B9F147CF4848B9003FF8F92C5DE0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>covered individual</term> means an individual who was involuntarily separated from an Armed Force solely on the basis of the refusal of such individual to receive a vaccination against COVID–19.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H955F95D101F14A4FBCDE0BDA8C1D645D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <term>Secretary concerned</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HDE5878E6EE1E4303AFD5B73A5574634D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reinstatement of Federal employees involuntarily separated for refusing To receive COVID–19 vaccine</header>
<paragraph id="HA1B8AB5FA2A1427CB63F0945691A5205"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any individual removed from the civil service (as that term is defined in section 2101 of title 5, United States Code) solely on the basis of the refusal of the individual to receive a vaccination against COVID–19 may, at the discretion of the individual, be reinstated to a civil service position at the same grade or level, and same rate of pay, as the position from which the individual was so removed.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H416BE7C0338A43E6A12AD6ED2831FB87"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other matters</header><text>Any notation of an adverse action with respect to such removal in the personnel record file of such an individual shall be removed. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H9A89D67C3B0241F8A92C7CBA946D162F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Unlawful employment practice under title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 for failure To receive a vaccination against COVID–19</header><text>For purposes of section 703 of title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2003-2">42 U.S.C. 2003–2</external-xref>), it shall be an unlawful employment practice for an employer—</text> <paragraph id="HB54E4F3584D644529C7AA026E58CF6F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to fail or refuse to hire or to discharge any individual, or otherwise to discriminate against any individual with respect to his compensation, terms, conditions, or privileges of employment, based on such individual’s failure to receive a vaccination against COVID–19; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H80ED07A48914487B8360D81F0030D3A2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to limit, segregate, or classify his employees or applicants for employment in any way which would deprive or tend to deprive any individual of employment opportunities or otherwise adversely affect his status as an employee, based on such individual’s failure to receive a vaccination against COVID–19.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

