<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDCE8300D6C334726B2DBE0348A272952" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2833 IH: Pretrial Release Reporting Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2833</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000471">Mr. Fitzgerald</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000478">Mr. Fry</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Director of the Bureau of Justice Statistics to submit to Congress a report relating to individuals granted bail and pretrial release in State courts, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD64628E164024C67BE4745FAD51FC551" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H766D80A6D1BF476A80F9D9C53CEDE324" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pretrial Release Reporting Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7E802112CAE143CDB21327ECC415C33A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HBD8C707DB26B426FAC91930CB6FE5B2D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Multiple jurisdictions across the United States—</text> <subparagraph id="H73EA8DCAA5214BA8ABEFA063FC643661"><enum>(A)</enum><text>broke annual homicide records in 2021; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H07E20835B1A9469C9F749D210DE34131"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have reported individuals committing violent felony offenses after being granted bail or pretrial release.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H657488EAFA9D4A968326733F19829C6E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The failure of felony defendants to appear for mandatory court appearances and felony bail jumping has increased in multiple jurisdictions across the United States.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H35CCC5CF40FB4D53BF29B7D0D951ECA4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The most recent report issued by the Bureau of Justice Statistics relating to the pretrial release of felony defendants in State courts is from 2007.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6521E8B49B4F43619A380ACF917A1EEF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The National Pretrial Reporting Program of the Bureau of Justice Statistics was created to collect information on criminal justice processing of individuals charged with felony offenses in State courts, with particular attention given to pretrial release and detention.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4A58F672888E4A1C8D9DD638AFF0FEED"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In 2020, the National Pretrial Reporting Program of the Bureau of Justice Statistics awarded a grant of $2,000,000 to collect information relating to individuals charged with felony offenses and released from criminal pretrial detention.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3ABD3870A9BF446CAFD125934CEA1412"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Neither the National Pretrial Reporting Program of the Bureau of Justice Statistics nor the Bureau of Justice Statistics has published any information relating to the pretrial release of felony defendants in State courts since the 2020 grant award.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HDC8D91762EC9439B86C6063931D9C7E0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report</header>
<subsection id="H4D6799D7B3A045BC8A95FBB3016263F6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of Bureau of Justice Statistics shall submit to Congress a report on information relating to individuals granted bail and pretrial release from State courts that are charged with 1 or more of the following violent felony offenses:</text> <paragraph id="HD636937AAC68483DBD74DCB42AF71B05"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Murder or attempted murder.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3E7177A8184F4FBC9941FB737DA87CDE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Manslaughter, other than involuntary manslaughter.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA83ADC4ECC94299BB465D9740BC0D96"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Rape or attempted rape.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5113B8EF30B14EE78088F407C5EC942E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Assault with the intent to commit murder.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE17ADC65E39343129CD10ACC07F6277A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Assault with the intent to commit rape.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H21B94BD14E4F41D7835F9E9AE04F7552"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Aggravated sexual abuse, sexual abuse, attempted sexual abuse, or abusive sexual conduct.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEDAF90DA90A84F7CB4EA4E5005EB69FD"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Battery or aggravated battery.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF06288F3E2C84600B1BEB2AAC2C513FF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Kidnapping.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4145B48FA5C04C69AEF9117D97E82E0B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Robbery.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3A6AE4464ECF498FBD308EDEF3BD5FAE"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Resisting or obstructing an officer.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H047E30B96E1E46C8A5579593A22EB1AB"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Carjacking.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA88BFAD158174A90BB6F0AAFE40CCD63"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Recklessly endangering safety.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA13AD4FF991D4B44AAEDDE4D75AD96BE"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Illegal possession of a firearm in the commission of a felony.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H895CAAFDED364B4F95BFA9B8CAD80E27"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Any other violent felony offense tracked by the jurisdiction in which the offense is committed.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H483F063910BB4A34A0B59C300D9FE0A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report submitted under subsection (a) shall include—</text>
<paragraph id="HB80E2653D32F4B9CA9D3E7CF81821365"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of individuals granted bail or pretrial release from State courts that are charged with an offense described in subsection (a);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4568A227167245D8B06D8326B03C3B87"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of individuals who, after being granted bail or pretrial release, are rearrested or charged with an additional violent felony offense;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE8ACF117327647C2A42EFE519A4A301A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the percentage of individuals granted bail or pretrial release from State courts who—</text> <subparagraph id="H3D7CC373C69D43DD8619D77049BCA799"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are charged with a violent felony offense; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEFFBE335C6F34DF79A66FC1D408F6C98"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have a prior arrest or conviction for a violent felony offense;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3FB095D9D1124E58A88E2CFC3951FE3D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>with respect to the pretrial releases described in paragraph (2) for which the pretrial release condition was bail, the amount of bail granted for each individual;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC713A4B090F8433EA30DF4EE92F2B096"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the number of missed mandatory court appearances by individuals charged with a violent felony offense;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H111FB69B03594B58ADFB7EEB7C855153"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the factors used by State courts for assessing whether to grant bail or pretrial release to individuals who have prior arrests or prior felony convictions for a violent felony offense;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0D69E1C3EFA94BC98B908104F9039F2B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>with respect to individuals who have committed a violent felony offense after being granted bail or pretrial release, the classification of the violent felony offenses;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E03A3AF02AD412D846844A78A766D47"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the status, as of the date of enactment of this Act, of the National Pretrial Reporting Program of the Bureau of Justice Statistics and the activities of that Program; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H31B0E0084FDE4A03BBD03A29F375BFA9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>an accounting for each fiscal year of the amounts that the Department of Justice has expended, or transferred to components of the Department of Justice, in order to collect information on bail and pretrial release in State courts including, with respect to any grants or contracts awarded for that purpose, the amount and the purpose of the grant or contract.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

