<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H545A2BAD0C3B461BAF87E55C2589C2FD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4045 IH: Hydropower Clean Energy Future Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4045</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To modernize the hydropower licensing process and to promote next-generation hydropower projects, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA2D6241599404DCDA339FB964D415BCF" style="OLC"><section id="H939ED882B3A6405F9ACC2A01D44DAB4B" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hydropower Clean Energy Future Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H9077C6E86AAB436DB3AAA814050A98C2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Confirming that hydropower is an essential renewable resource</header><subsection id="HA6862088C95A41459B03FA2C382B7D44" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress on the use of hydropower renewable resources</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H67183BC3D1B04B1EA9C82123F883D04F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hydropower is a renewable resource for purposes of all Federal programs and is an essential source of energy in the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74B5B93FCADD45D4A169904CD692D6A5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States should protect existing hydropower resources and increase substantially the capacity and generation of clean, renewable hydropower resources to address a changing climate and improve environmental quality in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA6A78965788F423C8C174DADA2602938" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Modifying definitions of renewable energy To include hydropower</header><paragraph id="HE8A626A8D23E4541A1F537AE77685B87" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Energy Policy Act of 2005</header><text>Section 203 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15852">42 U.S.C. 15852</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H560899E2429B4738A5112BA588CF5B8B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by amending paragraphs (1) through (3) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H88E430EC4FBC4B9283BA5A00493D2571" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H2541552AE1EA4F22AE6A8DB418A6AFE1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not less than 20 percent in fiscal years 2024 through 2025.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F11EE942FAD4CCFA160015CE5D176E6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Not less than 23 percent in fiscal years 2026 through 2027.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5383E42B96A747BC97E509E407F591C0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Not less than 25 percent in fiscal year 2028 and each fiscal year thereafter.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F1C9736666440049B9C3F7DC6B4444D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking paragraph (2) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block id="H87EA9C0E21B14E2DB71D432F8BFAEFD2" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H59A09E0C79F44F9195EA40B3ED030E87" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Renewable energy</header><text>The term <term>renewable energy</term> means energy produced from solar, wind, biomass, landfill gas, ocean (including tidal, wave, current, and thermal), geothermal, municipal solid waste, or hydropower.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE775EAA3E5B438A92512CFC5C5B7201" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other Federal regulations, orders, and policies</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, each Federal department and agency shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report demonstrating that the department or agency has amended any applicable regulation, order, or other policy of the department or agency related to renewable energy to ensure treatment of hydropower by the Federal Government consistent with the amendments made by paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6C6E6057FA28447BA76CE4DC96647F4F" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Licenses for construction</header><text>Section 4(e) of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/797">16 U.S.C. 797(e)</external-xref>) is amended, in the first sentence, by inserting <quote>to mitigate the effects of the applicable project on such reservation, so as to provide</quote> after <quote>deem necessary</quote> in the first proviso.</text></subsection><subsection id="H778BE346C6A24BC08BA5B24EB507AB06" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Operation of navigation facilities</header><text>Section 18 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/811">16 U.S.C. 811</external-xref>) is amended by adding before the period at the end of the first sentence <quote>to mitigate effects of the applicable project</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H0528422DCEDA489E97A683B43A751D25" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Protecting and promoting small and next-generation hydropower projects</header><subsection id="H7EFF41C98AFA44EA9E9E4B29908AAB78" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Exemptions from licensing requirements for certain small hydroelectric power projects</header><text>Section 405 of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2705">16 U.S.C. 2705</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (d) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block id="H451DB00198314087B355C8E0C0D201C9" style="OLC"><subsection id="HC4C9CC8DEE7641F0BBBD55263AA029EA" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exemptions from licensing in certain cases</header><paragraph id="H6C295BD5113A4F978BFB1388665B4088" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraphs (2) and (3), the Commission may in its discretion (by rule or order), upon application and on a case-by-case basis or on the basis of classes or categories of projects, grant an exemption in whole or in part from the requirements (including the licensing requirements) of part I of the Federal Power Act to any small hydroelectric power project—</text><subparagraph id="HBF1927C765944E8283BA340A9D00335C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>having a proposed installed capacity of 40 megawatts or less; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A384AB2234D4765A5664FF7C1A97D1F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for which a license was issued under part I of the Federal Power Act and the licensee applies for an exemption under this subsection, if—</text><clause id="H5DDC58917B4B4526885B97AF427953DB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the license was issued after the date of enactment of the Electric Consumers Protection Act of 1986;</text></clause><clause id="H2658FFC35F1643B4A06D8036C19DA21B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Commission determines, based on information available to the Commission, that continued operation of the project is not likely to jeopardize the continued existence of any species listed as a threatened species or an endangered species under the Endangered Species Act of 1973;</text></clause><clause id="HE6F7D487FAA648859AE46E6BFA08C718" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Commission determines, based on information available to the Commission, that continued operation of the project is not likely to result in the destruction or adverse modification of an area designated as critical habitat for any species listed as a threatened species or an endangered species under the Endangered Species Act of 1973; and</text></clause><clause id="HE3D960835CE54548AA2A0B6B7FAF13D4" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the project has an installed capacity of 40 megawatts or less.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H421C0233F48048A1A05B1BFBA61E6D22" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>An exemption granted under paragraph (1) shall be subject to the same limitations (to ensure protection for fish and wildlife as well as other environmental concerns) as those which are set forth in subsections (c) and (d) of section 30 of the Federal Power Act with respect to determinations made and exemptions granted under subsection (b) of such section 30 and subsections (c) and (d) of such section 30 shall apply with respect to actions taken and exemptions granted under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H53A1EDF687DB4177B4489D59977B4CD1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effects</header><subparagraph id="H729ECB64FB6D408FA140B6865BF91209" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the granting of an exemption to a project under this subsection shall in no case have the effect of waiving or limiting the application (to such project) of the second sentence of subsection (b) of this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8633BDD00D8B42DBA86D25A8845A4157"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Environmental review</header><text>The Commission granting an exemption under paragraph (1) may not be considered a major Federal action under section 102(2)(C) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5C8BA2A03F84492BD0433C40B8A85AB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Exemption process</header><text>The Commission shall make a determination with respect to any application for an exemption under paragraph (1)(B) not later than 90 days after submission of such application, which period shall include notice and opportunity for public comment. Any exemption granted under paragraph (1)(B) shall become effective upon the expiration of the applicable existing license.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H9EC42F3961244081AE89BCA5D6945BEA" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Expedited licensing of next-Generation hydropower</header><text>Part I of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/792">16 U.S.C. 792 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HF234EC5C907844568505D7E647D0309F" style="OLC"><section id="HC94221F3861349E99D89C9A4DBC7057D" commented="no"><enum>37.</enum><header>Expedited licensing of next-generation hydropower projects</header><subsection id="H610DC4FBF1A74A0F82D9F6B0651CE235" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall issue licenses for all next-generation hydropower projects in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB92658C0CB9E4BD2BECB30EA142CE824" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H803A37F2FA824D35B3E6D038A943FEF0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Emerging hydropower technology project</header><text>The term <term>emerging hydropower technology project</term> means a project that the Commission determines—</text><subparagraph id="HC2F6331B0BE04403B66C98A390F47220" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>will produce electricity from a generator driven by a turbine that converts the potential energy of falling or flowing water;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEA910D67F3F49D887A7855A46BA652A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>will utilize turbine or generating technology, an energy storage method, or a measure to protect, mitigate, or enhance environmental resources, that is not in widespread, utility-scale use in the United States as of the date of enactment of this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80AE0E7A6C0E4EF188DBABCCCB0261ED" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>will not be, based on information available to the Commission, likely to jeopardize the continued existence of any species listed as a threatened species or an endangered species under the Endangered Species Act of 1973; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H099E478321174089BA489CAB03C7C02C" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>will not be, based on information available to the Commission, likely to result in the destruction or adverse modification of an area designated as critical habitat for any species listed as a threatened species or an endangered species under the Endangered Species Act of 1973.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A67F7F173A6467C80BEF7D71D833C95" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Next-generation hydropower project</header><text>The term <term>next-generation hydropower project</term> means a project that—</text><subparagraph id="H4FC64F98519047018EADCDED0969DBF4" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may be licensed under this Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BDCEB12DA0D45338BC772C7B246558C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not—</text><clause id="H7477E8FE4E6B442A9FC4ABF08DA90DE4" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a qualifying conduit hydropower facility under section 30; or</text></clause><clause id="HBDF3D06E6E7B4FFD8858D7E4B1C2D811" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>exempted from licensing under—</text><subclause id="H320F7E59E7B54250BD6904FE58C80C7F" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>section 30; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HA8B7F6AE959C4F15BE7BFA2330D63A44" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>section 405 of the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act of 1978; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H340896913D474ACA8AAB9304E34928F5" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is—</text><clause id="H79B0FBE1A602472E9CDB10038864D449" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an emerging hydropower technology project;</text></clause><clause id="HF056E16B516C4153B95FB4F7C4F07FB5" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a qualifying facility, as defined in section 34;</text></clause><clause id="HF946D648914445B9A3578451D4B43BDD" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a qualifying closed-loop pumped storage project, as defined in section 35;</text></clause><clause id="HE84F84A933844A9D944463B65116C4A3" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a marine or hydrokinetic project, including a project that utilizes a wave technology, tidal technology, or in-river technology; or</text></clause><clause id="H8FA5509ABB4D456195005F4C9F14041D" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a hydropower facility within an irrigation, water supply, industrial, agricultural, or other open or closed water conduit system.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBEEFDF1C96D54122A5985C85B10DF793" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expedited licensing process</header><paragraph id="HCD75858454CB4B909ECA2DB25551EDB6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notification of intent</header><subparagraph id="H628D7AB32A124EDFA71370ADEFF734EB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Filing of notification</header><text>An applicant for any next-generation hydropower project shall commence the licensing process by filing a notification of intent with the Commission.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2288D86C90F644ECB145D00DA2FF0004" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Deadline for filing</header><text>Notwithstanding section 15(b)(1), an applicant for a next-generation hydropower project shall file a notification of intent at least 2 years before the expiration of the existing license, if applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA353AE4EDDF947EAA0378018A86AD02B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Filing of application</header><subparagraph id="HDE2197E5A49147F1A5B77112DE56236D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>General deadline</header><text>An applicant for a next-generation hydropower project shall submit to the Commission an application not later than 1 year after filing the notification of intent under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A0C18466C5240D3BB6B626416DBC395" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Existing licencee deadline</header><text>Notwithstanding section 15(c)(1), an application for any next-generation hydropower project shall be filed with the Commission at least 1 year before the expiration of the term of the existing license, if applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE414D5F9F00479CA1F9D79753526D4B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deadline for issuance</header><text>The Commission shall take final action on a license for a next-generation hydropower project under this section not later than 2 years after the applicant notifies the Commission of its intent to file an application for a license, as provided under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFF7F87B0B0B54759BA00A19F840AF8A3" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In issuing a license under this section the Commission and all resource agencies with regulatory responsibilities in the licensing process shall—</text><paragraph id="HA27093590C424A7CB6796521D799560F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>maximize reliance on existing studies and information and require any person or agency requesting a new study or information to demonstrate that collection of any new data or preparation of any new study will not jeopardize the Commission’s ability to meet the licensing deadline under subsection (c)(3);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEFC054FF8F34E748D3B8F93BBC88D0B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consider whether obligations under the National Environmental Protection Act of 1969 may be met through preparation of an environmental assessment or supplementing a previously prepared environmental assessment or environmental impact statement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D8263639F8E45CBAB2E14A48B8BEDE2" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>eliminate any nonessential meetings, reports, and paperwork, including interim study reports and a draft license application or similar document, without compromising effective consultation with, and participation of, Federal and State resource agencies, Indian tribe, and the public; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD36A6F40576B4CAE8467D6BB0C393DF5" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>consider existing project works and other infrastructure to be included in the environmental baseline.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C0CBB4820524C00A3735D14313CBB4E" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this section, and after consultation with the task force described in subsection (f), which 90 days shall include public notice and opportunity for comment, the Commission shall issue a rule implementing this section. Such rule shall include a process, not to exceed 60 days, for the Commission to determine on a case-by-case basis whether a proposed or existing project qualifies as a next-generation hydropower project prior to the initiation of the licensing or relicensing process.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFA25D379792B4A8DB22D47A3BC23033C" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Task force</header><text>The Commission shall convene a task force, with appropriate Federal and State agencies, Indian tribes, and licensees under this part represented, to coordinate the regulatory processes associated with the authorizations required to license next-generation hydropower projects pursuant to this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H676BB1BF0FF14BA9B19DC25ABA183692" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Identifying and removing market barriers to hydropower</header><subsection id="H839D3972D33542128E7BF897F63F802C" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report on hydropower barriers</header><paragraph id="H6500AC1367C546F7A1B2FBB14F4AB7E6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report—</text><subparagraph id="H903432EA2F244269BD5EEC80FB663369" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describing any barriers to the development and proper compensation of conventional, storage, conduit, and emerging hydropower technologies caused by—</text><clause id="HB23BF1839CCC48569DD4A3B454A6B4D1" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>rules of Transmission Organizations (as defined in section 3 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/796">16 U.S.C. 796</external-xref>)); </text></clause><clause id="HE245B7112B0A4C45AA5ADBB1E918C134" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>regulations or policies—</text><subclause id="H37996878629742A78ADE9FAF18A28712" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>of the Commission; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H0C8171FFE82D4DA8981A60F0A986FAD3" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>under the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/791a">16 U.S.C. 791a et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H4A3EC3FCD45B4B27A78F5F840BE452D9" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>other Federal and State laws and policies unique to hydropower development, operation, and regulation, as compared to other sources of electricity; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64E2B10260634200894ABB9CB49589E3" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>containing recommendations of the Commission for reducing barriers described in subparagraph (A) across regulatory and market sectors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H102A12C7E15648F9BC9E598475364CC6" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identifying and determining any regulatory, market, procurement, or cost recovery mechanisms that would—</text><clause id="H72DBA097D055482ABD3FC573BD004FAE" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>encourage development of conventional, storage, conduit, and emerging hydropower technologies; and</text></clause><clause id="H029983D306144353AD99241A073E87EA" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>properly compensate conventional, storage, conduit, and emerging hydropower technologies for the full range of services provided to the electric grid, including—</text><subclause id="H45F6A5FD27D74F559819706A36D2A3C2" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>balancing electricity supply and demand;</text></subclause><subclause id="H65180B6F712E40FE9A40DD696ACD8E63" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>ensuring grid reliability;</text></subclause><subclause id="HEF5D3BE26A0E4321B1FF96DDEE8BAF5A" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>providing ancillary services;</text></subclause><subclause id="HE6A688FFD6B94E418FBCC3342CBF4C87" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>contributing to the decarbonization of the electric grid; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0404643800FC42CF89DB586E1C65E488" commented="no"><enum>(V)</enum><text>integrating intermittent power sources into the grid in a cost-effective manner; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97BC8F8DD9064BB6BA9555357B9AEF86" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>identifying ownership and development models that could reduce barriers to the development of conventional, storage, conduit, and emerging hydropower technologies, including—</text><clause id="H6228D4AFA480409886E87B0B9D203E24" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>opportunities for risk-sharing mechanisms and partnerships, including co-ownership models; and</text></clause><clause id="HA7499F8C2611468CA695FD95B7BC8028" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>opportunities to foster lease-sale and lease-back arrangements with publicly owned electric utilities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C1D41BB877041CE97096F087B2BBBE9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission proceedings</header><text>The Commission shall base the report under paragraph (1) on the findings of the Commission in—</text><subparagraph id="HCAD8028CFEFD4D26B1DA14B9DB6B493B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Docket No. AD16–20;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H026287634A6242289B681C179A81307F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Docket No. RM16–23; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6ECAE0030AC4C77811076F92DE0F01A" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other relevant proceedings.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F1A1388A4984DA09B5318148B775BF4" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical conference and public comment</header><text>In preparing the report under paragraph (1), the Commission shall solicit public input, including by convening a technical conference and providing an opportunity for public submission of written comments on a draft report.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5589F953AE044CCCBE6F212D5E75851E" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H827CBEBD115541F292F6383D72744CED" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Ancillary services</header><text>The term <term>ancillary services</term> means the specialty services and functions provided by the electric grid that facilitate and support the continuous flow of electricity so that supply will continually meet demand, including—</text><subparagraph id="H98127D3E0E494935ABAC8BB3E1DB4B9E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>autonomous dynamic voltage support;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD92703AB87E40E19FEAEFD54EC5824E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>balancing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCEB1ADD5BB5144A6B2DE031D8CC2CC92" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>black start capabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29D3E5040EE44328B1643E4936655505" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>frequency control;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BDE903501BE4992A87953704C956FF3" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>load following;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24ACA712AB8640A7B6CB72EDFCCACA99" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>operating, flexibility, contingency, and other reserves;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H011C9B9E0243499FA2B0E77C0EF20C68" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>reactive power; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H48C31D9C40D34AC1BC11F4E8BC805D53" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text>synchronized regulation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50D16459C71B46B7B3522C89273E3F87" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conventional, storage, conduit, and emerging hydropower technologies</header><text>The term <term>conventional, storage, conduit, and emerging hydropower technologies</term> means hydropower in all its forms and modes of operation, including—</text><subparagraph id="HDAC8C7EFF70742AEA7F298573E8D6609" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the use of dams or similar infrastructure to store water in a reservoir or divert flows from a waterway, and to release stored or diverted water through a turbine to generate electricity according to any mode of operation, such as run-of-river, peaking, reregulating, storage, or load following;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0717405A9F854D68ADD352D56118421E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a configuration of two water reservoirs at different elevations that can generate power as water moves down through a turbine, and pump water back to the upper reservoir when the turbine operations are reversed, including both closed- and open-loop systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0D32674EEAF401D98CA4E18CDFA5730" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>marine and hydrokinetic technologies, including wave, tidal, and in-river systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA3CAFA4E6EF44C7BB30F55EDB91A609" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>mini- and micro-hydropower facilities within irrigation, water supply, industrial, agricultural, or other open or closed water conduit systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5344A08F156049B5838E93CBFAE6F9B2" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>other facilities that produce electricity from generators driven by turbines that convert the potential energy of falling or flowing water.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF0C7E9696DC14F0A82AF4DD67E95BD39" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Modernizing hydropower licensing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part I of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/792">16 U.S.C. 792 et seq.</external-xref>) is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HB6AE83A2EDCA4FBC86F7E1B7F4A9AB3C" style="OLC"><section id="H0A1E45DF2A4E4936A8DB6480BCC21E7B" commented="no"><enum>38.</enum><header>Licensing process coordination and improvement</header><subsection id="HADE71C525C734E1099F03DE0BFE50F63" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of Federal authorization</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Federal authorization</term> means any authorization required under Federal law (including any license, condition of any license by a Secretary under section 4(e), prescription submitted by a Secretary under section 18, permit, special use authorization, certification, opinion, consultation, determination, or other approval) with respect to an application for a license under this part.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB8690DF814E14CBAAD358B8044019604" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation as lead agency</header><paragraph id="HB45FE0E741C040C583D9D7896F142A2E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall act as the lead agency for purposes of all applicable Federal authorizations (including for purposes of complying with the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969), and for purposes of complying with any required State or local environmental reviews.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96B1B5E3E93E40789CF98EFCAAF06137" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other agencies</header><text>Each Federal, State, and local government agency considering an aspect of an application for a Federal authorization shall coordinate with the Commission and comply with the deadline established in the schedule developed for the license under this part, in accordance with the rule issued under subsection (d)(2)(C).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08729A676DFC4ACB9828C8475A10CF66" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of existing studies</header><paragraph id="HBD980ACDCACF4D61BB9D6E0244C5D267" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To the maximum extent practicable and in accordance with the best available science, the Commission and other Federal and State agencies with a responsibility for a Federal authorization shall—</text><subparagraph id="HD98DBC5CB85848AE9A3651781654D484" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>use relevant existing studies and data; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFE5306E7185471E9977A50B0D43A55E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>avoid duplicating current, existing studies that are applicable to the relevant project.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA80F6FBEFB8A4BE58905DD5B3E0C58AB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Demonstration</header><text>When requiring any new study or collection of information, the Commission or other Federal or State agency with a responsibility for a Federal authorization shall—</text><subparagraph id="H21668B40A7C647139C10D5983FD4DEE7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>explain how the new study or other information is necessary to support the agency’s decisionmaking with respect to the Federal authorization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EC2AE8760C94C3AB685B01688C56A33" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify how existing information reasonably available to the agency is inadequate to support the agency’s decisionmaking with substantial evidence; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8598632962614493BC6E3AFED0AE347E" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include an analysis of how the value of the required new study or other information outweighs the cost of producing it.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H73B39E463BBB4BABAF6C9D29768F5040" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Schedule</header><paragraph id="H864C69E9087240E186F7E5D5A6ACEC8A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Timing for issuance</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that, except as otherwise provided in this part, all Federal authorizations required for a project should be issued within a reasonable time, so as to facilitate a final Commission licensing decision within 2 years after the date on which the license application for the project under this part is considered to be complete by the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A8763F720F048B68B687DF4592F0D59" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission schedule</header><subparagraph id="H404513A370AA4147A715665257160236"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission, in accordance with the rule issued under subparagraph (C), shall—</text><clause id="HCA194DB34C304EBEAA1E87F27C35B010"><enum>(i)</enum><text>establish a schedule for—</text><subclause id="H286A18A912084570B41AEADF9AF65F64"><enum>(I)</enum><text> all filings and issuances necessary and appropriate for its issuance of a license issued under this part; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H21F40F64F1E04648AE30BC27A739B7C7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the issuance of all Federal authorizations for the applicable project; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB0B010D4ED9F44DEBEE3565FD2D78C37" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>issue such schedule when the Commission determines that the license application for the project is ready for environmental analysis.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22857661187448F981A80D52488FF71E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In establishing the schedule under subparagraph (A), the Commission shall—</text><clause id="H7A36A9A4D14D46ED92D9AADD1CFC5D13" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consult and cooperate with the Federal and State agencies responsible for a Federal authorization;</text></clause><clause id="HB9636D5E099448869276B9464DE894BC" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure the expeditious completion of all proceedings relating to a Federal authorization; and</text></clause><clause id="HF99C5EDB0B2E4366932BC5F9F2A97842" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>comply with applicable schedules established by Federal law with respect to a Federal authorization.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD77D7B7D186845AE9BDABAAE0E6EF524" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><clause id="H4844F08333D24896BC4F4651233B6D63" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Commission rulemaking to establish process to set schedule</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Commission, in consultation with appropriate Federal and State agencies and after providing notice and opportunity for public comment, shall issue a final rule establishing a process for setting a schedule under subparagraph (A).</text></clause><clause id="H9F794B8A7CFA4354BB174B36A173C5BC" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In issuing a rule under this subparagraph, the Commission shall ensure that the schedule for each Federal authorization—</text><subclause id="H82418FF3613F4AE1891644F80886D7CD" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>includes deadlines for actions by—</text><item id="H9C6054A10CF9463DA1CA70DBEA82D6D3" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>any Federal or State agency with responsibilities for a Federal authorization;</text></item><item id="HC4382AD45FD9427A9B9668F83F11A457" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the applicant;</text></item><item id="H44D55D546B9A40CC9AF3E31E250441CC" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the Commission; and</text></item><item id="HCEBD504811604E6390478BA5C005A59B" commented="no"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>other agencies and participants in a proceeding;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H91636A4573E54F75A22F2CA9DA88F91F" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is developed in consultation with the applicant and any Federal or State agency with responsibility for the applicable Federal authorization;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB8D3F698F795431B84E4C2538A44CCE3" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>provides an opportunity for any Federal or State agency with responsibility for a Federal authorization to identify and resolve issues of concern, consistent with subsections (e) and (f);</text></subclause><subclause id="HF4B1BCB8422E41E6A3D34FF57F79FF68" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>complies with applicable schedules established under Federal law;</text></subclause><subclause id="H9A7C2AAE5A1B4C00A6EA742B1E1D8825" commented="no"><enum>(V)</enum><text>ensures expeditious completion of all proceedings required under Federal and State law, to the maximum extent practicable; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H8E18C0AE3B294C98B3E3EB01EB9684BF" commented="no"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>facilitates completion of Federal and State agency studies, reviews, and any other procedures required prior to, or concurrent with, the preparation of the environmental document of the Commission required under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969, to the maximum extent practicable.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H01FBC98F4E30468CA240A5165A9D6909" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Adherence to schedule</header><subparagraph id="HE0590004BE3D4C3E869E8215E9660938"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission, Federal, and State agencies with responsibility for a Federal authorization, the license applicant, and all other agencies and other participants in proceedings for Federal authorizations for the project shall meet the deadlines established by the schedule developed under paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF034ADA5E6541E6871FC82052BFDB9D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extension of schedule deadlines</header><clause id="H10B38277CC004B47949E1C6C8D0F0320" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Federal authorizations</header><text>A Federal or State agency that is unable to complete its disposition of a Federal authorization by the deadline set forth in the schedule established by the Commission under paragraph (2) shall, not later than 30 days prior to such deadline, file for an extension with the Commission. The Commission shall issue a one-time extension of up to 90 days to any such Federal or State agency upon a demonstration of good cause.</text></clause><clause id="H465201DC76F24B328DE35867C65C8EF1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Other extensions</header><text>The Commission may grant extensions requested by the license applicant or other licensing participants to facilitate settlement, address unforeseen circumstances, or accommodate other showings of good cause if the Commission determines that any such extension would reduce the overall time period for decisionmaking on required Federal authorizations for the project, increase the administrative efficiency of the processes for Federal authorizations, or improve the quality of information available to Federal and State agencies with a responsibility for a Federal authorization.</text></clause><clause id="H8027FF053FA6405A9F5E3E691846FCEF" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Reissuance of schedule</header><text>If the Commission grants an extension under this paragraph, the Commission shall reissue the schedule and applicable deadlines to reflect the extension of time granted.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCF87811F8B544899AC9019C90F11657" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Notwithstanding the Commission’s authority to extend the schedule as provided in subparagraph (B), the Commission shall not grant any extension that would increase by 1 year or longer the time period in the original schedule issued under paragraph (2) for obtaining all Federal authorizations for the applicable project.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AD42D417BF24F43B77382790BB5EECB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Failure to meet schedule deadlines</header><subparagraph id="HB6168F2F3865458780BE484C06FFA946" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), if a Federal or State agency fails to complete its disposition of a Federal authorization in accordance with the schedule deadline established under paragraph (2) (as may be extended under paragraph (3))—</text><clause id="HC9E941F3F5B54D0B80B04ED237798E34" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a Federal agency, $5,000 of unobligated funds shall be rescinded; or</text></clause><clause id="H0FFDAE74633E4EDD9306EB183C2A104B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a State agency, $5,000 of unobligated funds shall be rescinded from Federal fish and wildlife or water resources funding programs to the State.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9734874CD07D49B08C45A0373214250F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Subsequent rescission</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), for each additional week after any deadline established by the Commission under paragraph (2) (as may be extended under paragraph (3)) remains uncompleted by a Federal or State agency with a responsibility for a Federal authorization, an additional rescission of $5,000 shall occur as provided in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C42F7FC259C4931B68C2FDF36A07BE3" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Maximum annual rescission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each individual Federal authorization for a project, the total amounts rescinded under subparagraphs (A) and (B) shall not exceed, in any fiscal year, $100,000.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H163B8F66A193471A82BC668332D50EB6" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>No head of a Federal or State department or agency shall reprogram funds from another Federal account or program for the loss of the funds under this paragraph. No head of a Federal or State agency shall report or include any rescinded funds as an administrative cost for purposes of annual charges under section 10(e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6F3D6F346C1D461A8161BBD8084D4352" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Inconsistent or conflicting license terms</header><paragraph id="H60F2D8560EB5447FBC07B833F65444B3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Consultation to resolve inconsistency or conflict</header><subparagraph id="H7D0B16929A354EA5909E177F976CBFD1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a term or condition of a Federal authorization submitted for inclusion in a license under this part conflicts or is otherwise inconsistent with another such term or condition, the Commission shall initiate and facilitate consultation between the Federal or State resource agencies submitting conflicting or inconsistent terms or conditions, to attempt to resolve the inconsistency or conflict, including with any such conditions recommended for inclusion in the license by the Commission.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF31509AE45940669B06F0B0CF6711A5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The consultation period under this subsection shall extend up to 90 days and shall include at least one technical conference or similar meeting. The Commission shall issue notice of any such conference or other consultation meeting, which shall be open to participation by the license applicant, other agencies, and other licensing participants.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB42001B7485E45288866B3F33F93EB4E" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Amendment and reissuance</header><text>If the agencies submitting the terms or conditions resolve the inconsistency or conflict, the Commission and other consulting agencies shall set a reasonable schedule and deadline, that is not later than 90 days after the conclusion of the consultation, for the agencies to amend and reissue their Federal authorizations to reflect the resolution, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2915DB3862704524AC4DC643DB5DBE92" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Resolution of inconsistency or conflict</header><subparagraph id="H8D900515529F4D86B92883E035397C01" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Statements</header><text>If agencies are unable to resolve an inconsistency or conflict under paragraph (1), not later than 30 days after the conclusion of the consultation process under such paragraph, the agencies shall submit to the public record maintained by the Commission a statement that identifies the inconsistency or conflict, explains the position taken by each agency causing the inconsistency or conflict, and provides an analysis, supported by information in the public record, of the factual basis for the inconsistent or conflicting position taken by each agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD949A432F0048F1BF661A192CCA4F5A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Referral</header><text>Following such submission, the Commission shall refer the matter for resolution as provided in subsection (f).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H58789106E4D44625BBDC4D684117E452" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Resolution of interagency disputes</header><paragraph id="HB4C94663FFCF4A0083D0B4BA0A23AFF0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Referral to OMB</header><text>For any dispute under subsection (c), (d), or (e) among Federal and State agencies with responsibility for a Federal authorization, as well as any dispute between any such agency and the license applicant, the Commission may, upon its own motion or the request of the head of any such agency or the license applicant, refer the matter to the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H143E590C4C4548C38836714AE22738CF" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Action by OMB</header><text>With respect to any dispute referred to the Director under paragraph (1), the Director, in consultation with the Chair of the Council on Environmental Quality, shall act as appropriate—</text><subparagraph id="H149BE12467E34BB68BB379719A791A52" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to ensure a timely participation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD503187F16C64965A4E621DA831C1447" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to ensure a timely decision;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBFAE79BC5FBD4EBFB1C09665E806F483" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to mediate the dispute; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFC835D39B16D42BB9E1E390FD4089AAA" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to refer the matter to the President.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BC028370A0947329C0F355004EB82B4" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Participation</header><text>The license applicant and other interested participants shall be provided the opportunity to participate in the resolution of any issues under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H99BFF2F1DA4249C3A56657384CBEB4E7"><enum>6.</enum><header>Hydropower development at existing nonpowered dams and closed-loop pumped storage</header><subsection id="H366A99966531445C9CBB362FDDBAABF5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Promoting hydropower development at existing nonpowered dams</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 34 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/823e">16 U.S.C. 823e</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H33E525DC20DE453D9ECB7827A60C81E3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending subsection (a) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H788376947EEE47E4B1AD5DFD1B24154B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H127DFACDCCA546B4960769197FC7DE3E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may issue a license under section 37 for any facility the Commission determines is a qualifying facility.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H632F063A0E0249BF8B14BB3647F71D6F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsections (b) and (c); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC6D3A975B094F6995DB7DE8813373FA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (d), (e), and (f) as subsections (b), (c), and (d), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H438E22F12EA648108F81D44248FB3BE8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Closed-Loop pumped storage projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 35 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/823f">16 U.S.C. 823f</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1064B07438EA4989ABFEC471CA7A3F46"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending subsection (a) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB8DB91A065A149D6B3150EC2E447E69D"><subsection id="H4922D79B11AA40D98C3A0DB3C72D4C70"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may issue a license under section 37 for any project the Commission determines is a qualifying closed-loop pumped storage project.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H03D9C518B39648028B96D04AACF5FEEC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsections (b), (c), (e), (g), and (h);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFFD9334E4614DD581B1E5D70EF96CA6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (d) and (f) as subsections (b) and (c), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7145F9E67B684031A6894AF4C8F3180E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD695C4FB46D2492197F6D81FD6FEE669" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H8E91DAB103DC4384B5343D1FD0BD0459" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No license required for certain projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 23(b), a closed-loop pumped storage project shall not be required to be licensed under this part if the closed-loop pumped storage project—</text><paragraph id="H4E4EF80B07674782866EB3BC6B941F4E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is not located upon any part of the public lands or reservations of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A5741EEB74D4EA38C02DDEA0F1BF74E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>does not use a federally owned dam or reservoir.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAF77A1D735AC4102922403B6D6FC8504" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section:</text><paragraph id="HA1A1D06A37F54BAAA78CC3952DF84B97" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Closed-loop pumped storage project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>closed-loop pumped storage project</term> means a project for the generation of electric power—</text><subparagraph id="HB8F7EDFCFC5A4FCB915CABE3DE8A600A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that—</text><clause id="H1EA50A84F41B49A5B93CEE1312648853" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is configured to use 2 or more natural or artificial reservoirs or other water bodies at different elevations; and</text></clause><clause id="HDC94CF7FB0E3475495221C543696E067" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>can generate electric power as water moves down through a turbine and recharge by pumping water to the upper reservoir;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1603CE0B419F4B71A6972D555E53603A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that will be constructed, operated, and maintained for the generation of electric power in a manner that ensures that the upper and lower reservoirs or other water bodies do not impound any stream channel of any surface body of water over which Congress has jurisdiction under its authority to regulate commerce with foreign nations and among the several States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC9EE4C033EE48D184106C27B1728A13" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in which any infrastructure connecting a project reservoir and a natural surface waterway is used for the sole purpose of the initial fill and periodic recharge of reservoirs needed for project operation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE4A765F4B2647A888920912C9925089" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifying closed-loop pumped storage project</header><text>The term <term>qualifying closed-loop pumped storage project</term> means a closed-loop pumped storage project that, as of the date of enactment of the <short-title>Hydropower Clean Energy Future Act</short-title>, is not licensed under, or exempted from the license requirements contained in, this part.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H47DE74371C114F2EBB7B4AE129E07A35" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Savings clauses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section affects—</text><paragraph id="H8432B35E2AC548169BF18B53C3D703E9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any requirement of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>), the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1251">33 U.S.C. 1251 et seq.</external-xref>), or the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4231">42 U.S.C. 4231 et seq.</external-xref>) that may apply to the construction, operation, or maintenance of a closed-loop pumped storage project; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EFA4130589140029962F798FF14C51A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">except as provided in subsection (d), any authority of the Commission to license a closed-loop pumped storage project under this part.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H454A47113C3C481EB2F0B34FB826C78F" commented="no"><enum>7.</enum><header>Extension of time to commence construction of certain hydropower projects</header><subsection id="HEB6E48E48A24446CA588D83086B1C1BA" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of covered project</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered project</term> means a hydropower project with respect to which—</text><paragraph id="H9ECA5F071F844D638620622FD08F8980" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission issued a license under the Federal Power Act before March 13, 2020; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H188189824D6342129855BEE476DA23A1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>construction has not commenced on the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE6F5944145547B09995EB36C5028F19" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of extension</header><text>Notwithstanding section 13 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/806">16 U.S.C. 806</external-xref>), on the request of a licensee of a covered project, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission may, after reasonable notice and for good cause shown, extend in accordance with subsection (c) of this section the period during which the licensee is required to commence construction of the covered project for an additional 4 years beyond the 8 years authorized by such section 13.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF503C37ABA2143F08186728766BC1CDB" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Period of extension</header><text>An extension of time to commence construction of a covered project under subsection (b) shall—</text><paragraph id="H1C3E28CB5EE848FC806AE70DF5BF9906" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>begin on the date on which the final extension of the period for commencement of construction granted to the licensee under section 13 of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/806">16 U.S.C. 806</external-xref>) expires; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H388A3CE603954E50A6F25C6D77C33CC1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>end on the date that is 4 years after the latest date to which the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission is authorized to extend the period for commencement of construction under such section 13.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

