<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1BA9490E5430473BBB93469E26078CC7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6072 IH: Independent Programmers Tax Incentive Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6072</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to provide tax credits for carriage of independent programmers by certain multichannel video programming distributors.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H25CE6723E2FC4D58B5ED90102D547B6B" style="OLC"><section id="H00175C05F29E403AA723916ED02520AB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Independent Programmers Tax Incentive Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HBF31FD0845174203AC69EE911E51D56F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Carriage of Independent Programmers Tax Credit</header><subsection id="H8FDEFEBF38A146E6AC4056B59C9B4A55"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart D of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2DCDD59E55D94777AFE90908092439CD" style="OLC"><section id="H2FA3DA6ED3324E31BEAFC501F6A4F104"><enum>45BB.</enum><header>Carriage of Independent Programmers Credit</header><subsection id="H5B9C4D286AFB4D4BACF4218C52B171BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Allowance of credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of section 38, in the case of any eligible distributor, the carriage of independent programmers credit determined under this section for the taxable year is, with respect to each agreement for qualifying carriage entered into by such eligible distributor, the lesser of—</text><paragraph id="H2C47250068B14F30A9C4C867125D3FB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the net license fees paid or incurred by such eligible distributor during such taxable year under such agreement for qualifying carriage, or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDAB07B5631E4F779EDE24A1FCA1397F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the product of $0.10 multiplied by the average number of monthly subscribers (for calendar months during such taxable year) to which carriage is provided under such agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H600DBCB5943E47618DB0E95A2FD90DD7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Maximum credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The credit determined under this section with respect to any eligible distributor for any taxable year shall not exceed the product of $0.30 multiplied by the average number of monthly subscribers (for calendar months during such taxable year).</text></subsection><subsection id="HD4FD96578D854405A596FE7BEDFF40D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions and special rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="H05EA630A78C74457AB85FC859188A027"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible distributor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible distributor</term> means any person which is either—</text><subparagraph id="H724A7C3AD6B04D21B1D7682A20CC5A8D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>engaged in the trade or business of being a multichannel video programming distributor, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B0E1D0F55A040CBA6DA4ABD1EBA5359"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a virtual multichannel video programming distributor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H401204C820EF4090B046208379F4BB98"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Multichannel video programming distributor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>multichannel video programming distributor</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 76.1000(e) of title 47 of the Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF188BF31C4E46DD894CBE892AF9FF36"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Virtual multichannel video programming distributor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>virtual multichannel video programming distributor</quote> means any person engaged in the trade or business of making available directly to the end user, by means of the Internet or other IP-based transmission path, multiple streams of linear video programming.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H217C27B1E9BC47DEAB349BE671B7981F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Video programming</header><text>The term <quote>video programming</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 79.4(a)(1) of title 47 of the Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB76C2C2E06E545AA83F75F29C91DB7E1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Agreement for qualifying carriage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>agreement for qualifying carriage</quote> means a written agreement between an eligible distributor and a qualified independent programmer that provides for new or expanded carriage of one or more linear video programming streams of a qualified independent programmer to at least 40 percent of the eligible distributor’s subscriber base in aggregate for such linear video programming streams and which requires the eligible distributor to pay a license fee to the qualified independent programmer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72844FE1A4FE4C00BBFDB3DC364581F8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Qualified independent programmer</header><subparagraph id="HFDF969303C4641C3BB0C15764C9293AB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>qualified independent programmer</quote> means a United States-based person engaged in the production, creation, or wholesale distribution of linear video programming (including, but not limited to, women-, minority-, or socially disadvantaged-, owned programmers) if—</text><clause id="HC957C7C9349F4859A703C6D2CC053653"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such person is not a publicly-traded company, multichannel video programming distributor, virtual multichannel video programming distributor, network, or television station company, and</text></clause><clause id="H2868434A4AA143F2B602F5F1D7E5C04D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no publicly-traded company, multichannel video programming distributor, virtual multichannel video programming distributor, network, or television station company has a cognizable interest in such person.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H889A66C93926479F9DCDEFAA4CFA4A6F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Socially disadvantaged</header><text>The term <quote>socially disadvantaged</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 124.103 of title 13 of the Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88B83C1FDA4C4D5CA36AD681E63D462E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Publicly-traded company</header><text>The term <quote>publicly-traded company</quote> means any entity if one or more equity interests in such entity are traded on an established securities market.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F5FD0CCE4314F999E6F4AE6BF0329C4"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Network</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>network</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 76.55(f) of title 47 of the Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9260FDBDE1834620ABCC3A6E743A4E45"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Television station company</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>television station company</quote> means any person if, after taking into account the audience reach of all television stations under common control with such person, such person has a national audience reach in excess of 3 percent. Terms used in this subparagraph which are also used in section 202(c) of the Telecommunications Act of 1996 (or in the regulations issued pursuant to such section) shall have the same meaning as when used in such section (or such regulations).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H362BCF16E4F0409599AE916A6B67FA50"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Cognizable interest</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>cognizable interest</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 76.1000(b) of title 47 of the Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H70E0CF5B494C47D792FF580A6AE40242"><enum>(7)</enum><header>License fees</header><text>Except as otherwise provided by the Secretary, in the case of an agreement for qualifying carriage which is net effective rate positive for the qualified independent programmer, the appropriate amount shall be treated as a license fee paid by the eligible distributor to the qualified independent programmer.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H147B7228C2444C47A8D30316B71D98A9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Denial of double benefit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No deduction shall be allowed under this chapter for any amount to the extent that such amount is allowed as a credit under this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA8C0EB9E99A446BBAFF776A3FBD074A1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Credit made part of general business credit</header><text>Subsection (b) of section 38 of such Code is amended by striking <quote>plus</quote> at the end of paragraph (40), by striking the period at the end of paragraph (41) and inserting <quote>, plus</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0A40395F6785441083D6C8767F6FF5DD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H320CB908972F4860906BDEF744421F65"><enum>(42)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the carriage of independent programmers credit determined under section 45BB.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HBA2E79CD9CB9406DB76CADA7475A7B10" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subpart D of part IV of subchapter A of chapter 1 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE9AD43AD7ED6487FAF56684FAC7596EE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc container-level="quoted-block-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" idref="H2DCDD59E55D94777AFE90908092439CD" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H2FA3DA6ED3324E31BEAFC501F6A4F104" level="section">Sec. 45BB. Carriage of Independent Programmers Credit.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H10F7AEF2905F4402B34E1223F4CBBFC1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to expenses paid or incurred after the date of the enactment of this Act, in taxable years ending after such date.</text></subsection></section><section id="HAE2E911F691340049B5C8EB362695621" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Biennial report by FCC to Congress</header><subsection id="H672243D200EF48FCAE7C081EAEA9CC63"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and not less frequently than every 2 years thereafter, the Federal Communications Commission shall submit to Congress a report that—</text><paragraph id="H2E0A33CE5D16458C97B44D1B25847728"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">states the number of qualified independent programmers that have a linear video programming stream that is distributed to subscribers of one or more eligible distributors and the average length of time for which such a linear video programming stream has been so distributed by the same eligible distributor;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5DB25E8FEA24BC6B1845B7BD3150016"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">states the number of qualified independent programmers that have a linear video programming stream that is distributed to subscribers of one or more multichannel video programming distributors and the average length of time for which such a linear video programming stream has been so distributed by the same multichannel video programming distributor;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E16B6D63F534BA09A16C19FA30E8425"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">states the number of qualified independent programmers that have a linear video programming stream that is distributed to subscribers of one or more virtual multichannel video programming distributors and the average length of time for which such a linear video programming stream has been so distributed by the same virtual multichannel video programming distributor; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2740D32B6A02405A8851260FD27A160E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>contains recommendations for how to increase the number of qualified independent programmers described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D6023246EAC4865A64FB8E3012AB89C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms <quote>eligible distributor</quote>, <quote>multichannel video programming distributor</quote>, <quote>virtual multichannel video programming distributor</quote>, <quote>video programming</quote>, and <quote>qualified independent programmer</quote> have the meanings given such terms in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/45BB">section 45BB(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as added by section 2.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDBE91AFAA8E849C8BB082FF480C82935" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disclosure of tax return information</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">Section 6103(l)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H34DDAA892066462E930B41D9371126AB" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H9D5EBF34264A46D392CDB1A2B02A4A07" commented="no"><enum>(24)</enum><header>Disclosure of return information to Federal Communications Commission for biennial reports to Congress</header><subparagraph id="HA7D2C7912A614DB0975ADFBAE3DE9044" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, upon written request from the Federal Communications Commission, disclose to officers and employees of such Commission such return information of taxpayers claiming the credit allowable under section 45BB as such Commission determines necessary to prepare the reports required under section 2 of the <short-title>Independent Programmers Tax Incentive Act</short-title>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7A4026590E548C8A729842AA102E11B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Restriction on disclosure</header><text>Return information disclosed under subparagraph (A) may be used by officers and employees of the Federal Communications Commission for the purposes of, and to the extent necessary in, preparing the reports required under section 2 of the <short-title>Independent Programmers Tax Incentive Act</short-title>. Such reports shall not include return information which is identifiable as being with respect to a particular taxpayer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

