<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H547880A62D5D424EB14118CDBF5B5BE3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2867 IH: Bruce’s Law</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2867</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000395">Mr. Rogers of Kentucky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish an awareness campaign related to the lethality of fentanyl and fentanyl-contaminated drugs, to establish a Federal Interagency Work Group on Fentanyl Contamination of Drugs, and to provide community-based coalition enhancement grants to mitigate the effects of drug use.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HFAE67C620DE64F3E8F151C7D50F7B245" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H49D4D7FCDFD84E0CA31A4B197FD2E212" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>Bruce’s Law</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H55E254C2FA5745ECB9818C5EAC4ECAC9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Awareness campaigns</header> <subsection id="HA299F6EB95784D2BBC696858AE91C82E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Opioid program</header><text>Section 102 of the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/198">Public Law 114–198</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3B0A2212152A4B75BE8A7FD0DB5AB015"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="section">relating to opioids</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="section">campaigns</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD27DA40D4BFB4F0DB7D3E2AE7B5AC6B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA53B9A10CE644ADCAD93E67FFB26F1EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H52289E6F9A8D4BBC9BFCB73D28794AC6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE2700DADA5D94563B6C68711BD92247F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H93C103166BFF4F2AA999B2B0BFBF5021"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional campaign</header><text>Title I of the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/198">Public Law 114–198</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 102 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0F1EEA0D515470FA7930E0DC8EE3B21"> 
<section id="H6B4E352D916C465982289431E52390FC"><enum>102A.</enum><header>Awareness campaign related to lethality of fentanyl and fentanyl-contaminated drugs</header> 
<subsection id="H9AA86F6BA34C44F9AA134C3EBC416ED0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services, in coordination with the heads of other Federal departments and agencies, shall, as appropriate, through a public awareness campaign, advance the education and awareness of the public (including school-aged children, youth, parents, first responders, and providers) and other appropriate entities regarding the risk of counterfeit drugs being contaminated with fentanyl or other synthetic opioids and the lethality and other dangers of synthetic opioids. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HF809D72BB5B6454380AC688D00803AE9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Topics</header><text>The education and awareness campaign under subsection (a) shall address— </text> 
<paragraph id="H49B7927EB86A48DE916C6A5A0B47E773"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the dangers of using drugs which may be contaminated with fentanyl or other synthetic opioids; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H858B5DFC28B34C9D90808BD0F8A54C0B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the prevention of substance use disorder and use of prescription drugs other than as prescribed, including through safe disposal of prescription medications and other safety precautions; and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB85FD4F5A374A02ABF3B094D0A7C533"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the detection of early warning signs of substance use disorder and addiction in school-aged children and youth.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBC6D8A31AAD447F58A40CD8017B45DE7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Other requirements</header><text>The education and awareness campaign under subsection (a) shall, as appropriate, take into account any association between the use of prescription drugs other than as prescribed and the use of drugs that can be contaminated by fentanyl or other opioids, including heroin.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9A89504EEE69417D996F2E2A8580286C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Drug defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>drug</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="H002BDFAA2C234E6082BF606EA85F0CBB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an illicit drug, such as marijuana, hashish, cocaine (including crack cocaine), inhalants, hallucinogens, heroin, a synthetic opioid, methamphetamine or other stimulant;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FFC64B0ED23424B97384049BC37B284"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a counterfeit prescription drug; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBB9049F6FDCE4C4A8364AFE407F0EE24"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a prescription drug that is sold illegally.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4AC3A961D64F4D93A520C35F4254AE02"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated for fiscal years 2024 through 2028 such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H8373B59DE73B4FF6A428D01F4D7CBEA1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Federal Interagency Work Group on Fentanyl Contamination of Drugs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/198">Public Law 114–198</external-xref>), as amended by section 2(b), is further amended by inserting after section 102A the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC144A877004546E1A7A5239666A47615"> 
<section id="H6D6E40241CF848079D220D81A4CB0077"><enum>102B.</enum><header>Federal Interagency Work Group on Fentanyl Contamination of Drugs</header> 
<subsection id="HBDEB667112A049C9989583D4646375FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish the Federal Interagency Work Group on Fentanyl Contamination of Drugs (referred to in this section as the <quote>Work Group</quote>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4F7FD590E6E74C3AACEF8E232F6BD115"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership; consultation</header> <paragraph id="H191E86A1BA754F74A12D5CAA786F0760"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of <short-title>Bruce’s Law</short-title>, the heads of the Office of National Drug Control Policy, the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration, the Administration for Children and Families, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Department of Justice, the Drug Enforcement Administration, the Department of State, the Department of Education, and other Federal agencies (as determined by the Secretary) shall designate representatives of the respective agency or office to the Work Group.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H32BA00E34974461F8D96B0B31A4305D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Work Group shall consult with—</text> <subparagraph id="HA70533596D114CF3B43672762A628BF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>experts at the State, Tribal, and local levels with relevant backgrounds in reducing, preventing, and responding to drug overdose by fentanyl contamination of drugs;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3B5FACE64E214CD9B0E16D53A696785E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">individuals in recovery from use of fentanyl other than as prescribed or use of other synthetic opioids;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB108A3E4098B4CA8848EE08EA82E1F52"><enum>(C)</enum><text>family members of adults who have overdosed by fentanyl-contaminated drugs; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H295A1A3BB59E49168DAEE493A6A26864"><enum>(D)</enum><text>family members of school-aged children and youth who have overdosed by fentanyl-contaminated drugs; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H251D712A3D1E48F0A34E14B61E9BAFF4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>researchers and other experts in the design and implementation of effective drug-related messaging and prevention campaigns; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA161DF45D3C54827A3E1EE2A77778875"><enum>(F)</enum><text>technology companies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H75CEF4FA09ED405C996ED000128F066D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Work Group shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H23A364E754CD477B90BBA0C5D6EC5162"><enum>(1)</enum><text>examine all Federal efforts directed towards reducing and preventing drug overdose by fentanyl- or other synthetic opioid-contaminated drugs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H55B283CA80EA44C487E249B0E7BA5E8B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify strategies, resources, and supports to improve State, Tribal, and local responses to overdose by fentanyl- or other synthetic opioid-contaminated drugs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3E13461846F54391A1C242871A6B7F45"><enum>(3)</enum><text>make recommendations to Congress for improving Federal programs and efforts and coordination across such programs and efforts to reduce and prevent drug overdose by fentanyl- or other synthetic opioid-contaminated drugs; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23BD67AF7798459097554E787A63221E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>make recommendations for educating youth on the dangers of drugs contaminated by fentanyl or other synthetic opioids.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF6E586EA938F43138F1FCEEE01C7953F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Annual report to Secretary</header><text>The Work Group shall annually prepare and submit to the Secretary, the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and the Committee on Education and the Workforce and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, a report on the activities carried out by the Work Group under subsection (c), including recommendations to reduce and prevent drug overdose by fentanyl or other synthetic opioid contamination of drugs, in all populations, and specifically among youth at risk for substance use disorder and use of drugs other than as prescribed.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H810C5FDD154A4377B80F526479167241"><enum>4.</enum><header>Community-based coalition enhancement grants to address local drug crises</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 103(i) of the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1536">21 U.S.C. 1536(i)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>2017 through 2021</quote> and inserting <quote>2024 through 2028</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H4A9112D9452140EBAD77BB3BF842AA12"><enum>5.</enum><header>Community-based coalition enhancement grants to educate youth on the risks of drugs contaminated with fentanyl or other synthetic opioids</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the Comprehensive Addiction and Recovery Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/198">Public Law 114–198</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 103 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1536">21 U.S.C. 1536</external-xref>) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBCC90553C826457792FB0E12C5B56198"> <section id="H771DFA056C5F4393B9BAC9FB786A3AB4"><enum>103A.</enum><header>Community-based coalition enhancement grants to educate youth on the risks of drugs contaminated with fentanyl or other synthetic opioids</header> <subsection id="HD63F7CC68C4F48F49AE5FB33223F05EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>The Director of the Office of National Drug Control Policy (referred to in this section as the <quote>Director</quote>), in coordination with the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, may make grants to eligible entities to implement education of the public on the dangers of contamination of drugs with fentanyl or other synthetic opioids.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8D271261C30B4B6F994B02F362ED2FFD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header> 
<paragraph id="HC85C9568A5D44B30B0F859791504030B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Director at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Director may require.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2BCE4FC031D944CAA34142035EEA95DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>As part of an application for a grant under this section, the Director shall require an eligible entity to submit a detailed, comprehensive, multisector plan for addressing the implementation of an evidence-based public education campaign on the dangers of drugs contaminated with fentanyl or other synthetic opioids, with a specific consideration given to education focused on youth at increased risk for developing a substance use disorder. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7283F74B827447418F7FDC6AC4A81E2A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity that—</text> <subparagraph id="H3258CC3A84964395BD2D8FBD14926766"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has documented, using local data, rates of drug overdose related to fentanyl or other synthetic opioids at levels that are significant, as determined by the Director; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCBAA3534ADA64795926F52E1FAE7D5BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has received a grant under the Drug-Free Communities Act of 1997.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2ECED520090C4376AA47AD337FAF3E5C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity shall use a grant received under this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDBF9A08CA6E1443685355C83ADFFB25B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for programs designed to implement comprehensive community-wide prevention strategies to address the dangers of drugs contaminated with fentanyl or other synthetic opioids, in the area served by the eligible entity, in accordance with the plan submitted under subsection (b)(2);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9855E4A5A9AB45428ACF5FAED654F75E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to obtain specialized training and technical assistance from the organization funded under section 4 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/82">Public Law 107–82</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1521">21 U.S.C. 1521</external-xref> note); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA35FE0AA12E3460C9990963B69A2E319"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for programs designed to implement comprehensive community-wide strategies to address the dangers of drugs contaminated with fentanyl or other synthetic opioids in the community.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1BB1C29DFA0B422E89A34A935F2C7BA4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text>An eligible entity shall use Federal funds received under this section only to supplement the funds that would, in the absence of those Federal funds, be made available from other Federal and non-Federal sources for the activities described in this section, and not to supplant those funds.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6B4C60A8706243C39CF9EF330F9437BD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>A grant under this section shall be subject to the same evaluation requirements and procedures as the evaluation requirements and procedures imposed on the recipient of a grant under the Drug-Free Communities Act of 1997, and shall also include an evaluation of the effectiveness at reducing the use of illicit fentanyl or other synthetic opioids.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6460FBFF0CCF4915AAECDE64D01CF447"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation on administrative expenses</header><text>Not more than 12 percent of the amounts made available to carry out this section for a fiscal year may be used to pay for administrative expenses.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFBC7AD11C281495FAC6333F26ABE54B2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Delegation authority</header><text>The Director may enter into an interagency agreement with the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to delegate authority for the execution of grants and for such other activities, as the Director determines necessary to carry out this section. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H2A3923E842D74969BC8B0827A9529205"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>drug</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102A.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC7A1CABA520E4E6790658F8F86DF255A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>For the purpose of carrying out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

