<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0A57040EE62E4A2DB04AB26CBA9EC98F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3523 IH: Perinatal Workforce Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3523</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001214">Mr. Mrvan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To grow and diversify the perinatal workforce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDA35223256BD45CDACA2EAF73472E2FB" style="OLC"><section id="H2C6B2ED023B6436CA468BD6BF74A1B32" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Perinatal Workforce Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H95807C91FB2C4544B9BA9FB3A4025BFA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>HHS agency directives</header><subsection id="H39731498165342F1BC616102F4E0C47C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Guidance to States</header><paragraph id="H52139FD5364F412896D7924E75BE69DE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall issue and disseminate guidance to States to educate providers, managed care entities, and other insurers about the value and process of delivering respectful maternal health care through diverse and multidisciplinary care provider models.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0005C60F9D084D6CAEB4D101C4A4538A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The guidance required by paragraph (1) shall address how States can encourage and incentivize hospitals, health systems, midwifery practices, freestanding birth centers, other maternity care provider groups, managed care entities, and other insurers—</text><subparagraph id="HFACE261AABEE49AC8D5CBFEC21AB05B5" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to recruit and retain maternity care providers, mental and behavioral health care providers acting in accordance with State law, and registered dietitians or nutrition professionals (as such term is defined in section 1861(vv)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(vv)(2)</external-xref>))—</text><clause id="HD9666A7A37DE42CBBDA9EDEDBEDC9A46" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">from racially, ethnically, and linguistically diverse backgrounds;</text></clause><clause id="H726C647407444238B39FE1A33803352B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with experience practicing in racially and ethnically diverse communities; and</text></clause><clause id="H5C57E918B7174667A63542C7A305E1E6" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>who have undergone training on implicit bias and racism;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC1180088A234F4EBDE2423F1362D2E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to incorporate into maternity care teams—</text><clause id="HC02569D3511444BCA79F6896F4B1163F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>midwives who meet, at a minimum, the international definition of a midwife and global standards for midwifery education as established by the International Confederation of Midwives; </text></clause><clause id="HFFA578697C394808AEE7EE72AB7E6EEB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>perinatal health workers;</text></clause><clause id="HBC22A1EAFC6D41BAB68CA8EE623705EB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">physician assistants;</text></clause><clause id="H3CEB5D1AB07949EE9701B0183EC388B0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>advanced practice registered nurses; and</text></clause><clause id="H37A58797D6EF42E0B3B22CED27D9A0E6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>lactation consultants certified by the International Board of Lactation Consultant Examiners;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D7FCA7F72284D75BF31F14EE787A838"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide collaborative, culturally and linguistically congruent care; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H768659A385814CB483682A02FF6E4A98"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide opportunities for individuals enrolled in accredited midwifery education programs to participate in job shadowing with maternity care teams in hospitals, health systems, midwifery practices, and freestanding birth centers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H801751BC5D554633A3F270C2C1CB73CE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study on respectful and culturally and linguistically congruent maternity care</header><paragraph id="H7F678586591A42FAA5BF47A734B92FDE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services acting through the Director of the National Institutes of Health (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall conduct a study on best practices in respectful and culturally and linguistically congruent maternity care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B6B3C32E81C485FABE71B71D3C1C4AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HCBB1375197724991918E578D13BDE860"><enum>(A)</enum><text>complete the study required by paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H021FDCAF0CA7449B85B326DB2B016CC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the Congress and make publicly available a report on the results of such study; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5E2AFDA4A014913AE7F7384CA7C0B5C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include in such report—</text><clause id="HBB00C46D97D34974A1AE7B96E8C6629A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a compendium of examples of hospitals, health systems, midwifery practices, freestanding birth centers, other maternity care provider groups, managed care entities, and other insurers that are delivering respectful and culturally and linguistically congruent maternal health care;</text></clause><clause id="H6C32B4E0D0254DB9AE957D914CB0196F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a compendium of examples of hospitals, health systems, midwifery practices, freestanding birth centers, other maternity care provider groups, managed care entities, and other insurers that have made progress in reducing disparities in maternal health outcomes and improving birthing experiences for pregnant and postpartum individuals from racial and ethnic minority groups; and</text></clause><clause id="HC019EE5840DF40839772003EF61F1CCA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations to hospitals, health systems, midwifery practices, freestanding birth centers, other maternity care provider groups, managed care entities, and other insurers, for best practices in respectful and culturally and linguistically congruent maternity care. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H637D374A02314B12BDACCDE2EE5BFC0C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Grants to grow and diversify the perinatal workforce</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title VII of the Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 757 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/294f">42 U.S.C. 294f</external-xref>) the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7A0FF18A571B4E48B4A31338E560F994" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HB8E5D43470FE4AEB9584E05ED1716837"><enum>758.</enum><header>Perinatal workforce grants</header><subsection id="H1E69861721A4450FA568FA37EE0D9E1D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants to entities to establish or expand programs described in subsection (b) to grow and diversify the perinatal workforce.</text></subsection><subsection id="H92FEFEEACC5647B8AECF8BAA059558C7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recipients of grants under this section shall use the grants to grow and diversify the perinatal workforce by—</text><paragraph id="HFA99689CEFAF412A81858315D1C63D27"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing accredited schools or programs that provide education and training to individuals seeking appropriate licensing and certification as—</text><subparagraph id="HB720796E479C4DBD89692B2B7BA3EAD4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>physician assistants who will complete clinical training in the field of maternal and perinatal health; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HACD6534B2225410E9DCFAECC317FBE5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perinatal health workers; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0CCE46A71394405C88FF7F732AAED1FF"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">midwives who meet, at a minimum, the international definition of a midwife and global standards for midwifery education as established by the International Confederation of Midwives; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA326437EEE7462480C28040246B49AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expanding the capacity of existing accredited schools or programs described in paragraph (1), for the purposes of increasing the number of students enrolled in such accredited schools or programs, such as by awarding scholarships for students (including students from racially, ethnically, and linguistically diverse backgrounds).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H77E50B03AD5C4890A8FEE5D6CACA701C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to a school or program described in subsection (b) that—</text><paragraph id="HCEAEFA1D476B42048087E28DB6F23609"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has demonstrated a commitment to recruiting and retaining students and faculty from racial and ethnic minority groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H735A9856620E4A4880FA3697B19035E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has developed a strategy to recruit and retain a diverse pool of students into the school or program described in subsection (b) that is supported by funds received through the grant, particularly from racial and ethnic minority groups and other underserved populations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38FC3E95E694490C95EEDE9EC061CE44"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has developed a strategy to recruit and retain students who plan to practice in a health professional shortage area designated under section 332;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DCCF9C968D1433AA86E15C51CA9FA0E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has developed a strategy to recruit and retain students who plan to practice in an area with significant racial and ethnic disparities in maternal health outcomes, to the extent practicable; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBE944C8B2FA41E7917AD0AF3C856AD2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes in the standard curriculum for all students within the school or program described in subsection (b) a bias, racism, or discrimination training program that includes training on implicit bias and racism.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF45C52175F4F42FC9467A13420D3424D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As a condition on receipt of a grant under this section for a school or program described in subsection (b), an entity shall agree to submit to the Secretary an annual report on the activities conducted through the grant, including—</text><paragraph id="H54ACA6CFCB7347B0B421271A67FC2532"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number and demographics of students participating in the school or program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3190AF71513F43ECB84715F6BB058312"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which students in the school or program are entering careers in—</text><subparagraph id="H8C6DFD1B79444BE8823BC4A26C8CB932"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">health professional shortage areas designated under section 332; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5DB236A53619421C873E6A49CCD48553"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">areas with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes, to the extent such data are available; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE8420934E4442D789DD49EB093A137B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>whether the school or program has included in the standard curriculum for all students a bias, racism, or discrimination training program that includes explicit and implicit bias, and if so the effectiveness of such training program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H15163FB3C3D5499B85E443EB83A94A49"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Period of grants</header><text>The period of a grant under this section shall be up to 5 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H061B095DBA604EE08E1D3165172562AA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To seek a grant under this section, an entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including any information necessary for prioritization under subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6315A3F5411E4F39A3CB17585C14DDAF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide, directly or by contract, technical assistance to entities seeking or receiving a grant under this section on the development, use, evaluation, and postgrant period sustainability of the school or program described in subsection (b) that is proposed to be, or is being, established or expanded through the grant.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF62CCE01172144E8B7633EC9BE885FA6"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Report by the Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the Congress, and post on the internet website of the Department of Health and Human Services, a report on the effectiveness of the grant program under this section at—</text><paragraph id="H9E325B95ED6D49C5A01654593865EA82"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recruiting students from racial and ethnic minority groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5EB7ECE1C1741C8A845AB32ACE731F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the number of health professionals described in subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) of subsection (b)(1) from racial and ethnic minority groups and other underserved populations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB11D5314CE84203B00D45746F9AF7C1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the number of such health professionals working in health professional shortage areas designated under section 332; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF83070B0F5684E5EB3A54148325EAC14"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the number of such health professionals working in areas with significant racial and ethnic disparities in maternal health outcomes, to the extent such data are available.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4C43698EB98143D29DC60518A78EBFE7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>racial and ethnic minority group</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1707(g)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="H14191E43C8A8485BAA6504B52BDDB059"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H012F2F4BCE0640E794B60DBCD0AB15A2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grants to grow and diversify the nursing workforce in maternal and perinatal health</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title VIII of the Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 811 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/296j">42 U.S.C. 296j</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H702FC943BEDE4095B7CBA61BB21D6B29" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H86AA3843273E406C86B8E097A301CBD0"><enum>812.</enum><header>Perinatal nursing workforce grants</header><subsection id="HB61875D5B27D45E2BF5C7F32405B70B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to schools of nursing to grow and diversify the perinatal nursing workforce.</text></subsection><subsection id="H17F8B2F83F0F4DFE8D1B7041CCF37210"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Recipients of grants under this section shall use the grants to grow and diversify the perinatal nursing workforce by providing scholarships to students seeking to become—</text><paragraph id="HDEE04D3B413C42D09E9775596272DC66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>nurse practitioners whose education includes a focus on maternal and perinatal health;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E2BC7095C7D4797BB769709751ED946"><enum>(2)</enum><text>certified nurse-midwives; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AFD4BCE75C142E19E14BAD053F63062"><enum>(3)</enum><text>clinical nurse specialists whose education includes a focus on maternal and perinatal health.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H217A8C845E194B549DC3F1F6798BD6D8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to any school of nursing that—</text><paragraph id="H94C5CACFD880441C9082ABC8FAF8431F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has developed a strategy to recruit and retain a diverse pool of students seeking to enter careers focused on maternal and perinatal health, particularly students from racial and ethnic minority groups and other underserved populations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F6596446D3F40B881D35F62E572DA70"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has developed a partnership with a practice setting in a health professional shortage area designated under section 332 for the clinical placements of the school’s students;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE8A97B685F146FABAB93A0F76ADAF03"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has developed a strategy to recruit and retain students who plan to practice in an area with significant racial and ethnic disparities in maternal health outcomes, to the extent practicable; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67D5C83EBB9D4134A51F904A56F60EF9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>includes in the standard curriculum for all students seeking to enter careers focused on maternal and perinatal health a bias, racism, or discrimination training program that includes education on implicit bias and racism.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A68BCDBB7C647479685CE6D49F5D630"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>As a condition on receipt of a grant under this section, a school of nursing shall agree to submit to the Secretary an annual report on the activities conducted through the grant, including, to the extent practicable—</text><paragraph id="HC260FC1F54374868A7BF65F4C3A76154"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number and demographics of students in the school of nursing seeking to enter careers focused on maternal and perinatal health;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6040E621EADC4D29BB8FD6AE4FD93B9B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the extent to which such students are preparing to enter careers in—</text><subparagraph id="H9AD44F58FD134EAEA32C8CD8D91B2A43"><enum>(A)</enum><text>health professional shortage areas designated under section 332; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAE43CD3A7BB471A937D9A1FB83268C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">areas with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes, to the extent such data are available; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A81276DBF034A62ABD5FFD45BB5AE27"><enum>(3)</enum><text>whether the standard curriculum for all students seeking to enter careers focused on maternal and perinatal health includes a bias, racism, or discrimination training program that includes education on implicit bias and racism.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0CB5F526EA5A4FC294F96CEB18BA19D0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Period of grants</header><text>The period of a grant under this section shall be up to 5 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2617ADF5D62647B49F9BAB04A427BBE7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To seek a grant under this section, an entity shall submit to the Secretary an application, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including any information necessary for prioritization under subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0AB35783C8DA4DE3ACBA7DC0C08E15DC"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall provide, directly or by contract, technical assistance to schools of nursing seeking or receiving a grant under this section on the processes of awarding and evaluating scholarships through the grant.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA9A86F9691AD45A1BE56A2535BF128E7"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Report by the Secretary</header><text>Not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the Congress, and post on the internet website of the Department of Health and Human Services, a report on the effectiveness of the grant program under this section at—</text><paragraph id="H1E79C73A6BEA4B2B902C0E3A0F311F87"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recruiting students from racial and ethnic minority groups and other underserved populations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H067BB22C6AB343A99C6D4D40D8EE6A83"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the number of advanced practice registered nurses entering careers focused on maternal and perinatal health from racial and ethnic minority groups and other underserved populations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED71584B7A404D339345B37F92C2B309"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the number of advanced practice registered nurses entering careers focused on maternal and perinatal health working in health professional shortage areas designated under section 332; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41BE08A547704CB4BFE51D67FED6CF1D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the number of advanced practice registered nurses entering careers focused on maternal and perinatal health working in areas with significant racial and ethnic disparities in maternal health outcomes, to the extent such data are available.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H712A9F783A1B4FCCB824939ABFDC1253"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HF625855A5F004607BFE8B2F70CBEB6DE"><enum>5.</enum><header>GAO report</header><subsection id="H9A9A254879614C28B47DFA3BE32C8BEA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act and every 5 years thereafter, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on barriers to maternal health education and access to care in the United States. Such report shall include the information and recommendations described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HF4ED35C55F794188AC31EA9C82838E92"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Content of report</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="HB82AF36B4A854494878650CCD77F6C64"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of current barriers to entering and successfully completing accredited midwifery education programs, and recommendations for addressing such barriers, particularly for low-income women and women from racial and ethnic minority groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A2F8BA0548848EC95481282E40BC52A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of current barriers to entering and successfully completing accredited education programs for other health professional careers related to maternity care, including maternity care providers, mental and behavioral health care providers acting in accordance with State law, and registered dietitians or nutrition professionals (as such term is defined in section 1861(vv)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(vv)(2)</external-xref>)), particularly for low-income women and women from racial and ethnic minority groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD12B0330B314A24A69D0C39E998CC44"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of current barriers that prevent midwives from meeting the international definition of a midwife and global standards for midwifery education as established by the International Confederation of Midwives, and recommendations for addressing such barriers, particularly for low-income women and women from racial and ethnic minority groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08E7690015B6465697F5818915C76B6B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of disparities in access to maternity care providers, mental or behavioral health care providers acting in accordance with State law, and registered dietitians or nutrition professionals (as such term is defined in section 1861(vv)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(vv)(2)</external-xref>)), and perinatal health workers, stratified by race, ethnicity, gender identity, primary language, geographic location, and insurance type and recommendations to promote greater access equity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05461B379CE94461840254491C8FC952"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations to promote greater equity in compensation for perinatal health workers under public and private insurers, particularly for such individuals from racially and ethnically diverse backgrounds.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDFC4D71F29E74AAFAC2B6C4E9CFB3B77"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H4824E7DF0B344C45BAB6172E6F127B69"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Culturally and linguistically congruent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>culturally and linguistically congruent</term>, with respect to care or maternity care, means care that is in agreement with the preferred cultural values, beliefs, worldview, language, and practices of the health care consumer and other stakeholders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12A8868692F2436EA08EAFFFCC71F231"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maternal mortality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternal mortality</term> means a death occurring during or within a 1-year period after pregnancy, caused by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications, including a suicide, overdose, or other death resulting from a mental health or substance use disorder attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB4980D314BF4F7CA2E80A386475EB67"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Maternity care provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternity care provider</term> means a health care provider who—</text><subparagraph id="H7702325D6ADE420FACC1EDC7F13B56EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a physician, physician assistant, midwife who meets at a minimum the international definition of a midwife and global standards for midwifery education as established by the International Confederation of Midwives, advanced practice registered nurse, or a lactation consultant certified by the International Board of Lactation Consultant Examiners; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H071A774336F14F8681B4E15BD16F8174"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has a focus on maternal or perinatal health.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C3C1050F2224C3998F3CEF67202DE31"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Perinatal health worker</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>perinatal health worker</term> means a nonclinical health worker focused on maternal or perinatal health, such as a doula, community health worker, peer supporter, lactation educator or counselor, nutritionist or dietitian, childbirth educator, social worker, home visitor, patient navigator or coordinator, or language interpreter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB46A9E79DEF4C90A3093A2DFDAE220D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Postpartum</header><text>The term <term>postpartum</term> refers to the 1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy of an individual.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F42CD15EB6E4178B9015E12BBFC1763"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Racial and ethnic minority group</header><text>The term <term>racial and ethnic minority group</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1707(g)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300u-6">42 U.S.C. 300u–6(g)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

