<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H50F3B9B89C74407FB4F05CD529F51987" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6004 IH: Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6004</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231019">October 19, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend titles XIX and XXI of the Social Security Act to improve Medicaid and the Children’s Health Insurance Program for low-income mothers.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H5F66193B67134DC59C3A4DA1579ECA64" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H64866B06E3774E6D8F3B5F961616AFB3"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MOMMIES Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H84CD1D4F08B44588ACAB144098C490A7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Enhancing Medicaid and CHIP benefits for low-income pregnant individuals</header> <subsection id="HA30FC665975749A9AAEFF829F8CAE0DE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Extending continuous Medicaid and CHIP coverage for pregnant and postpartum individuals</header> <paragraph id="HE2D4AEE180644193AEA5D9C399DC5461"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><text>Title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCF4083D5A3044E85BDE381F200E48664"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 1902(e)—</text> <clause id="HBF0115F230F946B7A15DAFA39BCF00DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>60-day period (beginning on the last day of her pregnancy)</quote> and inserting <quote>1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy (or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect)</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5D0D077D8DB94614A911ACFA0AFC607E" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (16);</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB0E2C1E8231B48568CC4643A61288A44"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 1902(l)(1)(A), by striking <quote>60-day period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy</quote> and inserting <quote>1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE90BAF54E4F643EFB1BD6FB12219057F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 1903(v)(4)(A)(i), by striking <quote>60-day period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy</quote> and inserting <quote>1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD33045BA205E40AF92D79A88F7201A5C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in section 1905(a), in the 4th sentence in the matter following the last numbered paragraph of such section, by striking <quote>60-day period beginning on the last day of her pregnancy</quote> and inserting <quote>1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy, or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect,</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4FF145E1B87D45DAB637B4A403F9B4A2"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">CHIP</header><text>Section 2112 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397ll">42 U.S.C. 1397ll</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H153262E91B67499293B2A8320EB6005B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d)(2)(A), by striking <quote>60-day period</quote> and all that follows through the semicolon and inserting <quote>1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy, or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect, ends;</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF529BDF823CF4D9C9A65DC4F40E76BAF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (f)(2), by striking <quote>60-day period (beginning on the last day of the pregnancy)</quote> and inserting <quote>1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy, or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect,</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE8184D6554F643F297E4C5AB176C649F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requiring full benefits for pregnant and postpartum individuals</header> <paragraph id="H71D2C374F06B427D95312C9CC8A8D45C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (5) of section 1902(e) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/24/1396a">24 U.S.C. 1396a(e)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5D4DCB82248B4604B8E7099FA2533A0B"> 
<paragraph id="H96D3315D735A4609ADDFD66CD1778516"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Coverage of full benefits for at least 1 year for pregnant and postpartum individuals</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD057F3F427A349C5B3C0B0CED5484285"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any individual who, while pregnant, is eligible for and has received medical assistance under the State plan approved under this title or a waiver of such plan (including during a period of retroactive eligibility under subsection (a)(34)) shall continue to be eligible under the plan or waiver for medical assistance through the end of the month in which the 1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy, or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect, ends, regardless of the basis for the individual's eligibility for medical assistance, including if the individual's eligibility for medical assistance is on the basis of being pregnant.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE9027A0641F84DA7876927A4F1192F6F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Scope of benefits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The medical assistance provided for a pregnant or postpartum individual described in subparagraph (A) shall— </text> 
<clause commented="no" id="H66A82FCBC66941FD8BF134661B1249AC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>include all items and services covered under the State plan (or waiver) that are not less in amount, duration, or scope, or are determined by the Secretary to be substantially equivalent, to the medical assistance available for an individual described in subsection (a)(10)(A)(i); and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H30886D5282D74A54B0F3411ED559C753"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be provided for the individual while pregnant and during the 1-year period that begins on the last day of the pregnancy, or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect, and ends on the last day of the month in which such period ends.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBCCA4710CC3D4F878E34CFA74E0FF7DD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H24B9A12D34DE424A9784DD385DF13128"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1902(a)(10) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(10)</external-xref>) is amended in the matter following subparagraph (G) by striking <quote>(VII) the medical assistance</quote> and all that follows through <quote>during the period described in such section,</quote>.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H938262C7A4C74E109099F5A1B447952B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2107(e)(1)(J) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397gg">42 U.S.C. 1397gg(e)(1)(J)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<clause id="H73B904F085874648A52561A54DB75D52"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Paragraphs (5) and (16)</quote> and inserting <quote>Paragraph (5)</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H5D1EABBD9CCD47F2BCF695905E581853" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(relating to</quote> and all that follows through the period and inserting <quote>(relating to the provision of medical assistance to pregnant individuals during and following pregnancy under title XIX).</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H837E74DB94DE4879A7004B36E415864E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requiring coverage of oral health services for pregnant and postpartum individuals</header> 
<paragraph id="H715E118492E94C42A7B68199D146AA92"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><text>Section 1905 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H91F715F063A2423B820B47C101BBC588"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(4)—</text> 
<clause id="HFF27E89382AF40C18E8D890CC23F4CFD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and (D)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (D)</quote>; </text></clause> <clause id="H5897E5472458488FB52EC37D2E901191"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and (E)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (E)</quote>;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4873DE3A2E2B4432B19F86CB03A06FCA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and (F)</quote> and inserting <quote>; (F)</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H1B09659E314344E4BD827AF6A0442516"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>; and (G) oral health services for pregnant and postpartum individuals (as defined in subsection (jj))</quote> after <quote>(or waiver of such plan)</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6F4B04A655244580835D5DDEB1B9B290"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="H8676F2025FD84734948BD1C8D1949D10"> <subsection id="HAC0A3861F9D24370853B4B620D2EE150"><enum>(jj)</enum><header>Oral health services for pregnant and postpartum individuals</header> <paragraph id="HAB9007ADD226471E9DAAFC5B3DCDF3E1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this title, the term <term>oral health services for pregnant and postpartum individuals</term> means dental services necessary to prevent disease and promote oral health, restore oral structures to health and function, and treat emergency conditions that are furnished to an individual during pregnancy (or during the 1 year period that begins on the last day of the pregnancy, or such longer period beginning on such day as the State may elect).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H430930D3D211425E9FFC1CCF5CF69882"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coverage requirements</header><text>To satisfy the requirement to provide oral health services for pregnant and postpartum individuals, a State shall, at a minimum, provide coverage for preventive, diagnostic, periodontal, and restorative care consistent with recommendations for comprehensive perinatal oral health services and dental services during pregnancy from the American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32432D5499D3415B809AA34257B46936"><enum>(2)</enum><header>CHIP</header><text>Section 2103(c)(6)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397cc">42 U.S.C. 1397cc(c)(6)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>or a targeted low-income pregnant individual</quote> after <quote>targeted low-income child</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCD08174740EE486FA6689615E8C10B04"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text>Section 2112(d)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397ll">42 U.S.C. 1397ll(d)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF9E2FB420B344EB9B8BF6C153E942AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the paragraph header, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">; targeted low-income pregnant individual</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">woman</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAD3963EFD09F47C998FCEEB21030A82E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the term <term>targeted low-income pregnant woman</term> means</quote> and inserting <quote>the terms <term>targeted low-income pregnant woman</term> and <term>targeted low-income pregnant individual</term> mean</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9D27675F16B840279CD43BCC6AF14201"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2AE8E3EAFAEF414AA46D15CD8C44491A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><text>Section 1902 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H70064A48D30A4085A0C5CC4D32F19619"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (74), by striking <quote>subsection (gg); and</quote> and inserting <quote>subsections (gg) and (uu);</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H57BFEDDDF1E340A7B9BC1A5D03AECCA1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="HBF8F63BD95044DA0AEDDE2E7006DBB4B"> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H2843989082054B379D788D3FECFA8D37"><enum>(uu)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort related to low-Income pregnant individuals</header><text>For calendar quarters beginning on or after the date of enactment of this subsection, and before January 1, 2025, no Federal payment shall be made to a State under section 1903(a) for amounts expended under a State plan under this title or a waiver of such plan if the State—</text> <paragraph id="HD50925323FC64AA0BD71D9329D3F45F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has in effect under such plan eligibility standards, methodologies, or procedures (including any enrollment cap or other numerical limitation on enrollment, any waiting list, any procedures designed to delay the consideration of applications for enrollment, any income counting rules, or similar limitation with respect to enrollment) for individuals described in subsection (l)(1) who are eligible for medical assistance under the State plan or waiver under subsection (a)(10)(A)(ii)(IX) that are more restrictive than the eligibility standards, methodologies, or procedures, respectively, for such individuals under such plan or waiver that are in effect on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</short-title>; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D254995E4B14F9A85310B468C36BC2B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reduces the amount, duration, or scope of medical assistance available to individuals described in subsection (l)(1) who are eligible for medical assistance under such plan or waiver under subsection (a)(10)(A)(ii)(IX) from what the State provided to such individuals under such plan or waiver on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</short-title>.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H78A92EA7899547E49BB5E9C9947C8D15"><enum>(2)</enum><header>CHIP</header><text>Section 2112 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397ll">42 U.S.C. 1397ll</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a), is further amended by adding at the end the following subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="HE1D4B81BE34B45DB99828C6571C4280E"> 
<subsection id="H7BF8D9CBF1D3425CA1E1B448915E1511"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>For calendar quarters beginning on or after January 1, 2024, and before January 1, 2028, no payment may be made under section 2105(a) with respect to a State child health plan if the State—</text> <paragraph id="H7F3D74135A5347F988D514CFDAB780C7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has in effect under such plan eligibility standards, methodologies, or procedures (including any enrollment cap or other numerical limitation on enrollment, any waiting list, any procedures designed to delay the consideration of applications for enrollment, or similar limitation with respect to enrollment) for targeted low-income pregnant individuals that are more restrictive than the eligibility standards, methodologies, or procedures, respectively, under such plan that are in effect on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</short-title>; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC29792E967FA495AB6076C1828C8D8EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides pregnancy-related assistance to targeted low-income pregnant individuals under such plan at a level that is less than the level at which the State provides such assistance to such individuals under such plan on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</short-title>.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3EA195C13E8440DAB58DBAABB4CF4426"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enhanced FMAP</header><text>Section 1905 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (c), is further amended—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC9A65B33439D4FAA9883CEDF3EE7B2D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>and (ii)</quote> and inserting <quote>(ii), and (kk)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E2656A22F454CBD88A8E761258EC396"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="HAFAE2786A9B94F87A184C1C19C42720A"> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HCE39331AEDD443F2970B518DFB335288"><enum>(kk)</enum><header>Increased FMAP for additional expenditures for low-Income pregnant individuals</header><text>For calendar quarters beginning on or after January 1, 2024, notwithstanding subsection (b), the Federal medical assistance percentage for a State, with respect to the additional amounts expended by such State for medical assistance under the State plan under this title or a waiver of such plan that are attributable to requirements imposed by the amendments made by the <short-title>Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</short-title> (as determined by the Secretary), shall be equal to 100 percent.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H20A962768DA84C748AC6C8C9FF8B7937"><enum>(f)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">GAO study and report</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7E9BE45E79ED402DB63E2BF2FBDA7E4F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on the gaps in coverage for—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H73128C30C4C64C41A483DED8D5E9DB14"><enum>(A)</enum><text>pregnant individuals under the Medicaid program under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Children's Health Insurance Program under title XXI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6DB079F412BF4726A15F6978D74B300D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>postpartum individuals under the Medicaid program and the Children's Health Insurance Program who received assistance under either such program during their pregnancy; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB425493BB5794EFC81F8F8A3BD5968D1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>birthing people between the ages of 15 and 49 under the Medicaid program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F12B8C6F23144C9BF9BE49E5EA48F63"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Content of report</header><text>The report required under this subsection shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H11593097D799469E859AA8CCF8C0FD82"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Information about the abilities and successes of State Medicaid agencies in determining whether pregnant and postpartum individuals are eligible under another insurance affordability program, and in transitioning any such individuals who are so eligible to coverage under such a program at the end of their period of eligibility for medical assistance, pursuant to section 435.1200 of the title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on September 1, 2018).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC0A0010044854E6CB7F70E66355DCFD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Information on factors contributing to gaps in coverage that disproportionately impact underserved populations, including low-income individuals, Black, Indigenous, and other individuals of color, individuals who reside in a health professional shortage area (as defined in section 332(a)(1)(A) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254e">42 U.S.C. 254e(a)(1)(A)</external-xref>)) or individuals who are members of a medically underserved population (as defined by section 330(b)(3) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b(b)(3)(A)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCC9DFE3D0CF742858C517B933A51CF65"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Recommendations for addressing and reducing such gaps in coverage.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD2A3F57165784DBAB73B8E0A825C7AA5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Such other information as the Comptroller General deems necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7B367337731A4708B39091144C2EAA0F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Data disaggregation</header><text>To the greatest extent possible, the Comptroller General shall dissagregate data presented in the report, including by age, gender identity, race, ethnicity, income level, and other demographic factors.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE8CCB82C56F469F8FEC55983DB6CB09"><enum>(g)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by subsections (a) and (b) shall take effect on January 1, 2024.</text></subsection></section> 
<section commented="no" id="HBECB7B39F41847CAA33D1BBA8B95F02D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Maternity care home demonstration project</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting the following new section after section 1947:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A1E14A9469848E6AD811B54D33D61A7"> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HA340AF22DC18495A8797A28938186092"><enum>1948.</enum><header>Maternity Care Home Demonstration Project</header> <subsection id="H33C6483D0D274147A99391137ADCF353"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall establish a demonstration project (in this section referred to as the <term>demonstration project</term>) under which the Secretary shall provide grants to States to enter into arrangements with eligible entities to implement or expand a maternity care home model for eligible individuals.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H95B80F5E038C4FECAEF160DFD90A1206"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H5D8DEA605F9841F8BD587DDD825173F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity or organization that provides medically accurate, comprehensive maternity services to individuals who are eligible for medical assistance under a State plan under this title or a waiver of such a plan, and may include:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA49342C1E1EE41A7973010AEE0813A24"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A freestanding birth center.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0B1B6CE03FF84C81A648DB12A47405B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An entity or organization receiving assistance under section 330 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCE61E12B31554BB6B8BBED773DA2ADD6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A federally qualified health center.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1686A57FB23B4CDCA85756EE6F1C63EC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A rural health clinic.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9FDB1D74968643CF9FBD30BBA881E84C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A health facility operated by an Indian tribe or tribal organization (as those terms are defined in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4B1E3855709A43DD9BB65F0A5D449823"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text>The term <term>eligible individual</term> means a pregnant individual or a formerly pregnant individual during the 1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy, or such longer period beginning on such day as a State may elect, who is—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H017885A63CAF450EB04A7A268F9C541E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enrolled in a State plan under this title, a waiver of such a plan, or a State child health plan under title XXI; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H4E7B13C1C29843B09A6758066CE306A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a patient of an eligible entity which has entered into an arrangement with a State under subsection (g). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H6770B540375C4C298C12549FFEFCF9D6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Goals of demonstration project</header><text>The goals of the demonstration project are the following: </text> <paragraph id="HEDA58A92236342BC935D6DC22E93B2FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To improve—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBCAF02A3D0E54B0AB8527D1C3F0D3864"><enum>(A)</enum><text>maternity and infant care outcomes;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEB1F1B484ABC40D0A9D501A7CFEDB15B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>birth equity;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1DC6BFC26D2F427BA56D72EF4489622A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>health equity for— </text> <clause id="HF2C3241AE76040E1A7E109306FBC3CBF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Black, Indigenous, and other people of color; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H33E89BC85FFF44438D4005700EDB474B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>lesbian, gay, bisexual, trans­gen­der, queer, non-binary, and gender nonconfirming individuals;</text></clause> <clause id="H4BD0E379E95A40EF98E8E2069957415F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>people who live in regions with limited or no access to obstetric care;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H50346573DFCE4D2F8B80DDEDEAE43C2D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">people with disabilities; and </text></clause> <clause id="HF4C3D626B7CB4C92A89AA6218FA16DCE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>other underserved populations; </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC76067CBE46444D385E9ECE43CA41D6F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>communication by and between maternity, infant care, and social services providers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H46E54F1586534BCE93D2E365AEA9E4CE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>integration of perinatal support services, including community health workers, doulas, social workers, public health nurses, peer lactation counselors, lactation consultants, childbirth educators, peer mental health workers, and others, into health care entities and organizations;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3639488EB7A04E21A1CA0E7876BDCAEE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>care coordination between maternity, infant care, oral health services, and social services providers within the community;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8C10DDAE13754253B9BDD4EC30013D44"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the quality and safety of maternity and infant care;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H675D34EDFA414B168EFC703FF92F4CD0"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the experience of individuals receiving respectful maternity care, including by increasing the ability of an individual to develop and follow their own birthing plans; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA722832735234B35A26F56692DE06176"><enum>(I)</enum><text>access to adequate prenatal and postpartum care, including—</text> 
<clause id="HB3B78A54DB0148D4BA8B83280565BBC5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prenatal care that is initiated in a timely manner;</text></clause> <clause id="HFBC0E5D4F5344EA79C76750CA36338DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not fewer than 5 post-pregnancy visits to a maternity care provider for postpartum care and support;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5D797B463AD940FE9E951CF40681D8AC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>interpregnancy care; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H974EBD5169714FB0809D944DEE8DC717"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>support and treatment for perinatal mood and anxiety disorders.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD1761BF672B04308B062D3C0207E933D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To provide coordinated, evidence-based, respectful, culturally and linguistically appropriate, and person-centered maternity care management.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H33D34A851A6C4E6AB0172A946D25557C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To decrease—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3CD1F5E12C514E75B9E0E1630E71FA5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>preventable and severe maternal morbidity and maternal mortality;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4FB333724C8748AFA1200F2149DCC77C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>overall health care spending;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE3DE109D51EA46E9A6B1E3C5DC5C9163"><enum>(C)</enum><text>unnecessary emergency department visits;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA846BA35A11D4D12B85521B9C6B65F0A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>disparities in maternal and infant care outcomes, including racial, economic, disability, gender-based, and geographical disparities;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H859299D637C2453BB8D7862F4ADD8D2E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>racial, gender, economic, and other discrimination among among health care professionals;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6F33428A03DE4D4992C16462B4C6E6C9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>racism, discrimination, disrespect, trauma, and abuse in maternity care settings;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8D03BF86F6D1493A907A4B45AB347427"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the rate of cesarean deliveries for low-risk pregnancies;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAAB8688029554123B1AA2041E90B6459"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the rate of preterm births and infants born with low birth weight;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5A30DED8E6A84596818B27E7180A9A1B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the rate of avoidable maternal and newborn hospitalizations and admissions to intensive care units; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1E277C55DECE42C4A3E1C182AEDA8936"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the rate of perinatal mood and anxiety disorders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0E2A94EB7A6340ADA4D930AA5F0BAC25"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In designing and implementing the demonstration project the Secretary shall consult with stakeholders, including—</text> <paragraph id="H8B24D96075B945A183FF465E47BF9612"><enum>(1)</enum><text>States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2EDF1DEC7DE54B82B568396B60D7AED4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>organizations representing relevant health care professionals, including oral health services professionals;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0331C9CA7D1B414E99128F25D51B1BF4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>organizations, particularly reproductive justice and birth justice organizations led by people of color, that represent consumers of maternal health care, including consumers of maternal health care who are disproportionately impacted by poor maternal health outcomes; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2BB8482DC8CD4CE9A9345D214005A85B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>representatives with experience implementing other maternity care home models, including representatives from the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H33050FD42FB840CDAF77A4FE77637FCC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>community-based health care professionals, including doulas, lactation consultants, and other stakeholders;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4A1FE2F156D548E595969BCF776BECAE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>experts in promoting health equity and combating racial bias in health care settings; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFBE0864C52DE4633BDE99DD00F63CB81"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Black, Indigenous, and other maternal health care consumers of color who have experienced severe maternal morbidity.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE5CDB1F529AF4A448481F3874FC114EA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application and selection of States</header> 
<paragraph id="H3BC7628CC2B04DF1AFD67EE11A6EB147"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State seeking to participate in the demonstration project shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary shall require.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H902EDA182A264741BBC041DEAABF57B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of States</header> <subparagraph id="HACB588DCE767414DBEC53D7BA0C7E9D7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall select at least 10 States to participate in the demonstration project.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H59ABE16F10DE4DE0A0B591CBA9B53CFD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection requirements</header><text>In selecting States to participate in the demonstration project, the Secretary shall—</text> <clause id="HDA1E662B0C9D44CC8716B3559FA7CCF8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>ensure that there is geographic and regional diversity in the areas in which activities will be carried out under the project;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFAB85CDA31124E3A9DE985A837C0BD81"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure that States with significant disparities in maternal and infant health outcomes, including severe maternal morbidity, and other disparities based on race, income, or access to maternity care, are included; and</text></clause> <clause id="H8688D5A022B9450B83D127E7ECE45426"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ensure that at least 1 territory is included.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9D8A7940D42C4048908A57B6FA8F027E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Grants</header> 
<paragraph id="H51483C344618454EB18D14C934DB32C1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From amounts appropriated under subsection (l), the Secretary shall award 1 grant for each year of the demonstration project to each State that is selected to participate in the demonstration project.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F2FF789ABFA47CC83082B3DCF2067B3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header><text>A State may use funds received under this section to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4E151A0947B747EF9195E02167E27AB2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>award grants or make payments to eligible entities as part of an arrangement described in subsection (g)(2);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H68C9A3814E7749B995C0CC69E61B7E37"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide financial incentives to health care professionals, including community-based health care workers and community-based doulas, who participate in the State's maternity care home model;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H594002C8E5394730930D5D859C15D54D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide adequate training for health care professionals, including community-based health care workers, doulas, and care coordinators, who participate in the State's maternity care home model, which may include training for cultural humility and antiracism, racial bias, health equity, reproductive and birth justice, trauma-informed care, home visiting skills, and respectful communication and listening skills, particularly in regards to maternal health;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCF463A96DF9C478EADF7186717B024B6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>pay for personnel and administrative expenses associated with designing, implementing, and operating the State's maternity care home model;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H937003D69D934374898C2BAF01AFE158"><enum>(E)</enum><text>pay for items and services that are furnished under the State's maternity care home model and for which payment is otherwise unavailable under this title; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H20187083B93242D5BC9B259BD999B01A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>pay for services and materials to ensure culturally and linguistically appropriate communication, including— </text> 
<clause id="HA0780DCAB8664DECA379032A073EF3BC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>language services such as interpreters and translation of written materials; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBF45CCE6B19940A1A9B2C517B1B65F36"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>development of culturally and linguistically appropriate materials; and auxiliary aids and services; and </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFFCDB30951F74DD88483F443C000CE76"><enum>(G)</enum><text>pay for other costs related to the State's maternity care home model, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEE177ABCBEA241ADA13A8BA68D3526B0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grant for national independent evaluator</header> <subparagraph id="HC48F1EEC332F466290588CEFE3481591"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From the amounts appropriated under subsection (l), prior to awarding any grants under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall enter into a contract with a national external entity to create a single, uniform process to—</text> 
<clause id="HFCC86904D6DD4D139595A4593B3AF7AB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>ensure that States that receive grants under paragraph (1) comply with the requirements of this section; and</text></clause> <clause id="HECC153C0059D437793C7679B5ADE64C5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>evaluate the outcomes of the demonstration project in each participating State.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC72E973303CF4581A2184D43F9B710FC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>The contract described in subparagraph (A) shall require the national external entity to submit to the Secretary—</text> <clause id="HC213E5AA5CA448EFA4622490728AC333"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a yearly evaluation report for each year of the demonstration project; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF4C108CAC7A74625BA7BE4A84662BC15"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a final impact report after the demonstration project has concluded.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H8D0B2AE10E794127B3AE2185DB436DE2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Secretary's authority</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph shall prevent the Secretary from making a determination that a State is not in compliance with the requirements of this section without the national external entity making such a determination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0E96D557FF75481A927C595718FFC5EF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Partnership with eligible entities</header> 
<paragraph id="H674216ADEEC1400CBCFF9E5A95B1435D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under this section, a State shall enter into an arrangement with one or more eligible entities that meets the requirements of paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1400AFD6366948849003C95C5480F6CF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Arrangements with eligible entities</header><text>Under an arrangement between a State and an eligible entity under this subsection, the eligible entity shall perform the following functions, with respect to eligible individuals enrolled with the entity under the State's maternity care home model—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9EB27F6B5F8946E8B0002A352C42B946"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide culturally and linguistically appropriate congruent care, which may include prenatal care, family planning services, medical care, mental and behavioral care, postpartum care, and oral health services to such eligible individuals through a team of health care professionals, which may include obstetrician-gynecologists, maternal-fetal medicine specialists, family physicians, primary care providers, oral health providers, physician assistants, advanced practice registered nurses such as nurse practitioners and certified nurse midwives, certified midwives, certified professional midwives, physical therapists, social workers, traditional and community-based doulas, lactation consultants, childbirth educators, community health workers, peer mental health supporters, and other health care professionals;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE0A91558DD594B70AC6AAA3D7238D8E4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>conduct a risk assessment of each such eligible individual to determine if their pregnancy is high or low risk, and establish a tailored pregnancy care plan, which takes into consideration the individual's own preferences and pregnancy care and birthing plans and determines the appropriate support services to reduce the individual's medical, social, and environmental risk factors, for each such eligible individual based on the results of such risk assessment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2FBD298F6812468FAD84537C71A0472A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>assign each such eligible individual to a culturally and linguistically appropriate care coordinator, which may be a nurse, social worker, traditional or community-based doula, community health worker, midwife, or other health care provider, who is responsible for ensuring that such eligible individual receives the necessary medical care and connections to essential support services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HECEA97C43D9348CCA425B262EC25E21D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide, or arrange for the provision of, essential support services, such as services that address—</text> 
<clause id="H8896DA23EE8D4BB39178685B23E5C55E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>food access, nutrition, and exercise;</text></clause> <clause id="H2AE944A29E5A4F2186BF3B25A7826BF7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>smoking cessation;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE550015F478C4C079E9EA2F470CB6775"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>substance use disorder and addiction treatment;</text></clause> <clause id="H733C9599340F456FB08062AB7D5F3CEC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>anxiety, depression, trauma, and other mental and behavioral health issues;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H834FA0F8B6AD47DF8CBF2CB677B4D61A"><enum>(v)</enum><text>breast feeding, chestfeeding, or other infant feeding options supports, initiation, continuation, and duration;</text></clause> <clause id="H1824868652FC43F2BA38EFC75493A3FB"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>stable, affordable, safe, and healthy housing;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H190B629781674721BC29B52AE02DFF48"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>transportation;</text></clause> <clause id="H4AE98B312D3743FDB7D44804775C7BEA"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>intimate partner violence;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBCA6C66FE53A4D308F341BEDE128029C"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>community and police violence;</text></clause> <clause id="H48B888299812478EA99DE1976F0F0116"><enum>(x)</enum><text>home visiting services;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA9200FD8F9DE4499A4EFF17CF34592C6"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>childbirth and newborn care education;</text></clause> <clause id="HDB575DBD04FC4892A965D92D1F95BBBF"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>oral health education;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD4A482E22C004B9DA0CBCA905EE5D729"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>continuous labor support; </text></clause> <clause id="H7A1749E0C7C44CEA82C03B74DC006D4C"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>group prenatal care;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCE63C0EE49554ED6A1939ECF5F945BCA"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>family planning and contraceptive care and supplies; and</text></clause> <clause id="H142E29CE651943B78F145237155D369F"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>affordable child care; </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA6661A08222148E5938C3093C14CA1BF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>as appropriate, facilitate connections to a usual primary care provider, which may be a reproductive health care provider;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF24BBF9B292B48209EAC2E0713D81AA4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>refer to guidelines and opinions of medical associations when determining whether an elective delivery should be performed on an eligible individual before 39 weeks of gestation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H85E120E0D6BF4B638762044D332B9D2B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>provide such eligible individual with evidence-based and culturally and linguistically appropriate education and resources to identify potential warning signs of pregnancy and postpartum complications and when and how to obtain medical attention;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H71F3F348481D44A9AB75CB1C9C6B668D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>provide, or arrange for the provision of, culturally and linguistically appropriate pregnancy and postpartum health services, including family planning counseling and services, to eligible individuals;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H99DECD2A59E74D2B8EBF577AF06C3483"><enum>(I)</enum><text>track and report postpartum health and birth outcomes of such eligible individuals and their children;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDA98A213C234493FB570CB94CC53993D"><enum>(J)</enum><text>ensure that care is person-centered, culturally and linguistically appropriate, and patient-led, including by engaging eligible individuals in their own care, including through communication and education; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBCBDC7B40BA6463DB3C5791B02CBE97D"><enum>(K)</enum><text>ensure adequate training for appropriately serving the population of individuals eligible for medical assistance under the State plan or waiver of such plan, including through reproductive justice, birth justice, birth equity, and anti-racist frameworks, home visiting skills, and knowledge of social services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H00D07523E2CF41999A6FBD18D3665502"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Term of demonstration project</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct the demonstration project for a period of 5 years.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HC1A9941153934E8D8EF24E1874497B37"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><text>To the extent that the Secretary determines necessary in order to carry out the demonstration project, the Secretary may waive section 1902(a)(1) (relating to statewideness) and section 1902(a)(10)(B) (relating to comparability).</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HDD7050D5E02348A68D5478E6D117431C"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a process to provide technical assistance to States that are awarded grants under this section and to eligible entities and other providers participating in a State maternity care home model funded by such a grant.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H5F4625AC95054F29B87831EBEB3DA15B"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H590BD8FDE99C4F4BB46EA73678DBC207"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this section and annually thereafter for each year of the demonstration project term, the Secretary shall submit a report to Congress on the results of the demonstration project.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HEB21B30FC65447BB9E8A0677B564BC78"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>As part of the final report required under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall include—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HE81D0AC6D919422EB9D1391D4BB41B5F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the results of the final report of the national external entity required under subsection (f)(3)(B)(ii); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H0D195C19211749D9BA226C97406EF79D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations on whether the model studied in the demonstration project should be continued or more widely adopted, including by private health plans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HCED6A60B262B46EDBFCF004EA8B0A522"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary, for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2031, such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HD3F2EACEE7594A938A8E41932B853EA0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reapplication of Medicare payment rate floor to primary care services furnished under Medicaid and inclusion of additional providers</header> <subsection id="HAEECB196F6DB4882AA9C6959BFDEC5E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reapplication of payment floor; additional providers</header> <paragraph id="H16E53AA88451449A8C7D2C92FF41DFFB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1902(a)(13) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(13)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2E86A7BCA1C14EE88B884A737C3B9FBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA116892F81A245DD940EF2E5E0784027"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking the semicolon and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB6938D47AF184816ACDDBBD7F5740DA0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="HD5EFFF7A1A544B2F9D8CDA68A59FF40D"> <subparagraph id="HB88E3F9824154E3BBD378A2C7AD2C95F"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">payment for primary care services (as defined in subsection (jj)(1)) furnished in the period that begins on the first day of the first month that begins after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</short-title> by a provider described in subsection (jj)(2)—</text> 
<clause id="H58826D82CD454581897FEA8997962659"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at a rate that is not less than 100 percent of the payment rate that applies to such services and the provider of such services under part B of title XVIII (or, if greater, the payment rate that would be applicable under such part if the conversion factor under section 1848(d) for the year were the conversion factor under such section for 2009);</text></clause> <clause id="H3BB132E7DEF24244BB6FA5B8541BBFF1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of items and services that are not items and services provided under such part, at a rate to be established by the Secretary; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD48B930F9762493082B18AD137821BE9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of items and services that are furnished in rural areas (as defined in section 1886(d)(2)(D)), health professional shortage areas (as defined in section 332(a)(1)(A) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254e">42 U.S.C. 254e(a)(1)(A)</external-xref>)), or medically underserved areas (according to a designation under section 330(b)(3)(A) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b(b)(3)(A)</external-xref>)), at the rate otherwise applicable to such items or services under clause (i) or (ii) increased, at the Secretary's discretion, by not more than 25 percent;</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H729A38339F124F3BBE286358D444885F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> <subparagraph id="H754D89CFE5D5462CB15A3004BF4C8120"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 1902(a)(13)(C) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(13)(C)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>subsection (jj)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (jj)(1)</quote>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H647DE68F6E28478692A4A0E4E5F5BBA6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 1905(dd) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(dd)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <clause id="H6289765396A14C4AB4C5E56FE8F2F550"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Notwithstanding</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5463C0C5C0244B979BA000C2256543E7"> 
<paragraph id="H45F325AEDB4F4513BE3B46EBB361364C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause> <clause id="HE64FF5461EB845EBA37BFE12336E07A6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>section 1902(a)(13)(C)</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraph (C) of section 1902(a)(13)</quote>;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDABE0949F1CB412F9773EDE2749DD0E1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or for services described in subparagraph (D) of section 1902(a)(13) furnished during an additional period specified in paragraph (2),</quote> after <quote>2015,</quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H8AE8114308B04068BCD98B24367FF4CB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by striking <quote>under such section</quote> and inserting <quote>under subparagraph (C) or (D) of section 1902(a)(13), as applicable</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC364D57A9C3E4E92BD287E657749604E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF6E2B0960568446A8A9C3310ABE24C76"> <paragraph id="H55A0F9BE53D34F9CB67A1B2B818687E8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional periods</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the following are additional periods:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H051CA40B022D4E53A39347A9F7F8E2CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The period that begins on the first day of the first month that begins after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Maximizing Outcomes for Moms through Medicaid Improvement and Enhancement of Services Act</short-title>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC0FCFDEC705147A48938A443B876D8F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Improved targeting of primary care</header><text>Section 1902(jj) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(jj)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H80104DFBF38D45DEB3D153A2BE1788E2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) and (2) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively and realigning the left margins accordingly;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7898E45F66D744899637C0AA1C810258"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>For purposes of subsection (a)(13)(C)</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE6912A7B250246749EBE3F5DC10C71C5"> 
<paragraph id="HB105476416E04C018C6B5ADBE64F0ABE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header> 
<subparagraph id="HADE1D005C0D74FDE86C9BED329618BD1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For purposes of subparagraphs (C) and (D) of subsection (a)(13)</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE2C296C16ABB4C808B919489136473B2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (ii) (as so redesignated) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H996C6686635049229EC6039F80DAF94B"> 
<subparagraph id="HBE4C8EFDCE9F461FB3D4D9F55E3D4886"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>Such term does not include any services described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (1) if such services are provided in an emergency department of a hospital.</text></subparagraph> <paragraph id="HFF6F917FB1CB47AA93054D32B365EF19"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional providers</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (D) of subsection (a)(13), a provider described in this paragraph is any of the following:</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3C9F13F418F8459BA207254CE7EAB6E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A physician with a primary specialty designation of family medicine, general internal medicine, or pediatric medicine, or obstetrics and gynecology.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H86F33D0D1F544B5C906A31A85B12D968"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An advanced practice clinician, as defined by the Secretary, that works under the supervision of—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5D25A7584E4847CBAAA2CAAACD00C36F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a physician that satisfies the criteria specified in subparagraph (A);</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAD1531BF0537411C8A05089E9667224D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a nurse practitioner or a physician assistant (as such terms are defined in section 1861(aa)(5)(A)) who is working in accordance with State law; or</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF88BE393F9B7465CA26DAC15082155C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>or a certified nurse-midwife (as defined in section 1861(gg)) or a certified professional midwife who is working in accordance with State law.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H314454BB86DF481AA911764C96EFDA7F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A rural health clinic, federally qualified health center, health center that receives funding under title X of the Public Health Service Act, or other health clinic that receives reimbursement on a fee schedule applicable to a physician.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H64419276A37041EA9668A77BFAB86969"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An advanced practice clinician supervised by a physician described in subparagraph (A), another advanced practice clinician, or a certified nurse-midwife.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2AE1D2134BD2463A845A841D4A7E6784"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A midwife who is working in accordance with State law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H807CA226A4C6447AA525454CE38F7041"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Ensuring payment by managed care entities</header> 
<paragraph id="H0BF3A7C7E6AA47B9850F798C80568D14"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1903(m)(2)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b(m)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HD6D33F5378084D5DBF2C707E33E303B0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (xii), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H47825F654A4142AFBD711B36C57125DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by realigning the left margin of clause (xiii) so as to align with the left margin of clause (xii) and by striking the period at the end of clause (xiii) and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFEDDA4C243994D2E95E57ACA3C512DCD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (xiii) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC28E2EE4030742CEA8A34E2604A4BBAD"> 
<clause id="H2CD5EDA4BED547B09D4172F8F8669924" indent="up2"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>such contract provides that (I) payments to providers specified in section 1902(a)(13)(D) for primary care services defined in section 1902(jj) that are furnished during a year or period specified in section 1902(a)(13)(D) and section 1905(dd) are at least equal to the amounts set forth and required by the Secretary by regulation, (II) the entity shall, upon request, provide documentation to the State, sufficient to enable the State and the Secretary to ensure compliance with subclause (I), and (III) the Secretary shall approve payments described in subclause (I) that are furnished through an agreed upon capitation, partial capitation, or other value-based payment arrangement if the capitation, partial capitation, or other value-based payment arrangement is based on a reasonable methodology and the entity provides documentation to the State sufficient to enable the State and the Secretary to ensure compliance with subclause (I).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B6E43996E3342969648326080BBEEDE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1932(f) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396u-2">42 U.S.C. 1396u–2(f)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF2D907D6529442A2A490D9CEC877E6BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>section 1902(a)(13)(C)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsections (C) and (D) of section 1902(a)(13)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDC720FE06D2F4DD1B5E2EBB443D418B0" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and clause (xiv) of section 1903(m)(2)(A)</quote> before the period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBEAF3387590B425A9FE01AA0B8716958"><enum>5.</enum><header>MACPAC report and CMS guidance on increasing access to doula services for Medicaid beneficiaries</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B6A2FCF7C314BF8AE286DC619C600EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>MACPAC Report</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5235ACF3D844231BD7BB21C96E48FDB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Medicaid and CHIP Payment and Access Commission (referred to in this section as <term>MACPAC</term>) shall publish a report on the coverage of doula services under State Medicaid programs, which shall at a minimum include the following:</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0B5086EE3F1F40A484BDE536F04A58C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Information about coverage for doula services under State Medicaid programs that currently provide coverage for such care, including the type of doula services offered (such as prenatal, labor and delivery, postpartum support, and community-based and traditional doula services), credentialing and provider enrollment requirements for doulas under State Medicaid programs, additional forms of support contributing to doula enrollment and reimbursement under State Medicaid programs, and data on outcomes with respect to doula services under each State Medicaid program, including the number of doulas registered under the State Medicaid program, the number of pregnant, birthing, and postpartum people served by doulas under the State Medicaid program, and the amount of time it takes for doulas to receive payment under the State Medicaid program for services provided under the program. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4722AA68ED4C4472A038702DB6E35450"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An analysis of barriers to covering doula services under State Medicaid programs.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4E69EC1411F04825B7C8809CE02D823A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An identification of effective strategies to increase the use of doula services in order to provide better care and achieve better maternal and infant health outcomes, including strategies that States may use to recruit, train, sutain, and certify a diverse doula workforce, particularly from underserved communities, communities of color, and communities facing linguistic or cultural barriers.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD3FC7331FBB8495E8B567860EC085B2F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Recommendations for legislative and administrative actions to increase access to doula services in State Medicaid programs, including actions that ensure doulas may earn a sustainable living wage that accounts for their time and costs associated with providing care and community-based doula program administration and operation. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6AAFFF782B2E49BBBB07432206DD2B05"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Stakeholder consultation</header><text>In developing the report required under paragraph (1), MACPAC shall consult with relevant stakeholders, including—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H12C2EF54CCF4420B81B2A63287962448"><enum>(A)</enum><text>States;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFC9C3A393707440EBFEE43BCA4A34345"><enum>(B)</enum><text>organizations, especially reproductive justice and birth justice organizations led by people of color, representing consumers of maternal health care, including those that are disproportionately impacted by poor maternal health outcomes;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2B7110D762B743C29CA605745432A477"><enum>(C)</enum><text>organizations and individuals representing doulas, including community-based doula programs and those who serve underserved communities, including communities of color, and communities facing linguistic or cultural barriers; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB08F945E97D45839844573396611B4C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>organizations representing health care providers; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98D164A0A97842CA9179666F387E3A16"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Black, Indigenous, and other maternal health care consumers of color who have experienced severe maternal morbidity. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1C77FBE134E244B5975650305523B202"><enum>(b)</enum><header>CMS guidance</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCD3D7E913DD54F68A767093FD8605471"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date that MACPAC publishes the report required under subsection (a)(1), the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services shall issue guidance to States on increasing access to doula services under Medicaid. Such guidance shall at a minimum include—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0CFD7AD862B1424DA5340CE1E38FCC88"><enum>(A)</enum><text>options for States to provide medical assistance for doula services under State Medicaid programs;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8ECD02431494CA3886AF91AC9095DF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>best practices for ensuring that doulas, including community-based doulas, receive reimbursement for doula services provided under a State Medicaid program, at a level that allows doulas to earn a living wage that accounts for their time and costs associated with providing care and community-based doula program administration; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B30306A741542D2B0B7092E5929E81B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>best practices for increasing access to doula services, including services provided by community-based doulas, under State Medicaid programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H33E5B88143F640888AF1D0758D5EF9BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Stakeholder consultation</header><text>In developing the guidance required under paragraph (1), the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services shall consult with MACPAC and other relevant stakeholders, including—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H54C29670D3F04CA886FF2B3E040C3659"><enum>(A)</enum><text>State Medicaid officials;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E316CAAC16143C18FCAB02BB537BEE8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>organizations representing consumers of maternal health care, including those that are disproportionately impacted by poor maternal health outcomes;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AB1FBB49B3E4327B27662D694A56E73"><enum>(C)</enum><text>organizations representing doulas, including community-based doulas and those who serve underserved communities, such as communities of color and communities facing linguistic or cultural barriers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1FDB074ED9054646A18FD9BD35BA2B3B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>organizations representing medical professionals; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD452DD37AF8C494294E8D64399A7A79E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>maternal health advocacy organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HDBC96E0E60DE4CBD8A20D46400716BB9"><enum>6.</enum><header>GAO report on State Medicaid programs' use of telehealth to increase access to maternity care</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit a report to Congress on State Medicaid programs' use of telehealth to increase access to maternity care. Such report shall include the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HC88D39AE5EA448C1BA2058083574E95F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of State Medicaid programs that utilize telehealth that increases access to maternity care.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7490A3AAE53A4347BA1BEFB9D3DB08C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>With respect to State Medicaid programs that utilize telehealth that increases access to maternity care, information about—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H10C0C783ECA947AAB71AC0786DC0D9EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>common characteristics of such programs' approaches to utilizing telehealth that increases access to maternity care;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2905C50044DC417BB32995B20EBB3800"><enum>(B)</enum><text>differences in States’ approaches to utilizing telehealth to improve access to maternity care, and the resulting differences in State maternal health outcomes, as determined by factors described in subsection (C); and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0EE371E0092441968980098B21343409"><enum>(C)</enum><text>when compared to patients who receive maternity care in-person, what is known about—</text> <clause id="H17E9FAE46916418BAE7A4F7B4C2A18F6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the demographic characteristics, such as race, ethnicity, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity, disability status, age, and preferred language of the individuals enrolled in such programs who use telehealth to access maternity care;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB34CD38E1C454B508ABBA75DDDCEAF41"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>health outcomes for such individuals, including frequency of mortality and severe morbidity, as compared to individuals with similar characteristics who did not use telehealth to access maternity care;</text></clause> <clause id="HA7C81948125144FB8C3078D5D1519107"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the services provided to individuals through telehealth, including family planning services, mental health care services, and oral health services;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC93C43A8997F4B1A9EBD45F3CDB4AFD8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the devices and equipment provided to individuals for remote patient monitoring and telehealth, including blood pressure monitors and blood glucose monitors; </text></clause> <clause id="H3E69F1A875E9418CBD0F356C42A20149"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the quality of maternity care provided through telehealth, including whether maternity care provided through telehealth is culturally and linguistically appropriate;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA7562755D48A4720B4B8C8E33C5D7EDB"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the level of patient satisfaction with an experience of maternity care provided through telehealth to individuals enrolled in State Medicaid programs;</text></clause> <clause id="H2C17469411824156BE42A54DBA78F7AE"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the impact of utilizing telehealth to increase access to maternity care on spending, cost savings, access to care, and utilization of care under State Medicaid programs; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7E178EE5F8D849BBB7C0D02882A8AB12"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>the accessibility and effectiveness of telehealth for maternity care during the COVID–19 pandemic. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB45E03F19F61499D899AE2A96866E254"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An identification and analysis of the barriers to using telehealth to increase access to maternity care under State Medicaid programs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H186DD25F9FAC4998AD905A8169FF2383"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Recommendations for such legislative and administrative actions related to increasing access to telehealth maternity services under Medicaid as the Comptroller General deems appropriate.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

