<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6D11736E31FE4771BEEB4462FC24032E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2407 IH: Nancy Gardner Sewell Medicare Multi-Cancer Early Detection Screening Coverage Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2407</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000375">Mr. Arrington</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide for Medicare coverage of multi-cancer early detection screening tests.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H376200EDA8534B05986EFDCDEC49D9D9" style="OLC"><section id="H6CA7E3D89A9F46AE8DC7390AAF618402" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nancy Gardner Sewell Medicare Multi-Cancer Early Detection Screening Coverage Act</short-title></quote> .</text></section><section id="H5F4628535A4145FBA6C79066D85F838A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purpose</header><subsection id="H0BFB34B9ACE4437DB80E6FB94BB1240A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HF981BF5481264193B6666810EDED227E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Detecting cancer early, before it has spread throughout the body, saves lives. Cancers detected when still localized can be treated more effectively and have a 4 times greater survival rate compared to cancers found after metastasis has occurred. Existing Medicare-covered early detection tests, such as mammograms and colonoscopies, have led to a substantial reduction in age-adjusted mortality.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC44903E0DC4142CBBF95DC40F7B59293"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Diagnosing and treating cancer earlier often results in less invasive treatments for patients, which are also less expensive. According to peer reviewed literature, treatment of early stage cancer is half the cost of metastatic cancer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6590505368B44FA4B81150E282D1C28A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Driving national strategies to broadly detect cancer earlier will help reduce pervasive health disparities since racial, ethnic, and geographic groups experience later stages of diagnosis, along with higher cancer incidence and mortality.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0BC1E9116834FC8900A408EC7CEBB62"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The benefits of early cancer detection to Medicare beneficiaries have been limited to five cancers. According to the National Cancer Institute’s Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results program, 71 percent of the 600,000 cancer deaths each year are from types of cancer without a Medicare-covered early detection test.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H794A9ACA6E8C477D9335E90BB2383DE1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Age is the leading risk factor for cancer, placing Medicare beneficiaries at elevated risk. About 1,000,000 Medicare beneficiaries will be diagnosed with cancer this year, as the median age for cancer diagnosis is 66 years of age.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H871588AA8F3D4511AD0DCC6E875714F4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Several innovative private and academic efforts are engaged in research, including advanced clinical trials to develop multi-cancer early detection blood-based tests. Published data indicate that these tests can screen for many cancers at the same time, including rare cancers, with one example currently able to screen for more than 50 cancers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC5784DD1A5B41A7A52CAC58182D8114"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Multi-cancer early detection tests can complement the covered early detection tests enacted by Congress and extend the benefits of early detection to more cancers and more Americans. Medicare coverage of comprehensive multi-cancer early detection screening tests could substantially transform cancer care for Americans, and the Medicare law needs modernizing to provide timely coverage and keep pace with medical innovation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB3E77C8ED13D4D39A1B93AC5B07D7B73"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this Act is to create a covered benefit for multi-cancer early detection screening tests to ensure Medicare beneficiary access to these tests without unnecessary delay once approved under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HDB36401F494342DBBED564D7B05C5D76"><enum>3.</enum><header>Medicare coverage of multi-cancer early detection screening tests</header><subsection id="H69380C7E44964D3F84A8E3E5C060BAA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Coverage</header><text>Section 1861 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H47286BAFC8924E0A9FB8032C074000A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (s)(2)—</text><subparagraph id="HEC47A43D52B64F4997A00F7FD4211CA6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking the semicolon at the end of subparagraph (JJ) and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BD96D522E7C4112B908787E017B3CEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block id="H3349305BB43D409DA2987C5EBB1D5298" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HA31A6998F29449C5B120C8B1F41CAE97"><enum>(KK)</enum><text>multi-cancer early detection screening tests (as defined in subsection (nnn));</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B7F41E0BC2D48DEAC0A998169B9B5F1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="H1047A825B35C4EEC8CE3487F10FED48E" style="OLC"><subsection id="HAE89C7E7779C4EA1AFB84D7A596E10B0"><enum>(nnn)</enum><header>Multi-Cancer early detection screening tests</header><text>The term <quote>multi-cancer early detection screening test</quote> means any of the following tests, approved or cleared by the Food and Drug Administration, insofar as the Secretary determines coverage of such tests is appropriate, furnished to an individual for the purpose of earlier detection of cancer across many cancer types (such as described in the National Cancer Institute’s Annual Report to the Nation on the Status of Cancer):</text><paragraph id="H2F37A53A0821478CB27BEBDB840AD540"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A genomic sequencing blood or blood product test that includes the analysis of cell-free nucleic acids.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AEA136445E9465C81BDB54254F7BA91"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such other equivalent tests (which are based on blood, blood products, urine or other sample of biological material) as the Secretary determines appropriate in providing results comparable to those obtained with a test described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB0A503793AE94A4AB09E9CA86C17A647"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payment and frequency limit</header><paragraph id="H3AD27B2238DF4A80B4F86F8563605DB0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Payment under fee schedule</header><text>Section 1833(h) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(h)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HD915707717754A2F9F32B9000143EC28"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A), by inserting after <quote>(including</quote> the following: <quote>multi-cancer early detection screening tests under section 1861(nnn), and including</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC5AA76AE3144032AD4DF388874F196B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block id="H6C35DC78BAFB4F7CBDE4E480C7ACF12F" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H6B8867C982894C078CD4B222E9CE7CB7"><enum>(10)</enum><text>No payment may be made under this part for a multi-cancer early detection screening test (as defined in section 1861(nnn)) for an individual if such a test was furnished to the individual during the previous 11 months.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D9635C4F8754182B09066E18FFF3BE2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1862(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395y">42 U.S.C. 1395y(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H2A2A37F955854A8A9C0F252BCCB85D69"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H5B24363D671948FABD5CFC5F9ED0DD16"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (O), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="H6AA454E9C30845B2A89A942CCF0C1CCA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (P), by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting <quote>, and</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HDA4140D362DD47AA905CB46384F34389"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block id="HA7405F89EEC94E6BB6745839C7310C69" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H09C1B7F8673C4E9EB737A74EBFD372AF"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>in the case of multi-cancer early detection screening tests (as defined in section 1861(lll)), which are performed more frequently than is covered under section 1833(h)(10);</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF47D235B1E04C2CB5E471A77CD2D50F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking <quote>or (P)</quote> and inserting <quote>(P), or (Q)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAE58C7F8A6B24A8784A6528965FFFF42"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction relating to other cancer screening tests</header><text>Nothing in this section, including the amendments made by this section, shall be construed—</text><paragraph id="H024A34F3D2ED48719F697F6D84760CAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of an individual who undergoes a multi-cancer early detection screening test, to affect coverage under part B of title XVIII of the Social Security Act for other cancer screening tests covered under such title, such as screening tests for breast, cervical, colorectal, lung, or prostate cancer; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAB9B9819F384FEB8B5F0EC25666DE77"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of an individual who undergoes another cancer screening test, to affect coverage under such part for a multi-cancer early detection screening test or the use of such a test as a diagnostic or confirmatory test for a result of the other cancer screening test.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

