<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H26FF4113C96440FFA1BF4567755553ED" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 929 IH: Puyallup Tribe of Indians Land Into Trust Confirmation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 929</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To take certain land in the State of Washington into trust for the benefit of the Puyallup Tribe of the Puyallup Reservation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAD740B31DDE44290BA5EC72DB808EA87" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HC80B4FEEDC3E4EA09693993B7B989E29"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Puyallup Tribe of Indians Land Into Trust Confirmation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H6A89B45892EA4797ABB90B111EF10501"><enum>2.</enum><header>Land to be taken into trust for the benefit of the Puyallup Tribe of the Puyallup Reservation</header> <subsection id="H1354A03C5F21473EBA31D27C38B9C054"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The approximately 17.264 acres of land owned in fee by the Puyallup Tribe of the Puyallup Reservation in Pierce County, Washington, and described in subsection (b) is hereby taken into trust by the United States for the benefit of the Puyallup Tribe of the Puyallup Reservation.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H2FBEF05C7E0F4824B81C168A78EC4B11"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Land descriptions</header>
<paragraph id="H48CE70768A9F429FB36818AC28BF78E7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Parcel 1</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Lots 1 to 4, inclusive, Block 85, Map of Tacoma Tidelands, as surveyed and platted by the Board of Appraisers of Tide and Shore Lands for Pierce County, according to Plat filed for record on September 14, 1895, in the Office of the County Auditor, in Tacoma, Pierce County, Washington.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF78F2C0B5EAC4C3BB72522C6FD5A3604"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Parcel 2</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Lots 5 to 9, inclusive, Block 85, Map of Tacoma Tidelands, as surveyed and platted by the Board of Appraisers of Tide and Shore Lands for Pierce County, according to Plat filed for record on September 14, 1895, in the Office of the County Auditor, in Tacoma, Pierce County, Washington.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6559601FA2D04978BEB2136103F442A6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Parcel 3</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Parcel A of City of Tacoma Boundary Line Adjustment MPD2011–40000166230, recorded October 12, 2011, under Pierce County Auditor Recording No. 201110125009, as corrected by Affidavit of Minor Correction of Map Recorded September 25, 2012, under Pierce County Auditor Recording No. 201209250440.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3F32BE85D157458F8D1910DBC15B22EC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Land taken into trust under subsection (a) shall be—</text>
<paragraph id="H60E1E32A65B14914B3965C13D11230D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">part of the Reservation of the Puyallup Tribe of the Puyallup Reservation; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF417FF83EF141A78DFEA9F5080BFB4D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>administered in accordance with the laws and regulations generally applicable to property held in trust by the United States for the benefit of an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFB7A349787724F46ACC722C1D2BA60EA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Environmental liability</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the United States shall not be liable for any environmental contamination that occurred on the land described in subsection (b) on or before the date on which that land is taken into trust under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3274E7806BC04C919AB5920FBC5C7723"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Gaming prohibited</header><text>Land taken into trust under subsection (a) shall not be used for any class II gaming or class III gaming under the Indian Gaming Regulatory Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2701">25 U.S.C. 2701 et seq.</external-xref>) (as those terms are defined in section 4 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2703">25 U.S.C. 2703</external-xref>)). </text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


