<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE309C1B26EEF4C7A835CE734BDD8BD4F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4314 IH: Stay Cool Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4314</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve response to, and preparation for, heat waves and extreme heat, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H69FB41CE900A43CD89AF66A6D59A1CC3" style="OLC"><section id="HB4563B2815B34051B2D6C643F46AC7E8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stay Cool Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7938A3B7EAB645B2BEB4AD6D2F1AAD97"><enum>2.</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HB4563B2815B34051B2D6C643F46AC7E8" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7938A3B7EAB645B2BEB4AD6D2F1AAD97" level="section">Sec. 2. Table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4397A386E3BB4A619866C1A32FE4FAF2" level="title">Title I—Heat Emergency</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC2EEB0B04C144C219C312051D351AC01" level="section">Sec. 101. National ranking system for extreme heat.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD00E759303E14B55A99C23800FA60A6D" level="section">Sec. 102. Study on naming heat waves.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H61BE5D1916694B26825E91B13C5324EC" level="section">Sec. 103. Grants for checking on seniors during extreme heat events.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA22494778D8B48D595270924F539A0CF" level="section">Sec. 104. Study for improved tracking of data on deaths related to heat or other environmental factors.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H800EFB0DDFE642EC80D3EDEE438D3865" level="title">Title II—Community Resilience and Cooling Centers</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5AB729B4C68448B58309E6C984A5E323" level="section">Sec. 201. Grants for community resilience centers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC20031969EE049D8AC88A3CEF210608A" level="section">Sec. 202. Grants for community resilience and cooling centers to purchase or repair HVAC systems and passive cooling systems.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H79EE0B8005044A71A3635BD5BB1CC25E" level="section">Sec. 203. Grants for outreach and publicity regarding community resilience and cooling centers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HED9BCEFD8F6B4F089CFEEC8B6B8E54A7" level="section">Sec. 204. Payroll credit for cooling centers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE8DC4014F45A457DBD16645B0F4F33BB" level="title">Title III—Housing</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1448A8A605684C2EA3A232717B8CBDDB" level="section">Sec. 301. Grants for providing cooling systems in public housing units.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF63FFC7A943F449C89DB5BEE5481239C" level="section">Sec. 302. Guidance on air conditioning costs and utility allowances.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5E4A531D742E416F9722B05D1862C73B" level="section">Sec. 303. Report to Congress on need for safe residential temperatures; regulations.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6F7CEB3FA3474F309D6F809957300E03" level="section">Sec. 304. Grants for providing safe residential temperatures in all federally assisted dwellings.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9F07E69BB15743EB9E597AC14FC9D70A" level="section">Sec. 305. Box fan expenses reimbursable through health saving accounts.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H282034082A4B4BA5B8760FA991FAF585" level="section">Sec. 306. Study on air conditioning recycling and rebate program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H44EB93B8820F40E3880005BF7935AADF" level="section">Sec. 307. Report on revising State allotment payments under the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0875D3E955C24A9489AFECE41731BB17" level="title">Title IV—Urban Development</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H51FC77288FAE47278D42BE578E44B571" level="section">Sec. 401. Grants for construction of usable public water features.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF112B460EE6D45319C92EFA3073D52A9" level="section">Sec. 402. Grant program to develop and improve high quality urban green spaces.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA4022B20960E4FF0902A10F45B5A36EF" level="section">Sec. 403. Tree planting grant program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCD1ABD3E6DED474F8FC8DB531C212255" level="title">Title V—Definitions</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1709BB5B476041F597024E4A8D5879D3" level="section">Sec. 501. Definitions.</toc-entry></toc></section><title id="H4397A386E3BB4A619866C1A32FE4FAF2"><enum>I</enum><header>Heat Emergency</header><section id="HC2EEB0B04C144C219C312051D351AC01"><enum>101.</enum><header>National ranking system for extreme heat</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Weather Service shall establish a national ranking system pilot program to evaluate and communicate to the public the severity and risk of extreme heat based on human health outcomes (mortality and morbidity). Not later than 1 year after the establishment of such program, the Director of the National Weather Service shall submit to Congress a report providing recommendations and evaluating the impact of the national ranking system for extreme heat on public preparedness and response.</text></section><section id="HD00E759303E14B55A99C23800FA60A6D"><enum>102.</enum><header>Study on naming heat waves</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Weather Service shall submit to Congress a report containing the results of a study on the impact that naming heat waves has on public preparedness and response.</text></section><section id="H61BE5D1916694B26825E91B13C5324EC"><enum>103.</enum><header>Grants for checking on seniors during extreme heat events</header><subsection id="HD112D882AEB2410FBD7674CFB4233901"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services may award grants to eligible entities to develop and implement a program under which each grant recipient—</text><paragraph id="H383A73AC48FC4D6C93E99F3D7B21D468"><enum>(1)</enum><text>operates a registry of seniors who reside in the jurisdiction of the grant recipient;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DDCE8BC2B044920BB3C0D93B2BD37B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes seniors in such registry only if they opt into being included; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6530E193D4D8426C8A96968299922D77"><enum>(3)</enum><text>during periods of extreme heat, provides for checks on the health and well-being of seniors in the registry—</text><subparagraph id="H713CEAD34B4E489CB36D6CA107E75D8E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by telephone; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBF04A8DD5F247EBBCE3569B0F63D0FD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by other means approved by the senior involved.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD62C4C23C9E24CA3B56306B908C12149"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to—</text><paragraph id="H6C62E6D884C2454093AE4344C31F2D19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>eligible entities described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of subsection (c) whose jurisdictions include one or more overburdened communities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9EC6E46E4D044B696542B4B249637CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>eligible entities described in subparagraph (D) of subsection (c) whose target populations for outreach and services include the residents of one or more overburdened communities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF5D7FACBE3BE48D28213894B7F8C44C9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HEE3EFCFFE53B4D7EA1DF9997B5278E97"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H001AA08521CA4FCFB28C729CDD2A8A9A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State, Territory, or Tribal agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57232D07C8C942038ADABA8D07452C65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a local governmental entity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78811A479ED94A27928C488442778754"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C0F3EBA45D3455DBF08B9889E5E8DAB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nonprofit organization, community group, clinic, or other entity engaged in providing outreach and services to seniors.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H603D123C89DF4145BA734CC868CB1DB5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given to that term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AB81ECE1B7148A68C4035967AF5CC21"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>local governmental entity</term> means any municipal government or county government with jurisdiction over local land use decisions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H761746EDE545425899BFF8A0E6311D38"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>overburdened community</term> means, as determined by the Secretary, an area where—</text><subparagraph id="HF703C651E1E04702BD3CF766D9E7EBE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>35 percent or more of households qualify as low-income households;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBED00C564324D0981424F5D09AF10AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>40 percent or more of residents identify as a minority or as members of a State-recognized Tribal community; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE96436C15C2E4C4B9561F6F6A4F82B98"><enum>(C)</enum><text>40 percent or more of households are limited English proficiency households.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2349D07CE9446BC8426492C2D0EF90F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0CB4EC89C4E40A780239B8639DACDF7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The term <term>senior</term> has the meaning given to that term by the Secretary for purposes of this section. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA41B88BD22844BF5A1B167BDD4114FE3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2032.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA22494778D8B48D595270924F539A0CF"><enum>104.</enum><header>Study for improved tracking of data on deaths related to heat or other environmental factors</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, acting through the National Vital Statistics System of the National Center for Health Statistics, in consultation with the relevant White House Interagency Working Group on Extreme Heat, shall—</text><paragraph id="H8EB163AE9FE146A1B19A207BABFF23AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct a study on the impact of meteorological conditions on all-cause mortality;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F7C317108A14569A9164636F2E02676"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as part of such study, develop recommendations for revising the United States standard certificate of death to collect information on deaths that are related to heat or other environmental factors; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3F6DC72E8C34CBABF25FA023442FB25"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, complete such study and submit a report on the results of such study to the Congress. </text></paragraph></section></title><title id="H800EFB0DDFE642EC80D3EDEE438D3865"><enum>II</enum><header>Community Resilience and Cooling Centers</header><section id="H5AB729B4C68448B58309E6C984A5E323"><enum>201.</enum><header>Grants for community resilience centers</header><subsection id="H8B4B1B1CC9A7402C835164EEE70EDB13"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a program under this section to make grants to eligible entities for the establishment and assistance of community resilience centers in overburdened communities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA0FB5009249E43A185934F720AF809E1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grants under the program under this section may be made only to a State, Indian tribe, unit of general local government, or nonprofit organization.</text></subsection><subsection id="H82655F2B9B504DC49A0BF8BCA214236B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible activities</header><text>Amounts from a grant under the program under this section may be used only to establish new, or assist existing, community resilience centers, including for—</text><paragraph id="HAB231104878749939A0FAA65994AF04E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">acquisition or improvement of facilities to serve as community resilience centers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFE14043DB254E5A86BBDCFF4C19036A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">acquisition or repair of cooling equipment, heating equipment, and generators for a community resilience center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE315F504AE348079BBE9CC734BEAB25"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">obtaining supplies of food, water, medical supplies, and emergency supplies for users of a community resilience center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFA0A8DDD50149DCBAB1BF5D676C0838"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">operating costs associated with a community resilience center, including hiring staff for a center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD84DCD084DEC4AFE850570C3969D318D"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">obtaining educational material on climate change resilience and other related educational material; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H745754972C314F33A5F43D2ECDA2EBA1"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other costs and activities relating to community resilience centers as the Secretary may provide.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H539F0E72932648A5AC31BC76394F35E6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide for eligible entities to apply for grants under the program under this section and shall require applications to include a community engagement plan for decision making relating to a community resilience center and an outreach plan to inform the community of the center.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4F61947B77144FAAAC998F2CF952668A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall select applicant eligible entities to receive grants under the program under this section based on a competition, in accordance with such criteria as the Secretary shall establish, which shall provide preference for selection for grants for—</text><paragraph id="H47A87B432D364E6BB34D2857A8DE3639"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">eligible entities that will use grant amounts for community resilience centers located in overburdened communities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD060057B1F3D482FAD56EC4B788C816B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">eligible entities that will ensure that educational activities relating to developing community resilience to extreme weather events will be carried out in connection with the community resilience center or centers assisted; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6275EBF0701E4D1DA84F20AD8B20796C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">eligible entities that will upgrade or improve existing spaces that are easily accessible to the community for use as community resilience centers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52CF83CC810A4133AC97869E1BB7A866"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for grants under the program under this section $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC20031969EE049D8AC88A3CEF210608A"><enum>202.</enum><header>Grants for community resilience and cooling centers to purchase or repair HVAC systems and passive cooling systems</header><subsection id="H34BFCE079CF3437DB9AEAAC47D5555F9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a program under this section to make grants to community resilience centers and cooling centers for the costs of acquiring new heating, ventilation, and air conditioning systems and passive cooling solutions for such facilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H72203AE5880C4FC489EC45B861ACD5C1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible HVAC systems</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts from a grant under the program under this section may be used to acquire only heating, ventilation, and air conditioning systems meeting such standards as the Secretary shall establish in consultation with the Secretary of Energy.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA9F1B601985043B8BD50D2C17AFAF904"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible passive cooling solutions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts from a grant under the program under this section may be used to acquire passive cooling solutions, which may include—</text><paragraph id="H7C8AF865DAB04845B07BC257824324DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>cool or green roofs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0F5EE1668264450B29833CC9CD3390B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>cool walls;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5C01A3B074242B0BC5E701281A2E2D3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>tree planting and maintenance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H038AFEDAA483460B9FE4B4C00A19CDAD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>cool pavements.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H601B8E73D22F490B8F59ED99E97F12ED" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide for community resilience centers and cooling centers to apply for grants under the program under this section and shall require applications to include a statement identifying the number of people served by the community resilience center or cooling center.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDB3E9778C3D24DC0AEA91C634E894A7A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide for community resilience centers and cooling centers to apply for grants under the program under this section and shall select applicants to receive grants under the program under this section based on a competition, in accordance with such criteria as the Secretary shall establish, which shall provide preference for selection for grants for community resilience centers and cooling centers located in overburdened communities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H65B2A0FC255A429EB4F433F210509400" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for grants under the program under this section $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034.</text></subsection></section><section id="H79EE0B8005044A71A3635BD5BB1CC25E"><enum>203.</enum><header>Grants for outreach and publicity regarding community resilience and cooling centers</header><subsection id="H842FD3C384A346E79A990017D356D1F2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a program under this section to make grants to States and units of general local government for use to carry out outreach, publicity, and education activities to inform the public regarding the location, function, and availability of cooling centers and community resilience centers, including for—</text><paragraph id="H331E3054D94341429F2EFCE5995DF4A5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collection of data regarding locations of cooling centers and community resilience centers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB9AE563F7C446B299FBFF39A8FCE49C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>development of platforms, websites, applications, and other tools and methods of communication to assist the public in locating such centers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H510A953C77724E53980ED13E590168D0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application; selection</header><text>The Secretary shall provide for eligible entities to apply for grants under the program under this section and shall select applicant eligible entities to receive grants under the program under this section based on a competition, in accordance with such criteria as the Secretary shall establish.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDCFD8A327ABE419C915A476831687979" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for grants under the program under this section $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034.</text></subsection></section><section id="HED9BCEFD8F6B4F089CFEEC8B6B8E54A7"><enum>204.</enum><header>Payroll credit for cooling centers</header><subsection id="H3F3991BCB8194D8DAFF57123B406DA34"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/3111">Section 3111</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3DFD910AC9B3442AB830E40F1D0C3403" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H03C5BC8009814BCA862E849A440A479C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Credit for cooling centers</header><paragraph id="HE20C8A8E27D14116A2B099E551E3BE22"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an eligible employer, there shall be allowed as a credit against the tax imposed by subsection (a) for each calendar quarter an amount equal to the sum of the amounts determined under subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE8407BE5F644AD7ACF61A1BDCF1F64C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount of credit</header><subparagraph id="H6C0C63216D3E4C1B977CB8FCE762556F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Extended hours</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount determined under this paragraph is the hourly cost of labor of the taxpayer multiplied by the number of hours such taxpayer remained open to the public outside of normal operating hours during a heat emergency during the calendar quarter.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15E5A6C80BF243CDB47F2AEBA407449F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Free admission days</header><text>The amount determined under this paragraph is the average daily admission revenue of the taxpayer multiplied by the number of days during the calendar quarter that such taxpayer waived admission fees during a heat emergency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4A92B2ECBA3426DA36C89E80F88F812"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Heat emergency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of this subsection, the term <term>heat emergency</term> means an excessive heat warning, excessive heat watch, or heat advisory issued by the National Weather Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE32904D7FEFD47E89EA0AD9446C5A894"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The credit allowed by paragraph (1) shall not exceed the tax imposed by subsection (a) for any calendar quarter on the wages paid with respect to the employment of all individuals in the employ of the employer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEE884F71A794410B05E89C9977C1AB5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Carryover of unused credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the amount of the credit allowed under paragraph (1) exceeds the limitation of paragraph (3) for any calendar quarter, such excess shall be carried to the succeeding calendar quarter and allowed as a credit under paragraph (1) for such quarter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC2F10D79D954693B665FD2C846EACDD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible employer</header><text>For the purposes of this section, the term <term>eligible employer</term> means a community center, library or museum that is described in section 501(c)(3) and exempt from taxation under section 501(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CAECDDE6DFB4624BC8E30141DAEA482"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Aggregation rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All persons treated as a single employer under subsection (a) or (b) of section 52, or subsection (m) or (o) of section 414, shall be treated as one employer for purposes of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA80A8A12F9C44D4580B5E2FFECDA2CF8"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Election not to have section apply</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall not apply with respect to any employer for any calendar quarter if such employer elects (at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may prescribe) not to have this section apply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F3942B91BBA4EBCBFA8DF3460D7BAFD"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall issue such regulations or other guidance as may be necessary or appropriate to carry out the purposes of this section. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H07ADA29B7F7448DD9296144300836221"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="HE8DC4014F45A457DBD16645B0F4F33BB"><enum>III</enum><header>Housing</header><section id="H1448A8A605684C2EA3A232717B8CBDDB" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>301.</enum><header>Grants for providing cooling systems in public housing units</header><subsection id="H7661484FBC7D41429F4679B14363A192"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a program under this section to make grants to public housing agencies for the installation of air conditioners or heat pumps for public housing dwelling units.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5F7945644B154786AB9ECF0E9A3D6427"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts from a grant under the program under this section may be used only for costs of acquiring and installing air conditioners or heat pumps that meet such standards as the Secretary shall establish regarding cooling capacity, safety, reliability, and energy efficiency and that serves public housing dwelling units that were constructed before the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEFF444AE437849ACB21F6F65C5868F73"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The Secretary shall provide for public housing agencies to apply for grants under the program under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFBCFA8D4A3F24F4081DE65D3302E8562"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>The Secretary shall select applicant agencies to receive grants under the program under this section based on a competition, in accordance with such criteria as the Secretary shall establish, which shall provide preference for selection for grants for—</text><paragraph id="H3320CA77C6A34E72A1CC93EB12EFA1CC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>public housing agencies that serve communities with limited access to cooling centers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9672996D0E6A43708700391A44DDD958"><enum>(2)</enum><text>public housing agencies located in areas prone to heat emergencies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF746B328812D4D5C85403F7F442C5DE6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated for grants under the program under this section $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2027.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF63FFC7A943F449C89DB5BEE5481239C"><enum>302.</enum><header>Guidance on air conditioning costs and utility allowances</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall revise the regulations under subpart E of part 965 of volume 24, Code of Federal Regulations (relating to resident allowances for utilities), to ensure that air conditioning costs are included when calculating utility allowance schedules and utility allowances for residents.</text></section><section id="H5E4A531D742E416F9722B05D1862C73B"><enum>303.</enum><header>Report to Congress on need for safe residential temperatures; regulations</header><subsection id="HBFC4CE046DE445CA911155362489E2AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), in coordination with the Secretary of Agriculture and in consultation with the relevant White House Interagency Working Group on Extreme Heat, shall submit to the Congress a report—</text><paragraph id="H756C8007CEF141D1ADAC643B36F8DB78"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying and compiling data on the availability of air conditioning in covered federally assisted rental dwelling units (as such term is defined in section 304);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40EAEC1ECAF64B4F8AA8DE963FEEEF71"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifying and setting forth safe residential temperature standards for such dwelling units;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1A035CC8A6E47F395BD62C23930358F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>estimating the cost for bringing all covered federally assisted rental dwelling units into compliance with such safe residential temperature standards; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F1908CD24264A7792176900813096F7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>setting forth a plan and mechanisms for bringing all covered federally assisted rental dwelling units into compliance with the safe residential standards.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3E93B852C3443639FCB68C6B66501C6" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Safe residential temperature standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, in consultation with the Secretary of Agriculture, shall issue regulations establishing safe residential temperature standards for covered federally assisted rental dwelling units based on the safe temperature standards identified in the report under subsection (a) pursuant to subsection (a)(2).</text></subsection></section><section id="H6F7CEB3FA3474F309D6F809957300E03"><enum>304.</enum><header>Grants for providing safe residential temperatures in all federally assisted dwellings</header><subsection id="H1676FB8D245441128DA2947FAE951F79"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), in coordination with the Secretary of Agriculture and in consultation with the relevant White House Interagency Working Group on Extreme Heat, shall carry out a program under this section to make grants to public housing agencies and owners of covered federally assisted rental dwelling units to enable covered federally assisted rental dwelling units to comply with the safe residential temperature standards in public housing and established pursuant to section 303(b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H1AA3DDE6658C4F5793346108F9C4CE46"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts from a grant under this section may be used only for costs of acquiring and installing air conditioning or other means or mechanisms that meet such standards as the Secretary shall establish regarding cooling capacity, safety, reliability, and energy efficiency, for covered federally assisted rental dwelling units that were constructed before the date of the enactment of this Act, to enable such dwelling units to comply with the safe residential temperature standards established pursuant to section 303(b) in a manner provided for in the plan set forth in the report under section 6(a) pursuant to subsection 6(a)(4).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6A931E29F06A4CF4BAD55E2BAF4CB40D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretaries referred to in subsection (a) shall provide for public housing agencies and owners of covered federally assisted rental dwelling units to apply for grants under the program under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA36B02A0C3AB4B53BBA0E5B7CBC26342"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretaries referred to in subsection (a) shall select applicant public housing agencies and owners of covered federally assisted rental dwelling units to receive grants under the program under this section based on a competition, in accordance with such criteria as the Secretaries shall establish, which shall provide preference for selection for grants for—</text><paragraph id="HEC7785E59D3848EEA46D1BEFEAEE0B72"><enum>(1)</enum><text>covered federally assisted rental dwelling units located in communities with limited access to cooling centers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6841B59025224FE7BF33DC6EFB846BAB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>covered federally assisted rental dwelling units located in areas prone to heat emergencies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCB863ED7B67345478AC2451156DE347F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For the purposes of this Act:</text><paragraph id="HD874BEC9608C4E6B84B1FA54D8F971E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered federally assisted rental dwelling unit</header><text>The term <term>covered federally assisted rental dwelling unit</term>’ means a residential dwelling unit that is made available for rental and for which assistance is provided, or that is part of a housing project for which assistance is provided, under—</text><subparagraph id="H701DEBB2B3224D088330725CA0FAE3B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the public housing program under the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437">42 U.S.C. 1437 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CF2B20F73164496A1702ECBDF4735D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a program for rental assistance under section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref>), including—</text><clause id="H07B35CD3ACDB46B3B608AE8B9B8CF04A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the program for project-based rental assistance; and</text></clause><clause id="H1657FE1AE3814D158CB187AC2789B0B7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the program for tenant-based rental assistance;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09CD74CEBC7D49A08658A327D71ADA33"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the AIDS Housing Opportunities program under subtitle D of title VIII of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12901">42 U.S.C. 12901 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41F7E1C9210940E3BF6959DBC25A0132"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the program for supportive housing for the elderly under section 202 of the Housing Act of 1959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1701q">12 U.S.C. 1701q</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88C6BA9E77584D6280D1FDF17E08771F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the program for supportive housing for persons with disabilities under section 811 of the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8013">42 U.S.C. 8013</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A7F0880FAAE4F53AA0CCBD729CD2421"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a housing program under section 515, 514, 521, or 542 of title V of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1471">42 U.S.C. 1471 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AA33A576B494BC291FE1F9960BC2B21"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Owner</header><text>The term <term>owner</term> means, with respect to a covered federally assisted rental dwelling unit, any private person or entity, including a cooperative, an agency of the Federal Government, or a public housing agency, having the legal right to lease or sublease dwelling units.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H984414A163E54365A37EE5E27857AE9A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for grants under the program under this section such sums as may be necessary for assistance under this section sufficient for all covered federally assisted rental dwelling units to meet the safe residential temperature standards established pursuant to section 6(b).</text></subsection></section><section id="H9F07E69BB15743EB9E597AC14FC9D70A"><enum>305.</enum><header>Box fan expenses reimbursable through health saving accounts</header><subsection id="HB3A4B4B284794CEDA385393269D60913"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/223">Section 223(d)(2)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting <quote>or box fans</quote> before <quote>shall be treated as paid for medical care</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HDC480B994ADC4029998F5041B88467CD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred in taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section><section id="H282034082A4B4BA5B8760FA991FAF585"><enum>306.</enum><header>Study on air conditioning recycling and rebate program</header><subsection id="H915EBB698A5E4DF7AFD53C7ACE189818"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy shall submit to Congress a report containing the results of a study on the feasibility of a nationwide air conditioner recycling and rebate program for more energy efficient home cooling systems.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFF1285611E2D444F9B83EA47CDA28B4E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>The report submitted under subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="H4CDFD015342F40608C512AF799DAA829"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of the ability of a program described in such subsection to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and to promote energy savings and efficiency; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD606E2F5967425AA8B8088C73574951"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations on how to promote access to such a program for low-income households, persons with disabilities, senior citizens, and residents of rural areas; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H672AEA6EED4345BCB4D4A56A33007C99"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an analysis of the potential economic impacts of providing rebates under such a program for the purchase of Energy Star certified or more energy efficient home cooling systems for low-income households, persons with disabilities, senior citizens, and residents of rural areas.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H44EB93B8820F40E3880005BF7935AADF"><enum>307.</enum><header>Report on revising State allotment payments under the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Human and Health Services, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy, shall submit to Congress a report on how the formula to allot amounts to States under section 2604 of the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Act of 1981 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/8623">42 U.S.C. 8623</external-xref>) could be revised to account for the energy needs of all low-income households in States, including low-income households that do not use, or under-use, a source of heating or cooling.</text></section></title><title id="H0875D3E955C24A9489AFECE41731BB17"><enum>IV</enum><header>Urban Development</header><section id="H51FC77288FAE47278D42BE578E44B571"><enum>401.</enum><header> Grants for construction of usable public water features</header><subsection id="H9783224FFB22421AB024827C3C467BDA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a program under this section to make grants to eligible entities for the construction of eligible water features in overburdened communities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H342600F092D94813B4769891B3F3F023"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grants under the program under this section may be made only to a State, Indian tribe, unit of general local government, or nonprofit organization.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCB8687A2AF5349D68D4CCF98E64DC5BF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible water features</header><text>Amounts from a grant under the program under this section may be used only for costs of constructing water features that—</text><paragraph id="H61993E75282A4698A95BC79388691FAF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide recreation or cooling for users, such as splash parks, wading pools, swimming pools, misting systems, and fountains;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BBA37C8CF2B44CB8953123D6EFFE45B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>can be used to provide relief to users from extreme heat conditions; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96192296F903409DA46D3A0BE5519C0C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are available for use by anyone without charge.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E555F73860543F2916C1A0EEB47C28A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><paragraph id="HD66C4CC9231647F094AA02345C811F48"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide for eligible entities to apply for grants under the program under this section and shall require applications to include a statement identifying the estimated number of people to be served by the feature.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E40B14334D74732B9336F8CDB14779B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community involvement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall require eligible entities to develop a public participation plan to ensure that residents of the area in which a project is to be implemented are involved in the project, which plan—</text><subparagraph id="HC07BC42DB5A641399E5BD91C23200956"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall provide opportunities for employment for minorities, low- and moderate-income residents in the neighborhood of the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F299AC2DFCA411F915B689AF6C9A6A2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall involve residents of the area in decision making regarding the project; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1548D54951924CF8A0DCBCE7519F6277"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may—</text><clause id="HFA85AED59E33459E84884066DA3FE59F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide opportunities for local nonprofits to be involved in the project;</text></clause><clause id="H39C743160C9940CC91324C197D9C6F7B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide opportunities for public input regarding the project; and</text></clause><clause id="H6105661D036F46A5AF5FD0D4E85F2203"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>include demonstrated support from the community.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7BA6351BEBCE472FAE031521EB67D609"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>The Secretary shall select applicant eligible entities to receive grants under the program under this section based on a competition, in accordance with such criteria as the Secretary shall establish, which shall provide preference for selection for grants for eligible entities that will construct eligible water features in areas without access, or with limited access, to cooling centers.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2B4FB8254F1B4D26BEEDB0ED76026867"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for grants under the program under this section $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF112B460EE6D45319C92EFA3073D52A9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>402.</enum><header>Grant program to develop and improve high quality urban green spaces</header><subsection id="H2E9B112D26C54527AC8133A14D3BF9EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), in coordination with the Director of the National Park Service, shall establish a grant program under which the Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities under subsection (c) to improve or develop high quality urban green spaces located in overburdened communities to lower surface temperatures through increased urban vegetation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9B5E7CA3AEAD43098AC5A51FA6294E4E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Projects and activities funded with grant amounts under this section shall provide environmental and cooling benefits to overburdened communities, including through planting trees, increasing the urban forestry canopy, improving stormwater management, increasing green infrastructure, employing water conservation measures, and adding green spaces.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD92BEA16FBE741D5B6B98A5A2BCB9624"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>A grant under this section may only be made to—</text><paragraph id="HC6B9FD02C95D4F799051E3F29EF7E309"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a State;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEAB79D9A73F4910913C3E7CC03A243F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEE56A4878A04BE4A1BA422AC808D4C0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a unit of general local government; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEEB15466F1441268357097BEB7B21A8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC0CB13C1FD34456BB3B4707DDCEB387B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><paragraph id="HF0DCA832F2B946B99EFF19A41DD0DBD2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that seeks to receive a grant under subsection (a) shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H385B6ABE752B47BC97E1AC876E043F79"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An application submitted under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H37A371B058E04078A4810926BF6CE150"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describe how the projects and activities to be funded with grant amounts will comply with the requirement under subsection (b); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7825A0D9D674EB8A7AFAD572C05650B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include a 5-year timeline and budget for the development and improvement of urban green space.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B4AED4FA1154F2FBA46412907FC5637"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Community involvement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall require eligible entities to develop a public participation plan to ensure that residents of the area in which a project is to be implemented are involved in the project, which plan—</text><subparagraph id="H3861E41C7E6741098237835F389A83E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall provide opportunities for employment for minorities, low- and moderate-income residents in the neighborhood of the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7A742D61F0F453D853FA8B7B833294B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall involve residents of the area in decision making regarding the project; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A73968B20F2409C82D249C3C45FC395"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may—</text><clause id="H793149BE0A40459DBE3FCCD1376FF0CE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide opportunities for local nonprofits to be involved in the project;</text></clause><clause id="H51C27557FCD6494BA6C867A12E6C1FD1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide opportunities for public input regarding the project; and</text></clause><clause id="H4E17DD9F8EBB4521994C974A7E478BAD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>include demonstrated support from the community.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAEA4273AD5F948E79406D61AA944D5EE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection</header><paragraph id="HD2C103D5E8CC4B1E89B2254A0BDB4AE8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall determine which eligible entities shall receive a grant under this section. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H185FB2245DF24D6380290C2D166ABF65" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under subsection (a), the Secretary shall give priority in selection for grants to eligible entities based on—</text><subparagraph id="H9053E64F25464966BF04B2CBFF46EDFB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which the eligible entity will contribute matching funds for activities conducted with amounts from a grant under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6814C58C9E104D8CA13FD2EE7C057B50" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based on the extent to which the project funded with grant amounts would— </text><clause id="H4844C8E3972149D3BC932653D9F82E00" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address demonstrated deficiencies in the condition of and access to cooling green space in the project neighborhood;</text></clause><clause id="H4B2F7E1AFABE4554B56281B45DAF413B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>build green spaces located within half of a mile of a public housing that is not within half of a mile of any green space;</text></clause><clause id="H3F05C50FB2AE462183BB140C0F33A75F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>work collaboratively with local governments, colleges, universities, and other institutions to study urban heat island effects and benefits of cooling green spaces;</text></clause><clause id="H76FCB8A125674908ACB98FBC04B01A97"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>use environmentally beneficial components, such as sustainable landscape features, upcycled and recycled materials, and materials with low carbon footprint;</text></clause><clause id="HE819A96A29364CD2879B822BF1D54362"><enum>(v)</enum><text>contain safe trails or routes, such as trails, bikeways, and sidewalks, that connect to neighborhoods and enhance access to green spaces.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9408C5D7238442629D0680933974B7E1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of amounts</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under subsection (a) shall use amounts provided to cover costs associated with—</text><paragraph id="H103C595D4FB449D6BC25A5DCCC6D83B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">rebuilding, remodeling, expanding, integrating, or developing existing or building new green spaces, including improvements in park landscapes, infrastructure, buildings, and support facilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CB71883E47A4E3DABD4174D84F41C20"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">planting vegetation in project areas, including maintaining and monitoring planted vegetation for a period of up to 5 years to ensure successful establishment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5C7EF6425A24FA38764FDD1AFB515B7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">preparing the project site and conducting construction, including the costs of labor and costs associated with use of machinery;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5DDE44CA0A24305BC53CAF8B562E861"><enum>(4)</enum><text>training activities associated with the construction; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE061310E90BD4BC0A97CF4F72B825ACB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>other relevant costs, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4DB19A225AF6484F952AF5A5B4AB2713"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out the Program $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA4022B20960E4FF0902A10F45B5A36EF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>403.</enum><header>Tree planting grant program</header><subsection id="H36626AE6FD2141FFB940E26FD53739F1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), in coordination with the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, shall establish a grant program under which the Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities to plant qualifying trees in overburdened communities for the purpose of mitigating and reducing high surface temperatures and cooling the surrounding area.”. </text></subsection><subsection id="HF48F16E11E76473498132AD137890968"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications</header><paragraph id="H29FF19A1D9B44FE19DBA12B5B34D1E32"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that seeks to receive a grant under subsection (a) shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83F640464038405092E3D5695A0C29A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An application submitted under paragraph (1) shall include a 5-year timeline and budget for the planting and maintenance associated with any qualifying trees awarded. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC6CA76928EB4E91B9049FA13AE0B9CE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Community involvement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall require eligible entities to develop a public participation plan to ensure that residents of the area in which a project is to be implemented are involved in decision making about the project and such public participation plan may include—</text><subparagraph id="H224D3E73197C4D68B4906874F4BB20CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>opportunities for local nonprofits to be involved;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99E4DFCEC44F4F3EAFE079CBDF8C56F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>opportunities for public input; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DCC6DB4735647CBA1AB87643A2B2BAE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>demonstrated support from the community.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC694051D66134A519D181B09FFD6A8F9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection</header><paragraph id="HF347D8F2012043FB9D6070E55D346773"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall determine which eligible entities shall receive a grant under this section. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6C7AC97537D4C56B982154932A6F30F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When awarding grants under subsection (a), the Secretary shall give priority—</text><subparagraph id="HEB8E8C5424C7409B947528D7BF3DD6E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to eligible entities that, as determined by the Secretary, have or are likely to develop a housing policy plan designed to avoid the displacement of current residents, including a plan for new housing development or a plan for increasing property value in the overburdened community; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD46F569CF207446B9419BC61B99F05FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">applications that utilize tree species that are proven to be more resilient to climate change and extreme weather events common in the area in which a project is to be implemented.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6AA3F1EDBF53474EA5401E3BA61C7D6F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of amounts</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under subsection (a) shall use amounts provided to cover costs associated with—</text><paragraph id="H9FA2DA34687B443A9A815034DC5F8CE7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">implementing the tree planting project in an overburdened community, including—</text><subparagraph id="HFF0F64824E664E078B31A700FA64A52B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>planning and designing the planting activity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H567C81D8331C427F9C52055A09628067"><enum>(B)</enum><text>purchasing qualifying trees; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A5ED17AFF954B338833E3566B83322C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>preparing the site and conducting planting, including the labor and cost associated with the use of machinery;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H91DF284B81D14B7D9747BE10718A88B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>maintaining and monitoring planted trees for a period of up to 5 years to ensure successful establishment of the qualifying trees;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H944B3D6DBBBA49CDB2FB45D30D7C207E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>training activities associated with the project; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47774248A04545969B0541A94E14429B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>other relevant costs, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF644EF50A6514684B0841D53CE58BEB3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out the Program $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEFF9CA2FAEB1478D9761805A18214A87"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H7885984A1B594C92AE40752246D04634"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H5309D98CF62949BFAC5DB75A32B43A8E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State, Territory, or Tribal agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC2CC969F0A645C68791173FD379E2A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a local government entity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4EF6BAF639A848BA87AC19DA1CB96B72"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2414B4F56B104B619166BE078C27EBD9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H481A30BA283740A89FFF55C5804BAB8D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limited English proficiency household</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>limited English proficiency household</term> means that a household does not have an adult that speaks English <quote>very well</quote> as determined by the United States Census Bureau. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD134243ABF694023974D3D1FE65F4CE2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Local governmental entity</header><text>The term <term>local governmental entity</term> means any municipal government or county government with jurisdiction over local land use decisions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB04306991EF24696B16746B88A2F186E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Qualifying tree</header><text>The term <term>qualifying tree</term> means a tree that—</text><subparagraph id="H87690273B55C4E42BE17AD54E278E0E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a species that is not an invasive species in the eligible area in which such tree is to be planted; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA877C63DA1B24CFA939650860B9C3A86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not a species that is, in the eligible area at the time of planting, being attacked by an invasive species, unless the eligible entity has a plan to limit the risk of death of the tree to be planted. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="HCD1ABD3E6DED474F8FC8DB531C212255"><enum>V</enum><header>Definitions</header><section id="H1709BB5B476041F597024E4A8D5879D3"><enum>501.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Except as specifically defined otherwise in this Act, for purposes of this Act the following definitions shall apply:</text><paragraph id="HF2E3FD040A19478A914CCA0CB6BD4B3E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community resilience center</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>community resilience center</term> means a facility that—</text><subparagraph id="H6DB1550DFDAD47F4A2E528DBEF5E7C1D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is operated by a State, Indian tribe, unit of general local government, or nonprofit organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DCFA29D87B4486689DEF60A4F2F483E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides a safe, air-conditioned environment meeting such standards as the Secretary shall establish for residents of the community in which it is located to take refuge during extreme heat events;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45B96254881E45D2A5E7BA4C7E03FCC8"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides a safe, heated environment meeting such standards as the Secretary shall establish for residents of the community in which it is located to take refuge during extreme cold events;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C29F79178C64101AE377F64AE9C78A5" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is available for such use by anyone without charge; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H899914A74D8C47278758D956DC9C7261"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conducts outreach activities to strengthen the relationship with the community in which it is located.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8BB429C4A9F4E2F83DCA521CB4500B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Indian tribe</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA478A5D1408B4B879891ED92D9C39F4A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit organization</term> means an organization that—</text><subparagraph id="H956480C63C874CF4889C82A6459DBFC6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/170">section 170(h)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA205B26637134FC8A49D5239DB5914A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>operates in accordance with one or more of the purposes described in section 170(h)(4)(A) of that Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H229E427B75B441E0A572903C9F8D60C4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Overburdened community</header><text>The term <term>overburdened community</term> means, as determined by the Secretary, an area where—</text><subparagraph id="H4318A9621BB245579161E439D814DE2A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">35 percent or more of households qualify as low-income households; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EA3DF349321488E956968A35CFB7482"><enum>(B)</enum><text>40 percent or more of residents identify as a minority or as members of a State-recognized tribal community; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3618D34D24874AF791D4BE106B368904"><enum>(C)</enum><text>40 percent or more of households are limited English proficiency households.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA793C132DCC74D84B5B41BFCCB9724E3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Public housing agency</header><text>The term <term>public housing agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3(b) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437a">42 U.S.C. 1437a(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57382ED205B94FB8892F9C686BC744EB"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102(a) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5302">42 U.S.C. 5302(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F5FE4B9690241B6AFF03F5827385CBD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Unit of general local government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>unit of general local government</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102(a) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5302">42 U.S.C. 5302(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

