<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3FF8988A6B224673ABF1C9755D7EF738" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 490 IH: Federal Infrastructure Bank Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 490</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Federal Infrastructure Bank to facilitate investment in, and the long-term financing of, economically viable United States infrastructure projects that provide a public benefit, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3CB50D7155FD4B68BB07638B65982FCE" style="OLC"><section id="H4A96E310B4794417961E2484ECF700E1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Infrastructure Bank Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H0384AC6DE60E41B3B44F5B2F76154318"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For the purposes of this Act:</text><paragraph id="HBCC39373A6304AAE86CC0C2844295262"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Bank</header><text>The term <term>Bank</term> means the Federal Infrastructure Bank established under section 4.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CDA83396E974C1A86E1F1A3E78FEA7A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HC890DC11008F4CB2B90262D2E11C810B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a corporation, limited liability company, or any other legally established corporate form;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1291B05AAF1D43D8ABC84160D74D1850"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a partnership, including a public-private partnership;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA74701884C74787856B28D0EA8132AA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a joint venture;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3B6DF2FEFF74B84AAB186023EBC7773"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a trust;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE117E9D0A2A04CE18C0530448842D7B1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86537B7808454A4993EB82B04E2736DD"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other governmental entity, including a political subdivision or any other instrumentality of a State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06BB328E372240DFA823FFC337110F56"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a revolving fund; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BCFA449A15F40B4AD4D52B3EEA21DAF"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a State infrastructure bank.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE3EEBF2E3F94CA5AA8979C55DB79486"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Holding Company</header><text>The term <term>Holding Company</term> means the <quote>Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company</quote> established under section 3.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D7E1CCC05FB43129830D7D96061F365"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Infrastructure project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>infrastructure project</term> means the construction, consolidation, alteration, operations, maintenance, or repair of projects, which provide public benefit or use, in the following categories:</text><subparagraph id="HE785716214244C129636223FA727FFE2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Highway and roadway facilities, including bridges and tunnels.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E8B0E5EBD4C47EC837C2C4FC7F5C66D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Port or marine terminal facilities, including approaches to marine terminal facilities or inland port facilities, and port or marine equipment including fixed equipment to serve approaches to marine terminals or inland ports.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6A535E2326C4088B03129CBC81B6795"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Airports, heliports, vertiports, spaceports, or air traffic control systems and facilities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3393A305840E4FB1A710985ECF3FB341"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Transmission or distribution pipelines.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H456DB1421CA440028B0D470F56B6E751"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Facilities or equipment for energy transmission, distribution, or storage.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC75294B30E9244558E8C0A8863528FB1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Intercity passenger or freight rail lines, facilities, or equipment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC6AAEE461EE49748D38E9D2E1070AAE"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Intercity passenger bus facilities or equipment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51E57F4D02E346889B3BDDDFFCD66655"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Public transportation facilities or equipment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6911ECED98C0482FA7F47EAD295DC14A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Inland waterways.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H850BC08CE3F84FFCAD1E12E2488E081E"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Intermodal facilities or equipment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A71C004892342B4A9BB994B2AA17F4D"><enum>(K)</enum><text>Water treatment and solid waste disposal facilities and associated infrastructure such as pipes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H298BA209676F4D5F8141A1591C964AA2"><enum>(L)</enum><text>Storm water management systems.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C2F73363D73472D9022646C1E0AAFB3"><enum>(M)</enum><text>Dams and levees.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D74A2767785438FB827402261744867"><enum>(N)</enum><text>Any other infrastructure project which the Bank identifies as providing a public benefit with regards to infrastructure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H17193B03E1D34D0197F05CF312CD59A2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Risk-based capital</header><text>The term <term>risk-based capital</term> shall have the meaning given that term by the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADFCF8FDFE0349E9835971AFE54C989F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Rural</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>rural</term> means any area not in a metropolitan statistical area with a population of 50,000 or greater.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BB9EEB281C94CCB98B4641B4F0C30D1"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the 50 several States of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, American Samoa, Guam, the United States Virgin Islands, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92158EA37FF746C4B6940F3392CBB008"><enum>(8)</enum><header>State infrastructure bank</header><text>The term <term>State infrastructure bank</term> means a State infrastructure bank or multi-State infrastructure bank established pursuant to—</text><subparagraph id="HDCFB8A77B4AB440EBCE054B55402F910"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 350 of the National Highway System Designation Act of 1995;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7705631418554FCAA5E1054EAA1D6E03"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 1511(l) of the Transportation Equity Act for the 21st Century;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBC554728A694009B975E0103B284627"><enum>(C)</enum><text>section 610 of title 23, United States Code; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3CFF4E0C22F4E80A503BF33E96F1957"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any State law as an agency, component unit, or other governmental entity of the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H2CFDABC1A69F4E0D96C5139AB40E6A08"><enum>3.</enum><header>Selection of the Formation Agent</header><subsection id="H473ADAEAAF014CCE89CC3F7195A55476"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 60 days of the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Chairman of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, shall select a Formation Agent which shall—</text><paragraph id="H5015C27F5A164DE088035746DC318FC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make and file with the Secretary of the Treasury an organization certificate for the Bank in accordance with such rules and regulations as the Secretary may prescribe, including the establishment of the Holding Company; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEC713EB1CB646C48B19BAFB92C725C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>have significant experience in infrastructure and infrastructure finance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC5840F47935246A18B5DC05EC28E95BE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of the Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 30 days after being selected under subsection (a), the Formation Agent shall establish the Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company, prescribe the governing structure of the Holding Company, and establish the Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company Board of Directors, which shall—</text><paragraph id="HF151B4149CFE4D609ECE51407ACA23EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>initially consist of 7 members;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3714A17516B2452DA306AFCE942C846B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be elected by the shareholders of the Holding Company;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1CFAD6AEDE24999A0EE76E2672A093B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>serve 4-year terms, only 2 of which may be consecutive;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00410873BD7E4A5A80155E3DD9C72D40"><enum>(4)</enum><text>within the limitations of law and regulation, determine and sign the articles of association that govern the operations of the Holding Company, and have the power to adopt, amend, and repeal bylaws governing the performance of the powers and duties granted to or imposed upon the Holding Company by law; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0AA71356CE94ED88284DC03BB5C8A7E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>select and effect the appointment of qualified persons to fill the office of the Chief Executive Officer of the Bank and such other offices as may be provided for in the bylaws of the Holding Company and the Federal Infrastructure Bank.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2C5A30901E0A4AA4B81FA0DD17678083"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Earnings And reserves not Government funds</header><text>The earnings and reserves of the Holding Company shall be the sole property of the Holding Company and are not Government funds or public funds.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF0B5C309B1924ABBA26BC1DCB3DC7129"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Treatment of shareholders of the Formation Agent</header><text>The Formation Agent shall issue equity securities of the Holding Company to each shareholder of the Formation Agent, in an amount that the Formation Agent determines has a value equal to the value of equity securities of the Formation Agent held by such shareholder upon the establishment of the Holding Company.</text></subsection></section><section id="HFB78570C648E4F7985D69059255EB43B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Establishment of the Federal Infrastructure Bank</header><subsection id="H9AE4B2FC80C246018F7C6D47450F24F1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Formation Agent shall establish the Federal Infrastructure Bank as a Delaware corporation and the Bank shall be a wholly owned subsidiary of the Holding Company.</text></subsection><subsection id="H986E5ECE602F4A09A051802AD25E77EA" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal banking charter</header><text>The Comptroller of the Currency shall grant a national bank charter to the Bank.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6631F42F3F304E4090E8FE5CBFECA5C5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regional offices</header><text>Within 5 years of the date of enactment of this Act, the Bank shall establish regional offices for the purpose of focusing on infrastructure projects in different areas of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC52DC921FCE346D69275788E8EA012ED"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Board of Directors</header><text>The Board of Directors of the Holding Company established under section 3 shall be the initial Board of Directors of the Bank.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0F0A3114A684493DBE78B613CF483F41"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Earnings and reserves not government funds</header><text>The earnings and reserves of the Bank are not Government funds or public funds.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3E9E33B4DD9B48369EA7F4F23C94BD89"><enum>5.</enum><header>Functions of the Bank</header><subsection id="H1AAD5315B4AA476CB169086750CBB7E7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bank shall provide equity investments, direct loans, indirect loans, and loan guarantees to eligible entities for the planning, pre-development, design, construction, operations or maintenance of revenue-producing infrastructure projects in the United States with sufficient revenue sources and guarantees to support the interest and principal payments to the Bank.</text></subsection><subsection id="H59BEA9FCD07B4AB0B447079F98E5F42F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Support for rural projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than 10 percent of the dollar amount of loans, equity investments, and loan guarantees provided by the Bank shall be with respect to infrastructure projects in rural areas.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4A83ACBA1F414801B7C1EF25327CC03E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Leveraging Bank investments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bank shall attempt to cross subsidize non-revenue infrastructure projects with revenue generating infrastructure projects to diversify the loan portfolio.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD3EE1C0779D14EEA92A82BD97CC93CAB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No commercial or investment banking activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Bank is prohibited from—</text><paragraph id="H463529461772445DB12509A99A5E2637"><enum>(1)</enum><text>accepting customer deposits; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1729635D8364CDEA2201ECF10B8B031"><enum>(2)</enum><text>engaging in financial or investment banking activities, except with respect to the Bank’s own revenues.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC201CFC95A0041068AE741D69B04FF63"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Pledge and credit facilities</header><paragraph id="H7A254E54F7AA46C8B3D87FA8D142B636"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Pledge</header><text>The Bank shall have the authority to pledge its loans to the discount window of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F28714137E746909F15E11572A1F7AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Purchase of obligations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury may purchase obligations issued by the Bank in the same manner and under the same requirements that the Secretary purchases obligations under section 306(c) of the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1455">12 U.S.C. 1455(c)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2CB1E8ECF7614160A5F2D1A311061118"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Leverage limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bank shall maintain risk-based capital at no less than 10 percent, collectively for the Bank and the Holding Company.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBCFCC15BEF9B4C838F629C0FFCE63B5C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Lifecycle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bank shall ensure that infrastructure projects account for long-term operations, maintenance, and life-cycle costs and obligations to ensure that the infrastructure projects maximize the useful life of each applicable asset.</text></subsection><subsection id="H69D8B0656CE44735A182C0D9D21F9A6F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Infrastructure delivery</header><text>The Bank, as a clearinghouse for infrastructure finance, may provide implementation advisory assistance, directly or indirectly, to infrastructure projects.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5E222BD5D98D4134985A949370B0172D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Credit rating</header><text>The Bank shall accept credit ratings consistent with typical infrastructure market practice to enhance deployment of capital.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA13BBB0A8F6C40EAA8E5F651400BE52A" commented="no"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Prohibition on funding of foreign projects</header><text>The Bank is prohibited from providing equity investments, direct loans, indirect loans, and loan guarantees for infrastructure projects not located within the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6B2D8B049A5543ABBEE7C926B15366FF"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Prohibition with respect to China</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bank is prohibited from providing equity investments, direct loans, indirect loans, and loan guarantees for infrastructure projects that are owned, directed, controlled, financed, or influenced by the Government of the People’s Republic of China, the Chinese Communist Party, or the People’s Liberation Army.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE7865F9AB7744CB7BA77737E4C0E6135"><enum>6.</enum><header>Holding Company securities</header><subsection id="H88ED5D4461D5415C8EA80E5DE72D539A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Equity securities</header><paragraph id="H142A3BD2BD9D42A5B1294A3EFF17FF1F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Holding Company shall issue such equity securities as the Board of Directors of the Holding Company determines appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45ADD02A702145F8A375E68F28796550"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dividends</header><text>The Holding Company may make such dividend payments on the equity securities of the Holding Company as the Holding Company determines appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7122F416AEE448349192892785D234D3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Restriction on voting rights</header><text>Any holder of an equity security of the Holding Company that is a non-United States individual or entity shall have no voting rights with respect to such equity security.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5341AEE8B44481198E09477563773FA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Bonds</header><paragraph id="HA81B71DCC51B4BA8805511A1D33EDB11"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Standard bonds</header><text>The Holding Company may issue standard bonds with maturities up to 30 years or longer, as needed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5DE48742A084E81B9ED41A50EADDB0C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other bonds</header><text>The Holding Company may issue other bonds, notes, and marketable securities with maturities and interest rates as the Holding Company determines appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FF4ACE2D3FD4D8FA354700B971EAD4F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authority to purchase bonds</header><subparagraph id="H384DFC24B5014527BAB59B79EFA84BF5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury and the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System may purchase bonds issued under this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6112C4DF7FA04458B8B29D4708C2385C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The aggregate amount of outstanding bonds purchased by the Secretary under this paragraph may not exceed 5 percent of the total amount of the outstanding bonds of the Holding Company.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3DEDBB6648B34687AEA957828EF7543E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Leverage limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Holding Company shall maintain risk-based capital at no less than 10 percent, collectively for the Bank and the Holding Company.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF729559B9CBE4AD181817325F279EAA4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Investment limitation on non-United States individuals and entities</header><paragraph id="H8D72A61E7C1C41648E217DDEC61C9619"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Non-United States individuals and entities may not hold more than 25 percent, in the aggregate, of the equity securities and bonds of the Holding Company.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75D8920733254885919DD6D2E5BFEE85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Formation Agent and Holding Company are prohibited from issuing any bond, note, marketable security, or other financial instrument to any person or entity—</text><subparagraph id="H17E506CC19684CF1B44F354C32996A02"><enum>(A)</enum><text>affiliated with, owned by, or directed, controlled, financed, or influenced by the Government of the People’s Republic of China, the Chinese Communist Party, or the People’s Liberation Army; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77D075211DA9457583075A1DAC65040C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>affiliated with, owned by, or directed, controlled, financed, or influenced by a State Sponsor of Terrorism, as so designated by the Secretary of State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE8358F6AC8454B7E913F4CF24E510B28"><enum>7.</enum><header>Oversight and regulation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System shall—</text><paragraph id="H4E9A8BDD8F9B4C2A93C0CFF08ACB2923"><enum>(1)</enum><text>have oversight and supervisory authority over the Holding Company and the Bank, in order to ensure the safe and sound operation of the Holding Company and the Bank; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24AA7FAFC53B438F90F7459EA5CE62C7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall regulate Bank activities to ensure compliance with the requirements set forth in this Act.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC581608B66A44D77A2DD2DB091E6ECF6"><enum>8.</enum><header>Infrastructure Guarantee Fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Bank shall establish an Infrastructure Guarantee Fund that shall be used with respect to specific loans or loan guarantees made by the Bank in the event of any non-payment by the recipient of such loan or loan guarantee.</text></section><section id="H8ADC9C5F9B174BFD9314E147F9B7E5CF"><enum>9.</enum><header>Holding Company and Bank exemption from taxation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective for taxable years ending on or after the date of enactment of this Act, the Holding Company and the Bank, including franchises, capital, reserves, surplus, advances, and income of the Holding Company or Bank, shall be exempt from all taxation imposed by the United States and any State, county, municipal, or local taxing authority, except that any real property of the Holding Company and the Bank shall be subject to State, county, municipal, or local taxation to the same extent according to its value as other real property is taxed.</text></section><section id="H00C1FA4667454947A79A680B50186CC6"><enum>10.</enum><header>Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company credit</header><subsection id="HC78CA85DA3374FC28CFFE069C62638E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart D of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><paragraph id="H35B4E3BF3F8243BB94BEEF7EBB393E1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="H7186B10D3A9942A1976915DB9E05B87F" style="OLC"><section id="HB6305B7D339A4759B181AFEBF1F7544D"><enum>45AA.</enum><header>Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company credit</header><subsection id="H55C16057F61649DC8706DD72D3922E03"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of section 38, in the case of a taxpayer who holds a qualified Holding Company equity investment on a credit allowance date of such investment which occurs during the taxable year, the Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company credit determined under this section for such taxable year is an amount equal to 10 percent of the amount paid to the Holding Company for such investment at its original issue.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5B4BC94D5FBD45E3B3569FF324F8F996"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Credit allowance date</header><text>For purposes of this section, the credit allowance date with respect to any qualified Holding Company equity investment is—</text><paragraph id="HD5597DA1CEDA494B849887CE194D6FEC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which such investment is initially made; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H876F22F1CCB3493DB51719DB1D679E7D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>each of the 4 taxable years thereafter.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD2FE1640991443987F1B536901322E2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Qualified holding company equity investment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <term>qualified Holding Company equity investment</term> means any equity investment originally issued by the Holding Company to the taxpayer under section 6(a)(1) of the <short-title>Federal Infrastructure Bank Act of 2023</short-title> not later than 3 years after the formation of the Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company pursuant to section 3 of the <short-title>Federal Infrastructure Bank Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H12BFF500AE3C4107BF1AFCD5147AB06F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Holding company</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>Holding Company</term> means the Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company established by the <short-title>Federal Infrastructure Bank Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H3538C09D2F95446CB85DD9E0BF1690B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the table of contents for such subpart, by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9CC0782CC02D461EB55647B3497E59C6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">45AA. Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company credit.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7C47A578DE3D43FF8171A26476288744" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="H91AC7E62CFB24323B2065A40F4AB1DA3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 38(b) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>plus</quote> at the end of paragraph (37), by striking the period at the end of paragraph (38) and inserting <quote>, plus</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block id="H1198763EBDE744C3A8CB02C98644E710" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HFED32D3BB0D94DD9870845DA80DC21D9"><enum>(39)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Federal Infrastructure Bank Holding Company credit determined under section 45AA.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H65573A985CC740D1B0C23FC6519668BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 1016(a) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (37), by striking the period at the end of paragraph (38) and inserting <quote>, and</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block id="H11FA3652A6FA47C4B2B122D737E16F6C" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HE3F03F62FDEC40A589E626A72C9F51AA"><enum>(39)</enum><text>to the extent provided in section 45AA(e).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H858FB78B760345B99495F280F11EF99E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H10595EB1EB094D159FC78071816A60F4"><enum>11.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Nothing in this Act may be construed as authorizing the Federal Government to guarantee the assets of the Bank or Holding Company.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

