<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA1B87AFEED0646DFB4BC6BE936DC8973" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2830 IH: Veteran Improvement Commercial Driver License Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2830</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000246">Mr. Edwards</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001132">Mr. Crane</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to revise the rules for approval by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs of commercial driver education programs for purposes of veterans educational assistance, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H702D1D4D79C94BAE9F60319CA63B4F1C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5CEEF1617A914B739F0212A69E40C584" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veteran Improvement Commercial Driver License Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HCDDCF1E03FAF4E67B1FB1CE761B7CBC8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modification of rules for approval of commercial driver education programs for purposes of veterans educational assistance</header> <subsection id="H659E26047A8A48EABF82BFAD5D3B1C3A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 3680A(e) of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HCB91C85DFD1A46CFBE2151558EC141AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) through (3) as subparagraphs (A) though (C), respectively;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6605E5DBE272480A9C01BAFB7C3CFE7B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the matter before subparagraph (A), as redesignated by paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> before <quote>The Secretary</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H51B8FEC127FF40E19CEC51F0365C51D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(B), as redesignated by paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>except as provided in paragraph (2),</quote> before <quote>the course</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5F4E2386552D41FDA0978C769FCE0F58"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph (2):</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7393238103154A5690539842283C608C">
<paragraph id="HB36CA2DAC8E142FAA75067322A12F271" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H386C9E4DD93A4CE58ACA4EA964037AE2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Subject to this paragraph, a commercial driver education program is exempt from paragraph (1)(B) for a branch of an educational institution if the commercial driver education program offered at the branch by the educational institution—</text> <clause id="HA912E3FB604A4D46A3818645600169F9" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is appropriately licensed; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HA13C79CD6570475DA07243D7D8C72791" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>uses the same curriculum as a commercial driver education program offered by the educational institution at another location that is approved for purposes of this chapter by a State approving agency or the Secretary when acting in the role of a State approving agency.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" id="HB8CA975B8BFD422DA232EF3FDF2EA8B7"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H200300F6917044D7AA6EB7DDA45E1A08"><enum>(i)</enum><text>In order for a commercial driver education program of an educational institution offered at a branch described in paragraph (1)(B) to be exempt under subparagraph (A) of this paragraph, the educational institution shall submit to the Secretary each year that paragraph (1)(B) would otherwise apply a report that demonstrates that the curriculum at the new branch is the same as the curriculum at the primary location.</text></clause>
<clause indent="up1" id="H3F4C2E6E35B943CAAA4529151428034C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Reporting under clause (i) shall be submitted in accordance with such requirements as the Secretary shall establish in consultation with the State approving agencies.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" id="H7E985E6C90744A24AAC5ADB578D03B82"><enum>(C)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF67354AA8DCD4DAC85A43375C1F07FEA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Secretary may withhold an exemption under subparagraph (A) for any educational institution or branch of an educational institution as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></clause>
<clause id="H4CE7C493A767488EBB24FD26E0E63E2C" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>In making any determination under clause (i), the Secretary may consult with the Secretary of Transportation on the performance of a provider of a commercial driver program, including the status of the provider within the Training Provider Registry of the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration when appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBFB4518ACD724EFC970BB116121CF102"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation</header> <paragraph id="H9A814DB8AC08484684D28631C4F6C166"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment of requirements</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish requirements under section 3680A(e)(2)(B)(ii) of such title, as added by subsection (a).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H72B57039644B4809B61531A2A5117661"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply to commercial driver education programs on and after the date that is 180 days after the date on which the Secretary establishes the requirements under paragraph (1) of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

