<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H77C62BBEF22F4792B62396AE61CC47A6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 167 IH: Patient Access to Urgent-Use Pharmacy Compounding Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 167</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000568">Mr. Griffith</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act to ensure patients have access to certain urgent-use compounded medications, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H69169D4F3A0141C8BD3A20AE3BA10731" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3A1A9186C2E54B9483D48187B94534CE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Patient Access to Urgent-Use Pharmacy Compounding Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3C242F8B3F7D477BB49B3697F46F51AC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Urgent-use compounding for administration in hospitals or other clinical settings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 503A(a) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/353a">21 U.S.C. 353a(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD367B5A6B78A4B5BB8BF7DD57231A2EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H445D239BAE22474FAC875B347EF5820E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B)(ii)(II), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H776C9D7773E5432296F8AF42C1F040EA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block id="HF321AB2523AF444AADB2437E0A5D80C0" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H0FD3CB8B915D4EB1B9713F489561E46D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">notwithstanding the requirement in the matter preceding paragraph (1) that the drug product is compounded for an identified individual patient based on a valid prescription order or notation described in such matter, is by a licensed pharmacist or licensed physician and the compounded drug product is compounded for distribution in limited quantities to a licensed prescriber for urgent administration to a patient in a hospital or other clinical setting, provided that all of the following are met:</text>
<subparagraph id="H3A6C6BCC67D74AC38C5C2BCAD425B785"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The licensed prescriber certifies by notation on the order to the compounding pharmacist or physician that the licensed prescriber has made reasonable attempts to obtain, and has not been able to obtain, to address the urgent medical need—</text> <clause id="H26762D6F7B5D400F9DCA50B8E42CBE94"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a drug product that is approved or authorized by the Food and Drug Administration with the same active ingredient and the same route of administration; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H8115818339F84DA88AF8C2701B25D8EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a drug product that is compounded by an outsourcing facility in accordance with section 503B with the same active ingredient and the same route of administration.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H882283487D914DB9A2B075D8C89D22C9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The compounded drug product is labeled with a beyond-use-date in accordance with applicable United States Pharmacopeia standards.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1A34DB64121C459F8C8FDC6E9BD6D100"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The licensed pharmacist or licensed physician marks the packaging of the compounded drug product with text—</text> <clause id="HB872AB56AE6C46229318FE6DFC06F778"><enum>(i)</enum><text>indicating that the drug product is provided to the hospital or other clinical setting only for urgent administration to a patient; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HA2E3F0D554CC4F30985DC6D2EA253287"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>requesting that the hospital or other clinical setting provide to the com­pound­ing pharmacist or physician the records that identify the patient or patients to whom the drug products were administered within—</text> <subclause id="H8B004A68F20943508EA5145A7B630B2B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>7 days of each such patient receiving such medication; or</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HF7D2EAB4C9E14796A6604E8A7EF12D00"><enum>(II)</enum><text>7 days of each such patient being discharged.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H359841D2E9B14997A0999797BECDE8E9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Upon receipt of records requested pursuant to subparagraph (C)(ii), the licensed pharmacist or licensed physician ensures that the patient information in such records is linked with the respective order.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA64450EA42E24FBA886FB86ED24C5023"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The licensed pharmacist or licensed physician reports adverse events associated with the compounded drug product as soon as possible but no later than 15 days after becoming aware of such events to the MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program of the Food and Drug Administration (or any successor program).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="H4401594025614E7883BCFB8D8929D206"><enum>3.</enum><header>Compounding for shortages for administration in hospitals or other clinical settings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (2) of section 503A(b) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/353a">21 U.S.C. 353a(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9CD746CDCDFF4FDB899A2322637B7C84" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H61E7D1539C224ED78DB83D93F21A2592"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1)(D), the term <term>essentially a copy of a commercially available drug product</term> does not include—</text> <subparagraph id="H9E974F8502554F1FBD420A3B59C9688B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a drug product in which there is a change, made for an identified individual patient, which produces for that patient a significant difference, as determined by the prescribing practitioner, between the compounded drug and the comparable commercially available drug product; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2C0413697AF143389EFDF445899C996A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a drug product that meets each of the following conditions:</text> <clause id="HA66E766EC1D44901957210703A4AFEE5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>At the time of compounding, distribution, or dispensing, the drug product appears on—</text>
<subclause id="H4213C8A3B48D4CBBB116C88DF6ABEE6D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the drug shortage list in effect under section 506E; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H16201BD5EB1E4AD086AE8ABD4AE56E53"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the drug shortage list maintained by the American Society of Hospital Pharmacists.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H4EC961E5A3904F64AD4E838EDCFDD58F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>If the drug product is not compounded for an identified individual patient based on a valid prescription order or notation, notwithstanding such requirement in the matter preceding paragraph (1) of subsection (a), then the drug product—</text> <subclause id="HDFE7CC17136845B68A74D0492162274B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is labeled in accordance subparagraphs (B) and (C) of subsection (a)(3); and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H8A83B888BB9243D8B55B0889D4F9A8CC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is documented by the compounding pharmacist or physician in accordance with subparagraphs (D) and (E) of subsection (a)(3).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

