<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H02118161511A4A3AB02D01BDEEF23E72" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 822 IH: Student Mental Health Helpline Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 822</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001192">Mr. Stewart</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to authorize the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, to award grants to eligible entities to establish or maintain a student mental health and safety helpline, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H265DA687D1E9496CB7C4E17106F76E87" style="OLC">
<section id="HFC87E25E3ACA435A899A7969E6C3A2E9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Student Mental Health Helpline Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H45D011C918CB44F08769237D4D9EB9D7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants for student mental health and safety helpline</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part D of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290dd">42 U.S.C. 290dd et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H77CD329124184FE0843650ADC8933ECE" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="H83B25494CDE045F49A1D0422C53672DD"><enum>553.</enum><header>Grants for student mental health and safety helpline</header>
<subsection id="HA588BA66BBC940C4A7C25BC79367DB2D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header>
<paragraph id="HCD8B77C14BC74243B647838C2F2E27CC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment or maintenance grants</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, and in consultation with the Secretary of Education, may award grants to eligible entities to establish or maintain a student mental health and safety helpline that—</text> <subparagraph id="HF8EAFF13DC7341A8805BEA13F3FEA7B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is free and confidential;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFC48DC68C0D04EFEB6DBDB26F58795E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is accessible to students through multiple platforms;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7BAE2F6587E64F5BA4BB119F0C7BCAC6" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides information to school officials about student health and safety issues, to the extent permitted by the HIPAA privacy regulations; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC4C7150C1AAF4F0299BABE9C7D6C2433"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">operates 24 hours a day, seven days a week, every day of the year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD5439420E4E411B9F68DFD0E155674F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transition grants</header> <subparagraph id="H92F52BB512C245D5A38168CA8A3B9953"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, and in consultation with the Secretary of Education, may award grants to States, local governments, Indian Tribes, and Tribal organizations to transition, by not later than 2 years after the award of the grant, a helpline that was in existence on the day before the date of enactment of the <short-title>Student Mental Health Helpline Act</short-title> to an agency or subdivision whose primary responsibility relates to health, public health, or education so as to become eligible for grants under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE8E3E80049ED408095AC6B7058BF3686"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A grant under subparagraph (A) shall be used exclusively for costs associated with the transition described in such subparagraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0DD6A9BE31A64242B3DAA9B21D1AA966" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application of HIPAA privacy regulations</header> <paragraph id="HC27E66BFA728443184104D804C7A4EAE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>A helpline funded under subsection (a)(1) shall be treated as a covered entity (as defined in section 106.103 of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations)), and information received by the helpline from students contacting the helpline shall be treated as protected health information (as defined in such section 106.103 (or successor regulations)), for purposes of the HIPAA privacy regulations.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H38783A9FC1B34508AED879236CBC74AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional privacy standards</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to preempt or otherwise prohibit the application, with respect to a helpline funded under this section, of privacy standards in addition to those applicable under the HIPAA privacy regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HADB31DEE95AB47FAAA2947BB14938B85"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible grantees</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under subsection (a)(1), an entity shall be an agency or other subdivision—</text>
<paragraph id="HB98C644D0C564FEAB12F35A52DE426ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>of a State, a local government, an Indian Tribe, or a Tribal organization; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H950C220F961348AFA537B785138E4E34"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whose primary responsibility relates to health, public health, or education.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H4D32886F540C422398CAC122EB8155DE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A recipient of a grant under subsection (a)(1) shall use the grant for each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H30BFD4D3038546A182CA25ED41A6A2B4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Supporting a phone line, texting, and social media accounts for students facing challenges with abuse, bullying, depression, risk of self-injury, risk of injury to others, or suicidal thoughts.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H879ED811D30C4E5F9CE91D53D809F1B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing such support in a culturally competent manner, including to students who—</text> <subparagraph id="H5F0AF1DD86D241F5A0F861370AD68C04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are from diverse backgrounds; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H251195ECEF6E4BF59E57A461F4DC082D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify with groups associated with a higher risk of bullying, abuse, and suicide, such as individuals who are LGBTQ or have disabilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD5FB10E1E3F14B77BBA12234C3C0D125"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Coordinating with—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCF25F52FB831428082F02232A63F7A63"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other mental health crisis lines;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6E25C42DA6464A3E9C0A40F9842A9627"><enum>(B)</enum><text>State and local mental health agencies and providers, local educational agencies, school administrators, and community-based health service providers; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFE6C830BFCAB465481C10852F94B424D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in cases of neglect and abuse, State and local family service agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE2F23794A937480CB906007900B7A260"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Ensuring that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9D8EC2A16EF34E7DB7AE3EEEF1733889"><enum>(A)</enum><text>activities funded through the grant are conducted in accordance with all applicable Federal and State privacy standards; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H685709145FB1496B8CEBC3E34BEDA27A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>health care information collected through such activities will be maintained in a secure manner.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCBD305BAB7C24ACDA3B4A16B9DAD25BB"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing a disaster recovery plan and redundancy measures to ensure continuous technical operations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H26E91BA7C8294B90AE13497B046AFF0B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Other allowable uses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of a grant under subsection (a)(1) may choose to use the grant for any of the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H472EC6ABDDEC4B0DACD193C9D484C323"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Supporting forms of communication in addition to those specified in subsection (d)(1), such as online forms and an email account.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9BA5061A8D3245C1852466D088694EE1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to coordinating with the entities specified in subsection (d)(3), coordinating with nonprofit organizations and institutions of higher education.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC0B2CC8B1FCF40EFAA908A5A785578DB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Developing educational curricula that schools may choose to offer, in conjunction with the helpline funded through the grant, to remove the stigma of mental illness, prevent bullying, prevent domestic violence, prevent suicide, or otherwise address student mental health and safety.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9C267AB6AA8C4B6982846BCF0B10552A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Promoting activities to encourage students to use the helpline funded through the grant.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H919CD38A8F3940F28EC6E392D95EDED4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Collecting and analyzing data on the use of the helpline funded through the grant to improve and adjust services offered through the helpline.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCFF879EAA65D487F87786618903B9E84"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing support in multiple languages in areas with a high concentration of multiple language speakers.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8434C4DE73E6484EA9878AA30254BAAA"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing, in accordance with best practices and guidelines of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration for behavioral health crisis care, protocols and training for identifying and responding to students who present an imminent risk of harming themselves or others.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE34CB7324625456D954F34AEC105D06D"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing training, technology, and personnel necessary to comply with the HIPAA privacy regulations or other relevant privacy standards.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7CF5D3C9C0EB4E7DA56B3CAC5A1C51F2"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Coordinating and sharing best practices with other student mental health and safety helplines, including other helplines funded pursuant to this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA46AF342075243F1AF87746B8503CAD2"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sharing personnel (such as crisis counselors), services (such as technology and data management services), and other resources deemed appropriate by the Secretary with other mental health and safety helplines that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H351F0A8A04F141159AE42AF553FFFEF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are operated by the recipient of the grant; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC8D4E783C7048A19EA09358BD2C564F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are operated by another entity and funded through the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2A1B4C16751A46838C4D8A855C20A7C3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Period of a grant</header><text>The period of a grant under subsection (a)(1) shall be not less than 5 years.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCFAFF60B299A4ACF8F0111463A7A5840"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Subgrants and contracts</header> <paragraph id="H9230FBBE5EAF49A4AFF43CDAC9FC87CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>A recipient of a grant under subsection (a)(1) may award subgrants and enter into contracts to carry out activities funded through the grant.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC7F2D9245A0542A481EB035AED6BB870"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible subgrantees and contractors</header><text>To be eligible to receive a subgrant or contract under paragraph (1), an entity shall be—</text> <subparagraph id="H84EDBFF67BD74FA18789F89B6ECAA596"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a local educational agency;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6CC1BFB0BC044C7C97B52FC5D556EBEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2BDB07B76CEA4152A80A2A49C0E536D4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF968DFF84D73467AAE7FE75FB7AE6DDA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a for-profit organization that provides—</text> <clause id="H630633DCE618486BBE81BB90C072924F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>website or data management services;</text></clause>
<clause id="H3B8A37D4245F4F979B11D2EBC26A237D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>specialized staff trained in crisis intervention to answer incoming messages; or</text></clause> <clause id="H4B4FF53633AC4F0D921F0C464ECBD847"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other products or services deemed by the Secretary to be appropriate for establishing or maintaining a helpline funded under subsection (a)(1);</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCA079BF6EAC34094A2C82F5128B9AB3D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a school; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H36F7CBC0F34C46EAAD97E6F654D012C4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>another type of entity deemed by the Secretary to be appropriate for subgrants or contracts under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5BD22494768C4E6AAF3475C274F9B733"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Accreditation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a subgrant or contract under paragraph (1) for specialized staff trained in crisis intervention to answer incoming messages, an entity shall be accredited by a nationally recognized accreditation entity that applies current evidence-based practices related to mental and behavioral health.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H286492ABED35410E9B8559CAF87A36DA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding subgrants and contracts under paragraph (1), a recipient of a grant under subsection (a)(1) shall give priority to eligible entities that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H586179DCE2FE432CAA1637E475DBBF2A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>retain a licensed mental health care practitioner on staff; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0FE0BF9B2C3F42C4AF1619DB07206F3D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>participate in the network of the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H44822E20F9C348F08B18B93CE58CDD12"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reporting</header>
<paragraph id="H7DDC4DCAD2DC47438A016A19EF85FA85"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each fiscal year for which grants are awarded under subsection (a)(1) or (a)(2), the Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HB34EFD3AC592451B9FF0E7573C61137D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>study the results of the grants; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H44344E95B21D4B94BCF5B5C760E182DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit to the Congress a report on such results, including—</text> <clause id="H4449A24BB9CD4EC79AC453BC658BB892"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an evaluation of the outcomes of the programs under subsections (a)(1) and (a)(2);</text></clause>
<clause id="H180BCBDA264D401AB7462595B0AB5B23"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a summary of activities carried out with grants under subsections (a)(1) and (a)(2) and the results achieved through those activities;</text></clause> <clause id="HE7FF8A335A394A309BF550337B2A205B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent practicable, the demographics of students served and nature of messages received through grants under subsections (a)(1) and (a)(2); and</text></clause>
<clause id="H7C103719B1E94ECDBA15DBB75FD9B787"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of grants under subsection (a)(2), an analysis of changes in the outcomes, activities, demographics, and nature of messages described in clauses (i), (ii), and (iii) as a result of transitioning helplines to different agencies or subdivisions.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02B9D880992E48DFBDC2F7E5E809404D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report on feasibility of a national student helpline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Student Mental Health Helpline Act</short-title>, the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Education and the Chair of the Federal Communications Commission, shall publish a report on—</text>
<subparagraph id="HABF0ABBC789F4281914AFC5F5DB4ECBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the feasibility of making a student mental health and safety helpline nationally available;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1C87C6B03B0C4C51B76D1D42659BAF3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how to successfully integrate the helplines of States and other entities into a consolidated national student mental health and safety helpline; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC860913A5F90484C95E83381BB22CA2D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the feasibility and potential benefits and drawbacks of adding a student-specific capability to the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H70F0838406AE45718959BB65D8AFFA1A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="HA7A2838DC7ED42008BCF274CFDEEBFA2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>HIPAA privacy regulations</term> means the Federal regulations (concerning the privacy of individually identifiable health information) promulgated under section 264(c) of the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320d-2">42 U.S.C. 1320d–2</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49CFAE5F11984BC4A80855F6C6D0220F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The terms <term>Indian Tribe</term> and <term>Tribal organization</term> have the meanings given to such terms in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H260A8C7A68204C5DB6815E5C2A8A858C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given to such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A99545DEBFD4DE091AAF4144A40695F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given to such term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBB92849C61B34CD8A9942212C844FA08"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The term <term>State</term> includes the District of Columbia and each territory or commonwealth of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB36BDF20B28748F2A281906DBAB2FB6D"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $55,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


