<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H93DFE50475334DB08F23FBBC398E9EB6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5306 IH: Department of Defense Ethics and Anti-Corruption Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5306</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230829">August 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote ethics and prevent corruption in Department of Defense contracting and other activities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF87DA554F7314C988A08BF31FC3096A9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H95D9D3BAD40448FC8C7E6BF69F1F0D52" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0B3177839FC04BE1B15102EC17107C58"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Defense Ethics and Anti-Corruption Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H453CFAEFC8714A0B8F7C518F615152D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H95D9D3BAD40448FC8C7E6BF69F1F0D52">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="title" idref="H9E89D646784C417B9F7E762CB3B4671D">TITLE I—Revolving door and contractor influence</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H59AB8583702A461B98CD7A041C2423FD">Sec. 101. Heightened revolving door requirements.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF4C019B7AA984E8E918A3B3F7E0FDE81">Sec. 102. Requirements for defense contractors relating to certain former Department of Defense officials and lobbying activities.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF65B9FC464E646AFBC5B763740ECCB5E">Sec. 103. Ban on hiring contracting officials enforceable on certain contracts.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HCC2D3E0B8E474766A16246C752462C51">Sec. 104. Ban on hiring senior officials by giant defense contractors.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H4D8C2392F3EB4A23B1C5CA14C7F698B3">Sec. 105. Modification of prohibition on lobbying activities with respect to the Department of Defense by certain officers of the Armed Forces and civilian employees of the Department of Defense following separation from military service or employment with the Department.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H794273719D064543B0200B27F3F15251">Sec. 106. Enhancement of recusal for conflicts of personal interest requirements for Department of Defense officers and employees.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H5587A40E61E2474DAE16C78DBEC51FBA">Sec. 107. Prohibition on ownership or trading of stocks in certain companies by Department of Defense officers and employees.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="title" idref="HE2A9CF017BAE464098CE0B9EEFEB408E">TITLE II—Limiting foreign influence</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HE1DB81BC8AF848CAADB7602942EF1E5D">Sec. 201. Ban on senior national security officials advising foreign governments.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HA8B0A28C298F47C1A010E58562011BE9">Sec. 202. Ban on former military and civilian intelligence officers from foreign employment.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="title" idref="H54F5839BB8B44A1B99E4D6830E0CB53D">TITLE III—Transparency</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H268E759349FA4633AC12F37B39E1CC76">Sec. 301. Affirmative contractor record disclosures.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H421365D8D7F5475F8EB60E96BE9306F2">Sec. 302. Publication of contractor evaluation ratings.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H823BA043D2A6436DA66940CAFD03371A">Sec. 303. Ownership of information.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H18E2FBA9C00E45359B9BC451BAF5D981">Sec. 304. Financial disclosure by large contractors.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HE15D5F4F4EAB40D8B1CABCD716BFCF61">Sec. 305. Availability on the internet of certain information about officers serving in general or flag officer grades.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section> 
<title id="H9E89D646784C417B9F7E762CB3B4671D" style="OLC"><enum>I</enum><header>Revolving door and contractor influence</header> 
<section id="H59AB8583702A461B98CD7A041C2423FD"><enum>101.</enum><header>Heightened revolving door requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 847 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/181">Public Law 110–181</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1701">10 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H72FCC7E9B6A74AC5A984676EC7C97EB1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1), by striking <quote>within two years of leaving service</quote> and inserting <quote>within four years of leaving service</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD3C49C26CBAA40C686E452103D407D73"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="H4813176817C5425384623A4BF329F9EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">requirement</header-in-text>.—Each request</quote> and inserting the following: “<header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">requirement</header-in-text>.—</text> 
<quoted-block id="H79A7EC51AE114D08BF0ADEC6198BB694" style="OLC" act-name=""> 
<paragraph id="HF4B5058934AC47DEB3926F3893FADD74"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Database</header><text>Each request</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9D7C5E26D7D41E5B1F8209746A5468C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>retained by the Department of Defense in a central database or repository maintained by the General Counsel of the Department for not less than five years</quote> and inserting <quote>retained by the Department of Defense in a central database or repository maintained by the Standards of Conduct Office of the Department for not less than 10 years</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HABEF3DFC1FB94DBDA8F891CA560E2A58"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and shall be posted on a publicly available internet website of the General Counsel Standards of Conduct Office</quote> after <quote>opinion was provided</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7CD971819DF2490CA86F01893E86D901"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E7B36CFE5DD47E9AED87D9F32238C9C"> 
<paragraph id="H68A57B8B678E4937B6A63FB94FFE93B4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inspector General review</header><text>The Inspector General of the Department of Defense shall conduct periodic reviews not less than biannually to ensure that written opinions are being requested, provided, and retained in accordance with the requirements of this section, as well as any related matters.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="HF4C019B7AA984E8E918A3B3F7E0FDE81"><enum>102.</enum><header>Requirements for defense contractors relating to certain former Department of Defense officials and lobbying activities</header> <subsection id="HE2154DD15D524D5E941F1AE877F5CFE5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/365">Chapter 365</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6EAAC18CE6DE4B8FB5E209F8CD7D818F"> 
<section id="H48B09215F774441B856180B59F275BA1"><enum>4705.</enum><header>Defense contractors report: requirements concerning former Department of Defense officials and lobbying activities</header> 
<subsection id="H9992D9FB20244E918DEF63FC7F2F44A0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each contract for the procurement of goods or services in excess of $10,000,000, other than a contract for the procurement of office supplies or food and beverage (vending) services, that is entered into by the Department of Defense shall include a provision under which the contractor agrees to submit to the Secretary of Defense, not later than April 1 of each year such contract is in effect, a written report setting forth the information required by subsection (b). The Secretary of Defense shall make these reports publicly available on a government website not later than July 1 of each year such contract is in effect. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H67DA9A15CBA341CD8929B3B75A36C097"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report information</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (c), a report by a contractor under subsection (a) shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCA9EDFD209A44FBE81E934AB7D7D96B4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>list the name of each person who—</text> <subparagraph id="H79B8F0425DB74C6988D3D03A68C5BB47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a former officer or employee of the Department of Defense or a former or retired member of the armed forces who served—</text> 
<clause id="H3B01231CE9404557821A3C5D829B547A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in an Executive Schedule position under subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 5;</text></clause> <clause id="H870B6D741C594D95B6EB6956C37DECE5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in a position in the Senior Executive Service under subchapter VIII of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 5;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC48CD2B685584CAD8713E2E1961F2073"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in a position compensated at a rate of pay for grade O–6 or above under section 201 of title 37; or</text></clause> <clause id="HCE235600FD75497793F2BD018BE8931F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>as a program manager, deputy program manager, procuring contracting officer, administrative contracting officer, source selection authority, member of the source selection evaluation board, or chief of a financial or technical evaluation team for a contract with a value in excess of $10,000,000; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4B274A31DEA44965ABFFE9D50C21ADA8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>during the preceding calendar year was provided compensation by the contractor, if such compensation was first provided by the contractor not more than four years after such officer, employee, or member left service in the Department of Defense;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC67A4E8E99544E9EB9527B4D9115D75E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of each person listed under subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H821993BC83124806BC519BACB7A30BBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify the agency in which such person was employed or served on active duty during the last two years of such person’s service with the Department of Defense;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H015858BB7A3A4E7CBD41E093BCEC9F0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>state such person’s job title and identify each major defense system, contract, modification, subcontract, task order, and delivery order in excess of $10,000,000, if any, on which such person performed any work with the Department of Defense during the last two years of such person’s service with the Department; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4067B4459E5F4F209F5BB3AC14EF6A3A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>state such person’s current job title with the contractor and identify each major defense system, contract, modification, subcontract, task order, and delivery order in excess of $10,000,000, on which such person has performed any work on behalf of the contractor; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6163EC1CE7F14CF3A87565209764B8B6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>if the contractor is a client, include—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7E2127598983403F90102B4F4D75CE4C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a statement that—</text> <clause id="HC20496E307C24E1CA3B31B758046A2E5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>lists each specific issue for which the contractor, any employee of the contractor, or any lobbyist paid by the contractor engaged in lobbying activities with the Department of Defense;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCE94065FCC314F3DB554AA0C29BDD28D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>specifies the Federal rule or regulation, Executive order, or other program, policy, contract, or position of the Department of Defense to which the lobbying activities described in clause (i) related;</text></clause> <clause id="HD67C5DCEAA0142F49459FD7942CA5C88"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>lists each lobbying activity relating to the Department of Defense that the contractor, any employee of the contractor, or any lobbyist paid by the contractor has engaged in on behalf of the contractor, including—</text> 
<subclause id="H0CE295B18557424A8CC8F16B5AA086EE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>each document prepared by the contractor, any employee of the contractor, or any lobbyist paid by the contractor that was submitted to an officer or employee of the Department of Defense by the lobbyist;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H840F3316FCDB493B96EBC602251F64CF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>each meeting that was a lobbying contact with an officer or employee of the Department of Defense, including the subject of the meeting, the date of the meeting, and the name and position of each individual who attended the meeting;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HFDF5E76D07B34EA19351A25177D0472E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>each phone call made to an officer or employee of the Department of Defense that was a lobbying contact, including the subject of the phone call, the date of the phone call, and the name and position of each individual who was on the phone call; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HAC7F0F2539D140BB99D1A1BAF072F54A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>each electronic communication (including emails, text messages, and other forms of electronic communication) sent to an officer or employee of the Department of Defense that was a lobbying contact, including the subject of the electronic communication, the date of the electronic communication, and the name and position of each individual who received the electronic communication;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H274E0120BCB6413FA763F0D808D1DDC8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>lists the name of each employee of the contractor who—</text> <subclause id="HE4D43EA8BD9D49999671CD43C934DAE2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>did not participate in a lobbying contact with an officer or employee of the Department of Defense; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0D56A7ADCA65456EAF3B2741BFD2DA2D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>engaged in lobbying activities in support of a lobbying contact with an officer or employee of the Department of Defense; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H0FA4768D69DA4792817DA4AD70F9EA26"><enum>(v)</enum><text>describes the lobbying activities referred to in clause (iv)(II); and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD30FD1588F8941CA840042B9BDA102A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a copy of any document transmitted to an officer or employee of the Department of Defense in the course of the lobbying activities described in subparagraph (A)(iv)(II).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0EBF91EB46D2468889C0C5579B283703"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In subsection (b)(3), the terms <term>client</term>, <term>lobbying activities</term>, <term>lobbying contact</term>, and <term>lobbyist</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 3 of the Lobbying Disclosure Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1602">2 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFE4E5B4D8A7C42658795D13EEF756C8D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section and the amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to contracts entered into on or after that date.</text></subsection> </section> <section id="HF65B9FC464E646AFBC5B763740ECCB5E"><enum>103.</enum><header>Ban on hiring contracting officials enforceable on certain contracts</header> <subsection id="H4992C4E67CE14233AFB5667135D0C891"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header> <paragraph id="H9658A8268FF2492F846EF19BFE629829"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any contract for the procurement of goods or services, other than a contract for the procurement of commercial products or services, with a value of excess of $10,000,000 shall include a contract clause prohibiting the contractor from providing compensation to a former Department of Defense official described in paragraph (2) within four years after such former official leaves service in the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC734D01653BA4A5580713ED53200DD6D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered Department of Defense official</header><text>An official or former official of the Department of Defense is covered by the requirements of this section if such official or former official is a former officer or employee of the Department of Defense or a former or retired member of the Armed Forces who served as a program manager, deputy program manager, procuring contracting officer, administrative contracting officer, source selection authority, member of the source selection evaluation board, or chief of a financial or technical evaluation team or directly managed someone in these roles for a contract with a value in excess of $10,000,000, and such person—</text> <subparagraph id="H83219180E7304FC588C20B34871F8477"><enum>(A)</enum><text>participated in the contract or license selection;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2FDAB443386845FC9F3F155742568444"><enum>(B)</enum><text>determined or signed off on the technical requirements of the contract or license; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE62DE8FF0F1D4375A66C2F92E0F11624"><enum>(C)</enum><text>granted the contract or license.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB4F733C0409F47A0BA2479BAF6C9A6B9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrative actions</header><text>In the event that an official or former official of the Department of Defense described in subsection (a)(2), or a Department of Defense contractor, knowingly fails to comply with the requirements of this subsection, the Secretary of Defense may take any of the administrative actions set forth in section 2105 of title 41, United States Code, that the Secretary of Defense determines to be appropriate.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H317525BB10AA40FA8D5384EC3A310D1D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5A8AAF4E38354D9184DC5552B3624813"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commercial product</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>commercial product</term> means any of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H066ECB5C9BAC49ACB1AA0B6352DB9638"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A product, other than real property, that—</text> 
<clause id="HD2D964C58CEE41C8A61BE7C3C09524B9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is customarily used by the general public or by nongovernmental entities for purposes other than governmental purposes; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC8F2F63604864253AB6E0AF41B6E4A85"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has been sold, leased, or licensed to the general public.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H319B40A30B514B0BA1D27F622A63A1B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A product that—</text> <clause id="HC2E661F375CE4E5B8392585B49912AF4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>evolved from a product described in subparagraph (A) through advances in technology or performance; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDCF1A39642D9449F8D9A9695F1AFC017"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not yet available in the commercial marketplace but will be available in the commercial marketplace in time to satisfy the delivery requirements under a Federal Government solicitation.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H190420D585E6487CA8D8B5823B044535"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A product that would satisfy the criteria in subparagraph (A) or (B) were it not for—</text> 
<clause id="HFB3EE58418854B909CD071357A9976AB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>modifications customarily available in the commercial marketplace; or</text></clause> <clause id="H590DEF5A8C4D4209BF6528FCEC273163"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>minor modifications made to meet Federal Government requirements.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF889D75C17784F658012B083E7B99E1C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any combination of products meeting the requirements of subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) that are customarily combined and sold in combination to the general public.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H895AFC8EAAAA438BAF590BFEAC0B6C10"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A product, or combination of products, referred to in subparagraphs (A) through (D), even though the product, or combination of products, is transferred between or among separate divisions, subsidiaries, or affiliates of a contractor.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H68180AE55C6C4C04940B6853E810832A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A nondevelopmental item if the procuring agency determines, in accordance with conditions in the Federal Acquisition Regulation, that—</text> <clause id="H8893291C692443BDBB54DDB56503486F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the product was developed exclusively at private expense; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB3426C3AB6DD4CA799D8BE7E94B53C35"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has been sold in substantial quantities, on a competitive basis, to multiple State and local governments or to multiple foreign governments. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD5D34E9057F44FF7960C00C2553886AE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commercial service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>commercial service</term> means any of the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE2BD842566C3494DA08B844B88132A58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Installation services, maintenance services, repair services, training services, and other services if—</text> <clause id="H06704C1673E94A74B62B2DB4F64F4E84"><enum>(i)</enum><text>those services are procured for support of a commercial product, regardless of whether the services are provided by the same source or at the same time as the commercial product; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H390D8856D71E49CD8BCF27F355B46C06"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the source of the services provides similar services contemporaneously to the general public under terms and conditions similar to those offered to the Federal Government.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBE046192D4964F0D9B50AD6B791F7B5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Services of a type sold competitively, in substantial quantities, in the commercial marketplace—</text> 
<clause id="H2509091DCA51458FB18DAFDE1E54F778"><enum>(i)</enum><text>based on established catalog or market prices;</text></clause> <clause id="H131F1B70537943499675789BD6D7FE06"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for specific tasks performed or specific outcomes to be achieved; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFC44C29B6F9048C5AF52A05183C6C184"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>under standard commercial terms and conditions.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB3AC07C3AFCE4D0C8B9CA79C5D9CBCA1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A service described in subparagraph (A) or (B), even though the service is transferred between or among separate divisions, subsidiaries, or affiliates of a contractor. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HCC2D3E0B8E474766A16246C752462C51"><enum>104.</enum><header>Ban on hiring senior officials by giant defense contractors</header> 
<subsection id="H3C82C6806A1F40E1A707670647E74B8F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header> 
<paragraph id="HEC7424207A3A4B4BABE1044A34619307"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any Department of Defense contract for the procurement of goods or services with a giant defense contractor shall include a contract clause prohibiting the contractor from hiring or paying (including as a consultant, lobbyist, or lawyer) any covered Department of Defense official within four years after such former official leaves service in the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEDA0876CA5424806BE517172C88FB1B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H70D5852B56174CDEBE15950B4D2491E2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Covered Department of Defense official</header><text>The term <term>covered Department of Defense official</term> means a former officer or employee of the Department of Defense or a former or retired member of the Armed Forces who served—</text> <clause id="HE5ECB4B6497C4170BD8AFF3A7DAD25DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in an Executive Schedule position under subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDBF6475B18BE410580DD349EF8248225"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in a position in the Senior Executive Service under subchapter VIII of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code;</text></clause> <clause id="H11F5C7733E134D44B0DBDA5257886DF7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in a position compensated at a rate of pay for grade O–6 or above under section 201 of title 37, United States Code; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1A9B6FB36B594AB4AA02FE7F1BF437EF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in a supervisory position compensated at a rate of pay for grade GS–15 of the General Schedule under section 5107 of title 5, United States Code, or higher.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H140E224EE5124DB0AE1E6342411016A5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Giant defense contractor</header><text>The term <term>giant defense contractor</term> means a contractor (other than an institution of higher education) that received an average of more than $1,000,000,000 in annual revenue from the Department of Defense or the Department of Energy for contracted work related to the United States nuclear program in the previous three fiscal years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF21DAD74278F4098A05D8B9B6BEB74DC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrative actions</header><text>In the event that a covered Department of Defense official, or a Department of Defense contractor, knowingly fails to comply with the requirements of this section, the Secretary of Defense may take any of the administrative actions set forth in section 2105 of title 41, United States Code, that the Secretary of Defense determines to be appropriate.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3614396D27A842539E5CBB7D88EC49F1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>The Inspector General of the Department of Defense shall submit to the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate and the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives an annual report listing the officials or former officials of the Department of Defense described in subsection (a)(2)(A), or any Department of Defense contractor, subject to any of the administrative actions from the Secretary of Defense under the requirements of subsection (b) during the prior calendar year.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H4D8C2392F3EB4A23B1C5CA14C7F698B3"><enum>105.</enum><header>Modification of prohibition on lobbying activities with respect to the Department of Defense by certain officers of the Armed Forces and civilian employees of the Department of Defense following separation from military service or employment with the Department</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1045 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/91">Public Law 115–91</external-xref>; 131 Stat. 1555) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HEF52F1B6790D4FCEAA944021B86050B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H74E2ACDBD731489EA6CA1DB1B99BD499"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">Two-year prohibition</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">Four-year prohibition</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H91D27A244B084B42B33330DA2F42FA83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>during the two-year period</quote> and inserting <quote>during the four-year period</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCD0226FF32924023AEB4EC77E5FF0169"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A), by striking <quote>grade O–9 or higher</quote> and inserting <quote>grade O–6 or higher</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H08461BD17950438B83FB8D9BF9E610E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsection (b);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE016231757DC4D5AB55B75699BB3BC93"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (b); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7FC8FC0D53114041963F1BDBFF5B6D43"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1)(A), as redesignated by paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>, including activities in support of lobbying contact with an officer or employee of the Department of Defense</quote> before the period at the end.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H794273719D064543B0200B27F3F15251"><enum>106.</enum><header>Enhancement of recusal for conflicts of personal interest requirements for Department of Defense officers and employees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1117 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/81">Public Law 117–81</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/971">10 U.S.C. 971</external-xref> note prec.) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HAFCE36A8C6D7414CA3146E5A001077CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H11FCCABDD114466E9298917E50743E80"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>particular matter</quote> and inserting <quote>covered matter</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD7EF6B638DA84E6BBF910940B6E7DA5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>where any of the following organizations is a party or represents a party to the matter:</quote> and inserting <quote>where any of the following organizations or entities is a party or represents a party to the matter, or where the officer or employee knows, or reasonably should know, the matter is likely to have a direct and predictable effect on the financial interests of any of the following organizations or entities:</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB43F3E5951214DA7877438AB414BA2A7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>2 years</quote> and inserting <quote>4 years</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1AB1CC1C044F49C5B25F309C0BB8D378"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC44AB6313DDB44B4AF329F6E1B206EC0"> 
<paragraph id="HA93D8888EAD7497CAE6784F94347F994"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A former direct competitor or client of any organization for which the officer or employee has served as an employee, officer, director, trustee, or general partner in the past 4 years.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC3D1840606154880A33B2C199B9EB649" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (d); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1CF2E0A2D2A44F24A1D2070521345FA9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after subsection (b) the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H485371CC31FA4A889CE50B92EB6135A4"> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H88F0EFEDFE40432087221B95DC89A623"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered matter defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>covered matter</term>—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD2A0BDDF71D3449F8A4CA7897DD66ABF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>means any matter that involves deliberation, decision, or action that is focused upon the interests of a specific person or a discrete and identifiable class of persons; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA903663E9B79441F8987D73D92B3CCD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes policy making that is narrowly focused on the interests of a discrete and identifiable class of persons.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H5587A40E61E2474DAE16C78DBEC51FBA"><enum>107.</enum><header>Prohibition on ownership or trading of stocks in certain companies by Department of Defense officers and employees</header> 
<subsection id="HFD7A2E3AEC814D8BB93425C0000A6D6D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on ownership and trading publicly traded stocks</header><text>Section 988(a) of title 10, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>if that company is one of the 10 entities awarded the most amount of contract funds by the Department of Defense in a fiscal year during the five preceding fiscal years</quote> and inserting <quote>if, during the preceding calendar year, the company received more than $100,000,000 in revenue from the Department of Defense, including through 1 or more contracts with the Department</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6469C3C815564CDFBCCC94DE7C390423"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition of covered official</header><text>Section 988 of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H06050ADD144548BEA438FB34D0D2719E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating subsection (c) as subsection (d); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2C6AC008BD7B423AA1D4FEA863075543"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1) of subsection (d), as redesignated by paragraph (1) of this section, by striking <quote>means any</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end of subparagraph (B) and inserting <quote>means any official described in section 847(c) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1701">10 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note).</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82540EBDC2C14D178D4B7D684E9E0B9B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 988 of title 10, United States Code, as amended by subsection (b), is further amended by inserting after subsection (b) the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82824DC52E254E719AA179F5354A6515"> <subsection id="HD472824C681C46F496DFBDFC1ED56CAF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Whoever violates subsection (a) shall be subject to the penalties set forth in section 216 of title 18, United States Code.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></title> 
<title id="HE2A9CF017BAE464098CE0B9EEFEB408E"><enum>II</enum><header>Limiting foreign influence</header> 
<section id="HE1DB81BC8AF848CAADB7602942EF1E5D"><enum>201.</enum><header>Ban on senior national security officials advising foreign governments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 207(f) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HA31E729053514E91A9EC3C9E441F95F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (4); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0822C9DE7E74732A7F6E1B175FCA75D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H46D82C296E234710ACBC798B49B23E6F"> <paragraph id="H20E6242EC76645A1A68608D902440B71"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Permanent restriction</header><text>Any person who has been employed as a senior official in the White House, the Department of State, the Department of Defense, or the Department of the Treasury who performs compensated work for the benefit of a foreign entity that stands to benefit from the knowledge obtained by the person as a result of such United States Government employment, shall be punished as provided in section 216 of this title.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HA8B0A28C298F47C1A010E58562011BE9"><enum>202.</enum><header>Ban on former military and civilian intelligence officers from foreign employment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">All military and civilian intelligence personnel employed by a military intelligence organization possessing a security clearance, upon separation from service or resignation, are prohibited from obtaining employment with a foreign government or a private company doing work predominantly on behalf of a foreign government. Any intelligence personnel who performs compensated work for the benefit of a foreign entity that stands to benefit from the knowledge obtained by the person as a result of such United States Government employment, shall be punished as provided in section 216 of title 18, United States Code.</text></section></title> <title id="H54F5839BB8B44A1B99E4D6830E0CB53D"><enum>III</enum><header>Transparency</header> <section id="H268E759349FA4633AC12F37B39E1CC76"><enum>301.</enum><header>Affirmative contractor record disclosures</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall publish on a publicly available internet website the following information to the extent such information is unclassified and non-confidential:</text> 
<paragraph id="H69E181CB994B4F10BB78E6F29CD79619"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of a contract with the Department of Defense for goods or services above the simplified acquisition threshold specified in section 134 of title 41, United States Code, copies of all contracts, subcontracts, purchase orders, delivery orders, task orders, lease agreements, and assignments entered into with the Department of Defense during the previous 3 fiscal years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0589A1B477694AC09C1359AFB0391D5E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the case of a contract with the Department of Defense for goods or services in excess of $10,000,000, all records related to lack of performance, failure to meet contract requirements, and any resulting corrective action plans, cure notices, show cause notices, and non-conformance reports.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6D9C99097159413F89CDBCB9908F3F10"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The contractor report required under section 4705 of title 10, United States Code, as added by section 102 of this Act.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H421365D8D7F5475F8EB60E96BE9306F2"><enum>302.</enum><header>Publication of contractor evaluation ratings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2313(c) of title 41, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFB3D3A092288489D88624FA05AC3B336"> 
<paragraph id="H9FED2C891D0649B583FFF1A59D244472"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Contractor evaluation ratings as provided for at paragraph (b)(4) of section 1503 of part 42 of title 48, Code of Federal Regulations, as of the date of enactment of this paragraph.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H823BA043D2A6436DA66940CAFD03371A"><enum>303.</enum><header>Ownership of information</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Any entity of the Department of Defense that enters into a contract or agreement with, or provides funding to, a nongovernmental entity for the purposes of procuring goods or services shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H72D3C3BA5B8A4FA19E9BB3EDE4E6ED3C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for the purposes of paragraph (3), be deemed to have control over all information of the entity related to—</text> <subparagraph id="HD6A71708CC0F4B6AA4C770E8152D7D05"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any costs or the expenditure of any funds related to the contract or agreement; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H53FFE3433818484AB0461EAAFEEC44DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other information related to the performance of the contract or agreement;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCEF2C8FC5FD94B928569D8F82570E21C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide access to the information described in paragraph (1), which shall be considered an <quote>agency record</quote>, to any person upon request made pursuant to paragraph (3); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8D919395E8F649B78BC849FE526E2456"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include compliance with this subsection as a material term in any contract, agreement, or renewal of a contract or agreement with any nongovernmental entity for the purposes of procuring goods or services.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H18E2FBA9C00E45359B9BC451BAF5D981"><enum>304.</enum><header>Financial disclosure by large contractors</header> <subsection id="HAE57735DBBDD48349E5EB2BB42C95401"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Disclosure requirement</header> <paragraph id="H3810029868B04577950993F43F160EAD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall require a covered contractor, as a condition for entering into a contract with the Department of Defense, to make publicly available on an annual basis the following information (excluding information determined to be classified by the Secretary):</text> 
<subparagraph id="H08769FEC32374DE6B1AD890432D1F199"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Audited financial statements.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF448D314637044409CA53ABCA9D79F5E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A listing of the salaries of employees performing work on the contract that receive compensation from the contractor in excess of $250,000 per year.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H904A4505447C49B6B17E0BB85DFF4A2B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of all Federal political spending, including lobbying, by the contractor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E0D36CE3C8842158ED5D407038E4CEF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Suspension and debarment</header><text>The Secretary of Defense may suspend or debar any covered contractor that fails to comply with the disclosure requirements under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H840C86A8F6574FB29536EC24BC8F9A32"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered contractor defined</header><text>The term <term>covered contractor</term> means a contractor (other than an institute of higher education) that—</text> <subparagraph id="H09D45A25DE2A4A16BBC0F277D78C359C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>received more than $10,000,000 in annual revenue from Federal Government contracts or licenses in any of the previous three fiscal years; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2C426822161D41CAA3362CACD226B08D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>earned more than 20 percent of its total annual revenue from Federal Government contracts or licenses in any of the previous three fiscal years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HE15D5F4F4EAB40D8B1CABCD716BFCF61"><enum>305.</enum><header>Availability on the internet of certain information about officers serving in general or flag officer grades</header> <subsection id="HC2479BD590A4408897E7EE100D579999"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Availability required</header><text>The Secretary of each military department shall make available on a publicly available internet website of such department the information specified in subsection (b) related to each officer in a general or flag officer grade under the jurisdiction of such Secretary, including any such officer on the reserve active-status list.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2264A7F5E99A4A5B8588888C8D8DA556"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information</header><text>The information on an officer referred to in subsection (a) is as follows:</text> <paragraph id="HF612B368FFB54B7AAD1FD361F99DF3AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The officer’s name.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD80710527A974A268BA384253C2C4F78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The officer’s current billet.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50B32DAAAD8248DDA88D048F4B409B98"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A biographical summary of the officer.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB7F64928F3DB47239A8BDA8C1A78FEAF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any financial disclosures made by the officer to or for Department of Defense purposes.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2883C49E13C84904B0E4A7650220468C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any substantiated reports of an Inspector General in the Department of Defense involving conduct of the officer.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA644F214C5C0487B86E0FB06C0A8FC1C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Summaries of any command climate survey conducted with respect to a command of the officer.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1FB6981F6A7F46E8BF58F87B3E8D1A86"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Redaction</header><text>Information made available pursuant to subsection (a) may be redacted in a manner that accords with the provisions of section 552a of title 5, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Privacy Act</quote>). </text></subsection></section></title> 
</legis-body></bill>

