<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H90232123896C4AC7A7C11998E33A00E2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3006 IH: To direct the Secretary of Education to carry out a grant program to support the placement of students and licensed professional social workers in public libraries, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3006</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230428">April 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to carry out a grant program to support the placement of students and licensed professional social workers in public libraries, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6562C8DD8A784FD6A416F17E0052F11E" style="OLC"><section id="H19DE0DB99869408E826C32DFE3177C81" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Grants for placement of students and social workers in public libraries</header><subsection id="H5D6ADF2C09CA4F36A1B9D6159758EB9B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Education (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a program under which the Secretary makes grants, on a competitive basis, to institutions of higher education to support the placement of students and licensed professional social workers in public libraries.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1354036F5B0E473F8D6823262BAE2F43"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="H613AA648841F49668F70D1999A8A3BB7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an institution of higher education shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. As part of such application the institution shall demonstrate that—</text><subparagraph id="HD2EF8209EA8C4674A1C8954C85393C80"><enum>(A)</enum><text>it has established a partnership with each library in which a social worker or intern is expected to be placed pursuant to subsection (d);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5C1F1DB3E914B429089DDCC8843373F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>it has developed a thorough plan, in coordination with each such library, to support such social workers and interns; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE489B873CB864D129FB10FC46823CD40"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each library in which a social worker or intern is expected to be placed pursuant to subsection (d) is in a community with a demonstrated need for social work support and services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H633EBB372C224268A6CFDAC6289ADF69"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting institutions of higher education to receive grants under this section, the Secretary shall give special consideration to institutions that will use the grant to serve communities that are under resourced or have a high level of need for social workers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA1A1AD5834504691A2C214CE57199F26"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall coordinate with the Institute of Museum and Library Services to develop and review grant applications under this section, which shall include the solicitation of feedback from relevant stakeholders in the development of such materials.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3A6408F003AC4ED394127E5A9D1C3B97"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An institution of higher education that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant—</text><paragraph id="H73A633DE26FC457FABC57CC3D2ABD8B6"><enum>(1)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD581D64E75134CB18BE13D0E24C84FDE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to employ one or more licensed professional social workers whom the institution shall seek to place on a full-time basis in public libraries in the geographic region surrounding the institution; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7D09AF0B381407094AC3192E0D1EE13" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to arrange placements of one or more licensed professional social workers who are employed by other entities, whom the institution shall seek to place on a full-time basis in public libraries in the geographic region surrounding the institution; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H159A4A68C57E4C86933A5510F0C68B97"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to arrange and fully fund internships and field placements at such libraries for students of the institution who are majoring in social work, including students pursuing a bachelor’s or master’s degree in social work.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H194FB04396BE42548C0479A99C8788A7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header><paragraph id="H8C3FC68D4C4B43B2817BAAEB0E59FB12"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Duties of institutions</header><text>An institution of higher education that receives a grant under this section shall—</text><subparagraph id="H2631CDE7F2F249418A7847E093784974"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be responsible for the payment and employment-related administration of the social workers placed at public libraries pursuant to subsection (d)(1)(A) and the interns placed at such libraries pursuant to subsection (d)(2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H447D213618BB4E4183F34339E8CB2FAE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>pay a wage of not less than $15 per hour to each intern serving in a public library pursuant to subsection (d)(2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E30E5E6C7A7486DBC90FAC713852C0B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensure that each such intern—</text><clause id="HA01E403533BF4EF08347354861892491"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is supervised by a licensed professional social worker (who may be a social worker employed by the institution or a social worker otherwise employed at the public library at which the intern serves); and</text></clause><clause id="H6C961324CC014D55BF89C40893993505"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">practices within the scope and limitations of a social work intern role as set forth by the accreditation standards of the Council on Social Work Education; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4ABDBC4A25194252B4C20F293040451B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enter into and maintain a partnership with each library at which social workers and interns are placed by the institution to ensure that such social workers and interns are—</text><clause id="HC4D550F6AEBB4EBCA90996A84671E00F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>continuously supported by the library and the institution; and</text></clause><clause id="H76FE8A90DF134DAE8D827DBC2C012E79"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>able to carry out their duties effectively.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6816A1C3F9046AA98F07DF545BCB5D6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties of social workers</header><subparagraph id="HB65F2354106B4A0B987A3EEEDCBBDA9E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The duties of a social worker placed at the public library pursuant to subsection (d)(1) shall be to provide services and support to the library and library patrons to boost the library’s capacity to address the holistic needs of patrons, including—</text><clause id="HDDA0D8AE6B2C4261BEC9A0F7CA3DB471"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information or referrals on health, mental health, nutrition, financial well-being and economic mobility, and other social services for which the patron may be eligible; </text></clause><clause id="H1F8623B5221D49D38CFE934625D77933"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">direct assistance in applying for and accessing such services;</text></clause><clause id="HFFAF56B9BD5D44F0A5E0B57B596DC529"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conducting library staff training on relevant topics within the social workers’ and social work interns’ competence and scope of practice; and</text></clause><clause id="HE4A9FF2C5B1B4DF7B0558F362238125C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other duties as may be determined by local conditions, the institution, and the participating library.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14F486E57CD54D5CBEFC1A2FDF92462F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Code of ethics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A licensed professional social worker or intern placed at the library pursuant to subsection (d) shall be required to adhere to the social work profession’s code of ethics as set forth by the National Association for Social Workers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B12D652996D42F784E715B29537FBF3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A licensed professional social worker or intern placed at a library pursuant to subsection (d)—</text><clause id="HA5E3E961640143EA8778D1A957B14BEB"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not be required to report an alien who is not in lawful immigration status to U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement and may provide such alien with appropriate professional services; and</text></clause><clause id="HC7F80EE3A9C248F886FFD63EEF3EF684" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not be required to provide direct healthcare and mental health services to library patrons, such as the administration of diagnostic medical tests.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H191E8F3FCBB14B50A708372F50077A63" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties of libraries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A library that enters into a partnership with an institution of higher education as described in paragraph (1)(D)—</text><subparagraph id="H6486B116ABFE4E3886DDFA4CE6F4E20C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall—</text><clause id="H50856E7105C54E8EB6B29F977E9ACBAA" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide social workers and interns placed at the library with general support, including access to resources (such as office space, technology, and staff time) to ensure such social workers and interns are able to effectively carry out their responsibilities;</text></clause><clause id="H628773E24B124FFBAABAF6A46D3DC288" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide input regarding the services and programming offered by such social workers and interns; and</text></clause><clause id="HA12A97F66EC844B4B21BB8A29B1E97D3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">adhere to the American Library Association’s code of ethics; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0AF460C183F490FB110B5A4A3B57B6E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may designate members of the library staff to serve as a preceptor or library task supervisor for such interns.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A9816DEB2B1409AA0FE8F616F6A118B" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Supplementary grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the availability of appropriations, an institution of higher education that receives a grant under this section may apply—</text><subparagraph id="H2DFBE33B552C446C8CE5FBEBB138323F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the Secretary for a supplementary grant which, if received by such institution, shall be used in accordance with the requirements of this section; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7FC0296FEAC4C02B6394C601FDB4F56"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the Secretary for additional funds to support the maintenance of a program or department established though the program under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H55D98BE0777F49A186A7C229ED04321F"><enum>2.</enum><header>National technical assistance center</header><subsection id="H74C14883B4A1457C8C36951860CD01E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary Education, in coordination with the Director of the Institute of Museum and Library Services and through the solicitation of feedback from relevant stakeholders, shall establish an evaluation, documentation, dissemination, and technical assistance resource center to provide appropriate information, training, and technical assistance to States, political subdivisions of States, federally recognized Indian Tribes, tribal organizations, institutions of higher education, State and local educational agencies, and individual students and educators with respect to—</text><paragraph id="H19CE896B6D68424B84EF34F1CDB3F683"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hiring and retaining social workers in libraries; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BAC3477EC7C490B834317E728572DA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>carrying out programs to facilitate the placement of social workers in libraries on a temporary or permanent basis.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD232871E0324BB69937D331DE9C3BC9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities of the center</header><text>The center established under subsection (a) shall conduct activities for the purpose of—</text><paragraph id="HF53C79B7603A4B0E963468E40FB36BAD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing and continuing statewide or tribal strategies for improving the effectiveness of the social work and library workforce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA8749FEDC8C419AB8CCCB93CA5F9B3C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>studying the costs and effectiveness of library social work programs at institutions of higher education to identify areas of improvement and provide information on relevant issues of importance to State, Tribal, and national policymakers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AEBC5CADE5540A08671E997D61A01B6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">working with Federal agencies and other State, Tribal, and national stakeholders to collect, evaluate, and disseminate data regarding social work ratios, outcomes and best practices of services provided, and the impact of expanding the number of social workers within libraries; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8454C8FEFAE4533B71C290E3CFA1ED7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing partnerships among National, State, Tribal, and local governments, and local educational agencies, institutions of higher education, libraries, nonprofit organizations, and State and national trade associations for the purposes of—</text><subparagraph id="HBC561992420B41518AEC87C0F567CB80"><enum>(A)</enum><text>data collection and dissemination;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD88F636CA29463189BD14FFBDF1CBD8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing a library social work workforce development program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H772BE90A3A654A76B48FF7DED9ED5370"><enum>(C)</enum><text>documenting the success of library social work methods on a national level; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6C579F753E049DC92E9A7FEE8E9944B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>conducting other activities as determined appropriate by the Secretary of Education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB6A3F39A9EF642A4A14424B7035532F3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HD97CBD85B2104A2EAC4F6A482CC8C570"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given that term in section 202 of the Museum and Library Services Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9101">20 U.S.C. 9101</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84E56FFFA1C6435C848D084F8E8480E7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> means an institution of higher education (as defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)) acting through a school of social work within the institution that is accredited by the Council on Social Work Education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70642DB794854277901C52CD3B4D0588"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>library</term> has the meaning given that term in section 213 of the Library Services and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9122">20 U.S.C. 9122</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05D860BB263F4B8694899A9E63C6F05E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>licensed professional social worker</term> means a social worker who has a master’s or doctoral degree in social work.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

