<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE99FF8A94BE24CBC846D716EDA328D30" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6518 IH: Workforce Data for Analyzing and Tracking Automation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6518</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231130">November 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Labor to take initiatives to measure the impact of automation on the workforce in order to inform workforce development strategies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAEC45A000DF74C96BAE5354F68EB37F7" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HE18132C825314891AE7402D17CBB92D1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Workforce Data for Analyzing and Tracking Automation Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Workforce DATA Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBDB9FF57FAFF440A817DC4C1568510AA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HE9412E8409DC4E0A8D190915340E3A8A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Automation</header><text>The term <term>automation</term> means using technology to produce a good or service previously produced by human work.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FA6D57C873643AB831A11CC12E89FB6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Board; subcommittee</header><text>The term <term>Board</term> or <term>Subcommittee</term> means the advisory board or subcommittee established or formed under section 4(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21A046043F634AA3A953E1D0450E0AEC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H681B04325DF24343AA00219318E402C3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine on measuring the impact of automation on the workforce</header><subsection id="H8176FFBF8831448A8CECB138C83243A9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall request the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine to enter into an arrangement with the Secretary for the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine to conduct a consensus study on how to measure the impact of automation on the workforce, including job creation, job displacement, job retention, and the shifting of skills in demand due to automation.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC810E3E9F51B4D8CB1BF052393EF84EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The study under subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="HBE9383883E5440F4AE08452BA552C174"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include a review of workforce data programs used by the Bureau of Labor Statistics, as of the date of enactment of this Act, for measuring the impact of automation on the workforce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA0FBB5A5B364619AA0819192D50CDBC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify and review other potential data sources for measuring such impact;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H780212F7E8D84C1DB8A0D8075A5B5958"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify appropriate statistical methods for using and integrating other data sources to supplement or enhance the workforce data programs described in paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8275FC7143145BC8FD85675C7EEBEBD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>advise the Bureau of Labor Statistics on research needed to acquire, evaluate, and incorporate additional data sources to adequately measure and assess, on an ongoing basis—</text><subparagraph id="HF29903FBCA7E457EAE1E292B3B30EE05"><enum>(A)</enum><text>industry sectors and occupations significantly impacted by automation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9189F0E6309943A7A8BC890A8F9E3DBD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>jobs and occupations created or substantially changed as a result of automation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BB6B3618C61416F88BE4398B9E40EC9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>occupational shifts in labor demand, including the number of workers displaced (or with a change in earnings) due to automation, and the demographics of such workers, such as the race, gender, age, level of education, location, employment status, and earnings of such workers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H593D04A4CA4F42068FA0FCB4DF885AD0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the consequences of displacement due to automation, including the consequences of workers becoming subsequently unemployed, exiting from the workforce, entering retraining, changing positions within a company, and experiencing a change in earnings;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H608303FAF6714BDEB21895DC25EB7107"><enum>(E)</enum><text>changes to workforce skills in demand as a result of automation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9172D5057DC433AB5A24A793CDD2880"><enum>(F)</enum><text>additional data recommended by the Board or Subcommittee under section 4(c)(1)(A)(iii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7FE15495F55844618D8649A6C3D08041"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress, and make publicly available, a report on the results of the study under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H14601DD552034B8F91CA25785B2C18A5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Plan for Bureau of Labor Statistics</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Secretary submits the report to Congress under subsection (c), the Secretary shall make publicly available a plan for how the Bureau of Labor Statistics shall respond to the findings of the study contained in such report.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1D8E7A53A26D4D559F32F0463FB9F248"><enum>4.</enum><header>Input on impact of automation from workforce advisory board or subcommittee</header><subsection id="HF40EA6E07CDE4EC3A9DF5F876464FD45"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an advisory board, or form a subcommittee of an advisory board that exists on the date of enactment of this Act, to provide recommendations on addressing the impact of automation on the workforce.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC1B3691B010E4C17841C970ED41A40C1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Board or Subcommittee shall consist of nationally representative members, including the balanced participation of—</text><paragraph id="H96CC13662CC64314B1CF68713D8F214C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>State boards, as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67F3E9E447EC4220891783343F36F3CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>labor organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70CADFB4DB384DE3AF668AF1F512467E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>industry representatives;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF97C882C46B743FB8CBE315818584928"><enum>(4)</enum><text>nonprofit entities, or community-based organizations, with experience researching the impact of automation on the workforce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H496F40700B6B45FEA7B4C5ED3F6BE1AE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>academic experts in the field of workforce development, labor economics, and program evaluation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F4123B3CBE142CC946F5276AA1BC1D7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any other stakeholders the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H18B0C635E05E4786BF0B5A30065196B9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><paragraph id="H20B39E5FD8574E10BF22EA19F74CD8D5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recommendations for additional data</header><subparagraph id="H772E320DF52E4A0DB2FF9D80D128A2DC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial evaluation</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Board or Subcommittee shall—</text><clause id="HA87724869E9D49D29C195FDB6D74C60F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify additional types of data related to the impact of automation on the workforce that would inform actions of business and labor stakeholders;</text></clause><clause id="H14C7096059844348A50BBC534BA5335D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify administrative data needed to guide policy formation related to easing impacts of automation; and</text></clause><clause id="H164857FDDADE4CE693DDFB2B3D1BF745"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for purposes of the assessment under section 3(b)(4), provide recommendations to the Secretary and the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine based on the additional data identified under clauses (i) and (ii).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B8BD41CBC934590BD9BFF26D1CDCD87"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Annual updates</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the recommendations are provided under subparagraph (A), and each year thereafter, the Board or Subcommittee shall evaluate the additional data identified under such subparagraph, and provide updated recommendations to the Secretary based on such evaluation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8589B522EF7420EB061C08DBB56252B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recommendations based on Bureau of Labor Statistics measurements</header><subparagraph id="HFC102A6560AA4F7E97899E85858015A8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act, and each year thereafter, the Board or Subcommittee shall—</text><clause id="H2DA80E65ADB645009D3624A2EF04DA5A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>evaluate strategies for workforce development, based on measurements of impact on the workforce due to automation determined by the Bureau of Labor Statistics and on other relevant evidence; and</text></clause><clause id="HE58A84C5E02645FC88DB7A0CA7D7D48B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide recommendations to the Secretary and to Congress based on such evaluation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H400A19E80AF64CB08F64A518E92D85D6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Public access</header><text>The Secretary shall disseminate the strategies recommended under subparagraph (A) to relevant stakeholders and make such strategies available to the public.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD3E3738641404B09A979562B3ED6863C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of Federal Advisory Committee Act</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">Chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the Board or Subcommittee.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

