<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H187AD3EF6EDF43ADB017BA4BF5BE11E8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4461 IH: Modernizing Department of Veterans Affairs Disability Benefit Questionnaires Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4461</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230703">July 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000603">Mr. Luttrell</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to make certain improvements relating to the transmission of disability benefits questionnaire data to the Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC0023F51905F43978F204DE133FBC389" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCDC9DF44A9634819B83A39B713B44B20" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Modernizing Department of Veterans Affairs Disability Benefit Questionnaires Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H80B0BEADF14D42E6891E5A7CE39836E8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modernization of Department of Veterans Affairs disability benefit questionnaires</header> <subsection id="H1F936C3A9E5042C997BEE36C5CD296E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement for transmission of certain information in machine-Readable format</header> <paragraph id="H737D197995644043A66F02F7B443D16A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall require all disability benefit questionnaire data collected in the course of medical disability examinations made by persons other than employees of the Department of Veterans Affairs under section 504 of the Veterans Benefits Improvement Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/275">Public Law 104–275</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/5101">38 U.S.C. 5101</external-xref> note) to be transmitted to the Department in a machine-readable format.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H10376623029541C6997167B3C4EB43E5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Issuance of standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall issue standards for the transmission of disability benefit questionnaire data in a machine-readable format as required under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB94ECB975FD5409CBA730733A24ED4AA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Updates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making updates to disability benefit questionnaires after the date specified in paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H87B1CD711AB34CC0B4E9106BA9666DAD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that the updates are made in a manner that allows for the data collected under the questionnaires to be in a machine-readable format as of the date on which the update goes into effect; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF466CFA88492402984379C564E6A7936"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 60 days before an update goes into effect, notify the persons conducting medical disability examinations (or the entities employing such persons) described in such paragraph of such updates.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFFDDA0A07D994470836CB4D83AB88032"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Plan for information technology system modification</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a plan to modify the information technology systems and processes of the Department to enable a non-Department health care professional selected by a claimant to transmit to the Department, in a machine-readable format, disability benefit questionnaire data, including complete disability benefit questionnaires rather than partial questionnaires or individual elements of medical evidence.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF140657601B44246B533B31F6A6F55BE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public availability of information</header><text>The Secretary shall make publicly available on the internet website of the Department referred to in section 5101(d) of title 38, United States Code—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2AEAD0CF47F84AB09CF880D7FEAC38DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the standards issued under subsection (a)(2); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H537582B3FE3F4778B9925E67A948D416"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the plan required under subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEB97EA9DEA6F41E4B3367DC337BDCAB2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H11C3D587D652473F92D3935982F0AEAC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>claimant</term> has the meaning given such term in section 5100 of title 38, United States Code. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H824F9FCC1B9A49DC9A036D65D4164DAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>machine-readable</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3502(18) of title 44, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

