<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD1C6E8B95D88408190C21274140C1229" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5285 IH: Staff Safety Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5285</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230825">August 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001116">Mr. Clyde</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 40, United States Code, to clarify that the regulations prescribed by the Capitol Police Board to carry out the law prohibiting the possession of firearms in the United States Capitol Buildings and on the United States Capitol Grounds must take into account the exemption provided under such law for Members, officers, and employees of Congress.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HACD94F700CED4617BB3E93657CD22779" style="OLC"><section id="H749C83E0924B4D4A9E89FF3B17C6E2AF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Staff Safety Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HAD8A8C240F76412ABED4D545A27D81AE" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HD051E46FB7794A799C63646DAFF1D45B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5104 of title 40, United States Code, exempts Members of Congress, employees of Members of Congress, officers and employees of committees of Congress, and any other officers or employees of either House of Congress from regulations pertaining to the carrying and possession of firearms on the United States Capitol Grounds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3AE42456B2E4FE5B8278074C140069C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Supreme court in District of Columbia v. Heller held that the Second Amendment protects the individual right to possess a firearm unconnected with service in a militia, and the use of arms for traditionally lawful purposes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB66A96826EF4116982C7AC2850E337C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Justice Clarence Thomas, in the majority opinion for New York State Rifle &amp; Pistol Association Inc. v. Bruen, affirms that the Second Amendment extends to carrying firearms outside of ones home, writing <quote>Nothing in the Second Amendment’s text draws a home/public distinction with respect to the right to keep and bear arms, and the definition of <quote>bear</quote> naturally encompasses public carry. Moreover, the Second Amendment guarantees an <quote>individual right to possess and carry weapons in case of confrontation</quote>, and confrontation can surely take place outside the home.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA5FBFAC8D8740BDA2B049806F247E22"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Current regulations found in the Traffic Regulations for the United States Capitol Grounds promulgated by the Capitol Police Board (in Appendix J) which prevent staff from carrying firearms on the United States Capitol Grounds violate both Federal law and the Constitution.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF8495D6AD5C54268ACC931F42C45F1CF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Clarification of applicability of exemption of Members, officers, and employees of Congress from laws prohibiting possession of firearms in Capitol and on Capitol Grounds to regulations of Capitol Police Board</header><subsection id="H64A596C8AF0C44D88C7E1FD3C961C8A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Applicability of exemption to regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5104(e)(3) of title 40, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>This subsection does not prohibit</quote> and inserting <quote>This subsection does not prohibit, and the regulations prescribed by the Capitol Police Board under paragraph (1)(A) shall not prohibit,</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H49C90B92E17E412D995B6DCFFD128532"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Revision of existing regulations</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Capitol Police Board shall revise any regulations prescribed under section 5104(e)(1)(A) of title 40, United States Code, to ensure that the regulations are consistent with section 5104(e)(3) of such title.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

