<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H82ECBFE4E3944A08AC9932A1BFC4269B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5633 IH: Veteran Suicide Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5633</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to conduct a review of the deaths of certain veterans who died by suicide, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H823AAC7605EE4DC7822CA1F7AF56DB04" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HCE3A5BAD655E4D08B6D75DF37EF3740E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veteran Suicide Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD68D51CAF5EA465F8CBB2E617627AAF3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs review of certain veterans’ deaths by suicide</header> <subsection id="HC95FB5C54DB84C54A92D74357178BE37"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall complete a review of the deaths of all covered veterans who died by suicide during the five-year period preceding the date of the enactment of this Act. Such review shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2FD6C0C104E8425CA98B32F08CFC0037"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number of veterans who died by suicide during the five-year period preceding the date of the enactment of this Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H107F45E41E504DF08A829CC4DCCBFB98"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a summary of such veterans that includes the age, gender, and race of such veterans;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5E6940E50ED446CBBA37330501D2A668"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a comprehensive list of the medications prescribed to, and found in the systems of, such veterans at the time of their deaths, specifically listing any medications that carried a black box warning, were off-label, psychotropic, or carried warnings that included suicidal ideation;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H09BC60D378B54F2F84D7B28E93C439F1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a summary of medical diagnoses by Department of Veterans Affairs physicians which led to the prescribing of the medications referred to in paragraph (3);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H90866D44BC7642ACAC922BEAE56AA465"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the number of instances in which the veteran who died by suicide was concurrently on multiple medications prescribed by Department of Veterans Affairs physicians;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99FF1A6FF36F46A4975FB44D4CE04EFA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the percentage of veterans who died by suicide who were not taking any medication prescribed by a Department of Veterans Affairs physician;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H015F54D502B64FE7875D4694F5A32DBD"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the percentage of veterans referred to in paragraph (1) with combat experience or trauma (including, but not limited to military sexual trauma, traumatic brain injury, and post-traumatic stress);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA18703ABAD01487984036A1D4205059B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Veteran Health Administration facilities with markedly high prescription and suicide rates of patients being treated at those facilities;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8B9EC3FB6C31470BBF598B10D3F3E75C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>a description of Department of Veterans Affairs policies governing the prescribing of medications referred to in paragraph (3);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD5F4530854D74EDEBCDC7CFDA04A0B40"><enum>(10)</enum><text>any patterns apparent to the Secretary based on the review; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDE22425CF57D4B56B5EDF0FF284149A7"><enum>(11)</enum><text>recommendations for further action that would improve the safety and well-being of veterans.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBBDF80B3AACA43CDB62618CFB3C5DE53"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the completion of the review required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDC26C9B672DE466EA7441D7C5D850DCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit to Congress a report on the results of the review; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H594600D0C65F40F1A573F07F120FA634"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make such report publicly available.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H45B41D3A3AE54AA7B84B8F4253B51ECB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered veteran</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H72F034925BFA4414B348FD605F50CB26"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>covered veteran</term> means any veteran who received hospital care or medical services furnished by the Department of Veterans Affairs during the five-year period preceding the death of the veteran.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2BBAF7CC60D2447C9EBF8FAB1D86BC0A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>black box warning</term> means a warning displayed within a box in the prescribing information for drugs that have special problems, particularly ones that may lead to death or serious injury.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

