<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC84805A4CD6B44A09ABD9944C6963601" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3550 IH: Safe Interactions Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3550</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide grants to enable nonprofit disability organizations to develop training programs that support safe interactions between law enforcement officers and individuals with disabilities and older individuals.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0EAF1A215D3E43D994389804FEBD32E5" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HEC12D421A750435288A536708631871D"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safe Interactions Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF8E69B180AD0400F86F6F71196AB825B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H98D8C3548BA74D47BBA190D072AD592E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Individuals with disabilities are 2.5 times more likely to be victims of violent crime.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1D795A46020A4E04A77617B42C4CFEFC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Individuals with disabilities are 3 times more likely to be victims of a serious crime.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1C8A48FCD4E14AB283A96DBA6847D2BD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Individuals with disabilities make up between one-third and one-half of all individuals killed by law enforcement officers.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H33DB80CF07C944E6B777F1CD7AE8563D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The purposes of this Act are to—</text>
<paragraph id="H7975BD0F0DB34ED6B432FA94E8AD16D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">authorize the Secretary to award competitive grants to nonprofit disability organizations to administer enhanced training programs to law enforcement officers who may encounter or provide services to covered individuals, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H79CD74FE96CB4490AF5206698DB2E318"><enum>(A)</enum><text>individuals with mental health disabilities, including schizophrenia;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB3398D91B5334D0AADABDC4280D58FD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>individuals who are deaf, deaf-blind, hard of hearing, or blind, are autistic, or have other intellectual or developmental disabilities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1F5ACBD269D840CFAA1A23080EA4D35A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>older individuals with dementia or other cognitive impairments; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HED47CE4CBDB543068BC84AFEB83246F8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>individuals with any other disability or chronic health condition;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9E2FD45EDF9D47DFBC267B7587C49F78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support, not replace, other specialized law enforcement officer training; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4CC1D9386F8D4B2383900E6DDE1E7CEF"><enum>(3)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H36D45C453AFF4A90B958ACCC366EA99B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the awareness, knowledge, and understanding of law enforcement officers about covered individuals and their unique needs and applicable Federal civil rights laws;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H34CC04F7961E4145A640FA2C08894D50" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce incidences of violence between law enforcement officers and covered individuals; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph indent="up1" id="H22F36F6C3D4948FD9C7652D26B2A2586"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expand the knowledge of law enforcement officers, in areas such as the signs of disabilities, identifying people with disabilities, communicating with people with disabilities, and effective ways to approach covered individuals to minimize situations of risk to—</text> <clause id="HF254BC099B5540008DC5A22A1B1FE0ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">those individuals; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H189A5E773E804FCB821D2F011505BC18"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the law enforcement officers who intervene or provide services to those individuals; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" id="HE58258C6A7964024A7703EEE05465A36"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increase the knowledge of law enforcement officers of community resources available for covered individuals to ultimately limit interactions with law enforcement officers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="HA823AD3103DF46959D9C2151D63675E9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H2F8FC0BE0ADB4CF5BAC6BF206B54075B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered grant</header><text>The term <term>covered grant</term> means a grant awarded under section 5(a).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBEF289E1C17F4B0E886897C8795BBFC6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered individual</header><text>The term <term>covered individual</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H782FA30E0C9D4E7EA51BE7CD1A49D6D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an older individual; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H95E29011115043199CAD38B9B64C735C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an individual with a disability.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D54971BC98B48B495F2C0093552FDB1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a nonprofit disability organization that has formed a partnership with a law enforcement agency or a consortium of law enforcement agencies to administer enhanced training programs to law enforcement officers of the agency or agencies on how to interact with covered individuals.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H12457D91419D4979B28487C00EC53D7E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1276491B2E974148A6759B236F2FBE25"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Individual with a disability</header><text>The term <term>individual with a disability</term> means any individual who has a disability, as defined in section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12102">42 U.S.C. 12102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2E2A0287428A4AE4B9598DA885B0BB0D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Initial training program</header><text>The term <term>initial training program</term> means a mandatory training program offered to new law enforcement officers during their orientation under section 5(d)(1)(A).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF47FB59B85F6462690F93522EAEE7E89"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Law enforcement officer</header><text>The term <term>law enforcement officer</term> means any officer, agent, or employee of a State, political subdivision of a State, or Indian Tribe—</text>
<subparagraph id="H822F938A7C3F4F239DF170FBEFCDF523"><enum>(A)</enum><text>authorized by law or by a government agency to engage in or supervise the prevention, detection, or investigation of any violation of criminal law; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA4F54BC64DF14FE9A36D2736E833CFD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>authorized by law to supervise sentenced criminal offenders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H013E7ABF901141BF8EFD4CA06CE023AE"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Nonprofit disability organization</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit disability organization</term> means a nonprofit organization—</text> <subparagraph id="HB0098D040716469CAA7E8CD6C6F6EBC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that serves covered individuals; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H5E37284E89D24638A0D00C35161CFE8F"><enum>(B)</enum>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H93FB4E08BBF94A0E993EFE50D2427B17"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is operated by a board of which the majority of members are covered individuals;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" indent="up1" id="H6A5E7FD49C29404D8A55353EF80B3615"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that has an advisory panel of which the majority of members are covered individuals; or</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H72B16664430E45329CBF04CBA61884E5" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the majority of the employees of which are covered individuals.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA3BD063050E544E9ACD9861526549BD1"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Older individual</header><text>The term <term>older individual</term> has the meaning given the term in section 102 of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3002">42 U.S.C. 3002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCD9B67203CC744DC9B892902B365AA6E"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Partner academy</header><text>The term <term>partner academy</term>, with respect to an eligible entity that receives a covered grant, means a law enforcement training academy with which the eligible entity partners to administer an initial training program, as described in section 5(b)(1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5615CC08A4E640AF83BD546B780DD29C"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Partner agency</header><text>The term <term>partner agency</term>, with respect to an eligible entity that receives a covered grant, means the law enforcement agency with which the eligible entity partners, or that is a member of a consortium with which the eligible entity partners, to administer enhanced training programs to law enforcement officers of the agency on how to interact with covered individuals.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD8B4AC4DC22E4AC38CCF8219749FB7F5"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Refresher training program</header><text>The term <term>refresher training program</term> means a training program offered to existing law enforcement officers under section 5(d)(1)(B).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF5C6118889042ECB3A2928DC9FA0B6A"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services. </text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H5F101759EE8E48159EF46EC40D1DF4B5"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grant program</header>
<subsection id="H4854A2A72A384B558F432820939783CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award competitive grants to nonprofit disability organizations to administer enhanced training programs to law enforcement officers who may encounter or provide services to covered individuals.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFBAE6AF8EE374207B29217948D3D139C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible entity seeking a covered grant shall submit to the Secretary an application that—</text>
<paragraph id="HDA068E02C57B4C358129A7074236107D"><enum>(1)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE4A82C6526214437A6A883B24D656DE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifies a law enforcement training academy with which the eligible entity will partner to administer an initial training program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H69F6F1668833499B80FB6A07F9B37298" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a memorandum of understanding entered into between the eligible entity and the law enforcement training academy;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H160EBF290AC94201A850A3977C900168"><enum>(2)</enum><text>describes the training program curriculum, which shall include training on how to interact with, identify, approach, and communicate with covered individuals that is provided, as of the date of submission of the application—</text> <subparagraph id="H0AE1660F3003414BBC966A8750C724EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by the partner academy to new law enforcement officers; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBABA4602D49946D4946CF834418F940A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by any partner agency to existing law enforcement officers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1CBB16632981499A80B1E7BCF0A213CC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>describes the learning objectives of the training programs that the eligible entity will administer using the grant;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE093C8F0C3C9479C8B2B39C5F9ACD11C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>describes the activities that will be carried out under the grant;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF217C8C152144ADB948737F71FB519CD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>includes a timeline of the activities described in paragraph (4); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD7F7CE37612E4195A7DDE2955A22D8EC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>demonstrates expertise in training related to covered individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAEFEA884878841C69C9A8F2000659B30"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text>In awarding covered grants, the Secretary shall ensure—</text>
<paragraph id="HDC081A7B2F8A4FCE852E32FAF474AF28"><enum>(1)</enum><text>geographic diversity of grant recipients, including grant recipients that serve rural localities; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAC2DA01F185E414986111D7B9C39B786"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that the training funded by the grant is provided to multiple levels of law enforcement agencies, including local, county, State, and Tribal agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF665ADDF2F1F4172B2B568508D69C6D4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header>
<paragraph id="H136CC51D222C47F9AFD9832316A2820C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mandatory uses</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a covered grant shall use the grant funds to—</text> <subparagraph id="HC2140F72285E41439DEC8B945ABF1D60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>modify the training provided by the partner academy to new law enforcement officers of each partner agency so that the academy provides not fewer than 8 hours of training on topics such as how to interact with, identify, approach, and communicate with covered individuals and applicable Federal civil rights laws, including not fewer than 4 hours of interactive learning taught by covered individuals; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5540575436A543EEB150AEDC97417D2B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop and implement an enhanced training program for existing law enforcement officers of each partner agency on safe, effective, and respectful interactions with covered individuals—</text> <clause id="H519AA0CB72324FF9B9035B145D402F18"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that includes—</text>
<subclause id="HDB568034DC8640488282DBEA5DE579AF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>awareness of and education about covered individuals, including—</text> <item id="H3D6AD1E1FF7849A0A7109BF3E80148BB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>individuals with mental health disabilities, including schizophrenia;</text></item>
<item id="H2D88B8A754BE4ECBA3466ED55CE26495"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>individuals who are deaf, deaf-blind, hard of hearing, or blind, are autistic, or have other intellectual or developmental disabilities;</text></item> <item id="HB69790192664438893B043BB2A8CF39B"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>older individuals with dementia or other cognitive impairments; and</text></item>
<item id="H66E04A836569450DBFC116368563A4A0"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>individuals with any other disability or chronic health condition;</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H616C0D09ACC742F1BD3E365E17AC96B3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>escalation avoidance and de-escalation techniques to be used when interacting with covered individuals, including procedures a law enforcement officer should follow to ensure the health and safety of a covered individual; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HB6DCFC8EDF644D6BAC80C4F57251615C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>communication strategies to be used when interacting with covered individuals, including individuals who do not use speech to communicate;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H61E11CD62E504A7896D0B7F0AEF774C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that utilizes—</text>
<subclause id="HFD2D88A3D7714EDC9F490E688C587754"><enum>(I)</enum><text>instructors who are covered individuals; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0F41BEFFE6BF49CCAB1AE8BC137FB3A2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>guest instructors or speakers who are covered individuals; and</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H8C5A8DFB4E73462CBF980AF26D6B9A71"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in which each law enforcement officer participates not less frequently than 4 hours every year.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD4C5F097EF8141F8AF2411236AA3F288"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Optional uses</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a covered grant may use the grant funds to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7154074D9ED147E08C82F1FCDBA0E565"><enum>(A)</enum><text>expand an existing training program regarding topics such as interacting with, identifying, approaching, and communicating with covered individuals that was provided to law enforcement officers by a nonprofit disability organization in conjunction with the partner academy or a partner agency before the eligible entity received the grant;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBEAE14760B454CC3B2AD0EED2578399F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reimburse staff members of the eligible entity for mileage and travel time expended to attend an initial training program or refresher training program occurring in person or online;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H23FCCC81EF964B0BA2698258C15D75D8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>develop a model of training that utilizes volunteer instructors, except that the eligible entity shall pay any instructor, including a guest instructor, who is a covered individual; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H29A727720B7F4AFA8AFEFEAE2EA09296"><enum>(D)</enum><text>acquire a computer system or software needed for the training programs; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9AF440E2B94741F6B086C694EC440FEF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>support the paid participation of individuals with disabilities and their family members as advisors. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCE19776E352A471FADFBF6778FBABDD3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a covered grant shall use the grant funds to supplement, and not supplant, any funds that would, in the absence of the grant funds, be made available from a State, political subdivision of a State, or Indian Tribe for the activities described in subsection (d).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H893C3D2B4AC74B828AA0F6DB7ECB7F41"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Advisory council</header>
<paragraph id="H45D1E2FDE33745259B80E3EF04623593"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a covered grant shall establish an advisory council composed of 15 members to advise the eligible entity on activities carried out using the grant.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0AFABED6A0884B219D3022A9C481F967"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>An advisory council established under paragraph (1) shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD96FEC23B08C4D84A8420A0FF9062240"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be composed of—</text> <clause id="H2BF3F99C00C24BE1A433370279EB39E6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>1 representative of the eligible entity who is a covered individual and shall serve as chair of the advisory council;</text></clause>
<clause id="H8B1F3708E50F4CE8BAA26CE9D52A3274"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 representative of the State law enforcement training academy or law enforcement agency for the State that the eligible entity serves, who shall serve as vice chair of the advisory council;</text></clause> <clause id="H3FB2C44B93C74B318E6DDEF3FBC66AF7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>3 representatives of community-based organizations that support individuals with disabilities, not fewer than 2 of whom have a disability;</text></clause>
<clause id="HC09F8855973F45C3BB3D389D1D91C39A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>2 representatives of community-based organizations that support older adults;</text></clause> <clause id="HD823F975E1F443249A3D693046F84CC5"><enum>(v)</enum><text>2 State officials or their designees;</text></clause>
<clause id="H97028AB2161046798965FDCF6C776B5A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>1 representative of an organization providing victim services;</text></clause> <clause id="HC86C7F6ABB3B484381ABD776B1BC557F"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>1 representative of a State public safety agency; </text></clause>
<clause id="H67C2AFAEA04140C3B76D41D4D50AD03A"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>3 members of the public with knowledge of individuals with disabilities and older adults with cognitive impairment, including not fewer than 2 self-advocates or family members of a covered individual; and</text></clause> <clause id="H92BA1A13EE7741F1B011908BDA9D1A1C"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>1 active local or State law enforcement officer representing a labor or representative organization; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H631A6BE257A64E1ABF909260AFF1A480"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include a majority of representation from racial and ethnic minority communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4669C094D1534C5C9758BA6575041802"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>An advisory council established under paragraph (1) shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H2D93B551C58049FD8848D61175DB0467"><enum>(A)</enum><text>advise the eligible entity and provide general oversight of grant activities carried out by the eligible entity, including development of the training curriculum and implementation of the training programs; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9FA377D374794EE1813A3F2DCFF5AF0C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide the advisory council with recommendations for the sustainability and expansion of the training programs, such as the development of a train-the-trainer model.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0ECAD5F3B4B543ACB1AFDC16F5E2FCA8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Annual report</header>
<paragraph id="HF11074C1607E4C1489FD24B4BED318FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report to Secretary by eligible entities</header><text>Not later than 1 year after receiving a covered grant, and each year thereafter for the duration of the grant period, an eligible entity that receives a covered grant shall submit the following information to the Secretary with respect to the preceding year:</text> <subparagraph id="H94E39F73E8E4459997D3D8330E806FA1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The number of individuals who benefitted from the training programs provided by the eligible entity using grant funds, including—</text>
<clause id="H07C03F7D24B949EDBB416FA8ACCC70CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of individuals who were trained through the training programs, including the total number of new law enforcement officers who participated in the initial training program and existing law enforcement officers who participated in the refresher training program; and</text></clause> <clause id="H31A655BF3C7E449F9D0C43943AAE3B4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the estimated number of individuals who were impacted by the training programs.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H22D502B2821648499127A0DBF9614453"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Demographic data, including age, sex, and race, for the law enforcement officers who received the training.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H499FDAD5BCD242D790FC5F1D6E54DDFD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The number of partner agencies that participated in the training programs.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF60120EA50E44DA2A6B8EB8200FA2007"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Each partner law enforcement agency, including the city and State in which the headquarters and each local office of the agency are located, and the result of that partnership.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H78E5D15378AE4D9A84329EA22887E6C9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Any recommendations for improving the grant program carried out under this Act. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3E3CE06168524BB1A770EF431556725A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress and the Attorney General by the Secretary</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, and each year thereafter, the Secretary shall submit a report on the grant program carried out under this Act, with respect to the preceding year, to—</text> <subparagraph id="HB4FCF1B33AD144CAA366FBA8A463BBF3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Attorney General;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE87A10D417194A7DB5AB3FACBDC6D092"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE7748F1AC19B4951A6B09A5ACAD3F779"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBF01ED208EAB4C7286FD2639D01BB5E1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Special Committee on Aging of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFEA3CD5033D0443E9083D3B0007191E3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1C34FD46C0EB47B39F632950567B4C77"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC7429027630F4505B9EBB1FB85D21768"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Evaluation</header> <paragraph id="HEFC1560824A34698A424825D2669DC0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall use not more than 2 percent of the amounts made available under section 6 for administrative purposes and for an evaluation of the grant program carried out under this Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8B73FFF8DF3349A8B069011A8B1C6EA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Independent evaluator</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into a contract with a third-party entity that is unrelated to any recipient of a covered grant to carry out the evaluation under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA227B69D1E6E49B98DD4ED1A05F454C7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>In carrying out the evaluation under paragraph (1), the third-party entity contracted under paragraph (2) shall report to the Secretary and the Attorney General on—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0BE368FC195A46A3A79180C8B510E09A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the demographic characteristics of the population served by the training conducted by eligible entities using covered grants; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA1B8192EDC8E4A4CB76F56DAEA347B96"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any change in the occurrence of violence in the communities served by training described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H8908C8308E7A41E7893AF6D000B1D3EC"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2026 to carry out this Act.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

