<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H972F1163CB4D43D18D212C9612FCBCBE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 5232 IH: Iraqi and Kurdish Peshmerga Forces Defense Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5232</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to develop a plan to equip and train Iraqi security forces and Kurdish Peshmerga forces, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAA290C74909A4DE7A4FDA66DCCB5471D" style="OLC"><section id="HD4B831DA3D0641E798E3D2FAEA1C3362" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Iraqi and Kurdish Peshmerga Forces Defense Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H977E9F022E674463889813D6B1C7093C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Plan to equip and train Iraqi security forces and Kurdish Peshmerga forces</header><subsection id="HCA5D04309EFF43DE8228A020D7D286FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than February 1, 2024, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall develop a plan of action to equip and train Iraqi security forces and Kurdish Peshmerga forces to defend against attack by missiles, rockets, and unmanned systems. The plan of action shall be based on and informed by the results of the report submitted by the Secretary of Defense pursuant to section 1237 of the James M. Inhofe National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/263">Public Law 117–263</external-xref>; 136 Stat. 2839).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE3A9FC020C6F4BA197DE2B85AE8F8B26"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters</header><text>The plan under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H675D3969CF604D749622621741D1CF76"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The provision of available equipment to Iraq and the Iraqi Kurdistan Region to counter the air and missile threats addressed in the report, to include air defense systems, to counter attack by missiles, rockets, and unmanned systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H693884B353174305BC7470A77C0495C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The provision of appropriate training of Iraqi security forces and Kurdish Peshmerga forces to support fielding and operational employment of the available equipment described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44A3EA71BB6C4724892F43E623324610"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation</header><paragraph id="H210C898765AC4598BB5C07AD2D6F4C9D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), not later than 90 days after the date on which the Secretary of Defense develops the plan under subsection (a), the Secretary shall commence the implementation of such plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58A3D849FBFC44CFBEF37A819B4BB248"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary of Defense may delay implementation of the plan under subsection (a) if—</text><subparagraph id="HFB41390D8AB143D1AFC277D55B5650F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary determines such implementation would adversely impact United States stocks and military readiness;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47488A46564F43248A2BFB6C5A06A6B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary notifies the congressional defense committees of the proposed exercise of such waiver; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9AB786184EF495C92D93B708B0ED960"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a 10-day period has elapsed since such notification.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0993FA635A364CD39A454733DEED8F2D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Continued congressional notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of Defense exercises the waiver authority under paragraph (2), every 30 days during the period beginning on the date of the initial notification under paragraph (2)(B) and ending on the date on which the implementation of the plan under subsection (a) commences, the Secretary shall notify the congressional defense committees of the exercise of such authority.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA690281674C84413947BDDA950478329"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Congressional briefing</header><text>Not later than July 1, 2024, the Secretary of Defense shall provide to the congressional defense committees a briefing on progress of the air defense equipping and training effort against the air and missile threat to Iraq, including in the Iraqi Kurdistan Region.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCFF1F4CB7EA145DD9C7CF9D374CBFD6F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Congressional defense committees defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>congressional defense committees</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

