<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H81B9E6AD22D844AAA54508AE7A40EFCB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4676 IH: Nuclear Red Tape Reduction Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4676</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230717">July 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act to direct the Nuclear Regulatory Commission to further utilize a risk-informed and performance-based approach to licensing, to amend the hearing requirements for certain licenses under the Atomic Energy Act of 1954, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2271B7C2D152449FB25EA6E93FF94CCB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H642CF0F7A53144D48CB64AAD53946041" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nuclear Red Tape Reduction Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HFCA133938EC148D988CE9107835FA3A6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Technology-inclusive regulatory framework for nuclear licensing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3(14) of the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2215">42 U.S.C. 2215</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBDAAB2474FA141C59A9383748D016073"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>where appropriate</quote> and inserting <quote>to the maximum extent practicable</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7E60BF9902E4AE5848286BE8D3F5031"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(consistent with the document issued by the Commission on June 22, 1998, and titled <quote>White Paper on Risk-Informed, Performance-Based Regulation</quote> (SECY–98–144))</quote> after <quote>risk-informed and performance-based techniques</quote>. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HEC62B0E07FA1461BB8A5DF8EAC538E98"><enum>3.</enum><header>Hearings and judicial review under the Atomic Energy Act of 1954</header> 
<subsection id="H47DDB4A6598B44C7B405A5CD1CD0E505"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 189a.(1)(A) of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2239">42 U.S.C. 2239(a)(1)(A)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6F4DAC7BFAA5484EB5EBD6C243936F1E" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="HB4BE16312AFF40DC9087A34170B0A6F2"><enum>(A)</enum> <clause id="HE5215B8A98714C28B9402540B3387CED" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>In any proceeding under this Act, for the granting, suspending, revoking, or amending of any license or construction permit, or application to transfer control, and in any proceeding for the issuance or modification of rules and regulations dealing with the activities of licenses, and in any proceeding for the payment of compensation, an award or royalties under sections 153, 157, 186 c., or 188, the Commission shall, subject to clause (ii), grant a hearing upon the request of any person whose interest may be affected by the proceeding, and shall admit any such person as a party to such proceeding.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2F430325E98F44118A74E8A8F794F684" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may only hold a hearing under this subparagraph for an application for a license under section 103 for a construction permit if the Commission receives a request for a hearing under clause (i) by a person described in such clause by not later than 30 days after notice and publication of the application for the license in the Federal Register.</text></clause> <clause id="HB7817030A14949708B26B3476153470C" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Commission shall hold a hearing after 30 days notice and publication once in the Federal Register, on each application under section 104 b. for a construction permit for a facility, and on any application under section 104 c. for a construction permit for a testing facility.</text> </clause> 
<clause id="H682BFF70E6FB4D21BB5AA432F455AFD8" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>In cases where such a construction permit has been issued following the holding of such a hearing, the Commission may, in the absence of a request therefor by any person whose interest may be affected, issue an operating license or an amendment to a construction permit or an amendment to an operating license without a hearing, but upon 30 days notice and publication once in the Federal Register of its intent to do so.</text></clause> <clause id="HEF91FEBACCE741759B678AA1449ABB99" indent="up1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The Commission may dispense with such 30 days notice and publication with respect to any application for an amendment to a construction permit or an amendment to an operating license upon a determination by the Commission that the amendment involves no significant hazards consideration.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HC6DCE266BD9B41C7AE012DBAAED36DD2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Combined licenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 189a.(1)(B)(i) of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2239">42 U.S.C. 2239(a)(1)(B)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>within 60 days</quote> and inserting <quote>within 45 days</quote>.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HFED0C3479F504AFFBA9CCB0AE1D93B29" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report on terms of renewed Nuclear Regulatory Commission licences</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report that describes—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0E9A2555288047C08923274A3A0C1EE5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the authority of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission to determine the terms of renewed licenses under the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2011">42 U.S.C. 2011 et seq.</external-xref>), including how the Nuclear Regulatory Commission determines the maximum term for such renewed licenses and in which circumstances the Nuclear Regulatory Commission may issue a renewed licence for a term in excess of 20 years; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48D25A38A0A340179E985DCAAA6AC2A3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the meaning of <quote>adequacy of licensee programs</quote> as used on page 64964 of the final rule titled <quote>Nuclear Power Plant License Renewal</quote> and published December 13, 1991 (56 Fed. Reg. 64943).</text> </paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

