<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9AEAC1E4A6634B53BE99581CC864E080" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6321 IH: Preservation and Reinvestment Initiative for Community Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6321</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a manufactured housing community improvement grant program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3B354AF77F4944A58516576BB5846762" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H4973FB221D8340099E9F8C1B747552A8"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preservation and Reinvestment Initiative for Community Enhancement Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PRICE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H9DD67EE1BC9B4D228FFFA089A73968F6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Manufactured housing community improvement grant program</header> <subsection id="HA8FF53988CA141848A86D32DF45900E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H571C1355D307415CAAA18B13D64375BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community development financial institution</header><text>The term <term>community development financial institution</term> has the meaning given the term in section 103 of the Community Development Banking and Financial Institutions Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/4702">12 U.S.C. 4702</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D30FE607CAA48B6858AC60FC18C5373"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligible manufactured home community</header><text>The term <term>eligible manufactured home community</term> means a manufactured home community that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5EF07CAF584A40D8A784C2AE2FB5FB57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is affordable to low- and moderate-income persons; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H27637936C9244DCE925BC7B1892E37E3"><enum>(B)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE7825210A1FD47409EAABF3435796FF5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is owned by the residents of the manufactured home community through a resident-controlled entity such as a resident-owned cooperative, as defined by the Secretary; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0B48113489AF4F9ABA15CBA45562F1DD" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will be maintained as such a community, and remain affordable for low- and moderate-income persons, to the maximum extent practicable and for the longest period feasible.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H787E86E9E0F044AE8363474D863864AD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible recipient</header><text>The term <term>eligible recipient</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D54FE3898AF453A9E4BD5D6D4675C3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an eligible manufactured home community;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAB14107FCCC04CA383FE86BA4FE616A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a unit of general local government, including a housing authority;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H33B5703F909F4ACBADE02A9555BD2E71"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a resident-owned community;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1CC70E3E94654905AA25B2A41A8ED4EA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a resident-owned cooperative;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H26F1DD6E23F54C06804108400D113905"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a nonprofit entity with housing expertise or a consortia of such entities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H954B8DF8616A48A8947507BB2FC370BC"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a community development financial institution;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7ECBC0236934C95B962C33B91C45941"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an Indian Tribe or tribally designated housing entity; or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H18017155064D4216A53218D92607D3E1"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other entity approved by the Secretary working with an eligible manufactured home community.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAAF588203DAD41DE853F349A29CCCCD3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 4 of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4103">25 U.S.C. 4103</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D2DCB57657547C0B86250D19786D669"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Low- and moderate-income persons; unit of general local government</header><text>The terms <term>low- and moderate-income persons</term> and <term>unit of general local government</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 102(a) of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5302">42 U.S.C. 5302(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4EDD4232B261480EB29F2B52AFBC725D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Manufactured home community</header><text>The term <term>manufactured home community</term> means any community, court, or park equipped to accommodate manufactured homes for which pad sites, with or without existing manufactured homes or other allowed homes, or other suitable sites, are used primarily for residential purposes, with any additional requirements as determined by the Secretary, including any manufactured housing community as such term is used for purposes of the program of the Federal National Mortgage Association for multifamily loans for manufactured housing communities and the program of the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation for loans for manufactured housing communities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD463F7A051D9493BA4CC5B5C4328EC5A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Resiliency activities</header><text>The term <term>resiliency activities</term> means the reconstruction, repair, or replacement of manufactured housing and manufactured home communities to protect the health and safety of manufactured housing residents and to address weatherization and energy efficiency needs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H219FBD230773492A8E3FB806F6D91EB1"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H71DCA308723F43E9BE14EF7F13EABA72"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a competitive grant program to award funds to eligible recipients to carry out eligible projects for improvements in eligible manufactured home communities.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7ADE8B0868CC4FBB8DF0AA8E1A8C0D9D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7C821EE80CB47AFBEBB23C7D580856C"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Amounts from grants under this section—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA4D2AABCFD84562A6CE90DD3C276CFD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be used to assist in carrying out a project for construction, reconstruction, repair, or clearance of housing, facilities and improvements in or serving a manufactured home community that is necessary to protect the health and safety of the residents of the manufactured home community and the long-term sustainability of the community; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82CFA41D9F9F4B828938AADDE2F0A3AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be used for infrastructure, planning, resident and community services (including relocation assistance, eviction prevention, and down payment assistance), resiliency activities, replacement of outdated homes, and assistance for manufactured housing land and site acquisition.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H300874123E194F5BBE7F8BB7C04302FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Replacement</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), with respect to manufactured housing that was built before 1976, amounts from grants under this section may be used only for replacement of that housing.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H30D9DCC8200E41AAAEA8F8DB5FB28DC9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall prioritize applicants that will carry out activities that primarily benefit low- or moderately low-income residents and preserve long-term housing affordability for residents of manufactured home communities. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H9055AF952B0A437A8F0F2FE098C83014"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Waivers</header><text>The Secretary may waive or specify alternative requirements for any provision of law or regulation that the Secretary administers in connection with use of amounts made available under this section other than requirements related to fair housing, nondiscrimination, labor standards, and the environment, upon a finding that the waiver or alternative requirement is not inconsistent with the overall purposes of such Act and that the waiver or alternative requirement is necessary to facilitate the use of amounts made available under this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H978B86A7A9DB440E98FD949839A0B976"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Implementation</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H59B96B0AF0B34F2E8DC47F2727F4A797"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>The Secretary shall have authority to issue such regulations, notices, or other guidance, forms, instructions, and publications to carry out the programs, projects, or activities authorized under this section to ensure that such programs, projects, or activities are completed in a timely and effective manner. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H168EDC0774FB4B359F924FD0436AD790"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fund</header><text>The Secretary may establish a separate fund to award grants under this section to Indian Tribes.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6BCD83AD0DC74A578B5527BDFA3E4F11"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

