<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBDF4F44598804E48B7C37157651773D1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3729 IH: Social Security Caregiver Credit Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3729</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title II of the Social Security Act to credit individuals serving as caregivers of dependent relatives with deemed wages for up to five years of such service.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H222726FF71204A538F0BC6783A2FED41" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="section-one" id="H4F82AB77B27140A4878454CBCF026774"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Social Security Caregiver Credit Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H2B2228B9C0BD4CD2A18A3E4B4BE251B2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings and sense of Congress</header> <subsection id="HA7F8333A485D4EEBA18CBA3A9F4A9477"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds that:</text> 
<paragraph id="HC4055D13F24846F5B07FE9A31A3A9BEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Caregiving is an essential element of family life and a vital service for children, the ill, the disabled, and the elderly.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0B235D8903684B62970831B8B8A64982"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The establishment of a caregiver credit would bolster the economic prospects of unpaid caregivers and would provide them with vital retirement security.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H07ADF14FBDFA402697FD55C607CC29B3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The 2022 Annual Report of the Board of Trustees of the Federal Old-Age and Survivors Insurance and Federal Disability Insurance Trust Funds concluded that the combined Trust Funds will be able to pay scheduled benefits in full until 2034.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAB0687CDF1A740E9B4A7383BFC56BA4A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that Congress should address the unfair exclusion of professional and hardworking home care providers who are not eligible to receive Social Security or Medicare because they provide paid care to a family member with a disability under programs operated at the State and local level for general health and welfare protection.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HCC51623EC68441A291302380592A6591"><enum>3.</enum><header>Deemed wages for caregivers of dependent relatives</header> 
<subsection id="H7A5487D0DEC34105BF3D33DCA7A714C6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title II of the <act-name parsable-cite="SSA">Social Security Act</act-name> is amended by adding after section 234 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/434">42 U.S.C. 434</external-xref>) the following new section:</text> <quoted-block style="traditional" id="H0C41F538917D408A966F81FEA85CF55E"> <section id="H035B3DD5855D4C55BC06952F5BF92214"><enum>235.</enum><header>Deemed wages for caregivers of dependent relatives</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9DA9BC93DE4D4500BCBA3C98B5AB9D68"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="H350320C26BA4449D9F53C82F145C983F"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HABD26FD5C4224FD59F1B865E3065CC2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the term <term>qualifying month</term> means, in connection with an individual, any month during which such individual was engaged for not less than 80 hours in providing care to a dependent relative without monetary compensation.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBF1EDD6548124098A8F316E0DAA9B288" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>qualifying month</term> does not include any month ending after the date on which such individual attains retirement age (as defined in section 216(l)).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD617B4F672D40FCAA565335B974BA7B" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), assistance provided to a family caregiver of an eligible veteran under section 1720G of title 38, United States Code, shall not be considered monetary compensation for providing care to such eligible veteran.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6BD1F9EB879C44EC9922E48548BFFB2E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>dependent relative</term> means, in connection with an individual—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB2F80DC2792A470C80B807ABC0E1AF5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a child, grandchild, niece, or nephew (of such individual or such individual’s spouse or domestic partner), or a child to which the individual or the individual’s spouse or domestic partner is standing in loco parentis, who is under the age of 12; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1CBA40CFA876417FBD96D2C95F2CD3F6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a child, grandchild, niece, or nephew (of such individual or such individual’s spouse or domestic partner), a child to which the individual or the individual’s spouse or domestic partner is standing in loco parentis, a parent, grandparent, sibling, aunt, or uncle (of such individual or his or her spouse or domestic partner), or such individual’s spouse or domestic partner, if such child, grandchild, niece, nephew, parent, grandparent, sibling, aunt, uncle, spouse, or domestic partner is a chronically dependent individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3E312DC96AA54BD8ABF2D91E8B912C4C"><enum>(3)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9F5E7E6829EA44E98D3A2A0AE16BE10F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>chronically dependent individual</term> means an individual who—</text> <clause id="H8642F4FF036E4C979EBE98BA123D67DA" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is dependent on a daily basis on verbal reminding, physical cueing, supervision, or other assistance provided to the individual by another person in the performance of at least two of the activities of daily living (described in subparagraph (B)) or instrumental activities of daily living (described in subparagraph (C)); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE6468D138AA84D73BF601BA02B9971E7" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>without the assistance described in clause (i), could not perform such activities of daily living or instrumental activities of daily living.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA1C451B444EE4100B426D7C4C394E78E" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The <quote>activities of daily living</quote> referred to in subparagraph (A) means basic personal everyday activities, including—</text> 
<clause id="HF157FAB6729D4067A81972F93C22361F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>eating;</text></clause> <clause id="HFAE15DF1448046D78FC10FF1236687C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>bathing;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF7C392C692AF48B5B4CFEE68D57B74DF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>dressing;</text></clause> <clause id="HB46A77CA8C7A442CB0958897A0E87219"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>toileting; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H76DF6829DD27438EAC5297390EB8DA40"><enum>(v)</enum><text>transferring in and out of a bed or in and out of a chair.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H55397146BA9646A9B3CE0A8B7FA47FA1" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The <quote>instrumental activities of daily living</quote> referred to in subparagraph (A) means activities related to living independently in the community, including—</text> 
<clause id="HC0ED95F480874F23B118AC980F43215D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>meal planning and preparation;</text></clause> <clause id="H9594566BB9D54D588A90D4FBFE68E972"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>managing finances;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB3100E4E24E04C8489CB97CFEA3F317B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>shopping for food, clothing, or other essential items;</text></clause> <clause id="HC5E80C68304741289A1EB3E3A442C2D1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>performing essential household chores;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB21DFFE1259645A6AABEB246CE7513B5"><enum>(v)</enum><text>communicating by phone or other form of media; and</text></clause> <clause id="H016DFA4F4700406EB1E605B272D35FDB"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>traveling around and participating in the community.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB881C72758784DE4AF4A1EE048FD2268"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deemed Wages of Caregiver</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6B0DFD49D9A047E3A9377749E13DDC7F"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H36E9FA0D092646AF82E9BE7C237D27E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For purposes of determining entitlement to and the amount of any monthly benefit for any month after December 2023, or entitlement to and the amount of any lump-sum death payment in the case of a death after such month, payable under this title on the basis of the wages and self-employment income of any individual, and for purposes of section 216(i)(3), such individual shall be deemed to have been paid during each qualifying month (in addition to wages or self-employment income actually paid to or derived by such individual during such month) at an amount per month equal to—</text> <clause id="H7430C4505B1D49AD9FF6D649DE64546B" indent="up2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a qualifying month during which no wages or self-employment income were actually paid to or derived by such individual, 50 percent of the national average wage index (as defined in section 209(k)(1)) for the second calendar year preceding the calendar year in which such month occurs; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3260297A117646D3936F19ADBD3AC9F3" indent="up2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any other qualifying month, the excess of the amount determined under clause (i) over <fraction>1/2</fraction> of the wages or self-employment income actually paid to or derived by such individual during such month.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9D37896532214E74B454D3389DB7D003" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In any case in which there are more than 60 qualifying months for an individual, only the last 60 of such months shall be taken into account for purposes of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7DDF79814AD74C64AB596ADD046CBBAC" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Paragraph (1) shall not be applicable in the case of any monthly benefit or lump-sum death payment if a larger such benefit or payment, as the case may be, would be payable without its application.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6180E339E9464207812C0D846A8264B9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rules and regulations</header> <paragraph id="H285D4B77DCF44006B22AA12342570951"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Commissioner of Social Security shall promulgate such regulations as are necessary to carry out this section and to prevent fraud and abuse with respect to the benefits under this section, including regulations establishing procedures for the application and certification requirements described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB34D7AE662D143D6933C83A99DAE099F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A qualifying month shall not be taken into account under this section with respect to an individual unless—</text> <subparagraph id="HC3E203108EA841C99943A605592E642C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the individual submits to the Commissioner of Social Security an application for benefits under this section that includes—</text> 
<clause id="H6784366BF6BC4E9AB594B8757BC12F4D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the name and identifying information of the dependent relative with respect to whom the individual was engaged in providing care during such month;</text></clause> <clause id="H09488E43F54E4818808E71D0481F84B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the dependent relative is not a child under the age of 12, documentation from the physician of the dependent relative explaining why the dependent relative is a chronically dependent individual; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFBC5892A42FD4745BF37B444AC8D4EAD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>such other information as the Commissioner may require to verify the status of the dependent relative; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEC2F563B5E014C9499815D6634E8167B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for every qualifying month or period of up to 12 consecutive qualifying months that occurs after the first period of 12 consecutive qualifying months, the individual certifies, in such form and manner as the Commissioner shall require, that the information provided in the individual’s application for benefits under this section has not changed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HADC5970704F94A70BDD2D2857763601F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 209(k)(1) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/409">42 U.S.C. 409(k)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HB8AD2C70E4AA408B8B7B3B3F57363FE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> before <quote>230(b)(2)</quote> the first time it appears; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H43F6978EBFC34FB88F005FBA660BE057"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and 235(b)(1)(A)(i),</quote> after <quote>1977),</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill> 

