<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7510384E69254BC0B4493336AC5CE1D3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 1377 IH: Promoting United States Wireless Leadership Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1377</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information to take certain actions to enhance the representation of the United States and promote United States leadership in communications standards-setting bodies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFC9A3744066641909B03912D74C53423" style="OLC"><section id="HE49E12F9739C43CBAC8E304CD0C91A88" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting United States Wireless Leadership Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H70978977EFB24930BDF0F5BD0B85FC41"><enum>2.</enum><header>Representation and leadership of United States in communications standards-setting bodies</header><subsection id="HF665C3BB2FC440989FEAF9F21642824D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to enhance the representation of the United States and promote United States leadership in standards-setting bodies that set standards for 5G networks and for future generations of wireless communications networks, the Assistant Secretary shall, in consultation with the National Institute of Standards and Technology—</text><paragraph id="HE01FF0B16D71476280EC029712310310"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">equitably encourage participation by companies and a wide variety of relevant stakeholders, but not including any company or relevant stakeholder that the Assistant Secretary has determined to be not trusted, (to the extent such standards-setting bodies allow such stakeholders to participate) in such standards-setting bodies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB86FD87B082F49F8BBE87073A6FD90F7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">equitably offer technical expertise to companies and a wide variety of relevant stakeholders, but not including any company or relevant stakeholder that the Assistant Secretary has determined to be not trusted, (to the extent such standards-setting bodies allow such stakeholders to participate) to facilitate such participation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H369D3266C2B94684A922E1C429EE6915"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Standards-Setting bodies</header><text>The standards-setting bodies referred to in subsection (a) include—</text><paragraph id="H791C327FE5F844499C2CF721972A48CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the International Organization for Standardization;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C68A2CE94E1455F88E498A8F58CC88A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the voluntary standards-setting bodies that develop protocols for wireless devices and other equipment, such as the 3GPP and the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89EF86724C654C6A80FA265E3B30E02C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any standards-setting body accredited by the American National Standards Institute or Alliance for Telecommunications Industry Solutions.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDF90BA6465954D4A952DC454B122AE7A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary shall brief the Committees on Energy and Commerce and Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and Foreign Relations of the Senate on a strategy to carry out subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HB38167BBC6BB44E2A7DAEE505C76DE87"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H209457B4E3A54F71A9A2CA6BEADEC3E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>3GPP</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>3GPP</term> means the 3rd Generation Partnership Project.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E4814D10AB04BFD91200F262627B3F9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>5G network</header><text>The term <term>5G network</term> means a fifth-generation mobile network as described by 3GPP Release 15 or higher.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H357DFF95B3D84262959873B1094E9B1D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Assistant Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Assistant Secretary</term> means the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA824CBA1E6D84B4CB980A85C0ED94DBE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Cloud computing</header><text>The term <term>cloud computing</term> has the meaning given the term in Special Publication 800–145 of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, entitled <quote>The NIST Definition of Cloud Computing</quote>, published in September 2011, or any successor publication.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C6CA643F6DE44938EE801BD6A24DE67"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Communications network</header><text>The term <term>communications network</term> means any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8B7E62CB4DED4056A2A9461A9B5257E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A system enabling the transmission, between or among points specified by the user, of information of the user’s choosing.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H410D91DEC2A94B1091D5F1F2E915D293"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Cloud computing resources.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCA0D5F762B3429BA308C6E75A3CC99D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A network or system used to access cloud computing resources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C738FF4142B42CC90F18F02824AA03D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Not trusted</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>not trusted</quote> means, with respect to a company or stakeholder, that the company or stakeholder is determined by the Assistant Secretary to pose a threat to the national security of the United States. In making such a determination, the Assistant Secretary shall rely solely on one or more of the following determinations:</text><subparagraph id="HF7C75A3609794D818BAEC5D6F535A263"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A specific determination made by any executive branch interagency body with appropriate national security expertise, including the Federal Acquisition Security Council established under section 1322(a) of title 41, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C2ADDA3F72E47698BDD815712B065AD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A specific determination made by the Department of Commerce pursuant to Executive Order No. 13873 (84 Fed. Reg. 22689; relating to securing the information and communications technology and services supply chain).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC47FABBF82F427F822E3C0E5B7C9750"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether a company or stakeholder produces or provides covered telecommunications equipment or services, as defined in section 889(f)(3) of the John S. McCain National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/232">Public Law 115–232</external-xref>; 132 Stat. 1918).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

