<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB70AF7D6216A40EBB83D7CF402796A9C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5812 IH: No Glory for Hate Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5812</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. S&#225;nchez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the use of Federal funds for the commemoration of certain former Presidents, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCFED173FBF3846DD893A5D1F5C310918" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HADF6BF9BF89A4182A60760785EF49137" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Glory for Hate Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5B566AE4198742C5939F7F0B48AC4C0A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal funds restriction on commemorating certain former Presidents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 3102 of title 40, United States Code, no Federal funds may be used to—</text>
<paragraph id="H03B64930205948A294D7EAB3ED2D1EFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">create or display any symbol, monument, or statue commemorating any former President that has been twice impeached by the House of Representatives on or before the date of enactment of this Act or has been convicted of a State or Federal crime relating to actions taken in an official capacity as President of the United States on Federal public land, including any highway, park, subway, Federal building, military installation, street, or other Federal property; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H71D685DE1EFD4AEC97A8DACC1733241C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">name, designate, or redesignate a Federal building or Federal land after, or in commemoration of, any former President that has been twice impeached by the House of Representatives on or before the date of enactment of this Act or has been convicted of a State or Federal crime relating to actions taken in an official capacity as President of the United States.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H8FFED2EF55204E8B9E5076E2023C2E1D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Restriction of Federal funds for property bearing the name of certain former Presidents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no Federal funds or other Federal financial assistance may be provided to a State, political subdivision thereof, or entity if any such funds or financial assistance will be used for the benefit of any building, land, structure, installation, or any other property that bears the name, or is named or designated in commemoration of, any former President that has been twice impeached by the House of Representatives on or before the date of enactment of this Act or has been convicted of a State or Federal crime relating to actions taken in an official capacity as President of the United States. </text></section> <section id="H1725317ED743449EA434F4BC3E643A9D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Former Presidents Act restriction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any provision of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide retirement, clerical assistants, and free mailing privileges to former Presidents of the United States, and for other purposes</quote>, approved August 25, 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/3/102">3 U.S.C. 102</external-xref> note; commonly known as the <quote>Former Presidents Act of 1958</quote>), any former President that has been twice impeached by the House of Representatives on or before the date of enactment of this Act or has been convicted of a State or Federal crime relating to actions taken in an official capacity as President of the United States is not entitled to receive any benefit, other than Secret Service protection, under such Act. </text></section>
<section id="HD3B7E8C858FD4473881B6E2534E8FA09"><enum>5.</enum><header>Prohibition of burial of certain former Presidents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 7722(a) of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H2B2D058FA67F4B68B56E953AA6789F78" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HCBAB2ACC50674BAFA76B42DE813A9CE4" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out paragraphs (1) and (2), the Secretary of Defense shall not approve a determination of eligibility for interment or inurnment in Arlington National Cemetery made by the Secretary of the Army that permits the interment or inurnment in Arlington National Cemetery of any former President that has been twice impeached by the House of Representatives on or before the date of enactment of this Act or has been convicted of a State or Federal crime relating to actions taken in an official capacity as President of the United States.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

