<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE020BA6A6AB54291AD2B83306BF4887D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6221 IH: Smoke Mitigation and Occupational Key Enhancements Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6221</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231103">November 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Labor to promulgate an occupational safety and health standard to protect workers from adverse air, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA4614D0854DF4342B0C564BAF6186583" style="OLC"><section id="HF61D68F3CC76429DA1D3302CC16F3C14" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Smoke Mitigation and Occupational Key Enhancements Act</short-title></quote> or <quote><short-title>SMOKE Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HAD04FFE1409E4BF9B1B0E83F364EE0F5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H356B72B5D03F4C6696708281A6353A31"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Climate change is making wildland fires more frequent and longer lasting.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H15785223D06C48CD9E37D60DC309FAE5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Wildfire smoke is a mixture of air pollutants, of which the principal public health threat is particulate matter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47DAD97FFB544A3784F9AC9D5E2C3549"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Wildfire smoke has been directly linked to poor air quality that can lead to significant health effects and costs to society (such as emergency department visits, hospital admissions, and deaths, often due to respiratory ailments).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H595806B3C6214139AF0A522C5D6C455C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to climate change, other factors—land use, large-scale insect infestation, fuel availability (including invasive species such as highly flammable cheatgrass), and management practices, including fire suppression—play an important role in wildfire frequency and intensity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H468B0C57A5FF4A128BE00513A93E6C50"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In summer 2023, smoke from wildfires in Canada drifted into the United States, leading to extremely poor air quality across the eastern United States. Since then, States across the country have issued poor air quality alerts, with New York City having reported the worst air quality in the world on June 7, 2023. Due to these fires, about 128 million Americans in 18 States were under air quality alerts. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA34DF44A55BE4FF68080CFD880A2F803"><enum>(6)</enum><text>While officials have warned Americans to be mindful of poor air quality conditions, including to limit time spent outside, worker protections are unclear in these circumstances.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H3D47C0AC0CA24363A06136A3D2977AA9"><enum>3.</enum><header>OSHA Standards</header><subsection id="H1B5352B73089497DB275E55E96F1C1E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Proposed standard</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall, pursuant to section 6(b) of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/655">29 U.S.C. 655(b)</external-xref>), in consultation with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency and the Secretary of Health and Human Services (acting through the Director of the National Institute on Occupational Safety and Health), and in accordance with the best available evidence, promulgate a proposed standard on prevention of workplace injury from exposure to adverse air.</text></subsection><subsection id="H64200A90DDC44CE4A8A6115FA91B2EAD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Final standard</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 42 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall promulgate a final standard on prevention of workplace injury from exposure to adverse air that shall—</text><paragraph id="H325A35A164034055BB18DFB5CF2A6ED0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">presume as feasible any requirement that—</text><subparagraph id="HAFBAEAC763724EDC8DF4B75CCB975D4C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is substantially equivalent to a requirement adopted by a State plan that has been approved by the Secretary under section 18 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/667">29 U.S.C. 667</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51FF1FE590734C3DAE4D1F7892144315" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has been in effect for at least 1 year;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB47F69A61D244076AEDA6F6FF6E82D73"><enum>(2)</enum><text>at a minimum, include the requirements described in section 4; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F20DC13EB054B31BE1347D3DC694402"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be effective and enforceable in the same manner and to the same extent as any standard promulgated under section 6(b) of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/655">29 U.S.C. 655(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB675BE242AC54E678897C38610EB5F66" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Interim final standard</header><paragraph id="H5388654A97974E65A2717BCEE3337A3D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the proposed standard described in subsection (a) is not promulgated, not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall promulgate an interim final standard on prevention of workplace injury from exposure to adverse air not later than 2 years and 60 days after such date of enactment—</text><subparagraph id="H91355CE9257444D2ADC379AFD84C0C6F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to require covered employers to monitor the AQI for PM2.5 and, if adverse air is present, communicate the AQI for PM2.5 to the covered employees of such covered employers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8C2AD733FA8418EB2332EF638610A67" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that shall, at a minimum, include a requirement to protect employees from discrimination or retaliation for exercising the rights of the employees under the interim final standard.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H67A3044B5F6B4597B7BD4B59D0C9E5F1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability of other statutory requirements</header><text>The following shall not apply to the promulgation of the interim final standard under this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H9DD0268B3F4C48F28CF517DBDD4B9A5B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The requirements applicable to occupational safety and health standards under section 6(b) of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/655">29 U.S.C. 655(b)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE3DA44490C04204950673E5B7CF387F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The requirements of section 553(c) of chapter 5 and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/6">chapter 6</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F36B8182C3440ABAAF1CCD291030C29" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The requirements of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H33AC4B77D8F640D6805ECCDE398C0E5C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date of interim standard</header><text>The interim final standard shall—</text><subparagraph id="H13C61C0405554360A1C9CCE1594E183F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>take effect on a date that is not later than 30 days after the promulgation of such standard;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFECEC382213438B9921BCEB95CBFB7A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have the same legal effect and be enforceable in the same manner and to the same extent as any standard promulgated under section 6(b) of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/655">29 U.S.C. 655(b)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9285139011DE446CA5773EE1F6B7C83D" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be in effect until the final standard described in subsection (b) becomes effective and enforceable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5B727C4C40664B4F8CC4532C33D28187"><enum>4.</enum><header>Requirements for final standards</header><subsection id="H79BA471E8E934E9AAFD37A6F6306E68A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The final standard promulgated under section 3(b) shall include the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="HC5AA7863ADA54E0DA1D5CFEDADF65CD1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Controls related to monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each covered employer shall, at the start of each work day or shift, and every 2 hours thereafter, determine whether adverse air is present at each covered workplace for each such work day or shift by monitoring or obtaining the AQI for PM2.5 forecasts from—</text><subparagraph id="HDD5D522910FF4BD59134ADA3CF056936" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Environmental Protection Agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA372FFB00C3D41F2B1691A87497B4806"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Interagency Wildland Fire Air Quality Response Program; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CB0D51596284CF7A03D11445441DE1F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the United States Forest Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC4D829C58FF48DF9C5614104DEA1703"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Employer communication of potential adverse air exposures</header><text>Each covered employer shall establish and implement a system to communicate the presence of adverse air in a language and manner readily understandable by covered employees, which shall include procedures that inform such employees of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H78C01DFFBC50488F8546CCDFA9467950"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each time during the workday when adverse air affects the workplace of such employees.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H668A21F75CF748CFA3DE39CBC664FC50"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The protective controls described in paragraph (3) available to employees to reduce exposure to adverse air.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA5BAAFCAE2945049A93F6FD367C32E0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The potential health impacts of breathing adverse air without proper protection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2103591C24574DCBBE0EAD4F9BB3F5AD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The policy of the employer that employees are encouraged to report to the employer, without fear of discrimination or retaliation—</text><clause id="H130F6A4D053C4843855D9F7D9F17C572"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the presence of adverse air in the workplace; and</text></clause><clause id="H669820B9E0714B1F8290754048E4221A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>adverse symptoms, including asthma attacks, difficulty breathing, or chest pain, that the employee is at risk of experiencing if exposed to adverse air.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AB7FE7921DE4DE399CEBDBEB8E552CF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Protective controls</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each covered employer shall provide the following at each covered workplace of the employer: </text><subparagraph id="H7E1945C2A82B47508FBEE27FFE9D1DE0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Engineering controls</header><clause id="HB3BE9B06732B46FB8EED8CE2FE6E29B8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Reduction of employee exposure to adverse air by engineering controls whenever feasible, such as by providing enclosed buildings, structures, or vehicles where the air is filtered to prevent exposure to adverse air within such buildings, structures, or vehicles.</text></clause><clause id="HBA546B6D06064CF79DD3E4204C5A67B0"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Insufficient engineering controls</header><text>If engineering controls are insufficient to prevent exposure to adverse air, reduction of employee exposure to such air to the extent feasible.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H488327AFC74F4BD0A218C6B9BE898250"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Administrative controls</header><text>Whenever engineering controls are not feasible or do not reduce employee exposures to adverse air, implementation, if feasible, of administrative controls, such as relocating work to a location where adverse air is not present, allowing remote work, changing work schedules, reducing work intensity, or providing additional rest periods.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7965C67D0D940CA9C37A43CFB4AAE1D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Personal protective equipment</header><clause id="HA257274B427D422A9FD07D4127CCCF58"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Whenever adverse air is present, the provision of a sufficient number of respirators that meet the requirements of clause (ii) to all covered employees for voluntary use and encouragement to employees to use such respirators.</text></clause><clause id="HBD0DC42EE17048FBAB672595E648D0CC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Respirators provided</header><text>A respirator provided under clause (i) shall be—</text><subclause id="H3DEEA31B2B3D4755B082B565F66CA252"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a device approved by the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health that effectively protects the wearers from inhalation of PM2.5, such as N95 filtering facepiece respirators;</text></subclause><subclause id="H377CFBA3E53942CCB9BB29910D60F70C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>cleaned or replaced as appropriate; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HDA47FE890B8143C39A8BC4A1862371B0"><enum>(III)</enum><text>stored and maintained in such a way so that such respirators do not present a health hazard to users.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H33B6532F94F14BF5BECE330B31B89C8B" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Adverse air related leave</header><subsection id="H13BB07109E9E41BD80630E743F81B509" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an employee whose health would be jeopardized by exposure to adverse air, such employee shall be entitled to a total of 12 weeks of unpaid leave per 12-month period for the purposes of avoiding such exposure at a covered workplace where the employee is employed.</text></subsection><subsection id="H94EEFE8A38994BAC93D6E3239644230D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Substitution of paid leave</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employee may elect to substitute any of the accrued paid vacation leave, personal leave, or family leave of the employee for leave provided under subsection (a) for any part of the 12-week period of such leave under such subsection.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7CE31EDE77AC439F8DE64BDFAC20EFA2" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Employment protection during adverse air related leave</header><paragraph id="H9DAE5DCDEAB24E1890303E55C17278A3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any eligible employee who uses leave under subsection (a) for the intended purpose of such leave shall be entitled, on return from using such leave—</text><subparagraph id="HF44E2E763EA647F1B86278EEF8E55256" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to be restored by the employer to the position of employment held by the employee when the use of such leave commenced; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CE22DC9351542D5AB93888543A2C0BA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to be restored to an equivalent position with equivalent employment benefits, pay, and other terms and conditions of employment. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1121A154923D4C1587E58812AB16FD31" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Loss of benefits</header><text>The use of such leave shall not result in the loss of any employment benefit accrued prior to the date on which the use of leave under subsection (a) commenced. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D6CA706024A47338B7FED1210CEDCBA" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to entitle any restored employee to—</text><subparagraph id="HC0AD765805D842C890F6CA96820C8640" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the accrual of any seniority or employment benefits during any period during which such restored employee uses leave under subsection (a); or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B8F57ACE3A2404A8DBF02902360563B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any right, benefit, or position of employment other than any right, benefit, or position to which the employee would have been entitled had the employee not used such leave.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A85C922A38B4623B5DA96DC489102D1" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit an employer from requiring an employee to report periodically to the employer on the status and intention of the employee to return to work.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8EB93100516E41AE8A4CF791812F0F0C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Certification</header><paragraph id="H983640EF46B3479388083395EFBD288D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An employer may require that a request for leave under subsection (a) be supported by a certification issued by the health care provider of the eligible employee. The employee shall provide, in a timely manner, a copy of such certification to the employer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F5DE7DBBA6442DBBC8B91495B08DDF7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sufficient Certification</header><text>Certification provided under paragraph (1) shall be sufficient if it states—</text><subparagraph id="HADBDB080A79D4A60B70E058CF51EB0B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the appropriate medical facts within the knowledge of the health care provider regarding the condition; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FB10032B5974C2CA80C0BA4D3273974" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a statement that the health of the employee would be endangered by exposure to unsafe air.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8770490D385A41A59FFECBC2E22F75CE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Subsequent Recertification</header><text>The employer may require that the eligible employee obtain subsequent recertifications on a reasonable basis.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1E6E2CF6FC9647AF8860CB4DF3C43E1D"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H3091EAC97BB84FB0AA3DE28442720562" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adverse air</header><text>The term <term>adverse air</term> means air with an AQI of at least 151 for PM2.5.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6F7DA2410B443BEB30352F196D2FF80" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>AQI</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>AQI</term> means the measure of the concentration of ozone, particulate matter, carbon monoxide, sulfur dioxide, and nitrogen dioxide in the air described under Appendix G to part 58 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H014B287DE19F4BA8AFE64B89BCDB3198"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered employee</header><subparagraph id="HD3A26C5D8D4E460DA2AB78AA9607B0C7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>covered employee</term> means an employee of a covered employer who works at a covered workplace, except as provided in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45579BCE0E8E42B38DA426BFBB5EE297"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered employee</term> does not include an employee who works in emergency operations that are directly involved in the protection of life or property, or the restoration of essential services and critical infrastructure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H726BDB9D290A48BFB66C10E1D76DBCC3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered employer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered employer</term> means any employer that employs an employee at a covered workplace.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CFA0C66D38E49EDA3D17ACD6559858D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Covered workplace</header><subparagraph id="HDF917A5AF24F4198B6002EFF2D326E1F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>covered workplace</term> means a workplace at which employees are, or may reasonably be expected to be, exposed to adverse air.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80BA4BE4CAC7492EA6F8E038156DB528"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>The following shall not be considered a covered workplace:</text><clause id="HFC4A658BC2BC415B99585C647571766F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>An enclosed building or structure in which the air is filtered by a mechanical ventilation system such that an employee is not exposed to adverse air, if the employer ensures that windows, doors, bays, and other openings are kept closed, except when it is necessary to open doors to enter or exit.</text></clause><clause id="H03CBE80C5AB949D294BAD0DCF2B34F70"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An enclosed vehicle in which the air is filtered by a cabin air filter such that an individual inside such vehicle is not exposed to adverse air, if the employer ensures that windows, doors, and other openings are kept closed, except when it is necessary to open doors to enter or exit the vehicle.</text></clause><clause id="H6E3902BEAA23427CB3D49AB217A92C23"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A workplace that exposes individuals to adverse air for a period not to exceed 1 hour during a shift.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H124945ACFCA2469B937445ACFD6EA0DD"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Employer</header><text>The term <term>employer</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/652">29 U.S.C. 652</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

