<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H40C1BEB8D3AB4DEEBD27335F816781DC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3553 IH: 21st Century American Atomic Energy Age Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3553</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Office of Nuclear, Economic, Environmental, and National Security of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, accelerate the deployment of small modular nuclear reactors, ban the import of Russian nuclear material, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAAD3DF3D39A04971BCA2C1D323AB93D4" style="OLC"><section id="HC1103454050B44F8B080DB5436224942" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>21st Century American Atomic Energy Age Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1C54BD54B255460085B25ACC05AD808D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H099804DE88614C78801DEC2B7C828AA9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States should promote and support the development of small modular nuclear reactors to provide safe, reliable, and affordable electricity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H725757E593C94A63A3409B44A7AF45B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission has the responsibility to issue construction permits and operating licenses for innovative nuclear reactors to meet the energy needs of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3513FD2338F046FC8E58CB35A7226B2F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United States relied on Russia for about 16 percent of its uranium in 2020.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HA9B09AC852684C38A686070AB103272C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Technical assistance for small modular nuclear reactor applications</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Commission shall provide technical assistance to applicants that apply for a construction permit, an operating license, or a combined construction permit and operating license for a small modular nuclear reactor under section 103 or 185 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (42 U.S.C. 2133 or 2235).</text></section><section id="HA60DD7400E1E4F18A6C84CD66A97363B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on import and use of nuclear fuel from Russia</header><subsection id="H7EAC068CC82B4ED681248737ED1692CD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on use</header><paragraph id="H88E3F968CC724CB6AE5DF1FDDB3BC428"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No person shall use nuclear fuel, including low-enriched uranium, that was produced in, or imported from, Russia to operate any small modular nuclear reactor located in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6ACD784C6AF7410EBF5038086FADA052"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 183 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of Commerce shall establish, by regulation, procedures to ensure compliance with this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H439C38A72A974B40B671EBAEE351DA05"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on imports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3112A of the USEC Privatization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2297h-10a">42 U.S.C. 2297h–10a</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAE8A28673DBA4A0388A53ACAD623B3B3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HAFCE3E7E6A734BC0B480B5F14457CD3C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 90 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, no low-enriched uranium that is produced in the Russian Federation or by a Russian entity may be imported into the United States.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H5075AC7B664347B8BEA06FC66D88B0A3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy, the Secretary of Homeland Security, and the Secretary of Defense shall, not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this section, submit to Congress a report that identifies critical infrastructure that can benefit from access to onsite or offsite electricity generated by a small modular nuclear reactor that is located at or near the critical infrastructure to achieve added energy resilience.</text></section><section id="HD32BFE91D168427A89AE8B9E5C7FEC50"><enum>6.</enum><header>Office of Nuclear, Economic, Environmental, and National Security of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission</header><subsection id="H05BAF37CA2124A7AA814024DAF89B663"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title II of the <short-title>Energy Reorganization Act of 1974</short-title> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5841">42 U.S.C. 5841 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 205 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2269CEDB941243EEB7B447DD0F7B0D82" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H5B0871613F7E44E7B39AC0650CE38C8F"><enum>205A.</enum><header>Office of Nuclear, Economic, Environmental, and National Security</header><subsection id="H62B21B5D40734D699BC3940987203E66"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is hereby established in the Commission an Office of Nuclear, Economic, Environmental, and National Security (in this section referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>) under the direction of a Director, who shall—</text><paragraph id="H330784F9326841AD9EF0CEAB778CB1DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be appointed by the Commission;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66C9221626F54791B11E02B8B74E2E77"><enum>(2)</enum><text>report directly to the Commission, as provided in section 209; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72107FC87144415B941C7367E34F1CA2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>serve at the pleasure of and be removable by the Commission.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA8A9A93009D04D5AB03214A58B24AC39"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Functions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Director of the Office shall perform such functions as the Commission shall delegate, including:</text><paragraph id="H2CD39C5139BE4072BF72215044B2F797"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Principal licensing and regulation involving all facilities, materials, and activities licensed under the Atomic Energy Act of 1954.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H104CEEE2C22B42F3878405C9B80F9895"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Review the economic, environmental, and national security benefits of all such facilities, materials, and activities, including evaluating the benefits to air quality, human health, carbon dioxide emissions reduction, economic activity, and national security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B3856FDEBDB416FBD4F774B3A8E9163"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Assessing the need for, and the feasibility of, establishing an agency within the Office to review the Commission’s licensing and related regulatory functions for the purposes of increasing the development and use of nuclear energy to ensure public health and economic security by providing for the effective and safe commercial use of radioactive materials.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HF9CE15B48D1C4273A0390AA68351E4B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Nuclear, Economic, Environmental, and National Security, established under section 205A of the <short-title>Energy Reorganization Act of 1974</short-title> (as added by this section), shall, not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, submit to Congress a report, including recommendations, based on the assessments made under subsection (b)(3) of such section 205A.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3D16F7497C99419CAAEA3A8ABA41F7B3"><enum>7.</enum><header>Extension of the Price-Anderson Act</header><subsection id="H894CE8222AEE4CC59B620F7E071CC937"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Extension</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 170 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2210">42 U.S.C. 2210</external-xref>) (commonly known as the <quote>Price-Anderson Act</quote>) is amended by striking <quote>December 31, 2025</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>December 31, 2045</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H79A8A9C523CB46628BEEB08F18DA20E0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 170 p. of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2210">42 U.S.C. 2210(p)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>December 31, 2021</quote> and inserting <quote>December 31, 2041</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="H513E47514BF94AEE835D7AF89896A74C"><enum>8.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act.</text></section><section id="HDAEC3DF90C054C7E9B9CDFB9148C2CFB"><enum>9.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall take effect 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section><section id="H4BECAE43A17A4DACB28EC2A5A1B67528"><enum>10.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H7BD6FB6B753A4809B1DD18D3FA882086" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46DCDB8E348D4335862101475E084CA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>critical infrastructure</term> means a facility, asset, system, or network, whether physical or virtual, that is so vital to the United States that the incapacity or destruction of such facility asset, system, or network would have a debilitating impact on national economic security, public health or safety, or any combination of those matters.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54E4F8F5055D4C0DB969A438A2BD0FAE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Key resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>key resources</term> has the meaning given such term section 2 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/101">6 U.S.C. 101</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E436D2E24AA4985BBED54FB525D6E15"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Small modular nuclear reactor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>small modular nuclear reactor</term> means a nuclear reactor with an electric generating capacity of not more than 200 megawatts. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

