<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3386EB5AF96C419DBC023D9FB8CE6758" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5977 IH: Sensible Classification Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5977</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231017">October 17, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HIG00"> Committees on Intelligence (Permanent Select)</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To improve the classification and declassification of national security information, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="HDDA8A1051A1342CA866C35D7F88E1751" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H10C7519B4E424FC18685E297A0E5B8C9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB89CF2B1C7D84BE7A604CF34F7612295"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sensible Classification Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE4A6AA3E0AB24CAD9227C3CF525CF520"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> 
<toc-entry idref="H10C7519B4E424FC18685E297A0E5B8C9" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HC97C1D5CE08F4556B7A2AAB5500CB8EA" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings and sense of Congress.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H261E729E3E074C26A8DFB616D675F70C" level="section">Sec. 3. Classification authority.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H987A651B43A64F968B535626E12D4972" level="section">Sec. 4. Promoting efficient declassification review.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H7303C37F465F40A087086A61FC6ADED3" level="section">Sec. 5. Training to promote sensible classification.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HD8197A46E604428C9840556727220CD1" level="section">Sec. 6. Improvements to Public Interest Declassification Board.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H3EF40A06E7544C85B1C72831DFC08046" level="section">Sec. 7. Implementation of technology for classification and declassification.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE08A87517CB84D8A9AF7A854B2075498" level="section">Sec. 8. Studies and recommendations on necessity of security clearances.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HAC7BD0BFA617497C909634A928985573" level="section">Sec. 9. Definitions.</toc-entry> </toc> </subsection></section> 
<section id="HC97C1D5CE08F4556B7A2AAB5500CB8EA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings and sense of Congress</header> 
<subsection id="H9F847A667DFD4AC6B87C191BD375ED21"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H57A8CEE07ECA4F5190E557606B93DE13"><enum>(1)</enum><text>According to a report released by the Office of the Director of Intelligence in 2020 titled <quote>Fiscal Year 2019 Annual Report on Security Clearance Determinations</quote>, more than 4,000,000 individuals have been granted eligibility for a security clearance.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0E6D3CF95E894124802232490FB70A39"><enum>(2)</enum><text>At least 1,300,000 of such individuals have been granted access to information classified at the Top Secret level.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H62A942C10E3148F4829E765D24279B30"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7C3B509EBF30453D9CADF7CDACD0F06F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the classification system of the Federal Government is in urgent need of reform;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H452A86FAC40B4A16AF3F4DD695A1617E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of people with access to classified information is exceedingly high and must be justified or reduced;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDBC4139C37214CA28766616B5FFD7082"><enum>(3)</enum><text>reforms are necessary to reestablish trust between the Federal Government and the people of the United States; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABC4E3B72E2F425CBB465912CDB92ACB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>classification should be limited to the minimum necessary to protect national security while balancing the public’s interest in disclosure.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H261E729E3E074C26A8DFB616D675F70C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Classification authority</header> 
<subsection id="H11D902E5CC21473E90F3B2746DC539F6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The authority to classify information originally may be exercised only by—</text> <paragraph id="HC2B6014589B8410FA2626383931E7BA9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the President and, in the discharge of executive duties and responsibilities, the Vice President;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD27EA99A13A1411CAD15D88AF389DE3A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the head or any other official of any agency authorized by the President pursuant to a designation of such authority in the Federal Register; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H338A95C7FAF1461BB0B817D03B7E7115"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an official of the Federal Government to whom authority to classify information originally has been delegated pursuant to subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE74C0321055D4EEC8A1DCB70FBFA6E45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scope of authority</header><text>An individual authorized under this section to classify information originally at a specified level may also classify information originally at a lower level.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H93467A913ED5478AB3B1F9BAF2F13464"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Delegation of original classification authority</header><text>An official of the Federal Government may be delegated original classification authority subject to the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HCEE154833A264D679B3B67B6EB2F6D7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Delegation of original classification authority shall be limited to the minimum required to administer this section. Agency heads shall be responsible for ensuring that designated subordinate officials have a demonstrable and continuing need to exercise such authority.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H68D554BFB6BB4D83BC14CBFF3FC4644A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Authority to originally classify information at the level designated as <quote>Top Secret</quote> may be delegated only by the President, in the performance of executive duties, the Vice President, or an agency head or official designated pursuant to subsection (a)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC453AE51CB7F4507B35FD205DE5BD2BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Authority to originally classify information at the level designated as <quote>Secret</quote> or <quote>Confidential</quote> may be delegated only by the President, in the discharge of executive duties and responsibilities, the Vice President, or an agency head or official designated pursuant to subsection (a)(2), or the senior agency official described in section 5.4(d) of Executive Order 13526 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3161">50 U.S.C. 3161</external-xref> note; relating to classified national security information), or successor order, provided that official has been delegated <quote>Top Secret</quote> original classification authority by the agency head.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1D32CCA1279A420A9D539DC3F28EA5D2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Each delegation of original classification authority shall be in writing and the authority shall not be redelegated except as provided by paragraph (1), (2), or (3). Each delegation shall identify the official by name or position title.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEB6B0CEB34C84E549887F35A66570665"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Training required</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6A8F447467A448FBAAFAE5837CFBDD51"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual may not be delegated original classification authority under this section unless the individual has first received training described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC9AFF6841714542BE8E7C071B7FD4F9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Training described in this paragraph is training on original classification that includes instruction on the proper safeguarding of classified information and of the criminal, civil, and administrative sanctions that may be brought against an individual who fails to protect classified information from unauthorized disclosure.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H71AAFFF95EE94268B0F58FFE47DC735A" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exceptional cases</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E62143DEB79477E9C73A17DFA11861C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When an employee, contractor, licensee, certificate holder, or grantee of an agency who does not have original classification authority originates information believed by that employee, contractor, licensee, certificate holder, or grantee to require classification, the information shall be protected in a manner consistent with Executive Order 13526 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3161">50 U.S.C. 3161</external-xref> note; relating to classified national security information), or successor order.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBCBDAAB503924BB6A5A03E1555EA0897"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transmission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employee, contractor, licensee, certificate holder, or grantee described in paragraph (1), who originates information described in such paragraph, shall promptly transmit such information to—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC997627433E540B1AA05BD81A8F47D06"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the head of the agency that has appropriate subject matter interest and classification authority with respect to the information; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0730AF01E5C47F7829171369C1888F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if it is not clear which agency has appropriate subject matter interest and classification authority with respect to the information, to the Director of the Information Security Oversight Office of the National Archives and Records Administration. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1653B611C3794D32B4FF8A6C7FB5EA3A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information Security Oversight Office action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Director of the Information Security Oversight Office receives information under paragraph (2)(B), the Director shall determine which agency has appropriate subject matter interest and classification authority and submit the information, with appropriate recommendations, to the head of that agency for a classification determination. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC508A361008B462BBDEEDC5F8E48A6BA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Timing of determinations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the head of agency receives information pursuant to paragraph (2)(A) or (3), the head shall make a determination as to whether to classify the information.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section> 
<section id="H987A651B43A64F968B535626E12D4972"><enum>4.</enum><header>Promoting efficient declassification review</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H89C7880F6E384C1F85FFFCB55F25E0EE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever the head of an agency is processing a request pursuant to section 552 of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>) or the mandatory declassification review provisions of Executive Order 13526 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3161">50 U.S.C. 3161</external-xref> note; relating to classified national security information), or successor order, and identifies responsive classified records that are more than 25-years-of-age as of December 31 of the year in which the request is received, the head of the agency shall review the record and process the record for declassification and release by the National Declassification Center of the National Archives and Records Administration.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6265C8C5D1954001909523036FD94CF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a) shall apply—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4BCC477838074159938FFB7E121AE484"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">regardless of whether or not the record described in such subsection is in the legal custody of the National Archives and Records Administration; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H773A3F8346C14A9DAF8EF72A09D75694"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">without regard for any other provisions of law or existing agreements or practices between agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H7303C37F465F40A087086A61FC6ADED3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Training to promote sensible classification</header> 
<subsection id="H0115EC7FD84B471F8445E9FA8C140EF0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Training required</header><text>Each head of an agency with classification authority shall conduct training for employees of such agency with classification authority to discourage over-classification and to promote sensible classification.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB409220BBDD04E358DE573AE9FC5D5A0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H147628B3C85548A09C44C2C339AF4C10"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Over-classification</header><text>The term <term>over-classification</term> means classification at a level that exceeds the minimum level of classification that is sufficient to protect the national security of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF4DA0D882FD4C1DA829AB4C52049C87"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sensible classification</header><text>The term <term>sensible classification</term> means classification at a level that is the minimum level of classification that is sufficient to protect the national security of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> 
<section id="HD8197A46E604428C9840556727220CD1"><enum>6.</enum><header>Improvements to Public Interest Declassification Board</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 703 of the Public Interest Declassification Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3355a">50 U.S.C. 3355a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H59879B8100454595982D72BD9E9F5049"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H24C94790F6E4485A9DF3F38B6369D40F"> 
<paragraph id="H499E03F4BA824E7794AE324B66BF177D" indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member of the Board whose term has expired may continue to serve until a successor is appointed and sworn in.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F8146C61B1D41079C42E23120EA3A99"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (f)—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H11035306722E4D15ADD8B53E7F4823D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> before <quote>Any employee</quote>; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8E02D5655275406BAB26F043A1E43272"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block id="H8E26AF6836D6438EAB0838AFD88DB928" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC" act-name=""> 
<paragraph indent="up1" id="HF63577F881EE4A0F9E2946C42BFF45CC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to any employees detailed to the Board under paragraph (1), the Board may hire not more than 12 staff members.</text> </paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H3EF40A06E7544C85B1C72831DFC08046"><enum>7.</enum><header>Implementation of technology for classification and declassification</header> <subsection id="H3EDC2FDC5DB9420AA241C2B63A5A7BAA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Office of Electronic Government of the Office of Management and Budget (in this section referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote>), in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, the Director of the Central Intelligence Agency, the Director of National Intelligence, the Director of the Information Security Oversight Office, the head of the National Declassification Center of the National Archives and Records Administration, and the Public Interest Declassification Board, shall—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H977CF3501D924ED59C3047B8EC20656D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">research a technology-based solution—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H180D64A3DAF24CBE8EA437B7A07E3B2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">using machine learning and artificial intelligence to support efficient and effective systems for classification and declassification; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE14ADACA06B64B85BFBA1A72A2391693"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to be implemented on an interoperable and federated basis across the Federal Government; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEAAD7026BC3642808E6618CFC3529133"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the President a recommendation regarding a technology-based solution described in paragraph (1) that should be adopted by the Federal Government.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE24C302DF1C34CC18D32F14C9C2C572A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Staff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may hire sufficient staff to carry out subsection (a). </text></subsection> <subsection id="HA7E4E8674FD64956A56A0A498787B92A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header> <paragraph id="HF4C3C92CFD144261896C24545D561EEE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>Not later than 540 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall submit to Congress a report on the technology-based solution recommended by the Administrator under subsection (a)(2) and the determination of the President regarding its adoption.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDBBF7D1D466541D78EFA08384DAC10ED"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report under paragraph (1) may be submitted in classified form.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HE08A87517CB84D8A9AF7A854B2075498"><enum>8.</enum><header>Studies and recommendations on necessity of security clearances</header> <subsection id="H39CFD73A816A45EE8835D24A142AA0B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Studies on necessity of security clearances</header> <paragraph id="H2CF35F98A98E447CBB61026BDBEEB9EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Studies required</header><text>The head of each agency that grants security clearances to personnel of such agency shall conduct a study on the necessity of such security clearances.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3A810EAEB2244D839F4EB93BF147F4F0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports required</header> 
<subparagraph id="HEB7CB28A9D3A4BFBB3D8AF3774D5042B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, each head of an agency that conducts a study under paragraph (1) shall submit to Congress a report on the findings of the head with respect to such study, which the head may classify as appropriate.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA0E110FC72494B368A4910FCD497CBB4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Required elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report submitted by the head of an agency under subparagraph (A) shall include, for such agency, the following:</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9DC910A54413434EA4E95FDE72A71F97"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of personnel eligible for access to information up to the Top Secret level.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B4F245201C24CCA9AF9C597F4698A96"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of personnel eligible for access to information up to the Secret level.</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H182794D3BBFE466A8324F4447D726FC5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information on the any reduction in the number of personnel eligible for access to classified information based on the study conducted under paragraph (1). </text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAB389A5479C04C4DBE0E24BFDA17AD7F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of how the head will ensure that the number of security clearances granted by such agency will be kept to the minimum required for the conduct of agency functions, commensurate with the size, needs, and mission of the agency.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA22F5E3F5B62438C988BF79CA4068D21"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Industry</header><text>This subsection shall apply to the Secretary of Defense in the capacity of such Secretary as the Executive Agent for the National Industrial Security Program. The Secretary of Defense shall treat contractors, licensees, and grantees as personnel of the Department of Defense for purposes of the studies and reports required by this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8E8DC317CF824B2DB18E508934F61E22"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Director of National Intelligence review of sensitive compartmented information</header><text>The Director of National Intelligence shall—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96D177719C0E425CA6FA5B48072BEE5C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review the number of personnel eligible for access to sensitive compartmented information; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H61E6034B5B334B1D913A35FB057EF65E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to Congress a report on how the Director will ensure that the number of such personnel is limited to the minimum required.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB22494FE62F147C1A9E4C41885248C58"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Agency review of special access programs</header><text>Each head of an agency who is authorized to establish a special access program by Executive Order 13526 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3161">50 U.S.C. 3161</external-xref> note; relating to classified national security information), or successor order, shall—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8CE60B647BC947699662CF6B82F77BAD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review the number of personnel of the agency eligible for access to such special access programs; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6AC0EA61A0524812844603896879F970"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to Congress a report on how the head will ensure that the number of such personnel is limited to the minimum required.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD474C72A930747C0AD913933DFAD7CED"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Secretary of Energy review of Q and L clearances</header><text>The Secretary of Energy shall—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBB1B035A293E4D06BF6CEF25A8786ED8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review the number of personnel of the Department of Energy granted Q and L access; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD0A3390084A4084A7E01FB22F8CF44F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to Congress a report on how the Secretary will ensure that the number of such personnel is limited to the minimum required.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFE5DA674946C4A408C3092B31B150E12"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Independent reviews</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which a study is completed under subsection (a) or a review is completed under subsections (b) through (d), the Director of the Information Security Oversight Office of the National Archives and Records Administration, the Director of National Intelligence, and the Public Interest Declassification Board shall each review the study or review, as the case may be.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HAC7BD0BFA617497C909634A928985573"><enum>9.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HEDCB43527E7849AFA667F6C91996D99A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given the term <quote>Executive agency</quote> in section 105 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8001C03689DF4220B4EBBD818FA6F8FD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The term <term>classified information</term> means information that has been determined pursuant to Executive order 12958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3161">50 U.S.C. 3161</external-xref> note; relating to classified national security information), or successor order, to require protection against unauthorized disclosure and is marked to indicate its classified status when in documentary form.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H928B7F5E50344290AFBD377CF0EA1CEF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Classification</header><text>The term <term>classification</term> means the act or process by which information is determined to be classified information.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD4A09924C8AB4122B63FDECE9EA165B8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Declassification</header><text>The term <term>declassification</term> means the authorized change in the status of information from classified information to unclassified information.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB0D61705F9D34358ACF9D0EC31F7B23A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Document</header><text>The term <term>document</term> means any recorded information, regardless of the nature of the medium or the method or circumstances of recording.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5581886D8B4404BBDEE76FBA4907215"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Downgrade</header><text>The term <term>downgrade</term> means a determination by a declassification authority that information classified and safeguarded at a specified level shall be classified and safeguarded at a lower level.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB089656DF92241EC8FE255B03F9FB475"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Information</header><text>The term <term>information</term> means any knowledge that can be communicated or documentary material, regardless of its physical form or characteristics, that is owned by, is produced by or for, or is under the control of the United States Government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5BCA253C9D95414A9BB7CF2B95578E34"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Originate, originating, and originated</header><text>The term <term>originate</term>, <term>originating</term>, and <term>originated</term>, with respect to classified information and an authority, means the authority that classified the information in the first instance.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0AADF1EC99AD4611AF71EA865163B155"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Records</header><text>The term <term>records</term> means the records of an agency and Presidential papers or Presidential records, as those terms are defined in title 44, United States Code, including those created or maintained by a government contractor, licensee, certificate holder, or grantee that are subject to the sponsoring agency’s control under the terms of the contract, license, certificate, or grant.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBD2F7A9CC9D845BFB56D49EA39FCB279"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Security clearance</header><text>The term <term>security clearance</term> means an authorization to access classified information.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEA48ED8749DA4ACE961D328988389070"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Unauthorized disclosure</header><text>The term <term>unauthorized disclosure</term> means a communication or physical transfer of classified information to an unauthorized recipient.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4EB396A9467B4A24B962E72525EF465E"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Unclassified information</header><text>The term <term>unclassified information</term> means information that is not classified information.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


