<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB44B1BE0F143455498A72D674A71DCBC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1119 IH: Freedom to Invest in a Sustainable Future Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1119</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 to permit retirement plans to consider certain factors in investment decisions.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H50243D3F50EB4604AC51732E2FDAD472" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H19C9480DFA9C4993A0F1833264909684"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Freedom to Invest in a Sustainable Future Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2C850E5F0F1E4CF5A86597E1C99EC534"><enum>2.</enum><header>ERISA amendments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (a) of section 404 of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1104">29 U.S.C. 1104</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H37483D77B5D44409BE6297A96EBB5D38"><paragraph id="H8EE9388F57A9409B87114FD2D3B2391B" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5BAE86CEFFA841DFA0933F4F8C2FF5AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Provided that a fiduciary discharges the fiduciary's duties with respect to a plan in a manner otherwise consistent with this subsection, a fiduciary may—</text><clause indent="up1" id="HA1FB9873ED1E4C00BD60C8119F4BB3A4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consider environmental, social, governance, or similar factors, in connection with carrying out an investment decision, strategy, or objective, or other fiduciary act; and</text></clause><clause indent="up1" id="H28C6925E6F01405B8596362A5872D8DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>consider collateral environmental, social, governance, or similar factors as tie-breakers when competing investments can reasonably be expected to serve the plan’s economic interests equally well with respect to expected return and risk over the appropriate time horizon.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="HAA4019784EE945D38BE6E548A77BBB15"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In a case described in clause (i) or (ii) of subparagraph (A), a fiduciary shall not be required to maintain any greater documentation, substantiation, or other justification of the fiduciary’s actions relating to such fiduciary act than is otherwise required under this part.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="HFADD81EB01564581B8AFCB3C7CAC32EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Nothing in this part shall preclude an investment selected in accordance with clause (i) or (ii) of subparagraph (A) from being treated as a default investment or a component of such a default investment (as described in regulations issued by the Secretary under subsection (c)(5)(A)), if such investment would otherwise qualify for such treatment under such regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

