<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H76F052AB061D44C585AD68A7D5E2F6A8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 596 IH: Anti-Border Corruption Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 596</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230127">January 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Anti-Border Corruption Act of 2010 to authorize certain polygraph waiver authority, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF641F338E9AE49FA9F6668203C855068" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H19313B401ED64AD988890C1AF615C39D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Anti-Border Corruption Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDA40B2F1214C4A62A4C62BB24A5568FD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Hiring flexibility</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3 of the Anti-Border Corruption Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/376">Public Law 111–376</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/221">6 U.S.C. 221</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (b) and inserting the following new subsections:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H22E7408F7B374574B76A9F77B969D92D" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HA295DD0FF99D4B3F8D3572F5C3895717"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><text>The Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection may waive the application of subsection (a)(1) in the following circumstances:</text> <paragraph id="H8119A158658148D3855BB6177EA3565B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of a current, full-time law enforcement officer employed by a State or local law enforcement agency, if such officer—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA96ACCAA958947D4AB9FBC2FC6D68650"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has served as a law enforcement officer for not fewer than three years with no break in service;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5C0DAB4E1E434461AE1FE6E4031EA16C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is authorized by law to engage in or supervise the prevention, detection, investigation, or prosecution of, or the incarceration of any person for, any violation of law, and has statutory powers for arrest or apprehension;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE39D0403EA7243C1B60008244C112753"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is not currently under investigation, has not been found to have engaged in criminal activity or serious misconduct, has not resigned from a law enforcement officer position under investigation or in lieu of termination, and has not been dismissed from a law enforcement officer position; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H7D6B0052224D4E09865987AF9312858C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>has, within the past ten years, successfully completed a polygraph examination, described in subsection (c), as a condition of employment with such officer’s current law enforcement agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H613EA89ADBBD41C9BB32D3911923219C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the case of a current, full-time law enforcement officer employed by a Federal law enforcement agency, if such officer—</text> <subparagraph id="H42A77E9DFB2E4291AE5EE63A2D6EF2F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has served as a law enforcement officer for not fewer than three years with no break in service;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB2F3BD497B9A448BB85D363E36D21337"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has authority to make arrests, conduct investigations, conduct searches, make seizures, carry firearms, and serve orders, warrants, and other processes;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3A680C56F108438E96570A5F439A9B32"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is not currently under investigation, has not been found to have engaged in criminal activity or serious misconduct, has not resigned from a law enforcement officer position under investigation or in lieu of termination, and has not been dismissed from a law enforcement officer position; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HB3B6594B0F124FA9AEB5431FAAC10F8E"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">holds a current background investigation to the level required for service as a law enforcement officer with U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB2D592110303449CBB76E5322E554FB4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In the case of an individual who is a member of the Armed Forces (or a reserve component thereof) or a veteran, if such individual—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA799AE29397D4C96B4DD115AB14A811E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has served in the Armed Forces for not fewer than three years;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5236E6AA6694D28A238702FDFB8A5FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>holds, or has held within the past five years, a Secret, Top Secret, or Top Secret/Sensitive Compartmented Information clearance;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H119BF5F5BE1644B691EA7965810899A8"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">holds or has undergone and passed a background investigation to the level required for service as a law enforcement officer with U.S. Customs and Border Protection;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB3797F78B21948B3907D24B43CA94E54"><enum>(D)</enum><text>received, or is eligible to receive, an honorable discharge from service in the Armed Forces and has not engaged in criminal activity or committed a serious military or civil offense under the Uniform Code of Military Justice; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFAC523A5C6384581805935274C15F6DC"><enum>(E)</enum><text>was not granted any waivers to obtain the clearance referred to subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF433E37EBC38401CBB31DC172490EC07"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Certain polygraph examination</header><text>A polygraph examination described in this subsection is a polygraph examination that satisfies requirements established by the Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Director of National Intelligence.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H12AEC5479E8C41D2B03B2BBC978459D1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Supplemental commissioner authority and definitions</header> 
<subsection id="H9864A51CFD454D07A31F376CB2E37C8E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Supplemental commissioner authority</header><text>Section 4 of the Anti-Border Corruption Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/376">Public Law 111–376</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block id="H0C20E063032742FCA7BF5B7A7B61A724" style="OLC"> <section id="HBB4BDCAE145740409B708E694E5E77C1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Supplemental commissioner authority</header> <subsection id="HAB84C84F88E84DBD9B7C741064FDD36F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Non-Exemption</header><text>An individual who receives a waiver under subsection (b) of section 3 shall not be exempt from other hiring requirements relating to suitability for employment and eligibility to hold a national security designated position, as determined by the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H624A8D4A3A52458FA41D62AD5AE6DE4C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Background investigations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any individual who receives a waiver under subsection (b) of section 3 who holds a current background investigation may be subject to further background investigation to the level required for service as a law enforcement officer with U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HCB04D600D9EC407CB6E1DD0182E7A1CE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Continuous evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any individual who receives a waiver under subsection (b) of section 3 shall not be exempt from any requirement relating to continuous evaluation established by the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2667A2F7806B4AA2A0F8D896646CFB0E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration of polygraph examination</header><text>The Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection is authorized to administer a polygraph examination to an applicant or employee who is eligible for or receives a waiver under subsection (b) of section 3 if information is discovered prior to the completion of a background investigation that results in a determination that a polygraph examination is necessary to make a final determination regarding suitability for employment or continued employment, as the case may be.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H2AC0ED07036849C4AC4DEB8145D9167E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Anti-Border Corruption Act of 2010 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HDFADA141C8D54C9E9C0FE79E4EBF6DA1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H64618AF6D3C44C3E89C10CAD7E00F2F3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section and every year for the next four years thereafter, the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection shall provide the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate information on the number, disaggregated with respect to each of paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (b) of section 3, of waivers requested, granted, and denied, and the reasons for any such denial, and the final outcome of the application for employment at issue. Such information shall also include the number of instances a polygraph examination was administered under the conditions described in subsection (d) of section 4, the result of such examination, and the final outcome of the application for employment at issue.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HA207A00BABA34AB89FD4E39AA641F485"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>The Anti-Border Corruption Act of 2010, as amended by subsection (b) of this section, is further amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H779936227AC14591AEFAC5228C4463F6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC712B922DCD44A6ABF28B4E683E90CB3"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HB1FF4B7FFE534020937D7A35779ED2F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Law enforcement officer</header><text>The term <quote>law enforcement officer</quote> has the meaning given such term in sections 8331(20) and 8401(17) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDD260C9988D44F879E279C173878DCDF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Veteran</header><text>The term <quote>veteran</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101(2) of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49248A69959A4B7D9B291071F8B9AF58"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Serious military or civil offense</header><text>The term <quote>serious military or civil offense</quote> means an offense for which—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H56F07A1127C84FAA905149EA63C438FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a member of the Armed Forces may be discharged or separated from service in the Armed Forces; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H71C5787F1D9140F58EDC109038FC52DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a punitive discharge is, or would be, authorized for the same or a closely related offense under the Manual for Court-Martial, as pursuant to Army Regulation 635–200 chapter 14–12.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H4F3FF815B0CE42E48F112C5912F26356"><enum>4.</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (15) of section 411(c) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/211">6 U.S.C. 211(c)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>section 3(1)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 3</quote>.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

