<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3D937B66FF444D77A2CB61567FA7F8F1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4952 IH: To amend title 10, United States Code, to establish the Office of Strategic Capital in the Office of the Secretary of Defense, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4952</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 10, United States Code, to establish the Office of Strategic Capital in the Office of the Secretary of Defense, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8FB4D6F255F0489A87E1759C9ED01802" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7D3BA1D3470543149A97F2EFE35C57E8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of Office of Strategic Capital</header> 
<subsection id="HDF9B5CC1903749628132E83AD6C82A91"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/4">Chapter 4</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> <quoted-block id="HC674E37050534B98B7D2D0693F1B7E96" style="USC"> <section id="HEF6E8A7310A6440E9F255AEC7368EA6D"><enum>148.</enum><header>Office of Strategic Capital</header> <subsection id="HE0311F43997D4E1FBEA369EC12610DBA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is in the Office of the Secretary of Defense an office to be known as the Office of Strategic Capital (in this section referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1367A777A84B4616A91BE5223E97C0FA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The Office shall be headed by an Executive Director (in this section referred to as the <quote>Director</quote>), who shall be appointed by the Secretary of Defense from among employees of the Department of Defense in Senior Executive Service or equivalent positions (as defined in section 3132 of title 5).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H729A855CCB864E4AA698EBE76FBBE419"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Office shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC6D5C2698C6A4871A4DCFE64F29DFDD7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify, accelerate, and sustain the establishment, research, development, construction, procurement, leasing, consolidation, alteration, improvement, or repair of tangible and intangible assets vital to national security;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A240B9C94354B618A05B566C00EC4D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>protect vital tangible and intangible assets from theft, acquisition, and transfer by countries that are adversaries of the United States; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H077DD46BA12D48A8A0A313C4A77C0428"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide capital assistance to eligible entities engaged in eligible investments.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0A47414A65444626A9B8A86F7D8FB2A1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity seeking capital assistance for an eligible investment shall submit to the Director an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Director may require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4A89A5231AB24C30B7AF1EF0059854BA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection of investments</header><text>The Director shall establish criteria for selecting among eligible investments for which applications are submitted under subsection (d). Such criteria shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H5C39C04C038C467EA9325222154C61F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the extent to which an investment is significant to the national security of the United States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB630E99B7C90436588E3EC2BAA1B5E1A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the creditworthiness of an investment; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBCC2C34CC79A4D40B043A2FE27518362"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the likelihood that capital assistance provided for an investment would enable the investment to proceed sooner than the investment would otherwise be able to proceed.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4B9C10B268054D42AE5AF0729B45EF16"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Capital assistance</header><text>The Secretary of Defense is authorized to provide capital assistance within this section.</text> <paragraph id="H6D323BC5CF0944C39037ECBA88766287"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Loans and loan guarantees</header> <subparagraph id="H5C6838835E8F4D3E948EF3F77912AE53"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Office may provide loans or loan guarantees to finance or refinance the costs of an eligible investment selected pursuant to subsection (e).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H26C2F42FA7FB492AAEC98E150DA4FF0C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Administration of loans</header> 
<clause id="H463AD15BD337435CBA6A5D80082E963C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Interest rate</header> 
<subclause id="H5EFD2995852C4397A7F929308732C74B"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided by subclause (II), the interest rate on a loan provided under subparagraph (A) shall be not less than the yield on marketable United States Treasury securities of a similar maturity to the maturity of the loan on the date of execution of the loan agreement.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB52F5F8072BD4152B25C1F3ACFF20268"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Director may waive the requirement under subclause (I) with respect to an investment if the investment is determined by the Secretary of Defense to be vital to the national security of the United States.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H140A9853028143408E16F5D61B8D225A" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>The Director shall establish separate and distinct criteria for the interest rates for loan guarantees with private sector lending institutions.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H85B937840C7449FAA0B0EC8B50F6D424"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Final maturity date</header><text>The final maturity date of a loan provided under subparagraph (A) shall be not later than 50 years after the date of substantial completion of the investment for which the loan was provided.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD1ABEBC43F1547DABC322C840D275FE7"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Prepayment</header><text>A loan provided under subparagraph (A) may be paid earlier than is provided for under the loan agreement without a penalty.</text></clause> <clause id="H4A5E62480B804FE29D279F4FCEE94407"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Nonsubordination</header> <subclause id="H247C4B28A53647E99BE19E80C30AD21E"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A loan provided under subparagraph (A) shall not be subordinated to the claims of any holder of investment obligations in the event of bankruptcy, insolvency, or liquidation of the obligor.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HCC3554CFF1744EB4AA967B05F8DA43DA"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Director may waive the requirement under subclause (I) with respect to the investment in order to mitigate risks to loan repayment.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HCD798253B90148BCB008B3A97737A672"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Sale of loans</header><text>For which a loan is provided under subparagraph (A) and after notifying the obligor, the Director may sell to another entity or reoffer into the capital markets a loan for the investment if the Director determines that the sale or reoffering can be made on favorable terms.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H83E198AF190A43FB94E12DF2EDE1C342"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Loan guarantees</header> 
<subclause id="HA8D4FE1DF13C44C5BF6A2ADE4B39A909"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Director determines that the holder of a loan guaranteed by the Office defaulted on the loan, the Director shall pay the holder as specified in the loan guarantee agreement.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H59F7862C11EF450A98236857AC22F77C"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Loan guarantee percentage</header><text>A loan guarantee agreement entered into by the Office under this paragraph shall specify the percentage of the principal amount of the loan guaranteed by the Office under such agreement.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H44E89E56BFA44A6C9E54A4CB7B35AAFB"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Terms and conditions</header><text>Loans and loan guarantees provided under subparagraph (A) shall be subject to such other terms and conditions and contain such other covenants, representations, warranties, and requirements (including requirements for audits) as the Director determines appropriate.</text></clause> <clause id="H0B2D83B46FDC497BB416778A2D72A1AC" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><header>Investment-grade rating</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall establish a credit rating system to ensure a reasonable likelihood of repayment of loans made or guaranteed under this subsection. The credit rating system may include the use of existing credit rating agencies as the Director determines appropriate.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFD13B852DEBE431484C0E2DE97CFA6DD"><enum>(ix)</enum><header>Applicability of federal credit reform act of 1990</header><text>Loans and loan guarantees provided under subparagraph (A) shall be subject to the requirements of the Federal Credit Reform Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661">2 U.S.C. 661 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDD4B43D0F3B3400F849C91ECDE9D1D3B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Equity investments</header> <subparagraph id="H2CE1A0F98279431EA8C4BB9079F20245"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director may, as a minority investor and subject to the availability of appropriations this purpose, support an eligible investment selected pursuant to subsection (e) with funds or use other mechanisms for the purpose of purchasing, and may make and fund commitments to purchase, invest in, make pledges in respect of, or otherwise acquire, equity, warrants, or quasi-equity securities or shares or financial interests of the eligible entity receiving support for the eligible investment, including as a limited partner or other investor in investment funds, upon such terms and conditions as the Director may determine.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8CFD580B13C34630953F4F7B553DBACE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Sales and liquidation of position</header><text>The Office shall seek to sell and liquidate any support for an investment provided under subparagraph (A) as soon as commercially feasible, commensurate with other similar investors in the investment and taking into consideration the national security interests of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11C3E10D0947459AA398C83756C34C3D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Director may provide technical assistance with respect to developing and financing investments to eligible entities seeking capital assistance for eligible investments and eligible entities receiving capital assistance under this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD8D234CD231744E6A41C3EAF86156730"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Terms and conditions</header> 
<subparagraph id="H38AEC6C5A96944B68C5BE3A0FEE8BBC3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Fees</header><text>The Director may charge fees for the provision of capital assistance under this subsection to cover the administrative costs to the Office of providing such assistance.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H90BA6E534F714461BCC5843BC22DC396"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use of fees</header><text>Fees collected pursuant to subparagraph (A) may only be used to pay for the cost of administering the activities authorized by this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDFBC9C844FF94CD3986248B4CC4F96BF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Amount of capital assistance</header><text>The Director shall provide to an eligible investment selected pursuant to subsection (e) the minimum amount of assistance necessary to carry out the investment.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5130EDB0B09A4C1DA6055A647F7C204E"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Use of United States dollar</header><text>All financial transactions conducted under this subsection shall be conducted in United States dollars.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H043A2179544643E1A4AA97405B096BEF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Establishment of Accounts</header> 
<paragraph id="H48216DCA29BA436AB8E7D399D5ED05EB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Credit program account</header> 
<subparagraph id="H1CAB1AE30B8045DDB7B3C8D145588383"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Treasury of the United States an account to be known as the <quote>Department of Defense Credit Program Account</quote> (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Credit Program Account</quote>) to make loans and loan guarantees under this section in accordance with the Federal Credit Reform Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661">2 U.S.C. 661 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H183A8B94F5F240A78FBFE38B6FCF8487"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Credit Program Account shall consist of amounts appropriated to the Credit Program Account pursuant to an authorization of appropriations and all fees as described in subparagraph (C).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA92EDC2E5DCF44C3B7FB1CC296B39AD3"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Fee authority</header> 
<clause id="H8FB2F11DACF3407EA81D0A77D0A3B367"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may charge and collect fees for providing capital assistance in an amount to be determined by the Secretary to cover the costs to the Office of providing such capital assistance.</text></clause> <clause id="H3AE339AB218947AB98D4B46624D58E03"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of the fees under clause (i) shall equal, but not exceed, the costs to the Office of providing capital assistance.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H852465226FF94874881A0EFE815812CC"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Use of fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fees collected pursuant to clause (i) may only be used to pay for the cost of administering the activities authorized by this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4AFA584D8E0D4031AE7A3A4AA7194437"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Equity account</header> <subparagraph id="H47603DC017A24079A7CCE9308EE3B1CC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Treasury of the United States an account to be known as the <quote>Department of Defense Strategic Capital Equity Account</quote> (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Strategic Capital Equity Account</quote>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H74EAF68185BB450D9623D95581871F29"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Strategic Capital Equity Account shall consist of all amounts appropriated to the Strategic Capital Equity Account pursuant to an authorization of appropriations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC24D3C0F9B974EEBBC4578BA44680DCA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to appropriations Acts, the Secretary is authorized to pay, from the Credit Program Account or the Strategic Capital Equity Account—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5A781732ACE54CE9AD7A46734E180D3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the cost, as defined in section 502 of the Federal Credit Reform Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661a">2 U.S.C. 661a</external-xref>), of loans and loan guarantees and other capital assistance;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0817CCCA2F664389AD44E6868AC6E2E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">administrative expenses of the Office associated with activities under this section;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB46695EE39EC42AF8A5442E5453C1C71"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">project-specific transaction costs under this section;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H053BFFAF70CA4C0B912EAF7E5A30D52E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the cost of providing support authorized by this section; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7CFD1C42C3934B64B9DF4CED44F60EF4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the costs of equity investments under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC709B2AAD7C649B7B9D48C9F81A18E20"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Regulations</header> <paragraph id="HEE85BDFA035B48C58DB72786F5ECF86A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall prescribe such regulations as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4F155DD531A9414691EE3F0BB0A3E9A1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation on authorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense may not exercise the authorities under this section prior to promulgating the regulations required by paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H85FDDC540DD94ACE8BC2A1EAB3483C20"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than the first Monday in February of each year, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the congressional defense committees an annual report describing the activities of the Office in the preceding fiscal year and the goals of the Office for the next fiscal year.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6C8CC04EF6D74A0289D08E29A6C613C5"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Congressional notification</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the Director exercises the authority under subsection (f) to make a loan or equity investment or to provide a loan guarantee, insurance, or reinsurance, the Secretary of Defense shall notify the congressional defense committees of such exercise of authority.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9155F6137C31484D857E46A6121060F6"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authorities provided under this section shall expire on October 1, 2028.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD08EA8C6F6C64C9591F33510BD1B38DF"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H6B48D3B5D63A4CC6821A798D223A1B73"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Capital assistance</header><text>The term <term>capital assistance</term> means loans, loan guarantees, equity investments, or technical assistance provided under subsection (f).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6C6F0A38E7B842C7B9239D1FC1B00752"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H6CE24FD0B11E47E297C658E0AA942316"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4F6F35589D5E4118AC725CF8B4986DC0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a corporation, including a limited liability corporation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCE1CA7F01D3540B3A289CA99C41F50AC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a partnership, including a public-private, limited, and general partnership;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC8F026CD8BDE439187A359EC72289999"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a joint venture, including a strategic alliance;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9718CC8BAE0C44809463B0DF94FCCC73"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a trust;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA844FE6A88F347729FE7776CE472FEC8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a State, including a political subdivision or any other instrumentality of a State;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H22218581E3F74067924C38AE96DE0832"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a Tribal government or consortium of Tribal governments;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAA61FF004BAC45519AB7A5AA96EA9241"><enum>(H)</enum><text>any other governmental entity or public agency in the United States, including a special purpose district or public authority, including a port authority; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H28CAC9A8C4584F608D20E696C6181DCE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a multi-State or multi-jurisdictional group of public entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9C502C0A7AFD4FF7B0460168B6FDF660"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible investment</header><text>The term <term>eligible investment</term> means an investment that facilitates the efforts of the Office—</text> <subparagraph id="H1A6F572262204BE08C3C4F181BDAB54F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to identify, accelerate, and sustain the establishment, research, development, construction, procurement, leasing, consolidation, alteration, improvement, or repair of tangible and intangible assets vital to national security; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3ED72A34F09F4F85B9F7604462B6B4AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to protect vital tangible and intangible assets from theft, acquisition, and transfer by countries that are adversaries of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB6E4226E1A664F848425A823C0DA02F5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Investment-grade rating</header><text>The Director shall establish a credit rating system to ensure a reasonable reassurance of repayment. This may include use of existing credit rating agencies where appropriate.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30713899624A4A23AD2DC13E176B3F87"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Obligor</header><text>The term <term>obligor</term> means a party that is primarily liable for payment of the principal of or interest on a loan.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEC668215F408428C94FA6E095FD2F858"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Rating agency</header><text>The term <term>rating agency</term> means a credit rating agency registered with the Securities and Exchange Commission as a nationally recognized statistical rating organization (as that term is defined in section 3(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78c">15 U.S.C. 78c(a)</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H999CE1F0AE844EE887476F0C5FACC92C"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Subsidy amount</header><text>The term <term>subsidy amount</term> means the amount of budget authority sufficient to cover the estimated long-term cost to the Federal Government of a loan—</text> <subparagraph id="H382756FAC66E4455B54C28B2EBA67AA3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>calculated on a net present value basis; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H905F4719D515441B8E7308825D8DADE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>excluding administrative costs and any incidental effects on governmental receipts or outlays in accordance with the Federal Credit Reform Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661">2 U.S.C. 661 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HB9928F4D89094667AD996661A1883CDB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 4 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H53D6BD6D36BC4368BD2CDA8601BCFF3B" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">148. Office of Strategic Capital.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

