<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6FDCBA5E3DE94A15A5FC7030ACF66A8F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5187 IH: Protect Prayer in Schools Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5187</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230811">August 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001132">Mr. Crane</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for a cause of action to remedy prohibitions on personal prayer in schools.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H07C6F8A02ACB44CA802968BEAD320378" style="OLC"><section id="HF02CC591BE824F8E982447875178C61C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Prayer in Schools Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H971721D14C5F48AA883D1FCB3BFEA04F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="HCC74BD362D344730862149BEA5CFDBC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States of America is a nation under God.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07D688E4732E4A079402B233E583C0B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Declaration of Independence makes clear that our nation was blessed by the <quote>Supreme Judge of the world</quote> and our laws are derived from <quote>Laws of Nature</quote> and <quote>Nature’s God.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4007C4D9BF2047FDB9D08B46752D5014"><enum>(3)</enum><text>At the time of the First Amendment’s drafting, many states observed state religions and referred to God in their constitutions—thus, the 1st Amendment was never intended to contrast with the existence and veneration of God throughout our states.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69AFCEAFC3384810B9B5AA0F9D7EC7AC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The intent of the Constitution was never to render the United States a secular country;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8AB7D59BE0D4D01946EE38B43F42B83"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Our Founding Fathers would be appalled to learn the Establishment Clause of the 1st Amendment was being weaponized not to prevent the establishment of a state religion, but to suppress religion in schools across the states, contrary to the Free Exercise Clause.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D3377C0C435443CAE8E2ED3653E633A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>John Adams said in 1789, while addressing the Massachusetts Militia, <quote>Our constitution was made only for a moral and religious people. It is wholly inadequate to the government of any other.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F5687BE1CB245ACB70760DE4C05DAF2"><enum>(7)</enum><text>On June 28, 1813, John Adams wrote to Thomas Jefferson saying, <quote>The general Principles, on which the Fathers Atchieved Independence, were the only Principles in which, that beautiful Assembly of young Gentlemen could Unite, and these Principles only could be intended by them in their Address, or by me in my Answer. And what were these general Principles? I answer, the general Principles of Christianity…</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF01C369AA5B543B093548A8E1601014E"><enum>(8)</enum><text>James Madison wrote in 1785 in his Memorial and Remonstrance Against Religious Assessments <quote>It is the duty of every man to render to the Creator such homage. Before any man can be considered as a member of Civil Society, he must be considered as a subject of the Governor of the Universe.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83BAEB864D4E42D79311CFCE9B8C7629"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Alexander Hamilton wrote to James Bayard in 1802: <quote>I now offer you the outline of the plan they have suggested. Let an association be formed to be denominated </quote>The Christian Constitutional Society,<quote> its object to be first: The support of the Christian religion. Second: The support of Constitution of the United States.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H979CE0743B6D473C9AB50FDB37AE8506"><enum>(10)</enum><text>George Washington, on October 3rd in 1789 at a National Day of Thanksgiving, wrote <quote>… it is the duty of all nations to acknowledge the providence of Almighty God, to obey His will, to be grateful for His benefits, and humbly to implore His protection and favor .</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AE80FAAAD084930BC71842214CC2635"><enum>(11)</enum><text>On May 9, 1833 Chief Justice John Marshall wrote to Jasper Adams: <quote>The American population is entirely Christian, and with us Christianity and Religion are identified. It would be strange indeed, if with such a people, our institutions did not presuppose Christianity, and did not often refer to it, and exhibit relations with it.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H458267154D834CB9A7E95CAE1AEAA636"><enum>(12)</enum><text>On March 28, 1787, Dr. Benjamin Rush wrote an open letter <quote>To the citizens of Philadelphia: A Plan for Free Schools</quote>, saying, <quote>Let the children . . . be carefully instructed in the principles and obligations of the Christian religion. This is the most essential part of education. The great enemy of the salvation of man, in my opinion, never invented a more effectual means of extirpating Christianity from the world than by persuading mankind that it was improper to read the Bible at schools . . . </quote> The only foundation for a useful education in a republic is to be laid in religion. Without this there can be no virtue, and without virtue there can be no liberty.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64383D9ABD0B4CF5BDCAB4D617C8DDC4"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The Same Congress that passed the 1st Amendment, also drafted Article 3 of the Northwest Ordinance which contained the following language: <quote>Religion, Morality and knowledge being necessary to good government and the happiness of mankind, Schools and the means of education shall be forever encouraged.</quote></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H498CCD91FC4E4B9BA5A2E8A50B1EFE50"><enum>(14)</enum><text>While the founders did not wish to establish state religion, they sought to encourage and protect religion throughout the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H15312D2A1B214B40B9F5C82014850F99"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The Supreme Court of the United States held in Kennedy v. Bremerton School District that the Free Exercise and Free Speech Clauses of the First Amendment protect an individual engaging in a personal religious observance from government reprisal.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0F6F03C34374FFB90E24A3FBA2E9CBE"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The Constitution neither mandates nor permits the government to suppress such religious expression.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H85B62A177B0745A4A9231107E349B3FD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Civil action</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Every person who, under color of any statute, ordinance, regulation, custom, or usage, subjects, or causes to be subjected, any citizen of the United States or other person within the jurisdiction thereof to any limitation on the ability of that person to engage in personal prayer in public elementary and secondary schools shall be liable to the party injured in an action at law, suit in equity, or other proper proceeding for redress, except that in any action brought against a judicial officer for an act or omission taken in such officer's judicial capacity, injunctive relief shall not be granted unless a declaratory decree was violated or declaratory relief was unavailable. For purposes of this section, the terms <quote>elementary school</quote> and <quote>secondary school</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

