<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H20C37372D53C4C0CB45A88236915869F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6340 IH: Improving Housing Outcomes for Veterans Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6340</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001090">Mr. Harder of California</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Under Secretary for Health of the Department of Veterans Affairs to provide certain information to Department of Veterans Affairs medical center staff and homelessness service providers regarding the Coordinated Entry program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB1FC738A444D43B9893491D0E0ABC9BE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBD6BA61D94344BE4A6E9082490664F8E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Housing Outcomes for Veterans Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3FE57377090541C2BEBCC303BFEEE3E7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs sharing of information related to Department of Housing and Urban Development Coordinated Entry program</header> <subsection id="H7CA8C1AB7E84467EAA789788DE0B0BCD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary for Health of the Department of Veterans Affairs shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H4F0F4C4371B24EB7AF8109D7EC0267E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide to Department of Veterans Affairs medical center staff and homelessness service providers the information described in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D529C027B6F4BD994FFA0EB2E6D0F45"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that such information, and other resources the Under Secretary determines are appropriate, are accessible to Department of Veterans Affairs medical center staff and homelessness service providers.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD5CBD889C08D40ACA6E448BF5370DA88"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information described in this subsection is information related to best practices with respect to the collaboration between Department of Veterans Affairs medical centers, homelessness service providers, and other local partners (including local Department of Housing and Urban Development offices or public housing agencies) on activities under the Coordinated Entry program of the Department of Housing and Urban Development, including making referrals and sharing data, as the Under Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HBAAE2B3B8BBB4BEFA18E8A4037ABDCC3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs communication with employees responsible for homelessness assistance programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Under Secretary for Health of the Department of Veterans Affairs shall clearly communicate with employees of the Department of Veterans Affairs whose responsibilities are related to homelessness assistance programs regarding—</text>
<paragraph id="H3E2759B0FBBD4FF1B9B9675615015CD1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the measurement of performance by the Homeless Program Office of the Department; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5CABFEEC6F744AB3AD4A4E38E022085D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>how to obtain and provide feedback about performance measures.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

