<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC20F1C5CAD60431DAAFCF01B9B622370" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1110 IH: Knowing the Efficiency and Efficacy of Permanent Telehealth Options Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1110</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Mrs. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Medicare Payment Advisory Commission, and the Medicaid and CHIP Payment and Access Commission to conduct studies and report to Congress on actions taken to expand access to telehealth services under the Medicare, Medicaid, and Children’s Health Insurance programs during the COVID–19 emergency.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H91C2740ED0C44B5E814721B8BD0E5623" style="OLC"><section id="H94ECE983CC6B4A4A90BF101BCD132B76" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Knowing the Efficiency and Efficacy of Permanent Telehealth Options Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>KEEP Telehealth Options Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8AD3D04B38404AF38F25C8F48899F18B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Studies and reports on the expansion of access to telehealth services during the COVID–19 emergency</header><subsection id="H5A46DCE945DC4F19A5DD3EEA6FEA84CC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>HHS</header><paragraph id="H1B92AF8C96994B3581AA6F3FBD7AECD7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary, in consultation with the Administrator, shall conduct a study and submit to Congress a report on actions taken by the Secretary during the emergency period described in section 1135(g)(1)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-5">42 U.S.C. 1320b–5(g)(1)(B)</external-xref>) and through December 31, 2024, to expand access to telehealth services under the Medicare program, the Medicaid program, and the Children’s Health Insurance program. Such report shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H2F8A5FDAFF024D8EBF26D50FFE29EBBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A comprehensive list of telehealth services available under such programs and an explanation of all actions undertaken by the Secretary during such emergency period and through December 31, 2024, to expand access to such services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C00FBD6A7EA47859271AC9B41400CA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A comprehensive list of types of providers that may be reimbursed for such services furnished under such programs during such period and through December 31, 2024, including a list of services which may only be reimbursed under such programs during such period and through December 31, 2024, if furnished by such providers in-person. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9C4AFF9225148408C6F1BF975E54071"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A quantitative analysis of the use of such telehealth services under such programs during such period and through December 31, 2024, including data points on use by rural, minority, low-income, and elderly populations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA47218EABCFF411FB1B52A1C43DBED62"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A quantitative analysis of the use of such services under such programs during such period and through December 31, 2024, for mental and behavioral health treatments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9B456B16BB34AE997D2BD97F378C6D2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An analysis of the public health impacts of the actions described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDAF15CED7594BFA9553B3980954C7B3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication of report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall publish on the public website of the Department of Health and Human Services the report described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H153EB7E0266A480D85B3B19009ED183A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>MedPAC and MACPAC</header><paragraph id="H9BC809EFB13D495B880BDF2B380FE996"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Medicare Payment Advisory Commission and the Medicaid and CHIP Payment and Access Commission, in consultation with the Inspector General of the Department of Health and Human Services, shall each conduct a study and submit to Congress a report on—</text><subparagraph id="H4BCD9A68829A4D1EB2419AC4250173CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any improvements to, or barriers in, access to telehealth services under—</text><clause id="H7581A84F0F0F492FA9989D690CDFD818"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of the report submitted by the Medicare Payment Advisory Commission, the Medicare program; and</text></clause><clause id="H2C9AD5B3BB5A49DDB153E11B20D86D7A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of the report submitted by the Medicaid and CHIP Payment and Access Commission, the Medicaid and Children’s Health Insurance programs;</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">during the emergency period described in subsection (a)(1) and through December 31, 2024; and </continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65C9D0EAB43F44F7AE1B95889228A8B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">what is known about any increased risk in increased fraudulent activity, including the types of fraudulent activity, that could be associated with the expansion of access to such services under such programs during such period and through December 31, 2024.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H86C65B7FFD5244839FDDB673853F90E4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The reports submitted under paragraph (1) shall include recommendations, as appropriate, on—</text><subparagraph id="H36CC889344074A30A00F00C2A0CD1D82"><enum>(A)</enum><text>potential improvements to telehealth services, and expansions of such services, under the programs described in paragraph (1)(A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1388063366F44E4B3097D0950D46A21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>possible approaches to addressing any fraudulent activity described in paragraph (1)(B). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

