<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H144796E84F7548D6A810B79FA06DEB12" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6868 IH: Protecting Women and Children Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6868</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Attorney General to conduct a review and submit a report to the Congress on grant and other assistance programs of the Department of Justice to support victims of domestic violence, sexual assault, dating violence, or stalking.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEFBD7F0D0785464292FE99440EC786A9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD11511C891D149D9B9D410628204A9A2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Women and Children Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H752BEEEF5C954745BC45BBE9A2DA9BEC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Review of and report on programs supporting victims of domestic violence, sexual assault, dating violence, or stalking</header> <subsection id="HD59B76A29E7E4B29A2E94414FB88D272"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General of the United States shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H395088FD126F4E0387E3B5FD66C5F7C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">complete a review of all grant and other assistance programs of the Department of Justice that support victims of domestic violence, sexual assault, dating violence, or stalking, including such programs under the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Victims of Crime Act of 1984 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20101">34 U.S.C. 20101 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3BA77ED6FB764231A64C6D2FF9C7EF27"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the Congress a report on the results of such review.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5AFDAFC08C214213A0C58DE1EA90C364"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report contents</header><text>The report required by subsection (a)(2) shall include recommendations for changes to the grant and other assistance programs referred to in such subsection—</text> <paragraph id="HADFE1E1164C44B7EAA9DD139BCAD6C21"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to increase protection and other support of victims of domestic violence, sexual assault, dating violence, or stalking, particularly in rural areas; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31CCA3C1D7F34F8BA101752CD9FCF535"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to provide such victims with pathways out of the environment in which the victims have been mentally, verbally, physically, or sexually abused; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H94648D74EC2A41ED97872AEA78815C68"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to encourage and increase long-term support for such victims.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H67F72470706F42C7B842F6C9CFD62016"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public awareness campaign</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General of the United States shall publish the report required by subsection (a)(2) and take such other steps as may be appropriate to increase awareness of the programs described in subsection (a)(1) among State agencies, nonprofit organizations, and other entities eligible to apply for assistance through such programs.</text> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

