<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDF90261AAECA459488365DDFE447AA06" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1103 IH: Hong Kong Economic and Trade Office (HKETO) Certification Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1103</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the President to remove the extension of certain privileges, exemptions, and immunities to the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices if Hong Kong no longer enjoys a high degree of autonomy from the People&#8217;s Republic of China, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAF912897E4D0414EBE3379D45F970978" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF6F03EE2209F409F9EB61DF6497C8D93" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hong Kong Economic and Trade Office (HKETO) Certification Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H428CD0F2BB58459F9180286BEDA71324"><enum>2.</enum><header>Certification on whether to extend certain privileges, exemptions, and immunities to the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices in the United States</header> <subsection id="H4B621EE3B51A4E51B08767D1010DAB85"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Certification required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and thereafter as part of each certification required by the Secretary of State under section 205(a)(1)(A) of the United States-Hong Kong Policy Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/5725">22 U.S.C. 5725(a)(1)(A)</external-xref>), the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a certification that—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC2F7D7E9307D4AA0863A114D0E78F7BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6E95DD88CFD34A92B003F14128A595D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">merit extension and application of the privileges, exemptions, and immunities specified in subsection (b); or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HF8F89D66F53847DA8895A7696F6237BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>no longer merit extension and application of the privileges, exemptions, and immunities specified in subsection (b); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC892F893A8DF4176AE9B23671BC90A53"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a detailed report justifying that certification.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5D58D80A827D45E7AE1FB1210C1F1AB5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Privileges, exemptions, and immunities specified</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The privileges, exemptions, and immunities specified in this subsection are the privileges, exemptions, and immunities extended and applied to the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices under section 1 of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to extend certain privileges, exemptions, and immunities to Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices</quote>, approved June 27, 1997 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/288k">22 U.S.C. 288k</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD9A8F8F554CC454AB8ABF3E1CC454A0D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effect of certification</header> <paragraph id="H768986C2A1254A73990B53A1108979C4" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>If the President certifies under subsection (a)(1)(B) that the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices no longer merit extension and application of the privileges, exemptions, and immunities specified in subsection (b), the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices shall terminate operations not later than 180 days after the date on which that certification is delivered to the appropriate congressional committees.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8481E396CB344C1398198A791BF6DD43"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Continued operations</header><text>If the President certifies under subsection (a)(1)(A) that the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices merit extension and application of the privileges, exemptions, and immunities specified in subsection (b), the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices may continue operations for the one-year period following the date of that certification or until the next certification required under section 205(a)(1)(A) of the United States-Hong Kong Policy Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/5725">22 U.S.C. 5725(a)(1)(A)</external-xref>) is submitted, whichever occurs first, unless a disapproval resolution is enacted under subsection (f).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB402F2B3AF4A4E4EA4D6633C1880D1A4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Revocation of extension and application of privileges, exemptions, and immunities</header><text>The President may revoke the extension and application to the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices of the privileges, exceptions, and immunities specified in subsection (b).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HBF0F83E0D6E04039A6BC6DB323EED1F5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination of certification requirement</header><text>If the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices terminate operations in the United States, whether pursuant to subsection (c) or otherwise, the President shall not issue additional certifications under subsection (a)(1) after the date on which those operations terminated. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HB75DC44217BE4785AF48C8B44519BD1D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Congressional review</header> <paragraph id="HF975B3CCE04D4277A7144BF5992FDFA9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Disapproval resolution</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>disapproval resolution</term> means only a joint resolution of either House of Congress—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCE06D860EF5F4E4A9C169033FEFFBE3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the title of which is the following: <quote>A joint resolution disapproving the certification by the President that the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices continue to merit extension and application of certain privileges, exemptions, and immunities.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H57CE648F0C114DE49A6B5C1E1542C448"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the sole matter after the resolving clause of which is the following: <quote>Congress disapproves of the certification by the President under section 2(a)(1)(A) of the <short-title>Hong Kong Economic and Trade Office (HKETO) Certification Act</short-title> that the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices merit extension and application of certain privileges, exemptions, and immunities, on ___. </quote>, with the blank space being filled with the appropriate date.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD3CB5FE3D03E429980A4F7533E6822B2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Introduction</header><text>A disapproval resolution may be introduced—</text> <subparagraph id="H943E112FF4984FFC80F4A578910B733C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the House of Representatives, by the majority leader or the minority leader; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD09224F72B3145FCBA5EF5E7FE216C74"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the Senate, by the majority leader (or the majority leader’s designee) or the minority leader (or the minority leader’s designee).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE0463A930BEB4108AC3BC13699CC14DB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Floor consideration in House of Representatives</header><text>If a committee of the House of Representatives to which a disapproval resolution has been referred has not reported the resolution within 10 legislative days after the date of referral, that committee shall be discharged from further consideration of the resolution.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5BA5238817AA43CC9D6958A8E330B994"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consideration in Senate</header>
<subparagraph id="H865733F48350451892742059AC033D78"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Committee referral</header><text>A disapproval resolution introduced in the Senate shall be referred to the Committee on Foreign Relations.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H52699BC50BEF4F979E357C4A6DA59411"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reporting and discharge</header><text>If the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate has not reported the resolution within 10 legislative days after the date of referral of the resolution, that committee shall be discharged from further consideration of the resolution and the resolution shall be placed on the appropriate calendar.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0939D132727241C8AD1805A24B18AF5F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Proceeding to consideration</header><text>Notwithstanding Rule XXII of the Standing Rules of the Senate, it is in order at any time after the Committee on Foreign Relations reports a disapproval resolution to the Senate or has been discharged from consideration of such a resolution (even though a previous motion to the same effect has been disagreed to) to move to proceed to the consideration of the resolution, and all points of order against the resolution (and against consideration of the resolution) are waived. The motion to proceed is not debatable. The motion is not subject to a motion to postpone. A motion to reconsider the vote by which the motion is agreed to or disagreed to shall not be in order.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42AD9166F3E14827BF96847B0BBDC1CF"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rulings of the Chair on procedure</header><text>Appeals from the decisions of the Chair relating to the application of the rules of the Senate, as the case may be, to the procedure relating to a disapproval resolution shall be decided without debate.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5A9E1DC0262D4520A527079CFB23EEF0"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Consideration of veto messages</header><text>Debate in the Senate of any veto message with respect to a disapproval resolution, including all debatable motions and appeals in connection with the resolution, shall be limited to 10 hours, to be equally divided between, and controlled by, the majority leader and the minority leader or their designees.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7BD6A62C770B444C911161768E6CA6B4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rules relating to Senate and House of Representatives</header> <subparagraph id="HADFD4D648B624EB4966A2D9CDA3C6190"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Treatment of Senate resolution in House</header><text>In the House of Representatives, the following procedures shall apply to a disapproval resolution received from the Senate (unless the House has already passed a resolution relating to the same proposed action):</text>
<clause id="H76AD5DC532EF4C579F3F20857413387B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The resolution shall be referred to the appropriate committees.</text></clause> <clause id="H3EC01AFBAE354652B375C5C82BABFC51"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>If a committee to which a resolution has been referred has not reported the resolution within 10 legislative days after the date of referral, that committee shall be discharged from further consideration of the resolution.</text></clause>
<clause id="HE0A1A15EF83D4D13B7B82723A002BE8D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Beginning on the third legislative day after each committee to which a resolution has been referred reports the resolution to the House or has been discharged from further consideration thereof, it shall be in order to move to proceed to consider the resolution in the House. All points of order against the motion are waived. Such a motion shall not be in order after the House has disposed of a motion to proceed on the resolution. The previous question shall be considered as ordered on the motion to its adoption without intervening motion. The motion shall not be debatable. A motion to reconsider the vote by which the motion is disposed of shall not be in order.</text></clause> <clause id="H3971C09BC89C44618F822C5E2C98BBB5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The resolution shall be considered as read. All points of order against the resolution and against its consideration are waived. The previous question shall be considered as ordered on the resolution to final passage without intervening motion except 2 hours of debate equally divided and controlled by the offeror of the motion to proceed (or a designee) and an opponent. A motion to reconsider the vote on passage of the resolution shall not be in order.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEC7D1BC49B46485D9B4CC976FC0C13C5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment of House resolution in Senate</header>
<clause id="H0BD8A174F24C4E209B41D5B80965382B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Received before passage of Senate resolution</header><text>If, before the passage by the Senate of a disapproval resolution, the Senate receives an identical resolution from the House of Representatives, the following procedures shall apply:</text> <subclause id="HB0CBE2578CB34521B34BB5B8C1B4618B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>That resolution shall not be referred to a committee.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H69ED71A5A2C246F9A4C0D53394DC4431"><enum>(II)</enum><text>With respect to that resolution—</text> <item id="HDE2683714DD14EC89A93897331AA3E66"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the procedure in the Senate shall be the same as if no resolution had been received from the House of Representatives; but</text></item>
<item id="H3319F1FDAD9043EC9D107AFD3EC2693E"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the vote on passage shall be on the resolution from the House of Representatives.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H2EE610E7DD8D4BEAB3F67945F8E648BC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Received after passage of Senate resolution</header><text>If, following passage of a disapproval resolution in the Senate, the Senate receives an identical resolution from the House of Representatives, that resolution shall be placed on the appropriate Senate calendar.</text></clause>
<clause id="H1E94B93EF6D94FC09B2D79EF3194B896"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>No Senate companion</header><text>If a disapproval resolution is received from the House of Representatives, and no companion resolution has been introduced in the Senate, the Senate procedures under this subsection shall apply to the resolution from the House of Representatives.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDCFC1BC691064781A3193A68458F6EF8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Application to revenue measures</header><text>The provisions of this subparagraph shall not apply in the House of Representatives to a disapproval resolution that is a revenue measure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAA1EABF6FB134AF798A0134304DA9039"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Rules of House of Representatives and Senate</header><text>This paragraph is enacted by Congress—</text> <subparagraph id="HD9B964CAD8EF4EB8993796EB6AEF4064"><enum>(A)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the Senate and the House of Representatives, respectively, and as such is deemed a part of the rules of each House, respectively, and supersedes other rules only to the extent that it is inconsistent with such rules; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H877A7BAC9B18439AB18D212EFAD0BCD6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H79BE6E17E7B7433B89C36400299F9DF8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3147943E857A4F58B7CF2233504762A2"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF4BB3BA2ACB4D1BB1727F0138890527"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices</header><text>The term <term>Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1(c) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to extend certain privileges, exemptions, and immunities to Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices</quote>, approved June 27, 1997 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/288k">22 U.S.C. 288k</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HC7E1FF61B1D3447883FE0143B66A2F9E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Limitation on contracting relating to Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices</header>
<subsection id="H555DA44AE39F4EC89F06EF7C72271501"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On and after the date of the enactment of this Act, an entity of the United States Government may enter into an agreement or partnership with the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices to promote tourism, culture, business, or other matters relating to Hong Kong only if— </text> <paragraph id="HBF364785DFA74DA98BD46FF01BD9FF02"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the President has submitted to the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives a certification under section 2(a)(1)(A) that the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices merit extension and application of certain privileges, exemptions, and immunities; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H01AFF7B0772C437DBA64467A17928FC6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a disapproval resolution under section 2(f) is not enacted during the 90-day period following the submission of that certification.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1B2FD76587E0448EB96434C051099754"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header> <paragraph id="H5683848AC18447C2AEF64978562FF235"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Existing agreements and partnerships</header><text>Not later than 100 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, any entity of the United States Government or any entity that holds a current Federal contract with the United States Government that has in effect an agreement or partnership with the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices, shall submit to the Secretary of State and the Administrator of the General Services Administration a certification described in paragraph (3) with respect to each such agreement or partnership.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2E16BF82C3694BA191A4AB9D34811395" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>New agreements and partnerships</header><text>Not later than 15 days after entering into an agreement or partnership with the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices, an entity of the United States Government or an entity that holds a current Federal contract with the United States Government shall submit to the Secretary of State and the Administrator of the General Services Administration a certification described in paragraph (3) with respect to that agreement or partnership.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HE9B5AA2272B84DEFA954A19DB43E67E6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Certification described</header><text>With respect to an agreement or partnership with the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices, a certification described in this paragraph is a certification that the agreement or partnership does not promote efforts by the Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region and the Government of the People’s Republic of China—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HFA2AD2B6767A498B8C33DE0E11DDB448"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to justify the dismantling of the autonomy of Hong Kong and the freedoms and rule of law guaranteed by the Sino-British Joint Declaration of 1984; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3B64595EAA914FAC8838FAF4CB145302" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to portray within the United States the Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region or the Government of the People’s Republic of China as protecting the rule of law or the human rights and civil liberties of the people of Hong Kong. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA8F2399F7769498288B37A3251671A92"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1(c) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to extend certain privileges, exemptions, and immunities to Hong Kong Economic and Trade Offices</quote>, approved June 27, 1997 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/288k">22 U.S.C. 288k</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> <section id="H846F7AB44B83420B9F515EAE862F7654"><enum>4.</enum><header>Policy of United States on promotion of autonomy of Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States—</text>
<paragraph id="HDD3B54DA039E410DBC8FA035C7C30FB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to ensure that entities of the United States Government do not knowingly assist in the promotion of Hong Kong as a free and autonomous city or the Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region as committed to protecting the human rights of the people of Hong Kong or fully maintaining the rule of law required for human rights and economic prosperity as long as the Secretary of State continues to certify under section 205(a)(1) of the United States-Hong Kong Policy Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/5725">22 U.S.C. 5725(a)(1)</external-xref>) that Hong Kong does not enjoy a high degree of autonomy from the People’s Republic of China and does not warrant treatment under the laws of the United States in the same manner as those laws were applied to Hong Kong before July 1, 1997;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50A49CA50E2C40CD8D897F2BCE36E626"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to recognize that promotion of Hong Kong as described in paragraph (1) should be considered propaganda for the efforts of the People’s Republic of China to dismantle rights and freedom guaranteed to the residents of Hong Kong by the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights and the Sino-British Joint Declaration of 1984;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB033FD82B16C47399D8688BF222E99F2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to ensure that entities of the United States Government do not engage in or assist with propaganda of the People’s Republic of China regarding Hong Kong; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1531B169CD6F469CBACDEE928D126618"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to engage with the Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, through all relevant entities of the United States Government, seeking the release of political prisoners, the end of arbitrary detentions, the resumption of a free press and fair and free elections open to all candidates, and the restoration of an independent judiciary.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

