<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5B3E2973296A4854A8088C44A73EC71A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6426 IH: Our Money in China Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6426</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231115">November 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">Committee on the Budget</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require annual reporting on the availability of Federal funds to persons and entities of China and activities conducted in collaboration with China, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAD0555567463442497B63B01F6017EBA" style="OLC"><section id="HD9949DFD12B142C193BC67024D61D948" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Our Money in China Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H7E11B7A00C3F4A9DA16EF070F0A89241"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on funding</header><subsection id="HCFBDC50FDBCE4C8BBB55B0B449798A91"><enum>(a)</enum><header>General report on Federal funding</header><text>The Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall include in the budget materials submitted in support of the budget of the President (submitted to Congress pursuant to section 1105 of title 31, United States Code) for each fiscal year beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act a report that specifies with respect to each account in the Treasury for which Federal funds are requested in such budget the information described in subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H502660ADA49042C58507F451E5900665"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional report on Federal funding</header><text>The head of each Federal department or agency shall include in the budget materials submitted in support of the budget of the President (submitted to Congress pursuant to section 1105 of title 31, United States Code) for each fiscal year beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act a report that specifies the information described in subsection (c) with respect to each account—</text><paragraph id="H8DA776343F6F419C9025983A24EB1D4B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>from which funds are made available to carry out the programs, projects, or activities of such department or agency; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE512EE800CD14529A82E8770AD638C5C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that is not included in the corresponding report required under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2C2EC58776894EDC8A2C5141C9CE1BFC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report requirements</header><text>The information described in this subsection is the following with respect to an account: </text><paragraph id="HB2D2E3378BB74F25985FC5D87D7EB4E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Each amount made available from such account during the preceding fiscal year to any Chinese person or entity, disaggregated by each such person or entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2ED822EC7FA94ED8BCE3AEAF50B7848D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each amount made available from such account during the preceding fiscal year to any Federal program, project, or activity conducted in partnership with a Chinese person or entity, disaggregated by each such partner.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H141938E8128A4BF98A34B2725287C308"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Each amount made available from such account during the preceding fiscal year to any Chinese person or entity that is owned or controlled by a United States entity, disaggregated by each such United States entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92B8616ADF034AF8B90A997DCDF4A79C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Each amount made available from such account during the preceding fiscal year to any Federal employee for the purpose of carrying out any program, project, or activity in China, disaggregated by each such program, project, or activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C02ADC7F6A74349AD530695159AE9AE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Each amount made available from such account during the preceding fiscal year to any joint, collaborative, or bilateral effort between the United States and China, disaggregated by each such effort.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6AB8E53C310D413C87A1CD92EDA93F69"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>The first report submitted after the date of the enactment of this Act under subsection (a) or subsection (b) shall include the information described in subsection (c) with respect to the 10 preceding fiscal years.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB740C40EBE5D46C9A06FC6AD02F00CCC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act—</text><paragraph id="H6E82EB6CF3234042878FFC5F893357A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chinese person or entity</header><text>The term <term>Chinese person or entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H1A3802FEB44B4C75A0ED99661526B482"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Government of China;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AA21D2AA1B845518174A2A41C29BDE1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Chinese Communist Party;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB12519541D6742FEA657EC21DF6EFEFD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any satellite or other foreign campus of a United States institution of higher education (as such term is defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)) that is located in China;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H128E2DEA195344A7AC2E27847692A51D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an individual who is a citizen or national of China and permanently resides in China; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB157912B6BD34947BF587190E305BFFF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other entity organized under the laws of China, or any jurisdiction within China, including—</text><clause id="H749FFA5E697F4BCFAD988EF6FD2AC3A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any United States branch of such entity; and</text></clause><clause id="HAE372B219E264724BA8E2F4933371F27"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any branch of a United States entity that is located in China.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA01D66380FD9458F9F8BBD617E4A9445"><enum>(2)</enum><header>United States entity</header><text>The term <term>United States entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H3E8162C3E5CE4C6198BAEF8D3FB5BE5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an institution of higher education (as such term is defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4D19BB749124DC6BCDFFB722B58D49C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other entity organized under the laws of the United States or any jurisdiction within the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

