<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="HB4AC28A778B04FDCAD84DC74F4A4E5BC"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5705 IH: Augmentative and Alternative Communication Centers of Excellence and National Technical Assistance Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5705</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To support national training, technical assistance, and resource centers, to ensure that all individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities have access to the augmentative and alternative communication the individuals need to interact with others, in order to learn, work, socialize, and take advantage of all aspects of life in the United States.</official-title></form><legis-body><section section-type="section-one" id="H056B315117F34A89ACA2B99B000AD2A7"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Augmentative and Alternative Communication Centers of Excellence and National Technical Assistance Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>AACCENT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1A8D572BFA87446890B5C73C4F2EC6B6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="HD00BDC47446C47EAA1CD8303DB14FB6A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Communication is a basic human need and fundamental right, and is essential to self-determination, social inclusion, and emotional and physical well-being. In enacting a provision of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (referred to in this section as the <quote>ADA</quote>), Congress recognized that <quote>physical or mental disabilities in no way diminish a person’s right to fully participate in all aspects of society,</quote> and that <quote>the discriminatory effects of communication barriers</quote> are a form of discrimination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9DF7A31ADC34300B0274B33E0CAC550"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Three decades after the passage of the ADA, Americans with significant expressive communication disabilities still experience discrimination in the form of communication barriers, institutionalization, segregation, and relegation to lesser services, programs, activities, benefits, jobs, or other opportunities compared to Americans without significant expressive communication disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE05C5B4724A24DB181FD39A24AA055C3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Data about augmentative and alternative communication is lacking, but it is estimated there are at least 4,000,000 people in the United States who cannot reliably meet their daily communication needs using natural speech.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6952C85F3D4443839B8E0BB1EDC57830"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The population of individuals with significant expressive communication difficulties is at substantial risk for limited education, unemployment, poor health outcomes, poverty, and low quality of life. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9825CDE823F4227A542DB6DDB24348B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>People can acquire a significant expressive communication disability and need augmentative and alternative communication as a result of many health and developmental conditions at all stages of life.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8060C7105BDE4262AA1434FC01ABCA65"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Research indicates that individuals who belong to racial or ethnic minority communities face a greater likelihood of being born with or acquiring expressive communication disabilities, as well as added difficulties in obtaining intervention services, including augmentative and alternative communication.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FD288C943564D9F978F4DDB1AE876CA"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities, schools, families, employers, direct support providers, health care providers, the justice system, and the general public need more information about how to effectively deploy, implement, and ensure continued access to robust communication tools, services, and other supports for individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5C8473D211A464897E0E5442D1E25AC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The lived experiences and writings of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities demonstrate the positive impact augmentative and alternative communication has on their lives. These lived experiences and writings also illustrate the harm that results from denying augmentative and alternative communication to those who need it.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H029BF427EE934E1199939CD0DF036FDD"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The leadership of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities is critical in crafting and implementing effective policies and programs affecting their lives, including policies and programs regarding augmentative and alternative communication. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AC66AD3B22B4F74A56322AFF102BEB6"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The freedoms of expression, and to be understood, are essential to both democracy and to individual well-being. Individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities must be afforded equal rights, opportunities, strategies, technologies, services, and other supports to effectively express themselves and participate in their communities and in democracy.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H622E52CA15234DEE96C768A66356841B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to work toward eliminating the continued discrimination, isolation, marginalization, and denial of equal opportunity of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities by providing for comprehensive national training, technical assistance, and resource centers to improve—</text><paragraph id="HB59055FA3A3C4BA49DD12CDF7C426C49"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">access to a full range of augmentative and alternative communication; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24C9B8F82A8C47B5812856AFBE610643"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">access to equal opportunity; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H786EDCD2F6D748848B76D081F44905E1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">awareness and implementation of relevant laws, policies, and practices; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9988C18C06A94F3680B76D03D0563ED1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">leadership and self-advocacy skills; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCAA355D8BB442F28C40B4E974322422"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">capacity, in the case of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities, educators, professionals, and families; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E77DCACBA934FC8B67A6A5C2EE5A898"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">national statistical data; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H167C5F8938C641B683689B8D7D8BA54B"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">societal awareness.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H939A4B09E95B49F6BBAA90AC0D87BEB8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H400B700CAC3A444EBF50AF2B562184D0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advisory council</header><text>The term <term>advisory council</term> means an 11-person advisory council that—</text><subparagraph id="HABC85F867607492C8256319CF31F4111"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides guidance, recommendations, and oversight to an eligible entity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11B964EACB084D17AAA8898EEEF55C18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is comprised exclusively of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities who collectively have diverse—</text><clause id="H409F8FEE2F294D778573CFD02757329A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>educational and professional backgrounds;</text></clause><clause id="H3D82FB9BE26140DDB5A80BFD9F088C65"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>racial, ethnic, gender, and linguistic identities;</text></clause><clause id="H91CD019D604B495FB3285E243977D294"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>disabilities, including intellectual disabilities, ages, and geographic locations;</text></clause><clause id="H8434B7EA11F44EC6BE2F98082440C49F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>levels of income; and</text></clause><clause id="HD0B8E0CFC0A24664BEF5FB83723AA083"><enum>(v)</enum><text>forms of augmentative and alternative communication relied upon; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF614E38F6F94FC0854F7E3DA6DF6C17"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is subject to each of the following conditions:</text><clause commented="no" id="H143AA8267AA7441382A430263D9EDAEF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The initial council members shall be identified in the grant application by the partners of the eligible entity.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H726078C1B9D147BBA6DE1603B48EE96C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Each member of the advisory council shall be appointed for a period of 5 years.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H234A69899B75469689116AF41FE53660"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Chair and Vice Chair of the council shall be selected by the council members at the first meeting and thereafter as the council determines to be appropriate.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H734A6BC407AA4B09BC8D6A91EA62703E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The council shall fill any vacancy in accordance with section 7(b)(8)(C).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H884244EF032E456FB1F1E1D9FE165288"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Augmentative and alternative communication</header><text>The term <term>augmentative and alternative communication</term> means any tool, method, technology, strategy, service, training, coaching, and other support used to supplement or replace speech.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD988889EE240479D851FF896AAA6742C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Competitive integrated employment</header><text>The term <term>competitive integrated employment</term> has the meaning given the term in section 7 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/705">29 U.S.C. 705</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE82E121532D04CF284A28FA6E7BE1193"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Disability</header><text>The term <term>disability</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12102">42 U.S.C. 12102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6056DBD6FBC0417EBDC894C8EE376A6D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a partnership of at least 2 organizations—</text><subparagraph id="HCEB3E2E5534D4EB19589F4951102D040"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for which the controlling partner of the partnership is a nonprofit organization headquartered in the United States that vests power and authority in individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities in terms of management, staffing, decision making, operation, and provision of services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA38B6080D7374BD5ABB6FF4D9E24CBC0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that includes at least one other organization headquartered in the United States that is either an institution of higher education or an association of professional service providers or educators in the field of significant expressive communication disabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF41028B7A244B9B9CBF1E4ED8D1AD31"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that has a cross-disability and cross-generational focus; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26748869EC924090B45ACE5B469597B4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>that is advised by an advisory council;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C33D83FB7B0473B9EFE478E35A598C8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>that has adopted a mission that values equal opportunity and the fundamental right of communication access, and operating principles that respect the rights of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities to express themselves in the manner of their choosing; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D66DC9A570A42FBA4892B95E9C8BB6C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>of which the organizational members, collectively—</text><clause id="HD32FDE58C70346F78B125E8946AFD881"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have knowledge, experience, and capacity in conducting training, technical assistance, or knowledge dissemination related to the priority activities described in section 6;</text></clause><clause id="H4E4AF9C167FC47B4B3F25BEDF78302DC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have experience working directly with individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities in association with—</text><subclause id="H00253F212FC94844B911B8997637D1C3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>early intervention programs, early childhood programs, elementary or secondary schools, or postsecondary education programs; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HD25E89A2A3DD4B93B02CB5353EB4060C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>2 or more types of entities from among—</text><item id="HED97B02953C641ACAF883F69CFB6D175"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>centers for independent living authorized under part C of title VII of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/796f">29 U.S.C. 796f et seq.</external-xref>);</text></item><item id="H01ED23812EE9467AA0EF6983837998BB"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>home and community-based service providers;</text></item><item id="H0A7A1969F0DC4137B970A2A270C40F69"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>employers;</text></item><item id="H0CBFD00CF2804181A7F945B02FFE308D"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>health care providers;</text></item><item id="H30E32F2725F14850ABE49DAE0E94E79A"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>protection and advocacy organizations;</text></item><item id="HBD938CA65DDD44A0ACC9E33DD7439905"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>aging networks;</text></item><item id="H4E4C787533D44F4AA49F3B3EE018F914"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>caregiver organizations; or </text></item><item id="H01641E54F6AA4CD0854E3E51A39B9114"><enum>(hh)</enum><text>State, Tribal, or local government agencies; and</text></item></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6750D6941F45433D9131AE77848647FE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>have experience developing and maintaining collaborative working relationships among disability-led advocacy organizations, institutions of higher education, professional associations, or caregiver organizations. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFD011602392C43C286521B3E4CAF802C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Evidence-based</header><text>The term <term>evidence-based</term>, used with respect to assistance that is knowledge, a resource, training, or technical assistance, means assistance—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA4C9A19B24D7418A8CC6EE3029918E0D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that demonstrates a rationale based on a high-quality research finding or positive evaluation that such assistance is likely to improve a communication outcome or other relevant outcome; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC537F36B834E4DDF9736CFEF86F33306"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for which ongoing efforts are made to examine the effects of the assistance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H46FC8BAE9BFA4E9AB1F1876D5CDD3332"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Individual with significant expressive communication disabilities</header><text>The term <term>individual with significant expressive communication disabilities</term> means an individual of any age—</text><subparagraph id="H15F14E33678442158685EDC2361A8AAB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who has 1 or more real or perceived significant expressive communication disabilities and may have other disabilities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC13469D102F244ECA3A0F01F573E30FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whose disabilities result in the individual's need for, or benefit from, augmentative and alternative communication and other supports to enable the individual to communicate and to aid the individual in participating in 1 or more aspects of life.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H55751256BB4D43CCB50ABFA3A8127605"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H104E89E9FAEA45999A7416DD8AAE0EBA"><enum>(9)</enum><header>National resource center</header><text>The term <term>national resource center</term> means a National Resource Center on Augmentative and Alternative Communication referred to in section 5(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H93E74DCA34D94804A2E18679DF2B25CA"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF24177CCAF949D5A85C18263D3F153A"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Significant expressive communication disability</header><subparagraph id="H6F6EB80C3A604EC3B6425CC1B406DD8A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>significant expressive communication disability</term> means any disability, whether congenital, developmental, or acquired at any point in life, that prevents or significantly limits an individual from understanding or being understood using spoken words, resulting in the individual’s need for or benefit from augmentative and alternative communication. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60D8A47E1907470AA83F0E5CE5A84C2D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The term does not apply to an individual whose primary communication disability is visual or auditory in nature, but does apply to an individual with a disability described in subparagraph (A) who also has a visual or auditory communication disability and who may communicate using sign language.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE074E73626C4A2D845F0DFD7850E560"><enum>(12)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means the 50 States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H74775FED2A87455B8DA401576BC60A9D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grants</header><subsection id="H838C6BECDB224D0286228C9001F2C8FE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award 3 grants through an open competition to eligible entities, with applications approved under section 7, to create, maintain, and administer a network of National Resource Centers on Augmentative and Alternative Communication. Each national resource center shall be a comprehensive training, technical assistance, and resource center created to work toward eliminating the continued discrimination against, isolation of, marginalization of, and denial of effective communication for and equal opportunity of, individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities, through activities including the priority activities described in section 6.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD306AA1D472D4A51A1086B85DC5B7371"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Awards for multiple centers</header><text>The Secretary shall award the grants for national resource centers in 3 geographically diverse locations, and shall designate one of the centers as the lead administrative center. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6BD9A7A402C74585841EDDB27CE38354"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Lead Administrative Center</header><text>The lead administrative center shall coordinate—</text><paragraph id="H33BB565D8347451FA0431D8590C2F2DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all activities of the centers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA58A343C3E1942B68A376D39926502DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>specialization of priorities among the centers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H852ED9AEE8C04AE3A4652F5A59DB3263"><enum>(3)</enum><text>dissemination of information among the centers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2DBFEFFE8D245D88A39A1836D42C462"><enum>(4)</enum><text>responses of the centers to the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DE8C6910A1D4D3393298C183D8718AB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ensuring that the full range of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities is served by the centers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H64B62ECF45404E4FB5BC6D4B0B2623FB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The Secretary shall, to the extent practicable, award the 3 grants in amounts that total not more than $9,000,000 per year of a period described in subsection (e).</text></subsection><subsection id="H4F248795F81F42E798BA540CF65A6255"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Periods</header><text>The Secretary shall award each grant for a period of 5 years, through an open competition held initially and at the end of each 5-year period. An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may reapply for such a grant at the end of the grant period.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE8D2FFE796CD448BB3514A74BF357254"><enum>6.</enum><header>National resource center priority activities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The priority activities of a national resource center shall be to—</text><paragraph id="H7DFE349BF5C84F238725A2DE2E0BE51D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>increase access to and effective implementation of the full range of augmentative and alternative communication for all individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities in the United States, regardless of age, race, ethnicity, gender, gender identity, LGBTQ+ status, immigration status, educational achievement, socioeconomic condition, primary language, nature or severity of disability, location of residence, and age of onset of the significant expressive communication disability;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H066D8000E204477C94D1E5883E0602BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>increase the capacity of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities, educators, professional service providers, families, and direct support professionals to support individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities by creating and disseminating evidence-based knowledge, resources, training and technical assistance, and recommended practices in ensuring individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities have the tools and other supports necessary to exercise self-determination and effectively access and participate in all aspects of life, including education, employment, health care, and community living;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25B020E0DD954789AC7CC1A480D8DBB2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promote awareness and implementation of the laws, regulations, policies, practices, procedures, and systems that facilitate access to the full range of augmentative and alternative communication and promote equal access and opportunity for individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E140C1690804570AE770B92A276B644"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support and enhance the skills and leadership of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities and their families to advocate for the rights of the individuals to effective communication, education, self-determination, access to justice, and equal opportunity and participation in all aspects of life;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2820032A103B486ABD98C58C4A4051F2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support the improved collection, availability, and dissemination of demographic and characteristic data, with a cross-disability and cross-generational focus, regarding individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities in the United States, the barriers the individuals experience to meaningful access to augmentative and alternative communication, and the unmet communication support and other needs of this population; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE21E9F4F7FD14829B8782C20D477B3D2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>increase societal awareness and knowledge about individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities and the importance of, need for, benefits of, and rights to meaningful access to effective communication tools and other supports in all aspects of community and life.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HCFF77159047942EBB6603788FEF34856"><enum>7.</enum><header>Applications</header><subsection id="HD36F78EEC03E45A39BF2F5AE47E1EC24"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be qualified to receive a grant under section 5, an eligible entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA136AE2DADB4110826B2B0990F8EFBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each such application from an eligible entity shall include, at a minimum, each of the following:</text><paragraph id="HADE1E41C2E0E48CCA931257601D71DD5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the experience of each partner organization in the entity in providing training, information, advocacy, and support related to augmentative and alternative communication and individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD850811203274FB2A078F2F9C7608620"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of each partner organization’s experience in providing training, information, advocacy, and support related to augmentative and alternative communication and to individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities, to—</text><subparagraph id="H464DACD010D44D0D95D8E5636DB5EC25"><enum>(A)</enum><text>early intervention specialists; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46EE5A1B82F243BBA30A637A67EFBA21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>elementary education, secondary education, postsecondary education, and specialized instructional support personnel as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCF135CEA2A043669D512049C3F202A3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>caregiver groups; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CDBB324C0B34E1EBAB47698E8457BAA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>providers of home and community-based services for adults;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE986DE28BE27455F931BA37C18EDFF6E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>health care providers and educators; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CF9B5E88CAE47AAB98FB3CB40178BA9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>employers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50B914595BD44E05AF8D15FFECEF07A6"><enum>(G)</enum><text>providers of services to older adults; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BB6936855A443AA9489E892AEEC3B34"><enum>(H)</enum><text>law enforcement agencies, courts, offices of district attorneys, and other public and private security agencies and businesses; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EFCF1C9745B4544BA09E94CC42B2BA8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>institutional long-term care services and support providers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD7B96CE45244D48AF7230C49CC0B5D4"><enum>(J)</enum><text>nursing home providers; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10CD677CBB0047D1B0E7C4CEB7EEF8E9"><enum>(K)</enum><text>other stakeholders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6AA329D7C1D47CF878C821638441D9F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of each partner organization’s experience working with State, local, or Tribal government agencies in providing training, information, and support related to augmentative and alternative communication for full expression and individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF68739F547E4373A3934B94F813B22A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of each partner organization’s prior partnerships with disability-led organizations focused on augmentative and alternative communication and individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64B35FC7B14A45FC84129660AFC48FE1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Evidence of how the applicant satisfies the requirements of section 4(5).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEACCDDC23E164D6D8D37FC764F4FE028"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A description of the applicant’s plan to ensure that the applicant will provide training, technical assistance, and information to target audiences, especially those audiences in need of knowledge and access to augmentative and alternative communication. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF096945559CA48EDB58735A2B70FEFC5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A description of the applicant’s plan to implement the priority activities in section 6, including how the organizational members of the eligible entity will partner, collaborate, and operationalize the activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD7C70A08BA648E58F341AEB06FC1122"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Advisory council information, including—</text><subparagraph id="H32A06A96398D4E538C34E833C56B7027"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the advisory council, including a list of the inaugural members of the advisory council;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75F5522515BE4241852687B126D14400"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assurance that the Chair and Vice Chair of the advisory council will be selected by the advisory council members at the first meeting of the advisory council and thereafter as the council determines to be appropriate; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E32504ACE144EBBBA90E3E9A96E1329"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assurance that, in filling a vacancy on the advisory council, the advisory council will—</text><clause id="HDF910CEEFBE04FEA92BE51B341E215F1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>solicit nominations from the population of augmentative and alternative communication users;</text></clause><clause id="H520A588AF2CD44A6A3977252FD86126F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if there is not more than 1 nominee for the vacancy, confirm the nominee as a new member; and </text></clause><clause id="H6A8C604283EE4A83B1C545C96DE2E9C0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if there is more than 1 nominee for the vacancy, vote to determine the nominee to fill the vacancy and subsequently confirm the nominee.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2E452ABD99F4148A33F1595F7A96F9B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A description of how other individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities will be involved in the governance and operations of the national resource center involved, especially through employment of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA784FBD55D3747589FD89A4E3ADFC27E"><enum>(10)</enum><text>A description of how the applicant will design and make training, technical assistance, and information available in accessible formats, including plain language.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5802D504CF0249688101C658D33DBAA0"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Assurances that the applicant, acting through the national resource center, will work with the stakeholders identified in section 9(d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF312A3E189F049C9BEC009E2C0451FF1"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Assurances that the applicant, acting through the national resource center, will provide the Secretary with requested data and information for purposes of evaluating the grant activities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD719EB2358C3466EB13BEA92C78D259F"><enum>8.</enum><header>Award priority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In awarding grants for activities described in this Act, the Secretary shall give priority to an eligible entity with at least 1 partner organization that—</text><paragraph id="H6C88B8C19800414DB3C72B2CE5F24E6E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>demonstrates a minimum of 3 years of experience providing training and technical assistance and disseminating information related to augmentative and alternative communication and individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities, and being otherwise engaged in the priority activities described in section 6;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F690D71B5954C81B5867F2999BE0F4F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>demonstrates that individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities and those who use augmentative and alternative communication are purposefully involved in the governance and operation of the organization, especially through their employment in service, delivery, and leadership positions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BE6FDCCE5834458ABBD24E54785D08E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>demonstrates the ability to collaborate with disability self-advocacy, education, direct service, health care, employment, aging, caregiver, and housing organizations, whether the organizations are public agencies or private entities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB653F57BA73A4FC5A80C6E50E5B483E7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>demonstrates expertise in promoting accessibility and the use of universal design (the latter as defined in section 103 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1003">20 U.S.C. 1003</external-xref>)) in providing training and technical assistance, and information dissemination.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB447E147BFF8446A9C64C28F91887145"><enum>9.</enum><header>Use of funds</header><subsection id="H951C57D8B1514671BEEE18CD26362877"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under section 5 shall use the grant funds to manage and carry out each of the priority activities described in section 6, activities described in this section, and any additional activities approved by the Secretary. </text></subsection><subsection id="HAFF18BE6B9724C6E850419E8015B1119"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination with Federal programs</header><text>The work of a national resource center shall link to current and future policy and activities undertaken throughout the Federal Government in relation to self-advocacy, supported decision making, person-centered planning, community living, and competitive integrated employment for individuals with disabilities and particularly for individuals with the most significant expressive communication disabilities, for the purpose of increasing—</text><paragraph id="H513FA8F56E494A81ADFC90EBE8295513"><enum>(1)</enum><text>success and self-determination in life; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C77C7BD41804D79B0BA5E3AEC6431A6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the provision of inclusive early intervention services, elementary education, secondary education, and postsecondary education programs; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FCEAB187055453CAD33E637CC4D7729"><enum>(3)</enum><text>competitive integrated employment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA78E9A84AED40DFAE2A8BE0960C57A0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>health, wellness, and personal safety;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72CD28578B0A47ECA2C5D992CEE7409D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>economic security; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H787D1EA4561546538B691FEA17CF3653"><enum>(6)</enum><text>civic engagement; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H013EB63AD32543BB995B4CC1BBB7A024"><enum>(7)</enum><text>community integration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB11C55FA9DDA4515A6D09B3B34245FA6"><enum>(8)</enum><text>improvement in other aspects of life.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAE5AD873D77F43DA8AA31F8E6B5529A8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Information dissemination</header><text>Notwithstanding the priority activities described in section 6, a national resource center shall ensure information and other resources about augmentative and alternative communication and individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities are made available as appropriate to—</text><paragraph id="H8F0B460540C34D2580D14EEE4CE68C57"><enum>(1)</enum><text>individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities and their families;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H011076A9FF6648BF8E671F8DC8A386EA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>institutions of higher education;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4DF7386500649AD853D51E358ADAAE1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>State, Tribal, and local educational agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF2E3ECCE3B54D159CD836D546777038"><enum>(4)</enum><text>law enforcement agencies, courts, offices of district attorneys, and other public and private security agencies and businesses; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16CFCB795532486C8199558002C5C798"><enum>(5)</enum><text>national, State, regional, Tribal, and local employers, to enable businesses to hire into competitive integrated employment more individuals who use augmentative and alternative communication;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF0612DA978142B79B3C394B0BFA7DB1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>national, State, Tribal, and local government agencies that provide services and other supports to individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities, including agencies responsible for emergency preparedness, employment support, and vocational rehabilitation, agencies responsible for State programs under the Assistive Technology Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3001">29 U.S.C. 3001 et seq.</external-xref>), agencies responsible for State alternative financing programs, State agencies responsible for the Medicaid program under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>), and the agencies overseeing the provision of home and community-based services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB3BE665C87C43ACBEC1D2FD07DA9748"><enum>(7)</enum><text>national and local disability and aging advocacy organizations, including disability self-advocacy organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FD1617A2B5D4C62B05FE6807EB8A776"><enum>(8)</enum><text>family support organizations, including the parent training and information centers supported under section 671 of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1471">20 U.S.C. 1471</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F54B44AE382413CB257EBD5393D4AF7"><enum>(9)</enum><text>centers for independent living and Statewide Independent Living Councils authorized by title VII of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/796">29 U.S.C. 796 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96D1A372105549F08258FAD4A077C66B"><enum>(10)</enum><text>network partners, including the State Councils on Developmental Disabilities described in section 125 of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15025">42 U.S.C. 15025</external-xref>), the protection and advocacy systems described in section 143 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15043">42 U.S.C. 15043</external-xref>), and University Centers for Excellence in Developmental Disabilities Education, Research, and Services supported under subtitle D of title I of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15061">42 U.S.C. 15061 et seq.</external-xref>), participating in activities under that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15001">42 U.S.C. 15001 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36610CE2D18842868512997C976FA963"><enum>(11)</enum><text>State agencies and area agencies on aging, entities carrying out long-term care ombudsman programs, and other entities funded under the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3001">42 U.S.C. 3001 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF30A999050E4B918F0ED6A29117F7D7"><enum>(12)</enum><text>health care providers and educators, health care advocacy organizations, nursing home providers, and institutional long-term care facilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3B6812C059845D89AE146692CEB527D"><enum>(13)</enum><text>professional organizations and organizations that certify preservice training programs; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA2175CB62E64B5295EB1D000318DFE2"><enum>(14)</enum><text>other groups and entities as identified by the eligible entity and the advisory council of the eligible entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE221EBBE5C4E40A8906FBC799D364D7A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Stakeholder collaboration</header><text>A national resource center shall collaborate with—</text><paragraph id="H94409B8F01394E42912667A14447983B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>organizations of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81739C894ACC478C9207075EA06047EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>disability organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BD1DC5070454217B628F33857DAC00E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>entities carrying out State assistive technology programs and State alternative financing programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29F5DDE696F546C896E8AC96FC39BE47"><enum>(4)</enum><text>State, Tribal, and local educational agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA2B34D79CFE40AEA32B39395F5CE443"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the councils, systems, and university centers described in subsection (c)(10);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE2144B1D020420385C79E1C0D06B5E4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>entities carrying out national, State, Tribal and Native Hawaiian, and local programs authorized by the Older Americans Act of 1965;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD007AAD916254A96837E3761F2118F1F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the federally funded Rehabilitation Engineering Research Center on Augmentative and Alternative Communication;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B3DF2FD0EA2414FAF1EDE43DAD53213"><enum>(8)</enum><text>State agencies responsible for vocational rehabilitation programs, as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9BCB5D07FB04C5C98E0EB59CFC012BE"><enum>(9)</enum><text>professional associations whose members come in contact with and support individuals who may use augmentative and alternative communication; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FC3DD50320F424ABEB902E6D5A613A6"><enum>(10)</enum><text>local boards, as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71B6980ACCAF4A95BBCBCCE2E1C558ED"><enum>(11)</enum><text>other State, regional, Tribal, and local entities with the ability to provide support for individuals who need and use augmentative and alternative communication.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5B9EBCE0313148F1A2093FA195949F12"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>A national resource center that receives grant funds under section 5 for a fiscal year shall use not more than 15 percent of the funds for the administrative costs of carrying out activities under this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H9F57533BCF9D4D738B61B598671CB0AA"><enum>10.</enum><header>Annual report</header><subsection id="H8FFEE535DE9143DA8DB309E0B7E13371"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Preparation</header><text>The lead administrative center referred to in section 5(b), in coordination with the other national resource centers that receive grant funds under section 5, shall annually prepare a report containing, consistent with criteria established by the Secretary, information on—</text><paragraph id="H4236F98FB09A4899B30AD8FBF396BC38"><enum>(1)</enum><text>activities conducted by each national resource center funded under section 5 to achieve the purpose of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C8D1D24BBF94F558EB58B0F37B22548"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collaboration by each such national resource center with other entities to achieve the purposes of this Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB81D84077EE4214BB6DD4D610CDE900"><enum>(3)</enum><text>barriers to and strategies for equitable access to augmentative and alternative communication and other supports for individuals who belong to racial, ethnic, and linguistic minority communities and face a greater likelihood of being born with or acquiring significant expressive communication disabilities as well as added difficulties in obtaining effective augmentative and alternative communication;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB3FD37447864624826625D6D317CEDF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identified gaps in available demographic and characteristic data on individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities in the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC95129C5BD38458DBE61E4DD805B5C74"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the unmet needs of individuals with significant expressive communication disabilities, from diverse backgrounds, in the United States and policy recommendations to address such unmet needs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H83F2702C2F2148C2A18CF2FAF2848A91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>The lead administrative center shall submit the report to—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H051E3C10947F460B9E2CCAAB9DAB8745"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H07DBDFDA3CA14F9F829718CB76A61A66"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Education; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H73D0788704B94E2499F265566B9DA730"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the relevant subcommittees of the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, the Special Committee on Aging of the Senate, and the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H91E64CCABD044BC38C75E6F93AA0C2E2"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Subcommittee on Labor, Health and Human Services, Education, and Related Agencies of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, and the Subcommittee on Labor, Health and Human Services, Education, and Related Agencies of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3E53ED5E2C4143FBB9419D46A7E8AD82"><enum>11.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $9,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></section><section id="H16E6C93B4C49480F987A27F4C8F3F1F0" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>12.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nogales Wastewater Improvement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H91F854B9C00A4AE4BFD50EAC50563574"><enum>13.</enum><header>Nogales wastewater improvement</header><subsection id="H6A24E66733D54DFCBD87506F8701F3DD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment to the Act of July 27, 1953</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The first section of the Act of July 27, 1953 (67 Stat. 195, chapter 242; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/277d-10">22 U.S.C. 277d–10</external-xref>), is amended by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic></proviso>, That the equitable portion of the Nogales sanitation project for the city of Nogales, Arizona, shall be limited to the costs directly associated with the treatment and conveyance of the wastewater of the city and, to the extent practicable, shall not include any costs directly associated with the quality or quantity of wastewater originating in Mexico.</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6BC85068B2CB4A87830F4B0198DA289E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nogales sanitation project</header><paragraph id="HB4E26FD439114D63BCA363B7F1EA73C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H3EBCF91D31D14EFDBA0D76CE3EE15F9C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>City</header><text>The term <term>City</term> means the City of Nogales, Arizona.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H895B276FAACE479C94FC0E1D9B37DDE1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the United States Section of the International Boundary and Water Commission.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE87B7362D38541809AAC47E9079E7D11"><enum>(C)</enum><header>International Outfall Interceptor</header><text>The term <term>International Outfall Interceptor</term> means the pipeline that conveys wastewater from the United States-Mexico border to the Nogales International Wastewater Treatment Plant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA68874D9A06B4C34A28598F5E1B99ED1"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Nogales International Wastewater Treatment Plant</header><text>The term <term>Nogales International Wastewater Treatment Plant</term> means the wastewater treatment plant that—</text><clause id="HDFD87C6C7A5E495183BDC2AF2B2D8849"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is operated by the Commission;</text></clause><clause id="H3C0DC6ECA4DD4813A66BB2C4DB5BA957"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is located in Rio Rico, Santa Cruz County, Arizona, after manhole 99; and</text></clause><clause id="HEEDCCCBE698B418DB7CFCAC4E6D85F28"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>treats sewage and wastewater originating from—</text><subclause id="H6CF45D6092E6493A88D3BB32EFC80ABF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Nogales, Sonora, Mexico; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HEF8499BD35324BBDBFC5C499EA0DCE83"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Nogales, Arizona.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE1C76E6D21C4660B385972045CD3845"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ownership and control</header><subparagraph id="HCE99F58EAEF34A079B79E72D3A3C386D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B) and in accordance with authority under the Act of July 27, 1953 (67 Stat. 195, chapter 242; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/277d-10">22 U.S.C. 277d–10 et seq.</external-xref>), on transfer by donation from the City of the current stake of the City in the International Outfall Interceptor to the Commission, the Commission shall enter into such agreements as are necessary to assume full ownership and control over the International Outfall Interceptor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD588FE65A5A44BDF836026D8FB624108"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Agreements required</header><text>The Commission shall assume full ownership and control over the International Outfall Interceptor under subparagraph (A) after all applicable governing bodies in the State of Arizona, including the City, have—</text><clause id="H2FD5E1C46BF64F86B91CC84BF042196E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>signed memoranda of understanding granting to the Commission access to existing easements for a right of entry to the International Outfall Interceptor for the life of the International Outfall Interceptor;</text></clause><clause id="H3F9067616E74410A9C8910B7A5B06BF9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>entered into an agreement with respect to the flows entering the International Outfall Interceptor that are controlled by the City; and</text></clause><clause id="H9BAD62C7DE8644F18CC27AD3D18606FE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>agreed to work in good faith to expeditiously enter into such other agreements as are necessary for the Commission to operate and maintain the International Outfall Interceptor.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F0968A0421D4A2985271FE436648E84"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Operations and maintenance</header><subparagraph id="H4D6AC3D0A6494D80813B83C92E7A87C5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning on the date on which the Commission assumes full ownership and control of the International Outfall Interceptor under paragraph (2)(A), but subject to paragraph (5), the Commission shall be responsible for the operations and maintenance of the International Outfall Interceptor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H050A7EFBB47A46E0A875FDB9EA74C3C5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Commission to carry out this paragraph, to remain available until expended—</text><clause id="H5D237FFCCD494074ADE98AA83C885A04"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$6,500,000 for fiscal year 2025; and</text></clause><clause id="H8E08DD2FE97C401F9F964919F2429279"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not less than $2,500,000 for fiscal year 2026 and each fiscal year thereafter.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7806A5E584B547D8BCFFACBB6659EF04"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Debris screen</header><subparagraph id="H2CC382938F6A485AA03D98F783B0C46C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Debris screen required</header><clause id="H24C5FD03933F4A4B87424DFC003498D0"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall construct, operate, and maintain a debris screen at Manhole One of the International Outfall Interceptor for intercepting debris and drug bundles coming to the United States from Nogales, Sonora, Mexico.</text></clause><clause id="H340DD2B5B827400DA3C468B8B59E1B24"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In constructing and operating the debris screen under clause (i), the Commission and the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection shall coordinate—</text><subclause id="HE19E352C92F4497F83C26F8CE52D7BE9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the removal of drug bundles and other illicit goods caught in the debris screen; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H5A0E1751FEA9474988FAF2D0FFDEDFC2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>other operations at the International Outfall Interceptor that require coordination.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52B8D403C81B430284E6515804B1DADC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Commission, to remain available until expended—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD23FCC678346415E806C8073FB4E4E1E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2025—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H265FA1F5CFC545A5A62D0DA4EC04E251"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$8,000,000 for construction of the debris screen described in subparagraph (A)(i); and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H390F1337AD2147DF9CFC0FA0A28B6414"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not less than $1,000,000 for the operations and maintenance of the debris screen described in subparagraph (A)(i); and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9D5577CE50724B32AE49B69357FFCC64"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not less than $1,000,000 for fiscal year 2026 and each fiscal year thereafter for the operations and maintenance of the debris screen described in subparagraph (A)(i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H562847DFCE4744D7AB484B5D9D1EC71B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Limitation of claims</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">Chapter 171</external-xref> and <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/28/1346">section 1346(b)</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Federal Tort Claims Act</quote>), shall not apply to any claim arising from the activities of the Commission in carrying out this subsection, including any claim arising from damages that result from overflow of the International Outfall Interceptor due to excess inflow to the International Outfall Interceptor originating from Nogales, Sonora, Mexico.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E4AED1CFAB74C40806E5046D5F01539"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section (including the amendments made by this section) takes effect on October 1, 2024.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

