<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8EE146AE48684A56AC45C3A4DB5A2925" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4474 IH: COCOA Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4474</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001126">Mr. Carey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to confirm the requirement that States allow access to designated congressional election observers to observe the election administration procedures in elections for Federal office.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H758AC7B2DEE04F8C86F314F27A32E959" style="OLC">
<section id="H165A093D16B74552ABF50BACA0888128" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header>
<subsection id="H07A2C7D915F34687BC2FB2EB9A146EE2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Confirmation Of Congressional Observer Access Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote>COCOA Act of 2023</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H644C8D92A17C48448150A162F1296421"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings relating to Congressional election observers</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H6D2A2960B67D4C029DEEE67C0E76745E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Constitution delegates to each of House of the Congress the authority to <quote>be the Judge of the Elections, Returns and Qualifications of its own Members</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7FD12700AAF34DB1B3880A5B7B02D8FE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>While, in general, Congress shall respect the determination of State authorities with respect to the election of members to each House, each House of Congress serves as the final arbiter over any contest to the seating of any putative Member-elect or Senator-elect.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H83AFC2C068544871845BE1401D3A1F2E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>These election contest procedures are contained in the precedents of each House of Congress. Further, for the House of Representatives the procedures exist under the Federal Contested Elections Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H614B60F9637549DE9C6499B6318BC5CB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In the post-Civil War modern era, more than 100 election contests have been filed with the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA1B7B30F7A994ACBA54EC282FC72E976"><enum>(5)</enum><text>For decades, Congress has appointed and sent out official congressional observers to watch the administration of congressional elections in the States and territories.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H33AC25E9C4124A6CB543626CFAF4228E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>These observers serve to permit Congress to develop its own factual record in preparation for eventual contests and for other reasons.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA94A12507E864C0B85D75A839CE3A303"><enum>(7)</enum><text>This section and the amendments made by this section do not establish any new authorities or procedures but are provided simply to permit a convenient statutory reference for existing Congressional authority and activity.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H53B66CF52A154CAEB1186A7D1E557886"><enum>2.</enum><header>Confirming access for congressional election observers</header> <subsection id="H2F9719A9E04D446E8B92A7D76E20532A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Confirming requirement that States provide access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HFFCF4177F9D74D0793F407DE50073B6D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 304 and 305 as sections 305 and 306; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H60975A2007894827BEB499A8441C4B8F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 303 the following new section:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB8774C8F850D40B48EEC8582ABFAAC21" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="H2FA1D2B1993148799122918D77126059"><enum>304.</enum><header>Confirming access for Congressional election observers</header>
<subsection id="HBEBC60E04B2548A9A944038D408B4E9E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Finding of Constitutional authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds that it has the authority to require that States allow access to designated Congressional election observers to observe the election administration procedures in an election for Federal office because the authority granted to Congress under article I, section 5 of the Constitution of the United States gives each House of Congress the power to be the judge of the elections, returns and qualifications of its own Members.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFFF059219D8D4ED5BABE5EB529BE6788"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requiring States To provide access</header><text>A State shall provide each individual who is a designated Congressional election observer for an election with full access to clearly observe all of the elements of the administration procedures with respect to such election, including but not limited to in all areas of polling places and other facilities where ballots in the election are processed, tabulated, cast, canvassed, and certified, in all areas where voter registration activities occur before such election, and in any other such place where election administration procedures to prepare for the election or carry out any post-election recounts take place. No designated Congressional election observer may handle ballots, elections equipment (voting or non-voting), advocate for a position or candidate, take any action to reduce ballot secrecy, or otherwise interfere with the elections administration process.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H0785F9A8BED24277B8DC08EE1D1F2CE8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Designated Congressional election observer described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, a <quote>designated Congressional election observer</quote> is an individual who is designated in writing by the chair or ranking minority member of the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives or the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate, or the successor committee in either House of Congress to gather information with respect to an election, including in the event that the election is contested in the House of Representatives or the Senate and for other purposes permitted by article 1, section 5 of the Constitution of the United States.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA45BB9BE7FE74EFDB05E017C8734EF55"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>303, and 304</quote>.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H404B3F1DA8B54F7C93D3434F282B1800"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HF5F1DC2D60AB4D1D8BE1503E19F4DB92"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the items relating to sections 304 and 305 as relating to sections 305 and 306; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6C3F1334C88049AE9DC865548569A97B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 303 the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAA137EB645FF427EA310CB33D29CE761" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 304. Confirming access for Congressional election observers.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

