<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCA70891C129B43509A7A315E14953F15" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 468 IH: Building America’s Health Care Workforce Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 468</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000615">Mr. Pence</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000612">Mr. Rose</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000929">Mrs. Spartz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XI of the Social Security Act to extend beyond the COVID&#8211;19 emergency period, with certain modifications, the Emergency Declaration Blanket Waiver relating to training and certification of nurse aides to alleviate burdens imposed on staff of skilled nursing facilities and nursing facilities.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H26679CC577094F3D8AE995982F12CD3F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDB806A05B02745B799203E948BC83267" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Building America’s Health Care Workforce Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H623C8F56B8684B24B12F66958F877574"><enum>2.</enum><header>Extension and modification of COVID–19 Emergency Declaration Blanket Waiver relating to training and certification of nurse aides for certain employment at nursing facilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1135 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-5">42 U.S.C. 1320b–5</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HB1F99220B4E740B4AC8EA64A8DB51BB1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1), by striking <quote>A waiver</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to subsection (h), a waiver</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BCA63C63C914157B593738045BE1A18"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5045DACBF8924261BF0CEA68FB935E70" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="H68FADD10E5114FB6A01FBFFDF67294E1"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Waivers for nurse aides in training</header>
<paragraph id="H7D2CDC6CADB64B97BD9675A9B20FAFAA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding sections 1819 and 1919, the emergency waiver of requirements under section 483.35(d) of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations, relating to training and certification of nurse aides for employment by skilled nursing facilities under title XVIII and nursing facilities under title XIX, granted by the Secretary under the COVID–19 Emergency Declaration Blanket Waivers for Health Care Providers pursuant to this section shall remain in effect, subject to paragraph (2), for a period that is not less than 24 months after the date of the enactment of this subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE8F151CDDDAD40EDA8612C82F9FF8FA5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Modifications</header><text>For the period described in paragraph (1), the emergency waiver described in such paragraph shall be applied consistent with the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="HC604296BBC8841408F6E3F89BFA087B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding sections 1819(f)(2) and 1919(f)(2), the waiver shall allow for time worked by a nurse aide during the emergency period described in subsection (g)(1)(B) to count toward the 75 hours minimum training described in sections 1819(f)(2)(A) and 1919(f)(2)(A).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H13FD4D24A5E14453A9D35C5959AD9271"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding sections 1819(f)(2)(B)(iii)(I) and 1919(f)(2)(B)(iii)(I), for purposes of sections 1819 and 1919, a competency evaluation of a nurse aide may be conducted at the skilled nursing facility or nursing facility at which the aide is (or will be) employed if the State in which the facility is located does not offer such an evaluation (in person or online) at least once a week.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE5CBC41644E94503A43EFC22AD1CE58B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall conduct a study, and submit to Congress a report, on the appropriateness of maintaining the waiver described in paragraph (1), as modified pursuant to paragraph (2). Such study shall include an examination of the extent to which the waiver and its continuation pursuant to this subsection, as modified, alleviated the burdens imposed on staff of skilled nursing facilities and nursing facilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

