<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE26D4861CA5D4A65859756B0FCFA2A01" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3330 IH: Connecting And Building Lines for Expedited Expansion Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3330</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Communications Act of 1934 to preserve cable franchising authority, provide for faster deployment of cable and other services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H19FA5746B99D4E43ADBA34CB31D82BE3" style="OLC"><section id="HEBAD8331AEB84605AA204E91D01E32D6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Connecting And Building Lines for Expedited Expansion Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CABLE Expansion Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HB21D6E0A2A964D9287FE4010D808666F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Request regarding placement, construction, or modification of cable equipment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 624 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/544">47 U.S.C. 544</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HED21577962D1415E84ED0AB127723063"><subsection id="H6A1B9D9414AC488ABAD89A807ACFA2CD"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Request regarding placement, construction, or modification of facilities</header><paragraph id="H178BA16AA4264948991963BCF5B80D72"><enum>(1)</enum><header>No effect on authority of certain entities</header><text>Except as provided in this subsection, nothing in this title shall limit or affect the authority of a covered entity over—</text><subparagraph id="H09413EE7FE094B71BFFC4B5FAEDBA09F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">decisions regarding the placement, construction, or modification of a covered equipment within the jurisdiction of such covered entity; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBEEA8AB92D994FF5A928499B2EDA8EB3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>safety standards for the placement, construction, or modification of such a covered equipment. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC92A002F7654BE6BB4DF2D778B5CBEE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitations</header><subparagraph id="H789977C0131D46658C81C02CAAB1F063" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Ability to provide or enhance cable service</header><text>With respect to the regulation by a covered entity of the placement, construction, or modification of a covered equipment, the covered entity shall not prohibit or have the effect of prohibiting the ability of a cable operator to provide, improve, or enhance the provision of service using a covered equipment under a franchise granted by such covered entity, or within the jurisdiction of such covered entity, as so may be the case.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H580658991A104DFFA44C350D8F8D1B16"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing of decisions on requests for authorizations to place, construct, or modify facility</header><clause id="HA7F1EED5F97D41D985964BFE279FF7F1" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Timeframe</header><text>A covered entity shall approve or deny a complete request for authorization to place, construct, or modify a covered equipment not later than—</text><subclause id="HFBCCC0263284432395E2E4619D5591C5" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if the request is for authorization to place, construct, or modify a covered equipment in or on eligible support infrastructure, 90 days after the date on which the covered entity receives the request; and </text></subclause><subclause id="HDE4544CDB806470385680C6F5C2E7A08" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if the request is not for authorization to place, construct, or modify a covered equipment in or on eligible support infrastructure, 150 days after the date on which the covered entity receives the request.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9130CE33550E4BBD87DEF52200C4E244"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>Notwithstanding any provision of this title, the applicable timeframe under clause (i) shall apply collectively to all proceedings required by a covered entity for the approval of the request.</text></clause><clause id="H9B9636A769164E849B157A6B6D3F1B96" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>No tolling</header><text>A timeframe under clause (i) may not be tolled by any moratorium, whether express or de facto, imposed by the covered entity on the consideration of any request for authorization to place, construct, or modify a covered equipment.</text></clause><clause id="H860FFD653F6D4FE9B95B351443290122"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Written decision and record</header><text>Any decision by a covered entity to deny a complete request for authorization to place, construct, or modify covered equipment shall be—</text><subclause id="H59BDE07EFDC74D89884B77000CD60506"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in writing;</text></subclause><subclause id="H88D234CF2E054B94AC72EFDFCEBE6B94"><enum>(II)</enum><text>supported by substantial evidence contained in a written record; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HB8068DFD6E4B4615932675DB6926CCB7"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">publicly released, and provided to the requesting party, on the same day such decision is made.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB4A5E99880D64699A939A7440AC9DF22" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Deemed granted</header><text>If a covered entity fails to grant or deny a complete request by the applicable deadline under subparagraph (A)(i), the request shall be deemed granted and authorized on the date on which the covered entity receives written notice of the failure from the requesting party.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H11C203C98C0B4E4D852936DB5BC71352" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>When request considered complete; received</header><subparagraph id="H7F69A2BB768B46E08DA0784A7445A44E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>When request considered complete</header><clause id="H7444DA714A944CA3A7867D84F236FBBB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purposes of this subsection, a request to a covered entity shall be considered complete if the requesting party—</text><subclause id="HCA5525BF4E144C7C9ABBDCE087F0E754" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has taken the first procedural step within the control of the requesting party—</text><item id="H2E1D25B7866B4F4DAEA8613605638F7E" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>that the covered entity requires as part of the process for reviewing such requests; or</text></item><item id="HD4A871E74F47458CBEBD3E343AE33B85" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to submit the type of filing that is typically required to initiate a standard review for a similar request in a jurisdiction that has not established specific procedures for the relevant review and approval of such a request; and </text></item></subclause><subclause id="H9C238CB2A13C473F884D6C0C83017425" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has not received a written notice from the covered entity within 30 days after the date on which the request is received by the covered entity—</text><item id="H369DD66F627646BDB35D86B4D736CEA6" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>stating that all the information (including any form or other document) required by the covered entity to be submitted for the request to be considered complete has not been submitted;</text></item><item id="H44AF9B8334834D0F9A9B5ACDC60ED91D" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>identifying information required to be submitted that was not submitted; and</text></item><item id="HF59CC4E1CA784DC9855825D3B743BA64"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that includes a citation to a specific provision of a publicly available rule, regulation, or standard issued by the government requiring that the information be submitted with such a request.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="HAC7309BB4C5B493E82048C21C68E09D0"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subparagraph, the term <quote>the date on which the request is received by the covered entity</quote> means—</text><subclause id="HDDEEDAC39FDD41A2BB185F17A5C1AD17"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the case of a request submitted electronically, the date on which the request is transmitted;</text></subclause><subclause id="H85DC2263CA274373A25060DFAE31FEAA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of a request submitted in person, the date on which the request is delivered to the individual or at the location specified by the covered entity or in-person submission; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H57DCB300752440E384DA6A18989A2EAF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in the case of a request submitted in any other manner, the date determined under regulations promulgated by the Commission for the manner in which the request is submitted.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92CF0AAEF74548108411B466856DB114" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>When complete request considered received</header><text>For the purposes of this subsection, a complete request shall be considered received—</text><clause id="HBC4BDBFC802E47C6B018415A2ECE1602" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>except as provided in clause (ii), on the date on which the requesting party submits to the covered entity all information (including any form or other document) required by the covered entity to be submitted for the request to be considered complete; or</text></clause><clause id="HD68C3E6A28D94840AC5C36551B58DE5B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a request with respect to which all such information is not submitted and that is considered complete under subparagraph (A)(i) because the requesting party has not received a written notice from the covered entity within the period described in such subparagraph, on the day after the last day of such period.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5BCBEC2C5FE47C1AABF3699F4D0FE4C" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Fees</header><subparagraph id="H8CA74119B50746298E0D0505CBB66D10" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A covered entity may charge a fee that meets the requirements under subparagraph (B) to consider a request for authorization to place, construct, or modify covered equipment. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H392FDF253A084E628E33954D0E7C7BC0" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A fee charged under subparagraph (A) shall be—</text><clause id="HE05AFF62AEA74B2BAE4F36EEDD04DDFA" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>competitively neutral, technology neutral, and nondiscriminatory;</text></clause><clause id="HF937AC7C1F9E41FEAE45122DF207933E" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>publicly disclosed in advance;</text></clause><clause id="H19A89A0A53FF4DF78CAEFEF6BBF28CDA" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>calculated—</text><subclause id="H03519E75DF3741FCB36EB2A5CC9A04C7" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>based on actual and direct costs for—</text><item id="HA3ECF44595F742B8A30CE2940710FC82" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>review and processing of requests; and</text></item><item id="HCDCCBBC8D5BB4DF086765D4A7372FFDE" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>repairs and replacement of—</text><subitem id="H6A9880B3E1BC4547AAB1B2E3DF76FA09" commented="no"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>components and materials resulting from and affected by the placement, construction, or modification (including the installation or improvement) of covered equipment; or</text></subitem><subitem id="HFCD4C10F73DF46988D97D4788EF9DD28" commented="no"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the modification (including the improvement) of eligible support infrastructure, or repairs and replacement of equipment that facilitates the placement, construction, or modification (including the installation or improvement) of such facilities or the modification (including the improvement) of such structures; and</text></subitem></item></subclause><subclause id="HF3483C66F2BA4E66B738138232AE1A90" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>using, for purposes of subclause (I), only costs that are objectively reasonable; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H81986D6ECB1B4C22B7E8A48A5F0AAA59" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>described to a requesting party in a manner that distinguishes between nonrecurring fees and recurring fees.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H458BC20ED9EC4C97BFEF13CAC52B2696"><enum>(C)</enum><header>No relation to franchise fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A fee charged under this paragraph to consider a request for authorization to place, construct, or modify covered equipment may not be considered a franchise fee under section 622. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC43D275A24DC4C4789EA63926E8CCC70"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H795BAE6CDC904BDB96EFD6B753609577" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Covered equipment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered equipment</quote> means equipment used in or attached to a cable system.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC54207682CEE433195B4EB3616DB802C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <quote>covered entity</quote> means:</text><clause id="H2EDC94AB42034AF7A10DFE53F9C15C68" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A State.</text></clause><clause id="H69797F036A0645418CC5FEEA917EFF9C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A local government.</text></clause><clause id="HB2642BAF4F494EF98CC05A60A240FDE0" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An instrumentality of a State or a local government.</text></clause><clause id="H32C5DFC120AC4AA4B7814F9426AF2571" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A franchising authority. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0706B800C29747A5B426C1986FEA957F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Eligible support infrastructure</header><text>The term <term>eligible support infrastructure</term> means infrastructure that supports or houses a facility for communication by wire (or is designed to and capable of supporting or housing such facility) at the time when a complete request to a covered entity for authorization to place, construct, or modify covered equipment in or on the infrastructure is received by the covered entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HC4B41ADE4F854D3AB1A8553F251E32C7" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Action on pending requests</header><subsection id="H77663C8DFB784EF9B6321A9694118666" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraphs (2)(B) and (4) of section 624(j) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/544">47 U.S.C. 544(j)</external-xref>), as added by section 2, shall apply to a—</text><paragraph id="H7547D32BB6A843669393696401015098" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>request received by a covered entity (as such term is defined in section 624(j) of the Communications Act of 1934)—</text><subparagraph id="H09DD5EB3569E4394AE8AE0AF2F2BFA6F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">before the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HABD5B5629EDE468A804438358D3B1E14" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has not been approved or denied by the covered entity on or before such date; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H86094420AD0C4A118DA145D88690011A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a request received by a covered entity on or after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H366D4838ECFF4B669BBA9C1E716AFD62" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Date of receipt</header><text>The date of receipt by a covered entity of a request described under subsection (a)(1) shall be deemed to be the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

