<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBDE2329F8EBB4CAAAF21251E880C6B73" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4114 IH: AAA Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4114</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Committee on Rules</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish procedures to reduce agency funding for failure to adhere to original congressional intent, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H074CC977530747D19B494DF4460D4F9B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD12FE679BD5C40658D931C4DDF946699" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Agency Accountability through Appropriations Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>AAA Act</quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5E95E9023F9A4997A061B89EEEFBBBCC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Procedures for reducing agency funding for failure to adhere to original congressional intent</header> <subsection id="H7CCF3BEA4730426CB8F5A9760B9224C1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report from the President</header> <paragraph id="H66E8A1CF25924187B7746B502EBA6509"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than October 31 of each year, the President shall submit to the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a report that includes, with respect to the previous fiscal year, each rule promulgated by an agency (as such term is defined in subsection (f)) which received funding pursuant to a regular appropriation bill. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H580F2ED2D17644CBBC8E033CDABA9FE6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report format</header><text>The report described in paragraph (1) shall separate each such agency and rule promulgated by each such agency into separate titles of the report pursuant to the regular appropriation bill which provides funding for each such agency.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA4CBDCD85DA142A6AA81CF46323EC9FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Committee hearing with respect to agency rules</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the date each committee described in <internal-xref idref="H7CCF3BEA4730426CB8F5A9760B9224C1" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> receives a report from the President under such subsection, each such committee shall hold a hearing with respect to whether each rule included in such report adhered to the original congressional intent of the relevant agency.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7E87DF62087D47B8AE9343C8E96A0772"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Committee report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During a hearing described in <internal-xref idref="HA4CBDCD85DA142A6AA81CF46323EC9FF" legis-path="2.(b)">subsection (b)</internal-xref>, the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate shall each, with respect to each title of the report submitted by the President under <internal-xref idref="H7CCF3BEA4730426CB8F5A9760B9224C1" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>—</text> <paragraph id="H01B497D6AF9C43C780F9A2CAE06EB5B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>vote on a report that contains the conclusions of the committee with respect to whether each rule promulgated by an agency adhered to the original congressional intent of the relevant agency;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD6EF6A77689E41E7B79E013E284B48A8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case that either committee, by majority vote, determines that any rule promulgated by an agency did not adhere to the original congressional intent of the relevant agency, include in the report a proposed reduction of funding in the regular appropriation bill which provides funding for each such agency for the subsequent fiscal year in the amount equal to one half percent for each rule promulgated that did not adhere with such congressional intent;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D9FB394E9734E76B9B6C83697A6018C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case that the report submitted by the President under <internal-xref idref="H7CCF3BEA4730426CB8F5A9760B9224C1" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> was submitted after the deadline required under <internal-xref idref="H66E8A1CF25924187B7746B502EBA6509" legis-path="2.(a)(1)">subsection (a)(1)</internal-xref>, include in the report a proposed reduction of funding in the regular appropriation bill which provides funding for the Executive Office of the President for the subsequent fiscal year in the amount equal to one half percent for each week during the period that starts on the deadline under <internal-xref idref="H66E8A1CF25924187B7746B502EBA6509" legis-path="2.(a)(1)">subsection (a)(1)</internal-xref> and ends on the date the President submits such report; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19AA1C96A64A4DFBA0ACE1708BA33C59"><enum>(4)</enum><text>submit such report to the House of Representatives or the Senate, as the case may be.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBF52D6768E7F4608A1B2658E0D364766"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Providing for reduction in agency funding</header> <paragraph id="H693F72CE823140D389B57561490BC72F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Procedures in the House of Representatives</header><text>Clause 2 of rule XXI of the Rules of the House of Representatives is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9B8825C18A254F5295E951E8A74326C6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<rules-clause id="H234F46FE532245099B8E7C169BF424B5"><enum>(h)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be in order, if offered by the chair of the Committee on Oversight and Accountability or the chair’s designee, to offer an amendment to a general appropriation bill for a fiscal year providing for a reduction in funding for an agency or, if applicable, the Executive Office of the President in such general appropriation bill in the amount equal to a proposed reduction of funding for such agency or the Executive Office of the President for such fiscal year as reported by the committee pursuant to subsection (c) of the Agency Accountability Act. </text> </rules-clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0CACEA629E7D4BE48CB8946B2B57AE9E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Procedures in the Senate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any rule of the Standing Rules of the Senate, it shall be in order, if offered by the chair of the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate or the chair’s designee, to offer an amendment to a general appropriation bill for a fiscal year providing for a reduction in funding for an agency or, if applicable, the Executive Office of the President, in such general appropriation bill in the amount equal to a proposed reduction of funding for such agency or the Executive Office of the President for such fiscal year as reported by the committee pursuant to subsection (c) of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H29C9A7EC4CAB40F1B57A13F5A788EA22" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exercise of rulemaking power</header><text>This section, except with respect to subsection (a), is enacted by Congress—</text> <paragraph id="H8B7DFCAA8CE24187917CC54F872E7E67"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the House of Representatives and the Senate, respectively, and as such shall be considered as part of the rules of each House, respectively, or of that House to which it specifically applies, and it supersedes other rules only to the extent that they are inconsistent therewith; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H75FC691AA72C4AC993E02CDC652C25CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD363618600764E8FBEC78FAA773C1DAE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the following definitions apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="HF80680DE9EC54EDB86C31F44DCE99D8D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 551(1) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCDF0484BBC544CF2AA495ACE4FEDE49D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule</header><text>The term <term>rule</term> has the meaning given the term in section 551(4) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5BC17DFFFE494763BE2AC99DF52DF036"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regular appropriation bill</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>regular appropriation bill</term> means any annual appropriation bill which, with respect to the Congress involved, is under the jurisdiction of a single subcommittee of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives (pursuant to the Rules of the House of Representatives for that Congress) and a single subcommittee of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate (pursuant to the Standing Rules of the Senate).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE2A93ACE9D93405293242FD02EAE4DA1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act. </text> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

