<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6ED5A618EF824F30BA762DC6BD1F57FD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4955 IH: To name the community-based outpatient clinic of the Department of Veterans Affairs in Monroeville, Pennsylvania, as the “Henry Parham VA Clinic”.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4955</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000530">Mr. Deluzio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To name the community-based outpatient clinic of the Department of Veterans Affairs in Monroeville, Pennsylvania, as the <quote>Henry Parham VA Clinic</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5085A27802694E338110AB05B6178713" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H20047EF93C794F64A93FECE97DA6CC4E"><enum>1.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text> <paragraph id="H4646A86CB80141628297791318CE85A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Henry Parham was born in Emporia, Virginia, in November 1921.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1D38D05B2D0A4B338F805C11479895B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>At age 21, Henry Parham was drafted into the Army and shipped out to England in 1943 with the 320th Barrage Balloon Battalion in preparation for the D-Day invasions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H24586FC52F634850BBD0743B8B674869"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The 320th Barrage Balloon Battalion, a segregated Army unit, consisted of approximately 700 African-American soldiers with the mission of hoisting barrage balloons designed to entangle incoming German planes and prevent them from conducting strafing runs on ground troops.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA99D0B00C52C4F52BE56B4A3C503E635"><enum>(4)</enum><text>On June 6, 1944, Private First Class Henry Parham and his section of the 320th Barrage Balloon Battalion landed at Omaha Beach. With the threat of enemy sniper and rifle fire ever present, PFC Parham’s unit performed their duties, hoisting their barrage balloons 2,000 feet into the air over the beachhead in Normandy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H46DD8088EAD6414B8E8076DADD666B2B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>For two months, Private First Class Henry Parham and the 320th Barrage Balloon Battalion stood watch at Omaha Beach, keeping the pipeline of incoming supplies and Allied troops secure before returning to the United States in September 1944.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4DF66DD1EADD44B3874DA5228DFAE7CF"><enum>(6)</enum><text>After his service, Henry Parham moved to Wilkinsburg, Pennsylvania, where he lived and worked as a heavy equipment operator until 1986. There, he met and married his wife, Ethel Parham, to whom he was married for more than 45 years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H346D3F52F0E24568896DBDB8BD1DF1CA"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Henry Parham died on July 4, 2021, in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, at the age of 99. He was survived by his wife, Ethel, both of whom served for decades as volunteers at the medical center of the Department of Veterans Affairs in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, and local chapters of veterans service organizations.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H62C571A9B69F44BD95B87948B70590BB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Henry Parham was the last surviving African-American combat veteran who took part in the D-Day landings on June 6, 1944.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H4DCB3C882D5643DE959D79B85E054D58"><enum>2.</enum><header>Designation of Henry Parham Department of Veterans Affairs Clinic</header> <subsection id="H5B7365F0A0544AAF945FEDE29EFE0E20"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The community-based outpatient clinic of the Department of Veterans Affairs in Monroeville, Pennsylvania, shall after the date of the enactment of this Act be known and designated as the <quote>Henry Parham Department of Veterans Affairs Clinic</quote> or the <quote>Henry Parham VA Clinic</quote>.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HED4A5C4E913D45719EA2EF5A3839ECFF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reference</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any reference in any law, regulation, map, document, paper, or other record of the United States to the community-based outpatient clinic referred to in subsection (a) shall be considered to be a reference to the Henry Parham VA Clinic.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

