<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H227CFAD6FF0A464A896165BC7F7BBB17" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 161 IH: Prioritizing Troops Over Tax Collectors Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 161</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To transfer funds from the Internal Revenue Service to the Department of Defense to increase the pay of certain members of the Armed Forces serving on active duty.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7C0A0F7E3C474E52841E4D465D80BA7C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H38FFBDEFBFE6402394F38778AAAA0202" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Prioritizing Troops Over Tax Collectors Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HAF0B3B89F29A4238BAF19F3E967597F0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Minimum rate of basic pay for a member of the Armed Forces</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the enactment of this Act, the rate of basic pay for a member of the Armed Forces under section 203 of title 37, United States Code, shall equal or exceed $31,200.</text></section> 
<section id="HE607160008044A1D89BFF079A2AC3F3E" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Transfer of certain unobligated funds from the Internal Revenue Service to the Department of Defense to carry out increase of minimum rate of basic pay</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The unobligated balance of amounts made available to the Internal Revenue Service under section 10301 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> (commonly known as the <quote>Inflation Reduction Act</quote>) are hereby transferred to the Department of Defense to carry out section 1.</text></section> <section id="HECFFF3A2EED84D03AF1D32A217A6E5E6"><enum>4.</enum><header>Limitation on Internal Revenue Service hiring until minimum rate of basic pay for a member of the Armed Forces is increased</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">During the period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act and ending on the date on which the Secretary of Defense certifies to the Commissioner of Internal Revenue that such Secretary has implemented section 1, the Internal Revenue Service may not hire any employee if such hiring would result in the number of full-time employees employed by the Internal Revenue Service exceeding the number of such employees so employed immediately before such period.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

