<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1D9C345E23E34F13A804A0B816C6A45D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 312 IH: Emergency Savings Accounts Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 312</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230112">January 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to provide emergency savings accounts for individuals.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBE74FE49E1CA4B24B27C4E036E85D35E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC1A930EEA2894FF48A5D52F7FFB233CE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Emergency Savings Accounts Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H501B6E5D19404D60B98434794E4A9F22"><enum>2.</enum><header>Deduction for contributions to emergency savings accounts</header> <subsection id="HDC913CE525234BFAA7B1F6C2CAF094E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part VII of subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (relating to additional itemized deductions for individuals) is amended by redesignating section 224 as section 225 and by inserting after section 223 the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E42DD014EAB44E4927CA32F9D5A666C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HEAC3C4072DE740138C37FED6AE47677A"><enum>224.</enum><header>Emergency savings accounts</header> 
<subsection id="H21732A308C4B435FB274BBB778C56C25"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Deduction allowed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a eligible individual, there shall be allowed as a deduction for the taxable year an amount equal to the aggregate amount paid during such taxable year by or on behalf of such individual to an emergency savings account of such individual.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2FA6D4CF050844858C1A916219F73057"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation</header> <paragraph id="HBAA8BCD660E743C3AE5EFE5B9238AA17"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amount allowed as a deduction under subsection (a) to an individual for the taxable year shall not exceed $5,000.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H642DF0F53CE6437BBC5C0AB5868CCD26"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Partial year of eligibility</header><text>In the case of an individual who is an eligible individual for only a portion of the taxable year, the limitation under paragraph (1) shall be same proportion of $5,000 as such portion bears to the entire taxable year.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4790B8CFEE4744FC86214746CC597F2A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>eligible individual</term> means any individual if such individual occupied any residence in the United States at any time during the taxable year.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0711804432484C2186CDF8C7904DD777"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Emergency savings account</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text> <paragraph id="HC90044A0E8C246ED9AC56260DDE8D46B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>emergency savings account</term> means a trust created or organized in the United States as an emergency savings account exclusively for the purpose of paying the qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses of the account beneficiary, but only if the written governing instrument creating the trust meets the following requirements:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5F50DC099BAB43018386B0F4C9391962"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Except in the case of a rollover contribution described in subsection (f)(5), no contribution will be accepted—</text> <clause id="HC65BA8B2A3254D8388381AD3A981E9A1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>unless it is in cash, or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7B4DA41B39D44DBEA396161073C02E6D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to the extent such contribution, when added to previous contributions to the trust for the calendar year, exceeds the dollar limitation in effect under subsection (b).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFEF464B84BFD417CB8CD8671D60E31AB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The trustee is a bank (as defined in section 408(n)), an insurance company (as defined in section 816), or another person who demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Secretary that the manner in which such person will administer the trust will be consistent with the requirements of this section.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB82268528B77477690D1EAD216FA9206"><enum>(C)</enum><text>No part of the trust assets will be invested in life insurance contracts.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEA949150CE2744AD841144F8A2559EDA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The assets of the trust will not be commingled with other property except in a common trust fund or common investment fund.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2CD971CCBDD249C19FC498356A716AE1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The interest of an individual in the balance in his account is nonforfeitable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF8722405CA94A96B7D7918B5A659D92"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses</header><text>The term <term>qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H039902DE736342A9BADA6C257FA664C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disaster mitigation expenses, </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H53460B557AE54E4EBD090C6DA5F08C33"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disaster recovery expenses, </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H84EF50797A1E4066A9B1E560B50EE5A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>public health emergency expenses, and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEAC001B96FB144519442522A08577C67"><enum>(D)</enum><text>unemployment related expenses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7379BE3E20274E41AC28BC7B4B3ADB7F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disaster mitigation expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>disaster mitigation expenses</term> means expenses for any of the following with respect to the residence referred to in subsection (c):</text> <subparagraph id="H29FDB5011377404D9FE79669BB7CF8A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tornado safe rooms manufactured or constructed in accordance with FEMA 320 or FEMA 361 guidance or tornado shelters manufactured or constructed in accordance with the National Storm Shelter/International Code Council 500 standard.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD92554FF2AAA494E93056A130A5D0305"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Opening protection, including impact and wind resistant windows, exterior doors, and garage doors.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE32F4D255BB14785AF1C0D1F20CA3EB3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Reinforcement of roof-to-wall and floor-to-wall connections for wind or seismic activity.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEB6EB7F15DA14E70BF19F9112EFDE9EB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Roof covering for impact, fire, or high wind resistance.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42668803D9EE4C2AADCDE1B59F1B6261"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Cripple and shear walls to resist seismic activity.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1926F9FBF3AF414ABE27033BE0ED8DB9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Flood resistant building materials.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC3802673C9F04B0D84040622743A357D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Elevating structures and utilities above base flood elevation.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H60DCF875012D41E89BD4B4C8D98FE416"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Fire resistant exterior wall assemblies/systems.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H71F85E4AB802490DBD63AF8E3A03C8AB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Lightning protection systems.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAFA365A1591A4F429FC658FC4A8A8F8D"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Whole home standby generators.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAA15604B18694B7E964E74A03FAA6347"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any activity specified by the Secretary as appropriate to mitigate the risks of future hazards (including earthquake, flood, hail, hurricane, sinkhole, lightning, power outage, tornado, and wildfire) and other natural disasters.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HF7D6E3620EEC41E4A0CBA755BC5851DF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Disaster recovery expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>disaster recovery expenses</term> means with respect to the residence referred to in subsection (c) any expense incurred to replace or repair disaster-related uninsured personal casualty personal losses totaling $1,000 or greater.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HF76A3C432965469393657AFAA074792F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Disaster-related uninsured personal casualty loss</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>disaster-related uninsured personal casualty loss</term> means a personal casualty loss (as defined in section 165(h)(3)(B), determined without regard to the second sentence thereof) attributable to a State or federally declared disaster for which a deduction is allowable under section 165 (without regard to subsection (h)(1)).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0EFF5C43E6364EAB9A92506BBC044116"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Federally declared disaster</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>federally declared disaster</term> has the meaning given such term by section 165(i)(5).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC0A73D19C6F64EBABCD38E68AE041D9F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Public health emergency expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>public health emergency expenses</term> means expenses for any of the following with respect to an individual referred to in subsection (c) if paid or incurred while a public health emergency declaration is in effect and while such individual is unemployed or has their employment status reduced from full-time status:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB7F26E870EB74428BBA75AE402F64D6B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Child care expenses. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7021CC2073E24FE0981C559B3C8EF557"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Out-of-pocket health care costs, including insurance premiums. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF8CDC7F1F00743D89940ECCA3AE50828"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Housing expenses including mortgage, rent, or property taxes. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCA6638170C37445999B5E8BB9E3C0BA7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Utilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA100D7C7AA6F45779B3175AEFAADDCAD" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Public health emergency declaration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>public health emergency declaration</term> means any declaration of a public health emergency by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under section 319 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d">42 U.S.C. 247d</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H12E7AD6300314CB69D71A454E82AA659"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Unemployment related expenses</header><text>The term <quote>unemployment related expenses</quote> means, in the case of an account beneficiary with any period of unemployment during the taxable year, any expenses during such taxable year which, in the aggregate, do not exceed $500.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE0730F57BE14A47AB54ECC21C40CA40"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Account beneficiary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>account beneficiary</term> means the individual on whose behalf the emergency savings account was established.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H95792640C47540B6B11AE88EBF56A4A2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Treatment of account</header> <paragraph id="H92A0AB7C261F4055A45D311B7F665719"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An emergency savings account is exempt from taxation under this subtitle unless such account has ceased to be an emergency savings account. Notwithstanding the preceding sentence, any such account is subject to the taxes imposed by section 511 (relating to imposition of tax on unrelated business income of charitable, etc. organizations).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF0A36A01D7D4B709F6371630BB8D33B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Account terminations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rules similar to the rules of paragraphs (2) and (4) of section 408(e) shall apply to emergency savings accounts, and any amount treated as distributed under such rules shall be treated as not used to pay qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HABECBA9BAF7344F79AD6059CDD199B02"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Tax treatment of distributions</header> <paragraph id="H1BB79B2D44B040B9A257958F69835BB0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amounts used for qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any amount paid or distributed out of an emergency savings account which is used exclusively to pay qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses of any account beneficiary shall not be includible in gross income.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3EAFEB79C87E4247A4447A416F437D72"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion of amounts not used for qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any amount paid or distributed out of an emergency savings account which is not used exclusively to pay the qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses of the account beneficiary shall be included in the gross income of such beneficiary.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2A2C06646E564898AC6ED619AB08B84A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Excess contributions returned before due date of return</header> <subparagraph id="H8EEB342B94614B298B45C61A78BECE83"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any excess contribution is contributed for a taxable year to any emergency savings account of an individual, paragraph (2) shall not apply to distributions from the emergency savings accounts of such individual (to the extent such distributions do not exceed the aggregate excess contributions to all such accounts of such individual for such year) if—</text> 
<clause id="H50A20FC4196B482189809E6777416903"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such distribution is received by the individual on or before the last day prescribed by law (including extensions of time) for filing such individual's return for such taxable year, and</text></clause> <clause id="HA2D0D76F041B4ABF8F38F76E524D3D97"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such distribution is accompanied by the amount of net income attributable to such excess contribution.</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">Any net income described in clause (ii) shall be included in the gross income of the individual for the taxable year in which it is received. </continuation-text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCAEF2EAF2FE74A49BCF0E18575A543A9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Excess contribution</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the term <term>excess contribution</term> means any contribution (other than a rollover contribution described in paragraph (5)) which is not deductible under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1FBB759E8B2B48E9AA14123CF7E7AC71"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Additional tax on distributions not used for qualified disaster and public health emergency expenses</header> <subparagraph id="H7DD84964EDA644099AE46679DD6C3385"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The tax imposed by this chapter on the account beneficiary for any taxable year in which there is a payment or distribution from an emergency savings account of such beneficiary which is includible in gross income under paragraph (2) shall be increased by 20 percent of the amount which is so includible.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3E3082ECFCDF48A4AA985722FA3AD19B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception for disability or death</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply if the payment or distribution is made after the account beneficiary becomes disabled within the meaning of section 72(m)(7) or dies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9A4623A2AD0E4C1BA126246ED82325C1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rollover contribution</header><text>An amount is described in this paragraph as a rollover contribution if it meets the requirements of subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text> 
<subparagraph id="H11DF86959C64430FA5090645950EEDC9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (2) shall not apply to any amount paid or distributed from an emergency savings account to the account beneficiary to the extent the amount received is paid into an emergency savings account for the benefit of such beneficiary not later than the 60th day after the day on which the beneficiary receives the payment or distribution.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC4F6EEB199484EE7BA1355E4CBE8E649"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>This paragraph shall not apply to any amount described in subparagraph (A) received by an individual from an emergency savings account if, at any time during the 1-year period ending on the day of such receipt, such individual received any other amount described in subparagraph (A) from an emergency savings account which was not includible in the individual's gross income because of the application of this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF7A574939088441DB71ED75722F7EFC4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Cost-of-Living adjustment</header> 
<paragraph id="H379BBB8CAEDA4CC18E384C3DF74E8C6B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any taxable year beginning in a calendar year after 2023, each $5,000 amount in subsection (b) and the $3,000 amount in subsection (d)(4) shall be increased by an amount equal to—</text> <subparagraph id="HF5A7C4A77FAD45B0856FDD535C5DE797"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such dollar amount, multiplied by</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H926F0D0A1618454F9F67EDEBFC32BF8C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year in which such taxable year begins determined by substituting <quote>calendar year 2022</quote> for <quote>calendar year 2016</quote> in subparagraph (A)(ii) thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A6139C707574B3CA06567330AA26A4B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>If any increase under paragraph (1) is not a multiple of $50, such increase shall be rounded to the nearest multiple of $50.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC06ABB1B8FB8402F9919646F2B47B4DA"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Special rules</header> 
<paragraph id="H2E6AD3A8E10A4A89961717723C13B3E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Denial of deduction to dependents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No deduction shall be allowed under this section to any individual with respect to whom a deduction under section 151 is allowable to another taxpayer for a taxable year beginning in the calendar year in which such individual's taxable year begins.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF03D8E31E3154E7A998BB29F67911C54"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Taxable year must be full taxable year</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except in the case of a taxable year closed by reason of the death of the taxpayer, no deduction shall be allowed under this section in the case of a taxable year covering a period of less than 12 months.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA47099E2285D4B74B15B8FD949518777"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Certain rules to apply</header><text>Rules similar to the following rules shall apply for purposes of this section:</text> <subparagraph id="H5012E379920F4BB5827AEA1A33D094D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 219(d)(2) (relating to no deduction for rollovers).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE5B31408FCC0443BB3571096567FCDA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 219(f)(3) (relating to time when contributions deemed made).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0FAF84C26A614AEB85CF95ED9437E2C6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 219(f)(5) (relating to employer payments).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5574179614104DA7898D5426CF61F5E5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Section 408(g) (relating to community property laws).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC394DF5AF10C480697F5B815AA6B2FB7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Section 408(h) (relating to custodial accounts).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H705C29961CDD420C960DFB7934D305A3"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Section 223(f)(7) (relating to transfer of account incident to divorce).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H717A597FABB34AA19BB4D1E1E81DDD18"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Section 223(f)(8) (relating to treatment after death of account beneficiary).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19551E3169B344C6AD8054E410A14559"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Coordination with casualty loss deduction</header><text>No deduction shall be allowed under section 165 for a loss for which a disaster recovery expense payment is made from an emergency savings account.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0C3D1019D8E048BAA44443BD86E8BBE2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may require the trustee of an emergency savings account to make such reports regarding such account to the Secretary and to the account beneficiary with respect to contributions, distributions, the return of excess contributions, and such other matters as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1F6D48EEDA184D9687902F3E7BD78667"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deduction allowed whether or not individual itemizes other deductions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 62(a) of such Code is amended by inserting after paragraph (21) the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2913B95A0E444D6587F27C77140846AF" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H49A319093E984A21879C3E1FAFB37D6D"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Emergency savings accounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The deduction allowed by section 224.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDA52C027B0AB46AABB1F1348934B41BC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Tax on excess contributions</header><text>Section 4973 of such Code (relating to tax on excess contributions to certain tax-favored accounts and annuities) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HEDB2DB6012A045C5AD59D0A308158B83"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subsection (a)(5), by inserting <quote>or</quote> at the end of subsection (a)(6), and by inserting after subsection (a)(6) the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H525B1261342A4703933586EB2024CC6D" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HD6E82884E98C44739656C221C6FB355B"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an emergency savings account (within the meaning of section 224(d)),</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H78D7208BA7184CE5AC551A1EAE8960F2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H08EE93A6C40C4FD19981A470E110AF96" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HA4ED9E51C83B4DD39A18153BCC6A2F28"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Excess contributions to emergency savings accounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, in the case of emergency savings accounts (within the meaning of section 224(d)), the term <term>excess contributions</term> means the sum of—</text> <paragraph id="H432E5FC95447463396246F18F9BD99D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the aggregate amount contributed for the taxable year to the accounts (other than a rollover contribution described in section 224(f)(5)) which is not allowable as a deduction under section 224 for such year, and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7D13884FDFAD498FB519A3DBE7F34EDB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the amount determined under this subsection for the preceding taxable year, reduced by the sum of—</text> <subparagraph id="H6F171E6FBBAE482F88327A675ED4F7BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the distributions out of the accounts which were included in gross income under section 224(f)(2), and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H909BA4CCDF24479CBEAD3AFAB847F85C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the excess (if any) of—</text> <clause id="HA9A82F2B47664636ACFB3622C71A19F1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the maximum amount allowable as a deduction under section 224(b) for the taxable year, over</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBF165CD342264EE69C19C1CBBE8E0369"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount contributed to the accounts for the taxable year.</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">For purposes of this subsection, any contribution which is distributed out of the emergency savings account in a distribution to which section 224(f)(3) applies shall be treated as an amount not contributed.</continuation-text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H30F041192F744595A213ED1E03A0CAF5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Failure To provide reports on emergency savings accounts</header><text>Section 6693(a)(2) of such Code is amended by redesignating subparagraphs (D), (E), and (F) as subparagraphs (E), (F), and (G), respectively, and by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9065FFA6B23843DD8B9B55D4D48D562D" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H568F6F901AA747A2BE1F7820EB7469DC"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 224(i) (relating to emergency savings accounts),</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H48FFFE73EB9B43DA9CF00C33A21AA6CC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for part VII of subchapter B of chapter 1 of such Code is amended by striking the last item and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE0CF51B49B4344DCA6DC643FF9B44E1A" style="OLC"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 224. Emergency savings accounts. </toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 225. Cross reference.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3A29E0229DB141BD9D41BFD7B3B1AE6E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2022.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

