<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7F72F70513C748E2A6E850D9914F7412" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5044 IH: Timber Innovation for Building Rural Communities Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5044</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Agriculture to carry out certain activities relating to research for wood products, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H38B71F10BBF2427F963E4F46D2BF9B81" style="OLC"><section id="H4FE7B478BF134AE89F2584E26261788B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Timber Innovation for Building Rural Communities Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H83198F7BB8CC4FA8A9C658B9E56674AB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definition of Secretary</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC27C114D2AEE4B38915E06715CF29532"><enum>3.</enum><header>Forest and wood products data provision</header><subsection id="H586DE5B58E4D490F996F11E13546B9B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in collaboration with the Chief of the Natural Resources Conservation Service and in consultation with federally recognized Indian Tribes, State foresters, and private sector partners, shall establish a platform to provide measurement, monitoring, verification, and reporting data regarding the carbon emissions, sequestration, storage, and related atmospheric impacts of forest management and wood products.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4366490EF6AD461BB08711C3BEAF25FE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary shall source data, information, and data analysis from Department of Agriculture programs, including—</text><paragraph id="H542DA9FBBCE449BE8FDDE70B0386B246"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Forest Inventory and Analysis program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AA4333DEBD943B5AD3897A4C341F7FB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Timber Products Output survey;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8403F25069EF4A24AC150CF1AAD0B0BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Forest Service and Natural Resources Conservation Service soil carbon estimations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08400D20C5A949678D931ABDF6B10F7B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Department of Agriculture entity-level guidance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F6811F81CF3452392911F74CFE5F81C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Forest Products Laboratory;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H309296F3E8674CA29D5541C4E1D7F3DC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Federal Life Cycle Assessment Commons;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF1BE9B53D974E5ABF6E73D12BCE0775"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Department of Agriculture entity level guidelines; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1A23C042D084C66AFD18C23D9940B04"><enum>(8)</enum><text>other relevant programmatic data and information sources, as they are published and made available.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE9D9DED892DB43BA84E948056047ABD8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priorities</header><text>The platform established by subsection (a) shall provide tools that calculate—</text><paragraph id="H3C1900FC884B4E32A16CE6BBF6B69A00" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the above- and below-ground forest carbon stocks and stock changes associated with species composition, forest management regime, and landowner types, including small area estimations for regional and localized geographies across the United States, made available through Forest Inventory and Analysis updates and annual reports;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC30565F8E11E4C58A91C270B101CAB73"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the embodied carbon involved in the manufacture of products, using data from published environmental product declarations and life cycle assessments, updated as new and more refined data becomes available;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD58E05B9FF7485C911163C2D4B14A7C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the long-term stored carbon in manufactured timber products; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FBCD4308C254336B386671515C80FAC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the carbon displacement of wood products, compared to other materials, using substitution factors.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0BEF54A2F76C4BACBF4A19AE433DDA7B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Timeframe</header><text>To the maximum extent practicable, the Secretary shall establish the platform under subsection (a) not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H67D45C754C6F4345AC00B76F37373EAE"><enum>4.</enum><header>Wood innovation grant program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8643 of the Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/7655d">7 U.S.C. 7655d</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9FF2E0B9F48642C39B1CB85A6998EE44"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d), by inserting <quote>50 percent of</quote> before <quote>the amount</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8334682DF2D74E98B4AD259D7502BC6B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsection (c) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H112B8FCE5B074BB0A58754131B3B7520"><subsection id="H67BC976AE87D46BD9F04CF43AE0ACE3F" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Targeting To support economic development, enhanced building design, and impact assessment</header><text>In selecting among proposals of eligible entities under subsection (b)(2), the Secretary may give priority to proposals for projects that—</text><paragraph id="HFC28C6465FBF4690B811370FC8050AF6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include the use or retrofitting (or both) of existing sawmill facilities located in counties in which the average annual unemployment rate exceeded the national average unemployment rate by more than 1 percent in the previous calendar year; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07EE56E2D63F416B80821D89F46E4B6D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recognize or enhance carbon reduction strategies in building design, including forest impacts, which can be improved or incentivized by North American procurement; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1008BD57FBF342AF8833AD4E792A5C4E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>report on the connection between their proposal and the resilience and economic benefits associated with wood products from anticipated wood supply areas, including wildfire risk reduction, increased fiber flow, forest or mill jobs, and support for forested communities created because of forest management.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HC5D943BF4A574DA4AF580AC29B6F48D7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Wood building education accelerator grant program</header><subsection id="H60D35A91522B409D83FD9EAB348CC2EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2734C6C5343A4648BBE22799C9302CA8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H8A4B4160AC514CD58938B864B64AA766"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an engineering, architecture, or design school at an institution of higher education; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H619D7C04350C4E6A94DFEE5ABAE32006"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a center of excellence that consists of 1 or more partnerships between forestry, engineering, architecture, or business schools at 1 or more institutions of higher education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA825077A62A24E5E8B6E07BB1265B4CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary, acting through the Research and Development deputy area and the State, Private, and Tribal Forestry deputy area of the Forest Service.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H91C9F79B72CB4A2D8D80758C65EE0C56"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant program</header><paragraph id="H5768C3D29C3D4E86A6F3125169D8B2D5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a program, to be known as the <quote>Wood Building Education Accelerator Grant Program</quote>, to annually award grants to geographically diverse eligible entities to support the development of curricula, programs, and best practices relating to the critical elements of designing and building with wood, including the use of traditional wood products, mass timber, and other advanced wood products.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0E36D502DAC4A6AABDF872A04C6C4CA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Proposals</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary a proposal at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H90E0C0834AF5407F894EA24C66359CB9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Review and awards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall review proposals submitted under paragraph (2), and award grants under this subsection, in consultation with nonprofit organizations, research organizations, or other private entities providing funding to eligible entities to support activities carried out using grants under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC7392510E5484FF380DC8C76EB5D5065"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under subsection (b)(1), an eligible entity shall provide funds equal to the amount received by the eligible entity under the grant, to be derived from non-Federal sources.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA2486CFF13184D2294CA1917FC40D795"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation on amount</header><text>The total amount of grants awarded under subsection (b)(1) shall be not more than $10,000,000 for each fiscal year. </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE40416AF879C4204B512A6776D164907"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Allocation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the availability of appropriations made in advance for such purposes, the Secretary shall allocate to carry out this section not more than $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="H7EEF5A7189954259ACD44F172DD895A7"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rural infrastructure and building pilot program</header><subsection id="HE74BB07BF8A84FAC81077CD531F18440"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HE01D62F6228F4BF48A9240826B602A4D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HDC6FE265952B4C96B2976A7C44140C9A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE982489E4E9470EBF14F41752514465"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a community-based organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7CFC3A7EB2B4A4F97E0870E279F3377"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a State, local, or municipal government; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3F4EDF86ACE43D098B112C9E0E06C24"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a tribally designated housing authority;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDFAB207165D45E2BE39EA7B5A6F9FD8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a private entity, as determined by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H837BF00181924AC999218747E554FB8F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a consortium of 2 or more entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (E).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CA24A515F51476C8BC2FF64AE70FD24"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Produced and assembled in the United States</header><text>The term <term>produced and assembled in the United States</term>, with regard to wood materials, means that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7E7C1B75460C497B8601B12A9AF9F1D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the wood materials, if manufactured, were manufactured entirely in the United States; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2D219F10EE2B47AAADAED508DBFC4F17"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the wood materials were produced, all production occurred entirely in the United States. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H33BB47C0ECFB492B96725AFB6847955E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public agency</header><text>The term <term>public agency</term> means a department, agency, other unit, or instrumentality of Federal, State, Tribal, or local government.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H005BA750CBF44EA0AD3C942A257AA1BB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rural</header><text>The term <term>rural</term> has the meaning given the term in section 343(a) of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1991">7 U.S.C. 1991(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30170318B5ED4DF0AB4EF5B7A64F4CE5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Under Secretary for Rural Development, in consultation with the Under Secretary for Natural Resources and Environment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2FC96E543B3149CFB2A5717C654BD213"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant program</header><paragraph id="H1751FD0F3C36455B91F9936E32EEF00C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities to carry out pilot projects to demonstrate the use of innovative wood products, systems, and technologies, such as mass timber, in the construction and renovation of rural infrastructure and building projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6EC104DE8C564FDE88C6E05210009DCD" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5E9F04B157CE4B8D95059999150242E1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Project requirements</header><text>A pilot project carried out using a grant received under subsection (b)(1) shall—</text><paragraph id="H1E36FA5D11A44B19885691317B083650"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be not longer than 5 years;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48576BE0895B4125895951933D5EBDFB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include collaboration between 1 or more eligible entities and 1 or more public agencies; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF593623E21A54BC98FEB11D652A42B9C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>primarily use for construction materials wood products that are manufactured and prefabricated offsite and assembled onsite as a <quote>kit-of-parts</quote> or by assembling finished modules;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8CF5D9A230F436BBAEF882B50222D89"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, use wood materials that are produced and assembled in the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA5FF9D25CBC4466B154E90A562C728D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>be located in or provide benefits to a rural community that, to the extent practicable, has a history in wood products manufacturing. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10C9885D3F854A14ABAB9034D0EE4B2F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under subsection (b)(1), an eligible entity shall provide funds, to be derived from non-Federal sources—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H74799F58A7744F1FBEBE77DB3360F323"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">except as provided in paragraph (2), equal to the amount received by the eligible entity under the grant; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H005C58AF012542EBBFA2448EC9E64FB8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a pilot project serving a population of—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC70D1C03C5DD4BF4BB3B93D02D8D09C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">less than 19,000 residents, equal to 50 percent of the amount received by the eligible entity under the grant; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H466B0D999D9F4541A42B80CB07723999"><enum>(B)</enum><text>less than 2,500 residents, equal to 25 percent of the amount received by the eligible entity under the grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1419C590C2D24DE89D0F207DB89C63A9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Limitation on amount</header><text>The total amount of grants awarded under subsection (b)(1) shall be not more than $10,000,000 for each fiscal year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H29028175C3224C4D85FACDEED7D3F567"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>The Secretary shall provide for an independent evaluation of pilot projects carried out under this section that includes—</text><paragraph id="HB15B805B7AEB47698FD38D19AAD28FEB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a summary of the activities conducted under the pilot projects;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CCDA4B94D634B52A8EDA71D2E11AF7B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an assessment of the effectiveness of the project requirements described in subsection (c); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE596735F9E4450390631B06B02A4DE0" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>best practices regarding the use of public-private partnerships for increased wood utilization to benefit rural communities. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H068D29C8B76E484FA01AEB7881264124" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Allocation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the availability of appropriations made in advance for such purposes, the Secretary shall allocate to carry out this section not more than $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

