<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9D39DB5B7D984B5086368FAB9B318643" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6385 IH: Situational Awareness of Flying Elements in Orbit Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6385</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231113">November 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote space situational awareness and space traffic coordination and to modify the functions and leadership of the Office of Space Commerce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7CB1D85D04FD4E27B0BCE9F84013F84E" style="OLC"><section id="H6DF112297DAF436789A0080B9A5B62B6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Situational Awareness of Flying Elements in Orbit Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SAFE Orbit Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA84DA72AA23A43418FD54B38D94F138D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Space situational awareness and space traffic coordination</header><subsection id="HC0F9BC109AD8436D979A7C8982EB5B34"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce shall facilitate safe operations in space and encourage the development of commercial space capabilities by acquiring and disseminating unclassified data, analytics, information, and services on space activities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFB76C0BF78784625BD898FF80C6309DF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Immunity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States, any agencies and instrumentalities thereof, and any individuals, firms, corporations, and other persons acting for the United States, including non-governmental entities, shall be immune from any suit in any court for any cause of action arising from the provision or receipt of space situational awareness services or information, whether or not provided in accordance with this section, or any related action or omission.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H093BFD864A894CC5AFED5C8B565BA294"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Acquisition of data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Space Commerce (established under section 50702(b) of title 51, United States Code, as amended by section 3) is authorized to acquire—</text><paragraph id="HB1637F2F2A094F638E6CDD5A15ADB62E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>data, analytics, information, and services, including with respect to—</text><subparagraph id="H48C6500C92254C528C5A02D0147EF8DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>location tracking data;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H998DF5479EAF461DBF7AD3668CBF3DCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>positional and orbit determination information; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9BA89C103DDE40DDA766E11B9429E388"><enum>(C)</enum><text>conjunction data messages; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C20D5AFCFAD4B2BAA438DA5BCE1BB20"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such other data, analytics, information, and services as the Secretary of Commerce determines necessary to avoid collisions of space objects.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HED81E118C3374808B7111C5B6360B7B6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Database on satellite location and behavior</header><text>The Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Space Commerce shall provide access for the public, at no charge, a fully updated, unclassified database of information concerning space objects and behavior that includes—</text><paragraph id="HA85EBF6350F14ACA942B7F62CC624510"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the data and information acquired under subsection (c), except to the extent that such data or information is classified or a trade secret (as defined in section 1839 of title 18, United States Code); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H694A9DC80B254342B0B2C2C878DEEBC4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the provision of basic space situational awareness services and space traffic coordination based on the data referred to in paragraph (1), including basic analytics, tracking calculations, and conjunction data messages.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6A298F2E797E4237A013B050C18C2810" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Basic space situational awareness services</header><text>The Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Space Commerce—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF9E7B49631764CAE9E7D4E1A765F7789"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall provide to satellite operators, at no charge, basic space situational awareness services, including the data, analytics, information, and services described in subsection (c);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF9AA0A65E1274D0FB7F4D44174B3E5C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in carrying out paragraph (1), may not compete with private sector advanced space situational awareness products, to the maximum extent practicable; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EFCC7A1E0444A3187EFE692B238CDAA" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not less frequently than every 3 years, shall review the basic space situational awareness services described in paragraph (1) to ensure that such services provided by the Federal Government do not compete with advanced space situational services offered by the private sector.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCAECAE1DD75D4550BBED5961E7C8A352"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Requirements for data acquisition and dissemination</header><text>In acquiring data, analytics, information, and services under subsection (c) and disseminating data, analytics, information, and services under subsections (d) and (e), the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Space Commerce shall—</text><paragraph id="H83563C07D0E6445BA15C582D0E47D0FD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>leverage commercial capabilities to the maximum extent practicable;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F740EA895494AC99833F33F46640388"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prioritize the acquisition of data, analytics, information, and services from commercial industry located in or licensed in the United States to supplement data collected by United States Government agencies, including the Department of Defense and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E03E638F20943709C80269D26F593C0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>appropriately protect proprietary data, information, and systems of firms located in the United States, including by using appropriate infrastructure and cybersecurity measures;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H007185BED9C34FC4BE0A8F3A48C0C4E0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>facilitate the development of standardization and consistency in data reporting, in collaboration with satellite owners and operators, commercial space situational awareness data and service providers, the academic community, and nonprofit organizations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9070E16A98834731A05224BBD60139E0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>encourage foreign governments to participate in unclassified data sharing arrangements for space situational awareness and space traffic coordination.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8791561669114E3A87A4880862CA3EBA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Other transaction authority</header><text>In carrying out the activities required by this section, the Secretary of Commerce shall enter into such contracts, leases, cooperative agreements, or other transactions as may be necessary.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDF0CD937FB664AA69617191BA4842A79"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Space object defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>space object</term> means any object launched into space, or created in space, robotically or by humans, including an object’s component parts. </text></subsection></section><section id="HEB247979C9D04BC890632A649619BC02"><enum>3.</enum><header>Modifications to Office of Space Commerce</header><subsection id="H4AD85D0ED6C540F289B03075B77FA6C1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Location of Office</header><text>Subsection (a) of section 50702 of title 51, United States Code, is amended by inserting before the end period the following: <quote>, which, not later than 5 years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>SAFE Orbit Act of 2023</short-title>, shall transition to a principal physical location within the Office of the Secretary of Commerce</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA0F91018ED6A4982BFCC3EA93301CB76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional functions of Office</header><text>Subsection (c) of such section is amended—</text><paragraph id="HCAA27ED00CB64BC895CA5BDB26064ECE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29E6F4A0054B4AD3A0BD7D0AB56AE64E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H683DB612E0DC4633B51567428B991E37"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA314D92820284A77AC3E73F2A40DF399"><paragraph id="H70587839C31746D7AE9EA46806B7380F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to perform space situational awareness and space traffic management duties pursuant to the <short-title>SAFE Orbit Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A79F094720B466BA7E208C4ACDAA5F5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Space Commerce</header><paragraph id="H782236AE05D14E4A8D550CBCC7201B2E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (b) of such section is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43D8F050298644B1B1DA789AB2C8129E"><subsection id="HF0155AABB29C445691825FD61ACEF537"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assistant Secretary</header><text>The Office shall be headed by the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Space Commerce, who shall—</text><paragraph id="H644793DC744F46A185F84B5CD40F6263"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H588120B38986491BAA1D563719235244"><enum>(2)</enum><text>report directly to the Secretary of Commerce; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79FA54C7B8DA453CBE34897119BCBB7C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>have a rate of pay that is equal to the rate payable for level IV of the Executive Schedule under section 5315 of title 5.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC7ED69120B7475C81C4674A574682AF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><subparagraph id="H6E00A9545C1F42C787FEE629B0EFB879"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 50702(d) of title 51, United States Code, is amended—</text><clause id="H02640340A43A4C45ADCFB7493B380AE9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text style="USC" level="subsection">Director</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="USC" level="subsection">Assistant Secretary</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H75F028E3B7E44B958FB36C4CB0AD7E30"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>Director</quote> and inserting <quote>Assistant Secretary</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF9BF8F024DF40A2A5CBD6ECBA23E546"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 5315 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>Assistant Secretaries of Commerce (11)</quote> and inserting <quote>Assistant Secretaries of Commerce (12)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6606C8618E8241B9A677565F917F0DB3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>References</header><text>On and after the date of the enactment of this Act, any reference in any law or regulation to the Director of the Office of Space Commerce shall be deemed to be a reference to the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Space Commerce. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

