<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCE7CCC1EA59C4B3C92D68697ED333327" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5448 IH: Countering CCP Fentanyl Trafficking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5448</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230913">September 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the imposition of sanctions with respect to Chinese officials determined to be involved in the Mexican fentanyl trade, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8B29C38774B2414E803BE2BF5DB3C29E" style="OLC"><section id="HD4747C1FF1DA4DE5877E9A7123B2DA13" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Countering CCP Fentanyl Trafficking Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7C2A616521BA49BFB52A2F5012446046"><enum>2.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to chinese officials involved in the mexican fentanyl trade</header><subsection id="H992D1931732448FF80AC2023EEDB3CEB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header><text>The President shall impose the sanctions described in subsection (c) with respect to each foreign person included in the most recent list submitted pursuant to subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE9CA4A3ABF7240F29E5691C09C94CD20"><enum>(b)</enum><header>List of persons</header><paragraph id="H843BFE5282B540658790679428C9ABDD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a list of officials of the Government of the People’s Republic of China who the President determines as having assisted in or approved with knowledge of the recipient, the transportation of pill presses, fentanyl products, or fentanyl precursors to 1 or more Mexican drug cartels.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0D9351A7C8A4CC7B6D39C887E5AB31A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Updates of lists</header><text>The President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees an updated list under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="HDD969A72CD1E4218A326D00AC9787C95"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act and annually thereafter for 10 years; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33AEF69376674E099B348F6855F726E4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>as new information becomes available.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD045F040483943D4BA58B180E2896FBA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The list required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D89865054ED4F7F90D0EC5A1257B726"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H09145AF5F784438C9E0A3B35AEE4E911"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text>The President shall exercise all of the powers granted to the President by the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) (except that the requirements of section 202 of such Act shall not apply) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in property and interests in property of the person if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09D3723EF63F4ABE88EE2D51E26662B9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inadmissibility of certain individuals</header><subparagraph id="HA97A2ABE4A6446BA974F28031DAC4D9E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visas, admission, or parole</header><text>A foreign person included in the most recent list submitted pursuant to subsection (b) is—</text><clause id="H20DFD58CA4FB4502AB45C7BE65EFE109"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></clause><clause id="H57D486990D0F4E6E902C45010D0928CE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="HBB3ACF441E4744799F428FA6B3B6C92F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAAA77E89FA8A43BDB9A4A09D1C020B09"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Current visas revoked</header><text>A foreign person described in subparagraph (A) is also subject to the following:</text><clause id="HEA5509448915410890F01DC59BC2C2ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Revocation of any visa or other entry documentation regardless of when the visa or other entry documentation is or was issued.</text></clause><clause id="H1BC77A0AA61549FA82C2DF1CD1131BAE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A revocation under clause (i) shall take effect immediately and automatically cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the foreign person’s possession.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4C3D7F932384126986CDDD196BF4857"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Sanctions under paragraph (2) shall not apply to an alien if admitting or paroling the alien into the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFF0B9BCC9B464D02A29B35AAC6A251CF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>The penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) shall apply to a person who violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of regulations promulgated to carry out subsection (a) to the same extent that such penalties apply to a person who commits an unlawful act described in section 206(a) of that Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H53018C3875DF44F1B9642280FA385594"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exception To comply with national security</header><text>The following activities shall be exempt from sanctions under this section:</text><paragraph id="HF31306F2DF584E4CA0D7A19F5388D24A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Activities subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69182A5820104960BEDD796B89695A21"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Any authorized intelligence or law enforcement activities of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6CD55AEACDCA448E9653D7DC9D75D182"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The President may, on a case-by-case basis, waive the imposition of any sanction under this section if the President—</text><paragraph id="H5EE20E6D265F46F4BA19285CBE4DAE35"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determines that such a waiver is in the national interest of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E000C60BDC5444E86AD1AE5DAA5C4C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 120 days after the date on which the President imposes the sanctions described in subsection (a), and every 120 days thereafter until the date of termination under subsection (g), the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the extent to which the President has used the waiver authority under paragraph (1) during the period covered by that report.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0DA5B0B875D14382BDA1429C10B1B921"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority to impose sanctions under this section shall terminate on the date that is 10 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1277161F3DC34D4D95DDE6BF104F23C2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this Act, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="HD3835ECFE65C4089A1693735395D4889"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9531079353AC476995C957A1F1CE7E5B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

