<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H68C0673F551D45ABA16EB7E249523AE6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4639 IH: Fourth Amendment Is Not For Sale Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4639</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230714">July 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001184">Mr. Massie</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend section 2702 of title 18, United States Code, to prevent law enforcement and intelligence agencies from obtaining subscriber or customer records in exchange for anything of value, to address communications and records in the possession of intermediary internet service providers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC59119C1200B4B6EAB6C53159BF3F190" style="OLC"><section id="H2F83294D57A24A65965C8814E80D4CE3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fourth Amendment Is Not For Sale Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HE39312A9B1EC4B3B9E2181DDC503FFA3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Protection of records held by data brokers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2702 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC258DCAF2D4C48ADA610DBAE245D2871"><subsection id="H3473B57CD14E4A549EC40897AD9586FC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibition on obtaining in exchange for anything of value certain records and information by law enforcement and intelligence agencies</header><paragraph id="H81EEABDFFCF7494ABD36E567C4A498AD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="H0A8E1B5F26784186A2DC088043BB6399"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>covered customer or subscriber record</term> means a covered record that is— </text><clause id="H13C9758122FB43978B3C1CA1D8F92017"><enum>(i)</enum><text>disclosed to a third party by— </text><subclause id="HF2DFFA94B2F24485971A6488FF1FACB8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a provider of an electronic communication service to the public or a provider of a remote computing service of which the covered person with respect to the covered record is a subscriber or customer; or </text></subclause><subclause id="HEAC85BC66B4F4AF9A695351E023E994D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an intermediary service provider that delivers, stores, or processes communications of such covered person; </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFD4F66F93E5C4692B8341888E6197223"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>collected by a third party from an online account of a covered person; or</text></clause><clause id="HAE1F50807ED14A89AAF214C470F3D0D2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>collected by a third party from or about an electronic device of a covered person;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B96E60A291C40BD8FF051F8B5F350E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>covered person</term> means—</text><clause id="H4994D66D886E4874A1D4E1462A239424"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a person who is located inside the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="HC1983FAE85A442709C2C2809ED271E9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a person— </text><subclause id="HBDF6EA64BCB24DC0BEE6B9CFB01BCC26"><enum>(I)</enum><text>who is located outside the United States or whose location cannot be determined; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H68A88072FE6E41D0A758B3A3495B5E21"><enum>(II)</enum><text>who is a United States person, as defined in section 101 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801</external-xref>);</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06710F9DEF5144D78471B6E85F460B89"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the term <term>covered record</term> means a record or other information that— </text><clause id="H6B6297D59A8544878E98317151546616"><enum>(i)</enum><text>pertains to a covered person; and</text></clause><clause id="H93657B9CD1114EB7BEFF2601730D9358"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is— </text><subclause id="HC78C3E08470E41319AAAD1A82471F4FC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a record or other information described in the matter preceding paragraph (1) of subsection (c); </text></subclause><subclause id="H1D96A1E76309449FBBF2DC313B4D50D3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the contents of a communication; or </text></subclause><subclause id="HEFA424C84FDA4754B8793522CE694396"><enum>(III)</enum><text>location information; </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6191DF46E7B44ECF9C9BA85587429B48"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the term <term>electronic device</term> has the meaning given the term <term>computer</term> in section 1030(e); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H981EDA2A049B4210B4994248DA38B219"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the term <term>illegitimately obtained information</term> means a covered record that— </text><clause id="H411FD5778D2A4D5CB44BC3D6C9A18D74"><enum>(i)</enum><text>was obtained— </text><subclause id="H9B267F86A9074B44B7455BF050A36402"><enum>(I)</enum><text>from a provider of an electronic communication service to the public or a provider of a remote computing service in a manner that— </text><item id="H98F2A039E3E14C4F8B4D3B03E67D1E9F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>violates the service agreement between the provider and customers or subscribers of the provider; or</text></item><item id="H8FC4696BB64C43C394C72AAC3DA9C6AE"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is inconsistent with the privacy policy of the provider; </text></item></subclause><subclause id="H285A4FCEAA5A4F15A8A52A840C01C0A0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by deceiving the covered person whose covered record was obtained; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HA0EE3AABE8FC4099B49A50CF2536B06C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>through the unauthorized accessing of an electronic device or online account; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H55829DCBAAC2432699BECD921B5FE774"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>was—</text><subclause id="HB8D7762B1F6245AE939A21E5B1DA903A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>obtained from a provider of an electronic communication service to the public, a provider of a remote computing service, or an intermediary service provider; and </text></subclause><subclause id="HC532F949C8994D3F935E178E3BCD2E68"><enum>(II)</enum><text>collected, processed, or shared in violation of a contract relating to the covered record; </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H707A74608E7C4DB396E9AA9B5B4712F8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the term <term>intelligence community</term> has the meaning given that term in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0ED5F5C928AE4F149AF16208791D1567"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the term <term>location information</term> means information derived or otherwise calculated from the transmission or reception of a radio signal that reveals the approximate or actual geographic location of a customer, subscriber, or device; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3402AF73E054C57A0B4524B0D11FF2D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the term <term>obtain in exchange for anything of value</term> means to obtain by purchasing, to receive in connection with services being provided for consideration, or to otherwise obtain in exchange for consideration, including an access fee, service fee, maintenance fee, or licensing fee; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B7E12E6EBF944B0AC4037D7A28B86E1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the term <term>online account</term> means an online account with an electronic communication service to the public or remote computing service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H371F64ABD2214FD8BA7104862CEB9C48"><enum>(J)</enum><text>the term <term>pertain</term>, with respect to a person, means—</text><clause id="H777EB3F2A90A43A38284A6A59126E0D3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>information that is linked to the identity of a person; or</text></clause><clause id="HB079602B97004D469F234AC72B0ABFA2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>information— </text><subclause id="HC45373176936426CA40B951EADB2B188"><enum>(I)</enum><text>that has been anonymized to remove links to the identity of a person; and </text></subclause><subclause id="HF46B7507DDE3439681243EF03CF3C90E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that, if combined with other information, could be used to identify a person; and </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4FBF52345214C4399E549DC546E5592"><enum>(K)</enum><text>the term <term>third party</term> means a person who—</text><clause id="HAAB994ACD155412C8C2E291ACA709969"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not a governmental entity; and</text></clause><clause id="H79DB445F76CA4812B9294D75F66B6DCF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in connection with the collection, disclosure, obtaining, processing, or sharing of the covered record at issue, was not acting as— </text><subclause id="H1BBD8080B15044F6B76F0D7BA59519DC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a provider of an electronic communication service to the public; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H855AB3AB39864893BB9F8B2C9926F188"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a provider of a remote computing service.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EF8B61BE5BB42269A3EF03481158F00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><subparagraph id="H851951611FFD4F5496C9D38F3BDBF0DD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A law enforcement agency of a governmental entity and an element of the intelligence community may not obtain from a third party in exchange for anything of value a covered customer or subscriber record or any illegitimately obtained information. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AA52117CA3F49A4AB66C9582F71C655"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Indirectly acquired records and information</header><text>The limitation under subparagraph (A) shall apply without regard to whether the third party possessing the covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information is the third party that initially obtained or collected, or is the third party that initially received the disclosure of, the covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H39E85F4ADE80428583E20AFB6F19B28A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limit on sharing between agencies</header><text>An agency of a governmental entity that is not a law enforcement agency or an element of the intelligence community may not provide to a law enforcement agency of a governmental entity or an element of the intelligence community a covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information that was obtained from a third party in exchange for anything of value.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAEE50163D6E4ED7B3EC25F9C573E860"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prohibition on use as evidence</header><text>A covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information obtained by or provided to a law enforcement agency of a governmental entity or an element of the intelligence community in violation of paragraph (2) or (3), and any evidence derived therefrom, may not be received in evidence in any trial, hearing, or other proceeding in or before any court, grand jury, department, officer, agency, regulatory body, legislative committee, or other authority of the United States, a State, or a political subdivision thereof.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58DF0F83B42B42E68B485F4EE21F36D1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Minimization procedures</header><subparagraph id="HF9008A8728304F1E955F693DC9DF0605"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General shall adopt specific procedures that are reasonably designed to minimize the acquisition and retention, and prohibit the dissemination, of information pertaining to a covered person that is acquired in violation of paragraph (2) or (3).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB74BA2FF74DB4D86B86231DD6956668A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Use by agencies</header><text>If a law enforcement agency of a governmental entity or element of the intelligence community acquires information pertaining to a covered person in violation of paragraph (2) or (3), the law enforcement agency of a governmental entity or element of the intelligence community shall minimize the acquisition and retention, and prohibit the dissemination, of the information in accordance with the procedures adopted under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H0CDF7C028A3644B3ABC4ADC2F945757F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Required disclosure</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2703 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF8FCA62AA1F74D268BCBB48E8F7FE617"><subsection id="H4D50F1A6EAEE42968FD2B6BCB64E51FF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Covered customer or subscriber records and illegitimately obtained information</header><paragraph id="H0B1975F4DC8F40AB96F35C77BB037F77"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>covered customer or subscriber record</term>, <term>illegitimately obtained information</term>, and <term>third party</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 2702(e).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7AFB37D1CF0041D5908123DF1D3A7008"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Unless a governmental entity obtains an order in accordance with paragraph (3), the governmental entity may not require a third party to disclose a covered customer or subscriber record or any illegitimately obtained information if a court order would be required for the governmental entity to require a provider of remote computing service or a provider of electronic communication service to the public to disclose such a covered customer or subscriber record or illegitimately obtained information that is a record of a customer or subscriber of the provider.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FFFA4B6D536446FBDCF2884CD1DC876"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Orders</header><subparagraph id="H32F8AC7CDDEF4B22BEA9995F89B93AB1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A court may only issue an order requiring a third party to disclose a covered customer or subscriber record or any illegitimately obtained information on the same basis and subject to the same limitations as would apply to a court order to require disclosure by a provider of remote computing service or a provider of electronic communication service to the public of a record of a customer or subscriber of the provider.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H329591297C0647B08763BDB795233999"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Standard</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), a court shall apply the most stringent standard under Federal statute or the Constitution of the United States that would be applicable to a request for a court order to require a comparable disclosure by a provider of remote computing service or a provider of electronic communication service to the public of a record of a customer or subscriber of the provider.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H072D1EF5F9B04E7AAA904F385E159AF8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Intermediary service providers</header><subsection id="H32DF75FC980848B6B7E7A80124CE5268"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 2711 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD9DC742393874EC8BF677A4CAA872E4F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1307272655BD438FB9AFE480BB8A5A42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6C59511C43B42D4AD8AED6397893778"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF4437BF5095F4890845EE3037F569D1C"><paragraph id="H51CF1B8EE3F3426DAA82A484FA205EF4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>intermediary service provider</term> means an entity or facilities owner or operator that directly or indirectly delivers, stores, or processes communications for or on behalf of a provider of electronic communication service to the public or a provider of remote computing service.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H99626DEEDDE3464B861F54A982685EB2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Section 2702(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H2C4167C74E2D46888E9218601E9123EC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D0F314858C94591B74D43B76FA5FD42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7E42E90E07A4BF1B08AFF8498CDBEC8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3AF863F77504F8CBDBECF57B0E02ED6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2F34C23B8D934889A05AD453FBCC17BB"><paragraph id="H4026DE7AC30F4540BC55A58162708E5E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an intermediary service provider shall not knowingly divulge—</text><subparagraph id="H628F95BEE9E04575ABBAEB267E4122B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to any person or entity the contents of a communication while in electronic storage by that provider; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50B499ED52004427846E55EAAFE427E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to any governmental entity a record or other information pertaining to a subscriber to or customer of, a recipient of a communication from a subscriber to or customer of, or the sender of a communication to a subscriber to or customer of, the provider of electronic communication service to the public or the provider of remote computing service for, or on behalf of, which the intermediary service provider directly or indirectly delivers, transmits, stores, or processes communications.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2C10FEF81415494B93A6C2A76F8CEB14"><enum>5.</enum><header>Limits on surveillance conducted for foreign intelligence purposes other than under the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978</header><subsection id="HD880C06DF83B4DAFAC689E82C33F2119"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 2511(2)(f) of title 18, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2ADA3B6C9A974D78B198AB0FF82F806A"><subsection id="H303AE8F8F8084D49B7554647BE92A88A"><enum>(f)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H67BFABA47D0D4FF8B8159F3E2916FD28"><enum>(i)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA3C1CE685EE2401B840B456E69AB1329"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Nothing contained in this chapter, chapter 121 or 206 of this title, or section 705 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>) shall be deemed to affect an acquisition or activity described in clause (B) that is carried out utilizing a means other than electronic surveillance, as defined in section 101 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8525FBC983BC4A60A3CFC0A04F7818DE" indent="up2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An acquisition or activity described in this clause is—</text><clause id="H554B13E06B0A4B4BBDC80F0E7BF75F91"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an acquisition by the United States Government of foreign intelligence information from international or foreign communications that—</text><subclause id="H02BE810560004880B9BC302BDFE78C91"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is acquired pursuant to express statutory authority; or </text></subclause><subclause id="HB22ED632C01F432C9D4FDD1F4F0D4744"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>only includes information of persons who are not United States persons and are located outside the United States; or </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HC25CE20A99DD418A89E87832031944F5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a foreign intelligence activity involving a foreign electronic communications system that— </text><subclause id="HEE3CCA662B5F479BB97471AE44A6115E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is conducted pursuant to express statutory authority; or </text></subclause><subclause id="HED8E03E71C9A4A96BBB62685DED043DD"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>only involves the acquisition by the United States Government of information of persons who are not United States persons and are located outside the United States.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H089633C2784B464BA1F4F2149308B6DF" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The procedures in this chapter, chapter 121, and the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) shall be the exclusive means by which electronic surveillance, as defined in section 101 of such Act, and the interception of domestic wire, oral, and electronic communications may be conducted.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H093BF59C8D6748DB8CD8627EB80715E4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exclusive means related to communications records</header><text>The Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) shall be the exclusive means by which electronic communications transactions records, call detail records, or other information from communications of United States persons or persons inside the United States are acquired for foreign intelligence purposes inside the United States or from a person or entity located in the United States that provides telecommunications, electronic communication, or remote computing services.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCD66D8675A2A4FFEA2F53B39B58C9C57"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exclusive means related to location information, web browsing history, and internet search history</header><paragraph id="H38C6A58A360846978FB18C95477EC32B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>location information</term> has the meaning given that term in subsection (e) of section 2702 of title 18, United States Code, as added by section 2 of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H177FC6DF44B849E6ABF94483A7EFBE31"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusive means</header><text>Title I and sections 303, 304, 703, 704, and 705 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>, 1823, 1824, 1881b, 1881c, 1881d) shall be the exclusive means by which location information, web browsing history, and internet search history of United States persons or persons inside the United States are acquired for foreign intelligence purposes inside the United States or from a person or entity located in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6010C2372E414CF0AD52F9FA238439CF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exclusive means related to fourth amendment-Protected information</header><text>Title I and sections 303, 304, 703, 704, and 705 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>, 1823, 1824, 1881b, 1881c, 1881d) shall be the exclusive means by which any information, records, data, or tangible things are acquired for foreign intelligence purposes from a person or entity located in the United States if the compelled production of such information, records, data, or tangible things would require a warrant for law enforcement purposes.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEEEA5D7D1BA046D685A64690C560E046"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>United States person</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801</external-xref>). </text></subsection></section><section id="H117AA660E761448E8EF9CE223418E321"><enum>6.</enum><header>Limit on civil immunity for providing information, facilities, or technical assistance to the Government absent a court order</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2511(2)(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H5A82C385F4BF4BD9823C3AD5325E617D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (ii), by striking clause (B) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD24A96C9CD3408AA2FA05057F890BA9"><subparagraph id="HBA5968DFA58B4B36ABE375C18F00C873" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a certification in writing—</text><clause id="H2BB7EA6DEF144B389198BA07DCA7927B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by a person specified in section 2518(7) or the Attorney General of the United States; </text></clause><clause id="HCB67F552BA1341058F2CEFD0307E6F0F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that the requirements for an emergency authorization to intercept a wire, oral, or electronic communication under section 2518(7) have been met; and</text></clause><clause id="HF81D0D776D7A48F28D2A26F3AC108F34"><enum>(III)</enum><text>that the specified assistance is required,</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H603205D1396147109F98B7001F717A22"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (iii) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFDF9A198F2F843E68BC06EE4E06F458B"><clause id="H9B72F14B9C5D4F0EA291D06E839CDDFA" indent="up3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>For assistance provided pursuant to a certification under subparagraph (ii)(B), the limitation on causes of action under the last sentence of the matter following subparagraph (ii)(B) shall only apply to the extent that the assistance ceased at the earliest of the time the application for a court order was denied, the time the communication sought was obtained, or 48 hours after the interception began.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

