<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFFBC2266AB59430894404F0E6B1E7674" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1315 IH: Prostate Cancer Community Assistance, Research and Education Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1315</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230301">March 1, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to establish a Prostate Cancer Coordinating Committee, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE8115074C2E041FFA66629CEC4C9A688" style="OLC">
<section id="H9B3B5B0F619C4E05926D1DDC15DC8ED2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Prostate Cancer Community Assistance, Research and Education Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PC–CARE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD3BC4B17B18541ADB65CDE8B25D35C13"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H483165F4BD0B4F419F0919A3E41F5325"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prostate cancer is the most commonly diagnosed non-skin cancer and the second leading cause of cancer-related deaths among men in the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5222C2D6955C481F9A17F0EE4F03D6E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Over 3,100,000 men in the United States live with a prostate cancer diagnosis and it is estimated that in 2023, 288,300 men will be diagnosed with, and more than 34,700 men will die of, prostate cancer.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAF0680AEB9BA43F882A03D6B3672EE26"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Men with at least one close relative who has been diagnosed with prostate cancer have twice the risk of having prostate cancer compared to the general population.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC8C455798AB546418598F30B364E8069"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At least 12 percent of men with metastatic prostate cancer have inherited predispositions to the disease and potentially actionable genomic alterations have been identified in over 90 percent of men with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H82679DF3690B4E53940CB63AD46A4CBB"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Advances in science to identify, test, and treat these men at increased genetic risk of disease are needed.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB6A3B483F4D04DB589D987499C7B5C8C"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">African-American men suffer from a prostate cancer incidence rate that is significantly higher than that of White men and have more than double the prostate cancer mortality rate than that of White men.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2E1FD39E32EE43DEA04353EF20FEEAE9"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Research has shown that veterans exposed to herbicides, such as Agent Orange, are at higher risk for and more likely to be diagnosed with aggressive forms of prostate cancer.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H96205BAC588745DDA35DA39CFDC17FD2"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Screening by a digital rectal examination and a prostate-specific antigen blood test can detect the disease at the earlier, more treatable stages.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H40E68E1AA71A45BCBBEE759833269551"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Men diagnosed with early stage disease have a nearly 100 percent 5-year survival rate but only 30 percent of men survive more than 5 years if diagnosed with prostate cancer after the cancer has metastasized.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD545770274134A83990DC08099578BEE"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Early-staged prostate cancer has no symptoms, raising the importance of early detection and screening.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEE6BD55AF1154B42B366AF2C41588BB6"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Defense, and the Department of Veterans Affairs all have a role in providing care for and conducting research on prostate cancer.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB057FF7623E54B2BB031D7E93E057217"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Multiple institutes at the National Institutes of Health are engaged in prostate cancer care and research, including the National Cancer Institute, National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering, the National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities, and the Clinical Center.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7288F12BC8124D27BDF5BEA2602E4152"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Additional agencies and offices within the Department of Health and Human Services conduct activities related to prostate cancer, including the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Food and Drug Administration, the Health Resources and Services Administration, the Office of Minority Health, and the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5DDF1710F83043738A4B909F3399C9C0"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Defense created the Prostate Cancer Research Program in 1997 and has funded more than $2,000,000,000 in prostate cancer research since that time.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B8337A91D324E27B6201B0C8CFC7F88"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Private foundations have provided substantial funding to the prostate cancer research community for almost three decades, including support for over 200 cancer centers and universities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC91C7536B1744C828E1E24897C550C94"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The Director of the National Institutes of Health has partnered with private prostate cancer research groups to study to study biological and nonbiological factors associated with aggressive prostate cancer in African-American men.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE629DE3F6C7147D695213550EB5FEDDF"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs has partnered with private foundations to establish precision oncology program hubs for prostate cancer.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H98576028A60D433E8DE775201DD839D1"><enum>(18)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention has partnered with multiple private stakeholder groups to increase awareness and education around prostate cancer in the general population and among high-risk groups.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H788373D559714E43900BD5F68B078917"><enum>(19)</enum><text>Increased coordination of governmental and nongovernmental activities can reduce costs and increase effectiveness of ongoing work.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H55093E09F35A42FFBB8C85FB5FEE6143"><enum>(20)</enum><text>Joint planning and goal setting across the Government and private sector can create a pathway toward eliminating prostate cancer deaths and improving care for millions of men.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HE0BE092A42364F6DAA552C652E549AF1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prostate Cancer Coordinating Committee</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title IV of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/281">42 U.S.C. 281 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE160C08677194A3089134447BE048361" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H630B89918C13432A9DB3C8B3299F4A54"><enum>404F.</enum><header>Prostate Cancer Coordinating Committee</header> <subsection id="H349FDDD1900D494BA7B87FF34389DB2D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a committee to be known as the Prostate Cancer Coordinating Committee (referred to in this section as the <quote>Coordinating Committee</quote>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H39B022BF037241EFA56FADE7FE24C147"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Coordinating Committee shall—</text> <paragraph id="H255333DC5DB5487CA1F6AE2D089F7D05"><enum>(1)</enum><text>monitor, coordinate, and evaluate activities with respect to prostate cancer research programs carried out by Federal agencies; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H819856F395E64E67A609E63100592352"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop and implement the plan under subsection (g).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC06ED53980A74714BA3E0ACC46A92257"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Composition</header> <paragraph id="H6D9E04860C27441C96D4D91DAB3615AF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Coordinating Committee shall be composed of not more than 24 members, to be appointed by the Secretary, of whom—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF91BA6E46740470E8D99022599B38722"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">one-half shall represent Federal agencies that carry out research or treatment activities with respect to prostate cancer, including—</text> <clause id="H2401F426601F459C82951EB90B7167D9"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Director of the National Institutes of Health (or designee);</text></clause>
<clause id="HC76C70DC2AB64E818493423EFF16DD1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the directors of the appropriate agencies of the National Institutes of Health (or designees), including the National Cancer Institute;</text></clause> <clause id="HE30F67988FF7436DA6D9092A6D397A6C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (or designee);</text></clause>
<clause id="HC7D0B92A019947BD9F75DDE776195CC5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration (or designee);</text></clause> <clause id="H15769A9C24E243D8AEDC0A5DDCC6915A"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (or designee);</text></clause>
<clause id="H51F8CAA91A3646F6B5BDD75379192882"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Commissioner of Food and Drugs (or designee);</text></clause> <clause id="H8B40CBDF81C244A8BFED020909A6994C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the Secretary of Defense (or designee); and</text></clause>
<clause id="H6C9FC7DBDA5549688B0D190B45F7F6EC"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>the Secretary of Veterans Affairs (or designee); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H317F7E1262CB4914AD2B73788B3420D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">one-half shall be individuals who have experience with prostate cancer, including—</text>
<clause id="HD93CA3C525764D01BF00C90F3EE5E55D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not less than 3 individuals who are living with prostate cancer (or a caregiver of such individual);</text></clause> <clause id="HC7034B27F2254D3AAC4946065515D6A2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not less than 3 researchers;</text></clause>
<clause id="H2C23ED288C1547D9BB33CA731D68BEC5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not less than 3 clinicians;</text></clause> <clause id="HF787D64B02054B69A2EAA98545926AEB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>not less than 3 representatives from patient groups; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H83907F5FD18542858315E9ED734A0475"><enum>(v)</enum><text>not less than 3 representatives from professional medical societies.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0079A14F40CD4B0CB81C5086124E11D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Physician requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the members appointed under paragraph (1), not less than one-half shall be physicians.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE3BF20941D5A46DD80C026614562B728"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Term; vacancies</header>
<paragraph id="H6D8C8784DB52485ABD652E3711F404EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A member shall be appointed for a term of 3 years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF8EFC91220364C88910CC0763D447983"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A vacancy on the Coordinating Committee shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment was made.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HAC4C2BAC98964AF6B0B5A61EE68A5D43"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reappointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may reappoint a member of the Coordinating Committee to an unlimited number of terms.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2E33D653856D435E88002E3E344CA159"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Chair</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall appoint the chair of the Coordinating Committee.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H9230167D19024FEA998683F810AF91CC"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Coordinating Committee shall develop and implement a plan (and update such plan every 3 years thereafter), in consultation with a broad range of scientists, patients, clinicians, and advocacy groups, on prostate cancer research programs and activities carried out by Federal agencies. Such plan shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="HAC988AC6E3724F0BA66446CB1D850A74"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The identification of existing prostate cancer programs and activities of the—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1DF32F4D0C514A8080E05BF2349265C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Department of Health and Human Services, including the National Institutes of Health;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7FBF775300DF40E1B4CB6E4B6E2380DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Department of Defense; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0BDC9344E3634B7182A653C402FD28C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H76E991A3C53D412D8A1860C8F0FDD362"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation on research with respect to the underlying causes, prevalence, treatment, and mortality of prostate cancer, including any disparity among African-American and other high-risk men (defined as men who have a family history of prostate cancer, a genetic predisposition for prostate cancer, or developed cancer due to exposure to certain chemical and radiological agents).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2998505BD4C54F24ABD4DFF4EAE16895"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to prostate cancer—</text> <subparagraph id="HA4B84536CB564964AC0F0363A0D11340"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an evaluation on the effectiveness of current screening and diagnostic techniques; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8283479FFBE44B4A8F648383996D03F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations for improving such techniques.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF269ACA86A40447B8FECCC8946AA5808"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation on the effectiveness of treatments for prostate cancer and the development of recommendations for new treatments, including new biological agents.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF55AFC96A023434A8BA166A78407150B"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to prostate cancer, an evaluation on the effectiveness of clinical practice guidelines and the development of recommendations to improve such guidelines.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3163E3EFDBC84FA2ACC2B308BDB7D91F"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The development of recommendations to improve clinical pathways in private and government-operated medical systems, including screening and diagnosis and information on informed and shared decision making.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2E8FD5D888F34BD8A8EAE4C7F3656E41"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The development of recommendations for research investigation methods for improving the quality of life of individuals who have survived with prostate cancer.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBC1BF51416AF4B97B9C0176C93A3CEC5"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to prostate cancer, an evaluation on the effectiveness of information and education programs for health care professionals and the public.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H30D2CBFA530945C48B2B5181E8E083AB"><enum>(9)</enum><text>With respect to screening and clinical trial enrollment for prostate cancer, recommendations to improve outreach and education, including best practices for outreach to African-American men and other high-risk men.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H423B2533974A4E67AAC659424AF8359F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Coordinating Committee shall meet at the request of the Secretary not less 3 times each year.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H00C45D52D8FA461D93DB70096B3FAD80"><enum>(i)</enum><header>FACA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in this section, the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the Coordinating Committee.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HECA3735559514A4791D56D68A36D0839"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Report</header> <paragraph id="H56C73B7C5075433D922FB182E4467F79"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Coordinating Committee shall submit recommendations using the plan under subsection (g) to the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H5AB3D3C042274CFDABD50BB45C73F93E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95B422CBA9B444B8A31BBB41101766FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC58C18D12872482C81597CEB1DBCF6DD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBC48B6C3BEFD4C6C917C40F5E0A2D5A4"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committees on Energy and Commerce and Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8B96F6A59ABD4D28A5B853600F285A4B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Committees on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions and Appropriations of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB08F7407E9D4434B97F263EFA5299E1A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Updated reports</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this section, and every 3 years thereafter, the Coordinating Committee shall submit to the secretaries and committees listed in paragraph (1)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC23724579E0F4998B5FB64083F94064B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>updated recommendations using the plan under subsection (g); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE320238280FE455CA8FD528CC3CCB221"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a summary of progress made with respect to recommendations submitted pursuant to this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1141328AB3CE4C439C85242F6A47AF13"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2030.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

