<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE4679EBAD733418ABF9617E0FB5E9564" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1606 IH: Veteran Entrepreneurship Training Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1606</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230314">March 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001220">Mr. McGarvey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Small Business Act to codify the Boots to Business Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H70A84E5194D24314A6B8319A9BA654EC" style="OLC"><section commented="no" section-type="section-one" id="H91A65A12D78244519A9BCBCDEFB88E3B" changed="not-changed"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veteran Entrepreneurship Training Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H5D53301B01704659ACD3B01B08565421" changed="not-changed"><enum>2.</enum><header>Boots to Business Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 32 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/657b">15 U.S.C. 657b</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HAA48134784674525BE696C2217E86FC4" changed="not-changed" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC"><subsection id="HD5E27061C3D641259210A15BDEB46B4D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Boots to Business Program</header><paragraph id="H692775FEB748409480285823BDFAAF9F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered individual defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>covered individual</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H6CF18AEA559F4AF9B5CAFFB21FF1690F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a member of the Armed Forces, including the National Guard or Reserves;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H308799977D4A4B699E038CFF58147B9C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an individual who is participating in the Transition Assistance Program established under section 1144 of title 10, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A202F5FE1B842E09E7DDF5F2B076DDA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an individual who—</text><clause id="H836A7B94419D408B8C6A417672DCC079" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>served on active duty in any branch of the Armed Forces, including the National Guard or Reserves; and</text></clause><clause id="H42B3E4D25AD04F34983022DB32D241A9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>was discharged or released from such service under conditions other than dishonorable; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3EF81DBF40043A694E0B50D721B8918" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a spouse or dependent of an individual described in subparagraph (A), (B), or (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DF3AFA56F204CE99533708DEE05467B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>During the period beginning on the date of enactment of this subsection and ending on September 30, 2028, the Administrator shall carry out a program to be known as the <quote>Boots to Business Program</quote> to provide entrepreneurship training to covered individuals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H364806B51C264D768615A8A2461CFB30" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Goals</header><text>The goals of the Boots to Business Program are to—</text><subparagraph id="H4B5A7D16D86D4620BA5F663D9FA2421A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide assistance and in-depth training to covered individuals interested in business ownership; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE225FFC2E7DA4C58962F2D8C910B4038" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide covered individuals with the tools, skills, and knowledge necessary to identify a business opportunity, draft a business plan, identify sources of capital, connect with local resources for small business concerns, and start up a small business concern.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H810C19959FA5419284599DE9FCFB8A6F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program components</header><subparagraph id="H3CF59B9D571F4D839F4A4C810C54C3AB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Boots to Business Program may include—</text><clause id="HFD127EAB70A24B9CA4E879482048C791" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a presentation providing exposure to the considerations involved in self-employment and ownership of a small business concern;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE89DBFF9E4F54F2CAAF5F99297CDBAE9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an online, self-study course focused on the basic skills of entrepreneurship, the language of business, and the considerations involved in self-employment and ownership of a small business concern;</text></clause><clause id="H66A382F46FF14AAE8AF29BCC6F90C411" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an in-person classroom instruction component providing an introduction to the foundations of self employment and ownership of a small business concern; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H2D8ACDB871A643CB93B3BFC4F7826DB9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in-depth training delivered through online instruction, including an online course that leads to the creation of a business plan.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86ACAC5DF3A540D0BD8E7C3A4FFD2224" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>The Administrator may—</text><clause id="H376B002A0DF549669B31FC36F94F90E9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>collaborate with public and private entities to develop course curricula for the Boots to Business Program; and</text></clause><clause id="H4DC3A0A99AC3494283E89DCD453C2443" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>modify program components in coordination with entities participating in a Warriors in Transition program, as defined in section 738(e) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2013 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1071">10 U.S.C. 1071</external-xref> note).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BE9780B299A4D789B497C4EA51144C6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Use of resource partners and district offices</header><clause id="H6A14D4378BF3499CB388C3A403F69517" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall—</text><subclause id="HD93BC0D14E3D45AB8283790F7143A3BB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that Veteran Business Outreach Centers regularly participate, on a nationwide basis, in the Boots to Business Program; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H5C78E49D4C6943E6857C0209592F0518" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, use district offices of the Administration and a variety of other resource partners and entities in administering the Boots to Business Program.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFCBCF993E3584EAE99C1D4124D56EC0D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out clause (i), the Administrator may make grants to Veteran Business Outreach Centers, other resource partners, or other entities to carry out components of the Boots to Business Program.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDFECA49324B4E839CBC254ABE0A7580" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Availability to Department of Defense and the Department of Labor</header><text>The Administrator shall make available to the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Labor information regarding the Boots to Business Program, including all course materials and outreach materials related to the Boots to Business Program, for inclusion on the websites of the Department of Defense and the Department of Labor relating to the Transition Assistance Program, in the Transition Assistance Program manual, and in other relevant materials available for distribution from the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Labor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1084BC5A01034EF3A656B018D3DC1754" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Availability to Department of Veterans Affairs</header><text>In consultation with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, the Administrator shall make available for distribution and display on the website of the Department of Veterans Affairs and at local facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs outreach materials regarding the Boots to Business Program, which shall, at a minimum—</text><clause id="H77AF233644FB48E287BE5CB585713591" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>describe the Boots to Business Program and the services provided; and</text></clause><clause id="HE9FD35A380464D0C90A377C5914F49F3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>include eligibility requirements for participating in the Boots to Business Program.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4EBA04594E204655A79F050C92FD07D7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Availability to other participating agencies</header><text>The Administrator shall ensure information regarding the Boots to Business program, including all course materials and outreach materials related to the Boots to Business Program, is made available to other participating agencies in the Transition Assistance Program and upon request of other agencies. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H024EF30F81A74FF4A77F8F216A1E61C0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Competitive bidding procedures</header><text>The Administration shall use relevant competitive bidding procedures with respect to any contract or cooperative agreement executed by the Administration under the Boots to Business Program. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11348D8B19814D4BBD685A66D4BE021E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Publication of notice of funding opportunity</header><text>Not later than 30 days before the deadline for submitting applications for any funding opportunity under the Boots to Business Program, the Administration shall publish a notice of the funding opportunity. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H94E0C852114A4947A359B38DEBF97CB3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, and not less frequently than annually thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate and the Committee on Small Business of the House of Representatives a report on the performance and effectiveness of the Boots to Business Program, which—</text><subparagraph id="H4484193B90574ACFB308405CF00F4326" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may be included as part of another report submitted to such committees by the Administrator related to the Office of Veterans Business Development; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90A364F75CE246379EE68749E01C414A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall summarize available information relating to—</text><clause id="H47D5896E21C6464988FC5A29C3C567A0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">grants awarded under paragraph (4)(C);</text></clause><clause id="H3F7FB3009A6E45FDB8BD1F3B387CAA79" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total cost of the Boots to Business Program;</text></clause><clause id="H3ED206D623AA43628FEE2187698BDD6F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of program participants using each component of the Boots to Business Program;</text></clause><clause id="H57641AB051C448AC898A38CB46358279" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the completion rates for each component of the Boots to Business Program;</text></clause><clause id="HE65D10F94E1F440281FBA09A6E87A6DE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>to the extent possible—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H54BE90F284CA4774A76D7FD2C0A449D6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the demographics of program participants, to include gender, age, race, ethnicity, and relationship to military;</text></subclause><subclause display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H92D4EDF9CEDE40A1BA55B358DD5B12AB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the number of program participants that connect with a district office of the Administration, a Veteran Business Outreach Center, or another resource partner of the Administration;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF64D07B03A2D47388C19B5E13852EF49" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the number of program participants that start a small business concern;</text></subclause><subclause id="H7AC6B966BC2C4DCE97D4453C90916888" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the results of the Boots to Business and Boots to Business Reboot course quality surveys conducted by the Office of Veterans Business Development before and after attending each of those courses, including a summary of any comments received from program participants;</text></subclause><subclause id="H2820B019A09F429EB64FBD3449DCF731" changed="not-changed"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the results of the Boots to Business Program outcome surveys conducted by the Office of Veterans Business Development, including a summary of any comments received from program participants; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3A0BE0D152884C62979CD85F29F6AD84" changed="not-changed"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>the results of other germane participant satisfaction surveys;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80D0850A32F6431ABB95D3A1828C9326" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an evaluation of the overall effectiveness of the Boots to Business Program based on each geographic region covered by the Administration during the most recent fiscal year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4FC7C416BC6F44D2A90C2E9D57919558" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an assessment of additional performance outcome measures for the Boots to Business Program, as identified by the Administrator;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCFD66DF962C7475F85FEACC800D308D1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any recommendations of the Administrator for improvement of the Boots to Business Program, which may include expansion of the types of individuals who are covered individuals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CAED915AAF34E3599BE9841CE2859EC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>an explanation of how the Boots to Business Program has been integrated with other transition programs and related resources of the Administration and other Federal agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD34E87B16E33475FBD235DC32FAE875A" changed="not-changed" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(G)</enum><text>any additional information the Administrator determines necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

