<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC5BD701A491F492ABE99C2D5B21FA827" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6125 IH: Online Dating Safety Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6125</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231030">October 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require online dating service providers to provide fraud ban notifications to online dating service members, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3DC96C260B1E4B9E82884347DB87DD7E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0F32DE7B5EEF442483AB2B78C3604C87" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Online Dating Safety Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF28E4369DB3A475CABC166E6817A6C27"><enum>2.</enum><header>Online dating safety</header> <subsection id="HFBE6B47846A74D73ABB027622D59D455"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Fraud ban notification</header> <paragraph id="HF21DBA5F121544899261ADBD4525759B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An online dating service provider shall provide to a member of the online dating service a fraud ban notification if the member has received a message through the online dating service from a banned member of the online dating service.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAAFCC84CFF7A4F278B88FCC4B5FCD342"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Required contents</header><text>A fraud ban notification under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H7616E278404743F98FC752E779C9C40D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The username or other profile identifier of the banned member, as well as the most recent time when the member to whom the notification is being provided sent or received a message through the online dating service to or from the banned member.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBBB177CDF5264F9788960F782A30182D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A statement that the banned member may have been using a false identity or attempting to defraud members.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H52B0E21E73954617AD17D6F2BEAB0FDF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A statement that a member should not send money or personal financial information to another member.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC1825F54A3CF4AEA99F7BDD0A763EC23"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An online link to information regarding ways to avoid online fraud or being defrauded by a member of an online dating service.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6206AC3E81E04879967445F272CD99FB"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Contact information to reach the customer service department of the online dating service provider.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H408D14020DF44E91AEB7C261915CDE92"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Manner and timing</header> 
<subparagraph id="H5456C935AFBF44238D0C6D7AEE64EC6E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Manner</header><text>A fraud ban notification under paragraph (1) shall be—</text> <clause id="H6CF4F208F0744E3AAD257EE055898867"><enum>(i)</enum><text>clear and conspicuous; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6B93902F9988407AAA3BFB2FB96A3E5A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provided by email, text message, or other appropriate means of communication consented to by the member.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85603944675343BC81E25B943CE95C5E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing</header> <clause id="HA09A3CEEA9E04460A4DCCD28579FDBB8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clauses (ii) and (iii), an online dating service provider shall provide a fraud ban notification under paragraph (1) not later than 24 hours after the fraud ban is initiated against the banned member.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7EAC83A406554A40A70AB6F0007F34A2"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Delay based on judgment of provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, in the judgment of the online dating service provider, the circumstances require a fraud ban notification under paragraph (1) to be provided after the 24-hour period described in clause (i), the online dating service provider shall, except as provided in clause (iii), provide the notification not later than 3 days after the day on which the fraud ban is initiated against the banned member.</text></clause> <clause id="HF8CA2E77701E4555821A6214BBBAC290"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Delay upon request of law enforcement official</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, due to an ongoing investigation, a law enforcement official requests an online dating service provider to delay providing a fraud ban notification under paragraph (1) beyond the time when the notification is required to be provided under clause (i) or (ii), the online dating service provider—</text> 
<subclause id="HF41AFBD64AF6406D911E80B956CFAA67"><enum>(I)</enum><text>may not provide the notification before the end of the period of delay (including any extension of such period) requested by the law enforcement official; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HBDFC2DEB6B864C88B55E6072EB266F7C"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall provide the notification not later than 3 days after the last day of the period of delay (including any extension of such period) requested by the law enforcement official.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54A2C7A3BB8B490993F18065C8AF6F1C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation of liability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An online dating service provider is not liable to a person in a civil action based on any of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H05A27DDB38E84C9EA4F9B7360FD386AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The means of communication used to provide a fraud ban notification to a member under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0C76B099586E4DF09C79273732EAEEA7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The timing of a fraud ban notification provided to a member under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H61683C47A5FC4A51BB2C901AA4AF6C28"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The disclosure of information in a fraud ban notification provided under paragraph (1), including the following:</text> 
<clause id="HFC031F700F494CC3AA1BD3D63A350387"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Information that a member is a banned member or the subject of a fraud ban.</text></clause> <clause id="H3ED45F94251D477BB7034712A07A45A2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The username or other profile identifier of the banned member.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4BF9C8BC6D2249A2AA0210A94EE606C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The reason that the online dating service provider initiated the fraud ban of the banned member.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB929F086DD5342308249E9B5B1F0D54A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No private right of action; preservation of certain immunity</header><text>This subsection does not create a private right of action or diminish or adversely affect protections for an online dating service provider under section 230 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/230">47 U.S.C. 230</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8920DBD8D218447E894D4A6D8ED493BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement by Federal Trade Commission</header> 
<paragraph id="HF0E19A4E9A9646B4BA01D93661C32AE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A violation of this section shall be treated as a violation of a regulation under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99D37FF909AB437A8CA4CFB589CB3E89"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall enforce this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section, and any person who violates this section shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCD1DEC6FC14D4329837165836D74AE0F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed to limit the authority of the Commission under any other provision of law.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3E588C2FD2BD476BA17A045D0F94C357"><enum>(c)</enum><header>One national standard</header> <paragraph id="HE43B420C9DB94B9E95286577735CD37E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State, or political subdivision of a State, may not maintain, enforce, prescribe, or continue in effect any law, rule, regulation, requirement, standard, or other provision having the force and effect of law of the State, or political subdivision of the State, that requires an online dating service provider to notify, prohibits an online dating service provider from notifying, or otherwise affects the manner in which an online dating service provider is required or permitted to notify, a member of the online dating service that the member has received a message from or sent a message to a banned member through the online dating service.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H929811BF822740DDAB2C324192EE5C56"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection may not be construed to preempt any law of a State or political subdivision of a State relating to contracts or torts.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H05221F345459486A9B7E2FDEC81914A4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H3C5D46A336CA4313BD26F091FF47F585"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Banned member</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>banned member</term> means a member of an online dating service whose account or profile on the online dating service is the subject of a fraud ban.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE37D8AA84D5D4C67805A90E3B9205281"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Trade Commission.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H028E2DD40A2C40A189DA2672A68E57C8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fraud ban</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fraud ban</term> means the termination or suspension of the account or profile of a member of an online dating service because, in the judgment of the online dating service provider, there is a significant risk the member will attempt to obtain money from another member through fraudulent means.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0AC6464E5561438CB2F589EFC57F7878"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Member</header><text>The term <term>member</term> means an individual who—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3AEBFA96FE22452CBC9A0AE5588FB166"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submits to an online dating service provider the information required by the provider to establish an account or profile on the online dating service; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF152306F898A4B77A6A550C62F7B68C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is allowed by the provider to establish such an account or profile.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H237EDBFBE2FB4457909AE9E462799F32"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Online dating service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>online dating service</term> means a service that—</text> <subparagraph id="HBDD9028346954B66BE0EF843935BF369"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is provided through a website or a mobile application; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3AAE980536A142CEA4C6B247EA10E589"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offers members access to dating or romantic relationships with other members by arranging or facilitating the social introduction of members.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C38044701D94DF9BC8B0E0DF41354FC"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Online dating service provider</header><text>The term <term>online dating service provider</term> means a person engaged in the business of offering an online dating service.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H62BEE78D07E24830820FB8A22FA6FC77" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>State</quote> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, each commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7905CF435EA44483AB767F4174352C47"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall take effect on the date that is 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

