<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="HD2A47C0CAF2F4A97807A60F9584164EB">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1174 IH: Dr. Norman C. Francis Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1174</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To award a Congressional Gold Medal to Dr. Norman Christopher Francis, in recognition of his contributions to the United States through his lifelong dedication to education, justice, and public service.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H3627EFD8188448EAB7F1D987B0178F87">
<section id="H5C8A6EB6B3BA4A26A5F40C7D2AD3A18C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Dr. Norman C. Francis Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5829138BB35942379D09681A5C1C91C1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H0C392F32770646E8A2FC4E15A01AA766"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Dr. Norman Christopher Francis was born in Lafayette, LA, on March 20, 1931, to Joseph A. Francis and Mabel F. Francis. His parents were a barber and a homemaker, and he had a Catholic education at St. Paul Catholic elementary and secondary schools in Lafayette.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4DE684D0F4F4457D966C6CEA73B9A47D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>After graduation, Francis attended Xavier University of Louisiana in New Orleans, where he graduated with a Bachelor of Science degree.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H496F58B8CDC0486993E447E56B422D9D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An honor student all four years at Xavier University of Louisiana, young Norman Francis conducted his work scholarship repairing damaged books in the university library. In his senior year, he was elected student body president.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC9740EA6373A46F0B343F4F44F979256"><enum>(4)</enum><text>From 1952–1955, Francis attended Loyola University Law School in New Orleans, where he earned his Juris Doctorate. He made history as the first Black graduate of Loyola University Law School in 1955.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5613E9F6965647A6B0B57195321A8C99"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Upon graduation he married the late Mrs. Blanche Macdonald, but then was drafted into the United States Army’s Third Armored Division, where he earned the rank of corporal specialist four. After a two-year tour of duty, Francis left the Army in 1957 and began his civilian career.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1DEBA84C9AFE4C0F94CB6C8B523A13DD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Upon his return from the military, he joined the U.S. Attorney’s Office and worked to help integrate Federal agencies.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H55FD54A942684B418FBFF8E70F44C458"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Dr. Francis used his law degree to represent civil rights activists as a young lawyer. One of his clients was Xavier student body president, Rudolph Lombard, who had been arrested for attempting to integrate the lunch counter at McCrory’s on Canal Street in New Orleans.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3A1D82E3FA78419D82C42B3C57E2874D"><enum>(8)</enum><text>As Dean of Men at Xavier University of Louisiana in 1961, he showed his moral courage and vision by housing the Freedom Riders in the historic St. Michael’s dormitory when the rest of New Orleans establishments had closed their doors to them or openly threatened their safety.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1A43ACAF007B42248AC318F0852FB8B6"><enum>(9)</enum><text>In 1963, he became Director of Student Personnel Services and one year later (1964) he was promoted to Assistant to the President. In 1967, he became Executive Vice President.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D5CA2FAB8CC4A1CA2ADA5C4E5A19560"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In 1967, Dr. Francis joined the brotherhood of Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Incorporated, Sigma Lambda chapter.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2F5B83D6106747ECA53CD1B4F76723C9"><enum>(11)</enum><text>On the day of the assassination of Dr. Martin Luther King, April 4, 1968, at the age of 37, Dr. Francis accepted the position as President of Xavier University of Louisiana, the Nation’s only historically Black and Catholic university, and his alma mater. He broke barriers on that day by becoming the first African-American lay person to serve in that position.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63F9ED0F97B148CD95E5CD992B3734A0"><enum>(12)</enum><text>His tenure as President lasted from 1968–2015, and he is one of the longest-sitting university presidents in the Nation’s history. Over that 49-year term, Dr. Francis steered the university to grow both in size and dimension.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFC5592F854E84C28819F6580A01A4810"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Dr. Francis was President of Xavier University of Louisiana during the height of the Civil Rights Movement, and while at the helm of the school, he more than tripled its enrollment, expanded course offerings, and transformed the campus grounds into an <quote>Emerald City</quote> of colorful green roofs. During his tenure, Xavier awarded more doctorate pharmacy degrees to Black Americans and sent more Black graduates to medical school than any other U.S. university.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED60D7365B4044CBBE657431767A378B"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Dr. Francis cofounded the Liberty Bank of New Orleans, one of the largest Black-owned banks in the country. Dr. Francis has served as its Chairman since the Bank’s inception in 1972 working to improve access to financial institutions for Black Americans.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD7DB5BF42F2C40CD9963A4E79938DACD"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Francis has served in an advisory role to eight U.S. presidential administrations—not only on education issues, but civil rights as well—in addition to serving on 54 boards and commissions. In 1983, Francis helped compile and release the report <quote>A Nation at Risk</quote> during his service on the National Commission on Excellence in Education. The report was a landmark piece that summarized racism and classism with the school system and called for comprehensive education reform.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD9DD3ECFECC44CD1942856C4F4BEAC6B"><enum>(16)</enum><text>He co-chaired the Louisiana Recovery Authority after Hurricane Katrina, playing a vital role in helping the people of New Orleans and the Gulf Coast rebuild their lives in the aftermath of Hurricane Katrina.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6CD5996A849648DA9BFD8E5E81642A96"><enum>(17)</enum><text>In 2006, then-President George W. Bush presented him with the Nation’s highest civil award, the Presidential Medal of Freedom in recognition of his, <quote>deep intellect, compassion and character.</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H62D70A27603D47138640746EC1127DBA"><enum>(18)</enum><text>In 2009, he was named one of <quote>America’s Best Leaders</quote> by U.S. News Media Group and the Center for Public Leadership (CPL) at Harvard Kennedy’s School of Government.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF159F554F01D4AFFB67A17B576FA6B6B"><enum>(19)</enum><text>He has received 40 honorary degrees from other universities, and at least 20 major awards in recognition of his leadership in higher education as well as his unselfish service to New Orleans and to the Nation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63FDBE0FBF19475EACE3651C0BDF075D"><enum>(20)</enum><text>Francis’ civic endeavors include service as Chair of the Louisiana Recovery Authority, past Chair of the Louisiana Disaster Recovery Foundation, past Chair of the Southern Education Foundation, Chairman of the Board of Liberty Bank and Trust and a member of the Times-Picayune Advisory Board. Previously he has been Chairman of the New Orleans Aviation Board, the Metropolitan Area Committee Education Fund and the Board of Directors of PBS-affiliate WLAE–TV.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB3CA7CAE52844827859B77A2E29DBCF8"><enum>(21)</enum><text>Dr. Francis has been involved at the national level as past Chairman of the Boards of the Educational Testing Service, the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, the College Board, the Southern Education Foundation and the American Association of Higher Education. He was also member president of the UNCF, a member of the Board of Trustees of Catholic University, and Chairman of SACS, the southern regional accrediting agency for more than 11,000 institutions in eleven States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAAD4A958F22F4A2185C6FFF2E10EFA8A"><enum>(22)</enum><text>A man of enduring determination, vision, faith, and strength, Dr. Norman C. Francis has forever changed the lives and landscape of the communities of New Orleans, Louisiana, and all of America. We are forever grateful for his service and are proud to present him with the distinguished recognition of a Congressional Gold Medal.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H312FF8B42768408CA661C9EBAB1460ED"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header>
<subsection id="HC87E092F5CE5426D8B560809FE113A64"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presentation authorized</header><text>The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the presentation, on behalf of Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design to Dr. Norman C. Francis, in recognition of his contributions to the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD3A0B2D927184680B512528000F32CD3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text>For purposes of the presentation referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike a gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary. The design shall bear an image of, and inscription of the name of, Dr. Norman C. Francis.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H96D71F8733FA4F40AFE47C2ECBC41F28"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck pursuant to section 3, at a price sufficient to cover the cost thereof, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></section> <section id="H7C19B5446DA14A6F824673701340DB2B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header> <subsection id="H7BC3E16503D04CEF8E5C29D87D4252A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text>The medals struck pursuant to this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H8A66721EC4D54BE7ACBB0C40224EBFFA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of sections 5134 and 5136 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H542DB5A6C2B14BF7B18ED2B2E7AAFA3E"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header> <subsection id="HEC42856A54C74E558949BD891AAE813B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck under this Act.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H638CEB6DC7314CCFB541BE5CF329114A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>Amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

