<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H72910EDAE9AA40ED89413FB70A07BB06" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5526 IH: Seniors’ Access to Critical Medications Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5526</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230918">September 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000459">Mr. Fleischmann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to clarify the application of the in-office ancillary services exception to the physician self-referral prohibition for drugs furnished under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDF9C4575985D40B5B52119E1FE847FC9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7C10B0494E214A57A98E68EA2F912BFF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Seniors’ Access to Critical Medications Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA754177E969D469CBB7F035AE6389476"><enum>2.</enum><header>Clarifying the application of the in-office ancillary services exception to the physician self-referral prohibition for drugs furnished under the Medicare program</header> <subsection id="HBB962242418A4466B575F5BF6FB6A2D2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1877(b)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395nn">42 U.S.C. 1395nn(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>With respect to services consisting of drugs, and any supplies necessary to administer such drugs, furnished on or after May 11, 2023, the requirement that such drugs and supplies be furnished in accordance with subparagraph (A)(ii) in order to qualify as a case described in this paragraph shall not apply.</quote>. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBFFF37AF52F546F29DCD42B2F664654F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Withdrawal of FAQs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall remove the frequently asked questions and answers published on the website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services on September 20, 2021, and May 19, 2023, which prohibit or seek to prohibit the arrangement described in the amendment made by subsection (a) and those frequently asked questions and answers shall be deemed to have never been published.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

