<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H3678AB64ED694EE78EF844C673C1D57B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 2988 RH: DOE and NASA Interagency Research Coordination Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 138</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2988</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–174]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001225">Mr. Sorensen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on April 27, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for Department of Energy and National Aeronautics and Space Administration research and development coordination, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HSY00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H543888E423E54932BAAF8308EB3DCEF0"><section id="H735EB0BF72E64F7D99A2F04A82FED7A4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DOE and NASA Interagency Research Coordination Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5702C98CD02146ADBC57911F3CA8852C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Energy and National Aeronautics and Space Administration research and development coordination</header><subsection id="HFFE44D2C6CD74525B180540C9D400397"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) and the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (in this section referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote>) may carry out, as practicable, cross-cutting and collaborative research and development activities to support the advancement of Department of Energy and National Aeronautics and Space Administration mission requirements and priorities. The Secretary and Administrator, in accordance with subsection (e), may make competitive awards to carry out such activities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC784505914954B7E8EFB682C455B56EA" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Memoranda of understanding</header><text>The Secretary and the Administrator shall coordinate the activities under subsection (a) through memoranda of understanding, or other appropriate interagency agreements.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9F80AC9DC1364D5E9FA2A2B234FD1105"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Secretary and the Administrator may—</text><paragraph id="H211A1E4D95CE4459A88E6AAE8AC91FEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct collaborative research and development activities in a variety of focus areas that may include—</text><subparagraph id="H149C53CEA4BA4C0EA34829408A7814D0" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>propulsion systems and components, including nuclear thermal and nuclear electric propulsion, radioisotope power systems, thermoelectric generators, advanced nuclear fuels, and heater units;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9748755A7E8047B8B1115082FC9E1CDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>modeling and simulation, machine learning, data assimilation, large scale data analytics, and predictive analysis in order to optimize algorithms for mission-related purposes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5811A890F81E4726802E1D73588492E1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fundamental high energy physics, astrophysics, and cosmology, including the nature of dark energy and dark matter, in accordance with section 305 of the Department of Energy Research and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18643">42 U.S.C. 18643</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9999F2FE019A4DF695ABA4B52D922373"><enum>(D)</enum><text>fundamental earth and environmental sciences, in accordance with section 306 of the Department of Energy Research and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18644">42 U.S.C. 18644</external-xref>) and section 60501 of title 51, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39488E8D7E844BD0BFFB6A6194A380B2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>quantum information sciences, including quantum computing and quantum network infrastructure, in accordance with sections 403 and 404 of the National Quantum Initiative Act (15 U.S.C. 8853 and 8854);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B599812DCCA412987196FDA2DB0724C"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">radiation health effects, in accordance with section 306 of the Department of Energy Research and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18644">42 U.S.C. 18644</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H072C261D10CE4D7AAE868858975D93B3"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ground- and space-based technology necessary for the transmission to the Earth’s surface of solar energy collected in space; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5B095189ED5475C82896D5B028BD73B"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other areas of potential research and development collaboration the Secretary and the Administrator determine important to achieving agency missions and objectives;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF851666FDD4E45B083A06E9D898FF192"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop methods to accommodate large voluntary data sets on space and aeronautical information on high-performance computing systems with variable quality and scale;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F3674AC9D694548BC52481C970F6259"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote collaboration and data and information sharing between the Department of Energy, National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the National Laboratories, and other appropriate entities by providing the necessary access and secure data and information transfer capabilities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F8FC3EE2C5F4EB2B60E62ECA5F2C49F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support the Administration’s access to the Department’s research infrastructure and capabilities, as practicable.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H74A3CC3B90BA4DFFA2F4D87CD1CAFD6D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Agreements</header><text>In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Secretary and the Administrator are authorized to—</text><paragraph id="H9DB361464037431A814D3D89CF1FAD72"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">carry out reimbursable and non-reimbursable agreements between the Department of Energy and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3FB2BF7C41D4036A2AB26D31BCA012C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collaborate with other Federal agencies, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC6046C7D62F743EF97F1C34ED14BCA9C" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Merit review process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary and the Administrator shall ensure any competitive awards made to carry out the activities under section (a) shall follow all appropriate laws and agency policies, including the following:</text><paragraph id="H054AC98467464A9382438E5AAD80D2D3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Selection by merit-review-based processes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D0E9C424E9345CC87EF98FD2955D14A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Consideration of applications from Federal agencies, National Laboratories, institutions of higher education, non-profit institutions, and other appropriate entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A5B1A6ADF6F487993E9452F7AB22947"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary and the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, a report detailing the following:</text><paragraph id="HA3B03B8BF8DC464595C1A98AE5E61363"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Interagency research and development coordination activities between the Department of Energy and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration carried out under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68052187C3174F71ACAD4353E6D78820"><enum>(2)</enum><text>How such coordination activities expand the technical capabilities of the Department and the Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H289CE0D8C68643D7A58A44DDECA0857D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Collaborative research and development achievements.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABE2269D7D824F009F42B249427F60F1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Areas of future mutually beneficial activities, including potential applications of clean energy technologies, such as marine energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H661B342E2FF749319261D270EB6B1126"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Continuation of coordination activities between the Department of Energy and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5E042A0A4A5D4037A976B8876582A133"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Research security</header><text>The activities authorized under this section shall be applied in a manner consistent with subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (enacted as division B of the CHIPS Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>)).</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

