<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H496360ECB4494C6782999713CC6A8885" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1243 IH: Federal Agent Responsibility Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1243</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230228">February 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit no-knock raids from being conducted by Federal law enforcement officers, and other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H90EB8526B693410EAEE81B5F26CC13A1" style="OLC"><section id="HE843ACB094AE4D5F9A4FD5F340E1D7A1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Agent Responsibility Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H29C661F53673469A91721CAB659A2525"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on no-knock raids</header><subsection id="H692CA77D3A064A489C14A2564CA9BAA1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition against financial aid or material aid and support</header><text>A Federal law enforcement officer or anyone employed by a Federal law enforcement agency shall not provide financial aid or material aid and support in furtherance of the execution of a non-Federal warrant requested by a law enforcement agency of a State or unit of local government.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7FCC55ACE67140838A9A9FA0DC7CBA35"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Medicine and other materials in support</header><text>For purposes of this Act, a Federal law enforcement officer shall not be considered to have provided financial aid or material aid and support in the execution of a non-Federal warrant if such officer—</text><paragraph id="HE1D04B5655AB4761A7687EC791FBBDF1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>gives or allows the use of medicine or other materials necessary to treat physical injuries; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A5E5F614FAD45A295468223DB73DD45"><enum>(2)</enum><text>helps a person escape a risk of a serious, imminent life-threatening injury. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H858D7F4C33654372A8758B62A92417B1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Exception for serious, imminent life-threatening injuries; report</header><subsection id="HB9B40CE613C3474E9692BDD52CA8C206"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Certain circumstances</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Federal law enforcement officer may forcibly enter a location subject to a Federal or non-Federal warrant, in less than 30 seconds, if there is a threat or risk of serious, imminent life-threatening injury to a law enforcement officer or others, and the law enforcement officer who enters provides a formal written report detailing such need to the judicial official responsible for authorizing the Federal or non-Federal warrant. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC5F54A9FE10A416A881898C601D6A658"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any report required under subsection (a) shall be submitted to the judicial official responsible for authorizing the Federal or non-Federal warrant not more 14 days after the date on which such warrant was executed. </text></subsection></section><section id="H7206D14BB07C4240936A5855366EB0D4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HF800C731941345CFA2EA102C37356F1B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal law enforcement agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal law enforcement agency</term> means any agency of the United States authorized to engage in or supervise the prevention, detection, investigation, or prosecution of any violation of Federal criminal law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D2689EEC39843F898D43CE443E123A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal law enforcement officer</header><text>The term <term>Federal law enforcement officer</term> has the meaning given in section 115 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43033D61BC86417C891DCF099AC85E6E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Federal warrant</header><text>The term <term>Federal warrant</term> means a warrant authorizing a search by a Federal law enforcement officer or personnel of a Federal law enforcement agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB9A53B030864C5FB9F9EA6EB2D3D85B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Material aid and support</header><text>The term <term>material aid and support</term> means voluntarily giving or allowing others to make use of lodging, communications equipment or services, facilities, weapons, personnel, vehicles, clothing, or other physical assets. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC18206EC5415495CB9C42AB4EDE7F6A7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Non-federal warrant</header><text>The term <term>non-Federal warrant</term> means a warrant authorizing a search executing an ex parte judicial order to confiscate a firearm by a law enforcement officer or a law enforcement agency affiliated with a State or unit of local government.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

