<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAE5037FC7E3D421FBE6260C37C71ED7D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3603 IH: Small Business Innovation Voucher Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3603</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230523">May 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001309">Mr. Burchett</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Small Business Administration to establish an Innovation Voucher Grant Program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF9729786840A4BFD92FAB7EB52CB1BA3" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H2930531FDA6148898DC882B9ED10D33B"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Small Business Innovation Voucher Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H64CE99F450C14361928A7ECF0EAE13CB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H6339FBA8145145AB9552807DD6028E35"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Small Business Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HEA7916D32926499582531F27E820CA2F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H04C2C651587D46DEB65EB8FF370CF71B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an institution of higher education, as defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H506319B022374EFB93262CFADB0194E5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a nonprofit research lab, institution, or other similar organization in the United States associated with educational or research activities, including a federally funded research and development center. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H107F68EDFDE140B48FB8FA753A80E056"><enum>(3)</enum><header>HUBZone</header><text>The term <term>HUBZone</term> has the meaning given the term in section 31(b) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/657a">15 U.S.C. 657a(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF7C9AA9727A4500B2A8F74E11AB159B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>Program</term> means the Innovation Voucher Grant Program established under section 3.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2430B1018E4E46EAB453C9E3BB540721"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Reservist</header><text>The term <term>Reservist</term> means a member of a reserve component of the Armed Forces named in section 10101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B51652E5B0144DFAD7E61C20DB40285"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Rural area</header><text>The term <term>rural area</term> means any county that the Bureau of the Census has defined as mostly rural or completely rural in the most recent decennial census.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74543CC2C61141D391F8FD7628483AC0"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Service-connected</header><text>The term <term>service-connected</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47AA9A32AE914966AF5EC4E70DBBE486"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Small business concern; small business concern owned and controlled by veterans; small business concern owned and controlled by women</header><text>The terms <term>small business concern</term>, <term>small business concern owned and controlled by veterans</term>, and <term>small business concern owned and controlled by women</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CE1BA64AF794936B85048E5115C3F39"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Small business concern in an underserved market</header><text>The term <term>small business concern in an underserved market</term> means a small business concern—</text><subparagraph id="H03FB2D3501FF447C82C42E13372699F1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is located in—</text><clause id="HDA2E02EEEF7F4950A2C46117C9E7F811"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a low- to moderate-income community;</text></clause><clause id="HFAE75B3D7A0C4248AFE4C00E7CB2D2BC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a HUBZone;</text></clause><clause id="HD2FCB6603F24466BA71733E08B14D4CC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a community that has been designated as an empowerment zone or an enterprise community under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1391">section 1391</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986;</text></clause><clause id="HF0A6EFFC36644F7C9E998EB4FC031CD8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a community that has been designated as a Promise Zone by the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development;</text></clause><clause id="H82BF150B5D4942A6AE9A6F0A0C2EC36B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a community that has been designated as a qualified opportunity zone under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1400Z">section 1400Z–1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; or</text></clause><clause id="HFCC3FEDC2AF3489AA84BEB47FA9E2C9E"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a rural area;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A840FAC701A4CE8BB8F97B3B6892C61"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for which more than 50 percent of the employees reside in a low- to moderate-income community;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF54757F8CF74A29993CE05B89428529"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that has been in existence for not more than 2 years;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H206D527CF1DF4D2CB51FD611A252F942"><enum>(D)</enum><text>owned and controlled by socially and economically disadvantaged individuals, including minorities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DA13942A9A44DA3A2E04A5055C3ACDB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>owned and controlled by women;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8126FAD8CCB42678CB3F515F9C32127"><enum>(F)</enum><text>owned and controlled by veterans;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4CE9C72A0E84C47A93761B78040416B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>owned and controlled by service-disabled veterans; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05C9735E3A7B457091641F0163C910FB"><enum>(H)</enum><text>not less than 51 percent owned and controlled by 1 or more—</text><clause id="H10B834C91EF3439D9885CAA7A602A781"><enum>(i)</enum><text>members of the Armed Forces participating in the Transition Assistance Program of the Department of Defense;</text></clause><clause id="HBA69EE302AC547EE9D4451BB277766F6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Reservists;</text></clause><clause id="H8B479BC25E2148D2AB642A9ED7EC4C20"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>spouses of veterans, members of the Armed Forces, or Reservists; or</text></clause><clause id="HFA0566346ED4412D9DD90AA0A7A8B832"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>surviving spouses of veterans who died on active duty or as a result of a service-connected disability. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9539632B95D94542B122FF5EDED300AE"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Small business concern owned and controlled by socially and economically disadvantaged individuals</header><text>The term <term>small business concern owned and controlled by socially and economically disadvantaged individuals</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8(d)(3)(C) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/637">15 U.S.C. 637(d)(3)(C)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HEE31C4393AD048C7BD3687FACB1C1894"><enum>3.</enum><header>Innovation Voucher Grant Program</header><subsection id="H8CF630713C2540769B54801D4B9F538E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall establish a program to be known as the <term>Innovation Voucher Grant Program</term> under which the Administrator shall, on a competitive basis and in accordance with subsection (g), award grants to small business concerns for the Federal share of the cost of purchasing from eligible entities technical assistance and services necessary to carry out projects to advance research, development, or commercialization of new or innovative products and services.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5A359BEF74014D5E9DE639EB4A01E684"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes of program</header><text>The purposes of the Program are—</text><paragraph id="HB645E00007C243DE917441B1BEE7BECD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to foster collaboration between small business concerns and research institutions or other similar organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA378F34B01634B94871086A790FDF033"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to facilitate access by small business concerns to capital-intensive infrastructure and advanced research capabilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDED4B2E755FE40E7A4B42B9E5032DD3F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to enable small business concerns to access technical expertise and capabilities that will lead to the development of innovative products;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H618AB726B1CF48D4951897772A4230B0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to promote business dynamism and competition;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBC563C6F23B4E57B25EBB4B76EC2EC1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to stimulate United States leadership in advanced research, innovation, and technology;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F0415AD5A12488D8A475BC6A8B82B5F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to accelerate the development of an advanced workforce; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57B4403F5752475AB8090D0EEE616F5E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to preserve and create new jobs. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A9A9BD0BC5F441BAE0576E226A6C80C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="H7EA9888EF6964E0CBE490138C58E8866"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A small business concern desiring a grant under the Program shall submit to the Administrator an application with the eligible entity from which the small business concern will purchase technical assistance and services using funds awarded under the grant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA03174D36DF94D578479D34F46086760"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the deadline established by the Administrator to submit applications under paragraph (1), the Administrator shall select the recipients of the grants under the Program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDEB7D78C14C7490085F081040D08E934"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>In evaluating an application for a grant under the Program, the Administrator shall take into consideration—</text><paragraph id="H4AE02CBC0F0B431E855FC8791A7C3C72"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the likelihood that funds awarded under the grant will be used to create or advance a novel product or service;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFBAA333F3EA44F4A3966A41E85915AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the feasibility of creating or advancing a novel product or service proposed to be created or advanced using funds awarded under the grant; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD62D88BE4E1646B19885E196C6E9456D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>whether creating or advancing a product or service proposed to be created or advanced using funds awarded under the grant could be accomplished without a grant awarded under the Program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8FFB714FC06647E7A227D440D3559401"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>A grant made under the Program shall be made in an amount of not less than $15,000 and not more than $75,000, which shall remain available to the grantee until expended.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0E70D22C9A644357A8274AE2074888C3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Amounts for small business concerns</header><paragraph id="HA8238D23AA544262B91FD3250D609684"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except to the extent that the Administrator determines otherwise, not less than 40 percent of the amounts made available for the Program in a fiscal year shall be set aside and expended through—</text><subparagraph id="H4283EC65D9C94178B23BD7474C4ECB32"><enum>(A)</enum><text>small business concerns in an underserved market; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27DF1A6D466746EEAAEC1A489999220C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>small business concerns in a region or State that has historically been underserved by Federal research and development funds. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H67198543FF944ACAA6185E7D87618E86"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Remaining amount</header><text>Any amount that is set aside under paragraph (1) in a fiscal year that is not expended by the end of the fiscal year shall be—</text><subparagraph id="HC3E9F6B64CB84B26A3B887D6AB63533C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>except as provided in subparagraph (B), available in the following fiscal year to make grants to small business concerns described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A2FEAE5A74A413BBC2E5EF2682BDF92"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on and after October 1, 2026, available to make grants to all small business concerns under the Program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H389BC31C642A43D8B3F619C4B5621BC1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>The Federal share of the cost of purchasing technical assistance and services described in subsection (a) using funds awarded under a grant made under the Program shall be—</text><paragraph id="HC8F0DCFE0B764420A5F6ECD9AAD51C5D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not more than 75 percent, if the amount of the grant is less than $50,000; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H367AB005EB094A589FF8D2894A60CF23"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not more than 50 percent, if the amount of the grant is not less than $50,000.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2373DE6A28534C9291DB3C4A35FA5FE3"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H07BEDA1E3F7F4124B3F0671E9D5C4B5B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports from grant recipients</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which a project carried out under a grant awarded under the Program is completed, the recipient of the grant shall submit to the Administrator a report on the project, including—</text><subparagraph id="H33235F5C94F24E96AFA7326576F1C70B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether and how the project met the original expectations for the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C10D44C9B264F92B5089DE0263F0F57"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the results of the project were incorporated in the business of the grant recipient; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9D9323E77BE4514AF45EE894E26D542"><enum>(C)</enum><text>whether and how the project improved innovation practices of the grant recipient.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H18B2761625F54C8D98720290C0BA12B3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report of the Administrator</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date on which the Administrator establishes the Program, and every 2 years thereafter until the date on which the amounts appropriated for the Program are expended, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate and the Committee on Small Business of the House of Representatives a report on grants awarded under the Program, including—</text><subparagraph id="H1956172901F7479284FF92CCA4A407EF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the grants awarded;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H964FBB8C9E1A4349BE74066BBA0C49A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the estimated number of products or services created or advanced under grants awarded under the Program that could have been created or advanced without grants awarded under the Program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6B7A3ED58D149338D67D9A100C8FC46"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the impact of the Program on knowledge transfer and commercialization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H79B9F3FB12544F6584343F865FD435D2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Final report of the Administrator</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which amounts appropriated for the Program are expended, the Administrator shall submit to the committees described in paragraph (2) a final report containing the information described in subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) of that paragraph.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6EACDE293C0440DEBCBE559A7A0D9859"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subsection id="H812F7EE86EC546D693D228AFDEE59617"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator to carry out the Program $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC015B75E434443DC8C3755EE79EC4819"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>Not more than 5 percent of amounts appropriated under subsection (a) may be used for administrative costs.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

