<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA33DD7CB747C45BAA452372342FFFB8C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1746 IH: Preventing Medicare Telefraud Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1746</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to establish requirements for the provision of certain high-cost durable medical equipment and laboratory testing, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA9B48F2A81734FD79210DAB271C1CC43" style="OLC"><section id="HDD0F89EBB6594FB58480031291AB5637" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing Medicare Telefraud Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD903A5DEC23940B39BEF67BB7AB1A045" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirement for provision of high-cost durable medical equipment and laboratory tests</header><subsection id="H0B0E9DCD3B3043A5B5C2591D55B7B34E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>High-Cost durable medical equipment</header><text>Section 1834(a)(1)(E) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(a)(1)(E)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0531DD0E3A9B406295C4281F82ACBC03" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H325D34C8096B4F45ADCCD804F0AE541B"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Standards for high-cost durable medical equipment</header><subclause id="H0706B96844B74D5A9C37D55B38B9933E"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Limitation on payment for high-cost durable medical equipment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Payment may not be made under this subsection for a high-cost durable medical equipment ordered by a physician or other practitioner described in clause (ii) via telehealth for an individual, unless such physician or practitioner furnished to such individual a service in-person at least once during the 6-month period prior to ordering such high-cost durable medical equipment.</text></subclause><subclause id="H26E94261C8B44C86BCBADE005E5AEDED"><enum>(II)</enum><header>High-cost durable medical equipment determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this clause, the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services shall define the term <quote>high-cost durable medical equipment</quote> and specify the durable medical equipment for which such definition shall apply.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H1EC32CA8EB804DE9A8C92D6CA51AAF1D"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Audit of providers and practitioners furnishing a high volume of durable medical equipment via telehealth</header><subclause id="H4C3EF260DBB4401DB9E244BB9F4AB353"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Identification of providers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning 6 months after the effective date of this clause, Medicare administrative contractors shall conduct reviews on a schedule determined by the Secretary, of claims for durable medical equipment prescribed by a physician or other practitioner described in clause (ii) during the 12-month period preceding such review to identify physicians or other practitioners with respect to whom at least 90 percent of all durable medical equipment prescribed by such physician or practitioner during such period was prescribed pursuant to a telehealth visit.</text></subclause><subclause id="HC9761A0687A44234883DBE3A94428489"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Audit</header><text>In the case of a physician or practitioner identified under subclause (I), with respect to a period described in such subclause, the Medicare administrative contractors shall conduct audits of all claims for durable medical equipment prescribed by such physicians or practitioners to determine whether such claims comply with the requirements for coverage under this title.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H0B15FB237B8847698F6DF3678317BC61"><enum>(b)</enum><header>High-Cost laboratory tests</header><text>Section 1834A(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m-1">42 U.S.C. 1395m–1(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8EDD72C7F56F450686B2285FB27F53C7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HF3B0C5D804184479AD3C138D0FE3641B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Requirement for high-cost laboratory tests</header><subparagraph id="HEADBA8848EE14796B8C70478330F079F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Limitation on payment for high-cost laboratory tests</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Payment may not be made under this subsection for a high-cost laboratory test ordered by a physician or practitioner via telehealth for an individual, unless such physician or practitioner furnished to such individual a service in-person at least once during the 6-month period prior to ordering such high-cost laboratory test.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE8050C85FDC4C4AB135B89D057174C3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>High-cost laboratory test defined</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the Administrator for the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services shall define the term <quote>high-cost laboratory test</quote> and specify which laboratory tests such definition shall apply to.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HED87C0B71CE545578D5CEAAEB4052501"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Audit of laboratory testing ordered pursuant to telehealth visit</header><subparagraph id="H87696BC75C9B4F6C87E0FD2D5AFD60A3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Identification of providers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning 6 months after the effective date of this paragraph, Medicare administrative contractors shall conduct periodic reviews on a schedule determined by the Secretary, of claims for laboratory tests prescribed by a physician or practitioner during the 12-month period preceding such review to identify physicians or other practitioners with respect to whom at least 90 percent of all laboratory tests prescribed by such physician or practitioner during such period was prescribed pursuant to a telehealth visit. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64C20D93E0E34E8286213C2F3BCA905E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Audit</header><text>In the case of a physician or practitioner identified under subparagraph (A), with respect to a period described in such subparagraph, the Medicare administrative contractors shall conduct audits of all claims for laboratory tests prescribed by such physicians or practitioners during such period beginning to determine whether such claims comply with the requirements for coverage under this title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H6A10EB30F31B4F69ABE2C24875E05EDA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect upon the termination of the emergency period described in section 1135(g)(1)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-5">42 U.S.C. 1320b–5(g)(1)(B)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="HAD4807E10666497CA8259E953A94CD9F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requirement to submit NPI number for separately billable telehealth services</header><subsection id="H0A9DADF5737D4ACB8E58CACA94AEB984"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement To submit NPI number for separately billable telehealth services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1834(m) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA177EF10B2C84F5D84A30620565E4BBC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H73FB6BDCD4ED4BC8A8AA48135F0B0C7D"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Requirement to submit NPI number for separately billable telehealth services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Payment may not be made under this subsection for separately billable telehealth services furnished by a physician or practitioner unless such physician or practitioner submits a claim for payment under the national provider identification number assigned to such physician or practitioner.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H56C5E07822924323B14F7FD966F80F4F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall take effect upon the termination of the emergency period described in section 1135(g)(1)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-5">42 U.S.C. 1320b–5(g)(1)(B)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

