<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2326D52A88EC49548EBB25579CEE32E9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4261 IH: Amputation Reduction and Compassion Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4261</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230621">June 21, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend titles XVIII and XIX of the Social Security Act to provide for coverage of peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries under the Medicare and Medicaid programs without the imposition of cost-sharing requirements, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H1B311F8057CC48DBAD5EB47E7806038D" style="OLC">
<section id="HFBFC344C82CD4514B8D2F02266AB63E1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header>
<subsection id="HC094225976284A2D9E8C8883F4D69A2F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Amputation Reduction and Compassion Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ARC Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBEA4648DDC9A488D9ECD3A1DEDC99093"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress makes the following findings:</text>
<paragraph id="H92F579C256894E07A3DD43DFC357EA32"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Atherosclerosis occurs when blood flow is reduced because arteries become narrowed or blocked with fatty deposits.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC8C72C8C721B4952B843BA15ED29B222"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Atherosclerosis is responsible for more deaths in the United States than any other condition, and heart attacks, resulting from clogged coronary arteries, are the leading cause of death in America.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBF9D485B3E144F64BB0CB6F28AD033A4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Atherosclerosis also occurs in the legs and is known as peripheral artery disease (in this subsection referred to as <quote>PAD</quote>) and having PAD significantly increases the risk for heart attack, stroke, amputation, and death.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD42CA7B87994F53A580529E3F8D5EB0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>While most Americans are aware of atherosclerosis in the heart, many Americans have never heard of PAD and Americans with PAD are often unaware of the serious risks of the disease.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3E6BF8BE925545E8B0534ADBADD933FF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An estimated 21 million Americans have PAD, and about 200,000 of them—disproportionately minorities—suffer avoidable amputations every year as a result of such disease.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF3B467AEFE442D5AB257BB72FC3735B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>According to the Dartmouth Atlas, amputation risks for African Americans living with diabetes are as much as four times higher than the national average.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H081D613CE7AB4858A257F901C96BA026"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Data analyses have similarly found that Native Americans are more than twice as likely to be subjected to amputation and Hispanics are up to 75 percent more likely to have an amputation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H06A0FBE43A2C4031B9E04BDFC7FF3C95"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Fifty-two percent of patients with an above-the-knee amputation and 33 percent of patients with a below-the-knee amputation will die within two years of their amputation.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF6F009F8C6CA4FEFABDD99D851774DA6"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Screening and arterial testing for PAD is cost-effective and should be part of routine medical care.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4A4F9FB6A491483087FC7BC69597CAF6"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Once PAD is detected, amputations and deaths can be reduced through the use of national, evidence-based PAD care guidelines.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5D00288C904845F190C3EC1C7D924B98"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Americans with a PAD diagnosis are associated with a 67-percent increase in the risk of cardiac death compared to people without a PAD diagnosis. Consequently, screening for PAD enables health care professionals to identify cardiac risk factors earlier and take proactive measures to reduce the risk of cardiac death.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H1D30137E4AD7478EAF863F9F9B2B3500"><enum>2.</enum><header>Peripheral artery disease education program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Part P of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/280g">42 U.S.C. 280g et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text>
<quoted-block id="H71A4DD2834FF48C499A8B284F586F447" style="OLC">
<section id="HE954B91DE52B48D496D4D124D1587734"><enum>399V–7.</enum><header>Peripheral artery disease education program</header>
<subsection id="H88A8257AD732425BBD992254874E53C2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, in collaboration with the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, leading clinical and patient advocacy organizations, and other interested stakeholders shall establish and coordinate a peripheral artery disease education program to support, develop, and implement educational initiatives and outreach strategies that inform health care professionals and the public about the existence of peripheral artery disease and methods to reduce amputations related to such disease, particularly with respect to at-risk populations.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5F90F13C6F084139B8E9687879F83F38"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>The Secretary shall, as appropriate, identify and disseminate to health care professionals best practices with respect to peripheral artery disease.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H2957086CE2FC4B7C9E273CCBCBE8DB71"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $6,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HE19C47F6838A41338B03D60780D8DE37"><enum>3.</enum><header>Medicare coverage of peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries without imposition of cost-sharing requirements</header> <subsection id="HE2289A354CAA41B28C9EEB1788C4D4CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1861 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HC83DE2B52F9C4FA493E3C2524B8FEE3C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (s)(2)—</text> <subparagraph id="HB93835DF135440A08E4D462D6DFAEE60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (JJ), by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFCB10691FE424C53B9E44BB26EC742B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block id="H87D4A88E893A480AA5911B20E22E651D" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H535E03FBC05C430EBC1E934BD718E533"><enum>(KK)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in subsection (nnn)).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H22296A7B448A4D8782884C6637D98C29"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBACD8C87881148E3B0743AB1E0364981" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H0563A801C4C146D9B931A123ACA204B4"><enum>(nnn)</enum><header>Peripheral artery disease screening test; At-Risk beneficiary</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H81AE77EA8E704876B135B2BA255C2EC5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>peripheral artery disease screening test</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H24EA93EF20A3460BB525286592A76B61" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>noninvasive physiologic studies of extremity arteries (commonly referred to as ankle-brachial index testing);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBB33AEB3A8B7486A8FCA055A602D013F" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">arterial duplex scans of lower extremity arteries vascular; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB9A53752A6EB4F95B2AF2BC1ED164DE3" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other items and services as the Secretary determines, in consultation with relevant stakeholders, to be appropriate for screening for peripheral artery disease for at-risk beneficiaries.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H12D9DAA47F42470F9494DE172689AA26" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>at-risk beneficiary</term> means an individual entitled to, or enrolled for, benefits under part A and enrolled for benefits under part B—</text>
<subparagraph id="H6F92A9728CB54D908DDB73E8AAE7511C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is 65 years of age or older;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0C3F84E40C93413CAD8CB659B41C0D3C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who is at least 50 years of age but not older than 64 years of age with risk factors for atherosclerosis (such as diabetes mellitus, a history of smoking, hyperlipidemia, and hypertension) or a family history of peripheral artery disease;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBF08D1176C2146AAAB103B540F1FB37D" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>who is younger than 50 years of age with diabetes mellitus and one additional risk factor for atherosclerosis; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBBCB4172AF454D568219D2EA5BAF2218" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>with a known atherosclerotic disease in another vascular bed such as coronary, carotid, subclavian, renal, or mesenteric artery stenosis, or abdominal aortic aneurysm.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H31ABE108DE0F4AC1AF364290AF619884" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, in consultation with appropriate organizations, establish standards regarding the frequency for peripheral artery disease screening tests described in subsection (s)(2)(KK) for purposes of coverage under this title.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA7B16EED3CA24596B7AF74E58E0BAFBD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusion of peripheral artery disease screening tests in initial preventive physical examination</header><text>Section 1861(ww)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(ww)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD1A3369E61104ADD9EAFCD19B60A98BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (N), by moving the margins of such subparagraph 2 ems to the left;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H33780F05FFB14DA39452464CB74DD4F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (O) as subparagraph (P); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9BA007BABA9E4EC3ADA68F534EC02087"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (N) the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block id="HDB58D4AFF401447BB5B5C9E139C68375" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H907F205A22F4461A9E729C0AC6589F38"><enum>(O)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at risk-beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in subsection (nnn)).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC7247A1B09A94C279F608C2AFEDFD1D8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Payment</header>
<paragraph id="H2259BBF64503446F9F68E16E2447057E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1833(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HC222967999F940A6A2C2E6AE71EC9DAB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text>
<clause id="H7EFFDA8E203E4F2782E19CA55C7036FE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (N), by inserting <quote>and other than peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in section 1861(nnn))</quote> after <quote>other than personalized prevention plan services (as defined in section 1861(hhh)(1))</quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H5085CA466BB943FE8416B5E927FD1F6D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> before <quote>(HH)</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H5A39B21B9D1C4B85B35D3D9BAB5901D3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>and (II) with respect to peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in section 1861(nnn)), the amount paid shall be 100 percent of the lesser of the actual charge for the services or the amount determined under the payment basis determined under section 1848;</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE42C84358E174CAE98EDFC5EBCC821F3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text>
<clause id="H9D110FEE024B4F5FA9FF2EC9034DF2B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause> <clause id="H07441B09AFB84568B0DBC2D7DE767C66"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (H), by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HA778168138684C50B214161661B7DAE0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (H) the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE93BEA48CADA4A99B87D9E8FB72B6A01" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H5E9E21CCF2924784896D7A6C92A03A55" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to peripheral artery disease screening tests (as defined in paragraph (1) of section 1861(nnn)) furnished by an outpatient department of a hospital to at-risk beneficiaries (as defined in paragraph (2) of such section), the amount determined under paragraph (1)(II);</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H444FCB7F534E437A8A3B5FBC6B8F4F90"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No deductible</header><text>Section 1833(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(b)</external-xref>) is amended, in the first sentence—</text> <subparagraph id="HE40CDCCFF5574E61A1BDCA7F53713CA5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, and</quote> before <quote>(13)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8C497D10FC7348A586E15CBCB276661B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, and (14) such deductible shall not apply with respect to peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in section 1861(nnn))</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E697D6EF29442DFBECC223659DFBFAB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exclusion from prospective payment system for hospital outpatient department services</header><text>Section 1833(t)(1)(B)(iv) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(t)(1)(B)(iv)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9FDF106BB97647DEBD6BC2FC6EA1AF77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, or personalized</quote> and inserting <quote>, personalized</quote>; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H62931F6D78F543D385D314B3B2F94D8F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, or peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in section 1861(nnn))</quote> after <quote>personalized prevention plan services (as defined in section 1861(hhh)(1))</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H11DE7CDDCC414895A8A8DEE82AFA9ECC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1848(j)(3) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(j)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>(2)(FF) (including administration of the health risk assessment) ,</quote> and inserting <quote>(2)(FF) (including administration of the health risk assessment), (2)(KK),</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1379F55E9BFE4CF4A971EC6FDADA52E2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exclusion from coverage and Medicare as secondary payer for tests performed more frequently than allowed</header><text>Section 1862(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395y">42 U.S.C. 1395y(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HB04534E9F3FB47C2B2EDA0A164E5C3A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (O), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1051548A94D648648DB7BFEE8FD732A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (P), by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting <quote>, and</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4AD5D3C23B304A8EB979DB02256F1033"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block id="H73A34D1E8DBF470CA05EC5F430ABF676" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H73107D8EAA934593985D82617064F29B"><enum>(Q)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in section 1861(nnn)), which are performed more frequently than is covered under such section;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF0FCCCC962D64A438AC3E0E1460E5034"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authority To modify or eliminate coverage of certain preventive services</header><text>Section 1834(n) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(n)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8168952A559B4F75854D01618B92BB3C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively, and moving the margins of such clauses, as so redesignated, 2 ems to the right;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC9F535D3BE8A4ED6BDD0917AD0C56B68"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) and (2) as subparagraphs (A) and (B), respectively, and moving the margins of such subparagraphs, as so redesignated, 2 ems to the right;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8CE82AAF00A04470B3C00D573CF0346A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Certain Preventive Services</header-in-text></quote> and all that follows through <quote>any other provision of this title</quote> and inserting:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDBFD64EDE3A64C10860DE9EFAA108A9B" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Certain Preventive Services.—</header-in-text></text> <paragraph id="H0E9AE154B4F846448E1A638A435D91DE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this title</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC004304E43E34ADEBE926CA26BDDFB93"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block id="H5659881762CF43FA9E98A8F8E25FCC76" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HE83BCDCA566341A0B4C6E026C60021A7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inapplicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretarial authority described in paragraph (1) shall not apply with respect to preventive services described in section 1861(ww)(2)(O).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H26A555A69CAC4F97B9F8D12692C686E7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to items and services furnished on or after January 1, 2024.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H424A2B6F79164522BABB32372979B070"><enum>4.</enum><header>Medicaid coverage of peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries without imposition of cost-sharing requirements</header> <subsection id="H985E0BF12D0E43149521FB660BA27E64"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1905 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD7C5DD5A990048EBAE687015579AE99F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HEEF7B640FCE74AB6831331B595F2DC29"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (30), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDA4E168415BD4D7891B0D8089E6696BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (31) as paragraph (32); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2BD260F288A54B84836150C01B3DE87E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (30) the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5AFA8AAF98EB4F66810D4FDE5F282057" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H245A2C7D3F5A460BBD581E0CC31EEFAA"><enum>(31)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in subsection (jj)); and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H04577916021B4441AC3F41082C06FD90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H21F424201EAD4A9E885ED77E9D348CB6" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="H9165DE7216A849919FCBE8AA14B57BB2"><enum>(jj)</enum><header>Peripheral artery disease screening test; At-Risk beneficiary</header>
<paragraph id="H165A921B4DFE4A818F3B72B2B4F40781"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Peripheral artery disease screening test</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>peripheral artery disease screening test</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H1D1465B222E24405BED81978E2913089"><enum>(A)</enum><text>noninvasive physiologic studies of extremity arteries (commonly referred to as ankle-brachial index testing);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFFD6AC951E7C4D80B60EFA4819B4592D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>arterial duplex scans of lower extremity arteries vascular; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF5E597CE81374E598108A19C4FAA62B6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such other items and services as the Secretary determines, in consultation with relevant stakeholders, to be appropriate for screening for peripheral artery disease for at-risk beneficiaries.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6763F5234DBD4FA0A975AA0835A6BACE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>At-risk beneficiary</header><text>The term <term>at-risk beneficiary</term> means an individual enrolled under a State plan (or a waiver of such plan)—</text> <subparagraph id="H15D8BBE400F84D2699A7C072C3EE4DEE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is 65 years of age or older;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H196776B063B14E19BE337E43CF200B27"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who is at least 50 years of age but not older than 64 years of age with risk factors for atherosclerosis (such as diabetes mellitus, a history of smoking, hyperlipidemia, and hypertension) or a family history of peripheral artery disease;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4F1F84FFC9A946DCADB3569B995D8849"><enum>(C)</enum><text>who is younger than 50 years of age with diabetes mellitus and one additional risk factor for atherosclerosis; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7506AA09107E4A83B19AA2EBFC947374"><enum>(D)</enum><text>with a known atherosclerotic disease in another vascular bed such as coronary, carotid, subclavian, renal, or mesenteric artery stenosis, or abdominal aortic aneurysm.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5691F1490965417ABEDB8E745E6ABBAE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Frequency</header><text>The Secretary shall, in consultation with appropriate organizations, establish standards regarding the frequency for peripheral artery disease screening tests described in subsection (a)(31) for purposes of coverage under a State plan under this title.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H10F3EC12498E4E7EB782A3DB18C60EC5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No cost sharing</header>
<paragraph id="H2B29628B9A35471A90C278D648BEFE8A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsections (a)(2) and (b)(2) of section 1916 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396o">42 U.S.C. 1396o</external-xref>) are each amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HF70A7AA44BD84236AB2F76DE28F664B2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFBB385513C1946EFB9E8FD3D933451DC" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting <quote>, or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H28FDDAE9A09D4A8EA82A9C784A2ECD76" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1E5B569E0FE44302B96151AA8C6C19B4" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subparagraph id="HC8D19E0DCD114AC0931E3C97447991C2" commented="no"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in section 1905(jj)); and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBCFBB7919BDB4343968BF6119A7CC994" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application to alternative cost sharing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1916A(b)(3)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396o-1">42 U.S.C. 1396o–1(b)(3)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6D40AE453D4D4429ACE3C7E1D4615FF5" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<clause id="H8590613EC414436BA8691D3B0DF25BD4" commented="no"><enum>(xv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Peripheral artery disease screening tests furnished to at-risk beneficiaries (as such terms are defined in section 1905(jj)).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC46CE9C361784DBCA78D3F5244716CC9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> <paragraph id="HD1276F71F09F44DDB76F85B667FACF24"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1902(nn)(3) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(nn)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>following paragraph (31)</quote> and inserting <quote>following paragraph (32)</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9AA948ADEB254EBF985A5FF9659F75CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 1905(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>following paragraph (31)</quote> and inserting <quote>following paragraph (32)</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H3A9C2315467C4D5984E1E1B501A26A30"><enum>5.</enum><header>Development and implementation of quality measures</header> <subsection id="H8AF0DB62C389420BB464354966A838CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall, in consultation with relevant stakeholders, develop quality measures for nontraumatic, lower-limb, major amputation that utilize appropriate diagnostic screening (including peripheral artery disease screening) in order to encourage alternative treatments (including revascularization) in lieu of such an amputation.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H6A047CA8AAD143E0B3455C7CE6C26A91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall complete appropriate testing and validation of the measures developed under subsection (a) and shall incorporate such measures in quality reporting programs for appropriate providers of services and suppliers under the Medicare program under title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref>), including for purposes of—</text> <paragraph id="HDD42E25B4C3141B48ED67B56D94CE769"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the merit-based incentive payment system under section 1848(q) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-4">42 U.S.C. 1395w–4(q)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0E9631C251344479BC7363B1E3B43CCF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>incentive payments for participation in eligible alternative payment models under section 1833(z) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(z)</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H034C4045D01A4DD9AD99E54B15F5841C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the shared savings program under section 1899 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395jjj">42 U.S.C. 1395jjj</external-xref>);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBDB3A750E26742FDA3DD6E19A11DA87C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>models under section 1115A of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1315a">42 U.S.C. 1315a</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF041A8F49C7346858EB3B3D5D836F55D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>such other payment systems or models as the Secretary may specify.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HEAB335B083DF4EF1B175D5203C17C90F"><enum>6.</enum><header>Amputation prevention pilot program</header>
<subsection id="H2C83A6289E494035AF26AC955BB74722"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1115A(b)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1315a">42 U.S.C. 1315a(b)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD974B96973C94F96A15537A5F9833399" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <clause id="H5A9F8A1FDA0E45AB94686D18CA454E76"><enum>(xxviii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Promoting voluntary, nontraumatic lower-limb major amputation prevention programs at hospitals, ambulatory surgical centers, and office-based centers that will increase access to amputation prevention services, reduce amputation rates, and reduce costs to such hospitals, surgical centers, and office-based centers, through—</text>
<subclause id="H3CE8577DC3584491A0690FB39BDF31E7"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">patient risk modification and management;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H28E70B19B1434B7DB8BA2BF30510AFEF"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">early screening and detection and surveillance;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HC8654E71B63D4F1D8784322BF9035866"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">testing and treatment for peripheral artery disease; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HFD56702B1E7847F79E419962A55C5CE6"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improved care coordination for individuals at high risk for amputation.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H89D2EE8B982C4D5B9659DE27CEC282D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Testing of model</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Deputy Administrator and Director of the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation shall test the model described under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

