<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" dms-id="H347ED445327A4040962C7CD891DD67A4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1093 EH: To direct the Secretary of State to submit to Congress a report on implementation of the advanced capabilities pillar of the trilateral security partnership between Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date></dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1093</legis-num>
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to submit to Congress a report on implementation of the advanced capabilities pillar of the trilateral security partnership between Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HAEE62ED6EBA04F2DB1B3CBBBEAAF102A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1EFEC85134DB49E49156CCA37DEEF8FB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Implementation of the advanced capabilities pillar of the trilateral security partnership between Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States</header> 
<subsection id="H0E968AF068084CACAB4029166680CCA3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text> <paragraph id="H1F991D74DFCF43139B5F4BDB04AF44D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the enhanced trilateral security partnership between Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States (in this section referred to as the <quote>AUKUS partnership</quote>) is intended to positively contribute to peace and stability in the Indo-Pacific region through enhanced deterrence;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9A01ECB7B9724507A550847ECEF0E6AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to this end, implementation of the AUKUS partnership will require a whole-of-government review of processes and procedures for Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States to benefit from such partnership and, in particular, to support joint development of advanced capabilities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFF64BF4AAF13479A9228832FFB120BA5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Department of State plays a pivotal role in the administration of arms exports and sales programs under the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151">22 U.S.C. 2151 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2751">22 U.S.C. 2751 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H73A190147375446FB8C48C3E9A2B2543"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Department of State should work in coordination with the Department of Defense and other relevant United States Government agencies to seek to expeditiously implement the AUKUS partnership; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H73040406EC46491F883433086476180D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Department of State, in coordination with the Department of Defense, should clearly communicate any United States requirements to address matters related to the technology security and export control measures of Australia and the United Kingdom.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA320A0B38241498B8376E8A02CC6F562"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="H8D73C528BE0F4482AEA3AC3B37B3552B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of Defense, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on efforts of the Department of State to implement the advanced capabilities pillar of the AUKUS partnership.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50CD6E5263F44DA291F81864CDC8B1D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matters to be included</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDD8159F3E3CF49D2988C437A61AA577C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For each of the calendar years 2021 and 2022—</text> <clause id="H15A3A072D3E041ACB3359713588ECA48"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the average and median times for the United States Government to review applications for licenses to export defense articles or defense services to persons, corporations, and the governments (including agencies and subdivisions of such governments, including official missions of such governments) of Australia or the United Kingdom;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1C728CDC01A34E6B916B81D77EA7AE84"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the average and median times for the United States Government to review applications from Australia and the United Kingdom for foreign military sales beginning from the date Australia or the United Kingdom submitted a letter of request that resulted in a letter of acceptance with; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD7BEB60E65E945CB8B2565B0BE9C56D6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of applications from Australia and the United Kingdom for licenses to export defense articles and defense services that were denied or approved with provisos, listed by year.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCB87BAF4D7C447099ACF05CB976419A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For each of the fiscal years 2017, 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, and 2022, the number of voluntary disclosures resulting in a violation of the International Traffic in Arms Regulations (ITAR) enumerated under section 40 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2780">22 U.S.C. 2780</external-xref>) or involving proscribed countries listed in section 126.1 of the ITAR, by persons, corporations, and the governments (including agencies and subdivisions of such governments, including official missions of such governments) of Australia or the United Kingdom, including information with respect to—</text> <clause id="H4EB862DAF5454A5CAD3290BB0C1804DD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any instance of unauthorized access to technical data or defense articles;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF6A0C9B83A4148FE9E992228B98F10A5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>inadequate physical or cyber security;</text></clause> <clause id="HA6984E51369547F6B2C9BFD0B0D9F8F6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>retransfers or re-exports without authorization; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9EB99980158D431A9456384D9CFF5234"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>employees of foreign companies that are United States persons that provide defense services without authorization.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDAD447760C3D4CC39BC6845E2F9DFF33"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The value of any civil penalties assessed from 2017 to 2022 for disclosures or violations described in subparagraph (B) on United States applicants that involved foreign persons, foreign corporations, and foreign governments in the United Kingdom or Australia.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3933010DDCCF4F56AF2FB0EA44635301"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A list of relevant United States laws, regulations, and treaties and other international agreements to which the United States is a party that govern authorizations to export defense articles or defense services that are required to implement the AUKUS partnership.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7023034D0770457AABA2EE30E5484201"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An assessment of key recommendations the United States Government has provided to the governments of Australia and the United Kingdom to revise laws, regulations, and policies of such countries that are required to implement the AUKUS partnership.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H51248EF7EC864D30949D5C0092B156B4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>An assessment of recommended improvements to export control laws and regulations of Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States that such countries should make to implement the AUKUS partnership and to otherwise meet the requirements of section 38(j)(2) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2778">22 U.S.C. 2778(j)(2)</external-xref>), and the challenges Australia and the United Kingdom have conveyed in meeting these requirements including with respect to sensitive defense technology security controls.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H01E6417B00AD4066B1AEAF15F0381995"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB1359B9D18B64A5B8F5E561B464DDCF9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Armed Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H864F0F44EDE143238C067F15DAF087CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Armed Services of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230322" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives March 22, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Cheryl L. Johnson,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation>
<endorsement display="yes"></endorsement>
</bill> 


