<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H24963EAC94B34F9C9FF754742463088A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5053 IH: Wage Equity Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5053</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000450">Ms. Foxx</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 to enhance provisions related to wage discrimination, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFF6BACE778044957A3B5F93355B16E19" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HAA69D12B86EA41BDB220C2359EFD05CE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be referred to as the <quote><short-title>Wage Equity Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA41079CA5DBF48D08D5E40F90D11AD2A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header> <paragraph id="HF4D4BA39111C4A0E8F19184457D736A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 1963, Congress passed on a bipartisan basis the Equal Pay Act of 1963 to prohibit discrimination on account of sex in the payment of wages for equal work performed by employees for employers engaged in commerce or in the production of goods for commerce.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2DC6B95052104BF9903267DB7B358924"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the passage of such Act, in 1964, Congress passed on a bipartisan basis the Civil Rights Act of 1964. Since the passage of both the Equal Pay Act of 1963 and the Civil Rights Act of 1964, women have made significant strides, both in the workforce and in their educational pursuits.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFD2C31B26FA84EE8AB9F879ECD5E1113"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Prior to the COVID–19 pandemic, there were over 77,000,000 women in the workforce, the most in American history. Of the 2,000,000 jobs created in 2019, 53 percent went to women. This follows a trend that has been rising for some time. Women are graduating from college at a higher rate than their male counter parts, making up 61 percent of all college degrees conferred in 2018. Additionally, according to a recent survey of working women, more than half are their family’s primary breadwinner.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBDD0C7898E8D444BBB86CB6FF8EC7728"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The COVID–19 pandemic has had a significant impact on working women, resulting in over 2 million women leaving the workforce since February 2020. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H641CD46A0CB34D378C730F02D4BC1651"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Despite these advances there is still concern among the American public that gender-based wage discrimination has not been eliminated.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HC02D97E713AE497AB8F64BD8672BD7C5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Clarifying sex-based discrimination prohibition</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(d)(1) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/206">29 U.S.C. 206(d)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>bona fide business-related</quote> after <quote>any other</quote>. </text></section> <section id="H40DB47E99EB144B5B13B93746A6FCE65"><enum>4.</enum><header>Job and wage analysis</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 16 of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/216">29 U.S.C. 216</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE0BD71AD4CB4251AF5A6B087E72807F" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HB36688DA38094E649829223213586D35"><enum>(f)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1148779A291345288D963852AD12B8A5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employer shall not be liable in an action brought against the employer for a violation of section 6(d) if—</text> <subparagraph id="H5EDBDC5EE1ED4EAB97760543B78521E7" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during the period beginning on the date that is 3 years before the date on which the action is brought and ending on the date that is 1 day before the date on which the action is brought, such employer completes a job and wage analysis audit to determine whether there are differentials in wage rates among such employees that may violate section 6(d); </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC731B4DB916642BEA51A246E2144D3E8" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such employer takes reasonable steps to remedy any such differentials; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4663A310B68C41D1B1A123D49D117224" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such job and wage analysis audit is conducted and such reasonable steps are taken in good faith to investigate whether any such differentials exist; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H27B7B92D37FB418191E304A3ADF502F9" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such audit is reasonable in detail and scope with respect to the size of the employer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0DA4307927B44CF59248A62835E402B0" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A job and wage analysis audit under this section and remedial action taken in response to the findings of such audit—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFDCB8A2903854EB2BBA4A88A55B36DD1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may only be admissible by the employer for the purposes of showing—</text> <clause id="HEFECC123EDCE426EAC8F79DD2BF0F916"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such audit was conducted; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE7361482A6ED4CC98FE7F1AE7039B700"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such reasonable steps were taken; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2AA47A415D1C46D6A9A3F273864A207C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not be discoverable or admissible for any other purpose in any claim against the employer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H05C9EB2AE3B4492DB4ACD21C2A78F235" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An employer who has not completed a job and wage analysis audit under this subsection shall not be subject to a negative or adverse inference as a result of not having completed such audit.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21ABED9614E241DF9480E5E8D291C228" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An employer who has completed a job and wage analysis audit that does not meet the requirements of subparagraph (D) of paragraph (1), but otherwise meets the requirements of such paragraph, shall not be liable for liquidated damages under subsection (b). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H094A6E52A19C43FE8706A5FD2286903C" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In this section—</text> <subparagraph id="H29413B5134494D259385724A0ACB66BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>job and wage analysis audit</quote> means an audit conducted by the employer for the purpose of identifying wage disparities among employees on the basis of sex; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBB83F06640E143BEA51FFEF6D3E78358"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>reasonable steps</quote>, with respect to differentials in wages among employees that may violate section 6(d), means steps that are reasonable to address such differentials taking into account—</text> <clause id="H8401F47B7FA0452ABE6559AB74144C10"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the amount of time that has passed since the date on which the audit was initiated;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H242A51E10BBC46F88EEF6C0B10102322"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the nature and degree of progress resulting from such reasonable steps toward compliance with section 6(d) compared to the number of employees with respect to whom a violation may exist and the amount of the wage rate differentials among such employees; and</text></clause> <clause id="H551E57C9D84049D4935A759A929DD976"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the size and resources of the employer.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HE57C7806C16842F997BBE0B184AAFEC4"><enum>5.</enum><header>Wage history; discussion of wages</header> 
<subsection id="H7FA28FD8B6CB4CF0BB2CE94BC75648C9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/201">29 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 7 the following new section:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F7EAFE059A04A9DA1C888E78F36D22D" style="OLC"> <section id="HB6EA52C856834694AF7AF761107E90F0"><enum>8.</enum><header>Provisions relating to wage history and discussion of wage</header> <subsection id="H2070D4AA236F47E2875D238887ADA495"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements and prohibitions relating to wage history</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be an unlawful practice for a person to, after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Wage Equity Act of 2023</short-title>—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD8A71578A76B4C879624B610FBC8EC36"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">rely on the wage history of a prospective employee—</text> <subparagraph id="HABA46096C9C1438CA0849AAD36383F96"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in considering such prospective employee for employment, including by requiring that the wage history of such prospective employee satisfy minimum or maximum criteria as a condition of being considered for employment; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE5999522278D4FA38F3B1BA7FD5C9D1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in determining the rate of wage for such prospective employee; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA3A492C5E6841A08FE022332AC7BEC8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">seek, or require a prospective employee to disclose, the wage history of such prospective employee.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H69839525E4304EA880A0291F0395F5B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Voluntary disclosure exceptions</header> 
<paragraph id="HCAFBB2ACBA8745ADAD706F6625F1690F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (a)(1) shall not apply with respect to a prospective employee who voluntarily discloses the wage history of such prospective employee. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H797C0FCDBC4F4C919642E8C4F9EC0202"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Wage history verification</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (a)(2), a person may take actions necessary to verify the wage history of a prospective employee if such wage history is voluntarily disclosed to the person by such prospective employee.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB28C71B3637B41EEB8C91549792DE6B6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prior inquiries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (a) shall not apply with respect to the wage history of an employee acquired by an employer before the date of enactment of the <short-title>Wage Equity Act of 2023</short-title>, including a current employee’s wage history with another employer that was requested and used to set an employee’s starting wage before such date and which is embedded in an employee’s pay and pay increases after such date.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H620667F6F5B74D1290BE5DB56135D5F0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prohibitions relating to discussion of wages</header><text>Subject to subsection (c), it shall be an unlawful practice for an employer—</text> 
<paragraph id="H72ED8F4050B04E10987F4A37D3741EF2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to prohibit an employee from inquiring about, discussing, or disclosing the wage of—</text> <subparagraph id="H05177E9BE2DB407FAA5F610A02D2DFD5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the employee; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H289F03E0071B47B0A471FE0FF0454F9B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other employee of the employer if such employee has voluntarily disclosed the wage of such employee; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39C9987E3C2A4A15AEF64A1D13C10ACD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to prohibit an employee from requesting from the employer an explanation of differentials in compensation among employees; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0AA14854C3EF495391A56A542D46BBD9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to take an adverse employment action against an employee for—</text> <subparagraph id="H202445CEAE9F483598F6BD5DDC757388"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct described under paragraphs (1) or (2); or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBC410245658545D1862561FDEBB97F22"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encouraging employees to engage in conduct described in such paragraphs. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB6D2CB6F9A8C4A1E8BE546D1913320B4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Limitations relating to discussion of wages</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9FF6C3CA081C4C16A4CD24F534275EBA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Time and place limitations</header><text>An employer may impose reasonable time, place, and manner limitations on conduct described under subsection (c) if such limitations are written and available to each employee.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA5FB08AB51F345C4A3E9AC0586E315AD" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Involuntary disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employer may prohibit an employee from discussing the wages of any other employee if such other employee did not voluntarily disclose such wages to the employee discussing such wages.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H83D3070914F142119746BDB14C31FA7D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Pay expectation conversation</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent a person from— </text> 
<paragraph id="H122C561297F54EC0B10B7988B8BC0687"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">inquiring about the pay expectations of a prospective employee; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97D843B0F0FE4DB9A007E75DBE5D2E7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>providing information to such employee about the compensation and benefits offered in relation to the position.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE5FA60200AEB4A78B5B66EE34472D362"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 3 of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/203">29 U.S.C. 203</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE6EB1DBEF86845869922E64CFB4D31D2" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H1FFFCCCC3A604929A5DEABA03C35EB7D"><enum>(z)</enum><text><term>Prospective employee</term> means an individual who took an affirmative step to seek employment with a person and who is not currently employed by such person, a parent, subsidiary, predecessor, or related company of such person, or an employer connected by a purchase agreement with such person.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA00948C38B61457EA6E02F134F67AA76"><enum>(aa)</enum><text><term>Wage history</term> means the wages paid to the prospective employee by the prospective employee’s current employer or any previous employer of such employee.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H8C18EB09085546E88868957278325503"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Retaliation</header><text>Section 15(a)(3) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/215">29 U.S.C. 215(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H606C5B2A226A419D8E98C8836DE5E0BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or prospective employee</quote> after <quote>any employee</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H58199D42B33742CA90E16684C8F2FDC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or prospective employee</quote> after <quote>such employee</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6D70621173654359B4CFDC40933DAF02"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalty</header> 
<paragraph id="HCF97E6340DA344BF92BE6DEDE841ACB0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 16(b) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/216">29 U.S.C. 216(b)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>Any person who violates the provisions of section 8 with respect to an employee or prospective employee shall be liable to such employee in an amount equal to the difference between the amount that the employee or prospective employee would have received but for such violation and the amount received by such employee or prospective employee, and in an additional equal amount as liquidated damages.</quote> after <quote>tips unlawfully kept by the employer, and in an additional equal amount as liquidated damages.</quote>. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11A95AEF036D4BCBBD006AF6E77078FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Civil monetary penalty</header><text>Section 16(e)(2) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/216">29 U.S.C. 216(e)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>6 or 7</quote> and inserting <quote>6, 7, or 8</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H63E2EFB763D545E1AFE815FF590B2A05"><enum>6.</enum><header>Wage negotiation skills education</header> 
<subsection id="HC2D3CDC5BA744A65941FAB3915995B48"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program authorized</header> 
<paragraph id="H42F457C78C694CDA9D0C7D21F1178B53"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, is authorized to establish and carry out a grant program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8945384D44D845719F8CE028DC45AAAF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the program under paragraph (1), the Secretary of Labor may make grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities to carry out wage negotiation skills education programs for the purposes of addressing wage disparities, including through outreach to women and girls.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD52FEC5E638645C0939040820744852E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an entity shall be a public agency, such as a State, a local government in a metropolitan statistical area (as defined by the Office of Management and Budget), a State educational agency, or a local educational agency, a private nonprofit organization, or a community-based organization.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC91EEC3F22D845F48CCE4A60771EF664"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an entity shall submit an application to the Secretary of Labor at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary of Labor may require.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDA12EA49F63B4624BDB432CCB40EA4D1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity that receives a grant under this subsection shall use the funds made available through the grant to carry out an effective wage negotiation skills education program for the purposes described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEA3AE04D23E94C5E88EDD8D569A215E9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Incorporating education into existing programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor and the Secretary of Education shall issue regulations or policy guidance that provides for integrating the wage negotiation skills education, to the extent practicable, into programs authorized under—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4C331278AC584BAB81F44760B8808419"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of the Secretary of Education, the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6301">20 U.S.C. 6301 et seq.</external-xref>), the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2301">20 U.S.C. 2301 et seq.</external-xref>), the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>), and other programs carried out by the Department of Education that the Secretary of Education determines to be appropriate; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H925A50CF2BD54106991DE723C5CA8098"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of the Secretary of Labor, the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3101">29 U.S.C. 3101 et seq.</external-xref>), and other programs carried out by the Department of Labor that the Secretary of Labor determines to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5A7786218D8E412893224307984BFCE1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, shall prepare and submit to Congress a report describing the activities conducted under this section and evaluating the effectiveness of such activities in achieving the purposes of this section.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H44DF42AACAC048E99A59628F8977F942"><enum>7.</enum><header>GAO Study</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Comptroller General shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, submit to Congress a study on the causes and effects of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H41EEC4041F9643EC93515F25E621C18B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>wage disparities among men and women;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB72F309C68FF4CE08B5CEC70DCBC04B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to employees that leave the workforce for parental reasons (commonly referred to as the <quote>Manager’s Gap</quote>), the impact on wages and opportunity potential; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8F06719CB24D49CE909CD1BC6D7480C6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the disparities in wage negotiation skills among men and women upon entering the workforce.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

