<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HD84B6BEF138B46A4A4CE7B58EFA0017C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3369 RH: AI Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 195</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3369</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–244]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001090">Mr. Harder of California</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on May 16, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information to conduct a study and hold public meetings with respect to artificial intelligence systems, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HIF00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H49D3467ADCDB44DE991BCE48484ED60B"><section id="H0BC3E2C3ACB9460BBC4C90FFC0A83E79" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Artificial Intelligence Accountability Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>AI Accountability Act</quote>. </text></section><section id="H460FAC1B39EC41629D7C8A8A1FA82774"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on accountability measures for artificial intelligence systems</header><subsection id="HA7A537614FFC420C9EF64CF3471E5BB6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information shall conduct a study on accountability measures for artificial intelligence systems, which shall include an analysis of the following:</text><paragraph id="H79231B4C47D341AF8DC3BEECC4F43ED5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How accountability measures are being incorporated into artificial intelligence systems used by communications networks (including telecommunications networks and social media platforms) and electromagnetic spectrum sharing applications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7872BFA559004C7480A9A0F0B8D4DD17"><enum>(2)</enum><text>How accountability measures for artificial intelligence systems can facilitate the closing of the digital divide and assist the promotion of digital inclusion in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDE9ED256F4D4832B73949470EB4A3C3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>How accountability measures may reduce risks related to artificial intelligence systems, including cybersecurity risks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AA619A4D1934831A4B270FE6BF70217"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How the term <quote>trustworthy</quote> is used and defined in the context of artificial intelligence, including how the term may be applied in various contexts related to artificial intelligence. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9FF1DC494D64A25AC0BC1C5ECDB4845"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The relationship, with respect to artificial intelligence, between the term <quote>trustworthy</quote> and other terms such as <quote>responsible</quote> and <quote>human-centric</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB389465C643C4079B168132571917AC2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Stakeholder consultation</header><text>In carrying out the study required by subsection (a), the Assistant Secretary shall hold public meetings to consult with relevant stakeholders for the purpose of soliciting feedback on accountability measures for artificial intelligence systems.</text></subsection><subsection id="H89BF78AE83E84C9AA9DB4D0471B86240"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the results of the study required by subsection (a) that shall include—</text><paragraph id="HAAEF537500BF49F9937CF00AF8A5DAE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the results of the analysis required by subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F75DEB4E83F406AA6B81179AF137ACA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the feedback provided during the meetings required by subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95BC5EEC70CD45918A51F28F589E8141"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommendations for governmental and nongovernmental actions to support effective accountability measures for artificial intelligence systems.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFE71D9859C4A4F5087F74172570FD162"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Accountability measure defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>accountability measure</term> means a mechanism, including an audit, an assessment, or a certification, designed to provide assurance that a system is trustworthy.</text></subsection></section><section id="H05034EBFEAB9442FA4A40C62256000A5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Availability of information on artificial intelligence systems</header><subsection id="H7F222C009ADF40748A941A48E56027DB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information shall hold public meetings to consult with relevant stakeholders (including representatives of industry, academia, and consumers) for the purpose of soliciting feedback on—</text><paragraph id="HE38B3E23BF094E1B85F042E156889169"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the information that should be available to individuals, communities, and businesses that interact with, are affected by, or study artificial intelligence systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H969841774EAD44B7A2C84CC30B42B866"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the most effective methods for making such information available to such individuals, communities, and businesses.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8BF8760833514FE39808D7657DEAFB10"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the results of the meetings required by subsection (a) that shall include—</text><paragraph id="H54500ADCF9B443AA81D5D7A95AE4E4CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the feedback provided during the meetings; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD49884B155774969A5E0FF7977EE70A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations with respect to—</text><subparagraph id="HD545BA1EE5624373A880C196BCE65364"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the information that should be available to individuals, communities, and businesses that interact with, are affected by, or study artificial intelligence systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E94753726F24C2B92A960C73103FB87"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the methods to be used for making such information available to such individuals, communities, and businesses.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

