<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H55CE269386CA4AFAB744B5ACE4ED3A86" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1614 IH: Range Access Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1614</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230317">March 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001213">Mr. Moore of Utah</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To facilitate the creation of designated shooting ranges on National Forest System land and public land administered by the Bureau of Land Management for the public to use for recreational target shooting, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC6601592426B417990CDAC937F718C8F" style="OLC"><section id="HCCDB8D6BBA3744029DAC84489BDDCDBB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Range Access Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBDA5C9059F1948029893E1A1378B11BA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Target shooting ranges</header><subsection id="HBAA3EB2BBF4A452CBD6642388E69D537"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of target shooting range</header><text>In this section, the term <term>target shooting range</term> means a developed and managed area that is authorized or operated by the Forest Service or the Bureau of Land Management specifically for the purposeful discharge by the public of legal firearms, firearms training, archery, or other associated activities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H40E7B24026D34128BC9041426A82DC71"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assessment; Identification of Target Shooting Range Locations</header><paragraph id="HDC7F6BFD028749AF80DE999F1CEBC2BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall make available to the public a list that—</text><subparagraph id="H5A286981F05149B38F2C3C7C1731BEFA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifies each National Forest and each Bureau of Land Management district that has a target shooting range that meets the requirements described in paragraph (3)(B);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7077AB3E7683413EAE1C33BE483FE29B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies each National Forest and each Bureau of Land Management district that does not have a target shooting range that meets the requirements described in paragraph (3)(B); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A957DE8A0A14D67BB71AD2C20167A88"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each National Forest and each Bureau of Land Management district identified under subparagraph (B), provides a determination of whether applicable law or the applicable land use plan prevents the establishment of a target shooting range that meets the requirements described in paragraph (3)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H526F3FF086EA4D36929626546925D1CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Identification of target shooting range locations</header><subparagraph id="H55F051BE4E674905B98085F082853431"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary concerned shall identify at least 1 suitable location for a target shooting range that meets the requirements described in paragraph (3)(B) within each National Forest and each Bureau of Land Management district with respect to which the Secretary concerned has determined under paragraph (1)(C) that the establishment of a target shooting range is not prevented by applicable law or the applicable land use plan.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H060DB7A6CF7E4BA1B3B2875EC5EC5878"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The Secretaries, in consultation with the entities described in subsection (d), shall, for purposes of identifying a suitable location for a target shooting range under subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="HA896984E8DFD49289405FEF28634938D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consider the proximity of areas frequently used by recreational shooters;</text></clause><clause id="H52B52DE36A11475E9D9155118F4128D3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure that the target shooting range would not adversely impact a shooting range operated or maintained by a non-Federal entity, including a shooting range located on private land; and</text></clause><clause id="HB7457F9EB1A842348546A6212A1A139E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>consider other nearby recreational uses to minimize potential conflict.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DAF1590DAA84F85A0B92E765CB4B28D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Establishment of new target shooting ranges</header><subparagraph id="H3E829EFB30D3402CB2735AC891FAFEDE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, at 1 or more suitable locations identified on each eligible National Forest and each Bureau of Land Management district under paragraph (2)(A), the Secretary concerned shall—</text><clause id="HEE761DC8B3764B28AA644E772050ACD6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>subject to the availability of appropriations, construct a target shooting range that meets the requirements described in subparagraph (B) or modify an existing target shooting range to meet the requirements described in subparagraph (B); or</text></clause><clause id="H2E23B04E0FC94D5CB3812CC404D0467F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>enter into an agreement with an entity described in subsection (d)(1), under which the entity shall establish or maintain a target shooting range that meets the requirements described in subparagraph (B).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B5FA1F1063D4406B6FD2EFB61A123D0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A target shooting range established under this paragraph—</text><clause id="HB205559ACA9C4DA29E955AE58B3EE5DA"><enum>(i)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7492647D9B3A44C69A10BAC37F142B81"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be able to accommodate rifles, pistols, and shotguns; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H4C4A7EFC57C74FD2B5A4E3DEED9E387C" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may accommodate archery;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H3F78DAC23A0A4145B5B11408C12756DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall include appropriate public safety designs and features, including—</text><subclause id="H0487754006AA48D2AB273BB366E67D3D"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">significantly modified landscapes, including berms, buffer distances, or other public safety designs or features;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6F38D862D91B4321AC433EAC2D059475"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a designated firing line; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7FF808BAC1D24CFEA17F75EE76CD9197"><enum>(III)</enum><text>benches;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H76E48BFC6624456296F6F452A09EFE19"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may include—</text><subclause id="H9CCFFABB385E4A55A48A4CA146A87827"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shade structures;</text></subclause><subclause id="H9633729858A440EBB7F5557020260838"><enum>(II)</enum><text>trash containers;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC2EE72979ED74E0CBF67DF17DD9A40B9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>restrooms; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD5D5AF8B540940168F35C514F123F78A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>any other features that the Secretary concerned determines to be necessary; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE5C6163AD705458FBB2EBBEE6D422451"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>may not require a user to pay a fee to use the target shooting range.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H115C2E28305B4018B173A5BB24E2234E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Recreation and public purposes Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A), the Secretary concerned may consider a target shooting range that is located on land transferred pursuant to the Act of June 14, 1926 (commonly known as the <quote>Recreation and Public Purposes Act</quote>) (44 Stat. 741, chapter 578; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/869">43 U.S.C. 869 et seq.</external-xref>), as a target shooting range that meets the requirements described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB8E08A3C508B48F69F0EB6F131698F32"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Restrictions</header><paragraph id="HC68A4E56122C4037BD3111C7DC2FE9E3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Management</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The management of a target shooting range shall be subject to such conditions as the Secretary concerned determines are necessary for the safe, responsible use of— </text><subparagraph id="H6F026487C07C4189BD73EAFFAC60C265"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the target shooting range; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5623B51795DD4B6A8F289550AE411A00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the adjacent land and resources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F9B727432994A30983A79AF7A6153CB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Closures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except in emergency situations, the Secretary concerned shall seek to ensure that a target shooting range that meets the requirements described in subsection (b)(3)(B), or an equivalent shooting range adjacent to a National Forest or Bureau of Land Management district, is available to the public prior to closing Federal recreational lands and waters administered by the Chief of the Forest Service or the Director of the Bureau of Land Management to recreational shooting, in accordance with section 4103 of the John D. Dingell, Jr. Conservation, Management, and Recreation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7913">16 U.S.C. 7913</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H29017D723C534A7B9207B4528F257455"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultations</header><paragraph id="H140ADE1AF260457382E5183290C947CD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretaries shall consult, as applicable, with—</text><subparagraph id="H3FF49596E23A4D639C6068B361FCE6F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>local and Tribal governments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9188211FB9704D2A9CFD250D7A7F2382"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nonprofit or nongovernmental organizations, including organizations that are signatories to the memorandum of understanding entitled <quote>Federal Lands Hunting, Fishing, and Shooting Sports Roundtable Memorandum of Understanding</quote> and signed by the Forest Service and the Bureau of Land Management on August 17, 2006;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4E47EF569624168AF808FB7D8359360"><enum>(C)</enum><text>State fish and wildlife agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9570B0038D724F2181FD4F8AA370B428"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shooting clubs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H640C61E264B148FC8E979466F09144F5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Federal advisory councils relating to hunting and shooting sports;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE487599CB9C34ED9A576F50DA1C9FE39"><enum>(F)</enum><text>individuals or entities with authorized leases or permits in an area under consideration for a target shooting range;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA73753628FDB424091E500882CEDB538"><enum>(G)</enum><text>State and local offices of outdoor recreation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79D9E7FAC15B44BF94B69EBDD2A1EB4D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>State and local public safety agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFF0092B78DF46C8A0241EFAF186DC82"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the public.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F977A7E589A4B37B89A151E943A82A2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text>The Secretaries may—</text><subparagraph id="HE942B1B474E84CEF9982873C268DEB24"><enum>(A)</enum><text>coordinate with an entity described in paragraph (1) to assist with the construction, modification, operation, or maintenance of a target shooting range; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E1CCF485A204735AA351814BFDA17FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>explore opportunities to leverage funding to maximize non-Federal investment in the construction, modification, operation, or maintenance of a target shooting range.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD745032DC5944B4291648BFFA9E07053"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act and annually thereafter through fiscal year 2033, the Secretaries shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives a report describing the progress made with respect to the implementation of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5C1EF912020F452EA118D7172DC6C5D7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text>Nothing in this section affects the authority of the Secretary concerned to administer a target shooting range that is in addition to the target shooting ranges that meet the requirements described in subsection (b)(3)(B) on Federal recreational lands and waters administered by the Secretary concerned.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

