<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC309DF8BA1DC4FB1BC68864B73EA8CFC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2659 IH: Pardon Disclosure Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2659</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230417">April 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a Member of Congress who makes and any individual who receives a request from a Member of Congress for a presidential pardon to disclose the request to the Select Committee on Ethics of the Senate or the Committee on Ethics of the House of Representatives, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H872DA08F040E43ADBBA3D41E0A9D97BA" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H95C6847D2B0845AF8931A556CE871F70" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pardon Disclosure Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H22EF8C4A46CC4513B0CED4B4C7BC7BC9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Disclosure of presidential pardon requests to congressional ethics committees</header> <subsection id="HE981D69B24BF4660B440D52AAF3F160E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Disclosure requirement</header><text>If a Member of Congress makes a request for a presidential pardon to be granted to the Member or to any other individual, the Member who made the request and any individual who receives the request from the Member shall each disclose the request to the supervising ethics committee in accordance with the requirements under <internal-xref idref="H5D4ECAAF0E854F968335E85A14CA6134" legis-path="2.(b)">subsection (b)</internal-xref>.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H5D4ECAAF0E854F968335E85A14CA6134"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline for disclosure</header><text>A Member of Congress who makes a request described in <internal-xref idref="HE981D69B24BF4660B440D52AAF3F160E" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> or any individual who receives a request described in <internal-xref idref="HE981D69B24BF4660B440D52AAF3F160E" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> shall each disclose such request to the supervising ethics committee—</text> <paragraph id="H129EF5A4002E47FF8B1ABC1A8436C8E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of any such request made or received after the date of the enactment of this Act, not later than 30 days after the date such request is made or received; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4AD3DD1DEBB24C53B162C31D2E30CD4D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any such request made or received during the period that begins on January 1, 2021, and ends on the date of the enactment of this Act, not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H23C67A8BB80A45A0BD9ACBC967BD6DA9" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Civil enforcement</header> <paragraph id="H2A13316F8907476D817F8B891F932BCF" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General may bring a civil action in an appropriate district court of the United States against any person who violates, or whom the Attorney General has reason to believe is engaging in conduct that violates, <internal-xref idref="HE981D69B24BF4660B440D52AAF3F160E" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7578CB1271744C9EB08E63F1955E5E29" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Civil penalty</header>
<subparagraph id="H3C0112CB34114A6A8292F32B1225C78A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the court finds by a preponderance of the evidence that a person violated <internal-xref idref="HE981D69B24BF4660B440D52AAF3F160E" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>, the court shall impose against the person a civil penalty of not more than $100,000.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB56B82EA47BE497C8BCF92E2E62191E8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>A civil penalty under this subsection may be in addition to any other criminal or civil statutory, common law, or administrative remedy available to the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1963D02ACD224845BBC87874BFAE11F7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the following definitions apply:</text> <paragraph id="HF19E3AF69986468F97F5854ECAA82702"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Member of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Member of Congress</term> includes a Delegate or Resident Commissioner to the Congress.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8044B8E5185844BA8E2B5A801ABEB0AC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Supervising ethics committee</header><text>The term <term>supervising ethics committee</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H09C5116E1EFA4481ABC601083948193A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of any request described in <internal-xref idref="HE981D69B24BF4660B440D52AAF3F160E" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> with respect to a Member of the Senate, the Select Committee on Ethics of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA492B85B456B47859208865CBD4E328B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any request described in <internal-xref idref="HE981D69B24BF4660B440D52AAF3F160E" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> with respect to a Member of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Ethics of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H1CC9F36317EF433B97F98CC8710509D1" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rules of the House of Representatives presidential pardon disclosure requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Clause 2 of rule XXVI of the Rules of the House of Representatives is amended by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>, except that Members, Delegates, and the Resident Commissioner shall also include in each annual financial disclosure report required under such title the disclosure of any request made by the Member, Delegate, or Resident Commissioner for a presidential pardon to be granted to the Member, Delegate, or Resident Commissioner or to any other individual.</quote>.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

