<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE3649F137B7C4934A9554ACBFE3815EA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3490 IH: Water Infrastructure Modernization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3490</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Water Pollution Control Act and the Safe Drinking Water Act to authorize grants for smart water infrastructure technology, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC5B7AFFFDCDA4B00AA878460996C612C" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H758113F3441F4A83B4A7F54B6DEB1FC5"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H1E048A10F8564F198856648B9949E0F5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Water Infrastructure Modernization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8D54CCC7613043FE9F97F23514B50C0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="H758113F3441F4A83B4A7F54B6DEB1FC5">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HBCCC253B5826492D81483D49DF89AFAA">Sec. 2. Purposes.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="HCD164504A07D4368B6C70960E3A7C805">TITLE I—Wastewater Infrastructure</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="HF5921AD6CBF340F091666755C666CE87">Sec. 101. Smart wastewater infrastructure technology for treatment works.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="title" idref="HF4BEC9E0B52B41C28CEE366A01AD5B8D">TITLE II—Drinking water infrastructure</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H00527C6AE7784EBD8364084D8CDFA86A">Sec. 201. Smart water infrastructure technology for drinking water.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HBCCC253B5826492D81483D49DF89AFAA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="H6B5DB9A974D841F5A260FAA0DC747FE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to upgrade and modernize the drinking water, wastewater, and stormwater systems of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31D6EF29841C4332B298B5F986AFB9BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to support the modernization of the publicly owned treatment works of the United States to maintain reliable and affordable water quality infrastructure that addresses demand impacts, including resiliency, to improve public health and natural resources;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07B7F6B372174408A06BEBAE200943D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to support the modernization of the drinking water infrastructure and management systems of the United States to maintain reliable, resilient, and affordable drinking water infrastructure and ensure the protection of public health; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE901D2BC14374B278B9FBCDB482513F4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to encourage the use of water-efficient technologies to address drought and prepare for the growing strain that population growth and climate change will have on over-allocated water supplies.</text></paragraph></section><title id="HCD164504A07D4368B6C70960E3A7C805" style="OLC"><enum>I</enum><header>Wastewater Infrastructure</header><section id="HF5921AD6CBF340F091666755C666CE87"><enum>101.</enum><header>Smart wastewater infrastructure technology for treatment works</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title II of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1281">33 U.S.C. 1281 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2831E3529C88490791B4AB2A448FD591" act-name=""><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H9A50EFFA72FF4EC986666112F9B754F8"><enum>228.</enum><header>Smart wastewater infrastructure technology</header><subsection id="H0B22F98045BD48128F34EFE634D016EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Administrator shall make direct grants to owners and operators of publicly owned treatment works for planning, design, construction, implementation, training, and operations relating to—</text><paragraph id="HC20908D1A5F942509CC232DFB87A155D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>intelligent wastewater treatment and collection systems and stormwater management operations, including technologies that rely on—</text><subparagraph id="H3F240A882697464C86062A96B08F1180"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the use of real-time monitoring, management, analytics, and data collection tools, embedded intelligence, and predictive maintenance capabilities that improve the energy efficiency, cost efficiency, reliability, and resiliency of wastewater treatment systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H109EE531017F426EA6392964D61D0DCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>real-time remote sensors that provide continuous monitoring of water quality in stormwater and wastewater treatment and collection systems to support the optimization of those stormwater and wastewater treatment and collection systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E843820F45045A9B361E2651E1E9998"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the use of artificial intelligence and other intelligent optimization tools that—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA1A609D84688498388E009D8FD141A1B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce operational costs, including operational costs relating to energy consumption and chemical treatment; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B51075DAAEF4AD7BE644FCECF4C998D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve decisionmaking;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD9DA78968584989BBC2C44B7C667014"><enum>(2)</enum><text>innovative and alternative combined sewer and stormwater control projects, including groundwater banking, that rely on real-time data acquisition to support predictive aquifer recharge through water reuse and stormwater management capabilities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7A3445C4D15451F94E76E8EE737392E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>advanced digital design and construction management tools relating to stormwater and wastewater treatment and collection systems, including advanced digital models.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4E877D70040449D3BA335088D6930941"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program implementation</header><paragraph id="HC9E303FABC5C42FE9A8629B61D55A475"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Selection</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4765A0B9CBE644DFA47C45EEC49951A5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The owner or operator of a publicly owned treatment works seeking a grant under subsection (a) shall submit to the Administrator an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Administrator may require.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2685932E5F324E80A136E22854351732"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall issue guidance to owners and operators of publicly owned treatment works on how to submit an application under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFBADBC91BC849948C597F80E6A68E34"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the owner or operator of a publicly owned treatment works seeking a grant under subsection (a) submits an application under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall determine whether to approve or deny the application.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13CBF04B85C34429BDE30E7C6A529C3C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Deficient applications</header><text>If the Administrator determines that an application submitted under subparagraph (A) is deficient, the Administrator shall—</text><clause id="H22E95FF3A15F4E59A31719C18A49748B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>advise the applicant of the deficiency; and</text></clause><clause id="HCA91DD893C31446193865CA22DFF7C82"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide an opportunity for the applicant to resubmit the application.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H631F2921951144D09F32DA70273F0713"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disbursement</header><text>If the Administrator approves an application under paragraph (1)(C), the Administrator shall disburse grant funds not later than 60 days after the date of the determination.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H812C36B9BC354DEBBCC7F5149D265D95"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cost-Share</header><paragraph id="H2190147183344DCC9D1607B4598B391A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the non-Federal share of an activity carried out using a grant under subsection (a) shall be 25 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D620A5D88444BAF917E4DD37897D5AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Administrator may waive the cost-share requirement under paragraph (1) if the Administrator determines that the cost-share requirement would be financially unreasonable due to the inability of a community being served by the publicly owned treatment works for which the grant is sought to comply with the cost-share requirement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9547B09303954D19AEBA19BB8A023712"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Compliance with Buy America</header><text>Section 608 shall apply to grant funds under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H94E0174618DA44E9B23C9F6B1E9A77A6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><paragraph id="H576C9C134E84472E90629CAFC5F7C6A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, and not less frequently than annually thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report that—</text><subparagraph id="HEC97E2B497AD4A179E5A47B160BA895C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describes—</text><clause id="H5B23260D34CE4D1587CAC4977B227BC4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the projects awarded grants under subsection (a); and</text></clause><clause id="HD8752FABA1A74C19B23E19D6A6B2EA19"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the improvements in the resiliency of publicly owned treatment works that resulted from the grants awarded under subsection (a); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA94821EEF68B4258AC06F1FB7633846A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any recommendations of the Administrator to improve the ability of grants under subsection (a) to achieve the purposes described in section 2 of the <short-title>Water Infrastructure Modernization Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC3E0FDE7C3F4D59A6544E38CEE2358D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>The initial report required under paragraph (1) shall include a description of the implementation of this section, including a description of—</text><subparagraph id="HEE9FC309093149ED9D7C3E740F44D60D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the projects approved for a grant under subsection (a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06330BB33B154C6994760F748BD0DC57"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the projects denied a grant under subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CF933D775594668BA9D83AE47A86A25"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for the projects described in subparagraph (B), a description of the reasons for which each project was denied a grant. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H79A735C28A5141148482B817F4652A88"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="H9BA7BF196949433EA06F13C1CEC895A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $25,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89F33F8B525D4FE6B58FC7E2B8C8382B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Set-asides</header><subparagraph id="HA2D84C8207E445DD9BC822F9F668F0B8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Rural communities</header><text>Of the amounts made available under paragraph (1), the Administrator shall use not more than 25 percent to make grants to owners and operators of publicly owned treatment works that serve communities with a population of not more than 10,000 individuals.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7DDBEF800A14402C87F125A619FD6947"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Tribal communities</header><text>Of the amounts made available under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall use not less than 10 percent to make grants to owners and operators of publicly owned treatment works that serve Indian Tribes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title><title id="HF4BEC9E0B52B41C28CEE366A01AD5B8D" style="OLC"><enum>II</enum><header>Drinking water infrastructure</header><section id="H00527C6AE7784EBD8364084D8CDFA86A"><enum>201.</enum><header>Smart water infrastructure technology for drinking water</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1452 of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300j-12">42 U.S.C. 300j–12</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H01D0BF45BA4040A78AF7B09BF4C69526"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (m)(1), by striking <quote>subsections (a)(2)(G) and (t)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsections (a)(2)(G), (t), and (u)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B3924739E1D402395021CE5B86F34AF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5F308227A2F946D18388B908CEC91ECC" act-name=""><subsection id="H5F437CB43677429D8685433827514251"><enum>(u)</enum><header>Smart water infrastructure technology</header><paragraph id="HD9CD373477A94366986A50D9D2FAFB9D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Administrator shall make direct grants to the owners or operators of community water systems for purposes of planning, design, construction, implementation, training, and operations relating to—</text><subparagraph id="H19AB77BC0CAB49D2AC4DE425BC6337C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>smart water network technologies that—</text><clause id="HD3C753109DFA422E93AEE5B48101D7DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>can identify or reduce water losses in a nondestructive or nondisruptive manner, including through analytical software, flow and pressure monitoring, or acoustic data collection; and</text></clause><clause id="H3D4A4FBC05314CCB8394E2B2351198AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7E5B78D6C11B418F8C0B17520B829296"><enum>(I)</enum><text>predictive and diagnostic information for informed decisionmaking;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6B8B6D7F524D440CBE2979A5E30F8F1E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>comprehensive data on pipeline integrity that document the presence of leaks or gas pockets; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HB9F025219DFD482385095885F2DA7F78"><enum>(III)</enum><text>information on the extent of such leaks or gas pockets, with an emphasis on detecting weakness of, vulnerability of, or damage to pipe barrels, pipe joints, or other pipe features;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA054857F26B04394B41F78453F2E259C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>real-time remote sensing technologies, including the use of advanced data management and analytics, that detect and alert operators to water quality events, leakages, and pipeline bursts on a real-time basis, including persistent sensor networks capable of measuring—</text><clause id="H1519EDDB3C4145529E36B82B333A3C9A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>acoustic signals;</text></clause><clause id="HCB22919272DF437F9E844D483E16BB85"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>pressure transient;</text></clause><clause id="H6C0524FBB31B4EF3BAEA61664E9E50E3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>water quality; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3D96524E607148F196238DA20AD683D3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>water flow;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96140624491E4903A247E21B5E1387D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>real-time decision support technologies that integrate sources of data about water treatment systems and distribution networks to deliver common operations information relying on data analytics that can improve operational decisionmaking, including nonrevenue water loss, energy optimization, cost efficiency, asset maintenance management, and water quality improvement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBFF693C8AD448028CE04982390B3E67"><enum>(D)</enum><text>advanced metering infrastructure, including meter data analytics and ratepayer technology—</text><clause id="HB38A727119A640E4880C61D74EFCD19F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to improve end user conservation; and</text></clause><clause id="H1828A98D8E9948918BE9D27DE146C2BE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in support of disadvantaged communities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB23CCC4EB40A42D482E62A3934DBDA14"><enum>(E)</enum><text>resilient water supply projects that may provide real-time monitoring of weather patterns and impacts on water supply and flood protection reservoirs and dams that enhance operations, including—</text><clause id="HE695198AD57843D192CA57710CA335EC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improved water supply reliability and management;</text></clause><clause id="H793B7975FFCC4E1F97DDD82892FB9460"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>protection of natural resources, including fisheries; and</text></clause><clause id="H3664F20245FC4D6B963769E018143232"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>temperature control;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H034974B59C7E45F3B608077BF66110C5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>innovative and alternative water supply projects, including groundwater banking, that rely on real-time data acquisition to support predictive aquifer recharge through water reuse and stormwater management capabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD19D15C51D0748CCB970AA9397177A3C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>artificial intelligence and other intelligent optimization tools that—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H074BFBD0588F4F16ACCEBF3F73DD4072"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce operational costs, including operational costs relating to energy consumption and chemical treatment; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC31ABA4691614CDAA22591EC42782098"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>improve decisionmaking; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5EC008CC73134209966EE875BA84FE8E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>advanced digital design and construction management tools relating to water treatment systems and distribution networks, including the development of advanced digital models.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD96050FC764A499FB91E6D8EAFBFDD8F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Program implementation</header><subparagraph id="HB4893B1B76254981AC612CD2020D1334"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Selection</header><clause commented="no" id="HB4A34748AA3F48388B1ED72F00664C40"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The owner or operator of a community water system seeking a grant under paragraph (1) shall submit to the Administrator an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Administrator may require.</text></clause><clause id="H75370B8E4B0743269CAC67E38837334B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator shall issue guidance to owners and operators of community water systems on how to submit an application under clause (i).</text></clause><clause id="HD1FD36BFC89141D295838B71ADD48681"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the owner or operator of a community water system seeking a grant under paragraph (1) submits an application under clause (i), the Administrator shall determine whether to approve or deny the application.</text></clause><clause id="H2CC9C441CF564121BB3643C483BDC551"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Deficient applications</header><text>If the Administrator determines that an application submitted under clause (i) is deficient, the Administrator shall—</text><subclause id="HAE0B551B39784801B915B1605237127E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>advise the applicant of the deficiency; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA0207E392B394066A396D83905763ACA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provide an opportunity for the applicant to resubmit the application.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A6802445C6E4AF89B38E84E1A1ABFFF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Disbursement</header><text>If the Administrator approves an application under subparagraph (A)(iii), the Administrator shall disburse grant funds not later than 60 days after the date of the determination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0F238B0A732492A88E5B0741C0743D2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cost-share</header><subparagraph id="H59DF4F8C4C304CA590668E1464DC7C9A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the non-Federal share of an activity carried out using a grant under paragraph (1) shall be 25 percent.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4521447799344368BADB282A23F10205"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The Administrator may waive the cost-share requirement under subparagraph (A) if the grant recipient is or serves a disadvantaged community (as defined in subsection (d)(3)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7AEA872BBA9483D837881CD8CBF543A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Compliance with Buy America</header><text>Subsection (a)(4) shall apply to grant funds under this subsection, without regard to the fiscal year limitation in subparagraph (A) of that subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E9D8E9E0CDF434285CEF4145D129801"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><subparagraph id="HEE4828F0C7C14942B9E3B19924661BF0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, and not less frequently than annually thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to Congress a report that—</text><clause id="HA9035C7A6BE344609E1E2604D775E29B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>describes the projects awarded grants under paragraph (1) during the applicable reporting period; and</text></clause><clause id="HC0E5576BF29F4607AB0082CA29768C25"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes any recommendations of the Administrator to improve the ability of grants under paragraph (1) to achieve the purposes described in section 2 of the <short-title>Water Infrastructure Modernization Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58E12B5593614F5A820100158B543A94"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>The initial report required under subparagraph (A) shall include a description of the implementation of this subsection, including a description of—</text><clause id="H35EA6D80828E42FA8A5FA8D92C20AD68"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the projects approved for a grant under paragraph (1);</text></clause><clause id="H2CF0FC70EB124F338E43EEE67A1C3008"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the projects denied a grant under paragraph (1); and</text></clause><clause id="HB0A31A846F0A4EF0946E1267C65C1DE6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for the projects described in clause (ii), a description of the reasons for which each project was denied a grant.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1778854C7AF74F4B89AD67AD054BCACE"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subparagraph id="HD2AE4A596537429F85A4F151953C91C0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection $25,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CBC0554792F41309F6F6F42390840C8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Set-asides</header><clause id="H7F03BDD7DDAF4E1FB5AFC1744C249F00"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rural communities</header><text>Of the amounts made available under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall use not more than 25 percent to make grants to owners and operators of community water systems that serve a population of not more than 10,000 individuals.</text></clause><clause id="H4F36B68310B243FDA52C6DE45B47795D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Tribal communities</header><text>Of the amounts made available under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall use not less than 10 percent to make grants to owners and operators of community water systems that serve Indian Tribes.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

