<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF93AC74F880D483798AA5244A6717A7F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 726 IH: Veterans for Mustangs Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 726</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230201">February 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. Garc&#237;a of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Wild Free-Roaming Horses and Burros Act to direct the Secretary of the Interior to implement fertility controls to manage populations of wild free-roaming horses and burros, and to encourage training opportunities for military veterans to assist in range management activities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H03856D7DE03F4923B60623517AF4F5A4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H997048B559054FFEB43D3B9513096C51" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans for Mustangs Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H47F5016B45A648769F709C2357166505"><enum>2.</enum><header>Amendments to the Wild Free-Roaming Horses and Burros Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3 of the Act commonly known as the Wild Free-Roaming Horses and Burros Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1333">16 U.S.C. 1333</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA570FBBC53674B229D82FA6C102F1466"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(2)—</text> <subparagraph id="H2126E6009E9741C88C0E3B69687C5055"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>that action is necessary</quote> and all that follows through <quote>until all excess animals have been removed</quote> and inserting <quote>that action is necessary to reduce the animal population or remove excess animals, the Secretary shall immediately take steps under this paragraph to achieve appropriate management levels. Such action shall be taken, in the following order and priority, until the animal population has been reduced or all excess animals have been removed</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF4EE762EDD2A4CCEAE424A4CC3E7DB0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subparagraphs (A) and (C);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H779878C4ED0C48449F6F83F0A484965A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H320929BFE361438E8B406750E8FB8165"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting before subparagraph (B) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H31A650F86F40443EB33AD000C5371998" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H54CE897EA63B40E790B12F5900C3C54E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall implement nonsurgical, medically safe on-range fertility controls to manage populations of wild free-roaming horses and burros. In implementing such fertility controls, the Secretary, through the Bureau of Land Management, shall prioritize the recruitment of military veterans to train and become certified in the application of fertility controls with respect to wild free-roaming horses and burros, including the certified PZP applicator certification offered by the Science and Conservation Center’s Certification Program. The Secretary shall provide appropriate compensation to military veterans participating in such a certification program. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary is authorized to contract with military veterans who have completed the training program under this subparagraph to carry out management activities under this Act. Individuals contracted with pursuant to this subparagraph shall not be regarded as officers or employees of the United States on the basis of such contract. </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBBF55CD2E39341B4AEAAA403D35800C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> <subparagraph id="H05C9F5DE70954925AB73C42E4CA286F7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDFB0A5B640BB4379952FAB92EAEE7C4C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (4) and (5) as paragraphs (3) and (4) respectively. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> </section> </legis-body></bill>

