<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6DBDD2FE149B462D856B53B23322A593" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4709 IH: U.S.-Israel Anti-Killer Drone Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4709</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230718">July 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000874">Mr. Hoyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000307">Mr. James</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000609">Mr. Rutherford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001195">Mr. Smith of Missouri</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000821">Mr. Westerman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020, to make improvements relating to cooperation between the United States and Israel to counter unmanned aerial systems, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H92F0B5C06D334884AF3FEA513389B3C1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF7C740A8F26C4A47A1287DD62DCF2C6A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>U.S.-Israel Anti-Killer Drone Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H53BA9884382D4CAE99BCB35F87FE6A59"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improvements relating to United States-Israel cooperation to counter unmanned aerial systems</header> <subsection id="H6A79B5964B8943C8A0C92EB81E1168FD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H253447CC8F224BAB8010A622EEB32DC9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The growing arsenal of unmanned aerial systems of Iran includes—</text> <subparagraph id="H9BB1787F002E4678AC39A5213AC799BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>unmanned aerial systems that engage in intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4771D692B67F4A4B8BAE32E8517E9021"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">armed unmanned aerial systems capable of striking battlefield targets, including loitering munitions, also known as <quote>suicide drones</quote> or <quote>one-way attack drones</quote>.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H9970712CCE944460B96A80F11D9AEE13"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Iran-origin unmanned aerial systems represent a threat to the Armed Forces and facilities of the United States in the Middle East, as well as to United States allies and partners such as Israel, Saudi Arabia, and the United Arab Emirates.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA6D30E06D08441F7AB63B4E53DFA34AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In February 2018, Iran allegedly launched an armed unmanned aerial vehicle from Syria into Israeli airspace which was ultimately destroyed by Israeli warplanes.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2CB417069E014792A5A4C148ABC02DC5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In September 2019, Iran launched cruise missiles and loitering munitions at key oil installations in Saudi Arabia.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A64CE9C2FDE4674911B11D146427263"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Throughout the takeover of Yemen by the Houthi, beginning in 2014 and continuing into the present, the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps Quds-Force, the al-Ghadir Missile Command of the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps Aerospace Force, and the Research and Self-Sufficiency Jihad organization of the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps has supported the capabilities of Yemeni rebels, including through the provision of unmanned aerial systems and other relevant technology, such as cruise missiles and ballistic missiles. Such support enables the Houthis to routinely strike civilian targets in both Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF047D3B874CB4611AA4B9B3606EE2DED"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In January 2021, Iran-backed Shiite militia groups in Iraq launched armed unmanned aerial vehicles at Saudi Arabia.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H541FC8B703874E8BB2A23D20F576E1C2"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In March 2021, Iran attempted to send two delta-wing unmanned aerial vehicles toward Israel which were ultimately downed by Israeli warplanes over the territory of an undisclosed Arab country.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H30876FA321B24ADBBEB2BE989ADE1BA0"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In July 2021, Iran launched an attack employing unmanned aerial vehicles, including loitering munitions against a Liberian-flagged, Israeli-operated tanker, <quote>M/T Mercer Street</quote>, near the coast of Oman that killed two people, a British and a Romanian national.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H624E1550F1C54CEA8487431B003DC9F8"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On March 27 and 28, 2022, Secretary of State Blinken met in Israel with counterparts from the governments of Israel, Bahrain, Egypt, the United Arab Emirates, and Morocco to promote normalization in the region and declared, <quote>Our commitment to the core principle that Iran can never acquire a nuclear weapon is unwavering. One way or another, we will continue to cooperate closely.</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCD327889B8DD4D1394D912A393E23ADC"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In May 2022, Iran inaugurated an unmanned aerial system factory in Tajikistan to manufacture and export the Ababil–2, a multipurpose unmanned aerial system with reconnaissance, combat, and suicide capabilities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFFFD41BA387A4635AE48E5F726F75D17"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On June 2, 2022, Iran-backed Hezbollah sent three unmanned aerial vehicles toward the Israeli-controlled Karish gas field, one of which was intercepted by an F–16 fighter jet, and two of which were intercepted by Barak 8 missiles launched from the Sa’ar 5-class corvette <quote>INS Eilat</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3FB71B5FFC1945B8A4D0D59294F5B654"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On July 2, 2022, the Israeli military reportedly shot down three unmanned aerial vehicles launched by Hezbollah in the vicinity of where an Israeli gas platform had been recently installed in the Mediterranean Sea. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB122E0066BD14DFBB8C9B9BB6A26B878"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On July 14, 2022, the United States and Israel adopted the Joint Declaration on the U.S.-Israel Strategic Partnership, reaffirming the unbreakable bonds between the two countries and the enduring commitment of the United States to the security of Israel.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29002554A1DB4B5AB91A1711418F72AB"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In late August 2022, Iran reportedly sent its first batch of Shahed–136 unmanned aerial systems to Russia for use against Ukraine. While Russia is rebranding these systems the Geran–2, United States officials revealed the agreement in the summer of 2022.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4AC00787B3FD474080036F54A688ABD4"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On September 12, 2022, Brigadier General Kioumars Heydari, who heads the ground forces of the Armed Forces of Iran, announced that the Armed Forces of Iran had developed the Arash–2 unmanned aerial system specifically designed to attack Tel Aviv and Haifa.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1466AFCA878A47BF90B8066B1F0C4C23"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On November 13, 2022, and on February 10, 2023, Iran-origin unmanned aerial systems allegedly targeted Israeli-owned oil tankers off the coast of Oman. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA696CAA825D14CB6B26509FA363B247B"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On February 14, 2023, United States forces in Syria reportedly shot down an Iran-origin unmanned aerial vehicle surveilling United States positions around oil facilities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7172CB5644E4446F9593B76B35711003"><enum>(18)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On November 1, 2021, the Secretary of Defense and the Defense Minister of Israel signed a memorandum of understanding establishing the United States-Israel Operations Technology-Working Group, which includes six sub-working groups, including sub-working groups focused on countering unmanned aerial systems and directed energy capabilities.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H052D2CDA6FD14FAB8CDDD19B1E1EAFCD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States should—</text> <paragraph id="HB2AAFB9807AA41C0802EE29587514E8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enhance ongoing cooperation with Israel in researching, developing, and fielding, as expeditiously as possible, mutually beneficial technologies and capabilities to counter unmanned aerial systems, for the purpose of addressing common military requirements and growing threats;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFC01A70E9C9743A8BB13C308C0306702"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">exchange with Israel information about the evolving threat of Iran-origin unmanned aerial systems; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H66C9FB022FA241078A14776E08CB07F3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use the United States-Israel Operations-Technology Working Group established pursuant to section 1299M(c) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>; 134 Stat. 4014), or any successor working group, as the epicenter of such efforts.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE2FEA2F932C44D26BAEBB5D594114F45"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report on United States-Israel cooperation to counter unmanned aerial systems</header><text>Section 1278 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref>; 133 Stat. 1702; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8606">22 U.S.C. 8606</external-xref> note) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HC4D6D20DDBC845CFA1DF7B71E545D266"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(4), by striking <quote>$40,000,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$55,000,000</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD505B4C79C9E4417AEA61C08788B8B19"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (e) and (f) as subsections (g) and (h), respectively; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H53F1EED78E9D4762B405B8C4C19F2319"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (d) the following new subsections:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H890B99B33E3B41148C4AF8449B174AD9" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H210A9DB9F8864AB1BAA763F7100BD11C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report on status of cooperation and certain Iranian threat</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report containing the following:</text> <paragraph id="H0BF11E6D6EE9492380881BCE7A7C42F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the status of cooperation between the United States and Israel on countering unmanned aerial systems, including an assessment of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3425D5954BBB46A4943CFD89D33248C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>capabilities to counter unmanned aerial systems under research and development;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC86C81DA36464ECDB8C24ADA2C8AA0B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">capabilities to counter unmanned aerial systems that have been fielded to the Armed Forces of the United States or Israel pursuant to this section;</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H98522D4CA3B14BC68E1B438B1D3937BE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">proposed changes to authorizations, appropriations, or other provisions of law that would result in more effective capabilities to counter unmanned aerial systems and expedite the provision to the Armed Forces of the United States and Israel of capabilities to counter unmanned aerial systems; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDF76E9AAD0DB49A7AAE6A3D013CA22DB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which the United States-Israel Operations-Technology Working Group established pursuant to section 1299M(c) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>; 134 Stat. 4014), or any successor working group, is being used to carry out the activities described in subsection (a)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61C24EF003774D3EA067B3A2126B59A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the threat to the United States and Israel posed by unmanned aerial systems from Iran and associated proxies of Iran, including an assessment of deployed or otherwise available anti-unmanned aircraft capabilities of the United States and Israel and the adequacy of such capabilities to offset such threat.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6310075C1ABA4660BBC8C6F9045E5611"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Unmanned aerial system defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>unmanned aerial system</quote> includes loitering munitions. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

