<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD1AD1E514F474DEEB47B84B5F158BF66" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4334 IH: HERO Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4334</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">chapter 171</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code, to allow suit against the United States for injuries and deaths of members of the Armed Forces caused by improper medical care, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9C712964FE264F33B320A80042FE4205" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC498413776024939ADCFC617EBEB0B65" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthcare Equality and Rights for Our Heroes Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>HERO Act</quote>.</text></section> <section id="H9FD820B68B4C41D7B003FEC6527B6176"><enum>2.</enum><header>Allowing claims against the United States for injury and death of members of the Armed Forces caused by improper medical care</header> <subsection id="H645E62011DC544B3A58F860DBC886C28"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">Chapter 171</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H11B80974236A4537B32FCF40D9A43FCD" style="USC"> 
<section id="HD427BE2F617B4E58A6607D1EA5C1B443"><enum>2681.</enum><header>Claims against the United States for injury and death of members of the Armed Forces</header> 
<subsection id="H446118FD82A94286931EC9F4C5D281CD"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text> <paragraph id="HF8F3DEB9A43D4339823C8BD340D19EF2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>Armed Forces</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of title 38; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7CCBAD85FC6E42DA9F1905547DB6B68D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>covered military medical treatment facility</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H6749825863C549D1BD871A9BE54AE2BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means the facilities described in subsections (b), (c), and (d) of section 1073d of title 10, regardless of whether the facility is located in or outside the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H705B52EC512B482DA166467130E41653"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not include battalion aid stations or other medical treatment locations deployed in an area of armed conflict.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD6E23F8130DB4B54BF888F083AE25336"><enum>(b)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A claim may be brought against the United States under this chapter for damages for personal injury or death of a member of the Armed Forces arising out of a negligent or wrongful act or omission in the performance of medical, dental, or related health care functions (including clinical studies and investigations) that is provided at a covered military medical treatment facility by a person acting within the scope of the office or employment of that person by or at the direction of the Government of the United States and shall be exclusive of any other civil action or proceeding by reason of the same subject matter against such person (or the estate of such person) whose act or omission gave rise to the action or proceeding.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC27EFC83302B456A87254DC2D9578776"><enum>(c)</enum><text>A claim under this section shall not be reduced by the amount of any benefit received under subchapter III (relating to Servicemembers’ Group Life Insurance) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/19">chapter 19</external-xref> of title 38.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H878F7F67B6F443F68E0564FD4EAA178D"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 2401(b)—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD08F5F3C57DD4D8EA96A2F21EF314A92"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">except as provided in paragraph (2), a claim arising under this section may not be commenced later than 8 years after the date on which the claimant discovered, or by reasonable diligence should have discovered, the injury and the cause of the injury; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC0AACE37ED464C0286CE0B7AFFB69D32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to a claim pending before the date of enactment of this section, the limitations period described in paragraph (1) shall begin on the date of enactment of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H112B0DB828FA4FF3B40EF8AB965C7F97"><enum>(e)</enum><text>For purposes of claims brought under this section—</text> <paragraph id="HBD7A81E2375C43C0884EB76EC254ABAD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subsections (j) and (k) of section 2680 shall not apply; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H22505365BD864251A50F81E0C666FB51"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of an act or omission occurring outside the United States, the law of the place where the act or omission occurred shall be deemed to be the law of the State of domicile of the claimant.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HF8A7C0EA284B4517B684B4F9C7AC3C95"><enum>(f)</enum><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this section, and every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to Congress a report on the number of claims filed under this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB682AFFD04614A888FE5423659EE3546"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">chapter 171</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HC00F46BCE29C4C02BF17A0EFC5337636" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">2681. Claims against the United States for injury and death of members of the Armed Forces.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H8AF956F3DC5C419DB94C01F04C899F85"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This Act and the amendments made by this Act shall apply to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H48AD1C48E83443368897C73D7C32087F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a claim arising on or after January 1, 2017; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4673F2EEC58347B7A2187434A09A65DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a pending claim arising before January 1, 2017.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H92E9D5F0E6674EC680D7CEA9E5B1C4A7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act or the amendments made by this Act shall be construed to limit the application of the administrative process and procedures of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">chapter 171</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code, to claims permitted under section 2681, as added by this section.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

