<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H44C992FB278F40E2A9435C0997EB3AE6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2783 IH: AANAPISI Opportunity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2783</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish an integrated research, education, and extension competitive grant program and scholarship grant program for certain Asian American Native American Pacific Islander-serving agricultural institutions, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H0697F4845B134A24A745B80EB5EE80B2" style="OLC">
<section id="H0EA52716DD7A43E29033F8606F7FAB94" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>AANAPISI Opportunity Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H127449D2509245019571F9399587DA4A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant programs supporting certain Asian American Native American Pacific Islander-serving agricultural institutions</header> <subsection id="H763C462B66A546E4872162BE06073625"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Integrated research, education, and extension competitive grants program established</header> <paragraph id="HEBCDF74DAAF740C693A15A714E968B74"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Competitive grants authorized</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations to carry out this section, the Secretary may award grants to covered institutions on a competitive basis for integrated agricultural research, education, and extension projects in accordance with this subsection. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H00B556A516F2487DA896C42DBF078FC8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria for grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grants under this subsection shall be awarded to address priorities in United States agriculture, as determined by the Secretary in consultation with experts in Asian American Native American Pacific Islander agricultural issues, that involve integrated research, extension, and education activities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0F78720B1B3404792033198C36C5C0D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Matching funds requirement</header> <subparagraph id="HE9FF03AED2474BA69FBAC6508A4F7009"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (C), with respect to a grant under this subsection that provides a particular benefit to a priority area specified in section 2(b)(2) of the Competitive, Special, and Facilities Research Grant Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3157">7 U.S.C. 3157(b)(2)</external-xref>), the recipient of the grant shall provide non-Federal matching funds (including funds from an agricultural commodity promotion, research, and information program) equal to 50 percent of the amount of the grant.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HADAA20A4256A44FCA6028658ED6528CA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>In-kind support</header><text>Non-Federal matching funds described in subparagraph (A) may include in-kind support. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H435B2A034CD54307A1EF6506DB1E2F48"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may waive the matching funds requirement under subparagraph (A) with respect to a grant if the Secretary determines that—</text>
<clause id="HC12ACCB3AC0A489188353A49A42AC284"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the results of the grant are of a particular benefit to a specific agricultural commodity, but those results are likely to be applicable to agricultural commodities generally; or </text></clause> <clause id="H965769DE187545A89A57EADB9A9566AF"><enum>(ii)</enum> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H291168F10D734042A97C52B5200F06B7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the grant—</text>
<item id="HCE8E939BBEDB499A9C5CE70C6A3BBBAD" indent="up1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the recipient is unable to satisfy the matching funds requirement; </text></item> <item id="HA7500032A5244B939EC518DB43342460" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>involves a minor commodity; and </text></item>
<item id="H1E3BCFE1BF224639B01180A9A71BC3AC" indent="up1"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>deals with scientifically important research; and </text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HF0B9765CBAA0410C8847C3C832C27A85" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the recipient is unable to satisfy the matching funds requirement. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7D118FF41D324D03A36AF12C2C6632F1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Term of grant</header><text>A grant under this section shall have a term of not more than 5 years. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H95508F4E7DF84553B17F18A5854C4B25"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scholarship grant program established</header> <paragraph id="H60F620358A5B4020A6D7E6C10363FDB5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall make grants to each covered institution for purposes of awarding scholarships to individuals who—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7EF82D078CA346F2A57B71EFFFAC18C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have been accepted for admission at such covered institution; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H62127897000E4CDF94B095B8B6FC0A08"><enum>(B)</enum><text>will be enrolled at such covered institution not later than one year after the date of such acceptance; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7287C6023C84467AB14A116E48D2F495"><enum>(C)</enum><text>intend to pursue a career in agriculture, including in the agricultural disciplines of business, management, economics, engineering, mechanics, production, technology, agronomy, crop science, animal science, botany, food science, forestry, home economics, nutrition, horticulture, natural resources management, soil conservation, soil science, farm and range management, non-medical biological sciences, pre-veterinary medicine, computer science, and such other disciplines as the Secretary determines appropriate. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HACA69DF4DD0A428D8F740BD206C41AFE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Condition</header><text>The Secretary may only award a grant under this subsection to a covered institution if the Secretary determines that such covered institution has established a competitive scholarship awards process for the award of scholarships to individuals described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HBC91B55CCFD144DFA22A2D643291AC3E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Beginning on the date that is two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every two years thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate a report detailing—</text> <paragraph id="H9C672864B2114F2D85D34DF4063B13D1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the amount of funds provided to each covered institution under subsections (a) and (b);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA59A82EDB19D428EA1FAE195BD4CF508"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of grants awarded under subsection (a) each fiscal year and the amount of each such grant; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF82687F87C494FDABB5EC2EFE6162482"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of scholarships awarded under each grant under subsection (b) each fiscal year and the amount of each such scholarship.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8B7EAD53EE804045BD2C08222A304CAF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H3C0B823EC8F045B196F0D1E9BF501C26"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered institution</header><text>The term <quote>covered institution</quote> means a community college, college, or university—</text>
<subparagraph id="H643605DC03EA42FB8BC54BA1546D39E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that has, at the time of an application for a grant under this section, a student body consisting of at least 10 percent Asian American Native American Pacific Islander students; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDDFB35442E914D9BAE1332D3CFAC31CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that offers associate, bachelors, or other accredited degree programs in agriculture-related fields.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H27A79CAC8883490EB438BF7FB795F143"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Agriculture.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

