<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4930CB25FC7B4DD1A041D4070F1D9450" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 665 IH: To amend title 5, United States Code, to provide authority to the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration to provide a cash award to Administration employees with foreign language skills, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 665</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. Gonz&#225;lez-Col&#243;n</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to provide authority to the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration to provide a cash award to Administration employees with foreign language skills, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE105670765BE4BC8B4224E6B77BADA68" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5561060A6D414EF8A3D3B7A85297C1AD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Cash award for Drug Enforcement Administration employees with foreign language skills</header>
<subsection id="HB129881E941149F0AE30BD63EE10C6AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5761 of title 5, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA72AC80CFB654136B7267197793AC130" style="USC"> <section id="HDB5FAA62CA9D416FA38BA0E27FBBCEEC"><enum>5761.</enum><header>Foreign language proficiency pay awards for the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Drug Enforcement Administration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation or the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration may, under regulations prescribed by the Director or the Administrator (as the case may be), pay a cash award of up to 10 percent of basic pay to any Bureau or Administration employee (as the case may be) who maintains proficiency in a language or languages critical to the mission or who uses one or more foreign languages in the performance of official duties.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H4EDBC95A87B34B4F8B961DBFFF9FA88E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for subchapter IV of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by striking the item relating to section 5761 and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H65110BB389B544F4BDAADEC6F440CA66" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">5761. Foreign language proficiency pay awards for the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Drug Enforcement Administration.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill> 

