<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDC48C5030EA242538D3BDE0B9EDE5D38" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2969 IH: Financial Technology Protection Act of 2023 </dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2969</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an Independent Financial Technology Working Group to Combat Terrorism and Illicit Financing, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAE8379D526774E0EB2FB61FE274046CA" style="OLC"><section id="H1CB6A8F781524B8AA4B4E51C326AA481" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Financial Technology Protection Act of 2023 </short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9491A9F45CD6492E9040CB8FCB0DF99D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Independent financial technology working group to combat terrorism and illicit financing</header><subsection id="H7F6D4C6384AA42BFA985CE54D3BA187F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established the Independent Financial Technology Working Group to Combat Terrorism and Illicit Financing (in this section referred to as the <quote>Working Group</quote>), which shall consist of the following:</text><paragraph id="H2C4B07948CFD430A8621E9CE78765984"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary of the Treasury, acting through the Under Secretary for Terrorism and Financial Intelligence, who shall serve as the chair of the Working Group.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99D2882CD4814A8685B6E3BA90A88E18"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A senior-level representative from each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H49EBB36D164846B2BFDBB0FAD411788E"><enum>(A)</enum><text> Each of the following components of the Department of the Treasury:</text><clause id="H091CF0F95C974919840870F80CAB037B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Financial Crimes Enforcement Network.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7CC5364391484D8A87EC82F3345DA330"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Internal Revenue Service.</text></clause><clause id="HE64DC4A7E1894F3E82C4FAB1C444E8AB" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The Office of Foreign Assets Control.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD475E8BB33C3425BBFDC749A4AB79AA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Justice and each of the following components of the Department:</text><clause id="HF80D13E7412F4831810492FB7E61F2E6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7CD44DA6258542C480027A84D99E0266"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Drug Enforcement Administration.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA371D346A3F40B08CAAD6457EBCA5B9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Department of Homeland Security and the United States Secret Service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6D5B562C87D49F981D612D96BC5AC80"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Department of State. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73DD42EF6C844DC280865B5494C0C85C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Central Intelligence Agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AFF042BE4B345B29299AF20D5EF985E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Five individuals appointed by the Under Secretary for Terrorism and Financial Intelligence to represent the following:</text><subparagraph id="HFFA2545DDBA84E7BB8C279D938D01EF8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Financial technology companies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H225D4959248A4AC4A0D372C8D91BC6E5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Blockchain intelligence companies. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H402BBFF94C644522A7E21E5CF559FA65"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Financial institutions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H563A2E92DE9547C78441075E45EACBA1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Institutions or organizations engaged in research.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2E9237583D440818B6F61A667E08DE4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Working Group shall—</text><paragraph id="H3FD7B93B20E94545936886AC312E603F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct research on terrorist and illicit use of new financial technologies, including digital assets; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H15F4BF0546BE4DE58702679A96EECA0F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop legislative and regulatory proposals to improve anti-money laundering, counter-terrorist, and other counter-illicit financing efforts in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H07269C1607604557A8CD6400E28F7761"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1ED9CAB02FF54003B315A97A2E1019E1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually for the 3 years thereafter, the Working Group shall submit to the Secretary of the Treasury, the heads of each agency represented in the Working Group pursuant to subsection (a)(2), and the appropriate congressional committees a report containing the findings and determinations made by the Working Group in the previous year and any legislative and regulatory proposals developed by the Working Group.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A70928573EC43C8BCEDDD4F424906C9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Before the date on which the Working Group terminates under subsection (e)(1), the Working Group shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a final report detailing the findings, recommendations, and activities of the Working Group. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDCAD54DD4DDD4117A5BB3515297F639A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>Members of the Working Group shall serve without pay, but shall receive travel expenses in accordance with sections 5702 and 5703 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2B6DBA749DEF4DE38B351A37F25F0AB5" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Sunset</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H72C0BB70C2F64344A9E74E7732E34D0A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Working Group shall, subject to paragraph (3), terminate on the date that is 4 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H723921BD9F754B29ADCF41896E61541D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expiration and return of appropriated funds</header><text>On the date on which the Working Group terminates under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H97157723E3224F9C938ED566612346F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">all authorities granted to the Working Group under this section shall expire, subject to paragraph (3); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBFD8F8C5F8DF4A178E61227B2D1995C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any funds appropriated for the Working Group that are available for obligation as of that date shall be returned to the Treasury.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H05F164BACDD148698C19FDA14D9159C9" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authority to wind up activities</header><text>The termination of the Working Group under paragraph (1) and the expiration of authorities under paragraph (2) shall not affect any investigations, research, or other activities of the Working Group ongoing as of the date on which the Working Group terminates under paragraph (1). Such investigations, research, and activities may continue until their completion.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H89E37097130E4562B8AE505C8562E739"><enum>3.</enum><header>Preventing rogue and foreign actors from evading sanctions</header><subsection id="H5678CDA23A534AFA9D73A7A56CF42A99"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report and strategy with respect to digital assets and other related emerging technologies</header><paragraph id="H69B1D9B0AF274858A162CB7A3CEF6AE0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President, acting through the Secretary of the Treasury and in consultation with the head of each agency represented on the Independent Financial Technology Working Group to Combat Terrorism and Illicit Financing pursuant to section 2(a)(2), shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that describes—</text><subparagraph id="HD0A310DEC3154C07A29E7FAC9897B394"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the potential uses of digital assets and other related emerging technologies by States, non-State actors, foreign terrorist organizations, and other terrorist groups to evade sanctions, finance terrorism, or launder monetary instruments, and threaten United States national security; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF43FDA241404B22B0194CB4C42E0E95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a strategy how the United States will mitigate and prevent the illicit use of digital assets and other related emerging technologies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AEB2ACB7AD743FA9FC464982ACACC08"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form of report; public availability</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD35770569CAC4ACA985C8BEE50ECC022"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4CC4346140CB44EB830A5E753E32E718"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The unclassified portion of each report required by paragraph (1) shall be made available to the public and posted on a publicly accessible website of the Department of Treasury—</text><clause id="H1DB35B0E28A74B2393032EA7D201E44E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in precompressed, easily downloadable versions, in all appropriate formats; and</text></clause><clause id="H0D1EFD0ACED44F869A2E15DC1FC9A5B3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in machine-readable format, if applicable.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0FF1FEACC364A4FB99BFD3151C8D293"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sources of information</header><text>In preparing the reports required by paragraph (1), the President may utilize any credible publication, database, or web-based resource, and any credible information compiled by any government agency, nongovernmental organization, or other entity that is made available to the President.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9CE419FB1488460DA64B80C504D3D398"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall brief the appropriate congressional committees on the implementation of the strategy required by subsection (a)(2).</text></subsection></section><section id="HB63D3ED21B1140B3A587AA327CB3B99D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H7DE0C0F53E344328A13769ED2A8F3C5E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H05E60FAE4F4C402AAC73BC46F7B93327"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Finance, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE681D51BA2C44468DED1343A5CA773D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Homeland Security, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Way and Means, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H98F0DC05C0634C98B9CBFF9813F1030C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Blockchain intelligence company</header><text>The term <term>blockchain intelligence company</term> means any business providing software, research, or other services (such as blockchain tracing tools, geofencing, transaction screening, the collection of business data, and sanctions screening) that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43BA1C9837BA43C2A2D009B16856DD24"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support private and public sector investigations and risk management activities; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4832533B547B4F929FE3CD5D75AD8F11"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">involve cryptographically secured distributed ledgers or any similar technology or implementation. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H53A43CC8B8C64E088BF82DAFFEB4A5B6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Digital asset</header><text>The term <term>digital asset</term> means any digital representation of value that is recorded on a cryptographically secured digital ledger or any similar technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DD80B1F3FBA43CA91CA59CC53D09322"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foreign terrorist organization</header><text>The term <term>foreign terrorist organization</term> means an organization that is designated as a foreign terrorist organization under section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3017C655EBE149A48473C289B807B5FA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Illicit use</header><text>The term <term>illicit use</term> includes fraud, darknet marketplace transactions, money laundering, the purchase and sale of illicit goods, sanctions evasion, theft of funds, funding of illegal activities, transactions related to child sexual abuse material, and any other financial transaction involving the proceeds of specified unlawful activity (as defined in section 1956(c) of title 18, United States Code). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3D32B7897A340C58E897B696B8A58C0"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Terrorist</header><text>The term <term>terrorist</term> includes a person carrying out domestic terrorism or international terrorism (as such terms are defined, respectively, under section 2331 of title 18, United States Code).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

