<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDAE3372DF0D24D5DA9B2B58160538C8D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6510 IH: Hydrogen Safety and Environmental Responsibility Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6510</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231129">November 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Transportation to study certain composite material pipelines, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H43AEA55C02694A739EBBC44B793C2992" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H91CDB842A20E495BABA921F28E412B04" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hydrogen Safety and Environmental Responsibility Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD6F89A8D929545219C61B1117E750BB9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on composite materials</header> <subsection id="H1BC42E481A7849228C4B67B949DDD363"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall complete a study assessing the potential and existing use of pipelines constructed with composite materials to safely transport hydrogen and hydrogen blended with natural gas.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2B1A77570DD84B1396F59C76F3F803B4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study considerations</header><text>In completing the study under subsection (a), the Secretary shall consider—</text> <paragraph id="HFF060E134B144646B4E2C7A1486B1A5E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any commercially available composite pipeline materials; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4AE7291FDF3B4CE2B1C581625F4B921A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any completed or ongoing tests and data available to the Secretary or other Federal agencies; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H613E001FEB7B4D58A2650E589E12C593"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any recommended standards, including consensus standards, and Federal agency authorizations relating to use of the composite pipeline materials.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7D632233C00D46C68753342F8F18492D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public participation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To ensure adequate public participation in completing the study under subsection (a), the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H3F88281E5CD34D7E9F20872C67FA8650"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hold a public meeting with interested stakeholders, including the affected industries, interest groups, and other individuals with relevant expertise; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8F1837275B548D18DA076CF6D77E701"><enum>(2)</enum><text>release a draft version of the study for public comment for a period of not less than 60 days; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13DEB60D481844DDA558F795FA05A24E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>address any substantive comments submitted by the public during the public comment period under paragraph (2) in preparing the final study.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H58B608B0E260448983D592418D737BD0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public meeting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the closing of the public comment period under subsection (c)(2), the Secretary shall hold a public meeting to present the findings of the study under this section and any responses to public comments received under such subsection.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7C76C5D4301B46518EBFACD05327872A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the meeting described in subsection (d), the Secretary shall issue a rulemaking that includes a Notice of Proposed Rulemaking to allow for the use of composite materials for pipeline transportation of hydgrogen and hydrogen blended with natural gas.</text> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

