<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE379D89F982A4A40B97AE07BA2CE660D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4939 IH: To authorize livestock producers and their employees to take crested caracaras in order to prevent the death of or injury or destruction to livestock, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4939</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize livestock producers and their employees to take crested caracaras in order to prevent the death of or injury or destruction to livestock, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9BA730005F934D3BB18B42E6FFE358C6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2ABFDA2D83FC49C29722A1304E0769DE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Authorization for livestock producers and their employees to take certain crested caracaras</header> 
<subsection id="H4062FC25B62D44A48C1D8F018C168919"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any provision of the Migratory Bird Treaty Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/703">16 U.S.C. 703 et seq.</external-xref>), a covered person may—</text> <paragraph id="H516484152C7947BA9DB2561F9F873B94"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">take or attempt to take a crested caracara that is causing, or that the covered person has a reasonable belief will cause, the death of or injury or destruction to livestock; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3DCBC96DC7CB472C919EEE8CDDFC4C8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the course of taking or attempting to take a crested caracara described in paragraph (1), cause injury to such crested caracara.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H009C2813EAE644A491A9679423E5600D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 31 of each year, a covered person that takes a crested caracara pursuant to subsection (a) in the preceding 12-month period shall complete and submit to the appropriate United States Fish and Wildlife Service Regional Office (as determined by the geographic jurisdictions described in section 2.2 of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation) an annual report using the form developed under subsection (c).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H296CEAD9782A453E98DA381935F12E54"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Issuance of form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Director of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service shall make available on the website of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service such reporting form as the Director determines appropriate for the purposes of taking reports under subsection (b). Such form may not be more onerous to complete than similar forms for permitted take under the Migratory Bird Treaty Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/703">16 U.S.C. 703 et seq.</external-xref>) required as of the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDC6259791B2F40D9976758053AA1C24F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HBE655B0FAA0449BD8D2030C02E9DCDD3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Crested caracara</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>crested caracara</term> means a bird of the species Caracara cheriway. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H40D38BD94F3F483591BADD39B1DE4AE7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered person</header><text>The term <term>covered person</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA2EC8E5F1AAD4376A598A5D57BEC6AF9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a livestock producer; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1DC22F2F0BF2448DB662A25C535BC48E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an employee of a livestock producer when such employee is actively engaged in livestock production. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB8D9990E898E4D8098092F175E214248"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Livestock</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>livestock</term> has the meaning given such term in section 602 of the Emergency Livestock Feed Assistance Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1471">7 U.S.C. 1471</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2AB3F7D40D274C6593A699CE58A69D10"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Livestock producer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>livestock producer</term> has the meaning given such term in section 602 of the Emergency Livestock Feed Assistance Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1471">7 U.S.C. 1471</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAD906C2356204E3BABCE8144BB9268A5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Take</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>take</term> means to capture, kill, disperse, or transport.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

