<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H59370BDC631C4BA3B9C46488B8881629" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2402 IH: Alan Reinstein Ban Asbestos Now Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2402</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Toxic Substances Control Act to prohibit the manufacture, processing, use, and distribution in commerce of commercial asbestos and mixtures and articles containing commercial asbestos, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H584A694A49B6455B8B8F4C8F4710E26B" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H7637CAB8D82B43B1BBC34E14EDC4679E"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Alan Reinstein Ban Asbestos Now Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H22564EEDFC4A46B88A390FBE8AE9D7A7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Commercial asbestos ban and reporting</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Toxic Substances Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2605">15 U.S.C. 2605</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H3ECCEEA7CB75494CA3C718BD092C4396"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating subsection (j) as subsection (k); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0F7686BC53A447DDB641200E0390AEC1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after subsection (i) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9ED1FD33CAF646E38162FD636510C545">
<subsection id="H88FA7616889342E2AD4723974D12051A"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Asbestos</header>
<paragraph id="H2A2C6C8A9EE74B568E27CA2F3A22F122"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="H62A9D83DE4F249C39FB7E747AF476358"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Commercial asbestos</header><text>The term <term>commercial asbestos</term> means the asbestiform varieties of the following fibers if extracted and processed for their commercial value:</text>
<clause id="H1BC091884B904B82B30D7C0488035EA8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Chrysotile (serpentine).</text></clause> <clause id="H826F28C041BA48DAAA3B971BAF435BC5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Crocidolite (riebeckite).</text></clause>
<clause id="HED66DDE74ABF494BACFBC56A6197FF1A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Amosite (cummingtonite-grunerite).</text></clause> <clause id="H4BEDC6F8736D41639DDBC0251594DE76"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Anthophyllite.</text></clause>
<clause id="H06F0CD3D659F4EA5BC41368B3550C48D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Tremolite.</text></clause> <clause id="HF0C7E749220B431CB7C6018D290C3A9A"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Actinolite.</text></clause>
<clause id="H1EAAA48CDE9B427790BCFB7BF4ED9177"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Richterite.</text></clause> <clause id="H93DB3A4DC48F453594584454C3B23F5D"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Winchite.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8ECF30EA85D94011A78ABAAAF2418FCE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Distribute in commerce; distribution in commerce</header>
<clause id="HC6202A6D0BEE4225B188553E6280F7C9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), the terms <term>distribute in commerce</term> and <term>distribution in commerce</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 3.</text></clause> <clause id="H25558C7FD4EA43C9B8CB53AF5E476AED"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>The terms <term>distribute in commerce</term> and <term>distribution in commerce</term> do not include, with respect to commercial asbestos—</text>
<subclause id="HDDDB02818485491A83A5F5193300BC05"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">end-use of a mixture or article containing commercial asbestos and installed in a building or other structure before the date of enactment of the <short-title>Alan Reinstein Ban Asbestos Now Act of 2023</short-title>; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HDF01BF28ABA74A3D9057BB466BA7068F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>distribution of a mixture or article containing commercial asbestos solely for the purpose of disposal of the mixture or article in compliance with applicable Federal, State, and local requirements.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB293DB963E494AC0A86A47BBB7FA7109"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Mixture or article containing commercial asbestos</header><text>The term <term>mixture or article containing commercial asbestos</term> does not include a mixture or article in which commercial asbestos is present solely as an impurity (as defined in section 720.3 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H137464EEAEC5473AAA2B6D22FC29C034"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability</header> <subparagraph id="H4C2DCB88F9444038ACA205AAA8B8B13E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The prohibitions, requirements, and definition of the term <quote>commercial asbestos</quote> in this subsection shall—</text>
<clause id="H11DF1581D4BA4D158D28773A55EABD5E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>apply only—</text> <subclause id="H0DCC1F0C35324C618A01EE377C721ECE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to chemical substances; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HABC89F8AF2434C07A4839BB6BD237623"><enum>(II)</enum><text>for purposes of regulating chemical substances under this Act; and </text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H207AD882541C4E498242989BE77E6158"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have no effect on—</text>
<subclause id="HB72BA42B95CF46C79B26AB78F669953F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any other prohibition or definition of the term <quote>asbestos</quote>; or </text></subclause> <subclause id="HA97B56524AFC4878A9D88DFA520DC103"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any other requirement regulating asbestos, including for purposes of—</text>
<item id="H7BF132D6D43E470CA1B547A3CBB4148C"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>regulating cosmetics under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>); and </text></item> <item id="HED4A6034693044DD904ECD4904AE1837"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>determining whether a cosmetic contains asbestos as an ingredient or as an impurity to an ingredient. </text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEAC8C57EBB2047AF81C760FE420C71A0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Impurities</header><text>Nothing in this subsection applies to any chemical substance, mixture, or article in which commercial asbestos is present solely as an impurity. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC3BCE803640F40E184F04B72C45143E6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition of manufacture, processing, use, and distribution in commerce</header><text>Effective 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Alan Reinstein Ban Asbestos Now Act of 2023</short-title>, no person may manufacture, process, use, or distribute in commerce commercial asbestos or any mixture or article containing commercial asbestos.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H45F6E90A7F7C414B9457CA7DE72E0326"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Chlor-alkali industry</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (3), an owner, operator, or agent of an owner or operator of a chlor-alkali facility that is in operation on the date of enactment of the <short-title>Alan Reinstein Ban Asbestos Now Act of 2023</short-title> may, until the date that is 2 years after that date of enactment—</text> <subparagraph id="H0FFE4860618F4F6A99C4F08437CA9552"><enum>(A)</enum><text>import processed commercial asbestos fibers solely for the purpose of manufacturing diaphragms for use in the chlor-alkali process;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H96FBF90DA92D423CB7F7F3097D6FCE7C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>use, hold, or process commercial asbestos fibers solely for the purpose of manufacturing diaphragms for use in the chlor-alkali process; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85BFD3C5CF2742D789FE709B3E4EEB5E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>use asbestos diaphragms in chlor-alkali production.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC833CF7B9C2C4D6D85E6F8B336598CD0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Exemption for national security reasons</header>
<subparagraph id="H74A7255A223943C390F12FFA4BC414E4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this subsection, the President may, on application, grant any person an exemption from the prohibition under paragraph (3) once for the manufacture, processing, use, or distribution in commerce of commercial asbestos or any mixture or article containing commercial asbestos only if the President determines that—</text> <clause id="H4BBB65D45DDF4E82B143F9FB5E1FCE6F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the manufacture, processing, use, or distribution in commerce of commercial asbestos or any mixture or article containing commercial asbestos by the person is necessary to protect the national security interests of the United States; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HE2CFBD8F365341279220DF6790174E9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>no feasible alternative to the manufacture, processing, use, or distribution in commerce of commercial asbestos or any mixture or article containing commercial asbestos exists for the intended use.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF1E7ABF4F68F4B5093643E677C93385F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Duration</header> <clause id="H845896D1DA8240FEB7D8289448CEFF71"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The period of an exemption granted under subparagraph (A) shall not exceed 3 years.</text></clause>
<clause id="H743B7A37967D42A0BD57E33F53473E75"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Extension</header><text>The President may, in accordance with subparagraph (A), extend an exemption granted under that subparagraph once, for a period not to exceed 3 years.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3E7A27531A33450FB5A9C7B7A5A37A81"><enum>(C)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Terms and conditions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An exemption granted under this paragraph (including any extension granted under subparagraph (B)(ii)) shall include such terms and conditions as are necessary to achieve the maximum extent practicable reduction in exposure to commercial asbestos.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H67136C2DDA924935AE384F17B2866B2A"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Publication</header>
<clause id="H2B172CE5825F4D2EB250C6DA2422CD1A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after receipt of an application for an exemption under this paragraph (including an extension under subparagraph (B)(ii)), the President shall publish the application in the Federal Register.</text></clause> <clause id="H03A1A1EB94C54AE8BC6DEC018C61CBAD"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exemptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after granting an exemption under this paragraph (including an extension under subparagraph (B)(ii)), the President shall publish in the Federal Register—</text>
<subclause id="H0DAEB536A346464AB0DEE197163832B9"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a notice of the exemption; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H06AFF558A43347A393B45BED70DE4450"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the terms and conditions included under subparagraph (C).</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H5D2989D458B9478788B766F7AA0B4509"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The President, on a determination that publication under this subparagraph of information relating to an application or granting of a particular exemption would harm the national security interests of the United States—</text> <subclause id="H2DCEF604819548D0BF8B1CC5930397D6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall not publish that information in the Federal Register; but </text></subclause>
<subclause id="H0237F03159304E44A709702DCF1570BC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shall provide that information to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HACFA27C50C8B4E5FA9840A21B9A5146E"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Application of waiver authority</header><text>Notwithstanding section 22, the Administrator may not issue a waiver under that section with respect to commercial asbestos.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
<section id="H55D88B25D43347FAA4AB3A0C62A73464"><enum>3.</enum><header>Public education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall develop and make publicly available resources that may be used by the Federal Government and other entities to educate the public and health professionals about—</text> <paragraph id="H241472364914458586BCA3E58832063C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the adverse health effects of asbestos exposure;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4B38A970044F4A9282905B045CA8D9D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any Federal resources, including easily understandable regulations, available to address the prevention and mitigation of asbestos exposure; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA637561F7E184854A5F0EF6F8808258A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>licensed commercial asbestos mitigation availability within each State, the District of Columbia, and each territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

