<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC913F705507546F79E37854BDC51CFD9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 6874 IH: Department of Veterans Affairs Watching over Electronic Benefits Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6874</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to implement a system or process to actively monitor the veteran self-service and data transmission functions of the main internet website of the Department of Veterans Affairs for certain adverse events, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H324D85B601424BD5933B06E15CE04CC0" style="OLC"><section id="HA7A67ED90F094F218FBB3FD37AE81215" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Veterans Affairs Watching over Electronic Benefits Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>VA WEB Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H517FE2D1C1DD48E794101BFA8ABD4B39"><enum>2.</enum><header>System or process to actively monitor certain functions of the covered website for adverse events</header><subsection id="H6865DCE1876546FD99584035E6BB527B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall develop and implement a system or process to actively monitor certain functions of the covered website, including covered features and any underlying interface or system, for adverse events. The Secretary may use the authority under section 701(a) of the Sergeant First Class Heath Robinson Honoring our Promise to Address Comprehensive Toxics Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/168">Public Law 117–168</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/324">38 U.S.C. 324</external-xref> note) to carry out this subsection.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3169C10BCBB14F178529BAD78FA715FE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>System or process requirements</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that the system or process developed under subsection (a) is designed to monitor, and log and store data, with respect to—</text><paragraph id="H4E7D3E6DA32F403D98C9BD32ECAFC3D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the volume of traffic to the covered website;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8874CC5E703C4FABAE3A2E7F379FCB09"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of submissions made using a covered feature;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62C193F808824F4AAFD507A24F8C8A5D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>software updates or other modifications to a covered feature or underlying interface or system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H53B0E66EEF284A0FA338EA6E317EFEC9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>needs, deficiencies, or obsolescence of a covered feature or underlying interface or system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCDB3D4C0DD724A5382DBE644ED00906C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>adverse events, including—</text><subparagraph id="H06872F9D77FE4252BD70D756408E39B8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date and time of any such adverse event;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75C04A4FE69B438D90571DB8FE757B59"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of users of the covered website who were affected by the adverse event;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H473307B96BAA4456AF8A0ED40A6468ED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of submissions affected by the adverse event; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB054AEF514A47B187A7C314E30F3591"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any factor related to an underlying interface or system that caused or contributed to the adverse event; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD65D6B9B43D4DFA9F25EEEE4B39F004"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any other factors, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD373699FEBF4A108DDCE26B7AABA185"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Notice and report regarding certain adverse events</header><paragraph id="HD491408F6DE64058A39205EAF697B7FF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any significant adverse event affecting the covered website, not later than 30 days after the date of such event, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives notice of the event, including a description of the event.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC5A43C0200141228595D382E501021B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after receiving a request from the Chair of the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate or the Chair of the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives for a report about an adverse event, including a significant adverse event, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the House of Representatives a report on the adverse event covered by the request. Each such report shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H919E9FF2B79D47A7B9EB8F043C93069B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the adverse event;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD963A5DF53E74D458A20BCBC0721CAD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date and time when the adverse event began and ended;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H299A7987D3AF487090AA76E1D712E59D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of users of the covered website who were affected;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A4972D5891D4237AF8688CCF5679511"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of submissions made using a covered feature that were affected; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B4C437BAC8F472F8C09B7C405F95063"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of any underlying interface or system that was affected.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA259D86DCFD413B8DCA3D7D2D21BEE2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The requirements under this subsection shall expire on the date that is seven years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H943F527B97534898BDD436CA9BCBC682"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report regarding exercise of certain authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary exercises authority under section 701(a) of the Sergeant First Class Heath Robinson Honoring our Promise to Address Comprehensive Toxics Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/168">Public Law 117–168</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/324">38 U.S.C. 324</external-xref> note) to carry out subsection (a), not later than 30 days after the date on which the Secretary first exercises such authority for such purpose, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the House of Representatives and the Committees on Appropriations of the Senate and the House of Representatives a report about the exercise of such authority. Such report shall include—</text><paragraph id="H90DE0659A30044228006278D7E83437C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the cost of implementing the system or process developed under subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC48F839FDC34B72B8A9E33186E0FE5B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of any modernization or replacement of an underlying interface or system necessary to implement the system or process;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H470A4645F80440CF869FE400417DD655"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an identification of any ways in which the covered website and any underlying interface or system is susceptible to any adverse event; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C8D8C07E9CF46DF9AC154ECBDA8FF75"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how the Secretary plans to eliminate or mitigate, to the extent possible, any such susceptibility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9A56644FB9B24E5684DAE9A6D9DAFB1F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Testing strategy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary for Information and Technology of the Department of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the House of Representatives a strategy to reduce the occurrence of adverse events by improving testing for each modification or software update to a covered feature or underlying system or interface.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD4D369736819426B94E87E92F8DF377C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H8EEFDEA26400485BBA44BF12F1155715"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>adverse event</term> means, with respect to the covered website, including covered features—</text><subparagraph id="H465FD583D7E54953ABB9FD8A047E0146"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a failure to properly receive or process a submission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE3B7135E069D4D2FA7265A85F3D6B5D5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a system outage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H453A982EBB3B42C29DFEC5544BA57C9B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an error in an underlying interface or system that prevents the transmission of data;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A2A1B74A1B84DA7A66B0B52B082A335"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a deficiency in information storage capacity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6EBA33CC3B44D6088C217BE9DF7970F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a loss of data;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFAA8A31CB3D4324B1D33C72DA59A194"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a presentation of incorrect information;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7A49101461D425A82C9CA1455670A4A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>an error regarding a status notification; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11381363E5004FF8B3738949726B2386"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any similar event that affects a function of the covered website, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HECAC0BF3AFEC4B6480CEDBB36721134C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered feature</term> means any feature or function of the covered website for use in the facilitation of the application, maintenance, or receipt of benefits under the laws administered by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H235837BBAD8A47F0ACDAD75321C71DEB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>covered website</term> means the main internet website of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2CA5FE9DAF149318732A258DD0B3CF5"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>significant adverse event</term>, with respect to the covered website, including covered features, means an adverse event that affects 1,000 or more users of, or submissions to, the covered website.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADC884FD15BA42ECB37015EA99D2A7AA"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>underlying interface or system</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HDC021C1804844CA4940D86901E8B769F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any information technology system that transmits data through, or accepts data from, a covered feature; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBAE16C746DBA4726944DAFF8492CCB5E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any mechanism through which any such information technology system connects and interacts with the covered website.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

