<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3F348BA2A1574F848EB6B3726356D0D8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1381 IH: American Dream Employment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1381</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230307">March 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that individuals who are beneficiaries of deferred action, deferred enforced departure, or temporary protected status shall be treated in the same manner as citizens of the United States for purposes of determining the eligibility of such individuals to serve as officers or employees of Congress.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDCD24180E19A428E8E4AABD250996D58" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA9013EFF83B14F47881DAC3285463037" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Dream Employment Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H55AC119EDC0B4864BDD1599DB0059C2D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Eligibility of beneficiaries of deferred action or temporary protected status for employment in Congress</header> <subsection id="HB95E81D3EA144DAB98888533F68B89ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Treatment in same manner as citizens of United States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of determining the eligibility of an individual described in subsection (b) to serve as an officer or employee of an office of Congress, the individual shall be treated in the same manner as an individual who is a citizen of the United States.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD4DAF7EC7F2F4683865BAF037F9E5B80"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Individuals described</header><text>An individual described in this subsection is an individual—</text> <paragraph id="H76712BE150EA448B8BA0AC38275BEBEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who has been issued an employment authorization document under the Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals Program of the Secretary of Homeland Security, established pursuant to the memorandum from the Secretary of Homeland Security entitled <quote>Exercising Prosecutorial Discretion with Respect to Individuals Who Came to the United States as Children</quote>, dated June 15, 2012, or pursuant to the rule of the Department of Homeland Security entitled “Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals” (87 Fed. Reg. 53152);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAC587076A3304E31ACC65387EE10FD8F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whose employment is authorized pursuant to a grant of deferred enforced departure; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF1CCCBAB145A44A7BC2978316DBB0D55"><enum>(3)</enum><text>who has temporary protected status under section 244 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S. 1254a).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6BA5B827C42D4209901C8A4CC37B58ED"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall apply with respect to fiscal year 2024 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

