<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H72BBBDB874544F578B8F9F2509958892" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2378 IH: Farmers’ Market and Food Bank Local Revitalization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2378</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230329">March 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide increased financial assistance for farmers markets and farmers market nutrition programs, to increase local agricultural production through food bank in-house production and local farmer contracting; and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3ADE68F7652F4874A3800C95A12F6F07" style="OLC"><section id="H16608C41B297430D878B04E8A78961C8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>Farmers’ Market and Food Bank Local Revitalization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1C1A8A21F47C42FC976E1359F7298E5F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings and purpose</header><subsection id="HAD2AEFABFE7F40048D700BCE5FA66BC9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H74EAB8D8BA8D4DAE821BDA3F272551F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Food insecurity, epidemic levels of obesity, hypertension, diabetes, and youth osteoporosis are caused by improper nutrition yielded by lack of nutritious, reliable, and locally available healthy food options.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FEA90104C9D45FDA757787E4164FBE0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The American Diabetes Association estimated a 41-percent increase in costs of diagnosed diabetes from 2007 ($174,000,000,000) to 2012 ($245,000,000,000) with most of these costs (62 percent) coming from senior health programs such as Medicare and Medicaid.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E88BBFFF13C49DF9FC58C6F73CD980A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Since sequestration in 2008, there has been no funding increase for the Senior Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCF9943FED184246A11053C353FBF99B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>From 2008 to 2020, the moderate at home food cost for a family of 2 (aged 51–70 years old) increased by an average of $70 a month. The Seniors Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program funding has not kept pace with such inflation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2BF919F0266478887BD87CEFABD130A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>According to the Department of Agriculture, Seniors Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program has a total program funding backlog of $20,065,021 and a season benefit level backlog of $16,120,741 across all participating States, territories, and Native American Tribes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88B29644D3BC4A13938FA571859995C7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Roughly 1 in 10 United States senior citizens (about 5,146,000) are forced to live well below the Federal poverty level, and the Seniors Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program is only able to reach about 725,000 due to inadequate funding.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H442A049CD4AE4D3DB0CA2BBB9B1752FE"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since sequestration in 2008, funding for the WIC Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program has fallen by over $6,000,000 and never rebounded.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90E54F5EEF874F08BF79343A2580E955"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> The WIC Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program is a vital safeguard for the nearly 1 in 7 children who will be born into poverty in the United States and will be at nutritional risk.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC4029F5ED9343079F81F1A368C658A7"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the Department of Agriculture, the WIC Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program has a total program and seasonal benefit funding backlog of $6,198,432 across all participating States, territories, and Native American Tribes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3733C3DB532B4B8CB0FEA35EBE11ECB2"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In the United States, food banks will provide meals to 1 in 7 people.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFFA93A944E746928D2F1391018CBEE7"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Many food banks share special relationships with local farmers who often donate their crops to food banks. The partnership allows for more efficient and sustainable procurement for food banks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E05EDC22BD24C8D92D19BACA40E1454"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Assisting food banks to grow their own food will aid local procurement and allow food banks to serve as farming resources to their communities, especially to those who are food insecure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4021E140A3FA42049E16B0C34795A874"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018, specifically required looking at ways to incorporate local goods to reduce food waste.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA4D996DE3C6A4AFF84F023A0318EEBBD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="H41D5668FF9A04048AE6D4EE19C1AC2AB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to increase and enhance funding for the Farmers’ Market Nutrition Programs to support seniors and food insecure families, and to increase market capacity for local farmers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A1C99C7C5454DB581010514452815F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to provide funding assistance for the expansion and construction of farmers’ markets in both rural and urban food desert areas;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AD4D60AB26C492188269C8F91ED92A6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to increase local food production through partnership with food banks by local farmer contracting and funding assistance to food banks to grow necessary produce through traditional or controlled environment agricultural farming.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA9081FA9896B459BA1D38F360D417071"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization and Additional Authorization of Appropriations for Seniors Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program</header><subsection id="H22ECE043804249618C5381346A91A6EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations for seniors farmers’ market nutrition program</header><text>Section 4402(a) of the Farm Security and Rural Investment Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3007">7 U.S.C. 3007(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>2023</quote> and inserting <quote>2028</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0DF6FB01B96F4F11A3A3F5D9B3B4AB9D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional authorization of appropriations To expand participation in the seniors farmers’ market nutrition program</header><paragraph id="H8A45E1C1273B4A25BF292852BE06E23D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Increased authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To expand and address season benefit level and total backlogs of the Seniors Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program, there is authorized to be appropriated—</text><subparagraph id="HE431337B25884DE09DA194994E4FAB78" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2024, an increase to $60,000,000;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB7DC28E38DF445A88B05BD58F160CA6" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2025, an increase to $70,000,000; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H125486560C12415794FA2CECF1E3DDF2" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for each of the fiscal years 2026 through 2028, and increase to $100,000,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07A5E465184C4121BB989B97548C9152" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Benefit enhancement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of expanding access to the Seniors Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program, funds appropriated under subsection (a) shall be used for the following purposes:</text><subparagraph id="HC2AB6CEE97BC4106B8D992D846AA8710" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Program eligibility income limit shall increase to 200 percent of the Federal poverty guideline.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7556E5F8E4284E8DA59E702155B2E11F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The minimum individual benefit shall be increased to $35.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F1D3BAC491048729D7C7C21B61DB364" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The maximum individual benefit limit shall be removed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H79FA7AB37571462F85932C94AEA6EA4B" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Minimum individual benefit increase under the WIC Farmers’ Market Nutrition Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 17(m) of the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1786">42 U.S.C. 1786(m)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HEE105A2388344DE093A1FD685B1D0FB6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>paragraph (10)</quote> both places it appears and inserting <quote>paragraph (9)</quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58D8A5942DA34990AC9F13C98B701617"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(C)—</text><subparagraph id="H8C467EB7B2674E1397C43148EB6FC7AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>$10</quote> and inserting <quote>$35</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16CB1E6A78D84F60BFB3B86CD2D53694"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>$30</quote> and inserting <quote>$60</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6B76BC39C5848BEB550E5422111209A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (9)(A), by striking <quote>2015</quote> and inserting <quote>2028</quote>. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HC1E201E2058548D9B7C300ACCAD0CEC6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header>Infrastructure funding for farmers markets</header><subsection id="HDDB433786B9B40668E2223ED3AB62CA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture shall make loans, loan guarantees, and grants to public agencies and nonprofit organizations for—</text><paragraph id="H064DEF13DF6D4C97864FF58D0DF2D3CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the construction of new farmers’ markets; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC01F690A7417400E93E724F8DEF825C1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the improvement or rehabilitation of existing farmers’ markets, including by adding or improving payment technologies used in such farmers’ markets.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A29FF35B3764F189B9B58ACFE02DA48"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a loan, loan guarantee, or grant under subsection (a) with respect to a farmers’ market the public agency or nonprofit organization involved shall—</text><paragraph id="H7B6E92952ADF493E8BCDD2C45DDAEB4D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>demonstrate financial need as determined by the Secretary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BE4F09A10884F2696FD7DC5C277FD63"><enum>(2)</enum><text>commit to reserving at least 50 percent of the floor area of the farmers’ market for the sale of products that are produced locally, as determined by the Secretary, by farmers, ranchers, or aquaculture, mariculture, or fisheries operators, or by associations of farmers, ranchers, or such operators.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H626F6F3DC1F44086AD79A068A90A9D69"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cost sharing</header><paragraph id="HADEE5AAFA54C4847BEBD37E9CC87CFC8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of a grant under this section shall not exceed 25 percent of the cost of the activity for which the grant is made.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D91F9A74622446EA690399F2D903C8B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The combined amount of a grant made and loan made or guaranteed under this section shall not exceed 80 percent of the cost of the activity for which the grant or loan is made or guaranteed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H20914414B801466DADB650548C000918"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Interest rate</header><paragraph id="H0DA5EA364AD642A5B9061BA298C130ED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A loan made by the Secretary under subsection (a) shall bear interest at the rate equivalent to the rate of interest charged on Treasury securities of comparable maturity on the date the loan is approved. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1158B06ED360418491B9DD5639B17733"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The interest rate referred to in paragraph (1) with respect to a loan referred to in such paragraph shall remain in effect for the term of the loan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H29927FEAAA1A489A8E6A1CE5FC84F376"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the funds of the Commodity Credit Corporation, the Secretary shall make available to carry out this section $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029. </text></subsection></section><section id="H7F7B292EC73D40418D90934F9C45225A" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Pilot program for food banks and local farmer contracting for local procurement</header><subsection id="HBB3DA23196E74340B146D84663ABA17C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture shall establish a pilot grant program in which food banks may voluntarily contract with their local farmers for them to grow produce for food bank programs to promote local procurement of produce. Food banks serving economically depressed or food desert areas hall be given priority to receive grants under this section. The Secretary shall make grants to food banks in 5 urban ZIP Codes (as designated by the Census Bureau), 5 suburban ZIP Codes (as designated by the Census Bureau), and 5 rural ZIP Codes (as designated by the Census Bureau) distributed as follows:</text><paragraph id="H993CA7866E5B4435A61681C6F03AC3B4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>3 of such grants in each ZIP Code selected under paragraph (1) shall be awarded to food banks in each Census Bureau Region of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBDFA70648EF4C00ABA203FA7700FACB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>3 of such grants among 3 of such ZIP Codes selected by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE59AFE629E2A48F79050EB2B875FEE1D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Methods</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under contracts made by food banks with grants received under subsection (a), local farmers may grow produce through traditional or controlled environmental agriculture farming.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF0A424650CBE4419B0F80A011D96022C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the funds of the Commodity Credit Corporation, the Secretary shall make available to carry out this section $7,500,000 for fiscal years of 2024 and 2025. The amount of a grant under this section shall be $500,000 per grant as to operate 15 separate pilot program grant locations in total.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1CE6579373E047AD9D5E4B6B54A1EC64"><enum>7.</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after effective date of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture shall submit to—</text><paragraph id="H1300E9B3A6DD482E98F46E86DA1A6A6B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Agriculture, and the Committee on Education and the Workforce, of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4901C0665A94DF4A65A1164F21322D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry, and the Committee on Aging, of the Senate,</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">a report that contains a review of the effect of this Act on local procurement of food, local farmers, who or what groups or entities are procuring the food, and the communities involved.</continuation-text></section><section id="H4FE97E2678104D64BA9843DCF25D3521"><enum>8.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall take effect 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

