<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC50D39AE00E843EC9F07D832235F0E7B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4630 IH: Supervision Reform Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4630</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230713">July 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Reserve Act to remove the designation of one of the members of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System as the <quote>Vice Chairman for Supervision</quote>, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H298691217CED4C7B8066F4C4031B23F3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H46114185639E471AB494F7DD17927F05" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supervision Reform Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H90E65368C06F4C43B6B363302D29EC17" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Removal of the Vice Chairman for Supervision designation</header> <subsection id="HD3B7BA4BA51B4C858A0942B911223325"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The second undesignated paragraph of section 10 of the Federal Reserve Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/242">12 U.S.C. 242</external-xref>) (relating to the Chairman and Vice Chairman of the Board) is amended by striking <quote>and 2 shall be designated by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, to serve as Vice Chairmen of the Board, each for a term of 4 years, 1 of whom shall serve in the absence of the Chairman, as provided in the fourth undesignated paragraph of this section, and 1 of whom shall be designated Vice Chairman for Supervision. The Vice Chairman for Supervision shall develop policy recommendations for the Board regarding supervision and regulation of depository institution holding companies and other financial firms supervised by the Board, and shall oversee the supervision and regulation of such firms.</quote> and inserting <quote>and 1 shall be designated by the President, by and with the consent of the Senate, to serve as Vice Chairman of the Board for a term of 4 years.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7B6936CA469841F08C720B6D227CFA86"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 10 of the Federal Reserve Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/241">12 U.S.C. 241 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (12).</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

