<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFFCAD1ECD2D74870932E123C647495D5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6499 IH: Beyond the Box for Higher Education Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6499</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231129">November 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to direct the Secretary of Education to issue guidance and recommendations for institutions of higher education on removing criminal and juvenile justice questions from their application for admissions process.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H79217283DAD14BC989616FAF46B8FAD0" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H0A8F137AFB6F4C3E8EFE185442E98F6D"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Beyond the Box for Higher Education Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H98289E33F22F4A2B8749E2C8CD75F055"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HFF6DDA37E1874332A594C1A45C80DBA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An estimated 70,000,000 Americans have some type of arrest or conviction record that would appear in a criminal background check.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBFBFEA81A5F48E8A75F1CFF033979DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each year, more than 600,000 people return to society from State or Federal prison.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H447D30CDAFB44509A9762A021FA039FD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Nearly 11,000,000 Americans are admitted to city and county jails each year, with an average daily population of more than 700,000 people.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F2862308B134D5098BFA310D15E9D04"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An estimated 2,100,000 youth under the age of 18 are arrested every year in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BAC1CEE224644A0B6E091FBBC6E0829"><enum>(5)</enum><text>1,700,000 juvenile delinquency cases are disposed of in juvenile courts annually.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB392B0042E9D410188C45DB67F20A770"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Juvenile records are not always confidential; many States disclose information about youth involvement with the juvenile justice system or do not have procedures to seal or expunge juvenile records.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C8E848EB3044B2F9BF90E84093BF65F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The compounding effects of collateral consequences due to criminal justice involvement hinder the ability of individuals to reenter society successfully.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H903CEE2A385047008D009C3F843EA57E"><enum>(8)</enum><text>People of color and low-income people are disproportionately impacted by the collateral consequences of criminal justice involvement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE521051E1CDC48CD8BF828D17B646755"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Incarceration leads to decreased earnings, unemployment, and poverty.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C413C4AA2924D37BC6E4809DCC92C21"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Upon reentry, lower educational attainment, a lack of work skills or history, and the stigma of a criminal record can hinder a formerly incarcerated person’s ability to return to their communities successfully.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A2EAD5F88E449BF81EFF49CFF55D91C"><enum>(11)</enum><text>One way to improve reentry outcomes is to increase educational opportunities for people with a criminal or juvenile justice history.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H275704EE7C5343E3BE6D697F36229173"><enum>(12)</enum><text>By reducing rearrests and reconvictions, and by increasing educational attainment, formerly incarcerated individuals are better situated to find stable employment, contributing to their communities.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD0CF161856B849809117F511D842A999"><enum>3.</enum><header>Beyond the box for higher education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title I of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1011">20 U.S.C. 1011 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9EEE4DDF181A4C0AA889EDEC248C1A4F"><section id="H99AD5A8108884E5D8E8B25EA9C56E29C"><enum>124.</enum><header>Beyond the box for higher education</header><subsection id="H4104507C42284BA0892727F9B5D394B5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Training and technical assistance</header><paragraph id="H2647190A58794B5282AE5E7F81141759"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Office of Policy, Planning, and Innovation of the Office of Postsecondary Education of the Department and with consultation from the Department of Justice and relevant community stakeholders, shall issue guidance and recommendations for institutions of higher education to remove criminal and juvenile justice questions from their application for admissions process.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEFEB11CA28D4B5E9FE54C16E7B22035"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidance and recommendations</header><text>The guidance and recommendations issued under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H7F26914743BC4596A3EF06D4F10A532E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>If an institution of higher education collects criminal or juvenile justice information on applicants for admission, it is recommended that the institution determine whether this information is necessary to make an informed admission decision and whether it would be appropriate to remove these questions from the application.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35A2E6B2A7F24D08B8E54832A0663E14"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If an institution of higher education determines that it is appropriate to remove criminal or juvenile justice questions from the institution's application for admissions process, it is recommended that the institution comply with the following:</text><clause id="H05614994FD824BA5B06C014732EFD814"><enum>(i)</enum><text>If criminal or juvenile justice questions are necessary for the other aspects of the institution's interactions with applicants, identify those specific interactions in which it is appropriate to ask such questions.</text></clause><clause id="H3BC4D7C57FA04ED5B606E5FB02180E55"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>In non-admissions interactions, inquire about criminal or juvenile justice history transparently and clearly inform applicants as early as possible how to respond to the inquiry.</text></clause><clause id="H42B58AF238F7495BBFEDBC6D673697BE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>In non-admissions inquiries about criminal or juvenile justice history, ensure the questions are specific and narrowly focused, and make it clear that answering the questions may not negatively impact applicants’ chances of enrollment.</text></clause><clause id="H8266BDA41F1C4860A08399181AC088F7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>In non-admissions inquiries about criminal or juvenile justice history, give applicants the opportunity to explain criminal or juvenile justice involvement and preparedness for postsecondary study.</text></clause><clause id="H431EED7F134B40D796B430435016B6E0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Provide staff of the institution who have access to a prospective or current student’s criminal or juvenile justice history, the necessary and proper training on the effective use of criminal or juvenile justice history data, including the problems associated with this information, the types of supporting documents that may need to be obtained, and the appropriate privacy protections that must be put in place.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4D165C58CD44D6CBD92705EA078A93C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>If an institution of higher education determines that it is necessary to inquire about the criminal or juvenile justice history of applicants for admission, it is recommended that the institution comply with the following:</text><clause id="H4890FCEA168F40ECAA1DDECC7A15A7F9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Delay the request for, or consideration of, such information until after an admission decision has been made to avoid a chilling effect on applicants whose criminal or juvenile justice involvement may ultimately be determined irrelevant by the institution.</text></clause><clause id="HCB0B9BEDA0AD47E2B160E8C43DA7CA52"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Provide notice and justification for applicants within 30 days if, upon receiving information regarding applicants’ criminal or juvenile justice involvement, the admission to the institution is denied or rescinded based solely on the applicant's criminal or juvenile justice involvement.</text></clause><clause id="H12EE1FD4D9B6400FAC25A663F5FB7C08"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Inquire about criminal or juvenile justice history transparently and clearly inform applicants as early as possible in the application process how to respond to the inquiry.</text></clause><clause id="H6393925200A14EEC83FA72C599779848"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Ensure the questions are specific and narrowly focused.</text></clause><clause id="HAACD3AE899F84A1E8699A4FBB151D495"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Give applicants the opportunity to explain criminal or juvenile justice involvement and preparedness for postsecondary study.</text></clause><clause id="HAA37B67B660D4882921C76C31F273706"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Provide admissions personnel, registrars, and any other relevant staff of the institution, as well as any other staff that should have access to a prospective or current student’s criminal or juvenile justice history, the necessary and proper training on the effective use of criminal or juvenile justice history data, including the biases or limitations associated with this information, the types of supporting documents that may need to be obtained, and the appropriate privacy protections that must be put in place.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9330E455795740689333D0ADC1299E28"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Training and technical assistance</header><subparagraph id="H498559819EAF42008C4078F7836C43B5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Office of Postsecondary Education of the Department, shall use funds available to the Department to provide institutions of higher education with training and technical assistance on developing policies and procedures aligned with the recommendations described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E4935E99AFF42EDB77529C67E8C7623"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Training</header><text>The training described in subparagraph (A) shall include—</text><clause id="H20947CE0932B4DABBE87A397CCD72E14"><enum>(i)</enum><text>training for admissions and financial aid personnel and enrollment management staff of an institution of higher education to understand and evaluate an applicant if—</text><subclause id="H7B79980C33EC4712A55CD66781771FA7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the institution makes a determination under paragraph (2)(A) to continue asking criminal or juvenile justice history questions in the admissions process; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H3F921A1A6EEA40D794685FE7BCF7A364"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the institution makes a determination under paragraph (2)(A) to remove criminal or juvenile justice history questions in the admissions process, but continues to make criminal or juvenile justice history inquiries in non-admissions settings;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H091E086310B44B3895BFB8D0A8492EB2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>training to ensure that if an institution does not ask criminal or juvenile justice history questions, that proxy questions or factors are not used in lieu of criminal or juvenile justice history information;</text></clause><clause id="HC06245FE0D0846949999108787F9591A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>training for financial aid personnel and any other staff of an institution of higher education involved with campus employment to provide guidance related to work study programs or on campus employment available to formerly incarcerated or juvenile adjudicated individuals;</text></clause><clause id="H4ED743DDF5354982B2016811B0A679C2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>training for registrars, academic counselors, student housing staff, student life staff, and any other staff of an institution of higher education who would have access to a student’s criminal or juvenile justice information when the student is an enrolled student; and</text></clause><clause id="H2DC4304D91224E7AA653FBBC470047AB"><enum>(v)</enum><text>training for career counselors to ensure that students with involvement in the criminal or juvenile justice system are provided with targeted career guidance, made aware of potential barriers to employment or licensure, and provided assistance to respond to these barriers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E1530EDAE4B4CD9898CCE8784385C8D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Resource center</header><text>The Secretary shall develop a resource center that will serve as the repository for—</text><paragraph id="H307A5B2ACD814F6C88B2D52B856792FD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>best practices as institutions of higher education develop and implement practices aligned with the recommendations described in subsection (a)(2) to ensure the successful educational outcomes of students with criminal or juvenile justice histories; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71908E7FE6BA4555A4FFCDD057C4EBF9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>supplemental research on criminal and juvenile justice-involved individuals and postsecondary education.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

