<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA17C9005ACBB47A6BC98D8E224C4525F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5957 IH: Robin Danielson Menstrual Product and Intimate Care Product Safety Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5957</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231013">October 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to establish a program of research regarding the risks posed by the presence of dioxins, phthalates, pesticides, chemical fragrances, and other components of menstrual products and intimate care products.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEC6A0AA80BA947DC9DD091A2047956A9" style="OLC"><section id="H0D63C2F8C226478BAE5D3CACAA22BEE0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Robin Danielson Menstrual Product and Intimate Care Product Safety Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1DE83F05CCC24B04AE7DF111349BBA14"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="H4781CA50B06E4FF3BE3B7A16DDC740FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Menstrual products and intimate care products are widely used in the United States today, but there is not enough research on the safety of or potential chemical exposure from components of these products.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H265BA1AE9B534BB08D97F6D7989BA55A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>People who menstruate may be exposed to substances in tampons and other menstrual products for as long as 40 years over the course of their reproductive lives. The average person who menstruates may use up to 16,000 tampons in their lifetime. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DA3FB455EEC406A99BD86C689DBBDB3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Trace amounts of dioxins can be found in tampons and other menstrual products. The Environmental Protection Agency and the International Agency for Research on Cancer, an arm of the World Health Organization, have concluded that dioxins are a probable human carcinogen (cancer-causing agent).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H477F20C28982442F88612B185164EE2E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Chemical testing of menstrual products from around the world have detected several additional chemicals of concern including phthalates, volatile organic compounds, pesticides, carbon disulfide, and per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1EC28C35DC849A3804A6C8363DFDA7E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Intimate care products frequently contain undisclosed fragrance chemicals, some of which may be allergens, reproductive toxins, and carcinogens. Such products also contain potentially harmful preservatives. Research released by Apothercare, Women’s Voices for the Earth, and Black Women for Wellness found that some intimate care products specifically inhibit the growth of lactobacillus, a crucial type of healthy bacteria found in the vaginal microbiome. Disruption of the vaginal microbiome can lead to significant health problems including bacterial vaginosis, increased risk of sexually transmitted diseases, and fertility concerns.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD8439C350884C43AC9377ECFA651426"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Intimate care products (especially douches and powders) have been associated with higher levels of toxic chemicals in the bodies of people who use them. Specifically, phthalate levels in urine were significantly higher in people who douche frequently. Another study found significantly higher levels of 1,4–dichlorobenzene in the blood of people who douche frequently and higher levels of ethylbenzene in the blood of intimate powder users.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74239098133E4147AD355BFF46F3A361"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Research regarding the presence of chemicals in menstrual products and intimate care products plays a role in advancing health equity for populations that have historically experienced health disparities, including Black people. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5CE5A310664C4E0F8F50992D3BFDC7DE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Regulatory oversight of the safety of materials in menstrual and intimate care products is limited. The Food and Drug Administration has historically relied on data provided by manufacturers of menstrual products in determining product safety. Intimate care products generally do not need approval by the Food and Drug Administration before they go on the market, and manufacturers have the responsibility to ensure the safety of their products.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H96E86F7F74C342508907ED3ACBBB4FC5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Research on dioxins and other potentially harmful components of menstrual products and intimate care products</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part F of title IV of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/287d">42 U.S.C. 287d et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="HB2CBAEC59EB7471595A01E630253B834" style="OLC"><section id="HE81EEA1F1FEA450E8B1D1EACB0954A30"><enum>486C.</enum><header>Research on dioxins and other potentially harmful components of menstrual products and intimate care products</header><subsection id="HF4D75392E01E41D38F587FF5BC60A6F2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Research</header><paragraph id="H17327F6F287F46BF91FBA857A555B0C0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of NIH shall provide for the conduct or support of research to determine the extent to which the presence of dioxins, phthalates, titanium dioxide, and other components (including contaminants and substances used as fragrances, colorants, dyes, and preservatives) in tampons and other menstrual products and intimate care products—</text><subparagraph id="H7EC24D4DE79245B3A5FC68FA11F871A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>poses any risks to the health of people who use the products, including risks related to gynecologic, breast, and other cancers, endometriosis, infertility and pregnancy outcomes, immune system deficiencies, pelvic inflammatory disease, toxic shock syndrome, the health of the vaginal microbiome, and other bacterial and yeast infections; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H990A6188DBAE4936B8EB73DD070E514D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>poses any risks to the health of children or people who used such products during or before the pregnancies involved, including risks related to fetal and childhood development.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4B2B2839C584D33827C3CA8A8F04E15"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="HCC3261784FD84B5BB24ACCA07E5CE345"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <quote>menstrual products</quote> means tampons, pads, liners, cups, sponges, and similar products used by people who menstruate with respect to menstruation or other genital-tract secretions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32A8C71E0C5F4499ABCF8940D4F6EF42"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <quote>intimate care products</quote> means douches, wipes, sprays, washes, powders, and similar products used with respect to vulva or vaginal cleansing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7215BFC72E314948AD42BC92A5E740B5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>For the purpose of carrying out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

