<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB1476607544E4C709541A1FAC85642E5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 658 IH: Strengthening Youth Apprenticeships Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 658</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Labor to award grants to eligible entities to carry out or expand youth apprenticeship programs.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H02232A7EABB74C72830F5E2374FD66E5" style="OLC"><section id="H19CAA825D9FF4084A1D657DCA8CE8718" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strengthening Youth Apprenticeships Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFFEBAF8704B242FA82A13B5B5BAFA3C6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Interagency agreement</header><subsection id="H2C5CB18C364343078848A4FC1DF351FA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the effective date of the <short-title>Strengthening Youth Apprenticeships Act of 2023</short-title>, in order to cooperate with the Secretary of Education and promote awareness and adoption of apprenticeship programs, the Secretary of Labor shall—</text><paragraph id="HE53F07D843504BD4AB83996CF8994FD3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>enter into an interagency agreement with the Secretary of Education to promote and support integration and alignment of programs under the national apprenticeship system with secondary, postsecondary, and adult education, through the activities described in this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C5924002EB84BB18C23DBFCEF5444D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of Senate, such agreement and any modifications to such agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H340DD7493A8B49CDAECC41F0126D8531"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Alignment for youth apprenticeships</header><text>In order to promote alignment between youth apprenticeship programs and high school graduation requirements, the interagency agreement under subsection (a) shall describe how the Secretaries will work to provide—</text><paragraph id="HA9B894E275B24CCCB4BF249E65420EE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>information and resources to—</text><subparagraph id="H671DE2DB93E347C0B7EA2193C6630D8A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>parents and students to promote a better understanding of programs under the national apprenticeship system and their value in secondary and postsecondary education and career pathways by not later than middle school; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95A7B68D7AA14F20975D9844B39A0D21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>school leaders (working with academic counselors, teachers, and faculty) about the value of such programs and information on how to effectively align youth apprenticeship programs with secondary and career and technical education programs; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C43DFECF29A4AEF8AE40A141F5F5A64"><enum>(2)</enum><text>technical assistance on how to—</text><subparagraph id="H78AF192FBCF4412BAF23DE9DF54CFD2E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>align related instruction and apprenticeable occupation skills and competencies to high school graduation requirements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9016941A939489DB7ACA863A42F1F0D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>offer related instruction through dual and concurrent enrollment programs and other accelerated learning programs, as described in section 4104(b)(3)(A)(i)(IV) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7114">20 U.S.C. 7114(b)(3)(A)(i)(IV)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB04101620762462BB383BBCC9AA050A3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>facilitate transitions for youth apprentices who have completed their youth apprenticeships into further education, including an associate, baccalaureate, or advanced degree, and related apprenticeship opportunities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2504A96B7B114C9BA7BF95926C7ABE25"><enum>(D)</enum><text>align activities carried out under this Act with eligible funding from, and planning processes, for the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2301">20 U.S.C. 2301 et seq.</external-xref>), the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6301">20 U.S.C. 6301 et seq.</external-xref>), the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act, the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, and the Higher Education Act of 1965.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2D0D481F9F2E4F21B1C907E790711B62"><enum>3.</enum><header>Grant program authorized</header><subsection id="HCFD50A06AF63481B80F9102BFF97F8B3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated under section 7, the Secretary of Labor, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, shall award grants to eligible entities to create or expand youth apprenticeship programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD69EE15B741A4BF5AF9D6721E691539D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this Act, the Secretary shall prioritize eligible entities that will use the grant to carry out or expand youth apprenticeship programs for individuals that include nontraditional apprenticeship populations.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB4C77873E6754468840B902A6C86FA41"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Geographic distribution</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary of Labor shall, to the extent practicable, ensure an equitable geographic distribution of grants, including an equitable distribution among States, within States, and to urban and rural areas.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4479BC7CB3C145EBB047A16A8BE2AE0C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">An eligible entity desiring to receive a grant under this Act shall submit an application to the Secretary of Labor, at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require, and which shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HC03F89F832A94B12AC59DD37460777A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>How the youth apprenticeship program the eligible entity will expand or carry out using the grant will meet the best practices and joint guidance developed under section 2.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1789FCFE041B46318A1F78C3C59D0CF5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>How such program will be aligned with and fulfill the indicators described in section 6(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F56F7EA5B0343EA8797814FF2F69200"><enum>(3)</enum><text>How such program will prepare individuals for work in high-skill, high-wage, or in-demand industry sectors or occupations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C701E18A3344582AC53736DB857639B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>How such program will recruit and retain to ensure that non-traditional apprenticeship populations participate in such program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6712D97078C049A18B5F2C01D9DC0A80"><enum>(5)</enum><text>How such program will, to the extent practicable, align with high school diploma requirements and career cluster.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E8ACF9EFC8F4AA6B283FD8460064151"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The ability of the applicant, directly or through partners to enroll, instruct, advance, and graduate youth apprentices served by the grant activities, and enable the participants to enroll in further education, gain employment after program completion.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30CF40D036134F19973530B2846068D8"><enum>(7)</enum><text>An assurance that the eligible entity will—</text><subparagraph id="HD12A4EB2BB074E86BC108798AC021224"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide information to the Administrator, as requested, for any such evaluations as the Administrator may carry out;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3BD5AD2365F4A8586DC4837392E9CB8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make program performance outcome data available (in accordance with applicable data privacy laws, including section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>)) to independent evaluators to enable the evaluators to prepare the evaluations and reports under section 6; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E02838298014DB79919A7D304C2C409"><enum>(C)</enum><text>coordinate grant activities with a State Apprenticeship Agency, if such agency exists in the State where the eligible entity is applying for a grant or carrying out activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H63F5DC1FEF174F009F33C15035DD078E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grant uses of funds</header><subsection id="HF61D600184BB43A49AAC3D1E30F50010"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that receives a grant under this Act shall use the grant funds that are not reserved under subsection (b) to carry out or expand a youth apprenticeship program, which may include using the grant funds for 1 or more of the following:</text><paragraph id="H1610639D885C48CFA02468F5D81A3654"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recruitment, retention, and completion of such program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC06AC1346E9C4415AC97A7BF6D44F567"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Program alignment with the challenging State academic standards adopted by the State in which the program will be expanded or carried out under section 1111(b)(1) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(b)(1)</external-xref>) with the technical skills and career competencies that are applicable to and transferable to high-skill, high-wage, or in-demand industry sectors or occupations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF061E1FD6E784A1BB292AD20ABFC6ED7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paying for the costs associated with curriculum development and alignment of that curriculum with industry-recognized credentials, high school graduation requirements, and related instruction, including curriculum development for dual or concurrent enrollment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1E9AD9D1DDF4A62A2EA3ED42D182F35"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Facilitating or expanding partnerships with a community college or consortium of community colleges to help with transferability of credits and the increased use of dual and concurrent enrollment programs. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3899EC97C8845FDAF434934CA183DB1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Engaging employers for participation in youth apprenticeship programs, which may include:</text><subparagraph id="H227526D53153461B9EC109DCE9AC8F0D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Creating and expanding industry or sector partnerships for the purpose of supporting new program development or program expansion. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H987134A54B9048778E0CE61C55537E2D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Providing employers technical assistance to support the participation of youth apprentices under the age of 18.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF39D533F36814D3B86C9CE123072BB0B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Providing technical assistance to support the participation of small- and medium-sized businesses in youth apprenticeship programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H403DCC3265C3493898A5A66D694711DC"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing supportive services and career planning activities, including career exploration of postsecondary opportunities such as apprenticeship programs, for the participants of the youth apprenticeship program, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="HEAB4EA8C0FF64B1EA1845A5D28A0FF6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promoting the early exposure of students to the opportunities and requirements of apprenticeship programs; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F156039711D41F1A5E9164AE12C7CC6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>creating opportunities for students to explore a career and develop occupational skills while in high school; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C671D4D3DF7410385F83CBDBC06F48E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting the costs associated with fees, transportation, child care, or mobility challenges.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H25C33C48F22C4BD1806A63968F210B2F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Providing teachers, career guidance and academic counselors, school leaders, administrators, specialized instructional support personnel, and paraprofessionals with professional development opportunities to build an understanding of apprenticeship opportunities available to students, including experiential opportunities like externships.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC04CA1FD847473BBE9789AE13ED28AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reservation of funds</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this Act shall reserve not less than 5 percent of the grant funds to provide direct financial assistance for recruitment, retention, and completion efforts with respect to the youth apprenticeship program, such as housing, transportation, childcare, food insecurity, and health issues. </text></subsection></section><section id="H31347B59D17D46FF8E1A883C5A5E61A7"><enum>6.</enum><header>Evaluation</header><subsection id="HE15003B35EF74CD19D67D6D4E43EDADE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this Act shall submit, on an annual basis, to the Secretary a performance report with respect to the participants of the youth apprenticeship program receiving assistance under this Act that measures—</text><paragraph id="HC77D05066EBC4450AB8F33C4BFA78E47" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the percentage of program participants who are in education or training activities, or in unsubsidized employment, during the second quarter after exit from the program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECA7E1F979AB42BC879916B42B7AC026"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the percentage of program participants who are in education or training activities, or in unsubsidized employment, during the fourth quarter after exit from the program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9968B9E2720F4769919E1000FA71DEE5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the median earnings of program participants who are in unsubsidized employment during the second quarter after exit from the program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8407C262A50411286F39A56DDE420D3"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of program participants who obtain, during participation in or within 1 year after exit from the program—</text><subparagraph id="H9448C951C48A44209D02DCDF98A2388D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a recognized postsecondary credential; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2869E222AE7C4E64910913B3B62428CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a secondary school diploma or its recognized equivalent, as measured by—</text><clause id="HDE75B9B732ED4E0FAA1475231A554422"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the four-year adjusted cohort graduation rate (defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965); and</text></clause><clause id="HC1A682BB022E485EB2C096941C0D0BA3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at the State’s discretion, the extended-year adjusted cohort graduation rate defined in such section 8101; </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H169BB45D8B8949B181EAF45F7DDE97DD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the percentage of program participants who, during a program year, are in an education or training program that leads to a recognized postsecondary credential or employment and who are achieving measurable skill gains toward such a credential or employment; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5BDEA59310F4B4DB1705F78E0D1F696"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of program participants who are in employment, an apprenticeship, or other education and training activities in an industry sector or occupation for which the youth apprenticeship program provides preparation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H89A011D847194921B956C3E183CBF3BC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each performance report submitted under subsection (a) shall be disaggregated by race, ethnicity, sex, age, and membership in a population specified in section 3(24) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102(24)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="HB1382C5481C84E1C8C72C0293C73F164"><enum>7.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act for fiscal year 2024 and each of the 4 succeeding fiscal years.</text></section><section id="H04D98AC36A6A4BDBB6EEA9637129D0EA"><enum>8.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H2B8BDD630DB849069D198B88B8C2F7A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Apprenticeship program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>apprenticeship program</term> means an apprenticeship program registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; 50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77E0BCA5014D4A80A912ECF5FE333C21"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community college</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>community college</term> means a public institution of higher education at which the highest degree awarded is an associate’s degree.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA883E12175A4DF5B3F2785E8AE8C314"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a partnership that—</text><subparagraph id="H297565A5EA4143C99A9451F25AD89E74"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall include—</text><clause id="H11A35BB6F6734D509B34893B84B5DC0F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">1 or more of the entities listed in clauses (i) through (iv) or clause (vii) of section 3(19)(A) of Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302(19)(A)</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="H933107A0FEFA4BA5836688FF6619DC69"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 or more community colleges; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00E3A626207347C486621395DE8B86C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, shall include—</text><clause id="H862E430B2D5C4E8191F717CBC70000B2" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a State or local board;</text></clause><clause id="H8685A88D236844B18C65B8983D47174B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an industry or sector partnership; </text></clause><clause id="HB1DABD3B4ED9434D933255F95D7D1E11" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a community-based organization; and</text></clause><clause id="H0B4D0619D69B48B2B67013E9B1E72E88"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the State Apprenticeship Agency, if such agency exists in the State in which the grant is awarded.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D4EFE8129FE4D3F8FDFAE235C00A213"><enum>(4)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <term>dual or concurrent enrollment program</term>, <term>high school</term>, and <term>secondary school</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAEA1689B448448D1B5310823B12D1091"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD7198196A554B4A98D09403877C2C53"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Non-traditional apprenticeship populations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>non-traditional apprenticeship populations</term> means individuals who are of a gender or from a race or ethnicity that comprises less than 25 percent of the individuals participating in apprenticeship programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF29EAFE0510B4ACA811464960658BFDF"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18C467A272E741D3A96C3BC2FD50C80E"><enum>(8)</enum><header>WIOA terms</header><text>The terms <term>local board</term>, <term>community-based organization</term>, <term>in-demand industry sector or occupation</term>, and <term>industry or sector partnership</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEA2BD70C6CA42B8A7D8B8AC1E48FE49"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Youth apprenticeship program</header><text>The term <term>youth apprenticeship program</term> means a program designed for youth apprentices who at the start of the program are enrolled in high school and which includes each of the following core elements:</text><subparagraph id="HDEFEC12853AA45899888FC9805DB1047"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The employment and training to be received by each youth apprentice participating in the program, including—</text><clause id="HB62884B3C93F4A85B515BF39B595A2CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an outline of the work processes or plan in which the youth apprentice will receive supervised work experience and training on the job or in an experiential setting;</text></clause><clause id="H07458587DDEB404A87F64A75E11ADC46"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the allocation of the approximate amount of time to be spent in each major work process;</text></clause><clause id="HDB2CF18409FA4AB88EB08E05E8989351"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">mentoring that will be provided to the youth apprentice; and</text></clause><clause id="H0CA21483569B4892889229CA7E135E67"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description or timeline explaining the periodic reviews and evaluations of the youth apprentice’s performance on the job and in related instruction.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64D11292A3304910B9563C4E587A9667"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A process for maintaining appropriate progress records, including the evaluations described in section 6.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8A6FF09039C4066AEC1F72F84E289A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Related classroom-based instruction, which may be fulfilled through dual or concurrent enrollment, and is, to the extent practicable, aligned with high school diploma requirements and career clusters.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EC048BF36E34F449D04A07C522C493B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A progressively increasing, clearly defined schedule of wages to be paid to the youth apprentice.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BD27F9499B8495886EB2F96C81B02C4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Provides all individuals with an equal opportunity to participate in youth apprenticeships under the program, including through the method for the selection of youth apprentices.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9617DC29D51A4B9B8A92DF5011223CC8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The methods used to measure skill acquisition for an apprentice, including ongoing assessment against established skill and competency standards, established against skill and competency standards.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7C5EE526094434F99EF585BC43A4FBC"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Prepares the youth apprentice for placement in further education, employment, or an apprenticeship program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15D30A6CEDFB48D585819858B1CE158F"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The program—</text><clause id="H2BE30227BFF04C659CC545F5A52D4FC7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has adequate and safe equipment, environments, and facilities for training and supervision;</text></clause><clause id="HAC6BCE00EC434CB2A0E2683CD2CB6908"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provides safety training on-the-job and in related instruction as applicable by apprenticeable occupation; and</text></clause><clause id="HA49CE8378906418780BF7782D391758D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provides adequate training for mentors and qualified instructors on providing a safe work and training environment.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFE472D168A24C94BF4094A4C9D22541"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The program awards a certificate of completion in recognition of successful completion of the program, evidenced by an appropriate certificate issued by the registration agency, and culminates in a recognized postsecondary credential.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3459EB0C0733433EB8B9B67AE5E54839"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The program provides that an individual who is to become a youth apprentice enters into a written apprenticeship agreement with the sponsor of the program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

