<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE amendment-doc PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/amend.dtd//EN" "amend.dtd">
<amendment-doc amend-type="engrossed-amendment" amend-degree="first"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1734 EAS: Testing, Rapid Analysis, and Narcotic Quality Research Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<engrossed-amendment-form>
<congress display="no">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="no">1st Session</session><legis-num display="no">H.R. 1734</legis-num><current-chamber display="yes">In the Senate of the United States,</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023.</action-date></action><legis-type display="yes">Amendment:</legis-type></engrossed-amendment-form><engrossed-amendment-body><section id="id34da487a7575482a84bfeaa859d8e5fb" section-type="resolved"><text>That the bill from the House of Representatives (H.R. 1734) entitled <quote>An Act to require coordinated National Institute of Standards and Technology science and research activities regarding illicit drugs containing xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other substances of concern, and for other purposes.</quote>, do pass with the following</text></section><amendment><amendment-instruction blank-lines-after="0"><text> Strike all after the enacting clause and insert the following: </text></amendment-instruction><amendment-block style="OLC" blank-lines-after="1" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic"><section id="idb861b2d7fdd54427a0f04beb73d24a28" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Testing, Rapid Analysis, and Narcotic Quality Research Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TRANQ Research Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="idf981f54968a545129e831c9ef1dcbd9b"><enum>2.</enum><header>Xylazine detection and analysis</header><subsection id="idc0a4509f70e148ee806782b0ae2a8bb5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="ida7be9199b3e5483dae1b716b1ff13f94"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1aa04e724d1d480bbf091b9c32bd1872"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal laboratory</header><text>The term <term>Federal laboratory</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3703">15 U.S.C. 3703</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id01600b9ef2274fe2aadd45ad587491eb"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institute</header><text>The term <term>Institute</term> means the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6303a951845e4d238ed720393197d7fc"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1001">19 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="idf59967e2d0c441488fb6b30fd3eb6f63"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit organization</term> means an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from tax under section 501(a) of such code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7d8ce98d24b34c1b98be56b355ed733b"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Xylazine</header><text>The term <term>xylazine</term> means the nonopioid tranquilizer methyl benzene compound frequently used in veterinary medicine as an emetic and sedative with analgesic and muscle relaxant properties.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id7d3edef837c94f8fa925d4fc242ea182"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall—</text><paragraph id="idf6b1f5602c404f4cb1e0335e50600cd5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support intramural basic measurement science and research of the Institute to advance—</text><subparagraph id="id32734d2b388b40488df9f9378efa4e1d"><enum>(A)</enum><text>analytical methods to identify, understand, differentiate, and categorize substances containing xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, or other new psychoactive substances;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id3598c328550f4d05aec69c5c6a25c634"><enum>(B)</enum><text>measurement technologies to shorten analysis timelines and enhance narcotic and opioid detection and analysis capabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ida06232ad2cb14c5086395041e366bc1c"><enum>(C)</enum><text>new data tools, techniques, and processes to identify and publicly disclose relevant information concerning substances containing xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, or other new psychoactive substances; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id5746ddc002814fbaa28690330db42bbf"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such other areas as the Director determines to be critical to the development and deployment of technologies to measure and analyze the presence of xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other new psychoactive substances;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idd769d9acc43a4362ba9f576b9de23569"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support activities to inform and expand the development of near-real time spectrometry capabilities regarding xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other new psychoactive substances;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5840990b164b4a54838d8f55fdcda278"><enum>(3)</enum><text>convene and consult with organizations engaged in the analysis of new psychoactive substances to develop coordinated strategies and voluntary best practices for the safe handling, transport, data-sharing, and analysis of substances containing xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, or other new psychoactive substances, including—</text><subparagraph id="idb867195a968643e9a0b19ac4b47b7bbf"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Drug Enforcement Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id1d741526677642dcac30b8e5744fa74c"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="ideda994a2a00c4e899357bd2f6a1d219e"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the National Institute on Drug Abuse;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="iddd317ec3c3724dacac8c998d62e6bac8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Federal laboratories;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id9eaa2e8df66c4e54baaaa9ee10770cd8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>States and territories;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idab89e74a767a475aa267baf7652ad291"><enum>(F)</enum><text>State fusion centers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id82d35951312544c8b11c766f26b00b99"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the private sector;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="idd1c6a34e1c284c029c630a80b3bdfe4d"><enum>(H)</enum><text>intergovernmental organizations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id70ff14662a78486a991f83d02c36b594"><enum>(I)</enum><text>institutions of higher education, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id92c38da2f201416184087399892740e0"><enum>(J)</enum><text>nonprofit organizations; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="idb3cba1de43cf44f9bc4e05006f0eb0a4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establish or expand collaborative partnerships or consortia with other government agencies and persons engaged in related research and development, such as institutions of higher education, Federal laboratories, public health agencies, intergovernmental organizations, and the private sector, to enhance narcotic and opioid detection and analysis capabilities regarding xylazine, novel synthetic opioids, and other new psychoactive substances; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id38d13748124c4d1b8e3e68afe7959abe"><enum>(5)</enum><text>encourage graduate and post-graduate research to include detection and identification of xylazine and other new psychoactive substances in relevant course studies when practicable. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id27bdf0c24edc4f219c6c8804a19a1417"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Controls</header><text>In carrying out activities under this section, the Director shall ensure proper security controls are implemented to protect sensitive information, as the Director considers appropriate and consistent with applicable provisions of law.</text></subsection><subsection id="id131164db55d74fdea6d582c7d75f6b8c"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives a report on the implementation of this section. Such report may include recommendations for legislative action to improve the ability of the Director to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="id46d5e6c588384a6d97b205899eefc3cd"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study on United States Government technologies and analytical methods to detect and identify new psychoactive substances</header><subsection id="id35b374ccceca478689976a61f4240d3a"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id7913cb0821ec4451bc27331911b981c4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study of the capabilities of the Federal Government to respond to the threats of new psychoactive substances such as xylazine.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id090a7b3631734c6fa160e4419e57ee8a"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matters evaluated</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The study conducted pursuant to paragraph (1) shall include an evaluation of the following:</text><subparagraph id="id0f5548734f56437a86adc7ef9a60385a"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The capabilities, including technologies and analytical methods, of Federal, State, and local agencies to detect and identify new psychoactive substances such as xylazine.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id6115573e55234f3e9e0fbb2c94d1eaad"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An analysis of timeframes for identification and development of technologies and methods to identify new psychoactive substances by Federal, State, and local agencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="id732aafe07f6b4dd78d9df0b7803a06a7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Facilities, including laboratories, used by Federal, State, and local agencies for the identification of new psychoactive substances such as xylazine.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="idbe651233fa9844048bb1a8afe2daf8bd"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Federal grant programs to fund new technology development to detect and identify new psychoactive substances.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id67eb324bd7b54c5fa485ac794a6f2a70"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives a report containing the findings of the Comptroller General with respect to the study conducted pursuant to subsection (a). </text></subsection></section></amendment-block></amendment></engrossed-amendment-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestor></attestor><role>Secretary</role></attestation-group></attestation><endorsement></endorsement></amendment-doc> 

