<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3B36F3C14A22466ABCF0D7169B4F8455" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5903 IH: To authorize the International Boundary and Water Commission to accept funds for activities relating to wastewater treatment and flood control works, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5903</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231006">October 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="R000603">Mr. Rouzer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the International Boundary and Water Commission to accept funds for activities relating to wastewater treatment and flood control works, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAD8CE6DA1E4C4E858B361021B1A49369" style="OLC"><section id="HAFED7EEE2E2B485E99FD711344CE955C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>International Boundary and Water Commission authority</header><subsection id="HC5287F4DD2674FB2BAF103613B34924A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission is authorized to accept funds from a Federal or non-Federal entity, including through a grant or funding agreement, to study, design, construct, operate, and maintain wastewater treatment and flood control works and related structures, consistent with the functions of the Commission.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6B2017838F8E4BDFAB347A287600017F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deposit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any funds accepted by the Commission under this section shall be deposited into the account in the Treasury of the United States entitled <quote>International Boundary and Water Commission, United States and Mexico</quote> and shall be available until expended to carry out the activities described in subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HF28BE0D5B9954D19B56420C9410CA79D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Commission defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>Commission</term> means the United States Section of the International Boundary and Water Commission, United States and Mexico. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

