<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1FA0433509B144EDBF1951328C48C0AA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>94 HR 3026 IH: To provide for the adoption of the Revised Organic Act of the Virgin Islands as the constitution of the United States Virgin Islands.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3026</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230428">April 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000610">Ms. Plaskett</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the adoption of the Revised Organic Act of the Virgin Islands as the constitution of the United States Virgin Islands.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7E3123C7F9E64FA0BDD46C2352DC9636" style="OLC"><section id="H5ABCD80E55224DE4B8F920387987B4DA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Adoption of constitution for the United States Virgin Islands</header><subsection id="H1CA67D40D5FE488394F60C0172255D18"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Revised Organic Act of the Virgin Islands (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1541">48 U.S.C. 1541 et seq.</external-xref>) (as amended through January 1, 2023)—</text><paragraph id="H24E68FA4B21D4056807B4414463D914F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is deemed to satisfy the requirements of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/94/584">Public Law 94–584</external-xref> (90 Stat. 2899) with respect to a constitution for the local self-government of the people of the United States Virgin Islands; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1298E8C8FA2E42238807B47D5B6339B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as of the date of the enactment of this Act, is adopted as the constitution of the United States Virgin Islands.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H798F1F18AC434E41A71C342CEA4066FC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendments to the constitution</header><paragraph id="HDD849D28620243EA97A0EB63833B1C47"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Proposed amendments</header><subparagraph id="HE8EAD98BBF9F47BA9009AA5BBEFFCE5B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Legislature of the Virgin Islands (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>Legislature</quote>) may propose amendments to the constitution of the United States Virgin Islands (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>constitution</quote>) by a resolution approved by not less than two-thirds of all of the members of the Legislature.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5C8012E5A4948EABB681CC8C236F2F7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Presentation to voters</header><text>All proposed amendments approved by the Legislature under subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H8EAB2924D0AE413C855FF192BC530F45"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be submitted to the qualified voters of the United States Virgin Islands (referred to in this subsection as <quote>qualified voters</quote>) in a referendum; and</text></clause><clause id="H249457AC0F3D4E349B36265002FC6955"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>published at least 3 months before the date of such referendum.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40301C5FB9264820A7262F19DF321FC1"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Referendum concurrent with general election</header><text>If the resolution is approved by not less than three-fourths of all of the members of the Legislature, the Legislature may provide that the referendum be held at the same time as the next general election.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6075A752CBA74F5F909441BA6DA2F50A"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Amendment requirements</header><text>Each proposed amendment approved by the Legislature under subparagraph (A) shall—</text><clause id="HF5D24C490E0642BBAE44E4AB273E14E9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be voted on separately;</text></clause><clause id="H644880D0749F47599B000C46F50C9DD4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specify the terms under which it shall take effect; and</text></clause><clause id="H0F3B4CED5D8442F9BA9922AA74089E95"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">become a part of the constitution if it is ratified by a majority of the qualified voters voting thereon. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H160D8E43875E4B3E97CD3F7331C40625"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Maximum number</header><text>Not more than 3 proposed constitutional amendments may be submitted at the same referendum.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H49140803EEEC4A94983893D59ECA5989"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Constitutional convention; Revisions</header><subparagraph id="HA1B0715660754F5FA8EDF7F5F10C8DCC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Question to voters</header><text>The Legislature, by a resolution approved by two-thirds of all of the members of the Legislature, may submit to the qualified voters at a referendum, held at the same time as a general election, the question of whether a constitutional convention shall be called to revise the constitution.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F4445277BD04E94BC8375DD49ED3E14"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effect of vote in favor of revision</header><text>If a majority of the qualified voters voting on this question vote in favor of the revision, it shall be made by a constitutional convention elected in the manner provided by law.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA978D48E13644835AD0E1B9682C4C974"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Special referendum on revisions</header><text>Each revision of the constitution shall be submitted to the qualified voters at a special referendum for ratification or rejection by a majority of the votes cast at the referendum.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C8F145E305641288FBE0552AE173B2C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No amendment to the constitution shall—</text><subparagraph id="HDD432C8FE73342C0ACDA795FDB1E80D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>alter the republican form of government established by it; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFB4BCA6FFF14CCA95C05C0112DAE73B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>abolish any right in the bill of rights. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H57BF1D9EDF714E6388EDEF38E9277540" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to create a cause of action under Federal law with respect to any claim that the Legislature of the Virgin Islands is in violation of the Revised Organic Act of the Virgin Islands (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1541">48 U.S.C. 1541 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

