<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE9996D8081C94C0B9B4877F9DF9C28D8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3361 IH: To direct the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information to submit a report on the digital divide and to update the Indicators of Broadband Need mapping application, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3361</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information to submit a report on the digital divide and to update the Indicators of Broadband Need mapping application, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5E956DB494874830A2E6A5FCE5BDB01C" style="OLC"><section id="HE6FF981049854B9381B54E31AF5CCB95" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Report on digital divide</header><subsection id="H339CEE74B4634AA2B341965583700476"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for the subsequent 10-year period, the Assistant Secretary, in consultation with the Federal Communications Commission, shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, and make publicly available on the website of the NTIA, a report on the state of the digital divide, which shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H468ECC65C991434C8713914FFE67BEA0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Information on and an analysis of—</text><subparagraph id="H732588C1EA574E3AAD7E42DFA2DC148F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>barriers to, and trends regarding, broadband access, adoption, and affordability;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B3834B3C3FD4BBAA314442257683A86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the connection between—</text><clause id="HA3F9551B1BDA4771BD6B76EAF9245FE3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>broadband access, adoption, and affordability; and</text></clause><clause id="H329F74A1332E4B5EBABC23B0FC2069B8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>various socioeconomic indicators; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2DAC0A843BBA4724B7FDCE04533423C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the impact of Federal programs on broadband access, adoption, and affordability.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H144B24B118024363BA1A7B6F0FBF0403"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the sufficiency of existing data collection and data sets with respect to the analysis described in paragraph (1) and, if necessary, recommendations for NTIA actions to improve data quality.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H317D0C95D8804B1581B68D549D202308"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations for legislative action to facilitate closure of the digital divide.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8843B1ACE09446ECAC8071349C6AAEA3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assembly process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In assembling each report required by subsection (a), the Assistant Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="HBD846765419644C4BEFE7DE8438673DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilize all available and relevant data, including data associated with the Indicators of Broadband Need mapping application of the NTIA and published research and data from individuals and entities other than the NTIA;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EFA08791F8548A7BD74473BD7D709C1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>solicit public comment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62DE67B5E59745D29E81CEC58AB64334"><enum>(3)</enum><text>hold public meetings with relevant stakeholders; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H570B3805432142CD871B53EA9B619FF5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>consult with experts on and representatives of communities that are unserved or underserved with respect to broadband.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3FE041870A834AE0AC76056432597402"><enum>2.</enum><header>Indicators of Broadband Need mapping application</header><subsection id="H8E91BB6BBD484A18986B7FF8DAF6499B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Update required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter, the Assistant Secretary shall update the Indicators of Broadband Need mapping application of the NTIA to ensure that such application incorporates, and includes display layers with respect to, the following:</text><paragraph id="H5CC0CBD6211A4FFEB4C1E0D00C97F621"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Data from the Broadband Data Collection system of the Federal Communications Commission, including data on availability and subscription rates for broadband tiers with a download speed of more than 25 megabits per second and an upload speed of more than 3 megabits per second.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D1862AA3996486D878390C824AF8D2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Third-party data on the results of mobile network speed and signal strength tests.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFB0418AA4D34741A9162A21A228289C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The identification of—</text><subparagraph id="HADD0C50163FC49A8B96991AA5DD957A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>areas of persistent poverty (as such term is defined in section 6702(a) of title 49, United States Code);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C16EF67DC6F4A62A79AAA2E1D94D1EC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>historically disadvantaged communities (as such term is used in section 6702 of title 49, United States Code);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H674DDF3E94434215956D26F108535D53"><enum>(C)</enum><text>areas impacted by previous redlining practices (as determined using maps produced by the Home Owners’ Loan Corporation); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA51D3D52FA5643CAAB1EEBA6D6DB5AE6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>congressional districts.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1A6217DAF3543129C1107510ABF392F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Data on eligibility and enrollment with respect to the Affordable Connectivity Program established under section 904(b) of division N of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1752">47 U.S.C. 1752</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F010C42F9FC49939CA95AF67CE09F3C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed to limit the authority of the Assistant Secretary to incorporate, as part of the Indicators of Broadband Need mapping application of the NTIA, elements in addition to the elements identified in subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H101AB57E9B4C49D396B3142CBA7DDF33"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H4C74A1A13F824A05874BC51814163988"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assistant Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Assistant Secretary</term> means the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF91A42D8B4E94C44AE431C2B846D3660"><enum>(2)</enum><header>NTIA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>NTIA</term> means the National Telecommunications and Information Administration.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

