<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8A869CBA68004F8893ECE4ED5301BC67" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4217 IH: Secure E-Waste Export and Recycling Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4217</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230620">June 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To control the export of electronic waste in order to ensure that such waste does not become the source of counterfeit goods that may reenter military and civilian electronics supply chains in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFFB67693F89944538DC8A919D5896AC8" style="OLC"><section id="HFA237A87C40943778D77C44CD36425FF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Secure E-Waste Export and Recycling Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5D0E7F5605914D36B6FD7B60140F5424"><enum>2.</enum><header>Export controls on electronic waste</header><subsection id="HDC60280AAA344011B7A9DF97209CEF1E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2E54C0CB6D9D45E4B83AFDE758FD7E03"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Electronic waste</header><subparagraph id="HF77115382B844111B64A533184D5DC85"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>electronic waste</term> means any of the following used items containing electronic components, or fragments thereof, including parts or subcomponents of such items:</text><clause id="H4E9362FA1AC44C6F865B6B5F10639DB5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Computers and related equipment.</text></clause><clause id="H0A62FAF3E94D490B9FA5538001C2B2A2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Data center equipment (including servers, network equipment, firewalls, battery backup systems, and power distribution units).</text></clause><clause id="H133B4EF203E845169E84BA5A1ECF56FB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Mobile computers (including notebooks, netbooks, tablets, and ebook readers).</text></clause><clause id="H29A4BB9DD67B43B0BC963B2EEBB99EAD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Televisions (including portable televisions and portable DVD players).</text></clause><clause id="H3F9ED5DFA7AF4C299F5492D19C4F504F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Video display devices (including monitors, digital picture frames, and portable video devices).</text></clause><clause id="H1508E637ACAD403295A277164D78BFD4"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Digital imaging devices (including printers, copiers, facsimile machines, image scanners, and multifunction machines).</text></clause><clause id="H9ACA8C727F284DBB95ADEDE1B3E63F0E"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Consumer electronics—</text><subclause id="H533F5B71243E4C49A64C8C2D833E6962"><enum>(I)</enum><text>including digital cameras, projectors, digital audio players, cellular phones and wireless internet communication devices, audio equipment, video cassette recorders, DVD players, video game systems (including portable systems), video game controllers, signal converter boxes, and cable and satellite receivers; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3CD56EB77C1A487389FF2A3F2F3809F0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not including appliances that have electronic features.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H38A811AFB5F1474086000F01BD34C2B1"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Portable global positioning system navigation devices.</text></clause><clause id="H341D121588114C6785572C8094925330"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Other used electronic items that the Secretary determines to be necessary to carry out this section.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED3D4ECF6C424A8CB02616A61CA882F5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exempt items</header><text>The term <term>electronic waste</term> does not include—</text><clause id="HE87436FA4B8444B5916498ACD5596FC0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>exempted electronic waste items;</text></clause><clause id="H0639CC4938184EA59AB2283EBC9823BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>electronic parts of a motor vehicle; or</text></clause><clause id="H0EED8694D3C940C3AD83641A2B440FDC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">electronic components, or items containing electronic components, that are exported or reexported to an entity under the ownership or control of the person exporting or reexporting the components or items, with the intent that the components or items be used for the purpose for which the components or items were used in the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E554E82251A4B6687BA4363D7278779"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exempted electronic waste items</header><subparagraph id="H8510FB1764154D24AB8C9A1FEE10D1F9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>exempted electronic waste items</term> means the following:</text><clause id="H964542165036407AAFCBCEDDED13C887"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Tested, working used electronics.</text></clause><clause id="H5285D9B0096B4D03B8389D403890211B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Low-risk counterfeit electronics.</text></clause><clause id="H75A9ACD531F34313842F9588D324F61D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Recalled electronics.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD24720B72231480CACBB5C81883F5265"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text><clause commented="no" id="HDEF28C7670E14EC5BEDF64AAF842B637"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Tested, working used electronics</header><text>The term <term>tested, working used electronics</term> means any used electronic items that—</text><subclause commented="no" id="H13974E755E144C249D670965CFAE30FF"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are determined, through testing methodologies established by the Secretary, to be—</text><item commented="no" id="HCFD3EFE0D1BF4BC39D078EC5DF003EAB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fully functional for the purpose for which the items were designed; or</text></item><item commented="no" id="HF749653D09674504A8F8F7694334B27A"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of multifunction devices, fully functional for at least one of the primary purposes for which the items were designed;</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HC92112621575477FACB175EDEEA2557D"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are exported with the intent to reuse the products as functional products; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H80BAF654F41E410281BCF2AFF5C0462F"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are appropriately packaged for shipment to prevent the items from losing functionality as a result of damage during shipment.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HF41737A262234EF897441FC1EEC3A9E7"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Low-risk counterfeit electronics</header><text>The term <term>low-risk counterfeit electronics</term> means any electronic components or items that—</text><subclause commented="no" id="H83337A1FB42447AF8850C97FF21EB4F2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>have been subjected to destruction processes that render the items unusable for their original purpose; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H6B8750A4070948FD99668B8422D66438"><enum>(II)</enum><text>are exported as a feedstock, with no additional mechanical or hand separation required, in a reclamation process to render the electronic components or items recycled consistent with the laws of the foreign country performing the reclamation process.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H72C449D772AB4F3EB2929DC1686B26AA"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Recalled electronics</header><text>The term <term>recalled electronics</term> means any electronic items that—</text><subclause commented="no" id="HB7F445653256457A82730E6DCC412073"><enum>(I)</enum><text>because of a defect in the design or manufacture of the items—</text><item commented="no" id="HB5FBC54770E14BCA898FAE0000A296DB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>are subject to a recall notice issued by the Consumer Product Safety Commission or other pertinent Federal authority and have been received by the manufacturer or its agent and repaired by the manufacturer or its agent to cure the defect; or</text></item><item commented="no" id="H7BF48FAEF5D84F1EA06BD673200B811B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>have been recalled by the manufacturer as a condition of the validity of the warranty on the items and have been repaired by the manufacturer or its agent to cure the defect; and</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H3F6D915878B54E4A85244831A5252433"><enum>(II)</enum><text>are exported by the manufacturer of the items.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HC63A2FAC626941B4ADF0583F05D337BF"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Feedstock</header><text>The term <term>feedstock</term> means any raw material constituting the principal input for an industrial process.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6744ED768EBA4199AA019445DEE71ED0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Counterfeit good</header><text>The term <term>counterfeit good</term> means any good on which, or in connection with which, a counterfeit mark is used.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DA8A97381F842F9B5C146D5761F1638"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Counterfeit military good</header><text>The term <term>counterfeit military good</term> means a counterfeit good that—</text><subparagraph id="HACE7E560F02B4F739AA8EC2B32EC438A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is falsely identified or labeled as meeting military specifications; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07A704F3E5EF40B2B6DE3431C005A175"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is intended for use in a military or national security application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF1DC1C3EF694AF7B0DD2B685815FFA8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Counterfeit mark</header><text>The term <term>counterfeit mark</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2320 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB00F9A22E9B346F482CF346CE540B73C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Export administration regulations</header><text>The term <term>Export Administration Regulations</term> means the regulations set forth in subchapter C of chapter VII of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations, or successor regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H713791222145497BAD2E089337B85CFC"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Export; reexport</header><text>The terms <term>export</term> and <term>reexport</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 1742 of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4801">50 U.S.C. 4801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1051C523D31F4BB5924AFA6F927DF6F1"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H588F5A07C369425DB7E2738DED4D869A"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Used</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>used</term>, with respect to an item, means the item has been operated or employed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HABCB849DF4644D13B4F7B72114BDFC84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Except as provided in subsections (c) and (d), no person or entity may export or reexport electronic waste or exempted electronic waste items.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCE1B63DFDAC645A6BA45AA43AD0BFDB9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Export prohibition exemptions</header><text>A person or entity may export or reexport exempted electronic waste items, but only if the following requirements are met:</text><paragraph id="HD2A3B919974940F5BBE46CE36DD584CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Registration</header><text>The person or entity is listed on a publicly available registry maintained by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6C470F38A184D0996AC4FB896831691"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Filing of export information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each export transaction, the person or entity files in the Automated Export System, in accordance with part 758 of the Export Administration Regulations (or any corresponding similar regulation or ruling), electronic export information that contains at least the following information:</text><subparagraph id="HC8AE5FDE25394E85B40BD7D17CA068A1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A description of the type and total quantity of exempted electronic waste items exported.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6410FEE0A1546D8A6B93D10F6144330"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The name of each country that received the exempted electronic waste items for reuse or recycling.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F0E9BFAE5DF4D8EA61AEB228E2552EF"><enum>(C)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H37D17FFF81C940AE90B3E430027C5BBC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The name of the ultimate consignee to which the exempted electronic waste items were received for reclamation, recall, or reuse; and</text></clause><clause id="H2AAE16E679794C8D9D18C4EF5BD79074" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>documentation and a declaration that such consignee has the necessary permits, resources, and competence to manage the exempted electronic waste items as reusable products or recyclable feedstock and prevent its release as a counterfeit good or counterfeit military good.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F6B47EE6AF7489E965A058DB2426E6E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compliance with existing laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The export or reexport of exempted electronic waste items otherwise comply with applicable international agreements to which the United States is a party and with other trade and export control laws of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB17031E1B863410FB8F70DEA711E25E3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Export declarations and requirements</header><text>The exempted electronic waste items are accompanied by—</text><subparagraph id="HFE7C9C0B32CF408AB2960A1B280F9277"><enum>(A)</enum><text>documentation of the registration of the exporter required under paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1F6099796414BD19C8D79E4874E83BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a declaration signed by an officer or designated representative of the exporter asserting that the exempted electronic waste items meet the applicable requirements for exempted electronic waste items under this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88F2F0BDEEB14708B48286FD3A287C37"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the contents and condition of the exempted electronic waste items in the shipment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E0B4A7C047A4C4D91CB3F245444C796"><enum>(D)</enum><text>for tested, working electronics, a description of the testing methodologies and test results for each item;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB615F1E4CCEB4EAD9BF800D2F0835543"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the name of the ultimate consignee and declaration of the consignee’s applicable permits, resources, and competence to process or use the items as intended; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FED5E9FADF04EF9B79EB25AC99BFA96"><enum>(F)</enum><text>with respect to low-risk counterfeit electronics only and when required by the importing country, the written consent of the competent authority of the receiving country to allow the products in such country.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H416B4C2170DB4306B2A65E42F8201805"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exception for personal use</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may provide for an exception to the requirements of this section, subject to such recordkeeping requirements as the Secretary may impose, for the export or reexport of 20 or fewer items that are or contain electronic components intended for personal use.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB85E9F63D36A4ADC97501A2792203676"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H9FCEE26F9A39450DB82906F6F373D2A7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), this section shall take effect upon the expiration of the 1-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB83DA59B8DFA491CBBB4792E81D14336"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Modification of ear</header><text>The Secretary shall, not later than the effective date under paragraph (1), ensure that the Export Administration Regulations are modified to carry out this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E5E7D24D49F4166B3F427F467169A75"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Penalties for violations</header><text>Any person who violates this section or the regulations issued under subsection (e)(2) shall be subject to the same penalties as those that apply to any person violating any other provision of the Export Administration Regulations.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

