<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAD62D2CEAC1C45849B067866C2DA6E76" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5208 IH: Health Care Provider Shortage Minimization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5208</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230815">August 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to clarify the treatment of locum tenens physicians and advanced care practitioners as independent contractors to help alleviate physician shortages, including in underserved areas.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6B280286A64F465895A0500AEA7B5C74" style="OLC"><section id="HA9087B7CA6184A9EBE95D1125E69B90C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Health Care Provider Shortage Minimization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H451F5A236F3D44AB8911968A59D17990"><enum>2.</enum><header>Treatment of locum tenens physicians and advanced care practitioners</header><subsection id="H51AA62AC76884D2E871884EE83FD98A3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/25">Chapter 25</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="H16A774ABE42944709BC6D4AFDA452054" style="OLC"><section id="H86E2397639D44BEBA4FF8C81808909D0"><enum>3513.</enum><header>Treatment of locum tenens physicians and advanced care practitioners</header><subsection id="H86B94A2099174FE9819BE31F141356A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>General rule</header><text>For the purposes of the taxes and other obligations imposed by this title, in the case of services performed as a qualified locum tenens physician or advanced care practitioner—</text><paragraph id="H336694E2361540A4A1C0130D1330CB33"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the individual performing such services shall not be treated as an employee,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD569A3E7623147658B63BB5E45DBFDF6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>neither the persons for whom such services are performed, nor any agency that contracts with a qualified locum tenens physician or advanced care practitioner, shall be treated as an employer,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7D69A5FEA00469AA16118E89206A097"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any payor shall not be treated as an employer, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB61509B1F331436CAC08EA97DFB681F8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the remuneration paid or received for such service shall not be treated as paid or received with respect to employment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H82F4577C686E4253BDCF6D5135A956AC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified locum tenens physician or advanced care practitioner</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="HF87B5788D2AC4C20B062E9B79959114F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>qualified locum tenens physician or advanced care practitioner</quote> means an individual if—</text><subparagraph id="H6B93BAD8CFEC4353AF21D347F48D9670"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such individual provides temporary physician or advanced care practitioner services as a locum tenens physician or locum tenens advanced care practitioner for a period of not more than one continuous year at a site of service,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H215BA029D06E4467BB23A467B8A18F21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such individual is—</text><clause id="H4FECA3D7F9A94CE7B2BEE564B830A3DF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a doctor of medicine, osteopathy, dental surgery, or dental medicine legally authorized to practice medicine, surgery or dentistry in the State, territory, or possession in which the individual performs such services,</text></clause><clause id="H2F4FD925DFBE4443AC856491ABC4EC78"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a doctor of podiatric medicine or doctor of optometry legally authorized to perform podiatric or optometry functions in the State, territory, or possession in which the individual performs such services,</text></clause><clause id="HDBCE2FB13F1341DD95608E402885F0EE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a physician, as defined in section 1861(r) of the Social Security Act Section (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(r)</external-xref>) or section 8101(2) of title 5, United States Code, or</text></clause><clause id="H5D7F3996B33446F7BEB9B101D13F0C0F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>an advanced care practitioner, and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD00D890CA542421DA2EC38741BDED1F7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the services described in subparagraph (A) performed by the individual are performed pursuant to a written contract and such contract provides that the individual will not be treated as an employee with respect to such services for purposes of this subtitle.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD303CBAB4C004EE6908EA2B8EEF0A64A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Advanced care practitioner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>advanced care practitioner</quote> means a nurse practitioner, physician’s assistant, or certified registered nurse anesthetist.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H966B1525CD1540BEA003456CC4639222"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections of chapter 25 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block id="H9B56671D49FB48D18454AC5BB7DE511D" style="OLC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 3513. Treatment of locum tenens physicians and advanced care practitioners.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H03868F630D0B434FB1A701C12F490C2E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to wages for services performed after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

