<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H894189BEDD9342519327EEB60B7CE076" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3703 IH: Helping Evaluate Appropriate Logistical Infrastructure for National Government Response Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3703</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Comptroller General of the United States to conduct and complete a review examining the efforts of the Secretary of Health and Human Services to ensure that the United States is prepared to rapidly produce certain medical countermeasures in the event of a public health emergency, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H90D56F64125845BEB251258B8A6D6182" style="OLC"><section id="HB57473DF7DE0401B886274CB3F8F826C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Helping Evaluate Appropriate Logistical Infrastructure for National Government Response Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HEALING Response Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H97B4627143614EA29F421BC4A13D679F"><enum>2.</enum><header>GAO review of HHS efforts to ensure rapid production of certain medical countermeasures in case of a public health emergency</header><subsection id="H804EA50ED2544E569F8258DE09A929D3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct and complete a review examining the efforts of the Secretary of Health and Human Services to ensure that the United States is prepared to rapidly produce qualified countermeasures (as defined in section 319F–1 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d-6a">42 U.S.C. 247d–6a</external-xref>)) in the event of a public health emergency declared under section 319 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/274d">42 U.S.C. 274d</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HC72FF4FF46054560BF83EBCD12A1EB92"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The review conducted under subsection (a) shall include a review of—</text><paragraph id="H9D856590A34E4F8B9232796ADEDDB38F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the efforts described in such subsection, including the Secretary’s efforts to transition from the Centers for Innovation and Advanced Drug Manufacturing program to any new efforts, including the National Biopharmaceutical Manufacturing Partnership and Industrial Base Expansion Connect; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE26FD358E194F80A2C3CCECF7433FCE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the progress made toward the implementation of such efforts; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E03AF03886F4C6EBAA4B2361FA7ED3F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the planning within the Department of Health and Human Services to assess risks and challenges associated with advanced development and manufacturing of qualified countermeasures.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H962EE02B569F4112A7131906E5A43EF9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after completing the review under subsection (a), the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Congress a report containing—</text><paragraph id="H806E571C4CA148328D16E8EC4FCAF64B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the review; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19B78E53E5C24A27962B9A855E27FAFB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Comptroller General’s recommendations for ensuring that the United States is prepared to rapidly produce qualified countermeasures in the event of a public health emergency.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

