<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCCF75872A3684A23961968A76AAF4911" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5620 IH: First Responders Passport Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5620</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To waive the passport fees for first responders proceeding abroad to aid a foreign country suffering from a natural disaster.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA1191B24734740FFAA01D22B9894DC09" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H78DB18154CF0448DA0F1242D7EE90565" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>First Responders Passport Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H24A7665818D742B2B0C982BF7720BD7B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Passports for first responders</header> <subsection id="H46AFCC1E56534E0E8E66D6029C28C737" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1 of the Act of June 4, 1920 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/214">22 U.S.C. 214</external-xref>; 41 Stat. 750; commonly referred to as the <quote>Passport Act of 1920</quote>), is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3B8B9506C22B455F8ABE17805FD138F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (b) as subsection (d); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9234AA6E529A482DA91DEEC08C5E5DE4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsection (a) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H871701BCC1604D8FB50A48545764BB9D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H58CF41CAA9D948B3B04BF893885ACB0D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be collected and paid into the Treasury of the United States a fee, prescribed by the Secretary of State by regulation, for the filing of each application for a passport (including the cost of passport issuance and use) and a fee, prescribed by the Secretary of State by regulation, for executing each such application, except that the Secretary of State may by regulation authorize State officials or the United States Postal Service to collect and retain the execution fee for each application for a passport accepted by such officials or by that Service. Such fees shall not be refundable, except as the Secretary may by regulation prescribe.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H57AA2E3D63AF44FCBDD50584BAA06B34"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception for passport fee</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (a), no passport fee shall be collected from any of the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD631027E02A14BD583CFD3115C831F5C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An officer or employee of the United States proceeding abroad in the discharge of official duties, or from members of his immediate family.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDED1C76C65244AD4BDA51F1C72E40101"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An American seaman who requires a passport in connection with his duties aboard an American flag-vessel.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1553990811C84834AFBD255C9FF4DD07"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A widow, widower, child, parent, grandparent, brother, or sister of a deceased member of the Armed Forces proceeding abroad to visit the grave of such member or to attend a funeral or memorial service for such member.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA02BC370FEBE4FDBBB739EB6189A1E44"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An individual or individuals abroad, returning to the United States, when the Secretary determines that foregoing the collection of such fee is justified for humanitarian reasons or for law enforcement purposes.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF11D0C22A15342548765236320953069"><enum>(5)</enum><text>At the discretion of the Secretary, an individual, including a volunteer, who—</text> <subparagraph id="HE410EE811D3046E594B1CBD93890C5E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is operating under a contract, grant, or cooperative agreement with the United States Government to proceed abroad to a foreign country to participate in search, rescue, and other related disaster relief operations within such foreign country within the first 7 days after a natural disaster affecting such foreign country; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB94107BBF2954F5FA45BF3858DBAC607"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is required pursuant to such contract, grant, or cooperative agreement to be available to so proceed abroad immediately upon notice from the United States Government.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8813585A3DF647099A315F2972B0A975"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exception for execution fee</header><text>No execution fee shall be collected for an application made before a Federal official by a person excused from payment of the passport fee under this section.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3FD87F7D64FA496DA2A2BA256BF4D0DB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the end of the first full fiscal year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the number of waivers of fees for the execution and issuance of passports to first responders under section 1 of the Act of June 4, 1920, as amended by subsection (a) of this section, for such fiscal year.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H29D9F8CCEF004DCBA0B82FFAFCA42759"><enum>3.</enum><header>Determination of budgetary effects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The budgetary effects of this Act, for the purpose of complying with the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010, shall be determined by reference to the latest statement titled <quote>Budgetary Effects of PAYGO Legislation</quote> for this Act, submitted for printing in the Congressional Record by the Chairman of the House Budget Committee, provided that such statement has been submitted prior to the vote on passage.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

