<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDAA748C3A9E746F9804AEB2A2F42C55A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 557 IH: International Financial Institutions Governance Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 557</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote United States interests at the international financial institutions, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD268A12FFCD54A4A87085DF836A7AAF5" style="OLC"><section id="HCED936699D834D85AC03010B427E10F4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>International Financial Institutions Governance Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HDEDD853630A245B58644309EF6919DCC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H6B7A886CD3F74E2D98D6F07D0EA81339"><enum>(1)</enum><text>directing the use of the voice and vote of the United States at the international financial institutions (IFIs) serves an essential role in promoting the national interest;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2AD0072604A4529A49F4D1097F9ADC0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>despite their importance, such mandates have grown to represent a significant compliance burden for United States representatives at the IFIs, having accumulated to more than 260 pages of statutory text over the course of decades-long participation by the United States in the IFIs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H139F7190830F4C4091F6F33ACC878D28"><enum>(3)</enum><text>while certain mandates provide appropriate discretion for United States representatives through waivers and sunset provisions, others may entail inflexible requirements that—</text><subparagraph id="H9E2B654BFEDE45F4845C8A604054BC47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prevent the representatives from achieving maximum effectiveness in the promotion of United States interests;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5717B03BBA4446B3ADDBBD4A32F5EA6C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>render the representatives less relevant in multilateral negotiations at the IFIs, including in discussions with United States allies; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87575D5515B244B7ADD07A577E24D520"><enum>(C)</enum><text>fail to adapt to intervening events and changing circumstances, thereby undermining the pursuit of United States interests.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H6D8E351BA237456592D8855231EF15E5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Pilot authority to waive voice and vote requirements, on a case-by-case basis, in the international financial institutions</header><subsection id="H246B261C5C114959A6D5E34DA8A237DC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may waive, on a case-by-case basis, a statutory requirement that directs the United States Executive Director at an international financial institution with respect to the use of the voice and vote of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H04537F3A777C48A2A833304ECE5E72BB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to a statutory requirement if the provision of law providing for the requirement provides for—</text><paragraph id="HC7AA104D29364B06A77D0D83A6F8BB7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a waiver of the requirement; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80272B7747A24446BF7425AD3CCAD9B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the termination of the requirement by a date certain.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H24176D22C85C44F99958650B9770CB8B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HAE2BA4B732CD4E25AAD4E685ACE805CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>International financial institution</header><text>The term <term>international financial institution</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1701(c)(2) of the International Financial Institutions Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2484F57623D44488843D9AB2399E5E4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Treasury.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE308C8697B174E8AA91FB5838E78413C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report described</header><text>Not less frequently than semiannually, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a written report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="H29BDB2FD7F5B42EF85453E47DFB3B321"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A list of each waiver issued under subsection (a) since the later of the date of the enactment of this section or the date the then most recent report was submitted under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7944BF3AC1894C768F40DE44DEAA1A41"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of any project, policy, or other matter to which the waiver involved applied.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25B9FF4127174ACBAE1514AD5C8B2023"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A detailed explanation of the reasons for the waiver involved.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEFBDFF5E1934FFA98025A3C3C97DA54"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A determination that the waiver involved allowed the Secretary to more effectively advance United States interests at the international financial institution involved.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC3E3A4A2CDCB45ACB781806394A90047"><enum>(e)</enum><header>No retroactive application</header><text>A waiver issued under this section shall not apply retroactively.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE4CDAE414D6745ECB8D936C290E904F0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Recommendations by the Secretary</header><text>Within 12 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the committees specified in subsection (d) any recommendations to revise or sunset a statutory requirement that directs the United States Executive Director at an international financial institution with respect to the use of the voice and vote of the United States. The recommendations should be aimed at achieving the following objectives with regard to the international financial institution:</text><paragraph id="H3131926D85DC475B8953AF229747981C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Strengthening United States leadership in the design, execution, and evaluation of activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H421265F7D7884D4A8A11AB8305CEAF5A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Permitting the Secretary to more effectively support policies, projects, and other initiatives that advance the national interest of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DD2B4ABB169419AA1B4E6F1415A34D0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Facilitating multilateral cooperation, particularly between the United States and its allies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A18420D7C104FEE871D1C5A93972470"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Updating a requirement to appropriately reflect changing conditions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DBCE7FBD7A84AE0B81503B880A3908D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Allowing for all appropriate accountability to the Congress with respect to United States governance at, and participation in, the international financial institution.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8263027DA948441E8C4CAB1EEC838B5E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The preceding provisions of this section shall have no force or effect on and after the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

