<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4EAC5998214F4B4ABE0DB4A515788394" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 887 IH: Securing Our Students Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 887</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001192">Mr. Stewart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize local educational agencies and non-public schools to use funds, services, or assistance provided under section 2001 or 2002 of the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 for school safety, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H892942C7765040FD9C5BBE2227ACF32D" style="OLC"><section id="HF8637DF1C3174CBAA1026613F6DA34A2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Our Students Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6BED3EBE9AD741DA9F5A16C207C30817"><enum>2.</enum><header>Elementary and secondary school emergency relief fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A local educational agency that receives funds under section 2001 of the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/3401">20 U.S.C. 3401</external-xref> note) may use funds not reserved under subsection (e)(1) of such section for school safety uses (in addition to the purposes specified in subsection (e)(2) of such section).</text></section><section id="H2E1C69FC68A04E3F98DF2CBFE532EC37"><enum>3.</enum><header>Emergency assistance to non-public schools</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A non-public school that receives services or assistance under section 2002 of the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/3401">20 U.S.C. 3401</external-xref> note) may use such services or assistance for school safety uses (in addition to any services or assistance authorized under the Emergency Assistance to Non-Public Schools Program).</text></section><section id="HFFA80594B1954BF3B41A9E911F9D8467"><enum>4.</enum><header>Application amendment</header><subsection id="H06D3A26DB0FF4388A0903E867E17EA2D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="HBCFFF328CBAD4457BE95C6580255986C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Elementary and secondary school emergency relief fund</header><text>A State making subgrants under section 2001(d) of the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/3401">20 U.S.C. 3401</external-xref> note) shall, not later than 10 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, inform local educational agencies eligible to receive such subgrants that the agencies may amend their subgrant applications to include school safety uses among the planned uses of funds not reserved under section 2001(e)(1) of such Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46EE0A3FC62D4E5492BBDFF8050C2DBD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Emergency assistance to non-public schools</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Governor providing services or assistance to non-public schools under section 2002 of the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/3401">20 U.S.C. 3401</external-xref> note) shall, not later than 10 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, inform non-public schools eligible to receive such services and assistance that the schools may amend their applications to include school safety uses among the requested services and assistance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H542140C21F794FA4BCA2EBD49B140484"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An amendment authorized under subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="H73D82CBECA6943A1A62FE259CF5BD470"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">what school safety uses are desired to be implemented and how such uses will support known needs for the local educational agency or non-public school; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3C290016E27462D8D54492283631941"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an assurance that such uses will be evidence-based;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3D3F9FAD57F4625A3CD7F33F58B8EDD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>what professional development for school personnel will be conducted to ensure compliance and understanding of the new school safety uses;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC48DA0277B34474B826C66F42640DCAA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>when the implementation of such uses will be completed; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A184B9EF94B447FBCEC7FE3FE465B42"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assurance that school safety uses shall be included in any required reporting under the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/3401">20 U.S.C. 3401</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1BBB15A4E5F448A895A74DC49B85D9F7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Approval</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or Governor shall approve expeditiously an amendment authorized under subsection (a) if it satisfies the requirements of subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H328534C853E9444CB4E077C51A6A15A3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or Governor shall report to the Secretary of Education what percentage of the funds provided to the State or Governor under section 2001 or 2002 of the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/3401">20 U.S.C. 3401</external-xref> note), respectively, are used for school safety uses.</text></subsection></section><section id="H600444F882F347F583010B2357B9CF38"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act:</text><paragraph id="H5608118BE94646729D9BED58E0D85AEC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A0334A868F746AF8D1CA2012A406D3D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>school safety uses</term> means improving school conditions for student learning by planning and designing school buildings and facilities, installing infrastructure, providing safety education for all school personnel and volunteers, and implementing technology or other measures, that strengthen security on school premises, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H2EF0FC0E83A448CC92A402C793FA4DB9" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>controlling access to school premises or facilities, through the use of metal detectors or other measures, including technology, in accordance with the particular needs of a school;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61ED109379594D1EACCD22E9E681556D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>infrastructure—</text><clause id="H3B7747DE81B141B48D65681318D34820"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to cover and conceal students within a school during crisis situations;</text></clause><clause id="HF618066EA62D438684888DE38B1AB27C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for school safety reinforcement, including bullet-resistant doors and windows; and</text></clause><clause id="HE0C9B4ECB3914D42A9159C89ECCA0E1B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for classroom access security measures;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFC35748282904D27B3AB51DADA59E15D" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing methods to provide notification to, and communicate with, relevant law enforcement, first responders, hospitals, and other necessary officials during a crisis situation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9AFC4119509448999C37E6906D8AEDF" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hiring school security officers, including school resource officers, to increase the safety of school students and staff; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4251820E937424FBEB4962D7CFDDABF" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing a communications system that can more rapidly and accurately communicate information to parents, including providing status updates during and after a crisis situation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

