<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4D6FFFE39064439C9C25CB3234764C99" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5070 IH: USDA Communication Regarding Oversight of Pesticides Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5070</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230728">July 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000375">Mr. Arrington</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001220">Mr. Strong</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Agricultural Research, Extension, and Education Reform Act of 1998 to improve interagency coordination in the pesticide registration process, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3EABECC1BA854F8281289A10C74BD5AE" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H1F660EEBE1344DA3AC3A0B2BCC3CE65D"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>USDA Communication Regarding Oversight of Pesticides Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>USDA CROP Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7CDBDE9FE5A849A28594AA810DE38DDA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Office of Pest Management Policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 614(c) of the Agricultural Research, Extension, and Education Reform Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/7653">7 U.S.C. 7653(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDDF828F873FA45FA8CCEE0EB82908DA0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>In support</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD13A407E4C0A4E0D8C547103D4E8D17E"><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDE7C8E4A354A4E4285069F71282009C6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In support</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H359289F1FFBF480398081D3A9CDC761A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0893409BEF794E18A3D1D7FD16535073"><paragraph id="H3A5BFE2E07084C28948D0AC8FD00C813"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Environmental Protection Agency</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2B08F22B373541A5BD8DC09A6D4460DF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Coordination of data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of Pest Management Policy shall coordinate with the Environmental Protection Agency during the pesticide registration and reevaluation processes under the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136 et seq.</external-xref>) and section 408 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/346a">21 U.S.C. 346a</external-xref>) with respect to any action that impacts the sale, distribution, or use of a pesticide to ensure that the Environmental Protection Agency has the following data for use and consideration in making decisions under those processes:</text><clause id="H30DC7198397F4209968B94D0870D6526"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Department of Agriculture agronomic use data.</text></clause><clause id="H84075659DB4943DEA0ECFBBAAA51C83D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Commercially available agronomic use data.</text></clause><clause id="HA4BEAB4A5AC941A491466A24A327D13E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Industry agronomic use data.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27150D069E91490F8E34B8267376C005"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Economic viability of alternatives</header><text>The Office of Pest Management Policy shall coordinate with the Environmental Protection Agency to provide information relating to the economic viability of alternatives for consideration by the Environmental Protection Agency in making registration and reevaluation decisions described in subparagraph (A) that may affect agricultural producers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H840B0A1B3812471CB1D9E8FF1A3CADAA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reasonable and prudent actions and measures</header><text>The Office of Pest Management Policy shall collaborate with the United States Fish and Wildlife Service and the National Marine Fisheries Service (referred to in this paragraph as the <term>Services</term>)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7726560F1E04EBDB35E8FE955D350D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to review the development of reasonable and prudent actions and measures as a result of consultations relating to actions under the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136 et seq.</external-xref>); and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1975BB960360498AADA40479A8AD3AE3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide feedback to the Services on decisions relating to reasonable and prudent actions and measures that may affect agricultural producers. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC7469FBDF764B31A9AB96AD700F4F40"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Response required from the Environmental Protection Agency</header><subparagraph id="H935C36B3FC114D55AA16A3C0DA890259"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Public comment</header><text>Before the publication of a proposed interim decision that includes more restrictive changes to a pesticide label, including a use, tolerance, or registration decision issued as part of a registration or reevaluation process under the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136 et seq.</external-xref>), the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency (referred to in this paragraph as the <term>Administrator</term>) shall provide to the Office of Pest Management Policy an opportunity to comment on the decision for a period of 90 days. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EA9E241909C4CF79FD64D95712C145F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Response</header><text>If the Administrator receives any comments under subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall—</text><clause id="H4024B07FCD1A4630AD35C18772BAE96A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>respond to the comments; and</text></clause><clause id="HE45FE9875ADB4099B06C1F61FC55763A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>publish that response in the Federal Register with the applicable proposed interim decision described in subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9C8EE2FFF0D481BB58F00C76CC4A0FE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Data and information provided by the Office</header><text>The Administrator shall publish with a proposed interim decision described in subparagraph (A), with respect to any data or information provided by the Office of Pest Management Policy under paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H4D1D5F95800F4EA6A2427C6505DC9057"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of the use of the data or information by the Administrator; or</text></clause><clause id="HE3578A3041D4469BAE1E4E5061530B71"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the Administrator determined not to use the data or information, a description of the reasons that the data or information was insufficient or otherwise not suitable for use by the Administrator.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D41E447372D4A8C8E7E3C9AD9117A80" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Delaying effective date; phase out</header><text>If the Administrator receives any comments under subparagraph (A) in which the Office of Pest Management Policy indicates that there is not an economically viable alternative, the Administrator shall ensure that an interim decision or final decision issued as part of a reevaluation regarding—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF835D78C671A4007B00FEEC93B17AED6"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">more restrictive changes to a pesticide label, including a revocation or cancellation of a registration, shall take effect not earlier than the last day of the full growing season that begins after the date on which the interim decision or final decision, as applicable, and any comments by the Office of Pest Management Policy, are published in the Federal Register; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H24559D33F33A49BB96999B50B8A4740C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>more restrictive changes to a pesticide label, including a revocation or cancellation of a registration and a use restriction under the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136 et seq.</external-xref>), that affect agricultural producers shall, in consultation with the Office of Pest Management Policy, take into consideration—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3C8AC4DC4AA54C718A8D947E29B7A02E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>permitting the continued sale and use of existing stocks of the pesticide in accordance with that Act; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HC4AAD97276E542E2B6E33A4B59ABE160" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any other authority to phase out the sale and use of the pesticide.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

