<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7ADBBBB1F9884442A7766D6486351CB4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6844 IH: Ensuring PBM Competition Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6844</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231215">December 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to prohibit the Secretary of Health and Human Services from entering into contracts with PDP sponsors of prescription drug plans that have a contract with certain pharmacy benefits managers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB7464002B0A34E7DAC77F219DEAE91CB" style="OLC"><section id="H20ADF48431DB4FC1B4B4155D8DE0F264" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ensuring PBM Competition Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H8A0A0CBC64834EAE8877B86D4FFBEF27"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibiting the Secretary of Health and Human Services from entering into contracts with PDP sponsors of prescription drug plans that have a contract with certain pharmacy benefits managers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1860D–12(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395w-112">42 U.S.C. 1395w–112(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H79A939F7ABD1470B98657EAB5F6091C5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H3933BEAB02954F0EB7E19E1477554561"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Prohibition on entering into contracts with PDP sponsors that have a contract with a certain pharmacy benefits managers</header><subparagraph id="H6E65B6292CD9470E8C1032D20A61570C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (B), beginning on the date that is 5 years after the date of enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall not enter into, or renew, a contract with a PDP sponsor for the offering of a prescription drug plan in a PDP region for a year if such sponsor has a contract for such year with a pharmacy benefits manager that, directly or indirectly, or through one or more intermediaries, owns, controls, or otherwise has a financial interest in, a pharmacy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46295C0ADF614ABBBA6625D2ADA47A5E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Authority to delay requirement</header><text>The Secretary may delay the requirement in subparagraph (A) by not more than 2 years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62500B506B12469CA9FAC61AEF3B379C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Pharmacy benefits manager defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph, the term <quote>pharmacy benefits manager</quote> means any entity (or any affiliate, subsidiary, or agent of such entity) that, pursuant to an agreement with a PDP sponsor, either directly or through an intermediary acts as a price negotiator or group purchaser on behalf of such sponsor, or manages the prescription drug benefits provided by such sponsor, including the processing and paying claims for covered part D drugs, performing drug utilization review, processing drug prior authorization requests, adjudicating appeals or grievances related to covered part D drugs, contracting with network pharmacies, controlling the cost of such drugs, or providing any services related to managing such drug benefits.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

