<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB40489AE7B1543688A79A606851C8A9A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3501 IH: Law Enforcement Training for Mental Health Crisis Response Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3501</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 to authorize a grant program for law enforcement agencies and corrections agencies to obtain behavioral health crisis response training for law enforcement officers and corrections officers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFACD4613F75F413897ED0F231E456C35" style="OLC"><section id="HE18DDBD021834E3C9BC8888E94F52315" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Law Enforcement Training for Mental Health Crisis Response Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H0CEEC4058F0A4733B505A65EE4E3064D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purpose</header><subsection id="HCBFE1A4AB4F6460087056B8A1F132273"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HA2B649D6D47F4CD28F131561CE27D7AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Law enforcement and corrections officers routinely respond to emergencies involving individuals suffering from a mental health crisis.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D5A5F0AA31C44EAB38FFFAC049125FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Recent statistics have shown that as many as—</text><subparagraph id="HF14F95D818C24468AA034E8CD1CA8EA7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>1 in every 10 calls for police response involve a person suffering from a mental illness;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F3D5B3A5CF24610885E07EE8905C9F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>1 in every 4 people killed by police suffer from a mental health problem; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24C5C35F9EB8467E9F472A680BBD676F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>1 in 3 people transported to a hospital emergency room for psychiatric reasons are taken by the police.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFF8B3A8798A485E920966947E5EBAE5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Law enforcement response calls to individuals suffering from substance use disorder have increased during the current opioid epidemic.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C4416182C9F4A788CA6F4B394DB9C19"><enum>(4)</enum><text>There is a need to ensure that law enforcement officers have access to proper evidence-based training in responding to mental health crises.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H623D9AA8D2E647F494F0F8F22AD08CC6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Proper training for response to individuals suffering from a mental health crisis can better protect the safety of the general public and law enforcement officers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H802B75081FBD406389842F58E1A7827C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Law enforcement and corrections officers in the United States can better serve their communities if the officers receive training to effectively and safely resolve the mental health crises.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1670624393E24026837E42D7BE159E9D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this Act is to provide grants to State, local, and Tribal law enforcement agencies and corrections agencies to obtain behavioral health crisis response training for law enforcement officers and corrections officers to—</text><paragraph id="H9174CEAFCDFC4A1EAC5D517A811B21C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>better train law enforcement officers and corrections officers to resolve behavioral health crisis situations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2DE6B6FBF224EE6B5F97DD5CC4860E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reduce the number of law enforcement officers and corrections officers killed or injured while responding to a behavioral health crisis; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H315689A626C74AED8168B8298E14EE1B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>reduce the number of individuals killed or injured during a behavioral health crisis in which a law enforcement officer or corrections officer responds.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB446FB3BC07F4FDA9D12AED328074E9E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Law Enforcement Training for Mental Health Crisis grant program</header><subsection id="H7FA1198B6C5F47A1BB483D4C980EFD3E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reservation of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 506 of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10157">34 U.S.C. 10157</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0735F39155D44D1E9F6D1C2C4000A9D5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HD8D0BB08556144199F10997250C3ACD3"><enum>(c)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the total amount made available to carry out this subpart for a fiscal year, the Attorney General may reserve not more than $10,000,000 to carry out the program under section 509. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HF211E2129D7C43CA82422007ADED5EA7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Law Enforcement Training for Mental Health Crisis grant program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart 1 of part E of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10151">34 U.S.C. 10151 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2DDE1FA3C8704DC5BA1ECC6044E81700" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HAD36425007B64460B768ADF11F73AF51"><enum>510.</enum><header>Law Enforcement Training for Mental Health Crisis grant program</header><subsection id="H01E24D1B73EE4CF5B9A110F7862E4782"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Attorney General is authorized to award grants to applicants for—</text><paragraph id="HA21AFBE652CB424089A71AF7641B77E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>law enforcement officers or corrections officers to receive training from a program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF5AAE7B7F0546D2B2223BD09D27B728"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the cost of transportation and lodging associated with law enforcement officers or corrections officers attending such program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H12203417728D44549A7A8EB05C3ECEFF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program standards</header><text>The Attorney General shall establish and publish qualification standards for organizations that provide programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC2161BD77F6B4014B2475E576030D7DA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of an applicant shall submit to the Attorney General an application that—</text><paragraph id="H92D253B494B8466BA7071279993BB108"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HC22F34A193EB428BB67D0745997FB9B0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a statement describing the program the law enforcement officers or corrections officers will complete;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCEA62DFD8E454F88A9B160F3635885D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the total number of law enforcement officers or corrections officers in the agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0E40D59FE43493E96D2FFBBBB091855"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of law enforcement officers or corrections officers of the agency that have been killed, or seriously injured while responding to a behavioral health crisis during the 5-year period preceding the date of the application; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H267F86FEBCF1425EA9AB318AC424731B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>whether the law enforcement officers or corrections officers employed by the agency receive any behavioral health crisis response training, including during basic officer training; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FDE063875E747559D2DC246F326E5ED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in addition to the information required under paragraph (1), may, at the option of the applicant, include information relating to—</text><subparagraph id="H8103E902DBAC408CBE7F46718D06084B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recent incidents involving officers of the agency during which behavioral health crisis response training could have played a role in protecting the safety of—</text><clause id="H535A35C7D29B4CAAAEA1219D933E45C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the law enforcement officer or the public, including the persons or persons the law enforcement officers encountered; or </text></clause><clause id="H149EE07D81464F1E9BD068CC7289F9E0" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the corrections officer or inmates at the correctional facility; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86D48DA0047941E9832248BE96D2905C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>estimated cost of attendance of a program per officer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F8350506EF64EC3ABB56CF5E55DB081"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Restrictions</header><paragraph id="H186D7C26E5854D76B3AFB6C4292DA530"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Supplemental funds</header><text>Grant funds shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, State, local, and Tribal funds made available to any applicant for any of the purposes described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27EC9DE468D64ACD91D307FDC630B78A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>Not more than 3 percent of any grant made under this section may be used for administrative costs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0EE6AFC80F48432E9EF7091C7D6DBB97"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports and records</header><paragraph id="H5150D6BDBEDE4868981FA3BD182974EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>For each year during which grant funds are used, the recipient shall submit to the Attorney General a report containing—</text><subparagraph id="H2FCD2B90D73F449DBFBBAAFA1049EF86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a summary of any activity carried out using grant funds;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5AB898BB95FE4F65831DF1842061388D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of officers that received training using grant funds; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H102D71EEF1244C64A329E61BD2EA356F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other information relevant to the purpose of this Act that the Attorney General may determine appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3E460BFA3BC4D08896572B237DDD48A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Records</header><text>For the purpose of an audit by the Attorney General of the receipt and use of grant funds, a recipient shall—</text><subparagraph id="H80886C9214C34BFCB47F3BABDE8DFD21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>keep—</text><clause id="H4D1181D1517242EEB1A266F185578B17"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any record relating to the receipt and use of grant funds; and</text></clause><clause id="HD19A3C1579BF42B49673467A7A47B33E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other record as the Attorney General may require; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93E39FDED48940C6A54CE182F06C9A2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make the records described in subparagraph (A) available to the Attorney General upon request by the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB2A357E12C2547B4B8441AD8202D7080"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H81043029DA694B60AC8EFA122F7356F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicant</header><text>The term <term>applicant</term> means a law enforcement agency or corrections agency that applies for a grant under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3949E4573654E8188F543308FF03A8E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Attorney general</header><text>The term <term>Attorney General</term> means the Attorney General, acting through the Assistant Attorney General for the Office of Justice Programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC69BE86B56814997AA43C1F68E792654"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grant funds</header><text>The term <term>grant funds</term> means funds from a grant awarded under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB801914BEE345178A3F63B1D842E39F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Law enforcement agency</header><text>The term <term>law enforcement agency</term> means an agency of a State or unit of local government that is authorized by law or by a government agency to engage in or supervise the prevention, detection, investigation, or prosecution of any violation of criminal law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEF2F8F5FD3F412DB564A19FB7F04B4B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>program</term> means a program or class that—</text><subparagraph id="H84DBCE3C98DD4033BB5AC13585CE1F88"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides instructional training to law enforcement officers or corrections officers for response to a behavioral health crisis, including response to people suspected to be under the influence of a drug or psychoactive substance, and response to circumstances in which a person is suspected to be suicidal or suffering from a mental illness; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA4BA959CC074F49AC215520C0813B9C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes training on techniques and strategies designed to protect—</text><clause id="H1357D62D01CA464BBAA6A65CD8636FE1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the health and safety of law enforcement officers and the public, including the person or persons a law enforcement officer encounters during a behavioral health crisis response; or</text></clause><clause id="HD513B81972DC40068373F87C31EC9285"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the health and safety of corrections officers and inmates at the correctional facility, including the inmate a corrections officer encounters during a behavioral health crisis response, or in the normal course of business of interactions with the inmate; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5A5A25C2DD34BBD8F5017814C5CE8BB"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is developed in conjunction with healthcare professionals to provide crisis intervention training focused on understanding mental and behavioral health, developing empathy, navigating community resources, de-escalation skills, and practical application training for officers. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE46C6F5883D4E9B84E3B80DF5BA9D05" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Recipient</header><text>The term <term>recipient</term> means an applicant that receives a grant under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

