<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H257CBED8C0BF4F94BEB6C8E1149C7FF3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5265 IH: Small Business Administration Rural Performance Report Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5265</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230825">August 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001314">Mr. Bean of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Small Business Act to require a report on the performance of the Office of Rural Affairs, to require a report on the memorandum of understanding between the Small Business Administration and the Department of Agriculture entered into on April 4, 2018, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2C59CDB5944141E8896104F6A9129B35" style="OLC"><section id="H013057EC4F70409CBDACFFA144223F82" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Small Business Administration Rural Performance Report Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H5E116F96801C4D0C87A61AB37A69E5DA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Small business rural performance reports</header><subsection id="H8434C99BE40E4667ADC4CB14BFC6619C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Office of Rural Affairs Annual Performance Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 26 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/653">15 U.S.C. 653</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H8E6067C9271E486BA67E3B9C778D8396" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H8C87DD091E224D498D61996A39776097"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H3994B24EF4AB46619E3F499C9401FFB5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Administrator shall make available on a website of the Administration, and submit to the Committee on Small Business of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate, a report on the activities of the Office during the year preceding the date of the report that includes the following elements:</text><subparagraph id="H64657BFED6AA4774B58559E550738670"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How the Office is promoting financial assistance pursuant to subsection (c)(1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA73F0C332DC2423BBF847A70153FC6FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Annual statistics compiled pursuant to subsection (c)(2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA73855C08CC4AB3BD7C00963348C881"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How the Office is providing information pursuant to subsection (c)(3).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99B4E6EE971A42DABD7010A09799A32B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How the Office is providing information pursuant to subsection (c)(4).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5522F54EB5184F8E9821E2024453BF2F"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of outreach events conducted by the Office to provide information described in paragraphs (3) and (4) of subsection (c).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C771F53AA7B4D72B93F4C60CC80819E"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Details of any partnerships that the Office engaged in to provide the outreach described in paragraph (5), including any partnerships with the National Travel and Tourism Office of the Department of Commerce.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3668C1B8DB654C50AEB186A33829E819"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The name of the director of the Office and the number of staff employed by the Office.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF916258C6BF14781A67C54559BC7952A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall annually submit, along with the budget the budget justification materials submitted in support of the Small Business Administration budget for a fiscal year (as submitted with the budget of the President under section 1105(a) of title 31), a report that includes the elements described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HB50BB55E7D324B9095285B57F6656EF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 26(c)(5) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/653">15 U.S.C. 653(c)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>United States Tourism and Travel Administration</quote> and inserting <quote>National Travel and Tourism Office of the Department of Commerce</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H1FEED3585B19456994ADB0EAEAD11439"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Memorandum of Understanding with Department of Agriculture Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall make available on a website of the Administration and submit to the Committee on Small Business of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate a report on the MOU. Such report shall include a description of the following:</text><paragraph id="H9DCE1C7B98EA4E48B022897B93A5D73F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>How many working groups convened pursuant to the MOU the Administration was part of and if the Administration is still part of any such working groups.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H787EE6B17E18416CB0B8348C2AB580EF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>How many staff employed by the Administration were and are still involved with a working group convened pursuant to the MOU.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB5D11FC6EAC4B278787945803EC5E97"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The findings specified in clauses (i) through (iv) of paragraph (1) of part 2 of the MOU.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0F700F0E89441668BFAD7874F7975CA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The findings specified in clauses (i) through (iv) of paragraph (2) of part 2 of the MOU.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA932D24CCF094253923563BCEEA681A9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HA11F29451E0E499B97BD235AE3F2C618"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Small Business Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA4ADB327FA54B2FA7B8845EB183723D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The term <term>Administration</term> means the Small Business Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD18B0AB91FE54EE38E2074292E65B2B3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>MOU</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>MOU</term> means the memorandum of understanding between the Department of Agriculture and the Small Business Administration entered into on April 4, 2018, about collaborative efforts to promote stronger businesses and agricultural economies in rural America.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H92CF718997264CE2956B92C8AF6BCA5D" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Compliance with CUTGO</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No additional amounts are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act or the amendments made by this Act. Such Act and amendments shall be carried out using amounts otherwise appropriated to the Administrator of the Small Business Administration. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

