<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC03CCED395AC4AD4A4602FBA972EE578" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5083 IH: To extend Federal recognition to the Wassamasaw Tribe of Varnertown Indians of South Carolina, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5083</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230728">July 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To extend Federal recognition to the Wassamasaw Tribe of Varnertown Indians of South Carolina, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE29E075093A24DF98DF97D69AB47FC26" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD44CE2DDE80D4B18B864AC55B4F13F8E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H14A0DECF756D4A689EDD214667268729"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDF8791ACC7D6405C8DD1FF06CAA819BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tribal member</header><text>The term <term>Tribal member</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H7D9999EE8C974AC7B338C5BE4E454636"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual who is an enrolled member of the Tribe as of the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2C56D097F0D34D2EBC80AE30E5C93EEB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an individual who is placed on the membership rolls of the Tribe in accordance with this Act. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H083565BE14F644B28192B43B7257930C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Tribe</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Tribe</term> means the Wassamasaw Tribe of Varnertown Indians of South Carolina.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HD1E216D139E14F8791CCD3C77EA35B29"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal recognition</header> 
<subsection id="HE784CCFC7D1C49EFB285253D61D1F82C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal recognition</header> 
<paragraph id="H1FB66906A2BD45B687DBFD9707C52CD5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Federal recognition is extended to the Tribe.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFDF543C936314672BB5F93A8B5494C4C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability of laws</header><text>All laws (including regulations) of the United States of general applicability to Indians or nations, Indian Tribes, or bands of Indians (including the Act of June 18, 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/461">25 U.S.C. 461 et seq.</external-xref>)) that are not inconsistent with this Act shall be applicable to the Tribe and Tribal members.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB6BA84DF6F5B4F469E2AFD344B46F597"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal services and benefits</header> 
<paragraph id="H02E9FA01F89D41B595BD9A4B08CCA3B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Tribe and Tribal members shall be eligible for all services and benefits provided by the Federal Government to federally recognized Indian Tribes without regard to the existence of a reservation for the Tribe.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE47A99552D5448FC8D7272197474430E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Service area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The service area for the purpose of the delivery of Federal services to Tribal members shall be determined in coordination and consultation with the Secretary not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H4345141D508B4A4195FC8C2A33288FE1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Membership; governing documents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The membership roll and governing documents of the Tribe shall be the most recent membership roll and governing documents, respectively, submitted by the Tribe to the Secretary before the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></section> <section id="H76123B3969DB4FBC923A2DA7CFB158DD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Governing body</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The governing body of the Tribe shall be—</text> 
<paragraph id="H217480674BDE4CBAB8815DBBA6C61B67"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the governing body of the Tribe in place as of the date of enactment of this Act; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB615CBA0420D4E449AA6475E3ABBB062"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any subsequent governing body elected in accordance with the election procedures specified in the governing documents of the Tribe.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H53306FEBC70A435990368A82FA36E3D9"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reservation of the tribe</header> 
<subsection id="H479ECF4C9A3D47C5A32BC1B523EC93CC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon the request of the Tribe, the Secretary—</text> <paragraph id="H54508C94E4E044258AEFFB9A8747875D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall take into trust for the benefit of the Tribe any lands held in fee by the Tribe that were acquired by the Tribe on or before January 1, 2023, if such lands are located within the boundaries Orangeburg, Beaufort, Berkeley, Charleston, Colleton, and Dorchester counties in South Carolina; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H79449441DFCD458D9B401F92C686694C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may take into trust for the benefit of the Tribe any lands held in fee by the Tribe, if such lands are located within the boundaries of Orangeburg, Beaufort, Berkeley, Charleston, Colleton, and Dorchester counties in South Carolina. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H234554478D1C4821A090BAD13B7556F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline for determination</header><text>Not later than 3 years of the date on which the Tribe submits a request for land to be taken into trust under subsection (a)(2), the Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5C8693762352452EAB9F1B46AF3B4085"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make a final written determination; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5B35E61349442EAB6E6A7426659ABAF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>immediately make that determination available to the Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H54FF1BD9E91A4E688D2EF4489CE5505B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reservation status</header><text>Any land taken into trust for the benefit of the Tribe pursuant to this section shall, upon the request of the Tribe, be considered part of the reservation of the Tribe.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3D39DAAF7A824F85A86B0E0E9F492625"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Gaming</header><text>The Tribe may not conduct gaming activities as a matter of claimed inherent authority or under the authority of any Federal law, including the Indian Gaming Regulatory Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2701">25 U.S.C. 2701 et seq.</external-xref>) or under any regulations thereunder promulgated by the Secretary or the National Indian Gaming Commission.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2323B956916B4C0999450D2B0AABC4B9"><enum>6.</enum><header>Hunting, fishing, trapping, gathering, and water rights</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act expands, reduces, or affects in any manner any hunting, fishing, trapping, gathering, or water rights of the Tribe and Tribal members.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

