<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H59714A4BEC4D4F47AAF748E0FDB07860" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 214 IH: Veterans’ True Choice Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 214</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 10, United States Code, to provide eligibility for TRICARE Select to veterans with service-connected disabilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC30F385B61BD454EBB998DD8D02D4A94" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1342C7730A3B4CBEA26CAAA761EF1543" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans’ True Choice Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H29A8B54A9A974E36A1421F38554E80AA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Eligibility for TRICARE for veterans with service-connected disabilities</header> <subsection id="H37BEA380F578489CB1B630D8400D422C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="HA9AB20CD954B4F96984BE131764436C9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Enrollment in TRICARE Select</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1075 of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H30A3B17BC48F43D7B8DD141606D235FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1)(B), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, and covered veteran beneficiaries under subsection (h), other than Medicare-eligible beneficiaries described in such subsection (d)(2)</quote>; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5F021A5EB5784EFBBFFA3971D7CC417E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (h) as subsection (i); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H66C2A0D396264E448CCF7CAF51086825"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (g) the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H5AB78749E87346948DF4FC5929834C47" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H54A5162DA4074B6BA13A7F5365CA0F85"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Covered veteran beneficiaries</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HED129642E05E49A4B60C237D0D37FF1F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to section 1086(d) of this title, a covered veteran beneficiary may elect to enroll in TRICARE Select during the annual open enrollment season of the TRICARE program. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H04B2473285E8414F820B1A811782387D" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The cost-sharing requirements under TRICARE Select for covered veteran beneficiaries shall be calculated pursuant to subsection (d)(1), regardless of the date of the original enlistment or appointment of the beneficiary in the uniformed services.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4EF35DDC5F494B69A09E1DD84928FA5C" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A dependent of a covered veteran beneficiary may not enroll in the TRICARE program solely by reason of the covered veteran beneficiary enrolling in the TRICARE program.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61D01E41CD73413BA590AB1A0FA67402"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enrollment in TRICARE for Life</header><text>Section 1086(d) of such title is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HFADA901B9A364068BBA7070385BFD9D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote> or pursuant to section 1075(h) of this title</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0546D133278D49C7B90DB2F0307B879A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraphs (2) and (4), by inserting <quote>, or section 1075(h) of this title,</quote> after <quote>a person referred to in subsection (c)</quote> both places it appears.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0B24CC04444D4AC28A0A888972CB41F9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 1072 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H904F14585360424DBEC58427AB041E5F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H8B59049ADB3A425AB67A4919B20BB86C"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered veteran beneficiary</term> means a veteran who—</text> <subparagraph id="H9DF1B648B8AC4B81998B5B0DA0551D55"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is eligible to enroll in the system of patient enrollment under paragraph (1), (2), or (3) of section 1705 of title 38; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H17886DCCCBAD4D54A70692D442D0CA06"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is eligible to enroll in the TRICARE program only pursuant to—</text> <clause id="H089DF9F5FDD64B4CA6BF4B345F68784D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>section 1075(h) of this title; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA09740C8F27548878F41CF0FF0E2726A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 1086(d) of this title by reason of being an individual who would be covered by section 1075(h) but for being a Medicare-eligible beneficiary covered by such section 1086(d).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB29C8C97801B4F62829BFE075EFD67CA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Enrollment in VA health care</header><text>Section 1705 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HA10E8980B14C417CA168A16C9A2C9FD3" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H7138310CD9DC4C29A6EED1D0998EBAAF"><enum>(d)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HBB1E7727A48A464CA16C5D191A8F10D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A covered veteran beneficiary who enrolls in the TRICARE program may not be concurrently enrolled in the system of patient enrollment under subsection (a), and the Secretary may not furnish medical care to the covered veteran beneficiary under this chapter or other provision of law administered by the Secretary while the covered veteran beneficiary is so enrolled in the TRICARE program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H451F20E2E6614D88ACD1BEA806567FB7" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>covered veteran beneficiary</term> and <term>TRICARE program</term> have the meaning given those terms in section 1072 of title 10. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEB90DC5C6499481E969F79A3D0A2C01A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense shall enter into a memorandum of understanding under which the Secretary of Veterans Affairs reimburses the Secretary of Defense for the costs of enrolling covered veteran beneficiaries in the TRICARE program pursuant to the amendments made by subsection (a), as jointly determined appropriate by the Secretaries.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H14B16E270A22493EAAE1A61F816D0751" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation</header> <paragraph id="HC1166B549A48439797CA7AA04392495F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect one year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H03AAAA064AA543AFB2765B776D6D7A68"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>During the one-year period following the date on which the amendments made by this section take effect, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense shall each prescribe regulations to carry out such amendments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB3BF4BBFDBF34CB98517F10D76ABB7E4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Phase in</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the one-year period following the date on which the regulations are prescribed under paragraph (2), the Secretaries shall phase in the enrollment of covered veteran beneficiaries in accordance with the annual open enrollment season of the TRICARE program.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5C92E226397040EDB937820F1AE6115A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>VA Center for Innovation for Care and Payment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out this subsection through the Center for Innovation for Care and Payment of the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9B96DAAAFE004474A853280653DFCF2D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header> <paragraph id="HB912D689676B4C5D98CBDF378A5A9A7C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports on implementation</header><text>On a quarterly basis during the two-year period following the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense shall jointly submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs and Armed Services of the Senate and the House of Representatives a report on the implementation of this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3FEC5F5AEEB74266B597BAEA57759C64"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date on which the final report under paragraph (1) is required to be submitted, and annually thereafter, the Secretaries shall jointly submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs and Armed Services of the Senate and the House of Representatives a report on covered veteran beneficiaries enrolled in the TRICARE program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H288F42D2F83145B3866C0C59E7006A83"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms <term>covered veteran beneficiary</term> and <term>TRICARE program</term> have the meaning given those terms in section 1072 of title 10, United States Code, as amended by subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

