<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C4D1D6F266D4DAA81FF06241C8566F2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 1007 IH: Nuclear Assistance for America’s Small Businesses Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1007</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000459">Mr. Fleischmann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act to assist small businesses that seek to engage in the research, development, and deployment of advanced nuclear reactors by delaying onerous licensing fees, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCBBF640F3B564A7AAC9813F158396621" style="OLC"><section id="H80E4866667274D4B99410F6165CAA8FE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nuclear Assistance for America’s Small Businesses Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDC5990ACE7D54C0ABE370A16688D66E2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Small business assistance</header><subsection id="H71CD321E036D45319A837C726416425A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 102(b) of the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/439">Public Law 115–439</external-xref>; 132 Stat. 5565) is amended by adding at the end following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H53E5269799244EE8A53BAFD97BC645EC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HFEBEB2A8FE6B4EE9933C3934AD30DC26"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Small business assistance</header><subparagraph id="H97069038BF2B44E2965D58BDB1682A5B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Pre-application fees</header><text>Beginning 1 year after the date of enactment of this paragraph, the Commission shall, upon request by an eligible owner, delay collection of up to 50 percent of fees that are assessed for activities relating to a covered application before the date on which such covered application is docketed.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D5A05C6EB9E49D6AF23978E4BAC8930"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Post-application fees</header><text>The Commission shall, upon request by an eligible owner, delay collection of up to 35 percent of fees that are assessed during—</text><clause id="H78AD8CC5DFA944859384C8A217BD0045" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the period that begins on the date that a covered application for a construction permit is docketed and ends on the date that the applicable operating license is issued; </text></clause><clause id="HE9BBEAD3105945998BEDB7AFE0F85752" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the period that begins on the date a covered application for a combined license is docketed and ends on the date that the finding required under section 52.103(g) of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations) for the combined license is made; or</text></clause><clause id="H65D4BFE554D64B91B002671E6EA87027" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any appropriate period of time that begins on the date a covered application is docketed, as determined by the Commission, under the framework developed in accordance with section 103(a)(4).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5082B704C3D44B8BE94D5EA45D3C64A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Collection of delayed fees</header><clause id="H73CBE7BD743E47C19DF83C6E3C4D285A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Default collection plan</header><text>For any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to subparagraph (A) or (B), the Commission shall collect, from the applicable eligible owner, 10 percent of the amount of such delayed fees—</text><subclause id="HC0DB9244ECD044619845E2F848F0E3F6" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9CDA594294C142DAB0C34AE008996601"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>on the date that the Commission—</text><subitem id="H6D6FF9F814BB4CF0BE2CFAD1BA7854C4" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>issues the applicable operating license; or</text></subitem><subitem id="HB0E9CFF3AF9A482484292046D3BA9765" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(BB)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">makes a finding required under section 52.103(g) of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations), for a combined license; or</text></subitem></item><item id="HCF4F0B5CA4124F85B96CA4CCB5C64267" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for fees assessed for any period described in subparagraph (B)(iii), not later than 1 day after the date that the period ends; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HD30EE8848834492DACCAF0E26D8C2D5F" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>annually thereafter for a period of 10 years.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HA09FA464DFCD46B38F962C30D183AA9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Failure to submit a covered application</header><subclause id="H80F9DE90BC8B4224B6A0B4E883057D1D" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subclause (II), in the event an eligible owner does not submit a covered application within 5 years after the date such eligible owner provides a formal response to the RIS–20–02, the Commission shall collect, from such eligible owner, 25 percent of any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to subparagraph (A) beginning on a date the Commission determines appropriate and annually thereafter for a period of 4 years.</text></subclause><subclause id="H609081B0F6D74F188D9EDC01FDB31861"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>If an eligible owner described in subclause (I) submits an applicable covered application within the 4-year period described in subclause (I), the Commission shall collect, from such eligible owner, any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to subparagraph (A) in accordance with clause (i).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H43E7086590B74ACC88DA0730E0AD0897"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Denied application</header><subclause id="HDDF320EE75B74FA3880A3BE4385308F9"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subclause (II), in the event that a covered application submitted by an eligible owner is docketed and then denied by the Commission, the Commission shall collect, from such eligible owner, 25 percent of any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to subparagraph (A) or (B) beginning on the date that is 1 year after the date such denial is issued.</text></subclause><subclause id="HD4CD8E9860CF4092852C37BB7F4EE9E4"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an eligible owner described in subclause (I) submits or resubmits a covered application within 1 year of the original denial is issued, the Commission shall collect, from such eligible owner, any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to subparagraph (A) or (B) in accordance with clause (i).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HF6C16B2474434BDE8D674BB3409EBC89"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Withdrawn or temporarily suspended covered applications</header><subclause id="HF63F331E912B4A92A80011F45CEB8B2D"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Withdrawn covered applications</header><text>In the event a covered application submitted by an eligible owner is docketed and then such covered application is withdrawn by such eligible owner, the Commission shall collect, from such eligible owner, 25 percent of any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to subparagraph (A) or (B) beginning on a date that is 1 year after the date such covered application is withdrawn.</text></subclause><subclause id="HDFEA7A4F7FB44C37946D65D3245C4C6B"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Temporarily suspended covered applications</header><item id="HE6862508BDED4588BBC52285C074768F"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Delay collection</header><text>In the event a covered application submitted by an eligible owner is docketed and then such covered application is temporarily suspended from review by such eligible owner, the Commission shall delay collection of any fees assessed prior to the temporary suspension until the sooner of—</text><subitem id="HE482D06D4F4147E4AF1B96A0F84BF265"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>such eligible owner resumes review of the covered application; or</text></subitem><subitem id="H7C8704264F1C4B53924548AD857E191A"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>a period of 3 years.</text></subitem></item><item id="H57E683769B064EFBB21B7C55FA5C480E"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Collection</header><text>In the event that a covered application is temporarily suspended, as described in item (aa), and an eligible owner has not resumed review of such covered application before the end the 3 year period described in item (aa)(BB), the Commission shall collect, from such eligible owner, 25 percent of any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to item (aa) beginning on the date that is 3 years after the date the eligible owner temporarily suspends a covered application.</text></item><item id="HF8F48CC1A0B44AAFBCF6C052A164693B"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>If an eligible owner described in item (bb) resumes review of a covered application within 3 years after the date such covered application is temporarily suspended, the Commission shall collect, from such eligible owner, any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to item (aa), in accordance with item (bb).</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA05CD9CC3FF34D9EBD3082F5D60D90BA" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Excluded activity from cost-recovery requirement</header><text>Any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to this paragraph shall be considered an excluded activity under paragraph (1)(B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAB6CD4185A3409F83ED6BB97255A5A8"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than December 31, 2029, the Commission shall prepare and submit a report to the appropriate committees describing the views of the Commission on the continued appropriateness and necessity of providing eligible owners with the ability to defer the collection of the fees in accordance with this paragraph.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H966BFFB9D5464A74BE61FBB8D181C59F"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph:</text><clause id="H25BE60147F5A4ECE847111E4E90987B9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Appropriate committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees</term> means—</text><subclause id="H598C51BF3A8C42238AA2B3EF285B650C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H94D7F89B443448B3874DDA31D676D90B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0ABCA66DC9614759848B1C73A8A71C49"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Combined license</header><text>The term <term>combined license</term> has the meaning given such term in section 52.1 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations). </text></clause><clause id="H80AE1F1DD2224C70908444AF62E36DAA"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Construction permit</header><text>The term <term>construction permit</term> means a construction permit described in and issued under part 50 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations).</text></clause><clause id="H06BABADF1FF54E19B8BD950C6D9D6A68"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Covered application</header><text>The term <term>covered application</term> means an application, to be submitted to the Commission, for a construction permit, operating license, or a combined license, for an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></clause><clause id="H3631EC35CEE749D3964DF9111C11631F"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Eligible owner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible owner</term> means an owner of a small business that—</text><subclause id="H022EFD4AE2E34DEC925445755248B006"><enum>(I)</enum><text>seeks to engage in the research, development, and deployment of an advanced nuclear reactor; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3599C8C565E64F7CB2799E581E85C66A"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has submitted a response to the RIS–20–02.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H40569463758A4EB0BF7877365181127A"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Operating license</header><text>The term <term>operating license</term> means an operating license described in and issued under part 50 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations).</text></clause><clause id="H54F595EA132E4E8AA5745C543A397005"><enum>(vii)</enum><header><enum-in-header>RIS–20–02</enum-in-header></header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>RIS–20–02</term> means the NRC Regulatory Issue Summary 2020–02 published by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission on August 31, 2020.</text></clause><clause id="H3CC95200270C438B9BB0366ADC3EE117"><enum>(viii)</enum><header>Small business</header><text>The term <term>small business</term> means a small business concern that is assigned a North American Industry Classification System code of 221113.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H6C529B00549149FC9BB91EA972637FD9" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 102(b)(1)(B) of the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/439">Public Law 115–439</external-xref>; 132 Stat. 5565) is amended by adding at the end following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0B27BDB17B654074B435A423848A783D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H4F9B7DF3D12B449CB90820A54578815A" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any fees the collection of which is delayed pursuant to paragraph (4).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

