<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC27CEC5245DC4E14A818939A47DA8DA3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5153 IH: To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to carry out a pilot program to employ veterans in certain wildland firefighting activities.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5153</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230804">August 4, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to carry out a pilot program to employ veterans in certain wildland firefighting activities.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H07CB2F5935B54CB7A12A5A40A2E96EAD" style="OLC">
<section id="H8F9B1585950D4E04B0FEFC1228BA0608" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Pilot program to employ veterans in positions relating to Federal wildland firefighting activities</header>
<subsection id="H3DCB7DDEB4054D7DBF6B62AE884FB4BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in coordination with the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior, shall jointly establish a pilot program to employ veterans in wildland firefighting activities.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H09BDFD8C7967430D81B80E6B894E8018"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under such pilot program—</text>
<paragraph id="HB83CFD2112524B15959DB10CEF87486B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall be responsible for administering such pilot program; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEDD1B182C70845F4A7ECF9DB5568C75C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior shall be responsible for—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1272B3C32D854BA9A1134EC394180EA2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying vacant positions in the Department of Agriculture and the Department of the Interior, respectively, that are appropriate for veterans selected for participation in such pilot program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H86C79CB41AE8452D905A9F68F5F83118"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, employing such veterans in such positions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6440DF28418844F28EBAE73BACAD6916"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application of civil service laws</header><text>A veteran employed under the pilot program under subsection (a) shall be treated as an employee.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC12651603F9A40F584A2093B81E79580"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish guidelines that include best practices for departments and agencies of the Federal Government that carry out programs to employ veterans who are transitioning from service in the Armed Forces. Such guidelines shall include—</text>
<paragraph id="HDE610329ACBB4E27A235115803FED585"><enum>(1)</enum><text>lessons learned under the Warrior Training Advancement Course of the Department of Veterans Affairs; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF50783DD8664D0A95A7495DC048B3DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>methods to realize cost savings based on such lessons.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H820400109A5E4851AC6C18C21B18EE96"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Partnership</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, the Secretaries concerned, and the Secretary of Defense may enter into a partnership to include the pilot program under subsection (a) as part of the Skillbridge program under section 1143 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA6C2766AE4044960A62E4C94E95515C8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports</header> <paragraph id="H30F91B7DA5D645A1A0E07C8ADDB904E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretaries concerned shall jointly submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the pilot program under subsection (a), including—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD934C1CD6BEB48058AFA9DAEF67C4635"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of how such pilot program will be carried out in a manner to reduce the unemployment of veterans; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H33825DF049834E5F99D2E3B3CF264519"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any recommendations for legislative actions to improve such pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1B60D6627E4548FC817CFE1FE84E175D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>Not later than one year after the date on which the Secretary of Veterans Affairs commences such pilot program, such Secretary and the Secretaries concerned shall jointly submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the implementation of such pilot program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCCF96D0BB9B34705980CB7E1F37A0A6D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which such pilot program concludes, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretaries concerned shall jointly submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes—</text>
<subparagraph id="H97DC7261977343B5B5AB6FB332BCB6DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an identification of—</text> <clause id="HF130E0519E33468C97865007C6DD163B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of veterans who applied to participate in such pilot program;</text></clause>
<clause id="H256FFDBE33DA4A889ABC0DE6BFA2B664"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of such veterans employed pursuant to such pilot program; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBF8C94DE9DF6495CB4C48E20082B7DAF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of veterans described in clause (ii) who transitioned to full-time positions with the Federal Government after participating in such pilot program; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H721C2DFAA4AF4690995B3C5589313F5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other information the Secretaries determine appropriate with respect to measuring the effectiveness of such pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5DA08F931E514E8EA9FD0031ED290ADA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination date</header><text>The authority to carry out the pilot program under subsection (a) shall terminate on the date that is two years after the date on which the Secretary of Veterans Affairs commences such pilot program.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDABC113ED6FC45BD83F19156BE950F8B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H4C525F1E5D7C42D99C2D335E59603290"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="HF3BD6E65129C438B822417A79309B37F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6F7A7F7A50004635B6391A7172B69E82"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6DF3CDB78907489DA84BAF61DDED6849"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDB9D878266C943139B4E491119582707"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H42E27070E0DC4F198DF78F5ED79C4869"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H969F126714EF4EE39AC96D61BCC1AE27"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7D1937D630F64B51AC6830C1946999C3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>employee</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2105 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7FA5D7CB97964B45B691347B0FD9DAD1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>wildland firefighting activities</term> means any temporary, seasonal, or permanent position at the Department of Agriculture or the Department of the Interior, and Tribal Firefighters, that maintains group, emergency incident management, or fire qualifications, as established annually by the Standards for Wildland Fire Position Qualifications published by the National Wildfire Coordinating Group, that primarily engages in or supports wildland fire management, including forestry and rangeland technicians and positions concerning aviation, engineering heavy equipment operations, dispatch, or fire and fuels management.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


