<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H18EEA0F21DD4463CB0016D64DF6D1D14" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1368 IH: Deter PRC Support to the Russian War Effort Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1368</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To impose sanctions with respect to the transfer of arms and related materiel by the People’s Republic of China to the Russian Federation or the evasion or circumvention of United States sanctions or multilateral sanctions by the People’s Republic of China with respect to the Russian Federation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6B1A108EF94440529654CFAD07F4C384" style="OLC"><section id="HD20D794F3FEF45CBB7B929661AD2CB66" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Deter PRC Support to the Russian War Effort Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H59837D7EA0BD4509BD910E4AA7490C72"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HCA3F1021A9F148A1906D7C68533BB1D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The People’s Republic of China (in this section referred to as the <quote>PRC</quote>) and the Russian Federation have, in recent years, forged a closer relationship, based largely on their shared interest in challenging the rules-based international order, in an attempt to reshape that order into one that is more welcoming to their authoritarian systems of government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H713C4986494F40BEB2E83926823BFA25"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rhetoric of the PRC’s leaders, including Xi Jinping, who called for the unification <quote>by force</quote> of Taiwan with the People’s Republic of China, mirrors the Russian Federation’s justification for invading Ukraine, poses a danger to international peace and security and the agreed to status quo on Taiwan in the Three Communiques exchanged between Beijing and Washington, and should be condemned by the international community.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52D3E047C2324B87908A9F9844FB2DFE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On February 24, 2022, Russia launched an unprovoked and unjustified full-scale invasion of Ukraine, and in addition, the United Nation has reported more than 7,800,000 Ukrainian refugees forced to flee across Europe and more than 5,000,000 internally displaced in Ukraine since Russia's invasion began.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D7F2D2938F746B1A0192B6F81428788"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The PRC’s Foreign Ministry spokesperson refused to categorize Russia’s attacks as an <quote>invasion</quote> or <quote>war</quote> and referred repeatedly to the Russian Federation’s statements on Ukraine, including reiterating criticisms of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and blaming the United States for starting the conflict.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC3926ED8504458E9F52596B6AEA5C44"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since Russia’s full-scale invasion of Ukraine, the Biden Administration has imposed several tranches of sanctions on Putin’s Russia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA5CB5696C90428187D04BC8BC66A364"><enum>(6)</enum><text>On February 22, 2022, President Biden issued Executive Order 14065, which blocks property of certain persons and prohibits certain transactions with respect to continued Russian efforts to undermine the sovereignty and territorial integrity of Ukraine, and expands the scope of the national emergency declared in Executive Order 13660 of March 6, 2014, Executive Order 13661 of March 16, 2014, and Executive Order 13662 of March 20, 2014, and takes additional steps with respect to Executive Order 13685 of December 19, 2014, and Executive Order 13849 of September 20, 2018, finding that the Russian Federation’s purported recognition of the so-called Donetsk People’s Republic (DNR) or Luhansk People’s Republic (LNR) regions of Ukraine contradicts Russia’s commitments under the Minsk agreements and further threatens the peace, stability, sovereignty, and territorial integrity of Ukraine, and thereby constitutes an unusual and extraordinary threat to the national security and foreign policy of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC78C62C747CB4DC38782FDEE27D8A395"><enum>(7)</enum><text>On March 8, 2022, President Biden issued Executive Order 14066, which prohibits certain imports and new investments with respect to continued Russian Federation efforts to undermine the sovereignty and territorial integrity of Ukraine, and expands the scope of the national emergency declared in Executive Order 14024 of April 15, 2021, and takes additional steps with respect to Executive Order 14039 of August 20, 2021, finding that the Russian Federation’s unjustified, unprovoked, unyielding, and unconscionable war against Ukraine, including its recent further invasion in violation of international law, including the United Nations Charter, further threatens the peace, stability, sovereignty, and territorial integrity of Ukraine, and thereby constitutes an unusual and extraordinary threat to the national security and foreign policy of the United States. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A0C15C4CBA240DBA8FE5026DDBEFF37"><enum>(8)</enum><text>On March 11, 2022, President Biden issued Executive Order 14068, which further prohibits certain imports and new investments with respect to continued Russian Federation efforts to undermine the sovereignty and territorial integrity of Ukraine, and takes additional steps with respect to the national emergency declared in Executive Order 14024 of April 15, 2021, and Executive Order 14039 of August 20, 2021, and expanded by Executive Order 14066 of March 8, 2022. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AAE300653FB4EEBB9DAA5E5CC82EF4E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>On April 6, 2022, President Biden issued Executive Order 14071, prohibiting new investment and certain services to the Russian Federation in response to continued Russian Federation aggression, and takes additional steps with respect to the national emergency declared in Executive Order 14024 of April 15, 2021, expanded by Executive Order 14066 of March 8, 2022, and relied on for additional steps taken in Executive Order 14039 of August 20, 2021, and Executive Order 14068 of March 11, 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AE7BE0A22924816BCA40CCAD9165186"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In March 2022, as the Biden Administration continued to increase pressure on Putin’s regime through rollouts of the aforementioned sanctions, the head of the PRC’s banking and insurance regulator said the PRC will not participate in the sanctions regime Western nations imposed on Russia and “will continue to maintain normal economic, trade and financial exchanges” with Russia despite its aggression against Ukraine.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H534C9C0CCCB84163A1433463FBB85667"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Indeed, that same month, according to PRC customs data, Russia bought 9,950 metric tons of alumina from the PRC, which is nearly 10 times more than what it purchased in the same period a year earlier. The PRC’s first-quarter exports of alumina to Russia are nearly six times the volume of all of 2021, suggesting the PRC may find new ways of providing support to Russia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07128A31638D48A2937871E030474DAD"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On June 28, 2022, the U.S. Department of Commerce, Bureau of Industry and Security, added five Chinese companies to the Entity List, in response to their continued support to Russia's military efforts since the imposition of export controls in response to Russia's invasion of Ukraine.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7913606DF5854A79958D5A25F2A527B6"><enum>(13)</enum><text>In December 2022, the PRC’s foreign minister stated his country would <quote>deepen strategic mutual trust and mutually beneficial cooperation</quote> with Russia, and trade between the countries has continued to grow.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3CB0CEB4F394365AA47411BFFEB45CF"><enum>(14)</enum><text>As of February 2023, reports based on customs records indicate Chinese state-owned and private companies have exported parts and equipment to sanctioned Russian entities that could be facilitating Putin’s war. This includes shipments of helicopter equipment, jamming technology, drones, and jet-fighter parts to sanctioned Russian government-owned defense firms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H592C723E7B8944B39E73027161604147" commented="no"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On February 18, 2023, the Secretary of State publicly stated that Chinese companies were already providing non-lethal support to Russia’s war effort and the PRC was considering providing lethal support, including weapons and ammunition. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HFFEBB8DD92D144DCA8B5545791AB0620"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HAA9C0EC064B14767998BF71485512EA5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Russia’s military invasion of Ukraine and the war crimes and human rights violations committed by the Kremlin, Russia’s military, and Russia’s intelligence and security services against the people of Ukraine should be strongly condemned;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H725F579435314184B23F20AD3ECE7B90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any country or entity that provides material support for Russia’s invasion is furthering Russia’s unlawful belligerence and committing of war crimes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89ECA6D7812046B690AB7EBA03A5DF51"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chinese Government officials and individuals and entities associated with People’s Republic of China that assist the Russian Federation, including Russian Government officials or individuals or entities associated with the Russian Federation, by providing material support or in evading sanctions imposed following the Russian Federation’s invasion of Ukraine are, in so doing, supporting the Russian Federation’s unprovoked attack on Ukraine and the Ukrainian people, including alleged war crimes committed by Russian Armed Forces against civilians; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A713B0275A34862BC492FCAF014FF05"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the President should continue to seek unity with European and other key partners and to uphold sanctions that continue to impose costs on Putin’s regime and deplete the Russian Federation’s war chest;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA03AB0C5320D41C4BC309C72EA9E94AE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the President should impose sanctions with respect to those sectors and individuals and entities of the Russian Federation, including Russian Government officials, that are evading sanctions imposed by the United States and allied nations following Russia’s invasion of Ukraine; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86091D3EE2644F3699AB98086ED19939"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the President should encourage other European countries and key partners to enact legislation that is similar to the provisions of this Act.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H992B974E826D45FF8B0971F59D24E27B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sanctions with respect to the transfer of arms and related materiel by China to Russia</header><subsection id="H14A511CF05AE4816ACCDC286B794DD25"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header><paragraph id="HDC038E048379435BACB5C3B94D4027CD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President is authorized to impose on a PRC person one or more of the sanctions described in subsection (b) if the President determines that such person has, on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, knowingly—</text><subparagraph id="H2B9028F4CAB540AB8C5E44656D72E4FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>exported, transferred, or otherwise provided to Russia financial, material, or technological support that contributes materially to the ability of the Government of Russia to undertake military action in Ukraine, such as—</text><clause id="HF819277014614383AB2147B04DD411AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>acquiring chemical, biological, or nuclear weapons or related technologies; </text></clause><clause id="H185CA4BE79604408B7BB376594C747BA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>acquiring ballistic or cruise missile capabilities;</text></clause><clause id="H1AB2BCCD352D4B8A9E24B63911EB5E16"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>acquiring advanced conventional weapons; </text></clause><clause id="H78069581F02242DE8B23C5C21DD389C3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>acquiring significant defense articles, defense services, or defense information (as such terms are defined under the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2751">22 U.S.C. 2751 et seq.</external-xref>)); or</text></clause><clause id="HEA1050A6FE2E41328E5750E4D79B12D1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>acquiring items designated by the President for purposes of the United States Munitions List under section 38(a)(1) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2778">22 U.S.C. 2778(a)(1)</external-xref>); or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3939E6C1DB2A4CA586A4D1FCAECED540"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitated or assisted in the evasion or circumvention of United States sanctions or multilateral sanctions with respect to the Russia.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H027BF4AC8F594DAFB074621EDAF11F96"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability to other PRC persons</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The sanctions described in subsection (b) may also be imposed on any PRC person that—</text><subparagraph id="H67906839A08349F88843CBCBDE2824C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a successor entity to a PRC person described in paragraph (1); or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0C0CEA918684B91B3A845526BF786FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is owned or controlled by, or has acted for or on behalf of, a PRC person described in paragraph (1) and has engaged in a sanctionable activity described in such paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC7E3F9AD1BAB4C82AE2313D1E1B729E6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The sanctions described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="HDC9D43A61354423E9456ABA8752FE69E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall exercise all powers granted by the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) (except that the requirements of section 202 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of the person if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B6E624FCE804D28ABC39C308E05430A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inadmissibility of certain individuals</header><subparagraph id="H0F57A54F07E946D79722E72B6AC8A4A7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visas and admission to the United States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual determined by the President to be a person described in subsection (a) is—</text><clause id="HC1234BEA99CC4060B0642A48A9CCD55E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></clause><clause id="H2EB5E02B2FAC4DA78F63782DB601F039"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="H39D2BA09C00D486CAFF8974A7927A645"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11F37E384FBD4A499D28CADC22B9285F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Current visas revoked</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual determined by the President to be a person described in subsection (a) is subject to the following:</text><clause id="HA49F9C161C8A4CCD90BFC56966F335CA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Revocation of any visa or other entry documentation regardless of when the visa or other entry documentation is or was issued.</text></clause><clause id="H28CE70A9155B4A6FBAF347510DDBDB58"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A revocation under clause (i) shall cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the person’s possession in accordance with section 221(i) of the Immigration and Nationality Act.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H63B7139D8EAE48D5BFBE93A5886564C6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Other sanctions</header><subparagraph id="H880BF78A507A4A939A39AB3011BA8276"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Export-import bank assistance for exports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may direct the Export-Import Bank of the United States not to give approval to the issuance of any guarantee, insurance, extension of credit, or participation in the extension of credit in connection with the export of any goods or services to the person. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD4EC0643C3943D489E6C6F30224D1F5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Loans from united states financial institutions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may prohibit any United States financial institution from making loans or providing credits to the person in any 12-month period unless the person is engaged in activities to relieve human suffering and the loans or credits are provided for such activities. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4EDD0086216840D380117722D4595297"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Loans from international financial institutions</header><text>The President should direct the United States Executive Director to each international financial institution to use the voice and vote of the United States to oppose any loan from the international financial institution that would benefit the person. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06BF96D4CF74433D8C1E5E825CDD020F"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Prohibitions on financial institutions</header><text>The following prohibitions may be imposed against the person if that person is a financial institution: </text><clause id="HD20F41018E654590B150F283CC209D0A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Prohibition on designation as primary dealer</header><text>Neither the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System nor the Federal Reserve Bank of New York may designate, or permit the continuation of any prior designation of, the financial institution as a primary dealer in United States Government debt instruments. </text></clause><clause id="HE32E3CDA064B4CD0BA0D3FBE8932A019"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Prohibition on service as a repository of government funds</header><text>The financial institution may not serve as agent of the United States Government or serve as repository for United States Government funds. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H279BAC72A9054FE0816CC8E0054C4864"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Procurement sanction</header><text>The United States Government may not procure, or enter into any contract for the procurement of, any goods or services from the person. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2904600AF7345A8A85C38FFC9CE1D04"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Foreign exchange</header><text>The President may, pursuant to such regulations as the President may prescribe, prohibit any transactions in foreign exchange that are subject to the jurisdiction of the United States and in which the person has any interest. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD1F3B2F29E74685AF50F7ED2481A530"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Banking transactions</header><text>The President may, pursuant to such regulations as the President may prescribe, prohibit any transfers of credit or payments between financial institutions or by, through, or to any financial institution, to the extent that such transfers or payments are subject to the jurisdiction of the United States and involve any interest of the person. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01B9941B7A3A45D4AD9D10FA59CB5752"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Property transactions</header><text>The President may, pursuant to such regulations as the President may prescribe, prohibit any other person from—</text><clause id="H6CA3A173FB3E40DAB593202D33EBE220"><enum>(i)</enum><text>acquiring, holding, withholding, using, transferring, withdrawing, transporting, importing, or exporting any property that is subject to the jurisdiction of the United States and with respect to which the person has any interest; </text></clause><clause id="HB41E7C5C9A9940B4A95AAC76442CDD41"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>dealing in or exercising any right, power, or privilege with respect to such property; or </text></clause><clause id="HC929C3A212604438BEB87EF82CDA175E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>conducting any transaction involving such property. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF173180262C6466EA9BAD8A1EA845C0F"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Ban on investment in equity or debt of person</header><text>The President may, pursuant to such regulations or guidelines as the President may prescribe, prohibit any United States person from investing in or purchasing significant amounts of equity or debt instruments of the person.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H76F3BFC54B004484BC009D16EBD585FC" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><header>Exclusion of corporate officers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may direct the Secretary of State to deny a visa to, and the Secretary of Homeland Security to exclude from the United States, any alien that the President determines is a corporate officer or principal of, or a shareholder with a controlling interest in, the person.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4936013746044C578A4324C027C32718"><enum>(K)</enum><header>Sanctions on principal executive officers</header><text>The President may impose on the principal executive officer or officers of the person, or on persons performing similar functions and with similar authorities as such officer or officers, any of the sanctions under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H135B748F64C7465A91BCD03CD94B813E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><paragraph id="H7566492D550B42A082FB3298C364302D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Exception for intelligence activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions under this section shall not apply to any activity subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>) or any authorized intelligence activities of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB61910F8A6B40D582B8E3781C8AC55D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception to comply with international obligations and for law enforcement activities</header><text>Sanctions under subsection (b)(2) shall not apply with respect to an alien if admitting or paroling the alien into the United States is necessary—</text><subparagraph id="HF73E5DBEF0094F39AAE1E83A7B82EF0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A13F77155C34275809A970574B2063D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to carry out or assist law enforcement activity in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0735A9753AF3497EA97CF6354D919F0C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception relating to importation of goods</header><subparagraph id="HA7B87E308CD8498A9E50DDEA868FB825"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The authority to block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property under subsection (b)(1) shall not include the authority to impose sanctions on the importation of goods.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE3D102DED07483893A56A0085697DF3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Good defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph, the term <quote>good</quote> means any article, natural or man-made substance, material, supply or manufactured product, including inspection and test equipment and excluding technical data. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H35E25C2650A446449E94E739C9BDA7EB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may waive the application of sanctions under subsection (b) with respect to a PRC person described in subsection (a) if the President determines that such a waiver is in the national interest of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB5F858610D4645C3B4A48F1B0AD6B018"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Implementation; penalties</header><paragraph id="H878BE5E2390948AF82E542FD24C6F2F7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The President may exercise all authorities provided under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to carry out the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5B04F27B8004735BC9BC743D4436C49"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>The penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) may apply to a person that violates, attempts to violate, or conspires to violate, or causes a violation of, subsection (a) of this section, or an order or regulation prescribed under either such subsection, to the same extent that such penalties apply to a person that commits an unlawful act described in section 206(a) of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H62E864D9FD9C4C8787EC9EC7A7CC04AD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF5EAAC1F09764B20ACE052051A830E02"><enum>(1)</enum><header>China</header><text>The term <quote>China</quote> means the People’s Republic of China. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84AE112DD9DF45E7A45377B57E10A8EC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Financial, material, or technological support</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>financial, material, or technological support</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 542.304 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations (or any corresponding similar regulation or ruling). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H043BB30069174CF29E611A3F9839610A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>PRC person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>PRC person</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="HDB245621A66248E1B80678A4D5CB0FD8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means—</text><clause id="HC5A98C7B2BA34123A626C89862C1DA2E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any citizen or national of China; or</text></clause><clause id="HE7518CFEB4E14D3498B7FBCAF8D92B02"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any entity organized under the laws of China or any jurisdiction within China; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1140B84640D64580B2A452A284C3215C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes the Government of China, the Chinese Communist Party, and any Chinese State-owned enterprise.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBCD53A1BE1347829FD3341A0550918F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>International financial institution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>international financial institution</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 1701(c) of the International Financial Institutions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/262r">22 U.S.C. 262r(c)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39C1570E7E5646B2BF6C459A3658CD62"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Russia</header><text>The term <quote>Russia</quote> means the Russian Federation. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AC127ABB34441B8A9870C118465FA8C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>United states person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HBAAA35BA9F0447ED8059EC5C1741FA3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97C3157CD6634AD7B712F22A0EB9CE1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC7BE328BB2B04E3FAF4277084321F20D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The provisions of this Act shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act, and such provisions, including any sanctions or penalties imposed under this Act, shall terminate on the earlier of—</text><paragraph id="H57B69608388A401AB0EFE42A6EEF4F1C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which the President determines the conflict in Ukraine has ended; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DB450083C41454CAD3E424A5F9D867A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date that is 2 years after such date of enactment.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

