<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H778602D7722747F6BA1B0DD0C519C71B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>107 HR 5839 IH: Maritime Border Security Technology Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5839</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230929">September 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000610">Ms. Plaskett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000307">Mr. James</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Homeland Security to assess technology needs along the maritime border and develop a strategy to address such needs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H62E9A0A83D6D4328AA98C1A48FD8A3A7" style="OLC"><section id="H7378280707214805A61656D7D637C894" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Maritime Border Security Technology Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE058A3509D8048E8AE23993D9BC16D6F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Maritime border security technology needs analysis and updates</header><subsection id="HACB9472254124B9C99E54974452009EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Technology needs analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a technology needs analysis for operational and border security technology along the maritime border.</text></subsection><subsection id="H193E124AF16443F68745CEE27B7EBB9F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The analysis required under subsection (a) shall include an assessment of—</text><paragraph id="HCB0D6105911C491789A4D7644C495591"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the operational and border security technology needs along the maritime border—</text><subparagraph id="H6AB84A6B36C8456399FB6D7BE3C94B94"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to prevent terrorists and instruments of terror from entering the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77FA2880CE75430AB015FE3B8E767430"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to combat and reduce criminal activity related to the maritime border, including—</text><clause id="H22074BE7B8C648818541FD75A61BD677"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the transport of illegal goods, such as illicit drugs; and</text></clause><clause id="H576666BC98564E7CA8111E01ED307AE3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>human smuggling and human trafficking;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17976DE2A4744A1B887572D9A68138B0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to enhance maritime domain awareness;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB87B4A021F4940959C2539103D773B6F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to enhance maritime detection and interdiction capabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA69B1BD773C94A95ACBA4FC8897A5FC1"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to enhance presence in the maritime domain; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4F9C7D3069F44E8A23946B70856C4C5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to facilitate the flow of legal trade across the maritime border;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6018E83367744799B3ABD60AD4D4A3F7"><enum>(G)</enum><text>to strengthen the security of maritime critical infrastructure and counter evolving maritime cybersecurity risks; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62FC68242CCA4EEDAF9183D8F7CA8829"><enum>(H)</enum><text>to preserve and uphold United States prosperity and economic security by safeguarding the domestic maritime transportation system and maritime resources;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1C7B093EEDC4B7796ABC05180263B70"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recent technological advancements in—</text><subparagraph id="H2E6522A3CC554432A2DD4FC787AEBCB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>manned aircraft sensor, communication, and common operating picture technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4ECFBEA976604272AEBB58CAA49FA8AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>unmanned aircraft systems, sensors, and related technology with maritime surveillance capability, including counter-UAS systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1B1329873DB4E4AB159BFE08CF69C27"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">unmanned maritime vessels with surface and subsurface surveillance, detection, and tracking capabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B5C84E7A09F47FEA0380CFA2CB9D058"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maritime surveillance and detection sensing capabilities for both emitting and non-emitting threat vessels;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92C73D4C13EC44B1BC1BC1E4122AAC64"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coastal radar surveillance systems; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H382ECD127CC545CE9F181095CC622E51"><enum>(F)</enum><text>nonintrusive inspection technology, including non-X-ray devices and other advanced detection technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08ED03761DA5426E968BCDA1A220D361"><enum>(G)</enum><text>maritime signals intelligence capabilities; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H614BA5B9572448439C453C1FC60AB267" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">voice and data communications, command and control capabilities, and information management and sharing capabilities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63D2E8745BB646D3AA7A466DE8B3AD42"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maritime port and waterway infrastructure systems to counter physical and cyber threats; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H68873D35F8E24A5E808B36D91E61B6E7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any other technological advancements that the Secretary determines to be critical to the Department’s mission along the maritime border;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFE4B3302FD14384954B676DEB0F854D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>whether the use of the technological advances described in paragraphs (2) and (3) will—</text><subparagraph id="HA20E7A124F1944B9AB5CB6BD75F65FC6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve maritime border security and establish persistent wide area maritime surveillance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E7B8E112E0D4647954A26544E1BE037"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improve the capability of the Department to accomplish its mission along the maritime border;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3649BA3D9E0F45C9826FB83326149E79"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce operational and security gaps along the maritime border; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4498BBA2A2D24393AE887399088B68D3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>enhance the safety of any officer or agent of the Department or any other Federal agency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB90CFA31E6E40B291BDD9A5B866CC91"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve deployment of high demand resources and improve data sharing between technology systems and the Homeland Security Enterprise;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3276E72AEAAA42A59A7DF5A0C117F426"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Department’s ongoing maritime border security technology development efforts, including efforts by—</text><subparagraph id="H4A7C89FC31DE4EBDA83D01CF43712C27"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the U.S. Coast Guard;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FD7DEC2E71F4188A43D729D8BEC265F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>U.S. Customs and Border Protection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA339708432094B1AA11CAD3ED58E1F8F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Science and Technology Directorate of the Department; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30D0B4F74F7E4C3EBC40D424AE17CB1F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the technology assessment office of any other operational component of the Department;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0F2956528D54562BCE5E16509A81960"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any other technological needs or factors, including maritime border security and shoreside infrastructure, that the Secretary determines should be considered; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB9DFA6D06EB4274B1DF1213557DF91B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>currently deployed technology or new technology that would improve the Department’s ability—</text><subparagraph id="H51F2CBCB9F1D4FD59B21F3C74A122CC2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to reasonably achieve operational control and situational awareness along the maritime border; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE9334F256D54B15BB9B93AF8C97837D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to collect metrics for securing the maritime border, as required under subsection (d) of section 1092 of division A of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/223">6 U.S.C. 223</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8847897E7B5949E88B68E5A1B06E89FF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Updates</header><paragraph id="HBE177B86FEC145C7AF0D87F90EB8BD38"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than two years after the submission of the analysis required under subsection (a) and biannually thereafter for the following four years, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees an update to such analysis.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3E4BEF0439443D899E4461C849C8A9A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each update required under paragraph (1) shall include a plan for utilizing the resources of the Department to satisfy operational and border security technology needs identified pursuant to subsection (b), including developing or acquiring technologies not currently in use by the Department that would allow the Department to bridge existing operational and border security needs along the maritime border.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF50939C31A2B4B9787FD22542FBB2198"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Items To be considered</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In compiling the operational and border security technology needs analysis and updates required under this section, the Secretary shall consider and examine—</text><paragraph id="H476D3EAD82E74C1F994B3983534340F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>technology that is deployed and is sufficient for the Department’s use along the maritime border;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD75CB6A81C1844E79FDDE0CB102DB9FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>technology that is deployed, but is insufficient for the Department’s use along the maritime border;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA52587877044BF5820FA858FA7502D0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>technology that is not deployed, but is necessary for the Department’s use along the maritime border;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD75C2F240AB84CFDA02F6B30261A2A23" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>current formal departmental requirements examining maritime border security threats and challenges faced by any component of the Department;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20FED474C60644C48106EF4A66D3B309"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">trends and forecasts regarding migration and the transport of illegal goods, such as illicit drugs, across the maritime border;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AED4990CEB446D09D5A9875B36E7D4B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the impact on projected staffing and deployment needs for the Department, including staffing needs that may be fulfilled through the use of technology;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D4C03FCDCE34C129505D038732B5EAD"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the needs and challenges faced by employees of the Department who are deployed along the maritime border;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B7941F3432E4F6EAE30943F0FE57F45"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the needs to improve cooperation among Federal, State, territorial, Tribal, local, and appropriate international law enforcement entities to enhance security along the maritime border;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF972A42A6AFD49B3980F916DB946A25E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the impact of any natural disaster or ongoing public health emergency that impacts Department operations along the maritime border; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8C7F62EB4514E829EFF539732AEC9C1"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the ability of, and the needs for, the Department to assist with search and rescue efforts for individuals or groups that may be in physical danger or in need of medical assistance along the maritime border.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H883118C8A9584EDABC6A23A178E0F677"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Classified form</header><text>To the extent possible, the Secretary shall submit the technology needs analysis and updates required under this section in unclassified form, but may submit such documents, or portions of such documents, in classified form if the Secretary determines such is appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC75817DBD1DE45C68D9CBD50387E0895"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H052081CE80724DAE8E1A6C5476C0F994"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H87CDFFC62CC54A0D819AFD025DC90655"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC34B0D4212E74E98B17643919F20E65E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4986AB7BDD6482281E9A441FCE73CC3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Government Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA689A08BAC8C4FD7B102A42E4325F208"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B58E353E852424A8EEAF2891437B761"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Counter-UAS system</header><text>The term <quote>counter-UAS system</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 44801 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H252F8122BF0A4AC5830BC8C0C1D8AF4E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>critical infrastructure</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 1016(e) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/56">Public Law 107–56</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C73AF9D5DA24DB2BF7301DDC3BAA859"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Cybersecurity risk</header><text>The term <quote>cybersecurity risk</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2200 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/650">6 U.S.C. 650</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33BEACEF4DE347A9A7B4CBCEFF3F9E5D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Homeland Security Enterprise</header><text>The term <quote>Homeland Security Enterprise</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2200 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/650">6 U.S.C. 650</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7A6465D1F05496C99BFEB0B939AFD7F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <quote>Department</quote> means the Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44332E63D3A2460AAD0A2BCF8A92DEC9"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Maritime border</header><text>The term <quote>maritime border</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H9C783402734E460EBECF3E4328C51609"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the coastal areas of the United States, including California, Florida, Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, Washington, the Great Lakes, Maine, and the Gulf Coast;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51C5873B145B4A3D9645B78615E2ECDB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the maritime approaches to the areas described in subparagraph (A), including, if applicable, the waters extending from the United States territorial sea baseline to the outer edge of the 200 nautical mile Exclusive Economic Zone;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD9AAD32CE7647C0A8550CEA5214D64B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the ports of entry along the areas described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7E98869C96C44E583077819E8398AF6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the transit zone.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H19EEACE2B5CF47A890EE2A7283A8FD5D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Persistent wide area maritime surveillance (pwams)</header><text>The term <quote>persistent wide area maritime surveillance</quote> means a system of sensors that provide surveillance and detection to aid in the classification and identification of surface and subsurface vessels of diverse sizes out to 200 nautical miles from shore to prevent terrorism, enhance security, secure the United States border, and enforce immigration laws.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4F9BABA138C4F30A290B436AA48FDD3"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA36CB5459F8A4AB1A8894DB1DF64E77A"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Transit zone</header><text>The term <quote>transit zone</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 1092(a)(8) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/223">6 U.S.C. 223(a)(8)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41523CC1496B49989E4B0EA99E97AE0E"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Unmanned aircraft system</header><text>The term <quote>unmanned aircraft system</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 44801 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

