<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0ADFAB22B92540FB9FBE725D5A54BE66" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 636 IH: Forest Litigation Reform Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 636</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230130">January 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an arbitration process pilot program as an alternative dispute resolution process for certain objections or protests to qualified forest management activities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H72ECB2AD63724FA39BD45D6769E08970" style="OLC"><section id="H09F34AE7A1DD45A9A657C62642E47C35" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Forest Litigation Reform Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5AD675F66D27468FB56D666D8D0903EE"><enum>2.</enum><header>No attorney fees for forest management activity challenges</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 1304 of title 31, United States Code, no award may be made under section 2412 of title 28, United States Code, and no amounts may be obligated or expended from the Claims and Judgment Fund of the United States Treasury to pay any fees or other expenses under such sections to any plaintiff related to an action challenging a qualified forest management activity.</text></section><section id="H34D72862E0294D6A9DC748C95034EAE9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Injunctive relief</header><subsection id="H2F02C4D1A0A3492995AE44020F17839C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Balancing short- and long-Term effects of forest management activities in considering injunctive relief</header><text>As part of its weighing the equities while considering any request for an injunction that applies to any agency action as part of a qualified forest management activity, the court reviewing the agency action shall balance the impact to the ecosystem likely affected by the forest management activity of—</text><paragraph id="HE21C85354E29443DAF6A9014BB521444"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the short- and long-term effects of undertaking the agency action; against</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEA0841F7D234BEBB1831967EEB1F221"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the short- and long-term effects of not undertaking the action.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE7A8F02936034E208FEFD67A65D9DE20"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Time limitations for injunctive relief</header><paragraph id="H4B62400FE4B440C08A555F4DCF72C296"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), the length of any preliminary injunctive relief and stays pending appeal that applies to any agency action as part of a forest management activity, shall not exceed 60 days.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25CB9F95C50C41599999A6E9003A97FC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Renewal</header><subparagraph id="HBF935EACEADF4E2EB1CD32575A846474"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A court of competent jurisdiction may issue one or more renewals of any preliminary injunction, or stay pending appeal, granted under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H098EC751D7F547AEAEF34CA0D6C01FA0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>In each renewal of an injunction in an action, the parties to the action shall present the court with updated information on the status of the authorized forest management activity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1AF4A84227B54ABE94E2DBB3D7B0813B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Use of arbitration instead of litigation to address challenges to forest management activities</header><subsection id="HAC1185DDB2744C6CA9BACB1DE85C13F1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Discretionary arbitration process pilot program</header><paragraph id="H17284A18FE9B4067BA2D309485CED6DD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture, with respect to National Forest System lands, and the Secretary of the Interior, with respect to public lands, shall each establish a discretionary arbitration pilot program as an alternative dispute resolution process for the activities described in paragraph (2). Such arbitration pilot program shall take place in lieu of judicial review for the activities described in paragraph (2). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H694290E472674DC7B7C378755E6A1386"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Activities described</header><text>The Secretary concerned, at the sole discretion of the Secretary, may designate objections or protests to qualified forest management activities for arbitration under the arbitration pilot program established under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H724BA0E8A80847A385F0C10BEB05CDC1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Maximum amount of arbitrations</header><subparagraph id="HF182A5B0B73A4D0C9B0C4B2278979EAD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Under the arbitration pilot program, the Secretary concerned may not arbitrate more than 10 objections or protests to qualified forest management activities in a fiscal year in—</text><clause id="H731881C9913946CBA42ED1E91A8F2EC9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each Forest Service Region; and</text></clause><clause id="H450165DA6D034FD79BB58BBB0E6FBC55"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each State Region of the Bureau of Land Management.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00628C135B1442D1A02E4F87C07DEF77"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Not subject to judicial review</header><text>A determination made by the Secretary concerned that an objection or protest to a qualified forest management activity is an activity described under paragraph (2) shall not be subject to judicial review. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA085215E36114E12AB14C24BECD6E78B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Determining amount of arbitrations</header><text>An objection or protest to a qualified forest management activity shall not be counted towards the limitation on number of arbitrations under paragraph (3) unless—</text><subparagraph id="HD8872E60872C46DB8B2C1AE458B771F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>on the date such objection or protest is designated for arbitration, the qualified forest management activity for which such objection or protest is filed has not been the subject of arbitration proceedings under the pilot program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2651CBBDBEAF4B21A5B0AF89D29C36E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the arbitration proceeding has commenced with respect to such objection or protest.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A37BB13515644A0B73E8C82397BA322"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Termination</header><subparagraph id="HD34153CB6CA54557B80E9E55B588947E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The pilot programs established pursuant to paragraph (1) shall terminate on the date that is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9642B8DE39847BB868FAA4EC01FC43D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Activity in arbitration</header><text>An objection or protest to a qualified forest management activity that has commenced but has not completed arbitration on the date of termination under subparagraph (A) shall continue until such arbitration is completed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCA879DF3BCB94AF98DEECCE9F26DD523"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Intervening parties</header><paragraph id="H8EE7CD98104148F293DF627801A852E0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Any person that submitted a public comment on the qualified forest management activity that is subject to arbitration may intervene in the arbitration—</text><subparagraph id="HB009794E03374413BFFF2F9DFA928ECE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by endorsing—</text><clause id="HF8D0E086314C48DA844EF49D6C06B27A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the qualified forest management activity; or</text></clause><clause id="HF92679D69879419AB2E54C51124BD44E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the modification proposal submitted under subparagraph (B); or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1C200876DF946A0ACC4AF44F315403E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by submitting a proposal to further modify the qualified forest management activity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E9DE161825F499D8AF46ACFDBCE61B1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for submission</header><text>With respect to an objection or protest that is designated for arbitration under this subsection (a), a request to intervene in an arbitration must be submitted not later than the date that is 30 days after the date on which such objection or protest was designated for arbitration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC496EEDC6235457AAC74ABE75F8D72DF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Multiple parties</header><text>Multiple intervening parties may submit a joint proposal so long as each intervening party meets the eligibility requirements of paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8BD80DEAD2474233BC6ADFD9A8A31D98"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appointment of arbitrator</header><paragraph id="HC45B316239D2449EB0E2DAB89391FFB2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior shall jointly develop and publish a list of not fewer than 20 individuals eligible to serve as arbitrators for the pilot programs under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF53A6ABBBE5341B4926A18767A557C9A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>In order to be eligible to serve as an arbitrator under this subsection, an individual shall be, on the date of the appointment of such arbitrator—</text><subparagraph id="H84D4DC5E239440348C8183238B4D8D63"><enum>(A)</enum><text>certified by the American Arbitration Association; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7DF1F307B64B451BBFDDB3921B2508A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not a registered lobbyist.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H29DF07EEF54E4ED7966A14C21A95BAFF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Selection of arbitrator</header><subparagraph id="H2F2CEBA3EDD5420496216D82536190DB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each arbitration commenced under this section, the Secretary concerned and each applicable objector or protestor shall agree, not later than 14 days after the agreement process is initiated, on a mutually acceptable arbitrator from the list published under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE46F016055BC4B49A2B808451AAA6987"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Appointment after 14 days</header><text>In the case of an agreement with respect to a mutually acceptable arbitrator not being reached within the 14-day limit described in subparagraph (A), the Secretary concerned shall appoint an arbitrator from the list published under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H61412602ABBA4FF3816389B8B3961AB0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection of proposals</header><paragraph id="HABE6C68B6B0445698F469FDE1D941B7A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The arbitrator appointed under subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="H225D471520E541F0A9AABE1304A5708F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may not modify any of the proposals submitted with the objection, protest, or request to intervene; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD00D1D486E0B432086A215493A72EACC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall select to be conducted—</text><clause id="HAC6E447B18734B9980BC84CCB0307AFF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the qualified forest management activity, as approved by the Secretary; or</text></clause><clause id="H5B4D19085F49482B838A7E690303C946"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a proposal submitted by an objector or an intervening party.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC121E10DE71D4B9DACA3619716EBCF85"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text>An arbitrator shall, when selecting a proposal, consider—</text><subparagraph id="H35BE5462BB2741C9AB6F77017C419494"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether the proposal is consistent with the applicable forest plan, laws, and regulations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BE1251204B941618A7328309D2C7E09"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether the proposal can be carried out by the Secretary concerned; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC67A8F89DD94EF28EFCEC52DE353C90"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the effect of each proposal on—</text><clause id="H8B4B99FCDDDB4B23AEE076FA5A638D8A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>forest health;</text></clause><clause id="H79CD59EDB42B47089F926D1A5A1A35EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>potential losses of life and property;</text></clause><clause id="HF06E6743BA204561BF2C13C882E5B16D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>habitat diversity;</text></clause><clause id="H3B240E56CDBC46F181C0B9F1298A9DF8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>wildfire potential;</text></clause><clause id="H03ADC9464BCD4FC6877DEE5E27AAA52F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>insect and disease potential;</text></clause><clause id="H81E40E8A8EB44670B76939CC4C834A04"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>timber production; and</text></clause><clause id="H4E3DB07A98184B03A729315F3618F758"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the implications of a resulting decline in forest health, loss of habitat diversity, wildfire, or insect or disease infestation, given fire and insect and disease historic cycles, on—</text><subclause id="H50E9F7A03A9D4CED8ADC605AD6233B7D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>potential losses of life and property;</text></subclause><subclause id="H81BED150209F41F8A9022AE097D311B5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>domestic water costs;</text></subclause><subclause id="H65A90823A97744C39642C776E2839833"><enum>(III)</enum><text>wildlife habitat loss; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H369478258799493AA5C34360CE6ED0FB"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>other economic and social factors.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB26C1429E47F41DCB77710210259BB26"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effect of decision</header><text>The decision of an arbitrator with respect to the qualified forest management activity shall—</text><paragraph id="HA8EFD43083D14E4EBF522571DB9A8D46"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not be considered a major Federal action;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4916285FC51B4FC99E2F56DCE5C4FF90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be binding; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5330E1F7EA974075AA909948AFA5508F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not be subject to judicial review, except as provided in section 10(a) of title 9, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H50C9CC52CC59483781A2921178D7A7CE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Deadline for completion</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which the arbitration is filed with respect to the qualified forest management activity, the arbitration process shall be completed.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6B557B1C7EEF4EE5A52C2D457A3AC1AF"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H84C79D83E793428A87530CCB0D7CF95B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Collaborative process</header><text>The term <term>collaborative process</term> means a process relating to the management of National Forest System lands or public lands by which a project or forest management activity is developed and implemented by the Secretary concerned through collaboration with multiple interested persons representing diverse interests.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D9F29E6F8D2495098A921FAD5A7192F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Community wildfire protection plan</header><text>The term <term>community wildfire protection plan</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6511">16 U.S.C. 6511</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B78E6BB63E04FD8BE256C1D5E4BA835"><enum>(3)</enum><header>National forest system</header><text>The term <term>National Forest System</term> has the meaning given that term in section 11(a) of the Forest and Rangeland Renewable Resources Planning Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1609">16 U.S.C. 1609(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F1A8D8E0A6B4678A3910361A6FF4843"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public lands</header><text>The term <term>public lands</term> has the meaning given that term in section 103 of the Federal Land Policy and Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1702">43 U.S.C. 1702</external-xref>), except that the term includes Coos Bay Wagon Road Grant lands and Oregon and California Railroad Grant lands.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B73708E34AF4F31AFB01848F3CD97EB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Qualified forest management activity</header><text>The term <term>qualified forest management activity</term> means any forest management activity that—</text><subparagraph id="H56700E23EF024840A2AE2F7102BE4F1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>will occur on lands identified as the Secretary concerned as suitable for timber production; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9D1F87D60204D5C843F8FD57419F8E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>meets at least one of the following conditions:</text><clause id="H89819F380B0F4231879ADCCF9828F468"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The forest management activity will occur on lands designated by the Secretary (or designee thereof) pursuant to section 602(b) of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591a">16 U.S.C. 6591a(b)</external-xref>), notwithstanding whether such forest management activity is initiated prior to the date of enactment of this Act.</text></clause><clause id="H2F76B881E4744B929A36C3D162EE3CA5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The forest management activity is developed through a collaborative process.</text></clause><clause id="HCCE7ED0AAB114DB9A990EFA303BD375C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The forest management activity is proposed by a resource advisory committee.</text></clause><clause id="H1A521BDBFFCE46ABBDEF895DC71D5B3F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The forest management activity is covered by a community wildfire protection plan.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7ABA87EB6EA94E2A91D71FE8E00CEC7D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Resource advisory committee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>resource advisory committee</term> has the meaning given that term in section 201 of the Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7121">16 U.S.C. 7121</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

