<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H72A3C3FC4A124B18956FA436304A93B7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2585 IH: Hawaii Air Tour Management Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2585</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to establish an air tour management plan for certain areas of Hawaii, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0BBF1926C8A24E60BCAFD619A3D2A4F6" style="OLC"><section id="H327B02BD36C6481CAA7E491A85337A55" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hawaii Air Tour Management Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H073FE2644CA245A0BF415F80D7C16937"><enum>2.</enum><header>Air tour management plan for certain areas of Hawaii</header><subsection id="HC6FD51AAFD72430DA18A9A449A753F57"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Air tour management plan</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E1E9F0E19FF45B88A49FD3A04D40D26"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 40128 of title 49, United States Code, subject to paragraph (2), not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, in consultation with the Governor of Hawaii, shall establish an air tour management plan for any area within the State of Hawaii that is not located within the National Park System.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H101F825AC59B4D2A8E3708D6C5E9C4FA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall enter into an agreement with the Governor of Hawaii to establish the contents of the plan required by paragraph (1), the procedure for establishing such plan (including with respect to any amendments to the plan), and the responsibilities of each party to such agreement in carrying out the plan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4BBCFE4007984DE49853FDACB1130433"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Interim authority</header><text>Until the date on which the air tour management plan is established under subsection (a), the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration may grant an air tour operator operating in an area within the State of Hawaii that is not located within the National Park System interim operating authority for that area.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE1C3657328CC4C739A74DCFFAB70E416" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Non-Application of the APA</header><text>The provisions of subchapter II of chapter 5, and chapter 7, of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Administrative Procedure Act</quote>) shall not apply to the establishment of an air tour management plan under this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

