<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE23D4DDCF3ED46EC8858A67FF31F16A7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5727 IH: National Instant Criminal Background Check System (NICS) Data Integrity Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5727</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the search and retention of certain records with respect to conducting criminal background checks, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCDFF103D8564494888580F9FACB7AB60" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB9CD1F21CF55479BBD872B9387D997F8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Instant Criminal Background Check System (NICS) Data Integrity Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB5660466ED5245FC8E3899BEDAE80AB8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Search of National Data Exchange</header> <subsection id="HE7D39850F1A9469DB5E233C316CF53CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Retention of Background Check Records</header><text>Section 103 of the Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40901">34 U.S.C. 40901</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H353E7EE029D14AE6824EF51D6B9B6238"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (h) through (k) as subsections (i) through (l), respectively; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H278CB877991A42D08FDA46C6AF11D5B7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (g), in the last sentence, by striking <quote>subsection (k)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (l)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H92A487745EB34887BC9D7838A077FAAE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (g) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3810566ADC6B4FC790F20A959F2263EA"> <subsection id="H108E8B7AC5974B228456338CB94BD281"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Record Retention</header> <paragraph id="HC31B8F0EE31049A89137CDA26815A4E9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deadline for Retention</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the system shall retain records related to a transfer or potential transfer of a firearm to a person who is the subject of a call to the system pursuant to subsection (s) or (t) of section 922 of title 18, United States Code, for as long as necessary to determine whether receipt of a firearm by the person would violate subsection (g) or (n) of such section or State law. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA8B2FA1B06E94A5DB3983F8A0C55D3AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice of Retention</header><text>If the system has not determined whether receipt of a firearm by a person would violate subsection (g) or (n) of section 922 of title 18, United States Code, or State law within 30 days after a call to the system with respect to the person, the system shall notify the person in writing (or by electronic mail if the person has consented to the use of electronic mail) that—</text> <subparagraph id="H42A54F4300204CC0A46C7AAC5392376D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the system may retain records relating to the person and the transfer of a firearm until the system determines that receipt of such firearm by the person does not violate subsection (g) or (n) of section 922 of title 18, United States Code, or State law; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H20A84C46B53943DB91D0B6EDE3007874"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the person may submit to the Attorney General information to correct, clarify, or supplement records (with respect to the person) retained by the system in accordance with this section and any regulation established by the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDC56C82C63AD4102894EBB7FD963B07D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Search of National Data Exchange</header><text>Section 103(e)(1) of the Brady Handgun Violence Prevention Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40901">34 U.S.C. 40901(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAE21C46746F6482C939702391BEC3E59"> 
<subparagraph id="HA02634713C7C43318B8D241FD0B55D87"><enum>(L)</enum><header>Search of National Data Exchange Database</header><text>When determining whether receipt of a firearm by a person would violate subsection (g) or (n) of section 922 of title 18, United States Code, the system established under this section shall search databases containing relevant information, including—</text> <clause id="H149C03A3418F4F71BBB875AF8BD2E7FD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the National Data Exchange;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8EF7BB64877643A5A40190FB14D4C78F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Interstate Identification Index System (as defined in article I of the National Crime Prevention and Privacy Compact, set forth in section 217 of the Crime Identification Technology Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/40316">34 U.S.C. 40316</external-xref>));</text></clause> <clause id="HC791DF4DB5B54716A69E61A5280FA4FF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the National Crime Information Center databases;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H31013E46DF1E44DDBD507E0426B79E65"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the database created for use by the National Instant Criminal Background Check System and that contains descriptive information on persons determined to be disqualified from possessing a firearm based upon State or Federal law (commonly known as the <quote>NICS Index</quote>); and</text></clause> <clause id="H8D1D9EF193E74961A4ABA4723B307143"><enum>(v)</enum><text>any other database determined by the Attorney General to be relevant to conducting a background search.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

