<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA7C80CAC8CED409180DFE5A60C241FB4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2483 IH: School Security Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2483</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230406">April 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001051">Mr. Carter of Texas</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 to strengthen school security.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H19D39FD0B0D84EBCB3E111C136D6F9D5" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HBE78C6D0486D4619871038C81D78E073"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>School Security Enhancement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H555EF6F2BB5A4532A0FE26BDF1146558"><enum>2.</enum><header>School security</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4104 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7114">20 U.S.C. 7114</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H2E6E7209FD99445E881D8123D1351586"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(3)(B)—</text> <subparagraph id="H314B1E641E014A4E986271FC2648A857"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7DE6578AB57F49E49897935B33043133"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (iv) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF342E09DA6C543E1A153816FCBAB23C7"> <clause id="HB4DAEA9C61E043C79813F6AEB0813104"><enum>(v)</enum><text>improving school conditions for student learning, by enabling local educational agencies to use funds available under subsection (a)(3) for the purpose of planning and designing school buildings and facilities, installing infrastructure, and implementing technology or other measures, that strengthen security on school premises, which may include—</text>
<subclause id="HEA650433E18F4A3697CD70DDAFACDA9E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>controlling access to school premises or facilities, through the use of metal detectors, or other measures, or technology, with evidence-based effectiveness (to the extent the State involved determines that such evidence is reasonably available), in accordance with the needs of the school;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H83FC38E537B74E878D6313B7560AB3B8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>implementing any technology or measure, or installing any infrastructure, to cover and conceal students within the school during crisis situations;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H169902221E0543B3B78F4F4B5809F248"><enum>(III)</enum><text>implementing technology to provide notification to relevant law enforcement and first responders during such a situation;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H7AB4A466381E408DA96AD512830D1A21"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>implementing any technology or measure, including hiring school security officers, or installing any infrastructure, with evidence-based effectiveness (to the extent the State involved determines that such evidence is reasonably available) to increase the safety of school students and staff;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H5D16999F65F34801A61FB41DD3CF1C6F"><enum>(V)</enum><text>implementing any technology or measure, or installing any infrastructure, for school safety reinforcement, including bullet-resistant doors and windows; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H717234B851DD424DA841331DECF6AB9E"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>implementing any technology or system that would reduce the time needed to disseminate official information to parents regarding the safety of their children during and immediately following a crisis; and</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF121D6CF41444438B8C55AE8A4001E8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H455B311ECDB74272A80CC6F3FA5854B3"> <subsection id="H18E5910DF1CA4CA0AE767C5C42795A72"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header> <paragraph id="H5D0DD20C6784449D8286B6FFE15DE8FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>No funds to provide firearms or training</header><text>No amounts provided as a grant under this part may be used for the provision to any person of a firearm or training in the use of a firearm.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H59D9B43D698A4CBB89C4D493DF084EF3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>No effect on other laws</header><text>Nothing in this part may be construed to preclude or contradict any other provision of law authorizing the provision of firearms or training in the use of firearms.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

