<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H749054B8F7364D81BD8A1E24DA08F115" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3258 IH: Targeting Resources for Equitable Access to Treatment for Long COVID Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3258</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Vel&#225;zquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Health and Human Services to award grants to eligible entities for creating or enhancing capacity to treat patients with Long COVID through a multidisciplinary approach.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB06DFE8EB4204FB3AB7FE82AB472790B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HFECDA2DE74BC4A5BB710234470F107C6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Targeting Resources for Equitable Access to Treatment for Long COVID Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TREAT Long COVID Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H808528C1F262483E9C987EF0E7B8C09B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program to support multidisciplinary Long COVID clinics</header> <subsection id="HFEB69EC9D582476E8DAF42F845F44F52"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall award grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities for the purpose of creating or enhancing capacity to treat patients with Long COVID (also referred to as Post-Acute Sequelae of COVID–19 and post-COVID conditions) and its associated conditions through a multidisciplinary approach.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H476FBB5171794670A1D90908887AC905"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall use the grant, for the purpose described in subsection (a), to—</text> <paragraph id="H9AB9D00119E245B3AFD7D7764D6BE9F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>enhance the capacity of one or more existing multidisciplinary Long COVID clinics to serve the Long COVID population; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H89BD9F1CE753499C9C582015CD9D7377"><enum>(2)</enum><text>create one or more multidisciplinary clinics to address the physical and mental health needs of Long COVID patients.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCBF394A79E4345808F184E2E937811F7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall be a health care provider, Federally qualified health center (as defined in section 1861(aa) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(aa)</external-xref>)), rural health clinic, urban Indian health center, or State or local public health department, that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H108427B6B5DF454C841756676E554C63"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HB84DDA88657D46BEABEA26F3EBF6D2F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>operates an existing multidisciplinary Long COVID clinic or other specialized Long COVID program; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAD69B6DA20D54B7C9D93C49E885422A5" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrates an intent to create a multidisciplinary Long COVID clinic or other specialized Long COVID program; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFCD7890FEB734AC9A01E3FA1ADB44F84"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submits to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information and assurances as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H799C3855405C4A18A8C9C5FEC09BB8E4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Equitable access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to ensure equitable access treatment—</text> 
<paragraph id="H89E29D6E823344B8A29ABE57D3DACD8A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no grantee under this section shall deny access to treatment with respect to Long COVID based on insurance coverage, date or method of diagnosis, preexisting conditions, or previous hospitalization;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29A6DD28AB034435B9D1066A0E60C9C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a grantee under this section shall with respect to Long COVID—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC0555A05A1544A008A80DA7C8426E417"><enum>(A)</enum><text>offer equity-centered resources, information, and training to safety net health systems; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H57BD00ACA1554B43A4A31D395D806D7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disseminate best practices and treatment approaches that enhance access to high-quality care to everyone where they live; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H99AA3781605943B69741E3E4711E006B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>treatment for Long COVID shall be included as a COVID–19 treatment, consistent with the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/2">Public Law 117–2</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE2A05666479948F99588B9480FDCB058"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>The amount of a grant awarded under this section shall not exceed $2,000,000.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4FBF0A26EFA4453781484AA7882D1250"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Grant period</header><text>The period of a grant under this section shall be up to three years, with an opportunity for renewal.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBBC0AA25EC684732BD5E60C3F1950760"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under subsection (a), the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF995680B03F84ABC8AD916986FB44E37"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit a plan to engage with Long COVID patient organizations, medically underserved communities, and populations disproportionately impacted by COVID–19, in a degree sufficient to advance health care equity in Long COVID treatment and outcomes; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7264F4E60B9242B9A867F977F0CAB228"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrate capacity (or an intent to build capacity) to facilitate patient access to multidisciplinary health care providers with expertise in treating Long COVID and its associated conditions, as well as other infection-associated chronic conditions, including such providers who are primary and specialty care physicians capable of comprehensive, systemic care, such as psychiatrists, neurologists, cardiologists, immunologists, pulmonologists, therapists, nurses, care coordinators, social workers, nutritionists, and behavioral health specialists; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB71213CC7E8E4FBC9EFFC368BD2637DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit a plan to ensure ongoing multidisciplinary continuing education on infection-triggered conditions for—</text> <subparagraph id="HF8DAB293A03E4C7D9DCEC9BF587A1BDF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">physicians treating Long COVID and its associated conditions; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6A16D2CC8FE847B9B45DC5EA8CC92C68"><enum>(B)</enum><text>other physicians and health care workers who are not treating Long COVID, but are otherwise serving patients in the community.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2D17D18CA00D4C0D87E2BCD75D03FB10"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header> <paragraph id="HE27CEDE8FD2D4B88A9C2802A8D26B6C0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual reports by grantees to Secretary</header><text>On an annual basis, a recipient of a grant under this section shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD476A81E10874093BA27FB45C970019E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit to the Secretary, and make publicly available, a report on the activities carried out through the grant; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB1575A3AD44F48E58F503091E1B986DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include quantitative and qualitative evaluations of such activities, including the experience of individuals who received health care through such grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9491CD7EEF7841BE8026214C2FA23E1C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual reports by Secretary to Congress</header><text>Not later than the end of each of fiscal years 2023 through 2025, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress, and make publicly available, a report that—</text> <subparagraph id="H8385E37536E840C69AC11B0EE14DC940"><enum>(A)</enum><text>summarizes the reports received under paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7BBB482E4BED43EF86494ECB651B8BA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>evaluates the effectiveness of grants under this section; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1F839520ECA3458C9554F6C04D8E7E8F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">makes recommendations with respect to expanding coverage for clinical care for Long COVID and its associated conditions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF55BBA803A08437FABE7D724B4DC4D79"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

