<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF059F7FC81B74B988D214B46B62A4B40" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 1114 IH: Long COVID Response is Care Optimized and Vitally Essential Resources that Yield New Opportunities for Wellness Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1114</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for optimized care, a coordinated Federal Government response, public education, and insurance reimbursement guidance for Long COVID, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H33E96A01289842F587493BF4E99D0FEB" style="OLC"><section id="H6B93E33EDFB24BA8A31FB100E637E065" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H992D0B272DF645D0B13BF4CA9A09C7E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the<quote><short-title>Long COVID Response is Care Optimized and Vitally Essential Resources that Yield New Opportunities for Wellness Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Long COVID RECOVERY NOW Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H29790168D69F475C84F76613A9850D3D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows: </text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H6B93E33EDFB24BA8A31FB100E637E065" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC0A44D2A2FD94744AEFE638753125148" level="section">Sec. 2. Targeting resources for equitable access to treatment of Long COVID.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2D9D32D20EC34CEFAD8D0F054C68A128" level="section">Sec. 3. National Long COVID technical assistance dissemination program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H15A85CD4C4D54EDDB5E41856105D505D" level="section">Sec. 4. Mental health and suicide prevention and treatment.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5FCCC6241838450A9092BDA02D977D36" level="section">Sec. 5. ONC best practices for Long COVID data.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCACBB051534941718E20C66EE7C5EAC5" level="section">Sec. 6. Long COVID Education Website.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB2196A17078848E4A2EF8FA63A175F11" level="section">Sec. 7. Providing Support for Long COVID Registries.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H305280BAF2F142FDAAF8C397B9001E89" level="section">Sec. 8. Medicaid Health Homes for Individuals with Long COVID.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8F954959C79B4391AC085E53F296279A" level="section">Sec. 9. State health officials guidance.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9DCECE87AA584707942B69FEDD3DFDFD" level="section">Sec. 10. Support under Medicaid for State Collection of Long COVID Data.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDF979F6396DE4B02847F70CA5990722C" level="section">Sec. 11. Grants for Pediatric Research on Long COVID.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HC0A44D2A2FD94744AEFE638753125148"><enum>2.</enum><header>Targeting resources for equitable access to treatment of Long COVID</header><subsection id="H17D5EE145BC64B69AF67629AA1D99C3D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><paragraph id="HD82705823D194AE3BEE5FEA79F7F1423"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall award, subject to subsection (f) and in accordance with the provisions of this section, grants described in the following subsections to carry out the purposes described in such subsections.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BF0DFDB1AED47798B3A05B16C63B953"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>The Secretary may establish a process for evaluating and determining the eligibility of Federally qualified health centers and rural health clinics for receiving a grant under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H74AB84AFCAA74326B75D679B92A5F9B7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants to FQHCs and RHCs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), the grants described in this subsection are grants to Federally qualified health centers (as defined in section 1861(aa)(4) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(aa)(4)</external-xref>) and rural health clinics (as defined in section 1861(aa)(2) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(aa)(2)</external-xref>) to—</text><paragraph id="H73F476912AF943E8B1573420657C24CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">adopt evidence-based Long COVID clinical practices that have been demonstrated to improve the wellness of individuals with Long COVID, including clinical validation of patient reported symptoms using established measures that yield structured, comparable data;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF8F243398A14652842D3A259113F42A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish or expand screening, referral, and navigation processes for health-related social needs that could interfere with Long COVID treatment, including food insecurity, housing instability, transportation needs, utility difficulties, and interpersonal safety; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9640E82A55943649EF23619DEF1E37B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in a format consistent with the standards and activities under the Data Modernization Initiative of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention) standardized, disaggregated, deidentified data (as specified by the Secretary) on the characteristics, diagnoses, and health care service utilization of Long COVID patients served under such grant, including disaggregated data on Long COVID patient characteristics, including patient age, gender, race, ethnicity, language spoken, disability status, nature and duration of validated symptoms, and other characteristics necessary to inform considerations for effective and equitable treatment for patients with Long COVID.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9574C24AA3C54F148FD16FA4F9E9405A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants to primary care practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), the grants described in this subsection are grants to primary care practices (other than Federally qualified health centers and rural health clinics) that satisfy such criteria as may be established by the Secretary to carry out the purposes described in paragraphs (1) and (3) of subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H098FD764DCED445EB49A812C2E20E444"><enum>(d)</enum><header>GRANTS For Multidisciplinary Treatment and Coordination</header><paragraph id="HA48336DD9E89424687D13AE20C687520"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall award grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities for the purpose of creating or enhancing capacity to treat patients with Long COVID through a multidisciplinary approach. The term <term>multidisciplinary</term> in this section refers to the coordinated work to provide care or treatment to a patient by physicians and other professionals, such as specialty or subspecialty providers, nurses and nurse care coordinators, dietitians, nutritionists, social workers, behavioral health professionals, physical and occupational therapists, speech pathologists, or any professionals determined to be appropriate by the State and approved by the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA9881410D7F4B7B8160EBEBDEDA9A27"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall use the grant, for the purpose described in subsection (a), to—</text><subparagraph id="H62BDFC2666D645F58619354855CE4E48"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enhance the capacity of one or more existing multidisciplinary Long COVID clinics to serve the Long COVID population; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAD1425DFF494CA0959255B20789DE79"><enum>(B)</enum><text>create one or more multidisciplinary clinics to address the physical and mental health needs of Long COVID patients.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H870FE868DFAB4FDC98B2A1BEA85D850E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall be a health care provider, Federally qualified health center (as defined in section 1861(aa) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(aa)</external-xref>)), rural health clinic, urban Indian health center, or State or local public health department, that—</text><subparagraph id="HF8C1CD82F0B94C55BBC3B171930D09E9"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6347E53E05B344C7ACDB9EF4168FDB32"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">operates an existing multidisciplinary Long COVID clinic or other specialized Long COVID program; or</text></clause><clause id="HDAAA8989346C4380BB5DC461E3DDBE64" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is an existing health care provider with experience providing care for individuals with Long COVID and who demonstrates an intent to create a multidisciplinary Long COVID clinic or other specialized Long COVID program;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H790D06D621284D85BD9353293BE3D1D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submits to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information and assurances as the Secretary may require; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H121E9442E10841FB91783F84CEA4F8EE"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">employs a framework that incentivizes participants to attain the program’s goals to establish and disseminate best practices, and allocates funds based on such attainment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD7F5896F16C42F98282D61955EFF85F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A physical clinical facility is not a requirement for eligibility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09CF3B8B4C944851B37A185BCD4844B5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that—</text><subparagraph id="H15347CDA5A5B4670AC9BA30ED12620B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit a plan to engage with medically underserved communities, and with populations disproportionately impacted by COVID–19;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4447837C5C16417184BB494029DF2398"><enum>(B)</enum><text>demonstrate capacity (or an intent to build capacity) to provide personalized treatment and facilitate patient access to multidisciplinary health care providers with expertise in treating Long COVID symptoms, including such providers who are primary and specialty care physicians (such as physiatrists, neurologists, cardiologists, immunologists, and pulmonologists), therapists, nurses, care coordinators, social workers, nutritionists, and behavioral health specialists; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84E610DA86574FF9BB274BF7DEAB81E7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>submit a plan to ensure ongoing multidisciplinary continuing education on infection-triggered conditions for—</text><clause id="HBF599414A07D4EE0AE9754FB6D0AD523"><enum>(i)</enum><text>physicians treating Long COVID; and</text></clause><clause id="HB4CE554530F643BA9F8A17B54434C8DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>other physicians and health care workers who are not treating Long COVID, but are otherwise serving patients in the community.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6CFCCA9D552B4E18B494E7488CE37F2F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Equitable access</header><text>In order to ensure equitable access treatment—</text><paragraph id="HA97426EC9ECC4F8BAA1DB152C2E74777"><enum>(1)</enum><text>no grantee under this section shall deny access to treatment with respect to Long COVID based on insurance coverage, date of diagnosis, or previous hospitalization;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC11F17C3C6674EF289DFA5BB1F99B2C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a grantee under this section shall with respect to Long COVID—</text><subparagraph id="H94B551CEFA6040A180F2CE5888213765"><enum>(A)</enum><text>offer equity-centered resources (such as the ability to offer resources in various languages), information, and training to safety net health systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC694EE8EA2564785A20E08FCD1D32F43"><enum>(B)</enum><text>disseminate to individuals and organizations that provide care best practices and treatment approaches that enhance access to high-quality care to everyone where they live; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H099D98E9F4C24C1AB3FCB7E0487FA2CB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>treatment for Long COVID shall be included as a COVID–19 treatment, consistent with the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/2">Public Law 117–2</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD61A995DF18A4B04AE963F221D3F84FC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Development of Evidence-Based Strategies for High-Value Care for Individuals with Long COVID</header><paragraph id="HE0C1846CF9864F7DAE5C925059A15163"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality shall, subject to appropriations pursuant to subsection (i), award multi-year grants to eligible entities meeting such criteria as specified by the Secretary through rulemaking for the purposes of—</text><subparagraph id="H6A4135DB6819485BA51D7C4C9CB08032"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supporting the generation of evidence about how to deliver high quality, high-value health care for individuals with Long COVID for the treatment of the condition;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEA488C21D474EC3B81D4F33B8920632"><enum>(B)</enum><text>creating tools and strategies to help health systems and hospitals, primary and specialty physicians, nurses, allied health care professionals, and caregivers provide high-quality, high-value care for individuals with Long COVID; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H969C20F287BE40F68D439CBCC7E60451"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing educational materials for health care providers, payers, and consumers on high-value care for individuals with Long COVID.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE28FBE79E3B4852BC0C7CF5DA918207"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, through rulemaking, specify a process for evaluating and determining the eligibility of primary care providers including Federally qualified health centers and rural health clinics; specialty care providers, hospitals, health systems, academic medical centers; and other entities for receiving a grant under this subsection. Such rules shall prohibit grant funds from being used to compensate or reimburse individuals or organizations excluded pursuant to section 1128 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320a-7">42 U.S.C. 1320a–7</external-xref>) from participation under the Medicare program under title XVIII of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B706414E6194F7FA312E49D1D383423"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Long COVID defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, the term <term>Long COVID</term> (also referred to as <quote>post-acute sequelae of COVID–19</quote>, <quote>post-COVID conditions</quote>, or <quote>persistent symptoms post-COVID</quote>) means the ongoing sequelae of COVID–19 that some individuals experience after infection with the SARS–CoV–2 virus, as diagnosed by a qualified health care provider. Such sequelae are defined as the “Post-COVID Conditions” identified and defined by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in 2021, or in subsequent revisions by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></subsection><subsection id="H52FDA39DACC646ABA5AF87D5639DD90C"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HC903F7974E56415E861E795C2CCBD17B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual reports by grantees to Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On an annual basis, a recipient of a grant under this section shall—</text><subparagraph id="H75AC00E00B6F46AAB1CD5D3EA78E66FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the Secretary, and make publicly available, a report on the activities carried out through the grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD88E48C0E134C9C83BCC623F44811C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include evaluations of such activities, including the experience of individuals who received health care through such grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE431CCEB53B49009A11B1874E74A59D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual reports by Secretary to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the end of each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress, and make publicly available, a report that—</text><subparagraph id="H03099A58E34A4BE9A7CAEF0857D93180"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">summarizes the reports received under paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC606BC479D2942A090D3F96226DCE51C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>evaluates the effectiveness of grants under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H863970D414BA416EB1AD4DA0604F3A44"><enum>(C)</enum><text>makes recommendations with respect to expanding coverage for clinical care for Long COVID.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB42B97888A02482AAE3FE02372A3FCA5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="HDD68DFF649A5407399B4BD8FAEBE6BAE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A1C45E06565483A8FEEC085D58DE55B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not more than 15 percent of the amounts made available to carry out this section for any fiscal year may be used for administrative expenses to operate the grants under this section. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2D9D32D20EC34CEFAD8D0F054C68A128"><enum>3.</enum><header>National Long COVID technical assistance dissemination program</header><subsection id="H15CF5479109640AE83625503512415A9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text><paragraph id="HA1A78234AAAE45959B7FEED3E04FAB3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a structured process to seek ongoing input from medical societies representing primary care, specialty care, and subspecialty care regarding the proven and promising practices for treating individuals who are diagnosed with Long COVID to support their wellness and recovery; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FDD848CD1AD43F29080CF6D7725D5B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enter into a memorandum of understanding with one or more organizations with specific medical knowledge on Long COVID or experience providing care and medical treatment to individuals with Long COVID to support the ongoing dissemination to the broader medical community of existing open source evidence, tools and strategies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2729363EBA94A328A897A3568B374B7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Organization described</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a), and organization described in this paragraph is an organization that satisfies at least the following:</text><paragraph id="H1D8EE0F69BC0468F90CCFA38DF4888D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The organization has clinical expertise related to the treatment of Long COVID.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4999119D6F247BDBA62FE2092EFBCBD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The organization has a robust understanding of clinical and business practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD79C4CA30B8246EFBFCF980276AE8744"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The organization has the ability to convene groups and disseminate information nationally.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE167871F0ABA4885897D961CCA861AFF"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The organization consults with medical specialty associations for purposes of developing and distributing clinical best practices for Long COVID diagnosis and treatment.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H15A85CD4C4D54EDDB5E41856105D505D" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Mental health and suicide prevention and treatment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1911(b)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300x">42 U.S.C. 300x(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>and, for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026, individuals with Long COVID (as defined in section 2 of the Long COVID RECOVERY NOW Act) who have also been diagnosed with a mental health condition (such as a serious mental illness or a serious emotional disturbance)</quote> after <quote>1912(c)</quote>. </text></section><section id="H5FCCC6241838450A9092BDA02D977D36"><enum>5.</enum><header>ONC best practices for Long COVID data</header><subsection id="HBCFD8CEEC17C463887EF8B82B2B2C016"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology, shall convene health care stakeholders to identify potential best practices for collecting, aggregating, and disseminating to health care researchers deidentified data that promotes learning about Long COVID and supports the further research of the characteristics of individuals diagnosed with Long COVID. </text></subsection><subsection id="HFC40A0AAC4E34422BF41A9BCAF413EA1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 160 days after the first meeting of such stakeholders pursuant to subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to Congress (and make publicly available on the website of the Office of the National Coordinator of Health Information Technology) a report summarizing the meetings and findings of the stakeholders as well as any recommendations, including recommendations on ways that federal health care policy can better support an understanding of the etiology, characteristics, care and potential treatments for individuals Long COVID to support individuals’ recovery and wellness. Such recommendations shall—</text><paragraph id="H1C24A7A60A0C4883A46B107CD7D37FC8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">take into account the perspectives of health data scientists, health services researchers, medical providers, health plans, hospitals and health systems, epidemiologists, public health experts, patient representatives and groups, health information technology companies, and other stakeholders; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8199FEF122C64C2688C060A450CDD453"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be informed by public and private sector efforts to characterize Long COVID, aggregate and disaggregate data, and promote data standardization, data standards, or open data access for furthering a greater understanding of Long COVID.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HCACBB051534941718E20C66EE7C5EAC5"><enum>6.</enum><header>Long COVID Education Website</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall, in consultation with medical societies representing the perspectives of primary care, specialty care, mental health professionals, medical researchers (including through the National Institutes of Health), public health experts (including the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention), and patient advocates, implement a Federal website (which may be implemented through an existing public website of the Department of Health and Human Services) that—</text><paragraph id="HA3EFAB9372C7405E87D453298D3455F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>collects, and curates educational materials for health care providers and consumers about Long COVID (as defined in section 2(e)) symptoms, diagnosis, characteristics, treatment, and access to care; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89BB3CC1EBBE42DDA19BC4C979D7BE8B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes, or provides a link to, comprehensive educational resources for health care providers, such as the interim guidance (and subsequent updates) for health care providers published by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention on how to treat individuals with Long COVID.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB2196A17078848E4A2EF8FA63A175F11"><enum>7.</enum><header>Providing Support for Long COVID Registries</header><subsection id="HA295E9DE49904BCDA6A52BA393CF5B4D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Director of the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality shall, subject to appropriations pursuant to subsection (d), award multi-year grants to eligible entities described in subsection (b) for the purposes of—</text><paragraph id="HF58A4EC4A1534CD3A6B304DD91857976"><enum>(1)</enum><text>supporting existing or creating new Longitudinal registries of patients with Long COVID (as defined in section 2(g));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2EE2F554ED1488A8164A9E88A8BAE0F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establishing voluntary standards for such registries that include common data elements and clear data definitions to enable the comparability and synchronization of data by researchers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB433A486B1AA4BB1A01028CE11E8D82A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>utilize data from such registries to help inform understanding regarding the efficacy of care, diagnostics, therapeutics, care pathways, behavioral health interventions, and other dynamics regarding individuals with Long COVID; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54E3AF2A48B44C8DB361F43CBC986C92"><enum>(4)</enum><text>informing health care providers’ efforts related to improving equitable access to health care by collecting data through such registries from individuals with Long COVID, including social needs, medical history, race and ethnicity, language, gender, and disability status, as specified by the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H26FEB9D11E384690A6055ED2767BD8CF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><paragraph id="HD638B33FC50D4943A3A867963ED15D74"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under subsection (a) an entity shall—</text><subparagraph id="HDE11CE2A63464C50ABBEBCFE78EE3549"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit an application to the Secretary in such form and manner as the Secretary may require;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00A1F0054D394229A15B266C6477F9FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>agree to adhere to such data definitions and standards as the Secretary may require, including privacy and security requirements, requirements to make findings of the organization, and the use of open-source technology to promote the dissemination of information related to Long COVID;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2D18B1FAB2642A4916D27FD8CF47280"><enum>(C)</enum><text>agree to make any information collected or produced by the entity pursuant to the grant available to the public through secure, non-proprietary means without a paywall or fee;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5453EFD12D3D418BACD25034E9F1F131"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrate to the Secretary, in a form and manner specified by the Secretary, that the entity has in place appropriate standards for handling proprietary, confidential, and medical information securely and in a manner that is compliant with applicable law;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C84BCC158EF4BFDA0AA7429D6AD212F"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have in place and demonstrate to the Secretary the adequacy of a plan for the Longer-term financial sustainability of such registry; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1597BDEEC7A041998697A757ACB8DE12"><enum>(F)</enum><text>be an organization described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3D0000C21CF42E89D8AD1FE43340375"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Organizations</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), an organization described in this paragraph is any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H766FD2D4D6B6491982BF0F482D188978"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A non-profit organization representative of individuals with Long COVID.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H441A6E7B7B2447CBBBCC315C9DE99591"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An organization of health care providers, such as health systems and hospitals.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0A382C9A5B14C358BB1A7662FBD9932"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An organization of data scientists.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAA19367FDF14FFE9804BE57B8732AED"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Multi-sector groups that consist of organizations described in 2 or more of the preceding subparagraphs that meet such standards as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4CEE058F288B43A199A238BDC943C0E3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text>In carrying out the purposes described in subsection (a), an eligible entity shall take into consideration the report made available under section 4(b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H9422F62E2E5F4C18A459C2C70C6BD25D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="H305280BAF2F142FDAAF8C397B9001E89" commented="no"><enum>8.</enum><header>Medicaid Health Homes for Individuals with Long COVID</header><subsection id="H1B5DE1E99A1E4A9FBCB621A1301229D9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Health homes for individuals with chronic conditions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1945(h)(1)(A)(ii) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396w-4">42 U.S.C. 1396w–4(h)(1)(A)(ii)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H934970822CDD4EAFBFA4DE1B15AA0885" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by striking at the end <quote>or</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5885F60B4B04C1CBC1B5032FEAFD675" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subclause (III), by striking at the end the period and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H453646951737433292088D1626A57308" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4F77884E9A14480D932BE2DE3993CB66" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subclause id="HD51B509CE6A1470D88114E22215F60D9" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Long COVID (as defined in section 2(g) of the Long COVID RECOVERY NOW Act).</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC0F95B53847E4747A29D721DE7C17A3E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Health homes for children with medically complex conditions</header><text>Section 1945A(i)(1)(A)(ii) of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. 1396w–4a(i)(1)(A)(ii)) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H000AE2792A5242688E7411B1EFD638A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subclause (I), by striking at the end <quote>or</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3422CB87956D4691A040565DE234076E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by striking at the end the period and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9DB192EA93A4A2D987F86583F125A19"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H35C89E47B9A04409B2DE11FAB316342E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subclause id="H2233DF98FDF14D2E8E56A566BBFA2113"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Long COVID (as defined in section 2(g) of the Long COVID RECOVERY NOW Act).</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8F954959C79B4391AC085E53F296279A"><enum>9.</enum><header>State health officials guidance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall issue guidance to State health officials specifying tools and strategies that may help States improve the health and wellness of individuals enrolled under the Medicaid program under title XIX of the Social Security Act or the Children’s Health Insurance Program under title XXI of such Act who have been diagnosed with Long COVID by facilitating strong primary care and supporting linkages to specialists, relevant social supports, or community-based organizations at the local level, that can help support the recovery and wellness of such individuals.</text></section><section id="H9DCECE87AA584707942B69FEDD3DFDFD"><enum>10.</enum><header>Support under Medicaid for State Collection of Long COVID Data</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1903(a)(3) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD5006A3D2396428F89DB4CEA5E91B91D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H1082DD929B0042F8AC95BE25FD8A1235" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">75 percent of the sums expended during a fiscal year quarter in 2024, 2025, or 2026 as are attributable to the collection and reporting of claims and encounter data on Long COVID (including identification of race, language, ethnicity, and duration of treatment) using the ICD–10 code U09.9 post COVID–19 condition, unspecified (or any successor to such code); </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HDF979F6396DE4B02847F70CA5990722C"><enum>11.</enum><header>Grants for Pediatric Research on Long COVID</header><subsection id="H6D2A2C3A81344A4AAC7C06561D052D58"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Director of the National Institutes of Health (in this section, referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), shall award grants to eligible entities to conduct research on Long COVID in pediatric populations.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF7354B3FB3A342FDB1E939761564DEAC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity selected to receive a grant under this subsection may use funds received through the grant to conduct research described in subsection (a), with a focus on pediatric immune system responses and neurodevelopment. </text></subsection><subsection id="HFBD1AC16828444C0A048DD9BCA3A575C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entity defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means a children’s hospital, pediatric researcher, pediatrician, academic medical center, or other organization determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1E8174C75C46447A914F863FE6699605"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

