<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBA8A309A183445779FE56D831B9779A8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5206 IH: To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to make a portion of research credit refundable for certain small businesses engaging in specified medical research.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5206</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230815">August 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to make a portion of research credit refundable for certain small businesses engaging in specified medical research.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4B93F95BA9454C38BE8A0A4289F7FCA8" style="OLC"><section id="H81ACBDA36A604154A4E6A0F0A4858EF3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Refundable portion of research credit for small businesses engaging in specified medical research</header><subsection id="H6F931ADF109F44B0825FB54C5A4758BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/41">Section 41</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H11BB76BA70BA4143B94D05D297B86216" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H9591D89D1DC34FDB84EFB86BEAD521C4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Refundable portion for small businesses engaging in specified medical research</header><paragraph id="H4374A50D05DA4A468B41655C1866DAAA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the election of a medical research small business, the portion of the credit determined under this section for the taxable year which is properly allocable to specified medical research shall be treated (other than for purposes of section 280C) as a credit allowed under subpart C (and not this subpart).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99FA2C58A7DA4E30B32C88A57377AAD8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Medical research small business</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>medical research small business</quote> means any domestic C corporation—</text><subparagraph id="HD4FCEE69FB884717B7A1C50559978D03"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">which conducts any specified medical research during the taxable year, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H046FF3ECBC504DC0A1916B51B49087C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the gross receipts of which (determined under the rules of subsection (c)) for the taxable year do not exceed $1,000,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B0D7927389C4FFD92FEF76CF154D8EC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Specified medical research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>specified medical research</quote> means any qualified research with respect to qualified countermeasures (as defined in section 319F–1(a)(2) of the Public Health Service Act (42 U.S.C. 247d–6a(a)(2))).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDEAAE2F94294B82B550CE9EAD4A3E4D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Election</header><text>Any election under this subsection for any taxable year—</text><subparagraph id="HC3012826C00143F78C03CF968C96993B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall specify the amount of the credit to which such election applies,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA894108BA81B4026835641AB3C3A9DE5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be made on or before the due date (including extensions) of the return of tax for the taxable year,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53073112EA644532B6B4E3CFBB1CE449"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may not be made for any taxable year with respect to any portion of the credit determined under this section with respect to which an election is made under subsection (h), and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2B08B95B8AF4DBBBEF6329A8325543F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>may be revoked only with the consent of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H02D0372D72624A73BC1ED961BCC86413"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prescribe such regulations for purposes of this subsection as may be necessary or appropriate for determining proper allocation to specified medical research of the portion of any credit allowed to a taxpayer for a taxable year under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H569B9FD18DF2486BB8C42AFBA6BB265E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 1324(b) of title 31, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>41(i),</quote> after <quote>6428,</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAFBD3B2449CF4DB3ACC47F1E4CA28357"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2022.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

