<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H082F1F8529A6423AADE0B411E9ACAF54" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1637 IH: Comprehensive Care for Alzheimer’s Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1637</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230317">March 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000585">Mr. LaHood</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To recommend that the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation test the effect of a dementia care management model, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5414F94A223A47E29013D7128BFDC1EC" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HC51789D48E2B4028A4DFD7E5EFDDA426"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comprehensive Care for Alzheimer’s Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE41DC20EECF94AE298A26B5855F4658C"><enum>2.</enum><header>CMI testing of dementia care management</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1115A of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1315a">42 U.S.C. 1315a</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8E751E8D8E564818858A1059E493A6DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(2)(B), by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0BE346DDEF9148D386E4DB55A6453643"><clause id="HBE5CE593FC824D84B4973F367F4CF6FA"><enum>(xxviii)</enum><text>Furnishing comprehensive care management services to eligible individuals with Alzheimer's disease or a related dementia through a Dementia Care Management Model, as described in subsection (h).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H212E9EC1D2D14F6FBD5D45590A1AD940"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB505D6ECA2184B7CA1FF45F5E7E9DBFD"><subsection id="HDF5DC86EB87247EA930EFFC19D7713F8"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Dementia Care Management Model</header><paragraph id="HBF78DEDD04C940C5BC4FB93FA6C09FA6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Description of model and requirements</header><subparagraph id="H6930C2C2D8C5442D88ABF767E0D160E8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Dementia Care Management Model described in this subsection is a model under which payments are made under title XVIII to eligible entities that furnish comprehensive care management services to eligible individuals with Alzheimer’s disease or a related dementia, in order to test the effectiveness of comprehensive care management services on patient health, care quality, and care experience, as well as on unpaid caregivers, and on reducing spending under title XVIII without reducing the quality of care.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC68080CC54954BF3804DF18BE8C59F62"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Voluntary participation</header><text>Participation under the Dementia Care Management Model shall be voluntary with respect to both eligible individuals and eligible entities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8256E9E490BC458EA8BC720FC90207A2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Implementation of dementia care management model</header><clause id="H451B4B6056A3478DA08FB7BDA4DC42BF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><subclause id="HA2932D6669B24E56873EBFBC3A0CCA52"><enum>(I)</enum><text>implement the Dementia Care Management Model as a stand-alone model; </text></subclause><subclause id="HDADD5CD5E52A4AF39262549ACCF6B675"><enum>(II)</enum><text>incorporate the Dementia Care Management Model into the Primary Care First Model; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H61993D3CCCD34A8B9A0F79617613CD3A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>incorporate the Dementia Care Management Model into—</text><item id="H1D01FDD3ED56477E929B2F5401F9218C"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the Primary Care First Model; and</text></item><item id="HFAC773E5025A41F58CA294B10B91E370"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the Direct Contracting Model.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H0C1164F060A3429088CD068176F0A248"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Additional authority</header><text>In addition to the models described in subclauses (I) through (III) of clause (i), the Secretary may incorporate the Dementia Care Management Model into other existing coordinated care models established under title XVIII or under this section, including accountable care organizations, value-based purchasing arrangements, and such other coordinated care models as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FB20C6E57214BFEB41CD372F65BF27D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Comprehensive care management services defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>comprehensive care management services</term> means the following services furnished by an eligible entity with respect to an eligible individual:</text><subparagraph id="H0F01B2131D6443079A5B08AC2CE456C5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Continuous monitoring and assessment</header><text>An eligible entity shall regularly assess and continuously monitor the following:</text><clause id="H4A1B02CF0AB5413FAB0B97305C1DFDF9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Neuropsychiatric symptoms, including behavior, physical safety, and function of an eligible individual.</text></clause><clause id="H550755FBA1BF43C68DE1583C023C650B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Comorbidities.</text></clause><clause id="H99D1026683FA401F870125CF78CB1B4B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Financial resources and needs.</text></clause><clause id="H053B1E2E241040A2B51A9C75703A70D5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Caregiver supports and resources, including caregiver education, training, and support.</text></clause><clause id="H5346A6225F9C41C5B19BA716C059E1EC"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The well-being of unpaid caregivers of the eligible individual.</text></clause><clause id="H5D0FFBF2505548839342F1C0FD222187"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Potential risks and harms of the eligible individual’s home and environment and the need for support for activities of daily living.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93726F5272E14979B45FC25AF92BB700"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Ongoing dementia care plan</header><text>An eligible entity shall develop and implement an Alzheimer’s disease or related dementia care plan, including advance care planning as appropriate, for an eligible individual. The care plan shall include patient-centered goals for the eligible individual as well as goals for unpaid caregivers of the eligible individual. Such care plan shall be continuously evaluated and modified as appropriate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D0992B911424174BD2E29ADE43AB36B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Psychosocial interventions</header><text>An eligible entity may implement psychosocial interventions designed to prevent or reduce the burden of cognitive, functional, behavioral, and psychological challenges as well as the associated stress on unpaid caregivers of the eligible individual.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0664BDCE2A24E429B4A8526F4AFA6E5"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Self-management tools</header><text>An eligible entity shall provide self-management tools to enhance the skills of the unpaid caregiver of the eligible individual to manage the Alzheimer’s disease or related dementia of the eligible individual and to navigate the health care system. Such tools shall include training and support for unpaid caregivers in managing the limitations of eligible individuals, including education, problem solving strategies, care navigation support, support after discharge from a hospital or nursing home, and decision-making support.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2DC8C375BB84194BDD15F5AE10534D6"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Medication management</header><text>An eligible entity shall furnish evidence-based medication review and management services to an eligible individual, including polypharmacy management, using a planned process to reduce or stop medications that may no longer be of benefit or may be having adverse cognitive effects, prescribing approved medications, and enhancing adherence to appropriate medications.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE838329399104E4AB11637374A41A921"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Treatment of related conditions</header><text>An eligible entity shall provide interventions to prevent or treat conditions related to the Alzheimer’s disease or related dementia of the eligible individual, such as depression and delirium.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H614A517DA90E4525A6AC74A818615FDA"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Care coordination</header><text>An eligible entity shall provide ongoing care management services and shall coordinate services and supports among providers of services and suppliers, as well as social and community resources. Such services shall include necessary assistance for referrals to social and community-based organizations, collaboration with primary care providers and the interdisciplinary team of the eligible individual, and support for care transitions and continuity of care.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2539C6BE3A147F5A6AAB495113F6A65"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Exclusion of palliative care and hospice care</header><text>Comprehensive care management services shall not include palliative care or hospice care.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E1928958769437A921C7335D8FB4B52"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Other services</header><text>The Secretary may require or permit other services, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF02288CEABD64BC9854BB68AB6F157DA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity, such as a health system, hospital, physician or nonphysician group practice, multiple physician practices, a Federally qualified health center, a rural health clinic, or an accountable care organization, that—</text><subparagraph id="H70EA377A3E1746F9B17F6240CE9284DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is qualified to furnish comprehensive care management services to an eligible individual, and any unpaid caregiver of such eligible individual, under the Dementia Care Management Model either directly or through arrangements with Medicare participating providers of services and suppliers as well as social and community-based organizations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H916BD89E6C6E47AE9BF759DCCC9A7DE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is accountable for the quality of comprehensive care management services furnished to an eligible individual under the model;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6E28F76595E48FE83BC657645162A3F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>furnishes comprehensive care management services through an interdisciplinary team that has at least 1 physician, physician assistant, nurse practitioner, or advanced practice nurse who devotes 25 percent or more of patient contact time to the evaluation and care of patients with acquired cognitive impairment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9FC6A8A88B940E99679AAAB05F281FF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>furnishes comprehensive care management services in a culturally appropriate manner;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9A47D7E7AAA43538EE013E3C95BB4F4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>utilizes a comprehensive, person-centered care management approach;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0A6852C47314F6AAD13326D5C7CEDA0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>furnishes wellness and healthcare planning, including medication review and management;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9FB3A6F882B4CEEA33702324C76F17D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>supports family and caregiver engagement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBAB649BDC33492FAE78594356C80A6B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>provides access to a primary care provider or a member of the interdisciplinary team 24 hours a day 7 days a week;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6355C3F33F894EC3A582F85E47FABA75"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has relationships with medical and nonmedical community-based organizations that support patients with Alzheimer’s disease or a related dementia and their caregivers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA2927A3E8684F73A2E1344EB192188E"><enum>(J)</enum><text>meets such other requirements as the Secretary may determine to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC490C35058EA433DB98A8A905CF9E6BE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible individual defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>eligible individual</term> means an individual—</text><subparagraph id="H6C311FBDA43B4CF2B5E89648B603B932"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who—</text><clause id="H70470F4368F5404AB46E92C32FF9BD8C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is entitled to, or enrolled for, benefits under part A of title XVIII and enrolled under part B of such title (including such an individual who is a dual eligible individual described in subsection (a)(4)(A)(iii)); and</text></clause><clause id="HEEFD967DEEF74A4FB1F28D7B2CAB727B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not enrolled under part C of such title or under a PACE program under section 1894;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA901A43D87444F468D6ACDE95B4E50A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who has been diagnosed with a form of dementia;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0688AE37F50346E88B031443919B46EC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>who has not made an election to receive hospice care; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1CCE9E95E5E4EA886B0B046883FAFBE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>who is not a resident of a nursing home.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H18F69A84BC2544B2B8C7EBE3176101D4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Patient pathways</header><subparagraph id="H650AAF3452E54EC0AA31B358E7880520"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial placement</header><clause id="HBB8ABA3C231148CFB3396B4C197AB621"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Placement of patients into care pathways</header><text>An eligible entity shall assign an eligible individual to an appropriate pathway (as described in clauses (ii), (iii), and (iv)) based on an assessment of the clinical and financial status of the eligible individual that is conducted not later than 60 days after the eligible individual is enrolled in the model.</text></clause><clause id="H5DB5C4D4F6CF423098287008963F127C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Pathway for uncomplicated dementia diagnosis</header><text>During the preceding 12-month period, the eligible individual has not more than 1 unplanned inpatient hospitalization or visit to a hospital emergency department.</text></clause><clause id="H1FDD3FED7AE0482F8A9A869A06420694"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Pathway for dementia diagnosis with enhanced care coordination needs</header><text>During the preceding 12-month period, the eligible individual—</text><subclause id="H8A9E41029E8D4E519B06BF88552B8F84"><enum>(I)</enum><item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H02A372F122B242F2B96F6F4BD46BD8E1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>has 2 or more unplanned inpatient hospitalizations or visits to a hospital emergency department; or</text></item><item indent="up1" id="H64E52D6310AB4B25A01FC0CA62F31088"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>has a psychiatric hospitalization; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HE82566F1856E407E86A9A9FBD9F35181"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has sufficient financial or caregiver resources (as determined by the Secretary).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HCBF17F9EC9FC4062B31E8940F94D3966"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Pathway for dementia diagnosis with complex care needs</header><text>During the preceding 12-month period, the eligible individual—</text><subclause id="H165866D275D744A498E15A4C8F77F02D"><enum>(I)</enum><item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3160BA353C9A49A69E4CA93289C3F43B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>has 2 or more unplanned inpatient hospitalizations or visits to a hospital emergency department; or</text></item><item indent="up1" id="H53B44AA53F664C8B882910C3EB95D562"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>has a psychiatric hospitalization; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H272A7A3AB5A34335A5627BDC19283197"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has insufficient financial or caregiver resources (as determined by the Secretary).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB3F20616EDB4647AF4FE4E1C6686A46"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Regular patient assessments for appropriate pathway</header><clause id="H76D1DBAB73C3469FA20793CFF5EFDC32"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>After determination of the initial pathway, at a frequency to be determined by the Secretary, but not less than once per year, an eligible entity shall reassess the pathway determination of each eligible individual enrolled under the model.</text></clause><clause id="H109B259607C14BAA9ECBFFE2A57A2ED7"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Increased ADL limitations</header><text>Each eligible individual enrolled in the pathway for uncomplicated dementia diagnosis (as described in subparagraph (A)(ii)) who has had increased limitations in performing activities of daily living since the prior assessment shall be assigned to the pathway for dementia diagnosis with enhanced care coordination needs (as described in subparagraph (A)(iii)) or the pathway for dementia diagnosis with complex care needs (as described in subparagraph (A)(iv)), depending on the eligible individual’s financial and caregiver resources applicable to each pathway.</text></clause><clause id="H1950F9D3C44949D98804E081DFCE36DA"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Enhanced or complex care needs</header><text>Each eligible individual enrolled in the pathway for dementia diagnosis with enhanced care coordination needs (as described in subparagraph (A)(iii)) or the pathway for dementia diagnosis with complex care needs (as described in subparagraph (A)(iv)) shall be assigned to 1 of the 2 pathways based on the eligible individual’s financial and caregiver resources applicable to each pathway.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA39DC94690444528AFCC1C2F0963FE5F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Quality assessment</header><subparagraph id="H75A6F9292D6D47998E69B63719AB7351"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall specify appropriate measures to assess the quality of care furnished by an eligible entity under the Dementia Care Management Model. Such measures shall include, as appropriate, measures for clinical processes and outcomes, patient and caregiver experience of care, and utilization of services for which payment is made under the original medicare fee-for-service program under title XVIII, including measures for—</text><clause id="HBAC052641FA649ABA7214F1AFD3A181E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>emergency department utilization;</text></clause><clause id="HEAE447C02C8F4750BC65BCD68248D86A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>inpatient hospital utilization;</text></clause><clause id="H1FF6CD3775434D05A35970C9E9A01221"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>documented advanced care plan;</text></clause><clause id="H3986230292C54D59BCC4C7E774D6A887"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>medication review;</text></clause><clause id="HFDB58FEFCB284FBCA50DC128DB781D11"><enum>(v)</enum><text>screening for future fall risk;</text></clause><clause id="HA20B42B139CE4C18BFE4C2701C27BD5B"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>depression screening for caregivers;</text></clause><clause id="HC132D2A4D051491AA4255618ABADA41B"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>caregiver stress assessment; and</text></clause><clause id="H308F3EB3A806432DAD3FF0DAEF7B66EE"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>caregiver assessment of outcomes.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF6669094E4D4341899BAA5ADFD11D7A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>An eligible entity shall submit data in a form and manner determined by the Secretary on measures specified by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25383CF79478485481BCDC534AFFE2B9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Performance assessment</header><text>In order to assess the quality of care furnished by an eligible entity under the model, the Secretary shall establish—</text><clause id="H78D95DC974AF4060B4D14D33D5618CE0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>quality performance standards; and</text></clause><clause id="HBBBF8AB14A304C128D5E529F26D6C8E5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>methodologies for quality performance scoring and related payment adjustments.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFD4B7A2EBFB4CC085710AB95C0DC2E0"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Stakeholder input</header><text>The Secretary shall seek input from eligible entities on final measure specifications, including appropriate adjustment for patient preferences.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFECAAC618ECF4168B3094D85BB7E65D0"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Payments</header><subparagraph id="HEC424D06FCDE439EAC9DA28E8986661A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Under the Dementia Care Management Model, the Secretary shall establish payment amounts for care management services furnished to eligible individuals, including initial investment costs. Such amounts shall reflect start-up costs and initial investments incurred by an eligible entity in establishing the Dementia Care Management Model.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFA1E17400BB4752B12C9557DC7912BB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Capitated basis</header><text>Payments under the Dementia Care Management Model shall be made on a capitated basis, such as a per-member, per-month payment, or such other similar payment mechanisms that the Secretary determines to be appropriate. Payments shall vary based on the assigned pathway of each patient as described in paragraph (5).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80C34B08563C4F8386A121BD40C6389C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Quality bonus</header><text>Under the Dementia Care Management Model, additional payments shall be made to any eligible entity for quality bonuses based on the performance of the eligible entity in providing quality care (as determined under paragraph (6)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H29F9D8F6978544368A6D9AEB238612BA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Zero cost-sharing</header><text>An eligible individual shall not be liable for any cost-sharing, including deductibles, coinsurance, or copayments, for care management services for dementia care furnished to such eligible individual under the model.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED43480D0E364A39A5E166A8E8D74D91"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Supplemental to payments for covered services</header><text>Payments made under the model shall be in addition to any payments for items or services not provided under the model for which payment may be made under title XVIII for services furnished to such eligible individuals.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33AE148A40D1488AAD0A7A01063D62AC"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Nonduplication</header><text>Payments for care management services furnished to eligible individuals under the Dementia Care Management Model may not duplicate payments for services furnished to such eligible individuals for which payments are made under the original medicare fee-for-service program under title XVIII.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD25933E00CFC443994B2EC2E2D75EDD8"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Waivers</header><text>The Secretary shall waive provisions of this title, and title XVIII, to permit an eligible entity operating a Dementia Care Management Model to provide the following:</text><subparagraph id="HE5027D39CD614D96B27C1300FBF7A10F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Beneficiary rewards</header><text>Gift cards or other rewards for patients who successfully participate in the program (as determined by the Secretary).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B83E3A05AE84DCB940BDEB3618ACF79"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Caregivers</header><text>Supports for caregivers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E9A981F03984E9F869A0A038597399D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Telehealth</header><text>Telehealth services without regard to geographic or other originating site limitations under section 1834(m).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF9748D74DA64EE484C108FFC217D368"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Services from community organizations</header><text>Payments, cost-sharing support, or both, for nonmedical services furnished by community-based organizations, such as limited caregiving services, respite care, adult day care counseling services, and such other services as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H200D13B0FF684E8F921CF5B9716B743A"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Modifications for application in the Primary Care First and Direct Contracting Models</header><subparagraph id="H6FC7DB33B6584DDB949613ADD397D0FF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided under subparagraph (B), if the Secretary elects to incorporate the Dementia Care Management Model into the Primary Care First Model, the Direct Contracting Model, or both, as provided for under paragraph (1)(C)(i), the Secretary shall maintain the requirements of this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F9B6F2C9BDA45629C714086208D5611"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Permissible modifications</header><text>The Secretary may adjust the requirements of this subsection to the extent necessary to ensure consistency of the Dementia Care Management Model with the Primary Care First Model, the Direct Contracting Model, or both, with respect to—</text><clause id="H042C573EB0234BA9B122E8D4F6B08686"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any eligible entity, including beneficiary alignment thresholds;</text></clause><clause id="HEA6EE1A7DC6845D7B866FC1680D1A90E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any eligible individual;</text></clause><clause id="H473D18D511074D9A9593F6594B3B7AEA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>capitated payments; and</text></clause><clause id="H42CB21C6C8804832A81743C72E77D890"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>quality-bonus payments.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0A11B041CC14B368F31936D99918AE0"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Consultation with stakeholders</header><text>Prior to making any adjustment under subparagraph (B), the Secretary shall consult with appropriate stakeholders and patient advocacy organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0204BA97CFFE4F5A889E5D77430A1B7C"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Outreach to underrepresented minority populations</header><text>An eligible entity shall carry out public outreach and education efforts, including the dissemination of information, for members of underrepresented minority populations regarding participation in the Dementia Care Management Model to ensure diversity in the patient population of such model.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40B399902A374FA2BECDC5AF6811AEC1"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Option to expand to Medicaid</header><text>The Secretary may design a model under which payments are made under title XIX, in a similar manner to the manner in which payments are made under title XVIII under the Dementia Care Management Model described in this subsection, to eligible entities that furnish comprehensive care management services to individuals who are eligible for medical assistance under a State plan under title XIX (or a waiver of such a plan) with Alzheimer’s disease or a related dementia, in order to test the effectiveness of comprehensive care management services on patient health, care quality, and care experience, as well as on unpaid caregivers, and on reducing spending under title XIX without reducing the quality of care.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

