<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCAF803849C43498187D7AC7341E05DEC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5630 IH: Taiwan Identification Terminology and Label Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5630</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require agencies to use the term <quote>Taiwan</quote> instead of <quote>Chinese Taipei</quote>, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H17F6EEC3BAF24B00B0A8899C30E48EC7" style="OLC"><section id="H4EA4EA8DD0AD479B905C748B77110B05" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Taiwan Identification Terminology and Label Enhancement Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TITLE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3D26528777A64911B5EB1F5A249551E3" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purpose</header><subsection id="HB1E3AEC13CFF4C378E8E91942B4AF6F1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds as follows: </text><paragraph id="H80CA88D6D44A448E8633A8C05D840964"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States Government has never officially recognized the People’s Republic of China’s claim of sovereignty over Taiwan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDDD702DD1C048BBB8B3465EDD11BC9F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Chinese Communist Party in the People’s Republic of China seeks to control Taiwan through means of persuasion and coercion, and potentially compellance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81A66329462146A6BF7194E64DC9C5BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The People’s Liberation Army has set a goal of 2027 to have the capability to invade Taiwan, which also marks the 100-year anniversary of the People’s Liberation Army’s founding.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F35706E5DE042E7811CFD630A41CEBD"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The People’s Republic of China refers to Taiwan as a <quote>region</quote> and to the President of Taiwan as <quote>the leader of the Taiwan region</quote>, illustrating the People’s Republic of China’s mistaken view that Taiwan is a region of China.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2A64BFF257B44B5BA7BAA173A4A3BF4"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Taiwan and the People’s Republic of China are separated by a <quote>median line</quote> in the Taiwan Strait, which acts as an unofficial boundary that has generally been respected since 1999, until September 2020, when a Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman stated, <quote>there is no so-called median line in the Strait</quote>, and People’s Liberation Army aircraft and vessels have repeatedly violated since.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88D8684884F54EDBA9F5D024CF7E31EC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Taiwan officially recorded 380 Chinese air incursions into the Taiwanese Air Defense Identification Zone in 2020, 969 Chinese air incursions in 2021, and 1,115 Chinese air incursions in 2022, illustrating a growing disregard to Taiwan’s sovereignty.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96CBEC50146243E88405488772FE8CA6"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Many Taiwanese individuals see the <quote>Chinese Taipei</quote> nomenclature as a symbol of oppression from the People’s Republic of China, of which originally stems from an effort to find a way for both Taiwan and the People’s Republic of China to participate in the 1980 Lake Placid Winter Olympics and the 1980 Moscow Summer Olympics.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BA437A7784E46088D67257813E37736"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In Mandarin language, Taiwan uses a version of <quote>Chinese Taipei</quote> in which <quote>Chinese</quote> is the cultural term <quote>zhonghua</quote> and does not have sovereignty connotations. Comparatively, the People’s Republic of China uses a version of <quote>Chinese Taipei</quote> in which <quote>Chinese</quote> is <quote>zhongguo</quote> or <quote>China</quote> which mistakenly implies that Taiwan is part of China.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A87555A0576425693D11E8B190D3E8C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that Congress—</text><paragraph id="HE8259FE8E59C44B2BE1826E7AAA07B66"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">believes the United States must stand firm in the commitments it made in the Taiwan Relations Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/3301">22 U.S.C. 3301 et seq.</external-xref>), which states that the United States must <quote>maintain the capacity of the United States to resist any resort to force or other forms of coercion that would jeopardize the security, or the social or economic system, of the people on Taiwan</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE12A903FE32E4E8980F0829B34275E22"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">continues to support and defend Taiwan as it withstands control-seeking persuasion and coercion from an increasingly aggressive People’s Republic of China; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4400CAB008A94E78AA6227F9F65CF47B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">decries the United States Government’s use of <quote>Chinese Taipei</quote> nomenclature, but instead favors the use of <quote>Taiwan,</quote> to ultimately exert the belief that Taiwan’s status must be resolved peacefully and include the wishes of the people of Taiwan. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H621BB7B8EE014A859F5CC38A9F03F31A" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Agency requirement to use <quote>Taiwan</quote></header><subsection id="H1BE385922AE24BB0B2804C03ED6FBAD8" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An agency may not use <quote>Chinese Taipei</quote> and shall use <quote>Taiwan</quote>, except—</text><paragraph id="HCBE75FB18B4B4AD490265D4117F7C237" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in historical context explaining the People’s Republic of China’s attempt to control Taiwan through persuasion and coercion; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF135E33005424A1DBFF8B08FCB02DE9E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the formal title of a Federal document.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H57DCC13152D24742BBB2D64E9A41FF9D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement To update agency websites</header><text>Not later than 14 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of each agency shall ensure the website of the agency meets the requirements of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCBD59051DB2D4AFA84ED34389D4815CB" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Agency defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

