<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H39DFCCFD7018477DB2AE17369ACA3E26" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1429 IH: Transformational Reforms and Updates to Ensure Educational Quality and Urgent Investments in Today’s Youth Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1429</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230307">March 7, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000874">Mr. Hoyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide for a Federal partnership to ensure educational equity and quality.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H70B7E632551349D4A4670C7E4932D6BA" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="H7FB27135EAF3408C839252AB2EBDD458"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transformational Reforms and Updates to Ensure Educational Quality and Urgent Investments in Today’s Youth Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TRUE EQUITY Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5E959A357E69441D885F751B29F571C8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H29B76D4123C54C4388D009EF579BDB03"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The fate of our Nation and the opportunities it creates for our children and grandchildren to enjoy successful careers and rewarding lives depends on the quality, equal access, and effectiveness of pre-kindergarten through twelfth grade education in every local school district across the country.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE798B095D3F34315A7A88677DC8A7B28"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Our education systems must prepare students to compete in an interconnected, global economy.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H121910E34BC64E018E06F11538FF58C8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Despite the current combinations of Federal, State, and local funding and innovative educational policies, States with historically well regarded kindergarten through grade 12 education systems may find their students falling behind their peers nationally and internationally. In Maryland, a State with a historically well regarded kindergarten through grade 12 education system, fourth and eighth graders placed in the middle of the pack nationally in reading and math scores on the National Assessment of Education Progress. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B6D8D959CB04AA581999372722D55A7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The United States as a whole scored well down the second quartile among students from 72 countries on the Programme for International Student Assessment.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC0882072D9634E27AE79C85179F13D97"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Even in States with reading and math scores higher than the national average, there may be significant and persistent racial, ethnic, and income disparity gaps between students of color and low-income students compared to their higher income and White peers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H76753425D2FF493585DF1AF66A6A7457"><enum>(6)</enum><text>These same disparities carry into college enrollment, with fewer students of color and low-income students enrolling in college than their higher income and White peers.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4EC4180C2A514CD3AE2FE920EC476E8D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The novel coronavirus (COVID–19) health pandemic forced the physical closure of schools nationwide in March 2020, moving students from the classroom to online learning. The public health necessity to turn to online learning further exacerbated the significant and persistent racial, ethnic, and income disparity learning gaps as students struggled to access educational technology devices and the internet.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H026989C43CD84AE5BC91D3137BC6C3F8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>At the start of online learning, Maryland school districts reported that on average, nearly 25 percent of Maryland students had not logged into their new online classrooms or picked up paper work packets, falling out of sight and behind their peers.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H14F8108F978C40E29FBC2A3DAAC298F5"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Millions of children fell further behind as a result of opportunity gaps that fail to provide students with ready access to individualized instruction, healthy meals, mental health counseling services, and hands on career training programs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E8EA4789C954802A32586779C97FDE1"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As school systems have returned full time to the in-person learning environment, assessments to determine the effect of COVID–19 have shown that achievement and opportunity gaps have only widened between students of color and low-income students and their higher income and White peers.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0FD4B84FF2ED46DEA3E1F7B46C947BD0"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to address these inequities in education and harm caused by COVID–19, certain States, including Maryland, have researched and enacted bold, transformative Federal, State, and local funding and policy changes to their pre-kindergarten through twelfth grade education systems, with five main policy areas under the 2021 authorized Blueprint for Maryland’s Future which include the following focus areas:</text> <subparagraph id="H2EFDF8C9CBD84340848D2F508E3F925C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Investing in high-quality early childhood education and care through a significant expansion of full day pre-school, to be free for all low-income three- and four-year-olds, so that all children have the opportunity to begin kindergarten ready to learn.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H777846594FDC4D7A87E381D5CE2169C4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Investing in teachers and school leaders by elevating the standards and status of the teaching profession, including a performance-based career ladder and salaries comparable to other fields with similar education requirements.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H218CF08576C74D58AC01506DE0D5CFE5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Creating a world-class instructional system with an internationally benchmarked curriculum that enables most students to achieve <quote>college and career ready</quote> status by 10th grade and then pursue pathways that include early college, Advanced Placement courses, or a rigorous technical education leading to industry-recognized credentials and high paying jobs.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H87186959FA714DBC9A2E50750096DFB4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Providing supports to students that need it the most with broad and sustained support for schools serving high concentrations of poverty, with after school and summer academic programs and student access to needed health and social services.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA633C81D4728477BA729EC37F3D7B79C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Ensuring excellence for all through an accountability-oversight board that has the authority to ensure transformative education system recommendations are successfully implemented and produce the desired improvements in student achievement. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="H2D104CB7DA1E4FF18121CC51B00C5967"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that— </text> <paragraph id="H7F217A6B0D254E26B7E9330A92DD89EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>no matter a child’s ZIP Code, they deserve equal access to a quality, public pre-kindergarten through twelfth grade education;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H89E5F0BF595A4C9180C4AAF7119B0DB9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>no inequities in student achievement, college enrollment, or Federal, State, and local funding should be tolerated;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H34ED8761BEE74F4CB0D3FE4ACA14F4BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Federal Government should live up to its original commitment in 1975 under the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1400">20 U.S.C. 1400 et seq.</external-xref>) to provide 40 percent of the cost to educate children with disabilities and assist State educational agencies and local educational agencies in providing a free appropriate public education; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H053F7A42A766414592C9EB4339041E7E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Federal Government should be an active partner with State educational agencies and local educational agencies that are willing to modify policies and commit additional State and local resources to address education inequities. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="H163B2B92F3BD47F58CBDA5ACFD31A88E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HD7642CB402CD4F6E90440B51C89036C9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HACEEF09E8687447A925EF406D09B1C6D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H28B662C1F96442A9A2C69C6C8866C4F2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State educational agency</header><text>The term <term>State educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> <title id="H830E7EB322334AD8AA428D707AFB7117" style="OLC"><enum>I</enum><header>Early childhood education</header> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H7DD5B2A8E3744651ADA6A5B9DAABC59D"><enum>101.</enum><header>Early childhood education grant program</header> <subsection id="H7B1BD27F7A0641918B9E57124E329A24"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header> <paragraph id="H7B165B49E7BC4863AE8A931116E02CAA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award a single grant, on a competitive basis, to an eligible State to enable the State to carry out the authorized activities described in subsection (c). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H56FF949FAE0440EDAB2875FE35C5A60D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible state</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible State</term> means a State—</text> <subparagraph id="H733C42FD69A84BE797981A77CDFA8952"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that has established a State Oversight Board as described in section 501; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF025BF0D0A6A4FE6BE3080E0B91BB1BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that commits to educational equity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFAD28EA07FE94BE39A49FB20DD3449D5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duration; renewal</header><text>The grant awarded under this section shall be for a 2-year duration, and may be renewed by the Secretary for not more than 4 additional 2-year periods if the State Oversight Board of the State determines that the State has met the educational equity goals of the State, as described in section 501.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H1225A6ADCCEA4D20A573CC1211AAE94D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>If the Secretary does not renew a grant awarded under this section to a State for an additional 2-year period for failure to meet the educational equity goals of the State, the State shall provide, from non-Federal sources, amounts for such 2-year period that are not less than the sum of the grant amount provided by the Secretary and the matching funds provided by the State under subsection (d) for the initial 2-year grant period.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H662E71C327644EB8B39103954D61C117"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible State that desires to receive a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require, including providing the State's educational equity goals and the accountability consequences for the State and local educational agencies in the State if the State Oversight Board determines that the State or a local educational agency fails to meet the educational equity goals of the State, including the potential withholding of funds, as described in section 501.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H793BBE6AC3394048A5F4450EF45BFBDA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header>
<paragraph id="H8F844D75DE4A4138A519EB0B79451DBD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible State that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to carry out activities authorized under the following provisions: </text> <subparagraph id="H039FC98027B34ED68C8D1D6E83910369"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 619 and part C of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (20 U.S.C. 1419 and 1431 et seq.). </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H61B4A45F70164876877AA02FDFFDD5C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Paragraphs (1)(B)(i), (5)(A), and (5)(B) of section 640(a) of the Head Start Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9835">42 U.S.C. 9835(1)(B)(i)</external-xref>, (5)(A), and (5)(B)).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H90C0A73C7D97499DAEAE12B9D9CE0DD9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 9212 of the Every Student Succeeds Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9831">42 U.S.C. 9831</external-xref> note). </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1AD433793CAD490BAACBCBDF8DBF5BD4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><text>An eligible State that receives a grant under this section may use the grant funds to award subgrants to local educational agencies to carry out the activities described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H98E4C5E3AB6C46B7944845145BFEB981"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compliance with programs</header><text>In using grant funds provided under this section or subgrant funds provided under paragraph (2) to carry out the activities described in paragraph (1), the eligible State or local educational agency shall comply with the requirements of the programs under which such activities are authorized. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE00DB1A40FA84453AFCA50B177DD31FE"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Matching requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible State that receives a grant under this section shall provide, from non-Federal sources, an amount equal to 200 percent of the amount of the grant (which may be provided in cash or in kind) to carry out the activities supported by the grant.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBFA84FC3A1424D88B47098C0C72D0793"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible State shall use Federal funds received under this section only to supplement the funds that would, in the absence of such Federal funds, be made available from State and local sources for activities described in subsection (c), and not to supplant such funds.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H18EE7A049DF64E818C0C05FC280E1D1E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text> <paragraph id="HFECB0DE08F8445D89E4C890ACF2DBDAA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$275,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H87DCE1295D424D9BB4D1F47CEB8F878F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$288,750,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6857FF0276724DCF8D86F291AB7C981F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$303,187,500 for fiscal year 2026; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H966D6A436EBF4628A44FD3ACD03347C1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$318,346,875 for fiscal year 2027; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H66067ADA68F44FA8987BDAC151230AB3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$334,264,219 for fiscal year 2028; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H31D42260441743C9BB7193A8A4BDF4B4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>$350,977,430 for fiscal year 2029; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEDFA6F3C00B949AEB7199CE886838989"><enum>(7)</enum><text>$368,526,301 for fiscal year 2030; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB4BA522803324F2499A0F54F0A86F5BB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>$386,952,616 for fiscal year 2031; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H495C74335589459CBC4F0C3332D5EAEA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>$406,300,247 for fiscal year 2032; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H19B2AAEF741D4E5A999F04979145E2F2"><enum>(10)</enum><text>$426,615,259 for fiscal year 2033. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></title> <title style="OLC" id="H921E4A3F811A480C957661D6F12AE5E1"><enum>II</enum><header>High-quality and diverse teachers and leaders</header> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H04420ADEBF25479F9A4BA83C7FB560A6"><enum>201.</enum><header>High-quality and diverse teachers and leaders grant program</header> <subsection id="H15215741368941F388A550A7717D2D4E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header> <paragraph id="HB85A2DA9B8B746CDA2D6B54300DB6694"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award a single grant, on a competitive basis, to an eligible State to enable the State to carry out the authorized activities described in subsection (c). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE8B5AA25E4E341388BC6A8831AEA88DB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible state</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible State</term> means a State—</text> <subparagraph id="H4A23F59ED4234D00AA133CBCFFDF0693"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that has established a State Oversight Board as described in section 501; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9163C6FBC693417DB55539B8DE583716"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that commits to educational equity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEE5928E72EEB44328C763AB88D6190B2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duration; renewal</header><text>The grant awarded under this section shall be for a 2-year duration, and may be renewed by the Secretary for not more than 4 additional 2-year periods if the State Oversight Board of the State determines that the State has met the educational equity goals of the State, as described in section 501.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF044575D319B4C0C9736AAD02926C137"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>If the Secretary does not renew a grant awarded under this section to a State for an additional 2-year period for failure to meet the educational equity goals of the State, the State shall provide, from non-Federal sources, amounts for such 2-year period that are not less than the sum of the grant amount provided by the Secretary and the matching funds provided by the State under subsection (d) for the initial 2-year grant period.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6FE4BE6810824730A402F0B1A2A0BC91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible State that desires to receive a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require, including providing the State's educational equity goals and the accountability consequences for the State and local educational agencies in the State if the State Oversight Board determines that the State or a local educational agency fails to meet the educational equity goals of the State, including the potential withholding of funds, as described in section 501.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H68569161E6014BAF84CC0543B7615290"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header>
<paragraph id="H8B85DB61111B4214B137C0345E8A3872"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible State that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to carry out activities authorized under the following provisions: </text> <subparagraph id="HC9C789773D524E68BA6A199605F1C021"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 2101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6611">20 U.S.C. 6611</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5676B2ED4E474FDDA64A57EA92BA41A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Subpart 1 of part B of title II of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6631">20 U.S.C. 6631 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4E596222A12D4F88A6B6170690826FF2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Sections 2242, 2243, and 2245 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6672">20 U.S.C. 6672</external-xref>, 6673, and 6675).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H97E965F790F4414D806BB9100EB17E6B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Section 3131 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6861">20 U.S.C. 6861</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H581BE204F90F4DAE8542914FEC8E3A72"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Subparts 1 and 2 of part D of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1451">20 U.S.C. 1451 et seq.</external-xref> and 1461 et seq.).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBB9B59F61E9943F782C32607D2E1ABAB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><text>An eligible State that receives a grant under this section may use the grant funds to award subgrants to local educational agencies to carry out the activities described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H86F001D95FBC406FA33F00611D49823E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compliance with programs</header><text>In using grant funds provided under this section or subgrant funds provided under paragraph (2) to carry out the activities described in paragraph (1), the eligible State or local educational agency shall comply with the requirements of the programs under which such activities are authorized. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6F5C4717B28746C5BDA19838ED695325"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Matching requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible State that receives a grant under this section shall provide, from non-Federal sources, an amount equal to 200 percent of the amount of the grant (which may be provided in cash or in kind) to carry out the activities supported by the grant.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H529DEC4DA7534BA99A5EED5310F733C5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible State shall use Federal funds received under this section only to supplement the funds that would, in the absence of such Federal funds, be made available from State and local sources for activities described in subsection (c), and not to supplant such funds.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD21E2F2B6EA04F2B8DA71D6E6284F5CB"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text> <paragraph id="HAC593821688D4D889C51A10E782E233A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$340,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H910D6A6F7F5F4E7FB92F1F74A87F375C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$357,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDC139E5F871A4AE69D30D57AACC40E97"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$374,850,000 for fiscal year 2026; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB76DA12F4E1B4FDE8C6525BE8FC0633D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$393,592,500 for fiscal year 2027; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1BD7F8E3BA342EAB11C65E14AAEB20E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$413,272,125 for fiscal year 2028; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFF2BB2BDAEDB43AFA0B255ED2C796043"><enum>(6)</enum><text>$433,935,731 for fiscal year 2029; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H80F4E07FE9EA48009F97DB15D9A1BC74"><enum>(7)</enum><text>$455,632,518 for fiscal year 2030; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDD3B565FC8C945ABAF5B32CD2AF7EA89"><enum>(8)</enum><text>$478,414,144 for fiscal year 2031; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE25CFD88F96C4ABCAF8E01AF13D5BC7B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>$502,334,851 for fiscal year 2032; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5D3E2E5F5332415C8E2A0037A7E37BAC"><enum>(10)</enum><text>$527,451,594 for fiscal year 2033. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></title> <title style="OLC" id="H9432B97051CD443B958DF49385D4402E"><enum>III</enum><header>College and career readiness pathways</header> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H2176309B29534EDBAA8BD33FE622170D"><enum>301.</enum><header>College and career readiness pathways grant program</header> <subsection id="HFFD8FA1259004EBAB2A8CF7E253474BA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header> <paragraph id="H8ED30AB7493E41FAA8A125EB5FFC5253"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award a single grant, on a competitive basis, to an eligible State to enable the State to carry out the authorized activities described in subsection (c). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFC6C25A1E0E9480FAFF57AC90B68F331"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible state</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible State</term> means a State—</text> <subparagraph id="HFDFA448635A74458B456521EE34DFFAB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that has established a State Oversight Board as described in section 501; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA3A578909D884A568CFF502DC26F0BF1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that commits to educational equity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2BA7178BBB644D4F9CF86CED5CE13965"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duration; renewal</header><text>The grant awarded under this section shall be for a 2-year duration, and may be renewed by the Secretary for not more than 4 additional 2-year periods if the State Oversight Board of the State determines that the State has met the educational equity goals of the State, as described in section 501.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B73A85D9B4B4950B41992BEEBA16D00"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>If the Secretary does not renew a grant awarded under this section to a State for an additional 2-year period for failure to meet the educational equity goals of the State, the State shall provide, from non-Federal sources, amounts for such 2-year period that are not less than the sum of the grant amount provided by the Secretary and the matching funds provided by the State under subsection (d) for the initial 2-year grant period.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H352AE4E515294CA089F68A6C13C673D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible State that desires to receive a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require, including providing the State's educational equity goals and the accountability consequences for the State and local educational agencies in the State if the State Oversight Board determines that the State or a local educational agency fails to meet the educational equity goals of the State, including the potential withholding of funds, as described in section 501.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H918191226D60483FA1EBA776F8C96E34"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header>
<paragraph id="H696AE63E9759481CA8BDDC6E6A26164B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible State that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to carry out activities authorized under the following provisions: </text> <subparagraph id="H09DC99749E044B52BBA87D0826E44D85"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 135 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2355">20 U.S.C. 2355</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7B862CC74DE04B98826CDAA33643E5F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Subpart 11 of part A of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965, as added by section 302 of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H94DE93ABE3FD47609BEE0A3A3EAEC67C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><text>An eligible State that receives a grant under this section may use the grant funds to award subgrants to local educational agencies to carry out the activities described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3CB103B463F84A5F9D53EC14081E6A0D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compliance with programs</header><text>In using grant funds provided under this section or subgrant funds provided under paragraph (2) to carry out the activities described in paragraph (1), the eligible State or local educational agency shall comply with the requirements of the programs under which such activities are authorized. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA89FAE7278E246239669BBBED03574D1"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Matching requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible State that receives a grant under this section shall provide, from non-Federal sources, an amount equal to 200 percent of the amount of the grant (which may be provided in cash or in kind) to carry out the activities supported by the grant.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H7588B35ADBC84103877C70D6B3066E7E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible State shall use Federal funds received under this section only to supplement the funds that would, in the absence of such Federal funds, be made available from State and local sources for activities described in subsection (c), and not to supplant such funds.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBDAD123ABCDB491DAF703C7410799E26"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text>
<paragraph id="HF7B6CA9086E44762B86C5A6E26C9D7C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$50,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0FE41B754145405285DE2702ED55C60C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$52,500,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3DA024F0FF6E4A52B80DE9398F37E154"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$55,125,000 for fiscal year 2026; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC8FB514F37B848CB956927C7B16E70B1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$57,881,250 for fiscal year 2027; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H57235687D0084A69A9A313B542188001"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$60,775,312 for fiscal year 2028; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2EB7B87DDEB94935BAE06329EFFD0DE3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>$63,814,077 for fiscal year 2029; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H79EF550074CC45F683E0017110324A66"><enum>(7)</enum><text>$67,004,780 for fiscal year 2030; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99B5BF80F101411095B69AAF7F1B1676"><enum>(8)</enum><text>$70,355,019 for fiscal year 2031; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9435BCEFA4584DE59F1D2A69C6D2EA3A"><enum>(9)</enum><text>$73,872,770 for fiscal year 2032; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE9B52989239D4A2899590695D5EE025F"><enum>(10)</enum><text>$77,566,408 for fiscal year 2033. </text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5DF82628AD4A4453BFE55AF2C7F43B46"><enum>302.</enum><header>Jumpstart to college grant programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H97572E37413343B99A7618FFB188E437"> <subpart id="H6B25E0F8F7E84354B9D78262647E6A1B"><enum>11</enum><header>Jumpstart to College</header> <section id="H2CA5B5DBE35D4EBB89C41B5F7F1C1EB8"><enum>420T.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this subpart:</text>
<paragraph id="H2D3E352EC1AD4660893FC8FB4833D3CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an institution of higher education in partnership with one or more local educational agencies (which may be an educational service agency). Such partnership may also include other entities such as nonprofit organizations or businesses, and schools in juvenile detention centers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABCDD73914FE475090141F44BA5F2C07"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H209B5C1A23164626A157D8EB5D564FF0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <term>dual or concurrent enrollment program</term>, <term>early college high school</term>, <term>educational service agency</term>, <term>four-year adjusted cohort graduation rate</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State</term> have meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD76F8CEE05264693815AE5D0AE7A9F99"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Low-income student</header><text>The term <term>low-income student</term> means a student counted under section 1124(c) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC651067D6A754AC6B677F11D43B847EC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Recognized postsecondary credential</header><text>The term <term>recognized postsecondary credential</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H4B876E8F1E4144D389A36E16CED75842"><enum>420U.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">To carry out this subpart, there are authorized to be appropriated $137,500,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each of the nine succeeding fiscal years.</text></section>
<section id="H2CE533A1F15C41DD8E50C231165EA280"><enum>420V.</enum><header>Grants to states</header>
<subsection id="HB36AC9C77D7F4439966C9DBBB797B47A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award a single grant to a State, on a competitive basis, to assist the State in supporting or establishing early college high schools or dual or concurrent enrollment programs.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H638A44BF2E9C4B6D9137888E6B07EBBB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The grant under this section shall be awarded for a period of 2 years, and may be renewed by the Secretary for not more than 4 additional 2-year periods.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HB76CD6C3BEC04157955A0E19623A74D8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that the amount of the grant under this section is sufficient to enable the grantee to carry out the activities described in subsection (f).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDD73E006D2BC4DA88A47C49D90E6BE93"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header><text>For each year that a State receives a grant under this section, the State shall provide, from non-Federal sources, an amount equal to 50 percent of the amount of the grant received by the State for such year to carry out the activities supported by the grant.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H7B6F9C4F0D4D4928B7746EEF57F43066"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>A State shall use a grant received under this section only to supplement funds that would, in the absence of such grant, be made available from other Federal, State, or local sources for activities supported by the grant, not to supplant such funds.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC04B09A3B2A54C5B9568ADC518DD2D5C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header> <paragraph id="HFF837BD1B416426FA2936DFA3B9BD804"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Mandatory activities</header><text>A State shall use grant funds received under this section to—</text>
<subparagraph id="HE8D1955DA8104150AA46621E54BC9422"><enum>(A)</enum><text>support the activities described in its application under subsection (g);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCD3E72D70CEA4305B9B67B30226B12D0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>plan and implement a statewide strategy for expanding access to early college high schools and dual or concurrent enrollment programs for students who are underrepresented in higher education to raise statewide rates of secondary school graduation, readiness for postsecondary education, and completion of recognized postsecondary credentials, with a focus on students academically at risk of not enrolling in or completing postsecondary education;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H78FF2FA23AC6440A9165C409944BCD0F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identify any obstacles to such a strategy under State law or policy;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB5E7BA3B2E8E4F61A1B210CA3E6541BE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide technical assistance (either directly or through a knowledgeable intermediary) to early college high schools and other dual or concurrent enrollment programs, which may include—</text>
<clause id="H7C03ACD8D27C4E1A99470DC0AEEE877F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>brokering relationships and agreements that forge a strong partnership between elementary and secondary and postsecondary partners; and</text></clause> <clause id="H8EA8981D93E346A9A0B75CC78B73F227"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>offering statewide training, professional development, and peer learning opportunities for school leaders, instructors, and counselors or advisors;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3716CBC4D6E44EF2B18607BE6D71A77B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>identify and implement policies that will improve the effectiveness and ensure the quality of early college high schools and dual or concurrent enrollment programs, such as eligibility and access, funding, data and quality assurance, governance, accountability, and alignment policies;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1911AB78AF484242B957B22EDEF4322A"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">update the State’s requirements for a student to receive a regular high school diploma to align with the challenging State academic standards and entrance requirements for credit-bearing coursework as described in subparagraphs (A) and (D) of section 1111(b)(1) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA6404DAD88D7417EB286765289144C9C"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">incorporate indicators regarding student access to and completion of early college high schools and dual or concurrent enrollment programs into the school quality and student success indicators included in the State system of annual meaningful differentiation as described under section 1111(c)(4)(B)(v)(I) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H849A9E3685774E0FB86561F5933C61C6"><enum>(H)</enum><text>disseminate best practices for early college high schools and dual or concurrent enrollment programs, which may include best practices from programs in the State or other States;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD7348F5FADCD4E7696180CAC6D34408D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>facilitate statewide secondary and postsecondary data collection, research and evaluation, and reporting to policymakers and other stakeholders; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8F59ABA19769442EA28AF9DB4F4A2630"><enum>(J)</enum><text>conduct outreach programs to ensure that secondary school students, their families, and community members are aware of early college high schools and dual or concurrent enrollment programs in the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCB1889CBA5104074ADA3F3C3E3A28D0C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Allowable activities</header><text>A State may use grant funds received under this section to—</text> <subparagraph id="HB5B6795D273149DDB7B2E11B93D8F298"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a mechanism to offset the costs of tuition, fees, standardized testing and performance assessment costs, and support services for low-income students, and students from underrepresented populations enrolled in early college and high schools or dual or concurrent enrollment;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9D691EEB703D400C9B48055059E13321"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish formal transfer systems within and across State higher education systems, including two-year and four-year public and private institutions, to maximize the transferability of college courses;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H69E128D9CAD64286899ED936894683BD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide incentives to school districts that—</text>
<clause id="HBB7215FA99314787BD14D58E931DFD67"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assist high school teachers in getting the credentials needed to participate in early college high school programs and dual or concurrent enrollment; and</text></clause> <clause id="H4EE1E4FE9A8845079300893DAE4A3BB0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>encourage the use of college instructors to teach college courses in high schools;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB4832C38680C4661AC9F05D33521B865"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support initiatives to improve the quality of early college high school and dual or concurrent enrollment programs at participating institutions; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H745F072953EB445BB922E73C489BA747"><enum>(E)</enum><text>reimburse low-income students to cover part or all of the costs of an Advanced Placement or International Baccalaureate examination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H60B4E9ECBC7D47D5933A8819EED38EC8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>State Applications</header>
<paragraph id="H832F31D9A1264AD49A099E83BB7B302F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a State shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD9D822FF6369465EB9662548828C69E3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of application</header><text>The application under paragraph (1) shall include, at minimum, a description of—</text>
<subparagraph id="H30BE79EC12424083958ABB7417525AC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how the State will carry out the mandatory State activities described in subsection (f)(1);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7BA777A69CBD4EC1A23B2B195D81C3FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how the State will ensure that any programs funded with a grant under this section are coordinated with programs under—</text>
<clause id="H4D18FCFC727246268C6D5BFA4A54C4CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2301">20 U.S.C. 2301 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause> <clause id="H5449CA16B27C48178EC6BDF3EFA96EB0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3101">29 U.S.C. 3101 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause>
<clause id="HDE9E1481238741EDB69609A7C577EEFB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965; and</text></clause> <clause id="H97ECFF8338AF486496D77450CBC663A6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDAD26777805D4869BD1907A1020A870B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how the State intends to use grant funds to address achievement gaps for each category of students described in section 1111(b)(2)(B)(xi) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCCC95811AEED41888DC6DED37B3BDF5D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>how the State will access and leverage additional resources necessary to sustain early college high schools or other dual or concurrent enrollment programs;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7A73F7FB3C834972A74F2F88EF87A947"><enum>(E)</enum><text>how the State will identify and eliminate barriers to implementing effective early college high schools and dual or concurrent enrollment programs after the grant expires, including by engaging businesses and nonprofit organizations; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H47F5D31E5DBE422AB5DDBE641AA240A2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></subpart><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title>
<title style="OLC" id="H1C0DD8A467C1407DA27C06B81B4876BC"><enum>IV</enum><header>More resources to ensure all students are successful</header>
<section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HD80E1C63A16D408E960FAD7422A62769"><enum>401.</enum><header>Student success grant program</header>
<subsection id="H4D67D0D4302646B19146AB8FE8D43A55"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header>
<paragraph id="H4ECAFF0CD3454E579AACEB3CA01B2444"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award a single grant, on a competitive basis, to an eligible State to enable the State to carry out the authorized activities described in subsection (c). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9EB7A72AC2C144D7800B2F9EF54311A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible state</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible State</term> means a State—</text>
<subparagraph id="H651A1130CDDE4370B3351674796BBDA0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that has established a State Oversight Board as described in section 501; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0F3CDDB2331A4597A30C72035E433068"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that commits to educational equity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H450322CCCFF34C88841926F55E95212E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duration; renewal</header><text>The grant awarded under this section shall be for a 2-year duration, and may be renewed by the Secretary for not more than 4 additional 2-year periods if the State Oversight Board of the State determines that the State has met the educational equity goals of the State, as described in section 501.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD78F1AE4FA104044A3230484C3C5189B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>If the Secretary does not renew a grant awarded under this section to a State for an additional 2-year period for failure to meet the educational equity goals of the State, the State shall provide, from non-Federal sources, amounts for such 2-year period that are not less than the sum of the grant amount provided by the Secretary and the matching funds provided by the State under subsection (d) for the initial 2-year grant period.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H16EB9514ED354815B523FF6B8E96FDBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible State that desires to receive a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require, including providing the State's educational equity goals and the accountability consequences for the State and local educational agencies in the State if the State Oversight Board determines that the State or a local educational agency fails to meet the educational equity goals of the State, including the potential withholding of funds, as described in section 501.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H94A6D410F99D4E29B9CC8E56D44CE0B7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header> <paragraph id="H5CF01FFD8A78405A81859092886ED565"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible State that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to carry out activities authorized under the following provisions: </text>
<subparagraph id="H2C1B10E265F64A54A634B7DA827AC7F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H625234902D3D45CAB6DDB14CF77772C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Part C of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6391">20 U.S.C. 6391 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC783988ECC914464ACA3D48C3C86C08E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Part D of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6421">20 U.S.C. 6421 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2477E9DD39414E8CB91B49B90CC727A9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Part E of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6491">20 U.S.C. 6491 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBB5013DC9575457A8067EDAECA6D3987"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Subparts 2 and 3 of part B of title II of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6641">20 U.S.C. 6641 et seq.</external-xref> and 6661 et seq.).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7812B25EF59B42DBB84F65A43942479E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Subpart 1 of part A of title III of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6821">20 U.S.C. 6821 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H80D7C85DB2794C239B4B5AD66B36D736"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Subpart 1 of part A of title IV of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7111">20 U.S.C. 7111 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCFFB24D3C9F24D46B628B25E70B018EB"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Part B of title IV of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7171">20 U.S.C. 7171 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3A7A55425E5E42B3894B1A336F1C352B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Part D of title IV of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7231">20 U.S.C. 7231 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF04C5C4005AD446D9E97B4C9FCB54C2D"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Sections 4624 and 4625 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (20 U.S.C. 7274 and 7275).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD963095236E341F0840AC3BE4529D3AD"><enum>(K)</enum><text>Section 4641 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7291">20 U.S.C. 7291 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB3DC821A6E9443B7B8BB8504A560E461"><enum>(L)</enum><text>Section 611 of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1411">20 U.S.C. 1411</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE0C9B2EF483A42A5A1B2E60D1225A50B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><text>An eligible State that receives a grant under this section may use the grant funds to award subgrants to local educational agencies to carry out the activities described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF3C77CED4AD42ED97E7B1BDFE52598F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compliance with programs</header><text>In using grant funds provided under this section or subgrant funds provided under paragraph (2) to carry out the activities described in paragraph (1), the eligible State or local educational agency shall comply with the requirements of the programs under which such activities are authorized. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF86EE333DD4B464BB165C996D14A39B2"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Matching requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible State that receives a grant under this section shall provide, from non-Federal sources, an amount equal to 200 percent of the amount of the grant (which may be provided in cash or in kind) to carry out the activities supported by the grant.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF8E654A450F54C4FA00A6A3EF5A1493B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible State shall use Federal funds received under this section only to supplement the funds that would, in the absence of such Federal funds, be made available from State and local sources for activities described in subsection (c), and not to supplant such funds.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1E95CFCFD93450E98DFECC0FE464A9D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text> <paragraph id="H4AEE23C179E44047AA05E130802942B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$750,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H29BA65F8274C41169E58D30A7252BAC0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$787,500,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBB99B9135E84F4FAD938FA447CF5FBB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$826,875,000 for fiscal year 2026; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA6B1593029DC40C2979044925210037E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$868,218,750 for fiscal year 2027; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5672042E2075448CAEC4D82A52EF0C1A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$911,629,688 for fiscal year 2028; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2A7ED71928E445738DB738FA284D7E5E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>$957,211,172 for fiscal year 2029; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6AAD11CEB4BD44868485F9EB41BAE37E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>$1,005,071,731 for fiscal year 2030; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4A13E3420F4E48698272251FB1732A27"><enum>(8)</enum><text>$1,055,325,318 for fiscal year 2031; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB602315CB9984B79A9078B9C09E3CCC5"><enum>(9)</enum><text>$1,108,091,584 for fiscal year 2032; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0A7FA3483E94AD4A658FAE4CC67A783"><enum>(10)</enum><text>$1,163,496,163 for fiscal year 2033. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></title> <title style="OLC" id="H55BB634FB6F4406293BC1553590675AA"><enum>V</enum><header>Governance and accountability </header> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H7B0B471E5DD34C6CBA9768B67E065FE1"><enum>501.</enum><header>State oversight boards</header> <subsection id="H3B15C4B5A8224D6EBE77459B8F106B76"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In order to be eligible to receive a grant under title I, II, III, or IV, a State shall establish a State Oversight Board that is independent of the State educational agency, ensures educational equity in the State, and holds the State educational agency and local educational agencies in the State accountable for failure to meet such educational equity. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="H1B8D86EF1C1F4BC9AB255C51CE96C4A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority of state oversight boards</header><text>A State Oversight Board established pursuant to this section shall— </text> <paragraph id="HD2F46CB260094A26ABD926C07912F1C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine implementation plans and guidelines for the State educational agency and local educational agencies in the State to meet the educational equity goals determined by the State under subsection (c); </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF89CE0A043134B449CF4B5864293A9C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>determine whether the State and local educational agencies in the State have met the educational equity goals determined by the State; </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H62396680860E4F9298FAA32ECE5B7112"><enum>(3)</enum><text>hold the State and local educational agencies in the State accountable for a failure to meet the educational equity goals, pursuant to the accountability consequences described under subsection (c); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H575120209A32428D91A89365B513F378"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide to the Secretary, on an annual basis, the progress of the State and local educational agencies in the State towards meeting the educational equity goals.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H23A73DFAD9D7493F83EE7E43C4843D77"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority of state</header><text>A State that establishes a State Oversight Board under this section shall determine—</text>
<paragraph id="H59063D35FCFD4754A73761C599B3E3B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the educational equity goals of the State, that includes a requirement that the State and local educational agencies in the State maintain a level of financial support for elementary and secondary education that is not less than the level of such support for fiscal year 2023; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H969E1CAA5DFD44A6878630AF41CA73EA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the accountability consequences for the State and local educational agencies in the State if the State Oversight Board determines that the State or a local educational agency fails to meet the educational equity goals of the State, including the potential withholding of funds. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H31A035CB34A04D9694496D5D08C6DFFE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical assistance and oversight</header>
<paragraph id="HD4AC5F87A6FB4970AEA1CB7DE0772C94"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary and the Office for Civil Rights of the Department of Education shall provide technical assistance—</text> <subparagraph id="H28BFFFCFB9814887A529A64D17E915AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to States in implementing the educational equity goals of the State; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H734E6A7C5A0B429EB991D150A8C2277E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to State Oversight Boards in carrying out subsection (b), including in determining whether the State and local educational agencies in the State have met the educational equity goals determined by the State. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11B781ED34364FF3B5130DC4C64FCE35"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection $1,000,000 for each fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title>
<title style="OLC" id="H14E6CA0F9DD740E5B79D907A96BCBD3C"><enum>VI</enum><header>State flexibility for equitable per-pupil funding</header>
<section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HBBD0A5B2AD7B4616A3CAD7558C77E6B5"><enum>601.</enum><header>State flexibility for equitable per-pupil funding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1501 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6491">20 U.S.C. 6491</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HEE5B36C58ED2413B8DF498EB4A558A0E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by inserting <quote>and certain State educational agencies on behalf of a State's local educational agencies</quote> after <quote>local educational agencies</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H669F41A654674076980BCF66A62E497C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="H760CAB6BAB0C4714BF9AB40080E2C61D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A), by inserting <quote>and certain State educational agencies on behalf of a State's local educational agencies</quote> after <quote>local educational agencies</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H47054A4FDF584B5D9E5FD77D4A29E5B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>and certain State educational agencies on behalf of a State's local educational agencies</quote> after <quote>local educational agencies</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDE49D0E7D2D0478A9208D2CFF733973D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA7913C0FBCA44D7CBC4F816675065CB0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>or 1 State educational agency on behalf of the State's local educational agencies</quote> after <quote>local educational agencies</quote>; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAB080FAEFDFD4047B1B1415D91119651"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text>
<clause id="HD30C5DFA52BF4E7FAD99AACBEFB1071F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or State educational agency</quote> after <quote>local educational agency</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H9C2069989C7B49DCB7277434C31E6C2D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or consolidated State</quote> after <quote>local</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCB13861D65304CAC9FBCD7919A0D4D0E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <clause id="HBFC770EE4E69432698F06DA6E6DB4D50"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>any local</quote> and inserting <quote>any</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H9BA24E6BCCDB402B93E7462E4E4C7D3B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>with local</quote> and inserting <quote>with the</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H10EDD218C46141BCA751122ACED57555"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H899FD65F97AF448E84F5E34F5A20B817"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <clause id="H80D091ACA2254A59A1D39E4E75D8EF6B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text>
<subclause id="H92FFA950598B467A9C224BA3DE60CDE3" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Each local</quote> and inserting <quote>Each</quote>; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2B7779EB06444E179DB7003B9C897DBC" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or consolidated State</quote> after <quote>local</quote>;</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H88D05AB7CBEB42BCB500E5411AAB0ED7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)(ii), by striking <quote>local</quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H3CA46ED935BD449E84414DB2C8A415C1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>local</quote>;</text></clause>
<clause id="H5F984BF516B742BF95A71EC881126E42"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H2FB624293109443DAC885972211253E0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>;</text></clause>
<clause id="H92A2577DE6FD4AF69AF0075699E3702D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subparagraph (H), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; </text></clause> <clause id="HD4E1E51515144280B2C8D1E5BC0986E1"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB0646402722D4790AACE8C6433C55BDD"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3A49837845514A75ADF573A539D96F33"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text>
<clause id="H1353F3161AA04ACAA4E4E545B90AC4DC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; </text></clause> <clause id="H0AD08F6F304C4960A6622CA0082E81C2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB5773D48C9D6484DB9112FA43547B904"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H657C265C55D54A6A90FA9579042FC31C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (e), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC2579AFC83584CFC898ABDB6A98DC37E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in subsection (f)—</text> <subparagraph id="H92C138165B514A1BA0E11607189E6721"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD252974621D8480FBFCE0FE7778E2CDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or consolidated State</quote> after <quote>local</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1C9AA2C24C68408AAC7ACCEE17CB26CF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in subsection (g), by inserting <quote>or consolidated State</quote> after <quote>local</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HECC91A510E38457FBD0CCF5110A7837C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>in subsection (h)—</text> <subparagraph id="HB3FB21880FAF4A27B71E86D3D9D034B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF12B68ACF299433BA4B963B4D674A993"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or consolidated State</quote> after <quote>local</quote>; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6EC79A1C8B984243ADD49ED2A36D7228"><enum>(9)</enum><text>in subsection (i), by striking <quote>local educational</quote> each place the term appears and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H81CB72BAA3FB48119536709708CBE741"><enum>(10)</enum><text>in subsection (j), by inserting <quote>or consolidated State</quote> after <quote>local</quote>; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1F785A7A3FAC4D23BD6F30AA60209597"><enum>(11)</enum><text>in subsection (k)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9375526309CB46B3B83B5961DB16268E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>local educational</quote> and inserting <quote>educational</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBCF21E501A134CD2A73525A829A58A40"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or consolidated State</quote> after <quote>local</quote> each place the term appears; </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB021FED5152D46D3B60770668CDA2E00"><enum>(12)</enum><text>in subsection (l)—</text> <subparagraph id="H50FC945366F447339FAED2252D60D7C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text>
<clause id="HA09C0F9522F34E24A4C8A711AACE8EBE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or State educational agency</quote> after <quote>local educational agency</quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H3D07633B8ED74E0E91619939B769EB1C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></clause>
<clause id="H82430DEE02E64FA19792AB6833E644CA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></clause> <clause id="HF55313E24E6B48CE84A2776FB6CFF448"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H73130F8A3CE645A39A3209F81E1E3137">
<subparagraph id="H4226D5E046D14CECB03F73620B1D1354"><enum>(F)</enum><text>title I of the TRUE EQUITY Act;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7016ECE2377E4EFCB44AD941DB011179"><enum>(G)</enum><text>title II of the TRUE EQUITY Act;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFCCCE4064F8F43C3A1CFA4D2AE974EA6"><enum>(H)</enum><text>title III of the TRUE EQUITY Act; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8A2EA87B976F4EF880BE217CCF21EE8C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>title IV of the TRUE EQUITY Act.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1A685BC37F514AA9AEEDC5AFDE6E8C64"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>is in the highest 2 quartiles of schools served by a local educational agency, based on the percentage of enrolled students from low-income families</quote> and inserting <quote>serves students not less than 55 percent of whom are students who are eligible for a free or reduced price lunch under the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1751">42 U.S.C. 1751 et seq.</external-xref>)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B91AE58EF874C329FE93B6F3DF8C1C6"><enum>(13)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H16B7FE4E9F484EDAB35420216AFAA793">
<subsection id="HF2579F1575654CA1A3676AD133D81D3C"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Funding flexibility for TRUE EQUITY Act funds</header>
<paragraph id="H13EA22F01D1C4175BF0BA5F399EE2DAF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>A State educational agency that submits a consolidated State flexibility demonstration agreement under this section shall provide technical assistance to local educational agencies in the State that desire to participate in the program under this section in submitting applications to enter into local flexibility demonstration agreements with the Secretary. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63CA7AF3BD214897AE348C0A74A38E31"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration and renewal</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, the Secretary—</text>
<subparagraph id="HEBE2C0A6ECBA4DB09D290ED7700B5564"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is authorized to enter into local flexibility demonstration agreements for not more than 2 years with local educational agencies that are selected under subsection (c) and submit proposed agreements that meet the requirements of subsection (d) for flexibility to consolidate eligible Federal funds that are described in subparagraph (F), (G), (H), or (I) of subsection (l); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3F487D9D6F9642F99F7344C5268FAC34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may renew for not more than 4 additional 2-year terms a local flexibility demonstration agreement described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></title>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


