<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1392E266E485494382C104E203B3B986" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3431 IH: Spectrum Coexistence Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3431</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information to establish a working group on performance criteria for radio receivers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC132B508179C4341A97EF89DCD261DBF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7DEA0B62C2604D61A42A4869C9194F1A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Spectrum Coexistence Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5E6E3FEE887D4408900049267A050371"><enum>2.</enum><header>Working group on performance criteria for radio receivers</header> <subsection id="HD1EEC971A6DC4FDEA2524D0BE42E5912"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <paragraph id="HA1CB7EC0E318417C9480F3F40A55C542"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 3 months after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Commerce, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information and the Commission, shall convene a working group to develop, and periodically update, criteria, ratings, and other measures, including voluntary standards of radio receivers operating in Federal systems.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H32C58068F40E4582941A57D3E0203AA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the criteria, ratings, and other measures, including voluntary standards developed by the working group, shall be to encourage the design, manufacture, and sale of radio receivers operating in Federal systems that incorporate appropriate measures to provide interference immunity to ensure that the reasonable current and future use of cochannel or non-cochannel spectrum, including use by non-Federal systems of spectrum designated by the Commission for commercial operations, will not result in receiver operations being seriously degraded or obstructed, or their operations repeatedly interrupted.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC6EDD1F294D144A0AF23FF71172F0366"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In developing the receiver criteria, ratings, and other measures, the working group shall take into consideration the unique technical and operational characteristics of the different Federal systems.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0165AA240F8C4B04875B7372704F4C3C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Chair; members</header><text>The Chair of the working group shall be the Secretary of Commerce and shall include representatives from the following:</text> <paragraph id="HCF82D3A0C0F146488FE18840DA6FB3B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7E6AAE73B8D64B56B561AB8137E2FA67"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Commission.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7111247B9EA48379B783EF74BF8A1DB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The telecommunications industry.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H92CF50BE5BD94379AC419D48ACDFEBCE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Academia.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6B2BAC4E10454042B1DCD798B4B7E20E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Publication of criteria, rating, and other measures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date on which the working group is established pursuant to subsection (a)(1), the Commission and Assistant Secretary shall publish the criteria, ratings, and other measures developed pursuant to subsection (a)(1) on a publicly accessible page on the website of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration and in the Federal Register.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H491CB3021CFA492382005AEC5E8C21D0" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Periodic review and update</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less frequently than every 4 years, the working group shall review and update, if appropriate, the criteria, ratings, and other measures published pursuant to subsection (c). Any such update shall be published as described in subsection (c) not later than 14 days after the date on which the update is completed. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H9B1CF51EF7944F52B5BFE4B11694338E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text>No action taken by the working group, the Assistant Secretary, or the Commission pursuant to this section shall be used to impose any obligation on manufacturers with respect to any radio receivers designed to operate exclusively in non-Federal systems.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1379DA1F19D444E9AFE6A7A431CCA8FE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HE4C80310BDEC407DAD254D6248CDC94D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assistant Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Assistant Secretary</term> means the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3DB79A14744F4A73BB32D23F75E1E749"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Communications Commission.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC44524C280C44D438875568CC3321CB0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Federal system</header><text>The term <term>Federal system</term> means a system of radio stations belonging to and operated by the United States that receives radio frequency signals on spectrum that is allocated exclusively for Federal Government use or allocated for both Federal and non-Federal operations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

