<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD2750DEF35A54E60B85944F870525B68" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5102 IH: ABLE MATCH (Making Able a Tool to Combat Hardship) Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5102</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230801">August 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to provide matching payments for ABLE account contributions by certain individuals, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC672072152D64390A8FFA6B4B39BBA51" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H081907C879A84012BC093079777BDF03"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>ABLE MATCH (Making Able a Tool to Combat Hardship) Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE4365960C4D64E75B78F37701F688346"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H0AC0C93D6E26484493E372212F52EBD2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>People with disabilities are more than twice as likely to live in poverty than people without disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD2E85CC9EEF443EB006F1BC8912FC04"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Households containing an adult with a disability that limits their ability to work requires, on average, 28 percent more income to obtain the same standard of living as similar households without a member with a disability.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC728786B06704551ADF0863ECC8859E6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The average income of households that include any working-age people with disabilities is $27,500 less than the average household income of people without disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97421826C93C46FB9E413ADB386451F2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Stephen Beck, Jr., Achieving a Better Life Experience Act of 2014 provided for qualified ABLE programs, which provided eligible people with disabilities the opportunity to open tax-advantaged savings accounts without the risk of losing the benefits they need to participate in society.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7097AC6FC5F54316926BFB98E92A7B0A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>As of September 2022, there were 131,436 ABLE accounts open in the United States with an average balance of $8,623.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H57F140553EB64268B912C681FDDDFB8E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="HCB9D569222DE4FDEABA48E27EB6F5A0D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to encourage and assist individuals with disabilities with fewer resources to save using ABLE accounts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA05B215FF09495892D1756A55EEAFAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to increase uptake and continued utilization of ABLE accounts by people with disabilities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H06530D3FFE3B49BCA4EAA70E4534FC02"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to provide for a Federal match for new and existing ABLE accounts held by individuals with an annual income less than 200 percent of the Federal poverty limit. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H7D6BEB9ADCE54F6DACA432A196D8B034"><enum>4.</enum><header>Matching payments for ABLE account contributions by certain individuals</header><subsection id="HD6179B1E5AED491E83ED6CCAC0A21F2D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/65">chapter 65</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H08A264B031794004A0528815068502EC"><section id="H2CB972CBE09A4CE295D92D8E88376DAC"><enum>6434.</enum><header>Matching payments for ABLE account contributions by certain individuals</header><subsection id="H05F99EC6B4F84EE3926872D22DD29F24"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H41BCAAC6AA784737942E0F28CC5578AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Allowance of credit</header><text>Any individual who is the designated beneficiary of an ABLE account as of the last day of the taxable year and who makes qualified ABLE account contributions for such taxable year shall be allowed a credit for such taxable year in an amount equal to the applicable percentage of so much of the qualified ABLE account contributions made by such individual for the taxable year as does not exceed $2,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32BF551673294A90BE5136AE04CBA29B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Payment of credit</header><text>The credit under this section shall be—</text><subparagraph id="H81AE671B70B649899EED2882A5604162"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treated as allowed by subpart C of part IV of subchapter A of chapter 1, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07D2DEFA5BC046F0BA1B0310FF14A21D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>paid by the Secretary as a contribution (as soon as practicable after the individual has filed a tax return making a claim for such credit for the taxable year) to the ABLE account of the individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7B93555581C84894A9DA54875C5638A0" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Overall limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of the credit allowed under this section with respect to any individual shall not exceed the excess of—</text><paragraph id="HDED0B34D7E054BFBB344D8654947975D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the amount in effect under section 529A(b)(2)(B) for the taxable year, over</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B25BEA337EF4E2990828A94E6F20F25" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the amount of contributions made to the ABLE account of the individual for such taxable year. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8F34B2BF10A4D2FAE108663FED13273"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicable percentage</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7FC3736E18B1465B875AF26A1AE82D82"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), the applicable percentage is 100 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H92C6B9B400864C36863F823D7DD10EB3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Phaseout</header><text>The percentage under paragraph (1) shall be reduced (but not below zero) by the number of percentage points which bears the same ratio to 50 percentage points as—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCE0FE81252104EB3B8258C692AB879DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the excess of—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H716A9700DD3648D5AB41769A17B15E6D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the taxpayer's modified adjusted gross income for such taxable year, over</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA341BE093A1B49F7913805A5744A6457"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the applicable dollar amount, bears to</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98012427584245B2B66A55E332074339"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$20,000.</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">If any reduction determined under this paragraph is not a whole percentage point, such reduction shall be rounded to the next lowest whole percentage point. </continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H163D2865FD504F4B9649A1193D2A7960"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicable dollar amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The applicable dollar amount is—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6638AD7B036A49EE8282D17730B578A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a joint return, $56,000,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H832668104A5744A48C193FBD5BAB56C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a head of household (as defined in section 2(b)), <fraction>3/4</fraction> of the amount applicable under subparagraph (A), and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4C5F2BA25866483793CDB61C6EAA0E2D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in any other case, <fraction>1/2</fraction> of the amount applicable under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1F20449FA0B944968581F8E895250636"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Qualified ABLE account contributions</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="HEA1D7F21DF034FB09118EA8A7D73CA4B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified ABLE account contributions</term> means, with respect to any taxable year, the amount of contributions made by the individual to the ABLE account of which such individual is the designated beneficiary. Such term shall not include any amount attributable to a payment under subsection (a)(2). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H115F9ED90CE148EBB0064CD5E8F1E255"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reduction for certain distributions</header><subparagraph id="H9C8DEFFEC13D4661B75C439D1289C34F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The qualified ABLE account contributions determined under paragraph (1) for a taxable year shall be reduced (but not below zero) by the aggregate distributions received by the individual during the testing period from the ABLE account.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7CCC12937D64102AAFD781275D1BA44"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Testing period</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the testing period, with respect to a taxable year, is the period which includes—</text><clause id="H154A8D35512044979E8E53205679C755"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such taxable year,</text></clause><clause id="H0ED8728EA2294AECB8AC237CA90F850A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the 2 preceding taxable years, and</text></clause><clause id="H758EAC6754364F55B5640B58E09CB0D3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the period after such taxable year and before the due date (including extensions) for filing the return of tax for such taxable year.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF09A1DEF96A2403D92A98C2C2B2001BF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Excepted distributions</header><text>There shall not be taken into account under subparagraph (A) the amount of distributions under a qualified ABLE program (within the meaning of section 529A) that is equal to amounts not included in gross income with respect to such distributions under section 529A(c)(1)(B) (relating to distributions for qualified disability expenses). </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA845CB26B7844B3ABD2B3229255D70B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Treatment of distributions received by spouse of individual</header><text>For purposes of determining distributions received by an individual under subparagraph (A) for any taxable year, any distribution received by the spouse of such individual shall be treated as received by such individual if such individual and spouse file a joint return for such taxable year and for the taxable year during which the spouse receives the distribution.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H291EF2E9C0914EBFB5FE539F2E44BA5A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>ABLE account</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>ABLE account</term> has the meaning given such term under section 529A. </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1C470426BC6D457398988D1BF83EC104"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Other definitions and special rules</header><paragraph id="HA2628E33FF014951BD329E105412A084"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Modified adjusted gross income</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>modified adjusted gross income</term> means adjusted gross income determined without regard to sections 911, 931, and 933.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCD9D464EED8844C888B4648EAD931BF8"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Erroneous credits</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9661C5B7B01B46FE97E99D0A8C7CE17B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any contribution is erroneously paid under subsection (a)(2), including a payment that is not made to an ABLE account, the amount of such erroneous payment shall be treated as an underpayment of tax (other than for purposes of part II of subchapter A of chapter 68) for the taxable year in which the Secretary determines the payment is erroneous.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H316D9048686F40A897856EBB7826E572"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Distribution of erroneous credits</header><text>In the case of a contribution to which subparagraph (A) applies, section 72 shall not apply to the distribution of such contribution (and any income attributable thereto) if such distribution is received not later than the day prescribed by law (including extensions of time) for filing the individual’s return for such taxable year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC29000DF3D664BC58D53401AA56AC1C9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception from reduction or offset</header><text>Any payment made to any individual under this section shall not be—</text><subparagraph id="H9387B40EECFF473CB5A67B78FF0D279F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subject to reduction or offset pursuant to subsection (c), (d), (e), or (f) of section 6402 or any similar authority permitting offset, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84C82E760958475C82BFBC25F508D676"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reduced or offset by other assessed Federal taxes that would otherwise be subject to levy or collection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA2F276EE70034BDC8788ABA8F8179AED"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Inflation adjustments</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6563F6E2B9B94B72A3730E1500C94A3D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any taxable year beginning in a calendar year after 2027, the $56,000 amount in subsection (c)(3)(A) shall be increased by an amount equal to—</text><subparagraph id="HE1DA9ED4EC9F4B19AA5E01E535C03EBC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such dollar amount, multiplied by</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4AC9A42380CA47A78848A7A96EB4001F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year in which the taxable year begins, determined by substituting <quote>calendar year 2026</quote> for <quote>calendar year 2016</quote> in subparagraph (A)(ii) thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H327E6BDA3D5D4B9D8D20BC6B09A9B7BE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>Any increase determined under paragraph (1) shall be rounded to the nearest multiple of $1,000. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H073F6C5D51464DE1A5B420D1131B8907"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Treatment of Certain Possessions</header><paragraph id="H0C817A91D05A46F99FD55DF336AD6960"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Payments to possessions with mirror code tax systems</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall pay to each possession of the United States which has a mirror code tax system amounts equal to the loss (if any) to that possession by reason of the amendments made by this section. Such amounts shall be determined by the Secretary of the Treasury based on information provided by the government of the respective possession.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H93F2543E5F394310A89540767C43044E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Payments to other possessions</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall pay to each possession of the United States which does not have a mirror code tax system amounts estimated by the Secretary of the Treasury as being equal to the aggregate benefits (if any) that would have been provided to residents of such possession by reason of the amendments made by this section if a mirror code tax system had been in effect in such possession. The preceding sentence shall not apply unless the respective possession has a plan, which has been approved by the Secretary of the Treasury, under which such possession will promptly distribute such payments to its residents.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D1253CFA2054FD1A384BC7553E19731"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination with credit allowed against United States income taxes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No credit shall be allowed against United States income taxes under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6434">section 6434</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by this section) to any person—</text><subparagraph id="HB49721DAFA0044CA8794A03BFF567B94"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to whom a credit is allowed against taxes imposed by the possession by reason of the amendments made by this section, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2911FA3114FE434FA33E8DF1DF89EF20"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who is eligible for a payment under a plan described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C43A26752DD41D28AC8A57AB2D74D01"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Mirror code tax system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>mirror code tax system</quote> means, with respect to any possession of the United States, the income tax system of such possession if the income tax liability of the residents of such possession under such system is determined by reference to the income tax laws of the United States as if such possession were the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA0D6B29EF3A48CA8A6ACE9EBFB955D4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Treatment of payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of section 1324 of title 31, United States Code, the payments under this subsection shall be treated in the same manner as a refund due from a credit provision referred to in subsection (b)(2) of such section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9C45E0CD3D6747078D63D419937D4E7B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deficiencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6211">Section 6211(b)(4)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>and 6433</quote> and inserting <quote>6433, and 6434</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4DB8664BC9D648E9BDA2E6F20C31B602"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Payment authority</header><text>Section 1324(b)(2) of title 31, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>or 6433</quote> and inserting <quote>6433, or 6434</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1C04B2FB36A646418D70E0C50F2A5A34"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H65104F64CB3A40D98EFCC60C19D16601"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subpart A of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking section 25B (and the item related to such section in the table of sections for such subpart).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4696E893CA0745EDBCFFECE37E30B41A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The table of sections for subchapter B of chapter 65 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H89F075A58AB6403D84EDA98E69EA8EBD"><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="H2CB972CBE09A4CE295D92D8E88376DAC">Sec. 6434. Matching payments for ABLE account contributions by certain individuals.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2C29018B9FAE48BA87EB43A44A80725D"><enum>(f)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2026. </text></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H16A5E199D0F74D2B8C1A4359E2CE3243"><enum>5.</enum><header>Demographic reporting with respect to ABLE accounts</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5FD285C07764C0C8BD9A84638149F97"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/529A">Section 529A(d)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>In addition to the information required under the preceding sentence, each officer or employee having control of the qualified ABLE program of their designee shall include in reports provided to the Secretary demographic information (including race, gender, and disability type) relating to the designated beneficiaries of ABLE accounts under the program.</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA539391D02EE4146AD62C2697E638DED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to reports made after the date of the enactment of this section. </text></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H28EE78DCE0334902B0E21D0D2C312E3E"><enum>6.</enum><header>Grants to promote use of ABLE accounts and the matching contribution credit</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF07C017E9804F49BB33DBACDC007967"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury (or the Secretary's delegate) may award grants to States to enable States to promote ABLE accounts (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/529A">section 529A(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) and matching payments for contributions to such accounts (as provided under section 6434 of such Code, as added by this Act). </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H365613F77FC14B5FA3F6BAECE42ABF62"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2029.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

