<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF7B03236822F4C0DA131F3B2EE2D9C36" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 693 IH: VA medical Center Absence and Notification Timeline Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 693</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000809">Mr. Womack</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To limit the detailing of directors of medical centers of the Department of Veterans Affairs to different positions within the Department, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HB0252FDFD0564DF39BE26866F4DBCB54" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7DB5B69C7C3246E88D474E461520213F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>VA medical Center Absence and Notification Timeline Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>VACANT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD3C1A97D8FB94147B20B97313E4BC6EA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitation on detail of directors of medical centers of Department of Veterans Affairs to different positions</header> <subsection id="H9032E24355F64D6D82ACFFB98B33109C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification</header> <paragraph id="H6C50170A3FDE4EA1AE9B4BB84740C451"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after detailing a director of a medical center of the Department of Veterans Affairs to a different position within the Department, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall notify the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives of such detail.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H56B2E1F5E84441CAA077C0ED6B8A6189"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>The notification required by paragraph (1) shall include, with respect to a director of a medical center who is detailed to a different position within the Department, the following information:</text> <subparagraph id="HA57B0258D61B4C2098D2F3CA822F38EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The location at which the director is detailed.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8C359880CFFB4F4BAFE0B1DE45FD941E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The position title of the detail.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFDC487120E4844568C84998787919807"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The estimated time the director is expected to be absent from their duties at the medical center.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H947E12B8CF33483997DC15DE1DEB0E44"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Such other information as the Secretary may determine appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBC8CDCB9FC3441C18E18CA75686DAFE9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appointment of acting director</header><text>Not later than 120 days after detailing a director of a medical center of the Department to a different position within the Department, the Secretary shall appoint an individual as acting director of such medical center with all of the authority and responsibilities of the detailed director.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4D8EC5013A1446DAAE5C26C1873D7E5F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Update on detail</header><text>Not later than 120 days after detailing a director of a medical center of the Department to a different position within the Department, and not less frequently than every 30 days thereafter while the detail is in effect or while the director position at the medical center is vacant, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives an update regarding the status of the detail.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBFE9DB826E1842B2B3C34A4D38BB0F66"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Return to position or reassignment</header> <paragraph id="H2B8F1811772C480496310EE375D9DD28"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), not later than 180 days after detailing a director of a medical center of the Department to a different position within the Department, for a reason other than an ongoing investigation or administrative action with respect to the director, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB5191CE856CC4EBB908C9287667C097F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>return the individual to the position as director of the medical center; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE35204BDCE1941D78FD50DAA614FBA9E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reassign the individual from the position as director of the medical center and begin the process of hiring a new director for such position.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAE06EBBECFBE4327877198219A3EFB24"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header> 
<subparagraph id="H1888026311D9427DAE8C2B47AB6F4C19"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may waive the requirement under paragraph (1) with respect to an individual for successive 90-day increments for a total period of not more than 540 days from the original date the individual was detailed away from their position as director of a medical center.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HED43647B2A514E44A2556DF7B8AE672C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>Not later than 30 days after exercising a waiver under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall notify Congress of the waiver and provide to Congress information as to why the waiver is necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


