<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H04E5F3C7544F431991B3D0B792AB57CA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3276 IH: Healthy Future Students and Earth Pilot Program Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3276</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act to establish a pilot grant program to make grants to school food authorities to provide 100 percent plant-based food and milk options, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H420A9BB34EB443F6A6C8B762F74823C6" style="OLC"><section id="H5F357786E1544C4387702493ED2EDF1C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthy Future Students and Earth Pilot Program Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HDC18E58188C94827BC887333361D6999"><enum>2.</enum><header>Plant-based foods in schools</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 18 of the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1769">42 U.S.C. 1769</external-xref>) is amended by adding after subsection (c) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H72D207EBF67A444A9CB60AEB308BFF30" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H5025AD07AF15493D965955063464F142"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Pilot grant program for 100 percent plant-Based food options</header><paragraph id="HAAFF820F288146A2A910088E090B90D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and carry out a pilot grant program to award grants to eligible school food authorities to carry out the activities described in paragraph (4).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B81D972C9994FA293216D362E205E67"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In general</header><subparagraph id="HB3ACF9721DF64A679BEC0BC945C1A934"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Term</header><text>The term of a grant awarded under this subsection shall be 3 years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D31599C555446489BF01252384A5DA5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall, to the extent practicable, award grants of diverse amounts. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3368EAB342BD4F48A7FB419BA4E16E7F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><subparagraph id="HDCC4DF9E426F487887272F322889E9A0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an eligible school food authority shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including—</text><clause id="H08FB85A7AE7442BE9048F1E6C39561FB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a participatory evaluation plan; and</text></clause><clause id="H83B4A67692BD4088BDA0119CC7F0D031"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a plan for providing culturally appropriate meals.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA75BCFC729D24FE4BD766714661BDC46"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the maximum extent practicable, in awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall give priority to an eligible school food authority that will use the grant funds to—</text><clause id="H4011AD8BDE974B95A0F623ABEEF8F28F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>serve a high proportion of children who are eligible for free or reduced price meals;</text></clause><clause id="H779A702B60AE49CAAA045F33C8261DC3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>demonstrate collaboration with nongovernmental and community-based organizations, agricultural producers, and other community partners with respect to the activities described in paragraph (4);</text></clause><clause id="HCE2D03A5C80540749E671391E022217E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>incorporate experiential and culturally appropriate plant-based food, nutrition, or agricultural education activities related to 100 percent plant-based food options in the classroom;</text></clause><clause id="H70B4463F7179415FB1C88D41ADF159C2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>incorporate organically produced 100 percent plant-based food options; and</text></clause><clause id="H2E50DE4E285241D8A8D257FBF7BBE953"><enum>(v)</enum><text>meets any other criteria that the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H06EA3FBB429F4E7FB7FD1E76EACFC8B4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A grant awarded under this subsection may be used for any of the following activities:</text><subparagraph id="H8210FBD593F54ABD9482403FCEC9868C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To contract with qualified third parties for professional development training for food service personnel on serving (including preparing, procuring, marketing, and creating menus) 100 percent plant-based food options.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFEDA680C70C74506904D95B73F1A9761"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To provide compensation, for each employee who participates in the professional development training described in subparagraph (A), at the regular rate of pay of such employee.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41EA2AD52CE24FBF94C6877622FF8BFB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>To provide technical assistance and student engagement and education on 100 percent plant-based food options, including providing taste tests, recipe development, and culinary education.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7DCE3E5DD6834471AB1C877BCC773ED9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>To provide compensation for additional work relating to serving meals that include a 100 percent plant-based food option.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07A8051116B84D6C9D648B9C0AE8772E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>To conduct outreach to, and cover costs of procurement of foods from, agricultural producers of 100 percent plant-based food options, including—</text><clause id="H2B52EE321FF3451EA8A7B7272126492E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>underserved producers;</text></clause><clause id="HA39BE776B8C54EB9AF8353295A1EA4F8" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>limited resource farmers or ranchers, as defined by the Secretary;</text></clause><clause id="H864AB381C09D4143BF59FF4A5478D525" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>producers on a certified organic farm; and</text></clause><clause id="HDD02C262EEFD434F85B64B77768D758B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>local farmers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EFFB1F879B24C9496DA7B6F20B2D9FC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Reports</header><subparagraph id="HB8972B1E368D453BBA7208807BD171B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Recordkeeping required</header><text>Each eligible school food authority awarded a grant under this subsection shall keep records of the 100 percent plant-based food options served pursuant to this subsection as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD10C130E9DE4BF38111D347DDC5AE1A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report required by school food authorities</header><text>Not later than 1 year after receiving a grant under this subsection, and annually for the duration of the grant term described in paragraph (2)(A), a school food authority shall submit to the Secretary a report on the pilot grant program, including information on—</text><clause id="HC1C29348841542AC98CCD8D3874B45BD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of 100 percent plant-based food options that the school food authority served during the grant period compared with the preceding school year;</text></clause><clause id="HDAF3575985C54158ADD53E2F0EF322FD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of schools served by the school food authority pursuant to the grant;</text></clause><clause id="H1D6ACAA8E3384C34AA8C60D4F52BF94F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of students served by the school food authority pursuant to the grant; and</text></clause><clause id="HBBA8D0C644104961AD623068720919E5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>how the school food authority used the grant funds.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA2DEF7EA65E4729AFCBF8D3F3698E9F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Report by Secretary</header><text>With respect to each school year during which the Secretary receives the report required under subparagraph (B), the Secretary shall, not later than 1 year after the date that is the last day of such school year, submit to Congress a report that includes—</text><clause id="H062E358EDCD5462AB65C297EBA853088"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a summary of the reports received during such school year; and</text></clause><clause id="HA28DCEEAFBFB45E3996F10D7AF5B7884"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such information with respect to the pilot program as the Secretary determines to be relevant.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD444302CBFBF4A1BA2BE58EA207A958A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall provide technical assistance and information to assist school food authorities—</text><subparagraph id="H0E664339AEE04AE3A3DE79A11168022F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to facilitate the coordination and sharing of information and resources that may be applicable to the activities described in paragraph (4); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63BA3F63144447F694CABF680CB16956"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to collect and share information on best practices.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFA06FDCFCAE4C2D955832C53B45AB58"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection $10,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available through fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC51D3782486946B491252FEE7A3B0331"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H3E4F650164884959A637D5457B77D715"><enum>(A)</enum><header>100 percent plant-based food option</header><text>The term <term>100 percent plant-based food option</term> means a breakfast or lunch meal option or component that—</text><clause id="H6CAF5FDAC0C64066B29E944432D997ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>includes a meat alternate as described in—</text><subclause id="H2DFF652A645E4A89AD73232007546256"><enum>(I)</enum><text>section 210.10 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations); or</text></subclause><subclause id="H0B40C2F506FD41D1A5CC35BA32E05865"><enum>(II)</enum><text>appendix A to part 210 of 7, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations); and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H2EDC3B55E926408E8A855B922B00EE4D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>does not contain any animal products or byproducts, such as meat, poultry, honey, fish, dairy, or eggs.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H978E1E54A68A4E9D9F81187831282FB5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Beginning farmer or rancher</header><text>The term <term>beginning farmer or rancher</term> has the meaning given such term in section 343(a) of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1991">7 U.S.C. 1991(a)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD986F6C89E044AC5BEBAA0D2EAE8AD03"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Eligible school food authority</header><text>The term <term>eligible school food authority</term> means a school food authority for which 50 percent or more of the students served by such school food authority are eligible for free or reduced price lunch under this Act or free or reduced price breakfast under section 4 of the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1773">42 U.S.C. 1773</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A44141346034631B971FC450ACEB352"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Food, Agriculture, Conservation, and Trade Act terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>certified organic farm</term>, <term>organically produced</term>, and <term>producer</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 2103 of the Food, Agriculture, Conservation, and Trade Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/6502">7 U.S.C. 6502</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18CEB84859C741F4A3F7617F3ED40DE2"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Underserved producer</header><text>The term <term>underserved producer</term> means an individual (including a member of an Indian Tribe) that is—</text><clause id="H52F68A49C8A147F5AC987F4132546C18"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a beginning farmer or rancher;</text></clause><clause id="H7F096207F2394C0D9FF7B1E32F7FCDA8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a veteran farmer or rancher; or</text></clause><clause id="HE03F3A5AE874478AAA36C4175673AC67"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a socially disadvantaged farmer or rancher.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD732720341842B4AFA6C2B351E7FB30"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Veteran farmer or rancher</header><text>The term <term>veteran farmer or rancher</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2501(a) of the Food, Agriculture, Conservation, and Trade Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2279">7 U.S.C. 2279(a)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H6D5BB37ED0AC4DF48BC8880DF3E6150A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Accommodating dietary requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 9(a) of the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1758">42 U.S.C. 1758(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE3695AFBB9AB4D00AD47D9153AB84CD8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="HB61BC75A779F4FA09A521B39F7133A9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by amending clause (i) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="HBB36F4A0AE7F4305B31F6ED4D99598F1" style="OLC"><clause id="H025D841DC84A4F0FBADDEE46E5A4EB6F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall not—</text><subclause id="H7AF6818D9D624D97BC2CF2F15367AF6F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be construed to prohibit the substitution of foods to accommodate the medical needs of individual students; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HC4C1F256744A45D1A64E856BA3BE3C1B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>be construed to prohibit the nutritionally equivalent substitution of foods to accommodate religiously based or other special dietary needs of individual students; and</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55BC762760334CEF8D6A913877D8C348"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>lower-fat versions of foods commonly used in the school lunch program under this Act</quote> and inserting <quote>foods that comply with the meal patterns prescribed by the Secretary</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA4E6EE95A634E0CBEAA2EA88DF16696"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><subparagraph id="H83D323A110F3487C98BBFF47820E9950"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (A)(iii) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="HFA8A71C8C7CC40159B18D929432F7696" style="OLC"><clause id="H02F59A60EC744BC49AF412A6DFB0E2EF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>shall provide, as a reasonable accommodation under the Americans with Disabilities Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>) and section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>), a substitute for fluid milk for a student whose disability restricts their diet.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE83573D27988477586D97B8AEF68BD2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (B) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H4DEE9D98FA994F6D981594F4C7EC3FCF" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H370976F784B44E789E8DD7D44D473A4B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other substitutions</header><clause id="H7BBD05CBD8D346EBA4515FA1E20584C6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Standards for required substitution</header><subclause id="H8D2A9BF8B2A148FA885AB8904A5703B1"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a student for whom fluid milk is not nutritionally appropriate due to a medical or other special dietary need other than a disability described in subparagraph (A)(iii) (as determined by the school in consultation with the parent or legal guardian of such student), a school shall substitute, for the fluid milk provided under subparagraph (A), a nondairy beverage that meets the nutritional needs of such student.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6521B83BD0B349A88CEBBAB25076AD47"><enum>(II)</enum><text>A school shall substitute, for the fluid milk provided under subparagraph (A), a nondairy beverage that is nutritionally equivalent to fluid milk and meets nutritional standards established by the Secretary if the parent or legal guardian of such student submits a written request for such substitution.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HD3612B76CB7D4E03B1FFCFBA78EB5038"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Standards for discretionary substitution</header><text>A school may offer each student a nondairy beverage as a substitute for fluid milk that is nutritionally equivalent to fluid milk and meets nutritional standards established by the Secretary.</text></clause><clause id="H52EDF9191A384673B32712D707C6759E"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Excess expenses</header><text>Except as provided under clause (iv), expenses incurred by providing substitutions under clauses (i) and (ii) that are in excess of expenses covered by reimbursements under this Act shall be paid by the school food authority.</text></clause><clause id="HD14A07E34365462AADC95F5F016721E3"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><subclause id="HAF77CEC267FE4B28ABDDB68E4D499BAC"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Program authorized</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, the Secretary shall establish and carry out a pilot grant program to award grants to eligible school food authorities to carry out subclause (III).</text></subclause><subclause id="H2508D93EE9EB434796B4C4334E2CC718"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this clause, the Secretary may give priority to—</text><item id="H28E154029C6F41B79978C880170AA144"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>an eligible school food authority that serves high proportions of students with high rates of lactose intolerance; and</text></item><item id="H2CF9439B91274C9396ED178D68A273DF"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an eligible school food authority that demonstrates, as part of the application for a grant under this clause, a need for nondairy beverages for students served by such school food authority due to dietary reasons.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H18895F2F4002469BBA1460DFEDEF0B13"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A school food authority shall use grant funds awarded under this clause to reimburse the full cost of providing nondairy beverages as substitutes for fluid milk under clause (i)(I) incurred by such school food authority.</text></subclause><subclause id="H00E3373E08274EB68B4FE65BF0013C0F"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Reports</header><item id="HAF7AD803D14241E9A84BBAFF89C6F1C2"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Annual report by school food authority</header><text>Not later than 1 year after receiving a grant under this clause, and on an annual basis for the duration of the pilot program thereafter, a school food authority shall submit to the Secretary a report on the pilot grant program, including information with respect to—</text><subitem id="H2520F551FCCB4B56925EDC1D1E49160B"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the number of schools served by the school food authority pursuant to the grant; and</text></subitem><subitem id="HA6F810B02E9B4D5585B44A4FE74F3549"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the number of students served by the school food authority pursuant to the grant.</text></subitem></item><item id="H29B75F479F054DC1BA8D1FA9CB78418B"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Final report by school food authority</header><text>The report that is the final report submitted under item (aa) shall include, in addition to the information required under subitems (AA) and (BB) of such item—</text><subitem id="H26122FDE7603429DA653765F146F2B35"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the number of nondairy beverages as substitutes for fluid milk that the school food authority served during the grant period; compared with</text></subitem><subitem id="HA86F68B0E44C40ACA5EA69D58C7E5F8E"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the number of nondairy beverages as substitutes for fluid milk that the school food authority served during the school year immediately preceding the start of the grant period.</text></subitem></item><item id="H46DA892E40914CDF8C419085A813A975"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Report by the Secretary</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date described in subclause (V), the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes a summary of the information included in the reports received under this subclause and any such information with respect to the pilot program the Secretary determines to be relevant.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H64F83EBFC2A84A6CA54074EEF59302FE"><enum>(V)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority to carry out this clause shall terminate on the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph.</text></subclause><subclause id="H8828D260BC9041ADAB60B6E4CB7208A0"><enum>(VI)</enum><header>Eligible school food authority defined</header><text>In this clause, the term <term>eligible school food authority</term> means a school food authority for which at least 50 percent of the students served by such school food authority are eligible for free or reduced price lunch under this Act or free or reduced price breakfast under section 4 of the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1773">42 U.S.C. 1773</external-xref>).</text></subclause><subclause id="H4C8E063BAA3741E9B9E476DA332348D8"><enum>(VII)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this clause $2,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available until the date described in subclause (V).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

