<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H61C2C244698C4701BA4EC69B81B43C6B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6531 IH: Training Responsible And Informed National VA Employees Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6531</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231130">November 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="V000135">Mr. Van Orden</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to develop a training program for certain senior executives and supervisors employed by the Department of Veterans Affairs.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE134FF8FCBB94EB296D0D00EA648A63B" style="OLC"><section id="H95287383238044E9B27794FB569089E0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Training Responsible And Informed National VA Employees Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TRAIN VA Employees Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF9EA40AF397C469B8956B689349168A1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Training program for certain senior executives and supervisors</header><subsection id="HF094CD3EA5DC4891B16113185AE908E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall develop a training program for all covered employees. Such training shall be mandatory for all such covered employees and for any individual who is hired to be such an covered employee.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9F88D4CB0E974B34979044E0BF258846"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing the training required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall consult with the heads of at least three other Federal departments and agencies, including the Department of Defense, to gather information about how such departments and agencies approach management training.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEEE04E572B534F3EBFF4D5A776E0D54A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Current employees</header><text>Any individual who as of the date of the enactment of this Act is an covered employee shall be required, as a condition of continued employment at the Department of Veterans Affairs, to complete the training program developed under subsection (a) by not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCAEF7CFDA85A4B2FAE72824601855238"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Refresher training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall develop a refresher training program for the program required under subsection (a), and each covered employee shall be required, as a condition of continued employment at the Department of Veterans Affairs, to complete such refresher training once every two years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6B67AB2849CF498387F6ADA320520FE9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Design of training</header><text>The training program required under subsection (a) shall be designed using principles of adult learning and industry standard instructional design. To the extent practicable, the training shall—</text><paragraph id="HB7AC4A14BA684AFA8CF0E5454D4A3F34"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be instructor-based and provided in-person; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFAE99F2619647E589BADCE514D269BA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>focus on—</text><subparagraph id="H07B57884900C428FB34286F3201AE66A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>developing and discussing relevant performance goals and objectives with the employees they supervise;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC075F41101AD432AA9EE745F6A1BD004"><enum>(B)</enum><text>communicating and discussing employees’ progress relative to performance goals and objectives, and conducting performance appraisals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12F7289D88D14DE39D6C06871A317E58"><enum>(C)</enum><text>mentoring and motivating employees and improving employee engagement, performance, and productivity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H419B648FFF4845FCA42828EBE3562230"><enum>(D)</enum><text>effectively managing employees with unacceptable performance, including training to understand the disciplinary options and procedures available to the supervisor;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF15E999A99742E4BEFED33143E8B6BE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>prohibited personnel practices, employee rights, and the procedures and processes used to enforce employee rights;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF41C8CF7264E408FB693E8870C6D30F8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>effectively using the probationary period to examine whether an employee has demonstrated successful performance or conduct to continue past the probationary period;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECBB3376AE57414D9C878F8BB6DC1F0C"><enum>(G)</enum><text>addressing reports of a hostile work environment, retaliation, or harassment of, or by, another supervisor or employee; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86C972667D184640A101F66F8AD2773E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>collaborating with human resources employees to recruit, select, appraise, and reward employees to build a workforce based on organizational goals, budget considerations, and staffing needs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD6631D2CB674FF684615CEE38EAB93D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>carrying out the duties or responsibilities of a supervisor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H47C269898AA94171ADC63EBEC104D27E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Covered employee defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>covered employee</quote> means an employee of the Department of Veterans Affairs who is— </text><paragraph id="H45C71F4BB07E4D8380DD2972166534C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a supervisor (as defined in section 7103(a) of title 5, United States Code); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F97595C5DB04767AD89A532D12C760D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a covered individual under section 713 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

