<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC7B624782015471FA63C7CB37A947CB8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 5377 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to extend and modify certain authorities and requirements relating to the Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5377</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to extend and modify certain authorities and requirements relating to the Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD965DAAA9ECB44C6B85BD321692C1517" style="OLC"><section id="HD1D5DC9A62C1487A9002B9B974409926" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Extension of temporary clarification of licensure requirements for contractor medical professionals to perform medical disability examinations for Department of Veterans Affairs under pilot program for use of contract physicians for disability examinations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2002(a)(4) of the Johnny Isakson and David P. Roe, M.D. Veterans Health Care and Benefits Improvement Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/315">Public Law 116–315</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/5101">38 U.S.C. 5101</external-xref> note) is amended by striking <quote>three years</quote> and inserting <quote>five years</quote>.</text></section><section id="HE18411AD57704F9C864E9333312E536E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Extension of period of applicability of certain relief for recipients of Department of Veterans Affairs educational assistance affected by closure or disapproval of educational institution</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 3699(c)(2)(C) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>September 30, 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>September 30, 2025</quote>.</text></section><section id="H1F4C9DECFB134AECB69E7E209F1BD1E7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Extension of authorization of appropriations for Department of Veterans Affairs emergency preparedness</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8117(g) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>2023</quote> and inserting <quote>2028</quote>.</text></section><section id="H67FAFB90316D4BF4BD44CAB746AF2EF2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Modification of certain housing loan fees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The loan fee table in section 3729(b)(2) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>November 14, 2031</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>November 15, 2031</quote>. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

