<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC4D43C9D35E6479CAB160E4EEAEFDE7A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6307 IH: Creating Legal Accountability for Rogue Innovators and Technology Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6307</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231108">November 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence (Permanent Select)</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit certain actions and require reporting to defend against the economic and national security risks posed by foreign adversarial blockchain networks, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H252A67197F0448B4893B61D0221999E2" style="OLC"><section id="H56C372299AB94924BE423DB3CA22E063" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Creating Legal Accountability for Rogue Innovators and Technology Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CLARITY Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H166348DE01FD40AEB280DA718CC36AB5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; sense of Congress</header><subsection id="H96A17AE216BD43DDAB7E61318B906451"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HAA5C79D784CC4242A131935032BC8E60"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Blockchain service activities by governments and organizations that are adversaries of the United States can create risks to the economic, national security and foreign policy interests of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB32792D2C9914F9F848184811257C71D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Blockchain-based Services Network of the People's Republic of China, and unregulated, self-proclaimed <quote>supra-national</quote> companies pose risks to the national security and foreign policy interests of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H23CD2755C741444FB92E9385DCDF23E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the development of a Federal Government strategy to protect the United States from risks created from the Blockchain-based Services Network of the People’s Republic of China and other foreign adversarial blockchain network infrastructure is essential to the national security and economic security of the United States. </text></subsection></section><section id="HDEDE51FEC9D445029F16C6D72FF22217"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibitions relating to covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services</header><subsection id="H5273DBF8A7BA469D96D67C049EEC06E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on acquisition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No head of an executive agency may acquire, or enter into, extend, or renew a contract or other agreement for, any equipment, system, or service that uses covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services as a substantial or essential component of, or critical technology as part of, such equipment, system, or service.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC586A16CFCBC4268B59584E6D7FCD824"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on loan and grant funds</header><paragraph id="H9830D050364F428C9458365367C4D09E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No head of an executive agency may obligate or expend loan or grant funds to acquire, or enter into, extend, or renew a contract or other agreement for, an equipment, system, or service described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFFCFE1DE51B4C4DA139046FFC04C7CA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In implementing the prohibition under paragraph (1), the heads of executive agencies administering loan, grant, or subsidy programs, including the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Secretary of Commerce, shall prioritize available funding and technical support to assist affected businesses, institutions, and organizations as is reasonably necessary for those affected entities to transition from covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services, to acquire replacement equipment and services, and to ensure that communications service to users and customers is sustained.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2E8DB0ED1738416999157675CB66FD56" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in subsection (a) or (b) shall be construed to—</text><paragraph id="H676B5B8F06484E678295F12066B8110A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prohibit the head of an executive agency from acquiring from an entity, or entering into, extending, or renewing a contract or other agreement with an entity for, a service that connects to the facilities of a third party, such as blockchain protocols, or interconnection arrangements; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5C61E668B8D4D249B833AD05ABB84A7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>cover wireless telecommunications equipment or third-party validators that cannot route or redirect user data traffic or permit visibility into any user data or packets that such equipment transmits or otherwise handles.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE551CDF172734C2ABEB7BA0F740DB109"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prohibitions under subsections (a) and (b) shall take effect on the date that is 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA3D2FD6327254D7CBE5AF8A6DE8DCFB8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><paragraph id="H3E1B2DE6221E475490864B72F16D854D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Executive agencies</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), beginning on the effective date under subsection (d), the head of an executive agency may, for a period of not more than 2 years per waiver, issue a waiver of the requirements under subsection (a) with respect to an entity that requests such a waiver. The waiver may be provided only if the entity seeking the waiver—</text><subparagraph id="H2F1A54ADF06C42578B5F573CB7880D84"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides a compelling justification for the additional time to implement the requirements under such subsection, as determined by the head of the executive agency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0344CE7FD124998AB810CF17E57B7A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submits to the head of the executive agency, who shall not later than 30 days thereafter submit to the appropriate congressional committees, a full and complete laydown of the presences of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services in the entity’s supply chain and a phase-out plan to eliminate such covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D5ACBC19D45475DA4458BD4B47CD2FE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements of the intelligence community</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the effective date under subsection (d), each head of an element of the intelligence community may waive the requirements under subsection (a) if such head determines the waiver is in the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0CF122B876124DD1A58D12B564E1F1D0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reports to defend against risks posed by covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services</header><subsection id="HFF7F2666F320409A852A218A54E28043"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of State, and the Director of National Intelligence shall jointly, and in consultation with the officials specified in subsection (b), submit to Congress a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="H2C1918DCD7ED4AEB80A358C6E47C2C52"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of interagency policies and procedures to defend the United States financial markets, United States sanctions, United States business interests in the People's Republic of China, and global supply chains from the economic and national security risks posed by covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF44AA77E32384BE699ECB693725384F1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of commercial and public administration activities used by the Government of the People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party involving the entities listed under subparagraphs (A) through (E) of section 7(2), including militarization, industrialization, international trade, and other commercial activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1172D71FB45B4ACEA296FBA73D1B9860"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> An assessment of the foreign policy and national security risks to the United States relating to transactions using covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services, including circumvention of United States and international sanctions, including through the Society for Worldwide Interbank Financial Telecommunication (commonly known as <quote>SWIFT</quote>) payments system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C8E6188DE3946BD9C92D2EC4F8B3C83"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of data collection, cybersecurity risks, and the use of data that involves United States persons by the Government of the People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party involving transactions relating to covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EA1757DF48C4C459D8020A558A73311"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the use of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services to collect data as part of the social credit system of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AC2098BB41647A9B380F84EBFBFF945"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the impact and national security risks of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services on data collection, cross-border payments, and economic integration, including with respect to countries participating in the Belt and Road Initiative of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2D8DBF7D5984045A0EC7AA47F21CE21"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the impact of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services on the United States blockchain technology and distributed ledger technology industries, to include an assessment of its commercial adoption globally and its integration with other smart city technologies in the United States and internationally. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB728FB0EC5474CA1AE872DB067526D22"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the technologies, system architectures, and protocols underpinning covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services, and recommendations with respect to strengthening export controls for United States technologies relating to the development and implementation of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CA4E5722E8E45D7B2631AE78F2DEE65"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the impact of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services on international illicit finance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E60A835C6B2433D9A17FCF0AC3675F2"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the impact of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services on global trade, investment, and other activities and how increased use of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services may affect the status and future of the United States dollar as the world reserve currency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A62F11D904C4E56AC05500A60EE24A7"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of how covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services fit into the national security and economic objectives of the People’s Republic of China and the Chinese Communist Party, along with other foreign adversaries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30730B7674E043CE9C0431C55A452778"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of coordination between the United States and allies of the United States with respect to the national security risks and best practices relating to covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE32FC222832C4100B98BB499F3D721C2"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other recommendations of the Secretary of Treasury, the Secretary of State, or the Director of National Intelligence regarding the foreign policy and national security implications of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFD9ED90F447D405DA0CF63262CFCBD97"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Officials specified</header><text>The officials specified in this subsection include the following:</text><paragraph id="H9C87D828C9FB4A66831D0556F52AF24A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA95D944E424A432896140F8167E735EA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary of Commerce. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AEB01176DF5476383B341DB8CB765A5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United States Trade Representative. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEC65592D92542ABB1123B115C593A08"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Attorney General.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H486ABD06EF1944CEBC48F28DC1D615DD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Chairman of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF73D0864B8784778B749B5C1F7664834"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology and the Under Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCDF4E8485844447BECB670F1FCE2C9B" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary of Commerce for Industry and Security of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H22A8F03BA356472A8400C6977D29B65E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text>Each report required by subsection (a) may be submitted in classified form, but if so submitted shall include an unclassified executive summary.</text></subsection></section><section id="H8F216630844E4D92B7E0BDA4295E7F40"><enum>5.</enum><header>Recommendations for Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after each date on which a report is submitted under section 4, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of State, and the Director of National Intelligence shall jointly submit to Congress a set of recommendations that contain— </text><paragraph id="HAD76BA85CDFF453B874919C7DCD11C6D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of existing enforcement actions that may be used to defend the United States from risks identified in the report; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB521574D616340CDA4BAF260B239C31D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an action-item plan on steps Congress may take to address such risks.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H349F804BFDF9429291FFD7FED075CFE4"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report on malign entities in blockchain and distributed ledger technology industry</header><subsection id="HA0ACE7833FA849DD8D81ABAA3A62D01A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of State, and the Director of National Intelligence shall jointly, and in consultation with the officials specified in section 5(b), submit to Congress a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="HBF29672E668341EF826CB542DF4110C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A list of countries, proxies, firms, and technologies that are malign in the blockchain and distributed ledger technology industry.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70D3063845E6434AB0281E8C0778AC91"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of what harms such countries, proxies, firms, and technologies cause to United States interests and sanctions enforcement, the use of the United States dollar, and international anti-money laundering and countering the financing of terrorism standards.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD06283FD25C646C98C53BC524243C92B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of what mitigating strategies the United States may use to counter such harms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4109AB451FDF4A20B8FE61529F15EAB8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations on how to add to or modify the list of covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services in order to capture new networks that emerge from foreign adversaries. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A8AE77C1ABE478CB4CE9372443E44B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) may be submitted in classified form, but if so submitted shall include an unclassified executive summary.</text></subsection></section><section id="H599357A41AF44195A8CBEC4BACD0896E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>7.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H6159E6B44E7847CAAA65D7B314E41A76" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term>’ means—</text><subparagraph id="H5FA781D1BDD9427EB9E66252C05835FB" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Foreign Relations, and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H924DE2C5C2F8422E842A3BA6A737D9F8" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Intelligence, and the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H218242131A514BEF8521F1C6A366B2D4" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services</quote> means distributed ledger technology and blockchain equipment or services of or originating from a foreign adversary, including any of the following parent companies or subsidiaries thereof: </text><subparagraph id="H82A6F7977788436EB51CB9A877B3EFEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Blockchain-based Services Network.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C625A895B764895A93CF5E0B7A80DF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Spartan Network.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82F13DB315864F1DAA7340BAD879F603"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Conflux Network.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H121393877C634C6E90843620D0B5AA98"><enum>(D)</enum><text>iFinex, Inc.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB8AD50133D149F2A6AF7545EDE34E87"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Red Date Technology Co., Ltd.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F66082F2DBA45D2B8E8ECD4D9194962" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Executive agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>executive agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 133 of title 41, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0764B0F73B74F5DB2B49B86FB49C004" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Foreign adversary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>foreign adversary</term> has the meaning given such term in section 7.2 of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63BCFCD4455F4FCDAD35CD614DF99EA0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Intelligence community</header><text>The term <quote>intelligence community</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

