<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H605AE5837B5D456A872D66AE4230C359" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2540 IH: End Child Poverty Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2540</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230406">April 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a universal child assistance program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H852FE604363845E4971AA6DBBDE3E20B" style="OLC"><section id="H5CABEA6831B048E48A42B2A9D2220E74" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>End Child Poverty Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H770909F17EBE44F2B3AE87CC0BA4F9A8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>2.</enum><header>Universal child assistance program</header><subsection id="H48568D316D194B5C88F5992C30250127"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H46B1DD1EF89147C9B338BFBD64E8B929"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commissioner</header><text>The term <quote>Commissioner</quote> means the Commissioner of Social Security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18698266FDAC451AB2082B42324725E7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deputy commissioner</header><text>The term <quote>Deputy Commissioner</quote> means the Deputy Commissioner of the Office of Universal Child Assistance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64800046433C43AA833703C36DCD734A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualifying child</header><text>The term <quote>qualifying child</quote> means, with respect to a month, an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="HF2BABB71C7DD4BA8AED4BE9257738C9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>resides in the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF82A8FEDF0FE4C8584DBB54CE20BDAB6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is—</text><clause id="HA1D3549F2A454152BAA653600EDED10C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a citizen or national of the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="H1F3A3E9A4B874717B52628E92F071D8C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a qualified alien (as defined in section 431 of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1641">8 U.S.C. 1641</external-xref>)); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCABF87441B174B7897B1A5E7CAE62174"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is less than 19 years old on the last day of such month.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9DCB3B71686B4B5FB7E6E59469B4FE21"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of office of universal child assistance</header><paragraph id="H40F75739F64D4D49A1C8D0D32808944C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established within the Social Security Administration an office to be known as the Office of Universal Child Assistance. The Office shall be headed by a Deputy Commissioner who shall be appointed by the Commissioner of Social Security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8014E4D7F6684E1CB5220108DF6A924F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Responsibilities of deputy commissioner</header><text>The Commissioner, acting through the Deputy Commissioner, shall be responsible for—</text><subparagraph id="H616F9238C1A8454F88D56CCB91552284"><enum>(A)</enum><text>hiring personnel and making employment decisions with regard to such personnel;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA8A2AC79D364728B30E6AEADD822155"><enum>(B)</enum><text>issuing such regulations as may be necessary to carry out the purposes of this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H797892E84D48427CB7282560BBC38384"><enum>(C)</enum><text>entering into cooperative agreements with other agencies and departments to ensure the efficiency of the administration of the program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H963B74BAF582445D8F5A5691C43C58F7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>determining eligibility for child assistance payments under subsection (c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CBEB66070BA41599EF59AC8438F8662"><enum>(E)</enum><text>making timely child assistance payments to qualified children in accordance with this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD119E32ED0DF42CF9782EFD2D5EB454F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>establishing and maintaining a system of records relating to the administration of this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14C2C4553A4E41C8B589B45A3567A6AE"><enum>(G)</enum><text>preventing fraud and abuse relating to child assistance payments;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0598F6C55BB8478CA155C8E26D8DF02D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>providing information on request regarding eligibility requirements, the application process, payment amounts, and limitations on payments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0593926C09694A38AF8FB9B197A30613"><enum>(I)</enum><text>tailoring culturally and linguistically competent education and outreach toward increasing utilization rates of payments under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C18C19B3051453A9E01853C67A30F4B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Availability of data</header><text>The Commissioner shall make available to the Deputy Commissioner such data as the Commissioner determines necessary to enable the Deputy Commissioner to effectively carry out the responsibilities described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA5FCC3611BF474F835ED1735ADFBB5B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Child assistance payments</header><paragraph id="HDBF27D5B393844E9A95D90FC47133F06"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For every month beginning after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commissioner shall pay to each qualified child who has in effect an application approved under subsection (d) a child assistance payment in an amount equal to the child assistance amount for the month (as determined under paragraph (2)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BC87092D70F40A597707E6E8A53FA61"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Child assistance amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of paragraph (1), the child assistance amount for a month shall be an amount equal to <fraction>1/12</fraction> of the excess of—</text><subparagraph id="H043FE6F361FB4515AC6619C11A55A708"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the annual poverty guideline for the calendar year preceding the calendar year in which such month occurs (as updated annually in the Federal Register by the Department of Health and Human Services under the authority of section 673(2) of the Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1981) as applicable to a two-person household, over</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H893F16DA915F44ADA728ADAAA0A6AB73"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the annual poverty guideline for such preceding calendar year applicable to a single individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3EF40B3A0A4C4F54B155560CE22D2481"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Representative payees</header><text>Section 205(j) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/405">42 U.S.C. 405(j)</external-xref>) shall apply to the payment of child assistance payments under this section in the same manner as such section 205(j) applies to the payment of benefits under title II of such Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0D242986DEB4261AC1DD8925BEFC0C0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Section 208 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/408">42 U.S.C. 408</external-xref>) shall apply with respect to child assistance payments under this section in the same manner as such section 208 applies with respect to monthly insurance benefits under title II of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H42C830F05C4D481189E9726821ABBFE7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="H518A8A75F42647128194332C340D1832"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No child assistance payment shall be made to an individual unless the Commissioner has approved an application for such payment in accordance with the requirements of this paragraph.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCC32A117B10499BB89E0A7D797B779E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text>An individual applying for a child assistance payment as (or on behalf of) a qualifying child under this section shall provide the Commissioner with an application in such form and manner as the Commissioner shall require, and such application shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HC0F183CA56024B6FB8F7D7D57B104343"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the name, date of birth, and social security number or taxpayer identification number of the qualifying child; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00A885F21C0145B8A98543B235F9B792"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such other information as the Commissioner deems necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1CF8E81C29241C5B8F3481EA7AAEEA8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Simultaneous application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner shall treat an application for a social security account number for a qualifying child as an application for a child assistance payment under this section, unless the applicant affirmatively indicates on such application an intent to opt out of such child assistance payments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB593968456014F81A611912CE37B5919"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Deemed applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any qualifying child identified to the Commissioner under the data sharing procedures described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">section 6103(l)(23)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as amended by subsection (e)) who has not otherwise submitted an application for child assistance payments under this section, the Commissioner shall treat such qualifying child as having so applied, unless the applicant affirmatively indicates to the Commissioner, under such procedures as the Commissioner may establish, an intent to opt out of such child assistance payments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8577214BA0241F2B1CB88F8CE358159"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Term of application</header><text>The Commissioner may provide that an approval of an individual’s application for a child assistance payment under this subsection shall expire after a specified number of months, after which the individual shall not be eligible for a child assistance payment until a new application is approved under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H76DE057734E746599BA8617D8CC0FFCD" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>IRS data sharing with Commissioner of Social Security</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">Section 6103(l)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC776D0B34507403080E5E759C2BC785C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H5E1DC04947F94493B4C68234A7DC9B8D" commented="no"><enum>(23)</enum><header>Disclosure of return information to Social Security Administration for purposes of child assistance payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, upon written request from the Commissioner of Social Security, disclose to the Commissioner any available taxpayer identity information from the individual master files of the Internal Revenue Service that the Commissioner deems relevant to identifying children of taxpayers or children who are taxpayers who qualify for a child assistance payment under section 2(c) of the <short-title>End Child Poverty Act</short-title>, including information relating to—</text><subparagraph id="HB0D3FA47B61A44CC8D98308609B27B38" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>citizenship status of a child,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE025EF5126F4C1282EB2036C5611245" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>age of a child, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D6BEBAA15C6403BB5B98F60A3C8D594" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>country of residence of a child.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCF111AFA905F48F3853863F5BD7B5D9E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Income disregard</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A child assistance payment made under this section shall not be taken into account as income and shall not be taken into account as resources for purposes of determining the eligibility of such individual or any other individual for benefits or assistance, or the amount or extent of benefits or assistance, under any Federal program or under any State or local program financed in whole or in part with Federal funds.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE71EE26EEF194B8784A9E7CC3F6479E6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Appropriation</header><text>There are appropriated to the Commissioner for fiscal year 2023 and each subsequent fiscal year such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H587E7A4BCF7747638592D9010FF76017"><enum>3.</enum><header>Repeal of child tax credit and earned income tax credit</header><subsection id="H73D4EED4277B48E0AE7BA6ACF42D5A53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Child tax credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/24">Section 24</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is hereby repealed. </text></subsection><subsection id="HB8A6CFB1612C4184A1A83B34FB63FC5F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Earned income tax credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 32 of such Code is hereby repealed. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4DA0B2A0B09A40228E67566CFD5AD6D8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="H4209E2F8FF10405680B90F9769E1402E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The table of sections for subpart A of part IV of subchapter A of chapter 1 of subtitle A of such Code is amended by striking the item relating to section 24.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BFE67EC81504EB3A4EFA01B2D99B731"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The table of sections for subpart C of such part is amended by striking the item relating to section 32.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B11D4CE8053436E8C56442B70012F62"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/45R">Section 45R(f)(3)(B)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting <quote>(as in effect on the day before the date of enactment of the Universal Child Assistance Act of 2018)</quote> after <quote>section 24(d)(2)(C)</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE55B063F55ED4AB5B978129E39F33C3C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Section 25A(g)(2)(B) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>, 32</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF63C2B0272814250BF28DDE10B9A771A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Section 86(f) of such Code is amended by striking paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80908F99352446C5BB5A609844D04E80"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Section 129(e)(2) of such Code is amended to read as follows: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5CF0945815194478BDDA833899D29E90" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H38E0CD8888284A1699675E2061749F9B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Earned income</header><subparagraph id="H181A4BF0304E4126982D0D64B62C973E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <quote>earned income</quote>—</text><clause id="HCC0CD828BB8C4670A78D4C18F3EBF591"><enum>(i)</enum><text>means—</text><subclause id="H62B52030227B43618521BB5281442F7A"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">wages, salaries, tips, and other employee compensation, but only if such amounts are includible in gross income for the taxable year, plus</text></subclause><subclause id="H1A5ADEE3E252475D94CFD7DAADC4F743"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount of the taxpayer's net earnings from self-employment for the taxable year (within the meaning of section 1402(a)), but such net earnings shall be determined with regard to the deduction allowed to the taxpayer by section 164(f), and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H2F2EA4C75912401BBC0B6F77D61470C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>does not include any amounts paid or incurred by an employer for dependent care assistance to an employee. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAAF86ECF1E34D8FA5BB7BF3B698B28F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="HB3931925712745419F93F584F9C2AC8A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the earned income of an individual shall be computed without regard to any community property laws, </text></clause><clause id="HEB83A211A1FD4655BE39FE31564FAA61"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>no amount received as a pension or annuity shall be taken into account, </text></clause><clause id="H4FF861273F5242B48A1192F1C5CB9733"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>no amount to which section 871(a) applies (relating to income of nonresident alien individuals not connected with United States business) shall be taken into account,</text></clause><clause id="H0D0199CD3B9E4A6BB22EA224FEA24012"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>no amount received for services provided by an individual while the individual is an inmate at a penal institution shall be taken into account, </text></clause><clause id="H27C2A7DFA8F148E7AF002F0901A8F42F"><enum>(v)</enum><text>no amount described in subparagraph (A) received for service performed in work activities as defined in paragraph (4) or (7) of section 407(d) of the Social Security Act to which the taxpayer is assigned under any State program under part A of title IV of such Act shall be taken into account, but only to the extent such amount is subsidized under such State program, and </text></clause><clause id="H6604CD79EF184F3A9C59C435B7BED58D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a taxpayer may elect to treat amounts excluded from gross income by reason of section 112 as earned income.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H10CCD906461D48E09B4333835A214CB4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Section 135(d)(1)(B) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>32, </quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5622CB5523B40879ACDB254E28971D7"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Section 152(f)(6)(B) of such Code is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H541BCC7A0D554B259A8EBEEC7D949C1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>, and</quote> and inserting a period, </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CEEEE287F6C48A0929395D01AE3B421"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking clauses (ii) and (iv), and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF591E0B5A78C42E8ABFC55E89085A541"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating clause (iii) as clause (ii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB76776D9D58147968A275F353463FBB2"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Section 501 of such Code is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HDBB8B7384BAD4DEFA539F7596B3DA957"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(26), by striking <quote>(as defined in section 24(c)</quote> and inserting <quote>(as defined in subsection (g))</quote>, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB2A854689A248448BD9E38999FD940C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending subsection (g) to read as follows: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9A4B281317AE466AA34DE7CC42361A5C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H5C10671CB11241A6A23C366AF97B80E0"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><paragraph id="HB80F3A4EB9A0469DA1A225BCFBCB3C58"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agricultural</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (c)(5), the term <quote>agricultural</quote> includes the art or science of cultivating land, harvesting crops or aquatic resources, or raising livestock.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D1B447D89494BF0B3795FF0E077EFC6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifying child</header><subparagraph id="H80EC79BECF284DD1AE64D94B976E28A6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (c)(26), the term <quote>qualifying child</quote> means a qualifying child of the taxpayer (as defined in section 152(c)) who has not attained age 17.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB19B846F8D6B4249B2F149A013F270CB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception for certain noncitizens</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>qualifying child</quote> shall not include any individual who would not be a dependent if subparagraph (A) of section 152(b)(3) were applied without regard to all that follows <quote>resident of the United States</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H83C4E7BFAFC446F59B540A5CC56ACDFA"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Section 995(f)(2)(C) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>32, </quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFF20AB122DB43F2921F58BF59938DAF"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Section 3402(f)(1) of such Code is amended by striking subparagraph (C) and by redesignating subparagraphs (D) through (F) as subparagraphs (C) through (E), respectively.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD7B1BCD2B0E4FA6ACEC85D93DF1B714"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Section 4293 of such Code is amended by striking <quote>chapter 32 (other than the taxes imposed by sections 4064 and 4121)</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A780CE4EFEC44368B832B210B89B085"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Section 6211(b)(4)(A) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>24(d),</quote> and <quote>32,</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E022CCAC0FF4ED187A53CB8F5F77FB5"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Section 6213(g)(2) of such Code is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H5418CA47F5C84D1BA87675CFE4101F97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (L), by striking <quote>, 24, 32,</quote>, </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D6F0440ACBF474196836C7C01677E77"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subparagraphs (F), (G), (I), (K), (M), and (P) and by redesignating subparagraphs (H), (J), (L), (N), (O), and (Q) as subparagraphs (F), (G), (H), (I), (J), and (K), respectively, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF51E554D6CC14C6EB6ADCF372167C157"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (J).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H969D10F3C66F4B6B826479F4E90AAC07"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Section 6402 of such code is amended by striking subsection (m) and by redesignating subsection (n) as subsection (m).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A622B595AAD4280AEC794E4C4115F44"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Section 6695(g)(2) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>24,</quote> and <quote> or 32,</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC3CA5643FD04134A46B37E66BBBF78A"><enum>(17)</enum><text>Section 1613(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1382b">42 U.S.C. 1382b(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (11). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAC1AB45254AF479195DE4D29292A9665"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2022.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3353A85681F94B38BAA7DD5D27B1779F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Refundable tax credit for adult dependents</header><subsection id="H92072FD8BDFF40C68D67D3500DDEBD50"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart C of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting before section 33 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H085E25F9FD5742AE822369547E07EE3D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H787C4F2B14B54361A5128E4716FD4DDB"><enum>32A.</enum><header>Adult dependent credit</header><subsection id="H6F5371C71ADA440EB60A497BFA3C9EFC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Allowance of credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an eligible individual, there shall be allowed as a credit against the tax imposed by this subtitle for the taxable year an amount equal to $600 for each qualifying dependent of the taxpayer.</text></subsection><subsection id="H354764B061304E78AE24F2CA650C8456" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>eligible individual</quote> means any individual if—</text><paragraph id="HF9FC88EC6A134FE1A832D99555D83EB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such individual is not a dependent for whom a deduction is allowable under section 151 to another taxpayer for any taxable year beginning in the same calendar year as such taxable year, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBC8677B02DC44F590F12431BED41EFD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such individual is not a nonresident alien during such taxable year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1639356D8E514A4F8F9E9FC79AD62AE0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Qualifying dependent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>qualifying dependent</quote> means a dependent (as defined in section 152) who is over the age of 18.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6DCE0A72429A455C8EFFB4193389DC08"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Identification number requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A qualifying dependent shall not be taken into account under subsection (a) unless the taxpayer includes the name, age, and TIN of the qualifying child on the return of tax for the taxable year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3D563B3276FB4EF0A456ED1806210B0C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header><paragraph id="HD69DC695881849DF9BC3315176175CD4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any taxable year beginning after 2023, the dollar amount in subsection (a) shall be increased by an amount equal to—</text><subparagraph id="H640CF95D825A4AF7A07178082C9D4C20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such dollar amount, multiplied by</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21BBBA2CB12C47E9849F1B1B0084872B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year in which the taxable year begins, determined by substituting <quote>calendar year 2022</quote> for <quote>calendar year 2016</quote> in subparagraph (A)(ii) thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6E149EF70DD4668832BBF366036B5D8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>If any amount as adjusted under paragraph (1) is not a multiple of $0.01, such amount shall be rounded to the next lowest multiple of $0.01.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HF30FC233C65B45A99ED92F7A98C7623B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subpart C of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 32 the following new item: </text><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section"><quote>Sec. 32A. Adult dependent credit.</quote></toc-entry></toc></subsection><subsection id="H992B27158F044FA38B7498E8F50F31B3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2022. </text></subsection></section><section id="H6B4D93BBE584422E84CE16AAF91FC421"><enum>5.</enum><header>Refundable tax credit for adults and families</header><subsection id="H17D95A8B97F74AA9BCF8195780A82FFE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart C of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended by section 4, is amended by inserting after section 32A the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBD735A1C39564F0284BF453C2A519992" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H9685C6828037426E84B953D57D8A7F28"><enum>32B.</enum><header>Credit for adults and families</header><subsection id="HCA1C13CD261C451F82F4D69B2354A8E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Allowance of credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an eligible individual, there shall be allowed as a credit against the tax imposed by this subtitle for the taxable year $600 ($1200 in the case of a joint return).</text></subsection><subsection id="HF13F4D7D161145D3B16B064607251A51" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation based on adjusted gross income</header><text>The amount of the credit allowed by subsection (a) shall be reduced by 5 percent of so much of the taxpayer’s adjusted gross income as exceeds—</text><paragraph id="H368034771ABF45739570AD8BC0777F66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$40,000 in the case of a joint return, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H616E028DC63F46DC9C5CD8AE8E990D0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$20,000 in any other case. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65D70E1796BB4123B630B69CD8ECB4EF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>eligible individual</quote> means any individual if—</text><paragraph id="HDA00E5A62543438FA64B961F827A5FE7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such individual (or, if the individual is married, either the individual or the individual's spouse) has attained age 19 but not attained age 65 before the close of the taxable year, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A0F95CBB340411E990B1EB0A6493141"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such individual is not a dependent for whom a deduction is allowable under section 151 to another taxpayer for any taxable year beginning in the same calendar year as such taxable year, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F998AD51F0343DFAF32DE43386C3918"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such individual is not a nonresident alien during such taxable year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H162422E875A340A295525A9DF48E5255"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Identification number requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No credit shall be allowed under this section to an eligible individual who does not include on the return of tax for the taxable year—</text><paragraph id="HB656CA9CA9404F439A22E23E66F9091A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such individual’s taxpayer identification number, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H575B3D02C5B148F190A1A250519AC7B7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the individual is married (within the meaning of section 7703), the taxpayer identification number of such individual's spouse.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBE9928B5947347EFA2D7E1D8DD63ABB2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header><paragraph id="HBE42D008415E4E2F8E79476FA49B899A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any taxable year beginning after 2023, the dollar amounts in subsections (a) and (b) shall be increased by an amount equal to—</text><subparagraph id="H19AE2BCC1ECC43D89F414C8D2AAD3566"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such dollar amount, multiplied by</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3025D7B96F48459C8B04269576E4B91D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year in which the taxable year begins, determined by substituting <quote>calendar year 2022</quote> for <quote>calendar year 2016</quote> in subparagraph (A)(ii) thereof.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H97476133A7B24A8CA3E27F4F9A1E0BDD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>If any amount as adjusted under paragraph (1) is not a multiple of $0.01, such amount shall be rounded to the next lowest multiple of $0.01.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCF7E4B9C4C5A49EA87F44F12D2102F1C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subpart C of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended by section 4, is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 32A the following new item: </text><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section"><quote>Sec. 32B. Credit for adults and families.</quote>.</toc-entry></toc></subsection><subsection id="H80C3F1A6D5314774BFD684BEC960A13A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after December 31, 2022. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

