<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBF1C31C2B10B48E58FA09207C8CFF5BC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6088 IH: Ensuring Safe and Ethical AI Development Through SAFE AI Research Grants</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6088</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000401">Mr. Kiley</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the National Academy of Sciences to establish a grant program to develop safe AI models and safe AI research, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7084AB4842854759A35892A4283187C7" style="OLC"><section id="H2873D8980F58486E9F86167EC376457A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ensuring Safe and Ethical AI Development Through SAFE AI Research Grants</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H83D40A46328147309CFCE2EFB197C0D9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program to develop safe AI models and safe AI research</header><subsection id="H31612D85905746C3AB2465581FF5087E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H3292E442732B4655A50243EC5D0E083B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The development and use of artificial intelligence (AI) have accelerated rapidly through all sectors of society opening the doors to untold benefit and innovation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABD90E88E76846E4BDA66B12955818EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>With this great potential also comes unknown risks. Research into the safety and risk reduction of AI development is urgently needed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1BE92964E27A47B09A48EEBF4D975857"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the policy of Congress to encourage research on AI safety and risk mitigation processes in order that AI is developed in a manner that ensures security, reliability, and consonance with human values. </text></subsection><subsection id="H0131F919769943CF814DB0457848A108"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Establishment of grant program To encourage safe AI models</header><paragraph id="HD089522AE5B844E09D62E5E076AF1C1E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), the Director of the National Academy of Sciences shall establish a grant program to encourage the development of safe AI models and safe AI research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F40ACFCB4A0433DA8BDFA0C959C0EAF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Development of guiding principles</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Academy of Sciences, in consultation with industry, government, academia, and high-tech stakeholders, and using a public comment process, shall develop a set of guiding principles and ethical considerations which will be made available to the public and used to inform implementation of the grant program under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D1397CDEF3F4FBD8ACCE465C07BC45B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Proposal</header><subparagraph id="HDFF901ADF45B43588E91C91BD18A8B43"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Academy of Sciences shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a detailed proposal of the grant program under paragraph (1), together with a budget for the administration of such grant program and a proposed appropriation request relating to the number of grants to be awarded. Such proposal shall include the following:</text><clause id="HF362C543B1A544ABA48DF4770ED70672"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A discussion and evaluation of—</text><subclause id="H25584DCBF6BA47FDAF257EDB366F1210"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the structure and operation of existing AI models;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6A0706DBE90D4631B08CC79A11106702"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the degree to which such models incorporate some version of safe AI into their operation; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H1682516019404E539ECE2F599975A9FC"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the methodology used to assess benefits and risks to society.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFB8739F4E37F4B039A1DB095700A13EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An identification of areas of safe AI which require additional research.</text></clause><clause id="H8CAF2010B7E94608A5306C1498937080"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A timeline for implementation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H328DC26B1D5C43B49EE4C5C51435F7D1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional elements</header><text>The proposal under subparagraph (A) shall also include information relating to the following elements:</text><clause id="HD12E337128374241A5FB98679D0D16C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The solicitation of grant proposals from prospective grantees.</text></clause><clause id="H6258CEFF55C746FA89BC4D9DECE88B07"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The evaluation of grant awardees.</text></clause><clause id="HC75F636FD9D2434F9A1EFCFDE16E0231"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The determination of whether awardees have achieved promised outcomes.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

