<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H39D24657F5F4400CAEF25AE7768092AC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4360 IH: Access to Capital Creates Economic Strength and Supports Rural America Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4360</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001225">Mr. Sorensen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to revise the shareholder threshold for registration under that Act for issuers that receive support through certain Federal universal service support mechanisms, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCF7059F713C24A71B2C956BA35BE2169" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HD06724B82A6E43DD84D7F543AB648A98"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Access to Capital Creates Economic Strength and Supports Rural America Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ACCESS Rural America Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8CE2F33B7D70428A8BB27E31386F3DFD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Shareholder threshold for registration of certain issuers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 12(g) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78l">15 U.S.C. 78l(g)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H152AEBA63B644758A4DF48A43EC78953"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H6DAAADD78FAA44B0A8FA5EDA9117A790"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)(ii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE16E3ED0AAFA43B8948EA82B5459BB26"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7A64AE90785424D9ABD727EFF67E1BA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (B) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2CDD1A005204448081EFE8BD854A23A9"><subparagraph id="HD6029DBB51B34CA0AB92CF2E3E58BFF5" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an issuer that, during its previous fiscal year, received support, directly or through an affiliate, through the Federal universal service support mechanism for rural, insular, and high cost areas established under section 254 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/254">47 U.S.C. 254</external-xref>) and filed the report described in paragraph (7) with respect to such fiscal year, and did not issue securities (other than splitting of existing securities) during the previous fiscal year and does not intend to do so during the present fiscal year, not later than 120 days after the last day of its first fiscal year ended after the date of enactment of this subparagraph, on which the issuer has total assets exceeding $10,000,000 and a class of equity security (other than an exempted security) held of record by 2,000 or more persons,</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4EF6F62244214F7DB621C06562314E95"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the flush text following subparagraph (C), as added by subparagraph (C) of this paragraph, by adding at the end the following: <quote>The dollar figures in subparagraph (C) shall be indexed for inflation every 5 years by the Commission to reflect the change in the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics, rounded to the nearest $100,000.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H210C3F2DDCA1413BAD75A5A49C29D48F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3DD0B48AFDA3428BB6B742B138BC50B7"><paragraph id="HA86C36F43C6547019F5C1C13EACC80EC" indent="up1"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Mandatory disclosures by certain universal service support mechanism recipients</header><subparagraph id="H181A4E0D5E734956A12BA8919DEA266C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall issue regulations to establish a financial summary form that shall, upon request by an investor, be made available by an issuer that—</text><clause id="H70852FE4C80841EB88B5CC06EFFA7B44"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during its previous fiscal year, received support, directly or through an affiliate, through the Federal universal service support mechanism for rural, insular, and high cost areas established under section 254 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/254">47 U.S.C. 254</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="HF0A80DA042364752837CFD4715345060"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has a class of equity security held of record by not fewer than 500, and fewer than, 2,000 persons.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H642C6A0C7A2A482D8BEBBCE65BBE63CD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The form described in subparagraph (A) shall include—</text><clause id="H21E56D002B854863B5A5A29871A6FAF9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a summary of the consolidated balance sheet and the consolidated income statement of the issuer;</text></clause><clause id="H59765D09ED524794851EAF57BFCFDB9F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a certification that the issuer did not issue securities (other than splitting of existing securities) during the previous fiscal year and does not intend to do so during the present fiscal year; and</text></clause><clause id="H4ACD0D0B50334B56810E7E0C5114AB25"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>such other information as the Commission determines is necessary and appropriate in the public interest and for the protection of investors.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

