<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD76D7AD76E704EA8BC5349A119FBEDC8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 2731 IH: Protect Our Waters and Expand Renewables on Our Reservoirs Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2731</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230419">April 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require assessments of opportunities to install and maintain floating photovoltaic solar panels at Bureau of Reclamation and Corps of Engineers projects, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE6A8821D118448C59001F920A5C14A68" style="OLC"><section id="HD3305FB6461B40F2A22D55F329CE57DE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Our Waters and Expand Renewables on Our Reservoirs Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>POWER Our Reservoirs Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF79C9DFE744B4D0EA6D5806455307A48"><enum>2.</enum><header>Floating solar energy at Reclamation projects</header><subsection id="H053AC1943DBC4AA481EB6E54313C2E17"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HBCDF44CFB2C643D2B115B8DB9CB18981"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commissioner</header><text>The term <term>Commissioner</term> means the Commissioner of Reclamation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97CD4361924F429F9AFB76C52F018BF6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reclamation project</header><text>The term <term>Reclamation project</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HB6A45BB554CA404BB97075492FB6264B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any reclamation or irrigation project, including incidental features of the project—</text><clause id="H2F10AA99B1A64793BA0AE2A43C52424B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is authorized by the reclamation laws;</text></clause><clause id="H279CD7FF84C14AB5995EDB8617A0971B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that is constructed by the United States pursuant to the reclamation laws; or</text></clause><clause id="HC15EA638C34F4640917209BAD9CFDFDB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in connection with which there is a repayment or water service contract executed by the United States pursuant to the reclamation laws; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55D4CA0218A94F7E82B928890E879FAE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any project constructed by the Secretary of the Interior for the reclamation of land.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD1C424B44F254BDC8A2F1B50891BCE93"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assessment</header><paragraph id="HB9BA6AEC973B47F4847B6D234CE80889"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commissioner, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy and the relevant National Laboratories of the Department of Energy, shall conduct an assessment of opportunities to install and maintain floating photovoltaic solar panels at Reclamation projects. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA86E8FF707634165860EFEFC32591A67"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In conducting the assessment under paragraph (1), the Commissioner shall—</text><subparagraph id="H4F497DC7DD6A4240A69421683DCA82DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determine the economic, environmental, and technical feasibility of installing and maintaining, or contracting with third parties to install and maintain, photovoltaic solar panels at Reclamation projects;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6742623F22D40E19BBC48340B859CC4"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3DB9DA62460142D1ADE0A9DD9E9A3746"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify Reclamation projects with a high potential for the installation and maintenance of floating photovoltaic solar panels, including which Reclamation projects are likely to have high cobenefits; and</text></clause><clause indent="up1" id="HC3F75FC7BA014AF58C44F1A13476139C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>determine whether the installation and maintenance at Reclamation projects identified under clause (i) would require additional authorization;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67685304ACCD43D18E09D92854BAD982"><enum>(C)</enum><text>account for potential effects and benefits on Reclamation projects and the authorized purposes of the Reclamation projects of installing and maintaining floating photovoltaic solar panels at the Reclamation projects, including—</text><clause id="HA2053A77DFEF4DB39D3106BAACFEA45B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>evaporation suppression;</text></clause><clause id="H28C7DBF272C94B2C9F9A0B4B75892360"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>energy yield;</text></clause><clause id="HDC978463C4194C46BC672496D423B517"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>dam safety;</text></clause><clause id="H7A9C52CE3EA646C5B840E405CA1BC118"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>recreation;</text></clause><clause id="H6293EC02BF34458895BBA2952290AF9D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>water quality; and </text></clause><clause id="HFB767CBE6BC84ED8B6820483BAFF31C1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>fish and wildlife;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0145BC6622904E65BAC30845F684F1CA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>account for potential damage to floating photovoltaic solar panels from—</text><clause id="H5E02755C775C4543859011EB8829051C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>weather;</text></clause><clause id="HAB464BEB301C4381AC71CF20962C4430"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>water-level fluctuations; and </text></clause><clause id="HDCC036CA1D994264AB883A1580AE8F7C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>recreational and other uses of the Reclamation projects;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89340283A31D4F28ADA38E90A5B40982"><enum>(E)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4534DA7AD0F34AE7820972BFC243C547"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify methods to monetarily quantify cobenefits of floating photovoltaic solar panel projects; and</text></clause><clause id="H5F58F2F237CC4B4C9FED7E6735F27FF4" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify mechanisms to pass those benefits to project developers, and assess whether the use of such mechanisms may increase the viability of floating photovoltaic solar panel projects; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B55C74FB93F4B2F915755081395DAD6"><enum>(F)</enum><text>account for the availability of electric grid infrastructure close to Reclamation projects, including underutilized transmission infrastructure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H85D023E396884BB1A9B8330859D1980D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commissioner shall submit to Congress and make publicly available (including on a publicly available website) a report describing the results of the assessment conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEFF5169EC50146FFA484DE4C94807B79"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><paragraph id="HAC9FC1BB80174037963FEDC9A6D0F163"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, if the Commissioner determines, based on the results of the assessment conducted under subsection (b), that establishing a pilot program is advisable, the Commissioner shall establish a pilot program under which the Commissioner, or an applicable non-Federal entity that is acting in partnership with the Commissioner, subject to paragraph (2), shall carry out projects to deploy floating photovoltaic solar panels at Reclamation projects identified under subsection (b)(2)(B).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D2C352B6E7A4FB3B47F75C96CA08866"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>To be eligible to carry out a project under paragraph (1), a non-Federal entity shall—</text><subparagraph id="H5A16E5846BCD49CEA965E9BC93F3DF9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text> agree to invest in and deploy floating photovoltaic solar panels at the applicable Reclamation project; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BD2FC0557494A7FA902B77FDE67FE9E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have the authority to enter into agreements, including through public-private partnerships, for the purpose of carrying out the applicable project under that paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4374B929E97D4E7494CEF82F6214AABA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>The Federal share of the cost of carrying out a project under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H7B13283AF5414C7CAD5DE33E3325EB6C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall not exceed 100 percent, in the case of a project carried out by the Commissioner; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23FB9EF7A79A42FB83CACE1B1A537DA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not exceed 50 percent, in the case of a project carried out by a non-Federal entity, acting in partnership with the Commissioner.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D529703564C4C738AC1D43114F16B01"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Commissioner to carry out this section $12,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA5DAAF44D0854F7F8832A298CD07B755"><enum>(e)</enum><header>No effect on project purposes</header><text>Nothing in this section affects the authorized purposes of a Reclamation project. </text></subsection></section><section id="H752EE3BBC5D541669DBE424A1A605AB2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Floating solar energy at Corps of Engineers projects</header><subsection id="HDEFEEA659DC14328A1304EEC5A837AF3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HCC1EC2E092344CF086AAEFF1E41DFF82"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Corps of Engineers project</header><text>The term <term>Corps of Engineers project</term> means any water resources development project—</text><subparagraph id="HEB6DEE169CB2419287CB5E2408F5F290"><enum>(A)</enum><text>constructed by the Secretary; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC80C0436F172458E8C77FC051CC8BF29"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for which the Secretary has financial or operational responsibility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3307BD6700D42E5A855B2B41F025B29"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Army. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3E47514776FD47B0B03EB07F92544FF0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sustainability reports</header><text>Beginning not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall include renewable energy from floating photovoltaic solar panels as part of any sustainability report and implementation plan of the Corps of Engineers.</text></subsection><subsection id="H921C097079B3448E99D987EE4F715E5F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><paragraph id="H26BE24F344014DA5887A80926EC2497D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, if supported by the results of the assessment conducted under subsection (a) of section 8232 of the Water Resources Development Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/263">Public Law 117–263</external-xref>), the Secretary shall establish a pilot program for the deployment of floating photovoltaic solar panels at Corps of Engineers projects identified under paragraph (2)(B) of that subsection under which the Secretary or an applicable non-Federal interest—</text><subparagraph id="HE8DF7C7CC7124E82B76F7DDEF44449E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>agrees to invest in and deploy floating photovoltaic solar panels; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F5189118B5742F88F898A76C02589A9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may enter into agreements, including through public-private partnerships, for the purpose of carrying out such activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1EF2FAAFC454403A9984B9F7B74E084"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cost share</header><text>The Federal share of the cost of a project carried out under this subsection shall be—</text><subparagraph id="H7385C851FA9F4A8791E13B15EA2173DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not more than 100 percent, in the case of a project carried out by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0E24AB6F85C4976A5913CD78E0DF1AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not more than 50 percent, in the case of a project carried out by a non-Federal interest. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H63658FEF5B674DC097A8C32C652036CE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Funding</header><paragraph id="H9BB895D0A66F4BFDA4EB8C9B2A0A5337"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out this section using amounts made available to the Secretary to carry out section 8232 of the Water Resources Development Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/263">Public Law 117–263</external-xref>) that are not otherwise obligated.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35F11BA980FE4014B0D265026DADD42E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>In addition to amounts made available under paragraph (1), there is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section $2,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available until expended.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF6A618260A27458A8455EAFEC966441B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>No effect on project purposes</header><text>Nothing in this section affects the authorized purposes of a Corps of Engineers project.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

