<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H021601F93AD543D3B0A3714192D79605" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 997 IH: English Language Unity Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 997</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To declare English as the official language of the United States, to establish a uniform English language rule for naturalization, and to avoid misconstructions of the English language texts of the laws of the United States, pursuant to Congress’ powers to provide for the general welfare of the United States and to establish a uniform rule of naturalization under article I, section 8, of the Constitution.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H63A18B0BC2AC4CADA9F20DC96D935F9C" style="OLC"><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3B0406A6A19420E95121F5AF274500B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>English Language Unity Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBD121BF745EF48D0826A734EF496C1F2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds and declares the following:</text><paragraph id="HA41EA0FEAEAE4C088317FF69F4DF4CD6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States is composed of individuals from diverse ethnic, cultural, and linguistic backgrounds, and continues to benefit from this rich diversity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00555C5057104E71932881F38BA1694B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Throughout the history of the United States, the common thread binding individuals of differing backgrounds has been the English language.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9224C69A82E04815AD94EDA7491CAC33"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Among the powers reserved to the States respectively is the power to establish the English language as the official language of the respective States, and otherwise to promote the English language within the respective States, subject to the prohibitions enumerated in the Constitution of the United States and in laws of the respective States.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H66B8380877984540B87CCFD0A7EF5D52"><enum>3.</enum><header>English as official language of the United States</header><subsection id="HE41693EFFB1B4F6B8AB6C31651981F27"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title 4, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new chapter:</text><quoted-block id="H05AB0336F4A74481BD939B959C010405" style="USC"><chapter id="HAEE511367B0941DD9642D71A6DD580E9"><enum>6</enum><header>Official language</header><section id="H79BB8BB180CE4D22AAE6AAB1433A4996"><enum>161.</enum><header>Official language of the United States</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The official language of the United States is English.</text></section><section id="HA2698FF2D74940EFA5C6415720BDE8DE"><enum>162.</enum><header>Preserving and enhancing the role of the official language</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Representatives of the Federal Government shall have an affirmative obligation to preserve and enhance the role of English as the official language of the Federal Government. Such obligation shall include encouraging greater opportunities for individuals to learn the English language.</text></section><section id="H5DFFC92FC5FF4147A8207A27775C355F"><enum>163.</enum><header>Official functions of Government to be conducted in English</header><subsection id="H4E1416C6029045D9BF0213AEDE112D55"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Official functions</header><text>The official functions of the Government of the United States shall be conducted in English.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC721465F81F943BC96B761FDF427CAB7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scope</header><text>For the purposes of this section, the term <term>United States</term> means the several States and the District of Columbia, and the term <term>official</term> refers to any function that (i) binds the Government, (ii) is required by law, or (iii) is otherwise subject to scrutiny by either the press or the public.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3471DE1C7CF9463EBA54CFA59345DFBC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Practical effect</header><text>This section shall apply to all laws, public proceedings, regulations, publications, orders, actions, programs, and policies, but does not apply to—</text><paragraph id="HBBB9795D58D144449E65F87EC9591F80"><enum>(1)</enum><text>teaching of languages;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC55E79283AED41FF8F97AE63CE2BCBDB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>requirements under the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF532FB500F174D5C86B1E7678346866C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>actions, documents, or policies necessary for national security, international relations, trade, tourism, or commerce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A1C9F9FFE5440EA878EA8A966E66803"><enum>(4)</enum><text>actions or documents that protect the public health and safety;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA40EFFA57D714ED3AA1DAA966CD56F3C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>actions or documents that facilitate the activities of the Bureau of the Census in compiling any census of population;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C5288BA9D4D46198DA2D8FF3AFA6DDE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>actions that protect the rights of victims of crimes or criminal defendants; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF2AB17357DD4709ADEB2EC9F7065FE8"><enum>(7)</enum><text>using terms of art or phrases from languages other than English.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H7DDDC7A50BCF4345BB86366EEA974575"><enum>164.</enum><header>Uniform English language rule for naturalization</header><subsection commented="no" id="H04C2B956429B4C03A96AAE605C09AA53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Uniform language testing standard</header><text>All citizens should be able to read and understand generally the English language text of the Declaration of Independence, the Constitution, and the laws of the United States made in pursuance of the Constitution.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H598C533CD42242E99D7E3232A2D9D657"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ceremonies</header><text>All naturalization ceremonies shall be conducted in English.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6CD6F4BE8ADD4B03BE8A20941F03472E"><enum>165.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this chapter shall be construed—</text><paragraph id="HECC72C58B16B4634B62B37D7EAF82556"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to prohibit a Member of Congress or any officer or agent of the Federal Government, while performing official functions, from communicating unofficially through any medium with another person in a language other than English (as long as official functions are performed in English);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H124B5163EFD247A08D136A259A337910"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to limit the preservation or use of Native Alaskan or Native American languages (as defined in the Native American Languages Act);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EE5246D9CD64A3A9802520D676AE794"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to disparage any language or to discourage any person from learning or using a language; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11319D78F9AB4328AFA5B18A354312BF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to be inconsistent with the Constitution of the United States.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD14AEAC1478D4EC4867BA4EB89FEFBA1"><enum>166.</enum><header>Standing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A person injured by a violation of this chapter may in a civil action (including an action under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/151">chapter 151</external-xref> of title 28) obtain appropriate relief.</text></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H7080D3BAF493431CA49B559E284A97E0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of chapters at the beginning of title 4, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 5 the following new item:</text><quoted-block id="HDA367DB7EF684D4BAA50E76F1ACE8D5F" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="chapter">Chapter 6. Official Language</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H17ED99C42BCA450A9BDFCBB2DCD3BA21"><enum>4.</enum><header>General rules of construction for English language texts of the laws of the United States</header><subsection id="HF98FE3B5851640EE95E9DCFC96436BC3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/1/1">Chapter 1</external-xref> of title 1, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="H93167EE912ED41889C595307C256AF99" style="USC"><section id="H0D9AFF1EAF7F4C13A5C527D642528C5E"><enum>9.</enum><header>General rules of construction for laws of the United States</header><subsection id="HDC8607F04F244114B52F8920DA50599B"><enum>(a)</enum><text>English language requirements and workplace policies, whether in the public or private sector, shall be presumptively consistent with the laws of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAD8AA327A67B454FB9C53FD657E9A5C8"><enum>(b)</enum><text>Any ambiguity in the English language text of the laws of the United States shall be resolved, in accordance with the last two articles of the Bill of Rights, not to deny or disparage rights retained by the people, and to reserve powers to the States respectively, or to the people.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H06F3437A2DE946E1AB0C5C37B72EF21E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/1/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of title 1 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 8 the following new item:</text><quoted-block id="H2377A358FAC14B069A8AA900BA667E87" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">9. General rules of construction for laws of the United States.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HEBD0BBCBAB834EACB062D75313BE2030"><enum>5.</enum><header>Implementing regulations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall, within 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, issue for public notice and comment a proposed rule for uniform testing of English language ability of candidates for naturalization, based upon the principles that—</text><paragraph id="H8C8D43E434094F81A6F3CAE1D2B11820"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all citizens should be able to read and understand generally the English language text of the Declaration of Independence, the Constitution, and the laws of the United States which are made in pursuance thereof; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H123DAA9344CC49B59438F0C1307104E3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any exceptions to this standard should be limited to extraordinary circumstances, such as asylum.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7D62E87BD51B4241A30BFE2AD4E36AD7"><enum>6.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by sections 3 and 4 shall take effect on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

