<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H15C745E833114CE0833F808A568C0A2B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4650 IH: American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Provisional Ballot Reform Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4650</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230714">July 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to establish certain requirements for casting a provisional ballot in a District of Columbia election, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC800D4A07A914B34AAFEC68C0BD87AE4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H571FB6136F984B7E844911A44C00E596" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Provisional Ballot Reform Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H02D761A289F744DF94329BE13DDDF7A8" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirements for provisional ballots with respect to District of Columbia elections</header> <subsection id="H65C5DFA50C25482A9192D7DB2F8EA267"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2133B63CD6AB464AB604395B1E29D049"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 304 and 305 as sections 305 and 306, respectively; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H24CBB014B05F4984AC17D35ECCFA5091"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 303 the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6BAB84A2D49A47EC90CBD1D6ABC0AC63" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H9B91FBBB6B274BD1BAC360069898EE78"><enum>304.</enum><header>Requirements with respect to provisional ballots in a District of Columba election</header> 
<subsection id="H3AC4F8AFADBB44BCB66B2F01CA58A6F2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), the District of Columbia shall permit an individual to cast a provisional ballot pursuant to section 302 if—</text> <paragraph id="HF2B1504AA7C840CBBB6A8EE0623432D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the individual declares that such individual is a registered voter in the District of Columbia and is eligible to vote in a District of Columbia election but the name of the individual does not appear on the official list of eligible voters for the polling place or an election official asserts that the individual is not eligible to vote; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A3A39912427419FA7CDB20BFE283177"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the individual declares that such individual is a registered voter in the District of Columbia and is eligible to vote in a District of Columbia election but does not provide a valid identification, except that the individual’s provisional ballot shall not be counted in the election unless the individual provides such identification to the chief State election official of the District of Columbia not later than 5:00 pm on the second day which begins after the date of the election.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9B2A1E9B791247A29ABBD85B794DCD4C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements with respect to counting provisional ballots in certain cases</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the name of an individual who is a registered voter in the District of Columbia and eligible to vote in a District of Columbia election appears on the official list of eligible voters for a polling place in the District of Columbia, such individual may cast a provisional ballot pursuant to section 302 for such election at a polling place other than the polling place with respect to which the name of the individual appears on the official list of eligible voters, except that the individual’s provisional ballot shall not be counted in the election unless the individual demonstrates pursuant to the requirements under section 302 that the individual is a registered voter in the jurisdiction of the polling place at which the individual cast such ballot. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H13E14774199B46BBAFFCFEDD8FCBC029"><enum>(c)</enum><header>District of Columbia election defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>District of Columbia election</term> means any election for public office in the District of Columbia, including an election for Federal office, and any ballot initiative or referendum. </text></subsection> </section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0E5017AD865F4D1CA5DAF15CC2AFEE9F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>303, and 304</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H205593852B9742949F167C25A83392A6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8448C9417D7540248B5505FAEF2EA901"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the items relating to sections 304 and 305 as relating to sections 305 and 306, respectively; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB4AB56B530F7444CBF2349FE580C2EAF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 303 the following new item:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2EDC70826D7F43058EE44D9BA7F502FC" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 304. Requirements with respect to provisional ballots in a District of Columba election.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

