<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD46D6914F7F34216B0F4C3155C16D8D9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4831 IH: Fair Pay for Federal Firefighters Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4831</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230724">July 24, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide a special rate of basic pay for Federal wildland firefighters during fiscal years 2024 and 2025, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HB99B4E68995E41A194B4576129734D12" style="OLC">
<section id="H06E547D8E40849E8816CB7911899A725" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fair Pay for Federal Firefighters Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H19DA306C0FA44FDFA3784FC3E3D0E3D2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increase in rate of basic pay for Federal wildland firefighters during fiscal years 2024 and 2025</header> <subsection id="HFC21445C9FAB4D20965112C493F738A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Special rate of basic pay</header> <paragraph id="HDA0DA5AAE91A41BF8E725E78B32CCE72"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including section 5332 of title 5, United States Code, during fiscal years 2024 and 2025, a wildland firefighter shall receive a special rate of basic pay, at grades 1 through 15, as provided under paragraph (2). Such rate of pay shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5A68B597CB294F55A5B44CEC9C806FDB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">replace the otherwise applicable General Schedule basic rate of pay, and shall be considered basic pay for all purposes including computing locality-based comparability payments under section 5304 or 5304a of such title;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H03E05B6377A640529B800270A2D0CE21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>when expressed as an hourly, daily, weekly, or biweekly rate, be computed from the appropriate annual rate of basic pay provided under paragraph (2) in accordance with section 5504(b) of such title;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD5E3B288A3EC46F3B54DC667AED62233"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be adjusted at the time of any adjustments to the rates of pay under the General Schedule; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD465CDFDBB824A9786A1E521FFE44E9B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>begin to apply in the first pay period beginning on or after October 1, 2023.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD7A040D22851409CAF563933F4C739E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rates of pay</header><text>The special rate of basic pay for a wildland firefighter shall be derived by increasing the otherwise applicable General Schedule rate of basic pay applicable to such wildland firefighter by the following percentage amount, rounded to the nearest whole dollar:</text> <subparagraph id="H201B3F58B2B648138CF6E5FA64240956"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">GS–1, 42 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA8EC3B664B8442959E3F2F06D0A2CE73"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">GS–2, 39 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6077F5411BA6466D9E062115706AA800"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">GS–3, 36 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2666BC56B371413495266FFE96A2C9AE"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">GS–4, 33 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4FEFA548BA214B3397BC48B822B4CA94"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">GS–5, 30 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFDD5E05E8C0C45CDB8C5C927F7101A52"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">GS–6, 27 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2D335C569BAB422FBDBCBA428B2433CC"><enum>(G)</enum><text>GS–7, 24 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9666A653431A4B459926C5488E3743A4"><enum>(H)</enum><text>GS–8, 21 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB8670F46F76B43F8A5C43A2CD8DA59CC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>GS–9, 18 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC45E526FEC7B4FBC95473F38A3EEB2F8"><enum>(J)</enum><text>GS–10, 15 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2373A42DF3224710A285292DF093BEAA"><enum>(K)</enum><text>GS–11, 12 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H33AA099A5D814137A8086F8E7E0F4E35"><enum>(L)</enum><text>GS–12, 9 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1DA791E3B4214E6BAF5B85441A62934F"><enum>(M)</enum><text>GS–13, 6 percent.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H794B2182A86149BD8720B886DA84249A"><enum>(N)</enum><text>GS–14, 3 percent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFBE35ECEB547414BB10D01E17A5F792B"><enum>(O)</enum><text>GS–15, 1.5 percent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5169FC90279242788CD5757110AD7608"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prevailing rate employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For any prevailing rate employee described in section 5342(a)(2)(A) of title 5, United States Code, who is a wildland firefighter, during fiscal year 2024 and 2025, the Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary of the Interior (as applicable) shall increase the wage rates of such employees by amounts that are generally consistent with the percentage increases given to wildland firefighters in the General Schedule under subsection (a). Such an increased wage rate—</text> <paragraph id="H7CFEDEBDBAA14852A7699E06DBA91087"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall begin to apply in the first pay period beginning on or after October 1, 2023; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H895B033FA2FB423E8CC47B7D443D39EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be determined at the sole discretion of the applicable Secretary, after consultation with the other Secretary; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H237382EB71CD4A0F95B3DB91D4C3A49E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be basic pay for the same purposes as the wage rate otherwise established under section 5343 of such title; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB59CC406E5FA4518BAD1D6C8027C7950"><enum>(4)</enum><text>may not cause an employee’s wage rate to increase beyond a rate that would produce an annualized rate in excess of the annual rate of pay for level IV of the Executive Schedule under section 5315 of such title.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFE4F3CCDA3264D11AB0B3EFB589EDD4E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rescission</header><text>The unobligated balance of amounts available under each of sections 50221 through 50224 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> (commonly referred to as the <quote>Inflation Reduction Act</quote>) are hereby permanently rescinded.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H23CFDC269CBB404888570E361CDF9563"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Wildland firefighter defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> means a firefighter—</text> <paragraph id="HAA23674E240E49ED9773BDB63D5DA4FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who is employed by the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCE3A4B34329142F3BC26D2CDAE117973"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the duties of the position of whom primarily relate to fires occurring in forests, range lands, or other wildlands, as opposed to structural fires.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HA8E38DEED6A94DF197EB51AF01CE7689"><enum>3.</enum><header>Wildland fire incident response premium pay</header> <subsection id="H32CEA934CFBC4B059C21AC9915822292"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter V of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/55">chapter 55</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/5545b">section 5545b</external-xref> the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HDB03BC95E9F74FC6A6765C9245EB936A" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="HAC74AA21FD12406E896DF33964A4EB38"><enum>5545c.</enum><header>Incident response premium pay for employees engaged in wildland firefighting</header>
<subsection id="H24EC8B77B6F84E1FB24AE18D9E16F464"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="HE143D1DA98AE4425BFB0F1E30E6E7763"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H46CFC9DD5FF24DCFB5B4FA5408BF0768"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H841E79A08D1940DC9ECA786F90ECB1DC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF4D2446FFC41452D99722F31AFF1757A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3CE9AF0CDF7C483EB7B9C02063A11017"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8B055B5A567845DDA12522AEF9582FD1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H08091B2AEA274A88AA2F5493B2FE4BFF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H538FF68084264C9B824E46C03FBB2EAC"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H272AC9856260428DAE935FB9F9D8E037"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA6C8F5A83FD345B3A585E2890C812518"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>covered employee</term> means an employee of the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior who is—</text> <subparagraph id="H5037559A327C42CDA317064CE3D76F6A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a wildland firefighter; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDAD54663D69746CB8F2B9C1C597B193A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>certified by the applicable agency to perform wildland fire incident-related duties during the period that employee is deployed to respond to a qualifying incident;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8C884F1BD73545C8A5FD13C8F4F6C8B3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>incident response premium pay</term> means pay to which a covered employee is entitled under subsection (c);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H25D732BB368445FC8D05F81F81441A3D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>prescribed fire incident</term> means a wildland fire originating from a planned ignition in accordance with applicable laws, policies, and regulations to meet specific objectives;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H70E8FFBA0BE340ADBBBBCA34B490382B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>qualifying incident</term>—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCEA254C7FCEE4AABA2AA256E99DCA097"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means—</text> <clause id="HA6B34C2A114743B49167E2F85AFE60BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a wildfire incident, a prescribed fire incident, or a severity incident; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HB1CB0079182F4A409D6D6E5ABFDA15A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an incident that the Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary of the Interior determines is similar in nature to an incident described in clause (i); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7C28142B11CB4B14BFE0A53D960221F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include an initial response incident that is contained within 36 hours; </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBAEB54C7FD0840FEB20C2BB779ECBA2A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <term>severity incident</term> means an incident in which a covered employee is pre-positioned in an area in which conditions indicate there is a high risk of wildfires; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF4A541C92E1944FBAB9C45DB241E9E60"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>wildland firefighter</quote> means a firefighter—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5E5C2EBFA9B845499E488F4EDE89C12C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is employed by the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDC98FF5768BD4B75962E88C4ABCC054B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the duties of the position of whom primarily relate to fires occurring in forests, range lands, or other wildlands, as opposed to structural fires.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2CDEFDE6D23940119BF9F24C9178CE39"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>A covered employee is eligible for incident response premium pay under this section if—</text> <paragraph id="HD0682BA62F5E42FBA5B624F6256D77ED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the covered employee is deployed to respond to a qualifying incident; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF5F7BCF3131345E2BCDDF3C7E7AA6A0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the deployment described in paragraph (1) is—</text> <subparagraph id="H4B3A05E2A2A441D5B345213C8632864B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>outside of the official duty station of the covered employee; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF41CF9E2D43A47969EBBF14C234C8A3B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>within the official duty station of the covered employee and the covered employee is assigned to an incident-adjacent fire camp or other designated field location.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBD71CB1D7C88448DAF2CE9766C1632DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Entitlement to incident response premium pay</header> <paragraph id="H409BA9805F2D4963978FEF21ED43473B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A covered employee who satisfies the conditions under subsection (b) is entitled to premium pay for the period in which the covered employee is deployed to respond to the applicable qualifying incident.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1E15E347963640659D3754E71BF12068"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Computation</header>
<subparagraph id="HF0A6C3B297CE4A5BA3FBD805BF3F712E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Formula</header><text>Subject to subparagraphs (B) and (C), premium pay under paragraph (1) shall be paid to a covered employee at a daily rate of 450 percent of the hourly rate of basic pay of the covered employee for each day that the covered employee satisfies the requirements under subsection (b), rounded to the nearest whole cent.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEA728F1ECC1A489BAFB816C0272FD392"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Premium pay under this subsection may not be paid—</text>
<clause id="H63C5124930EE46D5A94E560B13464A0F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to a covered employee for whom the annual rate of basic pay is greater than that for step 10 of level 10 of the General Schedule, at a daily rate that exceeds the daily rate established under subparagraph (A) for step 10 of level 10 of the General Schedule; or</text></clause> <clause id="H620E2682CA1F41D1B918B88037CFD08C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to a covered employee in a total amount that exceeds $9,000 in any calendar year.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H528A12BAC39440E7AC21822E26874345" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretaries of Agriculture and Interior may implement a waiver on the total limitation in subparagraph (B)(ii) if the National Wildland Fire Preparedness Level reaches or exceeds level three.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF795D2F5A4A24D909086953FBD1DD301"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Adjustments</header> <clause id="H8ADAE5A13ED74E4C96C41B1088F9AE70"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior shall assess the difference between the average total amount of compensation that was paid to covered employees, by grade, in fiscal years 2023 and 2024.</text></clause>
<clause id="HD57CE39B87A3495FA468140FC5B34498"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date that is 1 year after the effective date of this section, the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior shall jointly publish a report on the results of the assessment conducted under clause (i).</text></clause> <clause id="H448840000FDD43368DE32FFD7677D3C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Administrative actions</header><text>After publishing the report required under clause (ii), the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, may, in the sole and exclusive discretion of the Secretaries acting jointly, administratively adjust the amount of premium pay paid under this subsection (or take other administrative action) to ensure that the average annual amount of total compensation paid to covered employees, by grade, is more consistent with such amount that was paid to those employees in fiscal year 2023.</text></clause>
<clause id="HC1DAAFE81D034007AE62C7E03426EC45"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Congressional notification</header><text>Not later than 3 days after an adjustment made, or other administrative action taken, under clause (iii) becomes final, the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior shall jointly submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a notification regarding that adjustment or other administrative action, as applicable.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFAFF352CCE114EB0B4F9FD3B9A0C6136"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Treatment of incident response premium pay</header><text>Incident response premium pay under this section—</text>
<paragraph id="HF97A4327ECDC47E68DFF540D3388B6B2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is not considered part of the basic pay of a covered employee for any purpose;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE0D6869DB05E48869143EADD9410FB26"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may not be considered in determining a covered employee’s lump-sum payment for accumulated and accrued annual leave under section 5551 or section 5552;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC932E78B87E345F29062CEEB2E5DFDB3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>may not be used in determining pay under section 8114 (relating to compensation for work injuries);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H042BADCF74B44C269D46AD3E9B72DE52"><enum>(4)</enum><text>may not be considered in determining pay for hours of paid leave or other paid time off during which the premium pay is not payable; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0C1D3968E4E14083A15739799860A878"><enum>(5)</enum><text>shall be disregarded in determining the minimum wage and overtime pay to which a covered employee is entitled under the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/201">29 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HA035FA22E6A94A96BA9C5EB9FD4D4F4A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional premium pay amendments</header><text>Subchapter V of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/55">chapter 55</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H3EB26230B01A48F198469B21D7C4FAE1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 5544—</text> <subparagraph id="H404F9BE9DF8B4BB7A3D51C5E06B12AE6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending the section heading to read as follows: <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="USC">Wage-board overtime, Sunday rates, and other premium pay</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE746A3431113445C876B987D6C84F778"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H931C4D5CD0DA46629D3CBDCB7C397340" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="HD87142BA7B7A49C3B2C60FF9BA332838"><enum>(d)</enum><text>A prevailing rate employee described in section 5342(a)(2)(A) shall receive incident response premium pay under the same terms and conditions that apply to a covered employee under section 5545c if that employee—</text>
<paragraph id="HDEBDEB7169804C9EA2B6DB34F2092A9D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is employed by the Forest Service or the Department of the Interior; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H49CA42AAE89549F5BD60D45CD593D18B"><enum>(2)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD0AE70DDECEE415B8CE08940AF859587"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a wildland firefighter (as that term is defined in section 5545c); or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H441ECB8055C4465BA2373ED7A95D03F7" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is certified by the applicable agency to perform wildland fire incident-related duties during the period the employee is deployed to respond to a qualifying incident (as that term is defined in section 5545c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H354166E3D67B4BA591CBFC37B8F92D65"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 5547(a), in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>5545c,</quote> after <quote>5545a,</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HDEE678F6BB87439799813EFAB7B0F248"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><text>The table of sections for subchapter V of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/55">chapter 55</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H3C0096037ECE4BD6BC658EC1B66D5D58"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending the item relating to section 5544 to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HDF8D5352703141F8827B98DB8CBF6FD8" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">5544. Wage-board overtime, Sunday rates, and other premium pay.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA59BFACDE8184EE1B9A4F8AC832594E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after the item relating to section 5545b the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H20C2BD3DBE594D538177A366173A278A" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">5545c. Incident response premium pay for employees engaged in wildland firefighting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1CA8D252368C4FA9B5FAE05EB0D8295C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the first day of the first applicable pay period beginning on or after October 1, 2023.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H6D76CD4D348A42588F138307E1EEE3BE"><enum>4.</enum><header>Conditions in Forest Management</header>
<subsection id="HF37D66D497EB4093954CD90C201EE7D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mandatory use of existing authorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually after, with respect to each unit of public lands and within each unit of covered National Forest System lands, the Secretary concerned shall use not fewer than 1 of the following streamlined authorities including the authorities for environmental review:</text> <paragraph id="H570A4EF4895F452E97BECA96EA1D6CA4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 603(a) of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591b">16 U.S.C. 6591b(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H122BFEE2847C4667AC5039434B82EFA7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 605(a) of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591d">16 U.S.C. 6591d(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13A8B6707C934FD68931F430B7CA1A32"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Section 606(b) of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591e">16 U.S.C. 6591e(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H30AD6FE1CA6B4ED0ADF49279005533A2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Section 40806(b) of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6592b">16 U.S.C. 6592b(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC0672FBCF2FD469585F74DCC8A6922C0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Section 40807 of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6592c">16 U.S.C. 6592c</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H05352443007F45378BECB17E76240F75"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Section 207 of the Wildfire Suppression Funding and Forest Management Activities Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591c">16 U.S.C. 6591c</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1680739C588F4349937EE0066546C5C0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered National Forest System lands defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered National Forest System lands</term> means any area—</text>
<paragraph id="H5E3632B712474439BD8A3764EDB376BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>located within National Forest System lands;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9F6AD59730B240848C25BCEE6C983A4E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that the Forest Service has identified as being located in a fireshed ranked in the top 25 percent of wildfire exposure (as determined using the most recently published models of fireshed risk exposure published by the Forest Service); or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAAB01DB8F85C4190A338794EC8AC7BAA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that the U.S. Drought Monitor has rated as having a D2 (severe drought) intensity, D3 (extreme drought) intensity, or D4 (exceptional drought) intensity.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

