<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H83363279BD9C4EBDB5E56E88150ADFBA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3500 IH: Mountain Valley Pipeline Completion Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3500</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To expedite completion of the Mountain Valley Pipeline, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2BB74CE51CC34D84B31F8CFFD0918A28" style="OLC"><section id="HE7D73AD0125B454F86A49207A9168DC7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mountain Valley Pipeline Completion Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H36372BAE0289468BAD7692ABB3A0D9B1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expediting completion of the Mountain Valley Pipeline</header><subsection id="HAB2B03D2F76F4F4B8AAEFC9CEAFE8A86"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of mountain valley pipeline</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Mountain Valley Pipeline</term> means the Mountain Valley Pipeline project, as generally described and approved in Federal Energy Regulatory Commission Docket Nos. CP16–10, CP19–477, and CP21–57.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4C508A817FBC40EEB39DCF295E694AB9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Congressional findings and declaration</header><text>The Congress hereby finds and declares that the timely completion of construction and operation of the Mountain Valley Pipeline is required in the national interest. The Mountain Valley Pipeline will serve demonstrated natural gas demand in the Northeast, Mid-Atlantic, and Southeast regions, will increase the reliability of natural gas supplies and the availability of natural gas at reasonable prices, will allow natural gas producers to access additional markets for their product, and will reduce carbon emissions and facilitate the energy transition.</text></subsection><subsection id="HECB34095C3B24D77A2B07EB7420FF1DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Approval and ratification of existing authorizations</header><text>Congress hereby ratifies and approves all authorizations, permits, verifications, extensions, biological opinions, incidental take statements, and any other approvals or orders issued pursuant to Federal law related to the Mountain Valley Pipeline.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB5B386FAE64A4ED2A4F4D065260A8442"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Expedited approval</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, not later than 21 days after the date of enactment of this Act and for the purpose of facilitating the completion of the Mountain Valley Pipeline—</text><paragraph id="H67246C7B51EA448BA3E163AE7F9B9BFF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Army shall issue all permits or verifications necessary—</text><subparagraph id="HC3274F6C58C04E73A60F188265305FC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to complete the construction of the Mountain Valley Pipeline across the waters of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04927921CED44D05B8C90233023E1FFB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to allow for the operation and maintenance of the Mountain Valley Pipeline;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H31CDE909497948978984FE3D62DBDD46"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture shall amend the Land and Resource Management Plan for the Jefferson National Forest in a manner that is substantively identical to the record of decision with respect to the Mountain Valley Pipeline issued on January 11, 2021, as may be modified by a subsequently issued record of decision following the Supplemental Environmental Impact Statement issued on April 13, 2023; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D8D512D0C0545528E1AF8E8F71D0F96"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior shall grant and maintain all necessary rights-of-way and temporary use permits in a manner that is substantively identical to those rights-of-way and temporary use permits approved with respect to the Mountain Valley Pipeline issued on January 14, 2021, or as may be modified by any subsequently issued rights-of-way and temporary use permits.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9E304E20A95D45369EDE69942440A7C1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Judicial review</header><paragraph id="HEB4E02AAC01D4ACF9033EE90E0CEB043"><enum>(1)</enum><text>No action taken by the Secretary of the Army, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary of the Interior, or a State administrative agency acting pursuant to Federal law that grants an authorization, permit, verification, biological opinion, incidental take statement, or any other approval related to the Mountain Valley Pipeline, including the issuance of any authorization, permit, extension, verification, biological opinion, incidental take statement, or other approval described in subsection (c) or (d) of this section for the Mountain Valley Pipeline, whether issued prior to or subsequent to the date of enactment of this section shall be subject to judicial review, and any lawsuit (including any lawsuit pending in a court as of the date of enactment of this section) seeking judicial review of such an agency order or action shall not be filed or maintained in any court and shall be promptly dismissed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BC5F85A08FB44EEB58D8B880D47DE84"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit shall have original and exclusive jurisdiction over any claim alleging the invalidity of this section or that an action is beyond the scope of authority conferred by this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H224DF51C4458459AADAD294E11C1A5C6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effect</header><text>This section supersedes any other provision of law (including any other section of this Act or other statute, any regulation, any judicial decision, or any agency guidance) that is inconsistent with the issuance of any authorization, permit, verification, biological opinion, incidental take statement, or other approval for the Mountain Valley Pipeline.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

