<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0E62E648A5564720ADFCAAE1DBE02310" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5025 IH: National Office of New Americans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5025</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the National Office of New Americans within the Executive Office of the President, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H26B23CBBB9C14692A31230E405956BD1" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H07FF95CC15C540F9A1331C8944776819"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Office of New Americans Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1D71C69EFDAE415683B9A5EFC72C2070"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H17D945D72134476EAA8D316DFBE88B19"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Office of New Americans.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD358F8C9892848919F19BF7B36646DB9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> has the meaning given the term <term>agency</term> in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B02285689214D67A6A70DF86699B5D0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Office</header><text>The term <term>Office</term> means the National Office of New Americans established by section 3(a).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE4D2AA021D49454998F10E45FBA4FC63"><enum>3.</enum><header>National Office of New Americans</header><subsection id="H20204138520B44DAB70738BF81799F59"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established within the Executive Office of the President an office to be known as the <quote>National Office of New Americans</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0E695A73B4C94FD9AC11739A93C793C3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the Office are the following:</text><paragraph id="HB5E7442267CE45099D94EB062E6BB9A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To welcome and support immigrants and refugees in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38F03A9877BC4AA4804430A2DDAA4ACE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To promote and support immigrant and refugee integration into, and inclusion in, the social, cultural, economic, and civic life of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B61282F6A344DB399820A95F29E625A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To ensure that the Federal Government and Federal agencies promote the pursuit of United States citizenship among immigrants and refugees.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5738E0D64E4B4A2FB9B6A991A89591BC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>To ensure access to quality English language learning programs that support the successful integration of immigrant adults, including by enhancing—</text><subparagraph id="H7F8E70E5E1A943109944B4BD3A9F6BB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>employment and career prospects and economic integration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0BA663475D84F09850ADADE589FBD11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>social integration in local communities and participation in civic life, including engagement with State and local governments, schools, and private and nonprofit community institutions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB80F329B6F674C759C8D69586F1EF3DD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>To improve access to workforce development programs, including by ensuring that such programs meet the demand and the unique language, training, and educational needs of immigrants and refugees.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C0003B293C54E98AB55DB99AABC34C0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>To coordinate the efforts of Federal, State, and local entities to support the effective social, economic, linguistic, and civic integration of immigrants, refugees, and the children of immigrants and refugees.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33CAD52811284EF2BFCD5C8949C9C8E5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>To provide advice and leadership to the President, Members of Congress, and other Federal Government officials on the challenges and opportunities facing such entities with respect to immigrant and refugee integration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0418B327BE934A319553D0CD1E2150EE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>To evaluate the scale, quality, and effectiveness of Federal Government efforts with respect to immigrant and refugee social and economic integration, including access to United States citizenship, English language learning, education, and workforce development programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD564A38135484B17A958EE44AA99EC73"><enum>(9)</enum><text>To identify the anticipated effects of new Federal policies on existing integration efforts and advise the President on how to address potential integration needs and the effects of such policies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40520FFA79754A82B34520D9D37882DA"><enum>(10)</enum><text>With respect to immigrant and refugee integration efforts, to consult on a biannual basis with State and local government officials on challenges and opportunities presented by such efforts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C7CE7325D6D42D888E35C0F13001DEA"><enum>(11)</enum><text>With respect to the activities described in paragraphs (8) through (10), to ensure the inclusion of the perspectives of immigrants and refugees.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA516405BA2074E018DF52EE13CFBB895"><enum>(12)</enum><text>To submit to the President and the appropriate committees of Congress a biannual report that describes the activities of the Office and the results of the consultation processes described in paragraphs (8) through (11).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA19C64857A9447EBB80E745FC9EE793D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Director</header><paragraph id="H649CFC72EEF34292BC26C8EEA503FAAE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Office shall be headed by a Director, who shall be appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA241C248B09A448A899AEFF230F62222"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Director shall—</text><subparagraph id="H39913A943795462D994E4BFDCB644A14"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish policies, objectives, and priorities for the Office with respect to immigrant and refugee integration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BDFA1D1832D4246B00A10F13CA66287"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with the assistance of the Deputy Director for Citizenship and Inclusion, the Deputy Director for Workforce and the Economy, the Deputy Director for Children's Integration Success, and the Associate Director of State and Local Affairs, carry out the purposes of the Office, as described in subsection (b);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H467EC7DE5666489EB76F8F58FFAFB147"><enum>(C)</enum><text>serve as the chairperson of the Federal Initiative for New Americans established under section 4;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40398866399E4F23A5B88BD564CC5564"><enum>(D)</enum><text>make recommendations to the President on changes in the organization, management, programs, and budget of the Federal agencies to promote the integration of immigrants and refugees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4E07E74CC9D4AF2BEAD2D21380A1F7B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>with respect to efforts to promote United States citizenship and the integration of immigrants and refugees, consult, support, and coordinate with State and local governments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC09C7D0EF79434FA62AB07E29762E87"><enum>(F)</enum><text>serve as a member of the Domestic Policy Council and the National Economic Council.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AF8369DD1F54B269211C4AB504D3CE7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Powers of the Director</header><text>In carrying out the responsibilities under paragraph (2) and the purposes under subsection (b), the Director may—</text><subparagraph id="H38D9FD6D8DD84A41B8FFC688E46AA062"><enum>(A)</enum><text>select, appoint, employ, and fix compensation of such officers and employees as may be necessary to carry out such responsibilities and purposes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86C891C9C1D34AFB93581B5E08CBF38F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with the concurrence of the head of the applicable Federal agency, direct the temporary reassignment within the Federal Government of personnel employed by such Federal agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D883633D7DD44498F13C078FF0B845B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>use for administrative purposes, on a reimbursable basis, the available services, equipment, personnel, and facilities of Federal, State, and local agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE6F484C01AF4D1A985792BF168FF030"><enum>(D)</enum><text>procure the services of experts and consultants, in accordance with section 3109 of title 5, United States Code (relating to appointments in the Federal service) at rates of compensation for individuals not to exceed the daily equivalent of the rate of pay payable for level GS–18 of the General Schedule under section 5332 of title 5, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31B3748019AA43C68D7D090950DDC7DF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>accept and use donations of property from Federal, State, and local government agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C4B0DCE87244BBA896C66CF0F850406"><enum>(F)</enum><text>use the mail in the same manner as other Federal agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H110CA4F46A404BE380B61C4FD393147A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>monitor the implementation of immigrant and refugee integration-related activities of the Federal Government, including by—</text><clause id="H8AABF00465F74F798009C682E481ED02"><enum>(i)</enum><text>conducting program and performance audits and evaluations of each Federal agency; and</text></clause><clause id="H65B73D98505042068CDB67F854569C0C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>requesting assistance from the Inspector General of the applicable Federal agency in such audits and evaluations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H98F73488BE1D407E99AB521F9F9CE591"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deputy directors</header><paragraph id="H61DBFECE7ABD4D8A893EDDDEF06D6D9E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be in the Office a Deputy Director for Citizenship and Inclusion, a Deputy Director for Workforce and the Economy, and a Deputy Director for Children's Integration and Success, each of whom shall be appointed by the President, in consultation with the Director.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C57669F2A654A9D95B553ABBC4F4CB3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><subparagraph id="H6C9CA585941C4D4DB9C2626BF2ED057C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Deputy Director for Citizenship and Inclusion</header><text>The Deputy Director for Citizenship and Inclusion shall, among other duties as assigned by the Director, assist the Director in promoting—</text><clause id="HAC6C84E2C44D4D169043E1EE5804C2A0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inclusion of immigrants and refugees in the social, economic, and civic life of their communities and the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="HC540D00494EB45B393AE3A67660A00F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>access to United States citizenship.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9C07C77214A4047B947FCCAF6D7D85C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Deputy Director for Workforce and the Economy</header><text>The Deputy Director for Workforce and the Economy shall, among other duties as assigned by the Director, assist the Director in—</text><clause id="H8A7D9165549C4D67B6400A72C4D3E3BD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>promoting participation of immigrants and refugees in the United States workforce; and</text></clause><clause id="HEE20DCB867D24602A0FEF1D3AD0DFFD0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>increasing the contributions of immigrants and refugees to the United States economy.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A9487E9BD064480BEBCC199CDBA8FA9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Deputy Director for Children's Integration Success</header><text>The Deputy Director for Children's Integration Success shall, among other duties as assigned by the Director, assist the Director in ensuring that Federal policies and programs intended to support the healthy development and educational success of children are effective in reaching and serving the children of immigrant families.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9EF5ED21D76D4D42A65314EB5276EB3A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Bureau of State and Local Affairs</header><paragraph id="H25130E054C7F4162B8B0C83233D7D208"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established within the Office a Bureau of State and Local Affairs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H630BF580B65D4C1D9A4D5E2AB1BD5B66"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Associate director</header><subparagraph id="H8C5BA46BCDDD43F4AC8CBBCC6D12F43A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Bureau of State and Local Affairs shall be headed by an Associate Director of State and Local Affairs, who shall be appointed by the President, in consultation with the Director.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC8FB2BB589C44848B896C8C732420F3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Associate Director of State and Local Affairs shall, among other duties as assigned by the Director, assist the Director in coordinating the efforts of State and local entities to support the economic, linguistic, and civic integration of immigrants, refugees, and the children of immigrants and refugees.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C01620A8C24449FB10BF6BAA363C745"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An individual may not serve as Director, Deputy Director for Citizenship and Inclusion, Deputy Director for Workforce and the Economy, Deputy Director for Children's Integration Success, or Associate Director of State and Local Affairs while serving in any other position in the Federal Government.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8F9CB34EE97249B29D3C5B975A68C3AC"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Access by Congress</header><text>The establishment of the Office within the Executive Office of the President shall not affect access to the Office by a Member of Congress or any member of a committee of the Senate or the House of Representatives, including access to—</text><paragraph id="HC7B91B8EB4014B22A431D5F4BD49AEEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any information, document, or study in the possession of, or conducted by or at the direction of, the Director; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74E8C81CA9D1459F9DAE7FBC2367A9C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>personnel of the Office.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6A2A120E94D84F9B8B4CAE8FA7BB558C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Federal Initiative on New Americans</header><subsection id="HCEBBD32793BC4DE1BADD5A5B937CE32E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the confirmation of the Director of the Office, the Director shall establish within the Office a Federal Initiative on New Americans (referred to in this section as the <quote>Initiative</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HCF7B16B867164D7AA450358950199D91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purposes of the Initiative are—</text><paragraph id="H75C62CEB62A04D38BCB229279EF40BCD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to welcome and support immigrants and refugees in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DD9BC1170EE4FBAB45A85D8DBFA0055"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to establish a coordinated Federal program to respond effectively to immigrant and refugee integration issues; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H822581BF314740BE950BD0407D7C8307"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to advise and assist the Director in identifying and implementing the necessary policies to carry out such program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5D54DCB4DE674B6FBC2A11D0569A1A88"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Initiative shall be composed of—</text><paragraph id="H054C2FF9956F44A49664A5F9933AC3F3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Director, who shall serve as chairperson;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6046C39E5034F0F8991BCE035CDBFF7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Treasury;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0817CADD2CD144B6AB5F0A6D32E1AC91"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Attorney General;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4C91525EFE4471787972EE018D47188"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Secretary of Commerce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CA3BAF2F0DA455AB33A8CDC94CE0C05"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Secretary of Labor;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC39EA35B67B540A7BE6D043BBA45710F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Secretary of Health and Human Services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA60F65A5E37E4C6DA01507561235B154"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B3B6DDDC12E46D8808154AD31D45704"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Secretary of Education;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5370D0B5E0A346F0A58CBDEAFCD4EB9D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5665B896B78540E69F6C55D14A86387A"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the Secretary of State;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96CA8B0623E24A75B0277BCB0C4A9694"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Refugee Resettlement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33A861F6C5164A4DB53F4C16A3243D47"><enum>(12)</enum><text>the Director of the Small Business Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H014214E01CB4460DBC5DD02744ECB586"><enum>(13)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Management and Budget;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF05E1C75E0414D1DA5B5F5E41AA418AD"><enum>(14)</enum><text>the Director of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H417A95EA2F2646F98B204FA62A53174A"><enum>(15)</enum><text>any other individual—</text><subparagraph id="H950DEC349E0B4EDC85A34912D9552055"><enum>(A)</enum><text>invited by the Director to participate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07F9ED6326DF402BA03826651070CDC6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who occupies a position listed under level I or II of the Executive Schedule, as provided in sections 5312 and 5313 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA70151D3B370429F862B691DB5265A7F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><paragraph id="H6F582166B18A4DC3823569F1E1CE8E23"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Initiative shall meet at the call of the chairperson and perform such duties as the chairperson reasonably requires.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAD8D81E6DF74789B48B4837911FBD42"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordinated response to immigrant and refugee issues</header><text>The Initiative shall join with Federal agencies in providing a coordinated Federal response to adequately address matters that affect the lives of immigrant and refugee families and local communities with growing immigrant and refugee populations, including access to—</text><subparagraph id="H4348987BE81845AAA0BFB86562B41450"><enum>(A)</enum><text>English language learning;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1191126132244F1B245906FB894A1A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>adult education and workforce training;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H004A3F55A5E143FA9B2AB1A71F00976C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>occupational licensure;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3F8F98C640A4672B681070ABF5CED38"><enum>(D)</enum><text>early childhood care and education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD786A58A43046AA9C112C1CEDF6C9CB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>elementary, secondary, and postsecondary education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B3D29D0BC8E4F6CBAED28353538474F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>health care;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF83DDE02A1D64CC988E193C9800E3AAB"><enum>(G)</enum><text>naturalization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB0968F9DB134F2EA54C31919772583E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>civic engagement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE60FA53ED8D740ED826C28652B07ADC6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>immigration assistance and legal services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H681DEE1B2C8B49D5B64681D679A02411"><enum>(J)</enum><text>economic development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD0EFA24E0864F2CA8380FD5EB77CE64"><enum>(K)</enum><text>language access services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF874C34EE2C4A078D83EDD69E42FEBC"><enum>(L)</enum><text>other services the Director identifies as aiding the integration of immigrants and refugees into the social, cultural, economic, and civic life of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H795D1D448AAF4D7E90A9DD07B7E28519"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Liaison with Federal agencies</header><subparagraph id="H512299C8A4934B1DB09A0D8C87FFA947"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each member of the Initiative shall serve as a liaison to the Federal agency of the member to ensure that the Federal agency coordinates with and responds to the recommendations of the Initiative in a timely and meaningful manner.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C93F7C0C66A4DA2B2A342F17027AFA1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Duties of a liaison</header><text>The duties of each member as a Federal agency liaison include—</text><clause id="H741BB3DC7AA24E509845CEFFDA066094"><enum>(i)</enum><text>developing, for the applicable Federal agency, immigrant and refugee integration goals and indicators;</text></clause><clause id="H2B30D42138F44E25A876C45D869DB747"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>implementing the biannual consultation process described in section 3(b)(10) by consulting with the State and local counterparts of the Federal agency;</text></clause><clause id="HF65E4F96CCF840988B7BA142F15560A4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>reporting to the Initiative on the progress made by the Federal agency in achieving the goals and indicators described in clause (i); and</text></clause><clause id="H6E143539017C461C9A3085DE7DE47A0D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>upon request by the Director and subject to laws governing disclosure of information, providing such information as may be required to carry out the responsibilities of the Director and the functions of the Office.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB526DC7DB9BD445E8AD8A246B2F8253B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Recommendations of the Initiative</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Initiative becomes fully operational, and every 2 years thereafter, the Director shall submit to Congress a report that includes the following:</text><subparagraph id="H5C7205F0F0DF4AE483E2DAE69C5A47F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Findings from the consultation process described in section 3(b)(10), including a description of the immigrant and refugee integration opportunities offered by, and integration challenges facing, State and local governments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57BA97F6A982442B9310E426B404510F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An assessment of the effects of, and recommendations with respect to, pending legislation and executive branch policy proposals.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A14589D467D4E259A6B601B22229FB2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of the possible effects of pending legislation and executive branch policy proposals on immigrant and refugee integration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA45A0811394647BC8D7009BEEB41D550"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An identification of any Federal program or policy that has a negative impact on immigrants, refugees, and local communities with growing immigrant and refugee populations, as compared to the general population, and recommendations for changes to any such program or policy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35120010711F4B5EA8DD4BCE7473F3EE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Recommendations on legislative solutions to better support the successful integration of immigrants and refugees and the children of immigrants and refugees. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

