<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCCB5E06681134D9695EC5C71E67C9AF2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4913 IH: To establish in the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration a program to improve precipitation forecasts, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4913</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000308">Mr. Jackson of North Carolina</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish in the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration a program to improve precipitation forecasts, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H86A3C0CE87AE4203B5859021566A0FEE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HAA6150F240874ED58984411EA293DCBF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of NOAA precipitation forecasts program</header> 
<subsection id="H27B1B08EB04A4FE7BA27A601CB2DF78D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) a program to improve precipitation forecasts (in this section referred to as the <quote>program</quote>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H96920B81AD3D4CD48D0D3FAF490CFB5B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Goal</header><text>The goal of the program shall be to improve precipitation forecasts across all timescales through the research, development, and operational implementation of fully coupled Earth System Models. The program shall carry out the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE992B43AA9A74BD1B6F3036763F4341B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Improve the understanding and prediction of precipitation extremes from a wide variety of weather systems and climate patterns.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C0FF547759940D1AE726EE5790DC1FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Improve the development, production, management, assimilation, integration, availability, and curation of datasets for precipitation prediction.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBC5FCD26FF0F42ABAD3522F2D57845E3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Identify and improve observations and analyses necessary for precipitation prediction, including relating to water vapor, oceans, and boundary layers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H16BF96003C7946F384BB0BD190EF0B07" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Utilize high performance computing and other technologies, as appropriate, to advance Earth System Models predictions skill of precipitation extreme phenomena, including atmospheric rivers, tropical cyclones, and winter storms across weather, subseasonal, and decadal timescales. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6852AD14933A4A55A56B339B114B8FE4" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Advance understanding and modeling of precipitation processes key to improving models and precipitation forecasts from weather to subseasonal-to-seasonal (S2S) to seasonal-to-decadal (S2D) timescales.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E6CB37D38564A4098E85A5B0D0D5931" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Support research and development to improve the accuracy, reliability, and timeliness of precipitation prediction, in collaboration with academic and private sector partners to test and evaluate emerging technologies, including the use of machine learning and artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H96392A1755FE46AAAC60F4EF4B0EF759"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Improve weather, subseasonal, seasonal, and decadal skill for precipitation forecasts through the use of emerging techniques and technologies.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF6B188350344F5D9E7B4983496B0F37"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Support research in social and behavioral sciences to improve precipitation forecast products and communication, in collaboration with the Director of the National Weather Service.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA13301DBCC804BBB9CE45CF5840EECD6"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Lead the ongoing advancement of current and next-generation precipitation forecasting models.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H249327F9A1C64375A26FF42279439727"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Identify observational gaps, systematic errors, and model limitations in precipitation prediction systems.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H78A690F8878D431C8F12CB33070EF50C"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Improve, expand, and sustain operational precipitation products and applications for decision support.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H85FBCFC3C2E14C08A1B78A8D66AC85A9"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Coordinate across NOAA line offices to address priorities of the program.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4DCD2A854FE340F08C0B85CA443CF8E6"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Direct efforts to engage with Federal, State, local, Tribal, and academic entities and stakeholders, as appropriate, when conducting program activities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H967CC93CE7B7456789276E09804B45AA"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Ensure adequate data management, access, and archive processes are in place to ensure data and metadata are findable, accessible, interoperable, and usable by the science community and public.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0818BAF78E20447381833B2D6FD17753"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>The Administrator of NOAA shall revise and update, as necessary, the goals of the program at least once every two years. Such revisions and updates shall be incorporated into relevant NOAA strategic implementation plans as determined appropriate by the Administrator.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD09679BEE01244A5BC78353D44FDB146"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to carry out this section the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE304C061F8084FF683973AD8D4B2C23D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$15,000,000 for fiscal year 2024.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B3D43082D704A21A450AEFF2A8D93C3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$15,040,000 for fiscal year 2025.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9A857934279E4E64AAC47B8C5E196D99"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$15,080,800 for fiscal year 2026.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4EB362429C0F4FADBD8D024CCFE03098"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$15,122,416 for fiscal year 2027.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAA26A8FBF7A9433EAD922D10B5FBE0DA"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$15,200,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

