<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H29A4E7E492994F168127D482B7C3491A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6735 IH: Fighter Force Preservation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6735</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Air Force to develop a long-term tactical fighter plan for the active and reserve components of the Air Force, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB7D43E64FB5649C6B94F3D14D627BC0A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5CE525167FE34DE886C71D593C8F5469" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fighter Force Preservation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H9C308F639CC547C0AE3B769DBBAD043B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Plan for long-term Air Force fighter force structure</header> <subsection id="HA869426EA300401DABFE0201DAB23DD4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan required</header><text>The Secretary of the Air Force, in consultation with the Director of the Air National Guard and the Commander of the Air Force Reserve, shall develop a long-term tactical fighter force structure, recapitalization, training, and sustainment plan for the active and reserve components of the Air Force.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H01D7BBE37D80495591E89168ACAB4C5A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The plan under subsection (a) shall address each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H0A8E666D71C5438F8C4A2CB6D74D6CF2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The appropriate mix of tactical fighter aircraft force structure, with accompanying operational risk analyses, required for the Secretary of the Air Force to meet expected steady-state, global force management allocation plans and geographical combatant commander contingency operational plans tasked to the Air Force using active and reserve component units.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA5BBE910511A4284A54747D3C3DB4A94"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The procurement, divestment, unit activation, deactivation, or re-missioning plans or actions the Secretary plans to implement, fiscal year-by-fiscal year, unit-by-unit, for the next 12 years for each active and reserve component tactical fighter aircraft unit existing as of the date of the enactment of this Act, including the rationale and justification for any such plans or actions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD44ED9260CF4779B29A367BA94CD869"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The actions the Secretary will take to ensure that required operational readiness rates are maintained during any planned recapitalization, modernization, or change of mission affecting tactical fighter aircraft units.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H328FE25EE0AF4D39800A57C2AE0DFD52"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any plans of the Secretary to augment or supplant existing piloted tactical fighter aircraft capability or capacity with Collaborative Combat Aircraft Increment 1 or Increment 2 capability or capacity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74240858F18541569495C348F22A829E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any plans of the Secretary to augment or supplant existing piloted tactical fighter aircraft training events via acquisition and fielding of common, joint, all-domain, high-fidelity synthetic simulation environments.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA684A6E95F2D4F4E83256AD9B62F553E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than April 1, 2024, the Secretary of the Air Force shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report that includes the plan developed under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA74AAB55F5FD44CAA741CD396F2A2667"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Form of report</header><text>The report required under subsection (c) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1C5755C961F04D389E1E0141C2AE6A0A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Congressional defense committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>congressional defense committees</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101(a)(16) of title 10, United States Code.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

