<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0F2CFF8501AC44C9853B7A96D61E9C05" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5645 IH: Earn to Learn Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5645</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a matched savings program for low-income students.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2FCF6A6D10FA449B9CE52970871E080E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H987DF99CDAE1472384B0CC92F0C50736" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Earn to Learn Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4AD860C8242149B7A43EC3E161F83CDB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HF8987729D70E4BB5BB40BF24DE772A09"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Skyrocketing costs of higher education are outpacing available financial aid. Individuals in the United States owe more than $1,700,000,000,000 in student loan debt, and more than 3,000 student loan borrowers default on a student loan every day, many of whom did not complete their educational program before obtaining a degree.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H72D6CDBB34A04DA8B9ACE06BF9AC02A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The cost of paying for public higher education and workforce training programs continues to rise while the purchasing power of Federal Pell Grant aid has significantly diminished.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H02F5F6B9C5744E85B3C56C0575B7623C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The confluence of these issues forces prospective students to make the tough choice between foregoing postsecondary education and borrowing enough money to pay for it, an amount that is often many times their annual salary and can remain a financial burden for decades after these students graduate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H92BDF709935B496B95892F6F9380963D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The higher rates of loan delinquencies and default among low- and moderate-income populations often lead to increased financial hardship, fewer assets, and lower net worth.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H56F2E9FED95F41E18C7E271F54FA0801"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In 2013, the Brookings Institute found that the increasing debt burden represents a drag on recent graduates and also serves as a deterrent to would-be students who may question the trade-off between the debt burden and the payoff of a college degree.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6E47D20D4199405DA3E168C7E79104AD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>During the 2015–2016 academic year, the Department of Education found that nearly 3 in 4 students experienced unmet need, and that unmet need among postsecondary students had risen by 23 percent since the 2011–2012 academic year.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1DFDD4BBB3E0462983EE012D82EBBF71"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Federal Reserve System has determined student loan payments are displacing retirement savings, home ownership, small business development, and other forms of building wealth.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H658311302183452AA7CCBF4E53E66D8B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The Report on the Economic Well-Being of United States Households in 2018 by the Federal Reserve found that 2 in 3 graduates with a bachelor’s degree or higher feel that their educational investment paid off financially, but only 3 in 10 students who started higher education programs but did not complete a degree share this view.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF641B45D102A42DD88AE4874C1A1BCF2" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The United States urgently needs a new, innovative approach to financial aid to help low-income students achieve their educational goals, graduate with affordable amounts of student loan debt, and improve their financial capability.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H0E8CBB10D04A4DF4A5CBD0D06829DFA6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the purpose of this Act to—</text>
<paragraph id="H5CCC263F23664815BAEC3FB0C1423A3E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish a proven and innovative matched savings program for low-income students that provides the financial resources and support those students need to attain their educational goals;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD230B9A6E8BC47829D0A7F71E292020E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide a much-needed supplement to traditional financial aid options through matched savings;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA01C9C15F4EC45809EFFC772C77EE461"><enum>(3)</enum><text>give students the tools to succeed by giving students the opportunity to invest in their education and to improve their financial capability through financial empowerment training and success coaching; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA187DDA9E1AD4584AD89D20AA049BCEC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>help students—</text>
<subparagraph id="H28DDBB5283C0477CB41FAA5E53091503"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop healthy financial habits and life skills;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8C4DF5BAA9224C99BBDE8F4EDCF3128D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prepare to embark on a lifetime of healthy financial practices after graduation; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H91A6621D68AF49E2B4DBB4403EAE7126"><enum>(C)</enum><text>minimize or eliminate student loan debt.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H132886B6AA7646B5818A62F20E01A14B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="H6B55E69B3BD945AF8F91EB3A59C6A132"><enum>(1)</enum><header>529 account</header><text>The term <term>529 account</term> means a qualified tuition program as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/529">section 529(b)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H380DF78FA77147B38BB0C3CB44F2EE00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible educational institution</header><text>The term <term>eligible educational institution</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE7C1AB983024B1CA947FAAAD18E640E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an institution of higher education, as defined in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>); or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0C45FF0C6FFE4EE380D5AFB554E7EA75"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an area career and technical education school, as defined in section 3(3) of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302(3)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2FEDC0FA03B04E0F93D2A5D2B4381280"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a State or a nonprofit organization.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1D6FA512A60B417DBAC20E8E7F5D9231"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible student</header><text>The term <term>eligible student</term> means an individual who—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE9E5F22A156D40C394971520C8AC0F00"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is selected to participate in a postsecondary education match savings account program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F32ECEBB7034AFEA3730CA55EA22A08"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has been admitted to an eligible educational institution;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H59C8A3E311934051B7B86E52DA3064F1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a student from a low-income family, as determined by the eligible entity;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35A7BBC517104759A65C0636EFB13509"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">successfully completes a required prerequisite personal finance training program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H690444DA426A49EB8CB7DA820F4C6640"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">agrees to contribute savings to the postsecondary education match savings account administered by the eligible entity under this section; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8801909113CA464E8D057B56807B17AA"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets any other eligibility criteria as defined by the eligible entity. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H848A80C5B6D449188D96E85C7765F71B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Financial capability training platform</header><text>The term <term>Financial Capability Training Platform</term> means a program for use by a postsecondary education match savings account program carried out with a grant under section 5 that—</text> <subparagraph id="HCB4CEEC20E4F47279AC5FAE35B811928"><enum>(A)</enum><text>delivers financial capability training to participating students that is designed to help students improve their financial capability and overall financial well-being;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H80666EDADEBF417AA7ADD8415A38FA56"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes an initial assessment to identify individual learning goals and objectives;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H44E8B4CD1C974007B3D0E5A5DF4294C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>creates a personal and dynamic learning experience for each individual participant, including ongoing assessments and interim milestones related to learning objectives and longer-term goals; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1BACEB73935441F08D0D4C3A5A9CCB5D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>includes modules on student loans, financial aid, budgeting and credit, consumer debt, housing costs, retirement, the importance of emergency savings, banking (including checking and savings accounts), credit use and interest rates, predatory lending practices, privacy, and security, which shall be conducted by or at the direction of the eligible entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA8F80073B4949AEB425F995AE18640A" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Postsecondary education match savings account</header><text>The term <term>postsecondary education match savings account</term> means an account that is—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD8A7A7AF7EFB4C5D927224E502EBBA4A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a custodial account; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF24C4B8968714FE790398856EE60776F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a 529 account. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H57A3525B038542E581C7E9CD6E357408"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Program guide</header><text>The term <term>Program Guide</term> means a guide that includes program policies and procedures, a savings plan agreement template, a withdrawal form template, recommended timelines, other key forms, and the structure for implementing and reporting program results for a postsecondary education match savings account program carried out with a grant under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA36AC295C07449B0B79A2480296A46C0"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Reporting dashboard</header><text>The term <term>Reporting Dashboard</term> means a robust online data portal for postsecondary education match savings account programs carried out with a grant under this section that—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB3381C422B474DF8B4F791F26F9AB811"><enum>(A)</enum><text>allows eligible entities to monitor student progress, track achievement, and measure relevant behavioral change;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA88DBF7E235246B89E21A9B5FF07E2ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>standardizes and facilitates student evaluation across participating eligible educational institutions; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H121A8A63BB774041921B962CED24A1CA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is in compliance with the requirements of section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (commonly known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF4EC35E6605A4E6A8F33ED4A9FDF39BE"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF22925DBB1814F9ABC7EF0DF283AC242"><enum>(10)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Student with preliminary eligibility</header><text>The term <quote>student with preliminary eligibility</quote> means an individual who—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDEEFE2D1813F4DF2B13A53E29C664B18"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is from a low-income family, as determined by an eligible entity; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H91137945712940419C356EE960BBCC1D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">plans to attend an eligible educational institution; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA87A06E77CF8409FB903CE808E87BD3D"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets the requirements described in subparagraphs (E) and (F) of paragraph (4).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA66F37D2BEA54792964CE4BD895FB2DD"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Success coaching model</header><text>The term <term>Success Coaching Model</term> includes—</text> <subparagraph id="H0B0EC9D3615B4F86B4ECD519FB2B2B00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>financial capability training to address budgeting, managing student debt, savings, debit management, credit cards, retirement readiness, and credit reports;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC8396D44C9374FD8B947534D2A998BFC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>postsecondary education readiness training that provides mentoring to help students be better prepared for the challenges of postsecondary education; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F436C39AE574F0DA41A21E499B561CE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>workforce readiness training to learn interviewing, resume skills, and career exploration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="H043FF80BCBD548E3915903921C64FE3D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Postsecondary education match savings account demonstration grant program</header>
<subsection id="H5A6D8265515A4327A289B01405C63002"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant established</header>
<paragraph id="H7CD4CFC1941B445BB1BFDE6AA664295E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 9 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a postsecondary education match savings account demonstration grant program described in this section, through which the Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to enable those eligible entities to carry out the activities described in subsection (e).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC21521A7581449049D3B9FE267F2FD84"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tools for grantees</header><text>The Secretary shall develop the Reporting Dashboard, Financial Capability Training Platform, Program Guide, and Success Coaching Model and make those tools available to grantees.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE32F610162C34DC1BE546BA21866D78B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pell eligibility not affected</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that, notwithstanding any other provision of law—</text> <subparagraph id="HB2D7B0AB74C643ACAA25613EC208FAA5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>participation in the grant program shall not affect a student's eligibility for a Federal Pell Grant under section 401 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070a">20 U.S.C. 1070a</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H47C64274F16042CFB90BF6CDA4B51771"><enum>(B)</enum><text>funds deposited in a postsecondary education match savings account by a participating student, as well as any matching funds under this section, shall not be considered when a determination is made about that student's eligibility for Federal student aid under title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>), including for a Federal Pell Grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEB8A33FB95C840D0847B3B0A6B154986"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible entity that desires to participate in the grant program under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may determine, including, at a minimum—</text>
<paragraph id="H3E76588522464883888564F33BB031FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a demonstration of—</text> <subparagraph id="H87033161A6C24F38AF0D2D5076D099B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a commitment of non-Federal matching funds at a ratio of 1:1 (which non-Federal funds may be provided by an entity other than the eligible entity);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC34150F97C0A48A88D0678DCAAD33E5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the ability to launch and implement the program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEF8FB433CC824844B51F783281007065"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a plan for compliance with evaluation and program monitoring; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB6A82AC6B9034438B030C8951AD42203"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an assurance that the applicant will utilize the Reporting Dashboard, Financial Capability Training Platform, and Success Coaching Model developed by the Secretary under subsection (a)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC1BBB85822684BDB89347A2BD2C824F8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection</header> <paragraph id="HF90DB56BD45648A49CB69958E4B0DE5B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting eligible entities to participate in the grant program under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF19565397E63444BBEA5D72D62ED6AEB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>target eligible students and students with preliminary eligibility at a statewide level with networks of participating eligible educational institutions; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H443D95D1FF0E4FEF98F49A554326D448"><enum>(B)</enum><text>commit to supporting selected students through the student's graduation from an eligible educational institution.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H29893A6DD23C4B4D9E7E5436A9F25592"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Diversity of projects</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure, to the maximum extent practicable, that the eligible entities awarded grants under this section include eligible entities that represent a range of communities (both rural and urban) and diverse populations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H64112E7087144F98B20071B7FE4166B1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>A grant awarded under this section shall be in an amount not to exceed the lesser of—</text>
<paragraph id="H3A599B4F691841A8A623F7DE4A3E61C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the aggregate amount of funds committed as matching contributions from non-Federal public or private sector sources; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H17134B26F18146BCB35F0D51E5904159"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$10,000,000.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H4C2BA555419D45828155482810EFD2AE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header>
<paragraph id="H1637227359EA488B98E47A8852DE060E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to—</text> <subparagraph id="H88C8C7BA6EA14FF58CBE7C83C57500E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>select eligible students, or students with preliminary eligibility, in the State in which the eligible entity is located to participate in the grant program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H48C20343E0B84947BAC6F453907BCEFD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide selected students with financial literacy education using the Success Coaching Model;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H809F2C979A4142048235E11073D7A73E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>after ensuring that a selected eligible student or selected student with preliminary eligibility has completed an agreement regarding the terms and conditions of the postsecondary education match savings account, establish a postsecondary education match savings account for each participating eligible student or student with preliminary eligibility and allow students and their families to deposit funds in that account to save for attendance at an eligible educational institution; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5216B8499C5F4E1EB222979DD35AD4A3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>reserve matching funds for participating students in accordance with paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0221658C8F5140E6BF20A3C6BAD9AD9D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matching funds</header> <subparagraph id="HCEBE77204ADD40F0BA18FFD7F59CD798"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon a participating student or student's family depositing $100 into a postsecondary education match savings account for the appropriate academic year, the eligible entity shall provide a match of $8 into the student's postsecondary education match savings account for each subsequent dollar deposited by the student or student's family.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9F8F24EAC3DE4E8EA429F468864E79E0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Withdrawal from school</header><text>If a participating student withdraws from an eligible educational institution during the drop-add period at that eligible educational institution, the student shall be responsible for any amounts owed for that academic period and will not receive matching funds for that academic period.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1F92BA964C784A798D1F6391AA6B50FC"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Delay of attendance; extenuating circumstances</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), each eligible entity shall describe in the agreement under paragraph (1)(C) the eligible entity's policy regarding the availability of matching funds in the event a student decides to delay attendance at an eligible educational institution or in the case of extenuating circumstances, such as illness of a student.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H41D15309DE1B4481A357E409D11DB53C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Return of deposited funds</header>
<subparagraph id="H2070E07383544178B34272BE76E87EE8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each eligible entity shall ensure that a participating eligible student, or a student with preliminary eligibility, who does not meet or maintain the requirements of paragraph (4) or (10) of section 4, respectively, shall be entitled to withdraw funds that the student or the student's family contributed to the postsecondary education match savings account in accordance with the terms and conditions that are contained in the agreement for that postsecondary education match savings account, as described in paragraph (1)(C).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0AD853243F864493B1B7D3DC6DD5D2E8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Expiration</header> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7F0C563D92B42C491DA166EA82C5BB5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The participation of an eligible student or student with preliminary eligibility in the postsecondary education match savings account demonstration grant program shall terminate on the expiration date described in clause (ii). The eligible entity shall cease reserving matching funds on behalf of that student as described in paragraph (1)(D). Any remaining funds that the student or the student's family deposited in a postsecondary education match savings account shall be made available for withdrawal in accordance with subparagraph (A).</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H037A54725C2443EB9499425E23B39013"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Expiration date</header><text>The expiration date described in this clause is—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0891F5753534B7BB2FB552D23D133BF"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date that is 8 years after the date on which a participating eligible student first enrolled in an eligible educational institution; or</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCDA2F2ABE93D44F4A298E056F4E52845"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of a student with preliminary eligibility, or a participating eligible student who does not enroll in an eligible educational institution, the date that is 4 years after the date on which the student first agrees to participate in the postsecondary education match savings account demonstration grant program. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6250222AA18A4865A6D2A7872DB57380"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Management costs</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section may use not more than 5 percent of grant funds for management costs, which may include nonadministrative and administrative functions, including program management, reporting requirements, recruitment and enrollment of individuals, and monitoring.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1F95DE8D20EA48D38D6D538465F6771D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Data sharing</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall enter into a data sharing agreement with eligible educational institutions in order to exchange data necessary to carry out the activities described in this section. Such data sharing shall be carried out in a manner that complies with the requirements of section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (commonly known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8E2E84D301B340A1914E2A5122C01B51"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Annual progress reports</header><text>Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall prepare and submit to the Secretary an annual progress report containing the following information, in the aggregate and in a manner that protects personally identifiable information in accordance with Federal privacy laws:</text>
<paragraph id="H4D7850CF799D4276B366C53E48D001E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number and characteristics of participating students making a deposit into a postsecondary education match savings account supported under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF5BF925C978B49A49A39A0C6597DB42E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Data on program goals and achievements including enrollment rates, first-year retention rates, program completion, average Federal student loan debt, and share of participating eligible students borrowing Federal student loans.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA351A05336294C25AE1761317A8359A7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The amount that the eligible entity has reserved in accordance with subsection (e)(1)(D).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B4762BD0CD840A1A14172C61C3D6534"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The aggregate amounts deposited in postsecondary education match savings accounts by participating students and their families.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1E8C5C62E9484601935894584BC15F9A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>What service configurations of the eligible entity (such as configurations relating to peer support, structured planning exercises, mentoring, and case management) increased the rate and consistency of participation in the demonstration project and how such configurations varied among different populations or communities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB2DCC2D4718B479EBEB75CFE762D2B66"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Such other information as the Secretary may require to evaluate the demonstration project.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3A3A78486F93480B8ABE02BE9300E019"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the establishment of the demonstration project under this section, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to Congress a report containing the following information:</text> <paragraph id="H688430F777F34388B02209E80EEDF2FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The effects of incentives and organizational or institutional support on postsecondary retention in the demonstration project.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7F8A1D8BBBAE4A85AF48C600E049264E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The savings rates of individuals in the demonstration project, in the aggregate and disaggregated by demographic characteristics including gender, age, family size, race or ethnic background, and income.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3777A45D7A594C2D96309FA5929319B2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The effects of postsecondary education match savings accounts on savings rates and postsecondary education retention and completion, and how such effects vary among different populations or communities.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H057566C564BC4B5A8160E66922F741FE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The lessons to be learned from the demonstration projects conducted under this section and whether a permanent postsecondary education savings grant program should be established.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6E51A9D9FCDD490D81C08AC382486F2C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The characteristics of postsecondary education match savings accounts (such as threshold amounts and match rates) required to stimulate participation in the demonstration project, and how such characteristics vary among different populations or communities.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H08F16D29CDEA4DC5AB5F93A803DAD3C4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Such other factors as may be prescribed by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2B4684F19D7E4CBC960B98BC32D9B973"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary may reserve not more than 10 percent of the amounts appropriated under section 6 to provide technical assistance to eligible entities receiving grants under this section.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H9E65BDB069664A3CA4CB69B9301A0733"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $100,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each of the succeeding 4 years. </text></section> </legis-body></bill>

