<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H96FA05D891BC4A8795E911779E460139" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3655 IH: Preventing Our Next Natural Disaster Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3655</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230524">May 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance predisaster mitigation to prevent future natural disasters, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE43DB20245464D749541A63EFF2B6348" style="OLC"><section id="H910AF95AFA0A4082AF3719CD24005EB6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing Our Next Natural Disaster Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA650F0C8AD5E4092AD5CC1FBDE5F9985"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203(a) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5133">42 U.S.C. 5133(a)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD8E917018C054167B959A2D528CBABCD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H13CB26066E324424BE6260E68F52ACD4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="H2DBEDB370849406BBBF9B955140E7C77"><enum>(1)</enum><header>High hazard risk</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>high hazard risk</quote> means high rating of a natural hazard risk according to a tool such as the National Risk Index or another tool developed by the Federal Emergency Management Agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14BF21E5F3DF45F78FA8E3BDE848F058"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Environmental justice community</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>environmental justice community</quote> means a community primarily composed of communities of color, low-income communities, or Tribal and indigenous communities, that experiences, or is at risk of experiencing, higher or more adverse human health or environmental effects than most communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H813223EF3DB64958B84BC0C21205DAC3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Small impoverished community</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>small impoverished community</quote> means a community that is comprised of 50,000 or fewer individuals and that is economically disadvantaged, as determined by the State in which the community is located and based on criteria established by the President. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HCB3E8FAF49A84BD185443C39FFC2CE1F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203(e) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5133">42 U.S.C. 5133(e)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H742453CFF550476A9F0E29F5EB96537C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H15759C8F2B3247A6A2D6E310B5AF92B0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may develop guidance regarding how to incorporate climate change into—</text><subparagraph id="HF24877F65236465A8494D09B0C051064"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the National Risk Index;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E9E948D63604787853A3B448BF43862"><enum>(B)</enum><text>cost-benefit analyses; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB930919B378B4D60A4D331B4D0FBC06F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">adopting improved relevant consensus-based codes, specifications, and standards to address natural hazards.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA42D5FABF86147E6A86DFE3278B99DC9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Building, restoration, or rehabilitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may issue guidance to ensure that funds provided under this section are used to support the building, restoration, or rehabilitation of hazard mitigation projects that are—</text><subparagraph id="HE02AB7980AC24AF7B69159BD47122631"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">planned and designed around the future projections of climate change over the life cycle of the project; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC80590DA78E940F896A0D8D4E61A483F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">built to withstand future flooding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HEB797B205AF3466A9FAAB31D8F18F80A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Criteria for assistance awards</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203(g) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5133">42 U.S.C. 5133(g)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HDF109FD0ED0446B39C0505FC30E5448B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (11);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H337A7D6D3B9B400AB57D9A1CE7C828BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (12) as paragraph (13); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD259F59E49734F9AA1895EA4B041F06A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (11) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H608A442E57604AD98B22AF03FB3FC999" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H3735F588CD5E480C98351B7489851A4C"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">and prioritize communities that are in high hazard risk communities, environmental justice communities, communities with low tax revenue base per capita, and communities with a low rate of code adoption and enforcement and infrastructure maintenance expenditures (the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency shall establish guidelines to develop measurable criteria to determine such priority for high hazard risk communities and integrate the data into a tool such as the National Risk Index and use the Resilience Analysis and Planning Tool to help target the communities with the greatest need of assistance); and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H963F52FFCCE343C88182C4EC9FDF61F4"><enum>5.</enum><header>Federal share</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203(h)(2) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5133">42 U.S.C. 5133(h)(2)</external-xref> is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H47486629E86A423FA36AA810D1A47488" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H617DFA55C3124C0EB85F3D4F0D8A978E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Small impoverished communities and environment justice communities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding paragraph (1), the President may contribute up to 90 percent of the total cost of a mitigation activity carried out in a small impoverished community or an environmental justice community.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HE42AAAB17D164B37B3267184EDD66174"><enum>6.</enum><header>National public infrastructure predisaster mitigation assistance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203(i)(1) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5133">42 U.S.C. 5133(i)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF1EBAFDCF64C406DB511A3FFE87211DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>6 percent</quote> and inserting <quote>15 percent</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81C600C80CD44FB48C3E2CCBA3F878C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>From such total amount made available from the Disaster Relief Fund, with respect to each major disaster, the President may set aside 2 percent of the estimated aggregate amount of the grants to be made pursuant to sections 403, 406, 407, 408, 410, 416, and 428 for the major disaster for community planning and capacity building assistance.</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H43DC683A6FF94765A14D277C1F8BC3A9"><enum>7.</enum><header>Community outreach</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 203 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5133">42 U.S.C. 5133</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H606819CECB2C4893AACC53C8A3C46E07" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HB247F7E721494AA88C9482585478C3A5"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Community outreach assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, in collaboration with organizations, such as the United States Cooperative Extension System and the Extension Disaster Education Network, shall provide community outreach to communities under this section, with a goal of increasing applications from communities with high hazard risk, environmental justice communities, communities with low tax revenue base per capita, and communities with a low rate of code adoption and enforcement and infrastructure maintenance expenditures, regarding how to plan and prioritize projects based on current climate conditions, future hazard risk, and social vulnerability assessments as well as how to successfully develop, submit, and administer a grant under this section.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HB27EFEAC2096496EBC549064A1DD1921"><enum>8.</enum><header>Improved data collection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency shall establish a central Federal database at the Agency, in coordination with the Department of Housing and Urban Development, the Environment Protection Agency, the Economic Development Administration, the Small Business Administration, the Army Corps of Engineers, and any other relevant agencies the Administrator chooses to include, to consolidate funding data collected by all local, State, and Federal agencies involved in post-disaster response and predisaster mitigation spending and categorize the data by type of project, funding source, and hazard types using an user friendly database and interactive map. Such database shall also include—</text><paragraph id="H3FB4EAA88B1845799D996FEAF7182E23"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the collection and posting of census track data and post aggregate demographic data, pursuant to the Paperwork Reduction Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/44/3501">44 U.S.C. 3501 et seq.</external-xref>) as well as any future guidance by such office on data equity on the impact of natural disaster and Federal recovery efforts to better allocate and trace funds; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B04CAE09BC045A6A79973D8C618F2B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>post-project evaluations by the Agency to analyze disaster spending and report findings on what may have been saved by proper predisaster mitigation.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

