<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0BA0DC5B29CC471AA38936D259D357E2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2695 IH: WOlf and Livestock Fairness Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2695</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230418">April 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000136">Mr. Vasquez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Agricultural Act of 2014 to provide emergency relief to producers of livestock with herds adversely affected by Mexican gray wolves, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD23104CB528C4455976043976AB4075E" style="OLC"><section id="HDE328AD791374E1181EF6321B85347EF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>WOlf and Livestock Fairness Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>WOLF Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HA5592F782D9948F8A6BB7F175DE566F8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Livestock indemnity payment rates</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1501(b)(2) of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/9081">7 U.S.C. 9081(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>75</quote> and inserting <quote>100</quote>. </text></section><section id="HD38B9A96DF6249EC881C86A8539EA3A4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Emergency relief to mitigate effect of Mexican gray wolves</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1501(d) of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/9081">7 U.S.C. 9081(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H2D3D3484F72D41868C51E022C7A0D98A"><paragraph id="HD6C9A5B3C322408D85435F80FAD3F33F" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Emergency relief to mitigate effect of Mexican gray wolves</header><subparagraph id="H710825A1AC7145BB972A01CAD993BD62" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each fiscal year, the Secretary shall use funds made available under paragraph (1) to provide emergency relief to producers of livestock with herds adversely affected by Mexican gray wolves, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86A00F2619034A93A16FA1CD2C124107" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Formula</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall develop a formula to determine the amount of emergency relief to provide to a producer of livestock under subparagraph (A), which shall take into consideration the following factors:</text><clause id="H22DF8D344DC448DA8460925E2A715FF2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The herd size of the producer.</text></clause><clause id="H62B8D1CF4EFA4BF5BBF464D4F9D4EBF8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The average annual number of confirmed depredations by Mexican gray wolves per producer in the State in which the producer is located.</text></clause><clause id="HA3E13C4727884D0F872C67308F87FBDE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The average annual increase in management costs for producers due to Mexican gray wolves during the preceding 5 years in the State in which the producer is located.</text></clause><clause id="H075353E24465474387361EC5CAF89F75"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The average annual decrease in birth rates of herds of producers due to Mexican gray wolves during the preceding 5 years in the State in which the producer is located.</text></clause><clause id="H47CEA12B7A294C738947EE747A88D63F"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The depredation prevention practices carried out by the producer, if any, as reported through the wolf compensation and prevention program established by section 6202 of the Omnibus Public Land Management Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/8351">7 U.S.C. 8351</external-xref> note).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED5D9065379D4293BE04EA4F914BC65E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out this paragraph, the Secretary shall consult with, and request information from, as necessary, the Administrator of the Farm Service Agency of the Department of Agriculture, the Administrator of the Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service of the Department of Agriculture, and the Director of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3DD4F032F53411CB27476D3BF661514"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which emergency relief is first provided under this paragraph, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate a report on activities carried out under this paragraph, which shall include an identification of the following:</text><clause id="HBD3C902744ED44C48EA0B7C22C88FB7D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of emergency relief distributed to producers under this paragraph.</text></clause><clause id="HA873AB57AE094126B1E0F70E4059CBC1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The number of producers receiving emergency relief under this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

