<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1D8DD977389E4217BBDB7EE6125875E0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6902 IH: To direct the Department of Defense to report to Congress on the efforts of the Department to coordinate with the defense industrial base for purposes of countering certain capabilities of the People’s Liberation of Army.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6902</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231222">December 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Department of Defense to report to Congress on the efforts of the Department to coordinate with the defense industrial base for purposes of countering certain capabilities of the People’s Liberation of Army.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5654331EE5974DF792B024F1C2FDEF4E" style="OLC"><section id="H5D5FA87FE88C40BA9B016E9DAF309BF6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Report on efforts to counter certain capabilities of the People’s Liberation of Army</header><subsection id="H2DF176B79EC34D4BA59A960BE04D0098"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than March 30, 2024, the Under Secretary of Defense for Policy, in coordination with the Chair of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, the commanders of the combatant commands, and the Secretaries of the military departments, shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and the House of Representatives a report on the efforts of the Department of Defense to coordinate with the defense industrial base to counter the command, control, communications, computers, cyber, intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance (commonly referred to as <quote>C5ISR</quote>) capabilities of the People’s Liberation Army.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCF2BDC5E77AF439E9CDEAA4177EAA1DE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H7835DD3C97A541B2ACA263ECAA257C0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the efforts of the Department of Defense to better coordinate with the defense industrial base in the space and cyber domains for purposes of countering the C5ISR capabilities of the People’s Liberation Army.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B906DE8BAE44B11B9EA6EF989F284FF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A plan for expanding such coordination, including plans for—</text><subparagraph id="H28C0D2FA95944E76AD9ED89FED3450B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conducting table-top exercises with interagency and industry participants and institutions that interface with commercial partners of the Department; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5243276CF39B4761B44DD64D57FF33FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing mechanisms through which organizations in the defense industrial base can share information on C5ISR threats with the Department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CA04EEC7A39405F8983E23D624CE237"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Feedback from commercial partners and other departments and agencies of the Federal Government on—</text><subparagraph id="H2955719FBD0F43E7AA9E199FCA5B6BEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the implications for the defense industrial base of a potential conflict with the People’s Liberation Army involving C5ISR capabilities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50A58EF23E034C4E893A3B9E53F1D49E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>steps that may be taken to enhance the ability of the Department and the defense industrial base to counter such capabilities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

