<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDF6E3A305CDC4157BDB4AEBB18BEC850" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3533 IH: Home Advantage for American Families Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3533</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reduce the excessive appreciation of United States residential real estate due to foreign purchases.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB24D2C1C5E61446D90E797501FE4352B" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HCDCFF4093D23403E91D6A7360FD4A59C"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Home Advantage for American Families Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCDA6E195024545CBBAB478FFD0B5DB7D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expansion of tools to combat money laundering</header><subsection id="H2A95AA46664046C9AF5CDDFC53C46FB5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9CE4E9E7F24440C1A1D1BC67A46A1C41"><section id="H314BAB58ECC9474D95553063BB97907F"><enum>5337.</enum><header>Reports on applicable residential property</header><subsection id="H312FFD1931094F65886883248B23AF88"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2678BB0D8EF14C5F9C66002C75813670"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicable residential property</header><text>The term <term>applicable residential property</term> means property described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1445">section 1445(f)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and which is located in any of the 15 largest metropolitan statistical areas by population (as determined by the Office of Management and Budget). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4575EC23A11412F8EB73EC72802D432"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign person</header><text>The term <term>foreign person</term> means any person that is not a citizen or permanent resident of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA37900E5FFC94375842D0CFCFCF59016"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sale of applicable residential property</header><text>The term <term>sale of applicable residential property</term> means the sale of an interest in applicable residential property.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H386EEFB628C54AF1868A4AFE18CBF82C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Any foreign person involved in a transaction related to the sale of applicable residential property shall submit to the Secretary of the Treasury a report with respect to the transaction or any related transaction that contains—</text><paragraph id="H073E19849B9C4CA1A4A6A84F0592E965"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name and any other identification information that the Secretary determines is necessary of the individual purchasing the applicable residential property;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BD966A2C0204001B9E87BB2DFF80E6C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the amount and source of the funds received by the seller, as determined by the Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65054742A5814F03898ED866DDB65651"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the date and nature of the transaction; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67E179E8034D4432B0A739B58BAA2C3B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other information, including the identification of the person filing the report, that the Secretary determines is necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44750DD09138443A82842E4E3AB846FD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall promulgate regulations carrying out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H3F1FA25F8EE142DCABF24380E0C0A032"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/53">chapter 53</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H70B84A205E904808B6D770E59FF55FD3"><toc><toc-entry idref="H314BAB58ECC9474D95553063BB97907F" level="section">5337. Reports on applicable residential property.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HE46C454ADA2C4CA6BF40EDCCA18AC2C0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>List of top 15 largest metropolitan statistical areas</header><text>Not less frequently than every 5 years, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall update the list of the 15 largest metropolitan statistical areas by population.</text></subsection></section><section id="HCD4C6C4EBE2F4D848B0EE08C7A11213C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Increased withholding on sale disposition of certain United States real property interests</header><subsection id="H1AD0407DB88E46EE99FFA860D480E0FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1445">Section 1445</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (f) as subsection (g) and by inserting after subsection (e) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6EFDB3042A1244F49C2075F9057E9FAC"><subsection id="H0E16F6A50D694CC6917B0B44B611D3E8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Special rule for certain dispositions of residential real property</header><paragraph id="H9801A1D4D4A34B3897AF9442A43C84C6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of the disposition of any applicable residential property, subsection (a) shall be applied by substituting <quote>30 percent</quote> for <quote>15 percent</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AD4CEE8D8924478ADE061731D151589"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable residential property</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>applicable residential property</term> means any interest which—</text><subparagraph id="H09FC7B003D324C71B5A5F84F59AC4C38"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is an interest described in section 897(c)(1)(A)(i), and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF9882192AE44CE6895E14C6783725ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is an interest in residential real property.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H874BF64E4CAE4F62A7E6576D1ABE24A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply to dispositions after the date which is 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H60A2C8B7544743CEB502984748220F58"><enum>4.</enum><header>Increase in low-income housing tax credit State ceiling</header><subsection id="HCC3B4D459C164936AEBE40429417A6F8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/42">Section 42(h)(3)(C)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>plus</quote> at the end of clause (iii), by striking the period at the end of clause (iv) and inserting <quote>, plus</quote>, and by inserting after clause (iv) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA84D3858BBB484E98DFD14AED790856"><clause id="H2A8D1A12F9C0461D8EF0FF19107B37F9"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the qualified single-family housing amount determined under subparagraph (J).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H4C142C53A7114F44BA19072BA2F598E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified single-Family housing amount</header><paragraph id="HB51F9060250A47F0970CA27E6D1F0D31"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/42">Section 42(h)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8DFFB99DE6944EE1B860413526B8387C"><subparagraph id="HAC0FB03C469746FD97E161F49CBF4DEF"><enum>(J)</enum><header>Qualified single-family housing amount</header><text>The qualified single-family housing amount determined under this subparagraph for any calendar year is an amount equal to the sum of—</text><clause id="H497A630E1E4C4AF09455271A337877E8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>10 percent of the amount determined under subparagraph (C)(ii) for such calendar year (determined after application of subparagraphs (H) and (I)),</text></clause><clause id="HB6EBCFA02DAD4620B8A4741FD3755B4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the excess (if any) of the amount described in clause (i) for the preceding calendar year over the amounts allocated to projects described in paragraph (9) for such preceding calendar year,</text></clause><clause id="H892729F23633437BAD95AF2E65C13C7C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the amount allocated within the State (not in excess of the amount determined under this subparagraph for the preceding calendar year reduced by the amount described in clause (ii) for the second preceding calendar year) for any project—</text><subclause id="HC1B168C165B649ADBF355E46CEE960A3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>which is described in paragraph (9) and which fails to meet the 10 percent test under paragraph (1)(E)(ii) on a date after the close of the calendar year in which the allocation was made,</text></subclause><subclause id="HE5065C00F0E7440B81E3DAA9115B018A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>which does not become a qualified low-income housing project described in paragraph (9) within the period required by this section or the terms of the allocation, or</text></subclause><subclause id="H525C198F6CDC4B4EB87599E4E177333C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>which is described in paragraph (9) and with respect to which an allocation is cancelled by mutual consent of the housing credit agency and the allocation recipient, plus</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H50D0B1FC08234C3FAB3AB5BFC2E7471E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the amount, if any, determined under subparagraph (D), applied—</text><subclause id="H6D212E32DD5B451A8D3A99E2DB990765"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by substituting <quote>unused qualified single-family housing carryover</quote> for <quote>unused housing credit carryover</quote> in clause (i) thereof, </text></subclause><subclause id="H0F655EBA7C2244C0834E2D6D2596EE01"><enum>(II)</enum><text>without regard to clause (ii) thereof,</text></subclause><subclause id="HD0221A4BE48A4C17838E37E8A80D38E6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by substituting <quote>unused qualified single-family housing carryovers</quote> for <quote>unused housing credit carryovers</quote> in clause (iii) thereof, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H838B8364636A4EE28853F573772D6DE4"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by substituting <quote>an amount equal to its entire qualified single-family housing amount to projects described in paragraph (9)</quote> for <quote>entire State housing credit ceiling (determined without regard to amounts described in subparagraph (C)(v))</quote> in clause (iv)(I) thereof.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BAAF9897EF84343B1A548F7D6BEA77F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><subparagraph id="H1BCB4FC91EBF4758B7D07734FEC7690B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Section 42(h)(3)(C) of such Code is amended by inserting <quote>(other than amounts allocated from the qualified single-family housing amount)</quote> after <quote>the housing credit dollar amount previously allocated within the State</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H934AB3E660A44C05AB49E88D0A4E6D6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Section 42(h)(3)(D) of such Code is amended by inserting <quote>(determined without regard to amounts described in subparagraph (C)(v))</quote> after <quote>entire State housing credit ceiling</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H06C6202F83944C97920E1AB60E15BA75"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Set aside of increased amounts</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/42">Section 42(h)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9166D9C6306B4C79878613F09E7FFCC8"><paragraph id="H0DF02B4A62574E4B8188459C5DB98F40"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Set aside of qualified single-family housing amount</header><text>The portion of the State housing credit ceiling which is equal to the qualified single-family housing amount for any calendar year shall be allocated to projects consisting of 1 to 4 dwelling units that are located in qualified census tracts (as defined in subsection (d)(5)(B)(i)).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H96EECF4B2B5C4341A194A13DCB8D2B11"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to allocations made for calendar years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

