<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCE7A63B5D9C840218E353B5E721AEBA9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6443 IH: Jamul Indian Village Land Transfer Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6443</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231117">November 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To take certain land in the State of California into trust for the benefit of the Jamul Indian Village of California Tribe, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE32E63E3169647D788D516EDBB16E67C" style="OLC"><section id="H74B6CA1B6F9B41098BCFD542235CFA5B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Jamul Indian Village Land Transfer Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H2190C19920D34CE8A2DC0E113B150020"><enum>2.</enum><header>Land to be taken into trust for the Jamul Indian Village of California tribe</header><subsection id="H007AA9BCCD7845FE858814E2E9ABF431"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The approximately 172.1 acres of land owned in fee by the Jamul Indian Village of California located in San Diego, California, and described in subsection (b) are hereby taken into trust by the United States for the benefit of the Jamul Indian Village of California.</text></subsection><subsection id="H214EE792CFBB46A6A25ACF151F164ECA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Land descriptions</header><paragraph id="H8DF6C959B07E4CDDA4D453DF43D9388A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Parcel 1</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Those parcels of land totaling approximately 161.23 acres, located in San Diego County, California, that are held in fee by the Jamul Indian Village of California, as legally described in Document No. 2022–0010260 in the Official Records of the Office of the Recorder, San Diego County, California, and recorded January 7, 2022.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90606C956CE94D4B93EB4D64B4B2E59E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Parcel 2</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">That parcel of land totaling approximately 6 acres, located in San Diego County, California, that is held in fee by the Jamul Indian Village of California, as legally described in Document No. 2021–0540770 in the Official Records of the Office of the Recorder, San Diego County, California, and recorded July 29, 2021.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96A9482C419042699E65564B0AD66BBD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Parcel 3</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">That parcel of land totaling approximately 4.03 acres, located in San Diego County, California, that is held in fee by the Jamul Indian Village of California, as legally described in Document No. 1998–0020339 in the Official Records of the Office of the Recorder, San Diego County, California, and recorded January 15, 1998.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H94428E8D5F474F1A92121EF8EE301965"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Parcel 4</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">That parcel of land comprised of approximately 0.84 acres, located in San Diego County, California, that is held in fee by the Jamul Indian Village of California, as legally described in Document No. 2017–0410384 in the Official Records of the Office of the Recorder, San Diego County, California, and recorded September 7, 2017.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B5052CF41A24CD2B177A4F4FFDB65EF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>Land taken into trust under subsection (a) shall be—</text><paragraph id="HCA8405F6AAEF4E4AA313F02A00515FB1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>part of the reservation of the Jamul Indian Village of California; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H853A5B82E712460487A80C723F20B7E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>administered in accordance with the laws and regulations generally applicable to property held in trust by the United States for the benefit of an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H66618935DB3A47E180F9A7A44976BAF1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Gaming prohibited</header><text>Land taken into trust under subsection (a) shall not be used for any class II gaming or class III gaming under the Indian Gaming Regulatory Act (as those terms are defined in section 4 of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2703">25 U.S.C. 2703</external-xref>)).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

