<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H32092FB497424924BD46F484980510B9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 6792 IH: PSLF Administrative Improvements Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6792</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the public service loan forgiveness program under the Higher Education Act of 1965 to require an on-line portal, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H960027D9640F47B38CD895573A192F40" style="OLC"><section id="HE0460D0F74CD4C7F8FE337480B17BAA3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>PSLF Administrative Improvements Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA6BDC8CFAC714903AE3A405AF8D62A62"><enum>2.</enum><header>Additional public service loan forgiveness program requirements for the Secretary of Education</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 455(m) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087e">20 U.S.C. 1087e(m)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8294319444244D3386FEA312D38788FA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H9546CCD62383490591CBFBBFF6A82526"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Database of public service jobs</header><subparagraph id="H6FAC68E03F4D4616952F7377226AC3EA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of the PSLF Administrative Improvements Act, the Secretary of Education, in conjunction with the Secretary of Labor, shall—</text><clause id="H350CBF9A22EB4426873B085FD5464357"><enum>(i)</enum><text>establish and regularly update a publicly accessible database of public service employers, which shall include information required for the process for completion of the employment certifications forms required under this subsection; and</text></clause><clause id="H0FCC6CDAF7164FC2970085942C834A06"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure that such employment certification forms are available in languages other than English.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6428058FFF9495F9C90C8FED1173648" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection:</text><clause id="HA9CC83D1A80D4628950E2003081BC1F8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Public service employer</header><text>The term <term>public service employer</term> has the meaning given the term <term>public service organization</term> in section 685.219(b) of title 34, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></clause><clause id="HFB594E3DDF744155B0A70DCF6EAEE71D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>TEPSLF program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>TEPSLF program</term> means the Temporary Expanded Public Service Loan Forgiveness program carried out by the Department of Education, including the program carried out under section 311 of division H of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6421FE3F5D7E4CF3AE5ADEB72B0AA7B8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Notice of PSLF requirements</header><subparagraph id="HD12D35F03AA84385A67EA2B864EB5D1D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Employers</header><text>With respect to each employer whose contact information is maintained in the database described in paragraph (5), the Secretary shall, on an annual basis and in a manner that is consistent with Federal laws on data privacy—</text><clause id="HEFDC4FD765CB4DB6B8075815420DB6BD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide each such employer with standardized information on the program under this subsection, including eligibility requirements;</text></clause><clause id="H330AFA40487A46AFACBFD7DB2DDBEE93"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>encourage the employer to provide such information to new employees; and</text></clause><clause id="H529BB3DB55AA43B6BCC4323035D252BF" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an employer that is likely to be subject to a determination by the Secretary that the employer is failing to meet the definition of public service employer—</text><subclause id="H35A2877CDCE64EBE9CE9B5ECFF20BAC1" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>notify such employer that such a determination is likely, prior to such determination; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H06AD929C74E6451A9966F3847777598E" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provide the employer an opportunity to make changes in order to avoid such determination, and if applicable, an opportunity to appeal such determination.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02569571758D412AA970950403C152C3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Institutions of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each institution of higher education participating in any program under this title, the Secretary shall, on an annual basis, provide each such institution with standardized information on the program under this subsection, including eligibility requirements.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EE80BEFEF1E47C7A7007CED9427CF73"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Borrowers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each borrower who was denied loan cancellation under this subsection, the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="H4762EBA1B6D24BE989629434D408B14D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">without any further action by the borrower and subject to the limitation on total loan volume specified under the TEPSLF program and the availability of appropriations for such section 315, determine whether the borrower qualifies for the loan cancellation program under the TEPSLF, and if so, cancel the borrower’s loans in accordance with such program; and</text></clause><clause id="HB47C1195D14444F5A267E65B823F3684"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a case in which a borrower’s loans were not cancelled under clause (i), notify the borrower of other options (such as loan consolidation) to qualify for loan cancellation under this subsection, and how to successfully pursue such options.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H30C93AA26DD241D7A2869F8DD7A1B26E"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Data matching agreements</header><subparagraph id="HAD66E9A3549C4C65A7520D1E10AA94F2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into data matching agreements with relevant Federal agencies who possess records about the status of borrowers of loans made under this part as employees of public service employers for the purpose of eliminating, to the extent practicable, the need for a borrower or an employer to submit a certification of employment to the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD11385F03F334231874CBD5195D83109"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Specific Federal agencies</header><text>Notwithstanding any Federal law, the Secretary of Labor, the Commissioner of Internal Revenue, and the Commissioner of Social Security shall disclose any relevant records to the Secretary for the purposes of meeting the Secretary’s obligations to reduce barriers to certification of employment as described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C5F38174BC2447E91BDBB6210E0CB7D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Notice to borrowers</header><text>If the Secretary receives employer or employment information regarding a borrower from a Federal agency pursuant to this paragraph, the Secretary shall timely notify the borrower that—</text><clause id="HFE3B13C2B39443D38E5D155CCC8AA9F1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary received the information; and</text></clause><clause id="HCB5B1ED25DBB4A9CA3ED88E6C03513D9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the borrower, for the duration of the borrower's employment by the employer—</text><subclause id="H1E22E3BAB94148F19730A80E647192C9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is not required to submit a certification of employment for the employer under paragraph (8); or</text></subclause><subclause id="HFE5D417986CE42F2A7609AB7D14DA623"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if the information is not complete, only needs to submit a reduced set of information to the Secretary for the certification of employment.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A29CB118BAC43CF826094EB0DD267C7"><enum>(8)</enum><header>On-line portal</header><subparagraph id="H8562132D80C04750B5E2E8DAC5570B2D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Borrowers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of the PSLF Administrative Improvements Act, the Secretary shall ensure that borrowers have access to an on-line portal, integrated with the Federal Student Aid dashboard (or any successor dashboard or similar website) that provides each borrower who signs on to such portal with the following: </text><clause id="HA354FAC56D1A45238581B677B46164B9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Instructions on how to access the database under paragraph (5) so that the borrower can determine whether the borrower is employed in a public service job. </text></clause><clause id="HD5DD434D9C5142C5B4F5D7A64D026B98"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An identification of the loans of the borrower that are eligible Federal Direct Loans.</text></clause><clause id="H7AA2D2838F6C49F8A8DFCB54F8789E4D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>With respect to each such eligible Federal Direct Loan, the number of monthly payments on such loan that qualify as a monthly payment under paragraph (1)(A), and the estimated number of monthly payments under paragraph (1)(A) remaining on such loan before the borrower may be eligible for loan cancellation under this subsection. </text></clause><clause id="H323E92515C3B495F898FBA805B73A787"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>With respect to each loan of the borrower that is not eligible for loan cancellation under this subsection, an explanation of why the loan is not so eligible and instructions on what, if anything, the borrower may do to make the loan so eligible. </text></clause><clause id="H10EDDE9BFD004B1CB9A30C2FF2DF8A55"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Instructions for the submission of any forms associated with such loan cancellation, and an ability for the borrower to use the portal to electronically sign and submit such forms. </text></clause><clause id="H70E9DB84F9654B12AC6E1E4385DB7DA7"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>In the case of a borrower who disputes a determination of the Secretary relating to the entitlement of the borrower to loan cancellation under paragraph (2) or with respect to a determination that a loan is not eligible pursuant to clause (iv)—</text><subclause id="HEF2A04087F8E43219E22FF9B3E32A1AA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an ability for the borrower to file a claim with the Secretary to dispute such determination through the portal; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H526961DD65644378A6420C3935EFA729"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the case of such a claim that has been filed the status of such claim, for which updates shall be provided not fewer than once every 90 days.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17FD30899F984AA490E78DD61B4350B3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Employers</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that an employer of a borrower has the ability to electronically sign and submit any forms associated with loan cancellation under this subsection. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A2ECE5FB31D4BFB90E056FE12930287"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Information</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any information provided through the on-line portal described in this paragraph—</text><clause id="H5872B5ADA79949E2A1FFAC77C5E09EFB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is up-to-date information; and</text></clause><clause id="H3227F160897143EB8D1D9B4DF829D561"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that such information is also provided in a written-format through email or regular mail, if so requested by the borrower or employer.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0FEB61DB81F4C02B07162BA4FC68F77"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Standard procedures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the PSLF Administrative Improvements Act, the Secretary shall develop and make publicly available the procedures the Secretary (including the contractors and servicers involved) uses to determine whether a borrower meets the requirements for loan cancellation under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75BD758E295847DC86FB36B7EB7C2430"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit to the authorizing committees, an annual report with respect to the preceding fiscal year, on—</text><subparagraph id="HB3C4178740A040A9A803EEC45CFEFE71"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of borrowers who received loan cancellation under this subsection, and the number of such borrowers whose application for such loan cancellation had been previously rejected, disaggregated by each category of public service job listed in the employment certification form required under this subsection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94D026F556704FC882591184AA67784A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of borrowers whose application for loan cancellation under this subsection was rejected, and a description of why each such application was so rejected, disaggregated by each category of public service job described in subparagraph (A); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1E3C04C014D4A34AF99016AE04EB754"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of borrowers whose application for loan cancellation under this subsection had been rejected and who contacted the Secretary to determine how to qualify for such loan cancellation or loan cancellation under the TEPSLF program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E8BE805B6A04133998B64AEB0EBF2BE"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each reason why a payment made on an eligible Federal Direct Loan did not qualify as one of the 120 monthly payments under paragraph (1)(A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54A58057DA0C49208814253776F24A20" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of borrowers employed by an employer that—</text><clause id="HBF8305B2E32F4DA689D9DA32EF557C13" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code; and</text></clause><clause id="H33B69D3E0F694FD59540D3BCC5B9782E" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>was determined to meet the definition of public service employer; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2127D9F26FC14DF3BB9906CEAC287B8E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the number of borrowers employed by an employer described in subparagraph (E)(i) that was determined to not meet the definition of public service employer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H5CB54A10007440ECB06190825D180C93" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Clarification of TEPSLF</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A borrower may qualify for loan forgiveness under the Temporary Expanded Public Service Loan Forgiveness program carried out by the Department of Education, including the program carried out under section 311 of division H of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>), without regard to whether the borrower’s application for loan cancellation under section 455(m) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087e">20 U.S.C. 1087e(m)</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is rejected.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

