<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9D646624CCD84473A61083994EE92CF9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4547 IH: LESS Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4547</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a fund to promote the inspection and consumption of shrimp and products containing shrimp or shrimp parts.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1B888CE7F7D045D8960FB8D29B9A4C89" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H692330FCF147413AA212B4EA23111E87" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Laws Ensuring Safe Shrimp Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>LESS Act</quote>. </text></section> <section id="H7CC8ADBE5A11467492C6BFAAF460F6BC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inspection and Consumption of Shrimp and Shrimp Products Fund</header> <subsection id="H0749BD66F84647628279790BCB37067B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established in the Treasury of the United States a fund to be known as the <quote>Inspection and Consumption of Shrimp and Shrimp Products Fund</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Fund</quote>), consisting of such amounts as may be transferred to the Fund under subsection (b) and to be available as provided for under subsection (c).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8913EA834ACE4A61813FD30B6094B0FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transfer of amounts</header> 
<paragraph id="H1DEB2F39BDD149A9A97AF6A6832F896C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall transfer to the Fund, from the general fund of the Treasury, amounts determined by the Secretary to be equivalent to 70 percent of amounts received in the general fund that are attributable to duties assessed by the United States, including duties assessed pursuant to a countervailing duty order or antidumping duty order under the Tariff Act of 1930 or a finding under the Antidumping Act of 1921, collected on imports of shrimp and products containing shrimp or shrimp parts described in paragraph (2) for fiscal year 2024 and each subsequent fiscal year.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E84817292CB4AAFBB3B57F76AE7F15D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Shrimp and products containing shrimp or shrimp parts described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The shrimp and products containing shrimp or shrimp parts described in this paragraph are those products provided for in any subheading of the Harmonized Tariff Schedule of the United States, including subheadings 0306.16.00, 0306.17.00, 0306.35.00, 0306.36.00, 0306.95.00, 1605.21, and 1605.29 of such schedule (or successor subheadings). </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5568298DF5784FDE8A997410ECEE72CD" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of amounts</header><text>Amounts in the Fund shall be available for each such fiscal year as follows:</text> <paragraph id="H29FF09DD6AE742C188EA8E86CCF9D6B6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fifty percent of such amounts shall be used by the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, for—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4CE2FD906F284DCDB9AA4990028FA502"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the inspection, examination, sampling, and testing of shrimp that present a high risk of contamination from unapproved antibiotic residues to identify violations of the provisions of law carried out by the Secretary, acting through the Commissioner;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3179E5F01191448F85F555B4F580DADD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>seafood importer inspections, associated training, capacity building, regulatory partnerships, and development of data analytics in support of such work; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H93538C562C184D159F3CC930E9F4ED22"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordination and data sharing with the Secretary of Commerce, the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, and the heads of other relevant Federal agencies to ensure that imports of shrimp and products containing shrimp or shrimp parts described in subsection (b)(2) are not originating with forced labor or illegal, unreported, or unregulated sources pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/78">Public Law 117–78</external-xref> (an Act to ensure that goods made with forced labor in the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region of the People’s Republic of China do not enter the United States market, and for other purposes). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HADCF00CFFA5B4F339960BEDFC669BF00" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fifty percent of such amounts shall be used by the Secretary of Agriculture to, pursuant to paragraph (2) of the second sentence of section 32 of the Act of August 24, 1935 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/612c">7 U.S.C. 612c</external-xref>), encourage the domestic consumption of shrimp. </text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB9BA63D0A6DF43F5A9325EFE16151310"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Amounts in the Fund shall, notwithstanding any other provision law, remain available until expended.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5F95B704E1CF4C55B20E66964C7D3714"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The funding provided under subsection (c) to purchase shrimp shall supplement (and not supplant) other Federal funding (including funding made available under section 32 of the Act of August 24, 1935 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/612c">7 U.S.C. 612c</external-xref>)) to make such purchases, if appropriate. </text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

