<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7320867A44DC4496A94AFCFB67A1C93E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5908 IH: Strengthening Communities through Summer Employment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5908</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231006">October 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001135">Ms. Manning</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide funding to summer youth employment programs to expand the availability of subsidized jobs for youths and to develop innovative program activities that improve academic, economic, and criminal justice outcomes for youths, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB1A657157E81434389BD79832AEFCF75" style="OLC"><section id="H1CE183A7EBDA47AAB4D89F042FA6D057" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strengthening Communities through Summer Employment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HEF7ACC90EDE84DB5A1788C39EDA921FB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations; distribution of funds </header><subsection id="H3D4C2F7BD11245FB8E9B68E9EFF7F0EE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Labor to carry out this Act—</text><paragraph id="H8D214A8E27EF418585E937EF86C41492"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$200,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAF581832E344E8EA48A16324C452731"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$210,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5969CF5BF0945469410A91EAC07912E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$220,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46B5A544CAD04A36A54E3F832F411780"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$230,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H087D875CD04D44F782E3D0C1FA6B67F2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$240,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC9F31D2A3A7C421197D76665485D4710"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Distribution of funds</header><text>Of the amounts appropriated under subsection (a), the Secretary of Labor shall use—</text><paragraph id="H45A29155DECE4D6C970FE009AED01AE1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>45 percent of such amount to award grants under section 3;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9634A5E69CA545D38D00B1F9CAF6E3BA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>45 percent of such amount to award grants under section 4;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0C5EC0D40874C42AE3508BD0E49B75B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>5 percent of such amount to carry out evaluation activities under section 5(b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1A42CDACBDB4B98B20FE78E58717BCC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>5 percent of such amount to fund the Advisory Board under section 6.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HEDCC68BBBE7A44B18469DBA50E0CB8C6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Expansion and scaling of summer youth employment programs</header><subsection id="H47DFE603EFCF4EC19AAB6C3AA3136A12"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts available under section 2(b)(1), the Secretary of Labor shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to develop and implement new, or expand existing, summer youth employment programs in a State or local area, for the purpose of improving academic, economic, and criminal justice outcomes for participants, including—</text><paragraph id="HEA13984F24864D25B968EABAF21DF9EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">high school graduation rates;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18E8F0BA2CBC46FDA905B24BFC752641"><enum>(2)</enum><text>enrollment rates in postsecondary education;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2709B3A6942422594FF30F8279A9808"><enum>(3)</enum><text>employment and wage rates; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41B2E6880C8346FBBC3D18160B9F73EE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>arrest, conviction, and incarceration rates.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H15AD45C3C62D4DF99953FAD1B25CCE6F" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant prioritization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants to eligible entities under this section, the Secretary of Labor, in coordination with the Advisory Board, shall prioritize eligible entities that, based upon the applications submitted under subsection (c)—</text><paragraph id="H16FA50B55E7C4D49874A33C8E555BEE8" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have higher youth unemployment rates and violent crime rates in the local areas to be served;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H219B25602C3D4BDDA5BA700F992E4F63" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>will offer higher quality and more rigorous the summer youth employment programs (which shall include a consideration of whether the program has been evaluated and, if so, the impact of the program on the youth outcomes listed under subsection (a)); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3DE12687D674BEAA2C5DCC0475603A1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>will serve a higher number of youth historically underserved by summer youth employment programs, including youth in rural and suburban local areas.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H453AF2B3CF7541BBBC280E658FE9C980"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may determine to be necessary, which shall include information that demonstrates that the eligible entity will use such grant to develop and implement, or expand, a summer youth employment program that includes each of the elements listed in subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="HEDDA5DC195944B3581ED3485726FB706"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Required elements for summer youth employment programs</header><text>A summer youth employment program funded under this section shall include each of the following elements:</text><paragraph id="H4AAE02F66840497F99BB61740C22986F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Provides youth participants under the age of 25 with subsidized employment for at least 4 weeks during the summer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E57F92AAD3B45928115D650BFF6DBF3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Pays at least the greater of the applicable Federal, State, or local minimum wage.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF006316B653F4F359A7F6798E275217A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Provides community engagement and outreach to ensure equitable access to the program in terms of awareness, application process, and completion of the hiring process, including documentation of eligibility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7B6B85FE4A547EB849E4D444358B56C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Matches each youth participant with an employer based on the needs of the employer and the skills and interests of the youth participant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FC9F745E8F5417587A79FCA347BD05D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Provides coaching and mentoring services for each youth participant to support the participant’s completion of the summer employment program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5284103B303B4CECA943E8284F818A59"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Provides assistance to each youth participant in obtaining educational and employment opportunities after the completion of the program, such as by connecting participants with secondary school programs, postsecondary education opportunities, apprenticeships, career and technical education, or adult job training programs, if applicable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29B8FB467F1348CFA538894FAC9CC34D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Provides training, coaching, and mentoring services, and technical assistance to participating employers to best help such employers structure the job opportunities of the employers to meet the employer’s needs and the support the success of youth participants.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83C412AFBF38489399B342F151D069C1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Provides program supports to youth participants before, during, and after their program (such as digital literacy training, work-readiness opportunities, financial literacy training, specific job training for their summer job placement, and career counseling services).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6B034457D6D14F2D8362DC8CB4CDCC43"><enum>4.</enum><header>Implementation of innovative program activities</header><subsection id="H8FC46708FA0148459BE5B86D9D3A4EEB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated under section 2(b)(2) for this section, the Secretary of Labor shall provide grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities that operate summer youth employment programs that include each of the program elements listed in section 3(d) to integrate innovative approaches in carrying out such programs for the purposes of improving the youth outcomes listed under section 3(a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HB3967EB310404A868BD25B7EA20C6498" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant prioritization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants to eligible entities under this section, the Secretary of Labor, in coordination with the Advisory Board, shall prioritize eligible entities that, based upon the applications submitted under subsection (c)—</text><paragraph id="H832146A62D2340FE91798F7AEC0698BA" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have higher youth unemployment rates and violent crime rates in the local areas to be served;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C95793BF1D94939B544BABC5E635A40" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>will offer a higher quality and more rigorous summer youth employment program (which shall include a consideration of whether the program has been evaluated and, if so, the impact of the program on the youth outcomes listed in section 3(a));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9601279D86C4404CBF42E4B70EDEBE81" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">will offer a higher quality and more rigorous innovative approach for such program (which shall include a consideration of whether that innovative approach has been evaluated and, if so, the impact of the innovative approach on the youth outcomes listed under section 3(a)); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAB5149CFFE04D9C83000E414DE0317A" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>will serve a higher number of youth historically underserved by summer youth employment programs, including youth in rural and suburban local areas.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBDFF12CC6AAE404299C79CE4762B3E9A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, and in such manner as may be required by the Secretary, which includes a description of the plan to integrate one or more of the innovative approaches listed in subsection (d) into the summer youth employment program operated by the eligible entity.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7CE3C10F81DA44DDBB95A9134E995AF3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Innovative approaches to summer youth employment programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that operates a summer youth employment program that includes the required program elements listed in section 3(d) shall use funds received under this section to integrate into such program one or more of the following innovative approaches:</text><paragraph id="H55345ADB3BD54DB98EAF8E1495900478"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Individualized mentoring and coaching for youth participants, under which each youth participant— </text><subparagraph id="HA6DEF1F6C21B43ADB1F7D722CB992AD0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>before and after the participant starts the program and regularly during the program, meets one-on-one with a dedicated mentor;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB24229435BF548BE90FA020C811B4E4C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develops a comprehensive success plan with the mentor, including academic and employment goals and the steps needed to achieve such goals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H224E94820AA34E69BB9B71AACA723B97"><enum>(C)</enum><text>receives other support from the mentor, which shall include—</text><clause id="HC58310AA5D9B489C82D9C007B4D2B082"><enum>(i)</enum><text>coaching to overcome barriers that could impact progress in completing the employment received under the summer youth employment program;</text></clause><clause id="HE935BD9CBCCC485C8B208CC801663228"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>providing letters of recommendation; and</text></clause><clause id="HFDE217CC854A4FC896A43AF6C81734CB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>making referrals to educational and social services, where necessary.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A08621A96214ACF90F9FC3A6B304CF4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">High-quality job training, career counseling, or educational tutoring programs to be delivered in small group settings before the program, on evenings and weekends during the program, and after the program, with the goal of preparing youth participants for future employment, which shall include assisting youth participants—</text><subparagraph id="HC0386ED2B5A9418DAC90AD7ED764976C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with developing resumes and interviewing skills, and financial literacy; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2448B69268A45CBA2A59A1C28CA2B76"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in completing a regular high school diploma or its recognized equivalent and literacy classes, if applicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6DBA5C354174C52806798D78CAA3BDF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Social-emotional learning for youth participants, including proven interventions to help develop empathy, self-efficacy, positive decision-making, and communication skills.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C98EE4DF2EE42F492050AF57213F463"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Wrap-around financial assistance services, including for food, shelter, and transportation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF053E1391FF4218A43B979F49E4FE6D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Mental health supports for youth participants, as applicable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CC253A4D2894935A49C0D92BD78161C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Substance abuse and addiction treatment supports for youth participants, as applicable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H236704A6D7BD45FDAB243CA56BEB9B78"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The continuation of certain program elements (particularly the individualized mentoring, mental health and behavioral supports, and career counseling), in coordination with their school districts, for a period of time after the employment portion of the program ends to help participants continue their engagement with the education and employment system, with financial assistance available to youth who continue to participate in these program elements after their summer employment has ended.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E75AB098D1B44D9BEB8D938EBC5414B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The provision of one or more of the program elements listed in section 3(d) virtually to develop digital literacy and remote work skills that are a part of many professional settings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H785D700802504E6FA723CC7D8CE3EC44"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provision of Learn and Earn opportunities, in which participants take postsecondary or training courses during nonsummer months coupled with work experience in related fields during the summer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7059652789464B5381CD6AF9D994CC2F"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The expansion of private sector opportunities with employers in in-demand occupations or industry sectors (as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>)), such as information technology, health care, life sciences, and vocational careers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CB1C19B6DE34CC4AB7CA10F5D02F5FC"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The development of skill-based digital badges issued by cities that are recognized by high schools, community colleges, and employers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78A981B2362B4B3EB89F3C7707B92F01"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The laddering of job opportunities from one summer to the next to enable participants to build skills over multiple summers by progressing from entry-level to more senior positions that further develop soft skills (such as leadership skills) or hard skills (such as technical skills).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD1B1F178A2F4C4F8F71D60C7E206001"><enum>(13)</enum><text>A program element identified by the Advisory Board under section 6(i)(3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9119DA00F1EA4831852A4DD33A940714" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A new innovative program element that is not identified by the Advisory Board under section 6(i)(3) and is not listed in this subsection, which is—</text><subparagraph id="H81B6FD07FAA74C66B3121542281CEEF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>proposed by the eligible entity in the application submitted under subsection (b);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CA771135F4D4295A6CED7CA2C03821F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determined by the Secretary, in consultation with the Advisory Board, as being reasonably expected to demonstrate evidence, in the case of an element in which such evidence does not exist, in carrying out the purposes described in subsection (a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC0A7F7E47BC54C39B70532ABD73C90FA"><enum>5.</enum><header>Evaluation activities</header><subsection id="H3C8BAD65BB14442291A80FA3B4F400CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Performance measurement assessments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than 1 year after receiving such grant and for each succeeding year of the grant period, each eligible entity receiving a grant under section 3 or 4, in consultation with the Advisory Board established under section 6, shall develop and implement a performance measurement assessment of such program to assess whether the program is being implemented in a way that meets the requirements of section 3 or 4, respectively. </text></subsection><subsection id="H1BA130D17860414E9B9DD982EA764074"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Impact evaluations</header><paragraph id="H09DA5A04FE504C66808D92C32037371D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amounts appropriated under section 2(b)(3), the Secretary of Labor shall, in consultation with the Advisory Board established under section 6, award a contract to one or more independent research organizations or nonprofit organizations to carry out evaluations to measure the impact of each summer youth employment program that is being supported by a grant awarded under section 3 or 4.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BB1E9DA695F4AAE8B1CB4C7A93F2CBB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements of evaluations</header><text>An impact evaluation of a program that is being supported by a grant awarded under section 3 or 4 shall meet the following requirements:</text><subparagraph id="HE04B86B65C4244229BDA87976ECB6207"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The evaluation begins not later than 3 years after the program first receives such support.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F189218074A42378EC1FE9ADEC56019"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The evaluation shall meet each of the following:</text><clause id="H62EE357A619542B983AA0D853412C27F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Impact evaluation design and analysis methods are shared with the Advisory Board before the beginning of the evaluation. </text></clause><clause id="H6DA226212C464AA5AB46C670CED40CD2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The evaluation uses administrative data to assess the impact of the program as a whole on participants for 1 year, 3 years, and 5 years after the completion of the program on each of the following:</text><subclause id="H3ED4B9B67CCB4982A17380C403E6827A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>High school graduation rates.</text></subclause><subclause id="H23F84160E3224F988DA1503C961E1890"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Enrollment rates in postsecondary education.</text></subclause><subclause id="H7AE59939A4764E999B077036E8D14D23"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Employment and wage rates.</text></subclause><subclause id="H5C2869447B894DFD8D832C362063A60C"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Crime rates (such as arrest, arraignment, or incarceration rates).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H98A9452FA7074963BCE3A47A5887C885"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The evaluation uses survey data collected during the program to assess program impacts on short-term changes in soft skills (such as such as interpersonal, communication, and time management skills), academic and career goals, and job readiness.</text></clause><clause id="H99D45E3A5313449DB1A54001B83C9C7B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The evaluation uses randomized experimental designs, when feasible, or other research methods that allow for the strongest possible causal inferences when random assignment is not feasible.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H12390B541E86421BB5B0B4CD712F2807" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Advisory Board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In assisting the organization that receives a contract under this subsection, the Advisory Board established under section 6 shall provide additional resources to such organization to carry out the evaluations under this subsection, including assistance with using randomized experimental designs.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H23E0135471D64F3B86D9065956AE8CED"><enum>6.</enum><header>Advisory Board</header><subsection id="HA012C78337C943B5A7B3BC04AB8CBA1C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From the amounts available under section 2(b)(4), the Secretary of Labor shall establish within the Department of Labor an Advisory Board to carry out the duties listed in subsection (i).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0DB33CB210A744C3876665D4DB7370A8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Members</header><paragraph id="H5E215778599F463C81250A03ABCDD228"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number of members</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall determine the number of members to serve on the Advisory Board. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A509F4F5F5247F4841E5368C361C9EA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appointment and expertise</header><text>Each member of the Advisory Board shall be appointed by the Secretary of Labor, and shall have expertise in designing and administering summer youth employment programs or experience in program evaluation and evidence-based policy in the workforce development field.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F12A91F0BEB46B0A54936245723E5A4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Terms</header><subparagraph id="HD90EDC39648943AFB0D9160F16D381D2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member shall be appointed for a term of 4 years, and may be reappointed for subsequent terms by the Secretary. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14E96EE839F1437BA579D7B348CA9CB4" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Any member appointed to fill a vacancy occurring before the expiration of the term for which the member’s predecessor was appointed shall be appointed only for the remainder of that term. A member may serve after the expiration of that member’s term until a successor has taken office. A vacancy in the Advisory Board shall be filled in the manner in which the original appointment was made.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2DECD4A209154193B91D3A136BDCFF14"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Basic Pay</header><paragraph id="H99F64B283EA8444C9B257C2E99A18875"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Rates of pay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), Advisory Board Members and staff, including the Chairperson, Vice Chairperson, and Director, shall each be paid at a rate determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B5998EFD0BB42ABB85F3EA35E752B03"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition of compensation of federal employees</header><text>Members of the Advisory Board who are full-time officers or employees of the United States may not receive additional pay, allowances, or benefits by reason of their service on the Advisory Board.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F7F150923564C2AB38CA1E9E82094B2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>Each member shall receive travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code. </text></subsection><subsection id="H63A711CFE45D4B90898BA4602E4FB391"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fifty percent plus one members of the Advisory Board shall constitute a quorum but a lesser number may hold hearings.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6004BEB15282446BBD508DAAC5F7B879"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Chairperson; Vice Chairperson</header><text>The Chairperson and Vice Chairperson of the Advisory Board shall be designated by the Secretary at the time of the appointment. The term of office of the Chairperson and Vice Chairperson shall be 4 years. </text></subsection><subsection id="HFE31456BFA474ABE8E2A845CDFB1906C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Advisory Board shall meet monthly and at the call of the Chairperson or a majority of its members.</text></subsection><subsection id="H91615B571F024EF8B3AC213293ED658C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Director and staff of Advisory Board; experts and consultants</header><paragraph id="HCB5C7BF54F4C437DAFA784DB848FABFA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The Advisory Board shall have a Director who shall be appointed by the Chairperson. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A5181A0A7B54B0783D56975D6E13952"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Staff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Advisory Board Chairperson may appoint additional personnel as they consider appropriate. Such staff shall provide specific oversight and guidance, pursuant to the functions of the Advisory Board under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA849E97549C242FC8F5DF79538916912"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicability of certain civil service laws</header><text>The Director and staff of the Advisory Board shall be appointed subject to the provisions of title 5, United States Code, governing appointments in the competitive service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B4D1AC21EB644E993CA528C1F9425C6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Experts and consultants</header><text>The Advisory Board may procure temporary and intermittent services under section 3109(b) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30E5065067E14D6F96146040CBEB4B24"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Staff of Federal Agencies</header><text>Upon request of the Advisory Board, the head of any Federal department or agency may detail, on a reimbursable basis, any of the personnel of that department or agency to the Advisory Board to assist it in carrying out its duties under this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3AA69C2DE0BE46C89435F0450BD81ABC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Advisory Board shall assist the Secretary in carrying out each of the following:</text><paragraph id="H959862D4F16443A2832D871E603B7335"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Application review</header><text>Reviewing applications submitted by eligible entities under sections 4(d) and 5(b) to ensure that each eligible entity selected to receive a grant under this Act will use such grant as required under this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E396DFDE3AA4175A20F661D1212FB25"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><subparagraph id="HD2B202FA421440C9A2A93C853C0506A3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing technical assistance to eligible entities receiving grants under section 3, for the purpose of assisting such eligible entities to best implement the summer youth employment programs to be assisted with such grants, by identifying existing summer youth employment programs that demonstrate, through evaluations conducted under section 5(b) or through outside studies, that each of the program elements listed in section 3(d) and implemented under such programs have a significant impact on academic, economic, and criminal justice outcomes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3EBE04C328B6481E898652BAC1DC910A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Working group</header><text>Technical assistance may be provided under subparagraph (A) through the creation and administration of a working group of the administrators of eligible entities to share best practices regarding the implementation of summer youth employment programs. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FAA1A3E7D1C48CCB84801684935CE35" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Innovative program elements</header><subparagraph id="H28376A8B781649588F66464D469F75E4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Identifying program elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identifying any innovative approaches to summer youth employment programs for purposes of paragraph (13) of section 4(d) that are not listed in section 4(d), which demonstrate or are reasonably expected to demonstrate evidence of improving the youth outcomes listed under section 3(a).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1302AD29B4464C3B92B427B4ADA8CEE0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Approving new program elements</header><text>Providing recommendations to the Secretary with respect to whether any new program element proposed by any eligible entity under section 4(d)(14) demonstrate or are reasonable expected to demonstrate such evidence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA203BE6FE06A4ACB9DAB054DDBD4BE8F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Database of impact evaluations</header><text>Publishing a database of completed evaluations conducted under section 5(b), which maintains evidence on the impact of programs (including the program elements of programs) supported with grants under this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H589C99879E544159A25DE23A36A71ADC" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Program evaluations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing assistance with respect to impact evaluations described in section 5(b)(3).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF2456B1D5214461DA44429F4A58C2168"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H798522F1FE994C618E12DDCBC150477C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a State (or State board) or unit of general local government (or a local board), or a nonprofit organization, or a consortium of any of such entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DDCD28C495B40008C1BE485ED3D1DC4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE723AC3278E4FD5819D5BF03610DC89" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means any State of the United States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.<italic></italic></text></paragraph><paragraph id="H291D6BDB0B6F4A54B9C6F4F44C23A747"><enum>(4)</enum><header>WIOA terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>local area</term>, <term>local board</term>, <term>State board</term>, and <term>unit of general local government</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

