<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H022FA5216F724308934E312AABBED952" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1737 IH: Supporting Our First Responders Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1737</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001126">Mr. Carey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to establish the Emergency Medical Services (EMS) Grant Program through which the Secretary may make grants to qualified applicants, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H292964D191EF40CEAC2B29EE756209C6" style="OLC"><section id="H4718A57D6BD1440A8096C8738448BF5D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting Our First Responders Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H841A5E4BB545429DA2F356B886DE6F04"><enum>2.</enum><header>Emergency Medical Services Grant Program</header><subsection id="HA42F8A09DCA74EE1954CF0D3820A15ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Emergency Medical Services Grant Program</header><paragraph id="H86D4A3003F0D413F8785D02E07ED2317" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a program, to be known as the <quote>Emergency Medical Services (EMS) Grant Program</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>), through which the Secretary shall award grants on a competitive basis to qualified applicants.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD75530058F82441FB61E35A388FAF2D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under the Program, a qualified applicant shall submit to the Secretary an application at such a time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="H9D215957FD0943E5BE3D4884BCD7D40A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the financial need of the qualified applicant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7957CFE07B454D7086D10C803B5D0D06"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of the costs and benefits, with respect to improving medical transport and emergency medical services (referred to in this section as <quote>EMS</quote>), of the activities to be carried out through the grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8650FF388D14F16B1469AF1E084C7BC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Joint applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A qualified applicant may submit a joint application with one or more other qualified applicants under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D1732B3E71B4D4DB8EC4E1E412917D2" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Peer review of grant applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, after consultation with national qualified applicants, shall appoint representatives of volunteer, governmental, Tribal, for-profit, and nonprofit qualified applicants and entities to conduct peer review of applications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9609E34A7AB49808A9AF8C8FA39C299"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Selection considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under the Program the Secretary shall consider each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H45C386B513B24EACAF6083D1CBEFC64A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The findings and recommendations of the peer reviews carried out under paragraph (4).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3FC94651666470F893EDBE779537C4B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The degree to which an award will improve the coverage, response times, and ability of qualified applicants to provide medical transport and emergency medical services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C00020CFE644D89ACD1721AC42FB3A2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The extent of the need of an applicant for a grant under this subsection and the need to protect the United States as a whole.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDADF7CE3222C44E79B083C508418D355" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether a qualified applicant has previously received Federal funding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC77D5D828083472C9F11D3B43B7F022F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Prioritization among for-profit qualified applicants</header><text>In awarding grants under the Program, the Secretary shall, in selecting among qualified applicants that operate for profit, give priority to such applicants that are smaller for profit entities, determined on an annual basis based on the net profits of the entity and the number of employees hired during the preceding year. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C3F7EB131DC4508A6B5327837BDC67C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>Grants made under the Program may be used by recipient qualified applicants for the following purposes:</text><paragraph id="H3CA1AEA15A57479E8089E747D17340E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Maintaining, or, if appropriate, increasing, the number of trained front-line EMS responders, whether paid or volunteer, including providing salaries and stipends.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24C5D2BB4ED843D7A68A92D3A83A9653"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing mental health programs for qualified applicant personnel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84E7E181364D4D489396736056F43BF6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Covering or reimbursing costs associated with certification and recertification courses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD625E0BF79840A480D5A8F20EF412C0"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Obtaining resources, including purchasing personal protective equipment, uniforms, medicine, and medical supplies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FB78211460D4EF0A7396F5B857BCD9D"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Constructing or modifying facilities in such a way so as to improve coverage, response time, and ability of qualified applicants to provide medical transport and emergency medical services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H875D50935A3E415DBE1A7A31248D980A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Upgrading or purchasing EMS vehicles, communications equipment, and mapping equipment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0B736F68488415B9B5D8A4FDB9BD342"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Establishing or supporting community paramedicine or mobile integrated healthcare initiatives.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H81F406304BA146C1A3A6799DB8622B65"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Allocation of grant awards</header><paragraph id="H766E03D476DB45EB878F0A6708CA4311"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitation</header><subparagraph id="H728C628EF5324BA182A6D61B4AC68BA2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>For profit</header><clause id="HBC6DC9740BDB42BAAA86B3B216C0BC33"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not more than two percent of grants awarded under the Program may be made available to qualified applicants that operate for profit or to otherwise support efforts to establish or provide emergency medical services, or medical transport, for profit.</text></clause><clause id="HE4F8BF193F994D99938A1D84D5BAFD4B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>A grant under the Program to such a for-profit qualified applicant (if singly) or to such qualified applicants (if a result of a joint application) or to otherwise so support such efforts shall be in an amount not to exceed $100,000.</text></clause><clause id="HE17D733FBC204C94996B0CAABADB1681"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A qualified applicant that operates for profit may use funds awarded through a grant under the Program only for the purposes specified in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (b). </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H348B066D5C4D45E5A7E50C7EAACA70AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Time-based</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A for-profit qualified applicant (if singly) or qualified applicants (if a result of a joint application) awarded a grant under the Program may not apply for another such award for a period of three years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5096938C4E74703BCDFCF0F691A7E80"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Further limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant under the Program to a not-for-profit qualified applicant or a joint application shall be in an amount not to exceed $300,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45E9192878654054ACA061B44A8816AA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less than 20 percent of grants awarded under the Program shall be made available to qualified applicants in rural areas.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF686268F28D040AF80AD3A265DB341E2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Metrics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall develop metrics to assess the effectiveness of the Program in improving the coverage, response times, and ability of qualified applicants to provide medical transport and emergency medical services.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF874D8B6341A42E19A32AFB01A87A76D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Claw backs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall make every available effort to recover grant funds in case of noncompliance. To carry out this subsection, the Secretary shall establish a process through which notification is conveyed to qualified applicants determined to be in noncompliance, and such organizations are provided an opportunity to respond to such notification prior to the recovery of such funds.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF7D72C23FFF24EA6AA1074558007D0DE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Assessments; reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act and not less frequently than biennially after, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text><paragraph id="HE8456928F7AF41D3B7F268CD289A2666"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct an assessment of the Program based on the metrics developed pursuant to subsection (d); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE4E6584E3B84945A2DE2E1F57C34CC9" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate a report summarizing the findings of the assessment and recommendations to strengthen the overall program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0652F6C6D2E547F199104FA48E9F1083"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of Health and Human Services—</text><paragraph id="H82CA14BFC3374F24BE5210904785AA69"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each of the first 5 fiscal years following the date of the enactment of this Act, $50,000,000 to carry out the Program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E439691A7C04034AC09FEC8876C8DD1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each of such fiscal years, $5,000,000 to provide technical assistance to qualified applicants completing and submitting applications.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H63398F1BCEB849ED9FAF494513C5AAF4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H902136D4F8DB40CC83BD8D1438367B56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services, the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response, and EMS stakeholders, shall submit to Congress a report that—</text><subparagraph id="HFA0DC68FC75F48EEA4C25955E0D84149"><enum>(A)</enum><text>details the challenges, disparities, and inadequacies in providing Federal, State, and private (including commercial insurers) reimbursement for medical transport and emergency medical services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33D14994BBAF4623882C07B515914F56"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides recommendations for improvement with respect to providing such reimbursement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB94E468A51F34FC1A09DD72E7CA6D33C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified applicants</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services, the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response, and EMS stakeholders, shall submit to Congress a report that—</text><subparagraph id="HAAB419D3AA8B4E53A7C5789B5C905BD4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describes the challenges specific to qualified applicants, including with respect to Federal, State, and private (including private insurers) reimbursement rates and policies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H160CCDE4C95D448FA0C3CF72D2C43C2A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>contains an action plan to address such challenges through grants and other administrative action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6D2C4707C3745A892893212D0D3FD12" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Establishing a Federal EMS Office</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in consultation with the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services, the Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration, the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response, and EMS stakeholders, shall submit to Congress a report that assesses the feasibility of establishing a Federal office to—</text><subparagraph id="H39CA435D52E747079AAE3191F3A2B13F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>better advocate for EMS personnel, collect data, promote EMS education, research, and training; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD1E1B2EC8034BD7BB14C19A29299015"><enum>(B)</enum><text>implement recommendations and action plans based on the findings in the reports under paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBB4482DD4C094CF787BF7BAC7A208ED3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HDC9A4D2A09C7417D86769045C0A59828" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>EMS organization</header><text>The term <quote>EMS organization</quote> means a nongovernmental or governmental entity that provides emergency medical services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6E44A81A79F45A2A19D899ABD63D94C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Emergency medical services</header><text>The term <quote>emergency medical services</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="H29AFD65D77ED4C3DA9E15EE73EF0CA27" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means resources used by a licensed entity to deliver medical care outside of a medical facility under emergency conditions that occur as a result of the condition of the patient; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB145FC0B72A45C191753FFCBE953C54" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes services provided (either on a compensated or volunteer basis) at the location of the emergency or en route to, or at, a health care facility by an emergency medical services provider or other provider that is licensed or certified by the State involved as an emergency medical technician, a paramedic, or an equivalent professional (as determined by the State).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H44A2E97EFF514E7D9BA7275B74037338" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Medical transport</header><text>The term <quote>medical transport</quote> means the transportation, by ambulance, of sick, injured, or otherwise incapacitated persons who require emergency medical care to a health care facility, including a hospital, clinic, or alternative destination. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1969EB3142B844EC8A58089CDAA677C7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Qualified applicant</header><text>The term <quote>qualified applicant</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H08AA57A906684514BBEC4562BE011A29"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an EMS organization; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF25F043799C4C59B6E2D7B493EBFDAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State (or a political subdivision thereof), Indian Tribe, Tribal organization (as those terms are defined in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>)), territory, or municipality.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2993994D83D64951BED95DA316F7DDCB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rural area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>rural area</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H07C567C4F6304DD892E65ED3C34E9BBD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a nonmetropolitan statistical area;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EFE6FCEA69D4D8EA7A0B237B389C4D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an area designated as a rural area by any law or regulation of a State; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FB80498B3E04721AD8F31F221DB5B46"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a rural census tract of a metropolitan statistical area (as determined under the most recent rural urban commuting area code as set forth by the Office of Management and Budget).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F73FA28E7E941CD91E9E83500FCC649"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>State</quote> means a State of the United States, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, American Samoa, the Northern Mariana Islands, and Guam. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

