<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H716C37D96F1C40A68D565C62D8BD0C88" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4878 IH: Enabling More of the Physical and Occupational Workforce to Engage in Rehabilitation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4878</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to ensure appropriate supervision requirements for outpatient physical therapy and outpatient occupational therapy.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HFDA424D78BAB41A892756131DE461787" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H71A8A4F49CBF452B9F72FC2DAA65CCD7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Enabling More of the Physical and Occupational Workforce to Engage in Rehabilitation Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>EMPOWER Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H62A6DBD6430841D4ACE52CEE8F2EB161" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring appropriate supervision requirements for outpatient physical therapy and outpatient occupational therapy</header> <subsection id="H3E26EDE3F6A0469AA55E54919C9F6EC3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="HF4B60EA586E14AB4BC6AE756A557F4AD" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Payment</header><text>Section 1834(v)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(v)(1)</external-xref>) is amended in the second sentence by inserting <quote>, but in no case shall the Secretary impose a supervision requirement on such services that is different than any such requirement under applicable State law</quote> before the period at the end.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCDA56EA2741F4F24AA8AA492ED44B24C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 1861(p) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(p)</external-xref>) is amended in the first sentence of the flush left text following paragraph (4)(B) by inserting <quote>, but in no case may those conditions impose a supervision requirement that is different than any such requirement under applicable State law</quote> after <quote>as the Secretary may find necessary</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA9A78CC85DE44ED7AA0968D95EAA38D5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall take effect on January 1, 2024.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBD3DC7C5C0344CA2BF799915D87C037D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary may implement the provisions of, and the amendments made by, this section by program instruction or otherwise.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HB025643F8AF446719BCA43F0641BAAA4" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>GAO study on access to therapy services in rural and underserved areas</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than December 31, 2024, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct an analysis of how the Medicare part B 15 percent payment differential for services provided by occupational therapy assistants and physical therapy assistants has impacted access to occupational therapy and physical therapy services in rural and medically underserved areas, across all Medicare part B settings.</text></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


