<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDEB156C1BB9E461796864F99F2780C4E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3593 IH: Drone Infrastructure Inspection Grant Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3593</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Transportation to establish a drone infrastructure inspection grant program and a drone education and workforce training grant program, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H200CFA408559406E9156942FBD99BE9B" style="OLC">
<section id="H7BB889C2A5A64B39BFB8E83695BC1863" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Drone Infrastructure Inspection Grant Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H184697DE352E4A88AB717EE2E136EC47" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HA87E26E27B4647DC8FFEEAC54C458697"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <quote>critical infrastructure</quote> has the meaning given such term in subsection (e) of the Critical Infrastructures Protection Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H11BBB89C568D4D5AAD84BCD0AC915EAF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered foreign entity</header><text>The term <quote>covered foreign entity</quote> means an entity—</text>
<subparagraph id="H753EA171604D45D991320FD9C8C4B86F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>included on the Consolidated Screening List or Entity List as designated by the Secretary of Commerce;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H01557778A49B479ABA377B303D432079"><enum>(B)</enum><text>domiciled in the People’s Republic of China or the Russian Federation;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3565E8A74F0D4C719D4C37E87C6CC6DA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>subject to influence or control by the Government of the People’s Republic of China or by the Russian Federation; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC1EA2603A99B4E279522419BE4C40CD0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is a subsidiary or affiliate of an entity described in subparagraphs (A) through (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCD1D0C879D4442669ABEB3E2F242ECC8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Educational institution</header><text>The term <quote>educational institution</quote> means an institution of higher education (as defined in section 101 of the High Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)) that participates in a program authorized under sections 631 and 632 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/40101">49 U.S.C. 40101</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8221F9EA3AC342D2A711C519F41132BE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Element of critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <quote>element of critical infrastructure</quote> means a critical infrastructure facility or asset, including public bridges, tunnels, roads, highways, dams, electric grid, water infrastructure, communication systems, pipelines, or other related facilities or assets, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H360A0CF28B534D20AE833F7385430CCA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible small unmanned aircraft system</header><text>The term <quote>eligible small unmanned aircraft system</quote> means a small unmanned aircraft system manufactured or assembled by a company that is domiciled in the United States and is not a covered foreign entity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5A4B4179DEF14608A7E453F94F62F81A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Eligible small unmanned aircraft system technology</header><text>The term <quote>eligible small unmanned aircraft system technology</quote> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H700EB4D604E94530BBBC9F9965BE71D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an eligible small unmanned aircraft system; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEED8C3A7A6E54FDE81A8DD9EC912A483"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a major component of such a system that is not manufactured by or procured from a covered foreign entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H80A41CA0CC5A46F6986EF7C68C65C098"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Governmental entity</header><text>The term <quote>governmental entity</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H6ED0692A24104B19803F1577F30FEC6E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, a territory of the United States, or a political subdivision thereof;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5457ADB60F8D46A1A404DBA106B2534D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a unit of local government;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H274E846302AC4089BE2D4F3EAF7F769C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a Tribal government;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA5C24B86678A4D32B11EC5E998DC1C21"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a metropolitan planning organization; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9636D3DC87664F23B55EAF10582A9281"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a consortia of more than 1 of the entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (D).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H00F269578BE24A20A89FEA2F77DE38B4"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Project</header><text>The term <quote>project</quote> means a project for the inspection, operation, maintenance, repair, modernization, or construction of an element of critical infrastructure, including mitigating environmental hazards to such infrastructure.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B5D808D5BD34A749781C14B6895943C"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Small unmanned aircraft; unmanned aircraft system</header><text>The terms <quote>small unmanned aircraft</quote> and <quote>unmanned aircraft system</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 44801 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HC0CCC664C1024BF893234784717F3301" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Drone infrastructure inspection grant program</header>
<subsection id="H32312CFCA28645DE8A759B59AE1D00F7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall establish a drone infrastructure inspection grant program to make grants to governmental entities to facilitate the use of eligible small unmanned aircraft systems to support more efficient inspection, operation, construction, maintenance, modernization, and repair of critical infrastructure to improve worker safety related to critical infrastructure projects.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3D82C023CAA24B8199A43734C203EA1D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of grant amounts</header><text>A governmental entity may use a grant provided under this section to—</text>
<paragraph id="HA310609F56274C0C8C2B49F7BE454560"><enum>(1)</enum><text>purchase or lease eligible small unmanned aircraft systems;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB4BA3CD7651457EAEE945AA580352B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support operational capabilities of eligible small unmanned aircraft systems by the governmental entity;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H597A0E6246A744538C349FEC7D48B967"><enum>(3)</enum><text>contract for services performed using an eligible small unmanned aircraft system in circumstances in which the governmental entity does not have the resources or expertise to safely carry out or assist in carrying out the activities described under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0EE5DE0FA83641C68FF04A156DDF0857"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support the program management capability of the governmental entity to use an eligible small unmanned aircraft system.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC8B2B20F1C424C3F90575A7E75A618D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a governmental entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including an assurance that the governmental entity or any contractor of the governmental entity, will comply with relevant Federal regulations.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H335E910D3A7E4B9ABB98249330AABEEF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection of applicants</header><text>In awarding a grant under this section, the Secretary shall prioritize applications that propose to—</text>
<paragraph id="H39EBFC79CF514AA89E2D0A1AD0B472A5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out a critical infrastructure project in a variety of communities, including urban, suburban, rural, tribal, or any other type of community; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5802271CDE5E4363A5E2F291FB51767B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>address a safety risk in the inspection, operation, construction, maintenance, or repair of critical infrastructure.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H9E322211557B4DDAAD29059B05B8207B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed as to interfere with an agreement between a governmental entity and a labor union, including requirements under section 5333(b) of title 49, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFC1F355B1D0D494F8B78D500856D88BA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the first grant is provided under this section, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report that evaluates the program carried out under this section, including—</text>
<paragraph id="H310B6588DB4B45AEA33495353C0AE037"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the number of grants awarded;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H03E5192786D4474AA7DF2914EAF3A25B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the amount of each grant;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H67429EE87FD44CDE9D6EFBBA9712E7D6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the activities funded under this section; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6D922960D49E4E00885F218E026647EE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the effectiveness of such funded activities in meeting the objectives described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB71C5C69B9E24BAA9C0D730290A5E3F4"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Funding</header>
<paragraph id="H75C100A94D4F4F9DB2427293F8061DA3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal share</header>
<subparagraph id="HC3C5A23247164BAF870B64E4BB0D9146"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the Federal share of the cost of a project carried out using a grant under this section shall not exceed 50 percent of the total project cost.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDBA70BC48DEE40CFBE2C32A40D4F6A1C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary may increase the Federal share requirement under subparagraph (A) to up to 75 percent for a project carried out using a grant under this section by a governmental entity if such entity—</text>
<clause id="H75345C383F344A1E98AA96B650C6B343"><enum>(i)</enum><text>submits a written application to the Secretary requesting an increase in the Federal share; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA31E6611302A4BF1BB712947769F4759"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>demonstrates that the additional assistance is necessary to facilitate the acceptance and full use of a grant under this section, such as alleviating economic hardship, meeting additional workforce needs, or such other uses that the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB1EA5E6C15D74D5588A946756A7461A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text> <subparagraph id="HFB09265CBE3945F8974D2B3722F6489F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$2,000,000 for fiscal year 2024; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7C79F95E6C5A44458F1DBF673F3B32C1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDFAF24C97E3F4DF6A54DAE301CB927D6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA126F29CAD254782AA606C2CBF2065FE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE11C55920BF64F56AFF142E3170EF7AE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H6DFA25BCB5674694AFABFFDD1BDE2699"><enum>4.</enum><header>Drone education and workforce training grant program</header>
<subsection id="H0390C26C434C422F86EE6FD710163A4E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall establish a drone education and training grant program to make grants to educational institutions for workforce training for eligible small unmanned aircraft system technology.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2B6F377E8CC54DCAA4ACF8BE2B5AF1E2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of grant amounts</header><text>Amounts from a grant under this section shall be used in furtherance of activities authorized under sections 631 and 632 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/40101">49 U.S.C. 40101</external-xref> note).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HFDAD25A79E9E40BA9CE2B382EB4CDC20"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an educational institution shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H708CB03D65704BBD8C5A7DCE7EB1E1AD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text>
<paragraph id="H2E0A4BBE6C964D2AA4A8457239846136"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$2,000,000 for fiscal year 2024; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4A14859D42B04C0F8C9EB25BD0688C1D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8EBF2C3ACE3742D4A1DEB8655AE1E94F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H956BD50047E34A55A4142969D4770EC4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC4AF3AD4C4F748EC8792869836D46EC5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$12,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

