<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H85050553C87E4014B51F6AD27E003BF3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6869 IH: To withdraw certain land within the San Bernardino National Forest in California from location, entry, and patent under mining laws, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6869</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To withdraw certain land within the San Bernardino National Forest in California from location, entry, and patent under mining laws, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBE6B12F4D7EA438681CD1CD76E5C7E56" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H691247AE62A349A69E518EECD474723A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Withdrawal of certain land within San Bernardino National Forest</header> 
<subsection id="H99F846FDB679409DA0A15646F6652D63"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H223EF4A4BE9F4CF5A2FF9D15A52D99CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Agriculture, acting through the Forest Service, has implemented a strategy known as the Carbonate Habitat Management Strategy to conserve listed threatened and endangered species where minerals co-occur with those species’ habitats to allow for species conservation and efficient administration of mining activities on the San Bernardino National Forest.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2BCAD9BA6FD4478681B051D971DFC6A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The withdrawal of certain land in the San Bernardino National Forest will help preserve habitat to protect 4 listed threatened and endangered plant species from the effects of mineral development and other forms of entry, appropriation, and disposal under the public land laws.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF82A42C1E5B24730AC8158BCE523DF7C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to valid existing rights, the Proposed Withdrawal is withdrawn from all forms of—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD19633984FF54266A061D42143F65FDD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>entry, appropriation, and disposal under the public land laws;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5C23D0598880483683141CD3FCC7B468"><enum>(2)</enum><text>location, entry, and patent under the mining laws; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H95B3814FA2C94C999E352A44EF582CB5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>operation of the mineral leasing, mineral materials, and geothermal leasing laws.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H78AB952CFC8A4D84AB2FD3556BFFEA0B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The withdrawal under subsection (b) shall take effect—</text> 
<paragraph id="H219F04BE28BA4BB2A6534E180D0780BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the date of the enactment of this section, with respect to Federal land; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBECC9840887744B08F20245F174ECF1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>on the date the land is acquired by the United States, with respect to non-Federal land.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF76D1FF6F5854386B5A1D3FF20B390B3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HAD861593AD254CA0B58AECD5CEA1C5CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal land</header><text>The term <term>Federal land</term> means the approximately 2,775 acres of land generally depicted on the Map as <quote>National Forest Land</quote> within the Proposed Withdrawal.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D3D43FD0171469BB7A777E89506E563"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Map</header><text>The term <term>Map</term> means the map titled <quote>Proposed Mineral Withdrawal, San Bernardino National Forest, Mountaintop Ranger District</quote> and dated October 19, 2020.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD85B28E5D8C34C7EA9C724F0F6113B9E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Non-Federal land</header><text>The term <term>non-Federal land</term> means the approximately 280 acres of land generally depicted on the Map as <quote>Non-National Forest Land</quote> within the Proposed Withdrawal.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H06B6A5E99D10487B930DF703C337FA50"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Proposed Withdrawal</header><text>The term <term>Proposed Withdrawal</term> means the approximately 3,055 acres of land generally depicted on the Map as <quote>Proposed Withdrawal</quote>.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

