<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB8F5DF7305AC4FE48FD38AF911CD78AF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4024 IH: Clean Shipping Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4024</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230612">June 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Clean Air Act to provide for the establishment of standards to limit the carbon intensity of the fuel used by certain vessels, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H540FBE945C18488DADA882AF773891E3" style="OLC"><section id="H090DBEE9943340A2A3668B0281681622" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Clean Shipping Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBB1225CD15484DFFA60F86FC9D0BF2CB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Marine Zero Greenhouse Gas Fuel Standard</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Clean Air Act is amended by adding after section 212 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7546">42 U.S.C. 7546</external-xref>) the following new section: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0885998EA6EA4B5FA76073FCDD90C220" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H9C75C207948E4B268C72114D647918CC"><enum>212A.</enum><header>Marine Zero Greenhouse Gas Fuel Standard</header><subsection id="HD5398CB1438B4DB899EF64854892D87E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Marine vessel fuel carbon intensity standards</header><paragraph id="H75AB52CDD5AC4138AC38D8691DCC6FB1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall, by regulation, require each vessel on a covered voyage to comply with standards for the carbon intensity of the fuel used by such vessel so that such carbon intensity is—</text><subparagraph id="H62CE1F01FA65478E9BE7E214232D37A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in each of calendar years 2027 through 2029, at least 20 percent less than the carbon intensity baseline;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2CF4BFFE0FC47CDBCE51747BB8DECDE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in each of calendar years 2030 through 2034, at least 45 percent less than the carbon intensity baseline;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC461449F7A8446E9B89B73C00F17FB2"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in each of calendar years 2035 through 2039, at least 80 percent less than the carbon intensity baseline; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H685A34BCDCAA43039361B3935E7774D0"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in calendar year 2040 and each calendar year thereafter, 100 percent less than the carbon intensity baseline.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H13CF7A2E52784098862A0C9D3DD96476"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Promulgation of standards</header><text>The Administrator shall finalize—</text><subparagraph id="HC4FAC749C13246F2B79D00A8E4F93FD5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the standard required by paragraph (1)(A) by not later than January 1, 2026; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H012194A18D6D4E348D4434815E334A5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the standards required by each of subparagraphs (B) through (D) of paragraph (1) by not later than 2 years before the respective standard goes into effect.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDED78750FF4446858E368D2EFE843696"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technological or economic feasibility</header><subparagraph id="H2431422523044BC196806183F93FB924"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator determines that a reduction in carbon intensity required under paragraph (1) is not technologically or economically feasible by the applicable deadline under such paragraph, the Administrator, in lieu of promulgating the standard otherwise required by paragraph (1), shall promulgate a standard that will achieve the maximum reduction in the carbon intensity of the fuel used by vessels on covered voyages that is technologically and economically feasible by such applicable deadline.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD221887172174E69B33A323B16814B81"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining technological and economic feasibility for purposes of subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall take into account the net reduction of emissions of greenhouse gases and potential adverse impacts on public health, safety, and the environment, including with respect to air quality, water quality, and the generation and disposal of solid waste.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H819BD8DC553C4F1D8395A5B099AB6E29"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Harmonization with international standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator determines that standards mandated by the International Maritime Organization for reduction of the carbon intensity of fuel used by vessels for a calendar year are equally or more stringent than the standards under paragraph (1) for such calendar year, the Administrator may adopt such standards.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9D528303DCD41E9A563FEEB1640A47A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any vessel that is on covered voyages for 30 days or fewer during a calendar year shall be exempt from the standards promulgated under this subsection for that year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H127237D09968405D97755832DCBFA429"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Common ownership or control</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of determining compliance with any standard established under this subsection, the Administrator may allow the carbon intensity of the fuels used by vessels under common ownership or control to be averaged.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04069535F9094278A28FC1B8AA4FBBEB"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Overcompliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may allow vessels to credit overcompliance with any standard established under this subsection towards demonstrating compliance with any future standard under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H549F0D05F2904100B6378E37BB673577"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Monitoring and reporting</header><paragraph id="HAEB6A16CCD854FB4A6A85DCA85CBFF0D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>List of methods</header><subparagraph id="HB0E087F38F9F46F3A83583CC1E9F2115"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall develop a list of acceptable methods for monitoring and reporting compliance with the standards established under subsection (a).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CF5AE45C563428EAADE0A829A9377CA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consistency of methods</header><text>The Administrator, to the maximum extent practicable, shall ensure the consistency of the methods listed under subparagraph (A) with similar reporting schemes developed by the European Union and the International Maritime Organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59583C9BE8E54CBB9E5DF3E169BB2ED9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual reporting requirements</header><text>For each calendar year, a vessel shall report to the Administrator—</text><subparagraph id="H20CA03E4785D40EEB48F88A8C0B6F2F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the carbon intensity of the fuel used for each covered voyage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB40E7681C674B83B1213C3131BAD83C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount of fuel used for each covered voyage; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F67DFDD17E84784959281EBFD90AA82"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total greenhouse gas emissions measured in carbon dioxide equivalent for all covered voyages.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H93A26A59A2B24F97BC3694107B435F0D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the end of each annual reporting period under paragraph (2), the Administrator, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation and Commandant of the Coast Guard, shall publish a report that—</text><subparagraph id="H334C4E0A6E3D4532A9E88E3DE82D7CE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>compiles the data reported under paragraph (2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4E65F53560B4CDEA5721E27187FC5F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes an explanation intended to facilitate public understanding of—</text><clause id="H9D691227CFC746499D10C65FCB7DCB45"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the carbon dioxide equivalent emissions of vessels on covered voyages; and</text></clause><clause id="H3C2786260E0344ADA1DC336A2DBC27F3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the carbon intensity of fuels used by such vessels.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2D276FBC5B348BCBB7D614577CE22D8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The standards established under subsection (a) and the annual reporting requirements of subsection (b)(2) shall be considered an emission standard or limitation for purposes of section 304(a)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="HCEF3473FD0804C1BBC5E39627C3C0C85"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H48A9546AA38D49209ADDBFFFF1032F9E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Carbon dioxide equivalent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>carbon dioxide equivalent</term> means the number of metric tons of carbon dioxide emissions with the same global warming potential as one metric ton of another greenhouse gas, as calculated using Equation A–1 in section 98.2(b) of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of enactment of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6AB8B98B2E54EA5B340C2AF2174F3A5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Carbon intensity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>carbon intensity</term> means the quantity of lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions per unit of fuel energy, expressed in grams of carbon dioxide equivalent per megajoule.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H678A5C0791E448EF82CC609E29F93BF3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Carbon intensity baseline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>carbon intensity baseline</term> means the average carbon intensity of the fuel used by all vessels on covered voyages in calendar year 2024.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1CEE13DBF6E4A6DAC26ED852CA535C3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered voyage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered voyage</term> means any voyage of a vessel for the purpose of transporting passengers or cargo for commercial purposes—</text><subparagraph id="H6B455BDD740946E1B536848FB0C898A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is between any ports of call under the jurisdiction of the United States; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3CFE37CDB9A6407F91CDFDE55070D402"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that is between a port of call under the jurisdiction of the United States and a port of call under the jurisdiction of a foreign country.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7E14168FBDE4A3FA080FE8A78734305"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Greenhouse gas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>greenhouse gas</term> means carbon dioxide, methane, nitrous oxide, hydrofluorocarbons, perfluorocarbons, and sulfur hexafluoride.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H199029CA1BD048C090CAB712DD14DFC9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions</term> has the meaning given such term in section 211(o).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE573C2B404D244E98B0EF9F135D3C21F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Port of call</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>port of call</term> means the port where a vessel stops to load or unload cargo or to embark or disembark passengers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H143D298F24394151810562748DAE9586"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Vessel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>vessel</term> means a vessel of 400 gross tonnage or more.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H8DC00CCA1E794EAE9CFBBE036AF392A2"><enum>3.</enum><header>In-port marine vessel zero emission standards</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 213 of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7547">42 U.S.C. 7547</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8963FDDF23204E8197E4F6FB7ED69F15" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H6B0438B87EB74251AB140ECF0E2B2CBB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>In-Port marine vessel zero emission standards</header><paragraph id="H56F6A5F4F6F64D81A26BED30D1E15974"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2) and not later than January 1, 2026, the Administrator shall promulgate (and from time to time revise) standards to eliminate, by not later than January 1, 2030, emissions of greenhouse gases and air pollutants for which air quality criteria have been issued under section 108 from vessels at anchorage or at berth in the contiguous zone of the United States (as described in Presidential Proclamation 7219).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BED25449872481AB0F1CC17818FF0AB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator determines that standards required by paragraph (1) are not technologically or economically feasible, the Administrator shall promulgate standards that achieve the maximum reduction of such emissions from such vessels that is technologically and economically feasible.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D86DAACDD8643A3B6433E78180B5B5A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining technological and economic feasibility under paragraph (2), the Administrator shall take into account the net reduction of emissions of greenhouse gases, the net reduction of emissions of air pollutants for which air quality criteria have been issued under section 108, and potential adverse impacts on public health, safety, and the environment, including with respect to air quality, water quality, and the generation and disposal of solid waste.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

