<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC74DEBF3397C498580561BF6E853C770" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4855 IH: SNAP Ban Study Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4855</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Comptroller General of the United States to conduct a study to evaluate the effects of the post-incarceration ban under section 115 of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 on participation in the supplemental nutrition assistance program by drug felons, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBCD2261EFF274C1E98969F51CED78CDE" style="OLC"><section id="H658962337DD944D799CD59E7D0E8720A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>SNAP Ban Study Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6FA204590DD5487BBAE45BFA281D0BF5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study of SNAP ban and waiver provisions affecting drug felons</header><subsection id="HB23F45ADB954400883F93FF1380B4CD6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study to evaluate the effects of the post-incarceration ban and waiver provisions regarding participation in the supplemental nutrition assistance program by drug felons, as in effect under section 115 of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/286a">42 U.S.C. 286a</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H9A1FAC314CE24D9D93553C1B966D57F9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements of the study</header><text>The study conducted under subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="H147CE3035B8B4445A60EA93EEC98346E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify the full range of options States have implemented with respect to the supplemental nutrition assistance program ban, including—</text><subparagraph id="H1B0D1E9E116E4685ACD0C79285624397"><enum>(A)</enum><text>implementing the full ban;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86F3D2F031854C9C8091818DE2CE83EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>using their discretionary power provided in the law to opt out of the ban partially, including the various different modifications States have made or completely repealing the ban; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CBBB57BDE564924BD3A8298D4A71DCA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>when each of those States has made substantive revisions to their laws in this area over the past 15 years;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H45C4FE81FD344F1DA159BDC411DC3F32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for each group of those convicted of felony use, felony distribution, and felony trafficking offenses, the rates, 5 and 10 years after release from the incarceration that triggered the supplemental nutrition assistance program ban, of—</text><subparagraph id="H6B3199A9991C4AFB88E7EAE96824D128"><enum>(A)</enum><text>subsequent arrest for one or more felonies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4926C0F47EEA4B3BB2EDAB9DAD006FE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text> subsequent conviction for one or more felonies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB424F1E9516C4D31AB27DB3AADE0F7D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text> return to prison for such offenders;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2D26B1F2ABF4B269B8F38F3FD43ACCE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">measurements of the well-being of released drug felons who would be eligible for supplemental nutrition assistance program in the absence of the ban imposed by section 115 of the Personal Responsibility and Work Opportunity Reconciliation Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/286a">42 U.S.C. 286a</external-xref>) and substantive differences, if any, that might be identified by tracking the full range of State implementations of such section from a full ban to—</text><subparagraph id="H14173ED585B042DD9F113C07590816C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to various conditions required of drug felons to receive supplemental nutrition assistance program benefits short of a full ban, to a full waiver, and how otherwise eligible drug felons in each jurisdiction had, after 3, 5, and 10 years;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5FDFC817964F433CB6BCBA0BC460E96C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>changes with respect to recidivism, as described in paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87481F91278B4D0D8612EC77D7DBE05D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>family formation, including marriage rates;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F23EDB02AAE4D42A682361A8B9AB4F1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>average hours worked per week for those who are non-disabled and between the ages of 18 through 64;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4F38AA0D312404AA46A28E5FCF81336"><enum>(E)</enum><text>changes in individual and family income;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E23486B29804BEB8E61503CBA662020"><enum>(F)</enum><text>changes in educational attainment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE25D4A1E68D4976AEA3FEA90DCAA5CE"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other factors that the Comptroller General of the United States considers worthy of study;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50E372578AF047D7874FBB451B4570D9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>how the various impacts of such effects play out separately for those convicted of felony use, possession, and trafficking offenses;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AD5F196BC9C44A383C1F0ED8E72E6EB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the additional costs expected to be borne by the Federal and State governments if such a ban was made unlawful or such section was repealed;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1614937A700E4CD3969A434B593461AA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the amount of unpaid restitution, legal judgments and costs, and Federal and State taxes outstanding by the average post-incarceration drug felon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FB51D4CB7F44A7B9E3CF227BA57600D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the average total economic cost to each surviving child, parent, spouse and sibling of those killed by misuse or abuse of a controlled substance at 5, 10, and 15 years after that death;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF230096D1E04614B6B565EAD46098DB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the utilization rate of supplemental nutrition assistance program by surviving children, parents, spouses, and siblings of those killed by misuse or abuse of a controlled substance at baseline, 5, 10, and 15 years after that death, compared to the rest of the population, both in raw numbers and after adjusting for confounding factors;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2724FC9B5B194ABC961039FAEA0A4B01"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the extent to which programs assisting victims of violent crime could be enhanced if amounts identified in (5), above, were instead directed to State violent crime assistance programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA864D92C853E42EC809BDE7A2078C810"><enum>(10)</enum><text>an assessment of the levels of evidence used in research for this report and in the most-cited existing research related to supplemental nutrition assistance program eligibility by released drug felons and closely related issues;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9393C0D6D7C471FB755832907C5538B"><enum>(11)</enum><text>an assessment of the ability of social science and economic research to determine if any apparent material differences in various measures are persuasive, or are too prone to noise and confounding, as those terms are used in the fields of medical and other research, to be the basis for legislative action; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE89C21CD8D64C8D948F8B8DFBC24BFE"><enum>(12)</enum><text>any other matters the Comptroller General considers to be appropriate for evaluating the strengths and shortcomings of the existing supplemental nutrition assistance program lifetime ban and waiver contained in such section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD384B0280A194AA8BE90579B11ECFD28"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H01BE3F6D3BBE405EA9C43D68B3C01049" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit a report to the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate, the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition and Forestry of the Senate,, the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives, that contains the results of such study, including the findings and conclusions of the study.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB925AE0241C4D31A04DA80CA4EE0684"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Such report shall also be made available to the public on the website of the Government Accountability Office.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

