<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFE225678250A4A0D8E510C78F55AF1B5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1495 IH: Precision Agriculture Loan Program Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1495</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Food, Conservation, and Energy Act of 2008 to establish a precision agriculture loan program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3C2812FAFC2A47109F3BE0CC4530BD1E" style="OLC"><section id="H99D4087791AC479690972DD8EEB08013" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Precision Agriculture Loan Program Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDB96F04641384DD390CA3DEF2F2CCB3A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Precision agriculture loan program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subtitle F of title I of the Food, Conservation, and Energy Act of 2008 is amended by inserting after section 1614 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/8789">7 U.S.C. 8789</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF870294087E6483896FD1FD0EFE74F1F"><section id="H4A8574C2C2074EC78296B28DC294FCE9"><enum>1614A.</enum><header>Precision agriculture loan program</header><subsection id="HB3876CE42DCC4CA18BA0BC4760DB57DE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HD090A10511CB488B9540D65599A07278"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Precision agriculture</header><text>The term <term>precision agriculture</term> means managing, tracking, or reducing crop or livestock production inputs, including seed, feed, fertilizer, chemicals, water, and time, at a heightened level of spatial and temporal granularity to improve efficiencies, reduce waste, and maintain environmental quality.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8849C8D1BEDF41A98BE2401B60CB2739"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Precision agriculture equipment</header><text>The term <term>precision agriculture equipment</term> means any equipment or technology that directly contributes to a reduction in, or improved efficiency of, inputs used in crop or livestock production, including—</text><subparagraph id="H8047E43FCA6E4A9FBAE662F03C7BE645"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Global Positioning System-based or geospatial mapping;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB674AA255E8541B48C32E36C99F50F53"><enum>(B)</enum><text>satellite or aerial imagery;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F781ABE5CBE48EEAC89869848862F60"><enum>(C)</enum><text>yield monitors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94B4937D898146B697274E608CF31F9E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>soil mapping;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA38183709E204953A788BA10E8DC0725"><enum>(E)</enum><text>sensors for gathering data on crop, soil, or livestock conditions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF14A51B6F5E04FAFA1F1BFAB9BD5FE60"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Internet of Things and telematics technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5769817328014DCCA4048BF790225D79"><enum>(G)</enum><text>data management software and advanced analytics;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2B0433269A74B6DBB6A5990E08B1277"><enum>(H)</enum><text>network connectivity products and solutions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB09C34FCC6D44E438C63D9362B8DF7C0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Global Positioning System guidance or auto-steer systems;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86267836786846BF9E819BCCE04EBBDE"><enum>(J)</enum><text>variable rate technology for applying inputs, such as section control; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C6AB4E3BEA145FAAA68CCDDC7186CE8"><enum>(K)</enum><text>any other technology, as determined by the Secretary, that leads to a reduction in, or improves efficiency of, crop and livestock production inputs, which may include seed, feed, fertilizer, chemicals, water, and time.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5E010FF2DFFB4BADB6BEC96E503138C7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program</header><text>As soon as practicable after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall establish a precision agriculture loan program to encourage the adoption of precision agriculture by providing funds to producers engaged in livestock or crop production for the purchase of precision agriculture equipment.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7ED823DBC82A4671813C9604A7256165"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The precision agriculture loan program under this section shall be administered by the Secretary, acting through the Deputy Administrator for Farm Programs of the Farm Service Agency.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3BD0FC49485245BCA20B1FB90303BA90"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible producers</header><text>A precision agriculture loan under this section shall be made available to any producer described in subsection (b) that, as determined by the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="H5F39058C9760492F97428A67B06F09EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has a satisfactory credit history;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3F481783193404DAA178EF5C33A32F6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>will use the loan funds to purchase precision agriculture equipment; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2F121470431439CB36430C00646D3B6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>demonstrates an ability to repay the loan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94266052244F467E857AD72026A9CAF0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Term of loans</header><text>A precision agriculture loan under this section shall have a maximum term of 12 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4EB8649CD9154A23823000B9C9D46F8A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Loan amount</header><text>The maximum aggregate loan amount of a precision agriculture loan under this section shall be $500,000.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC2F61BDB4054D9CAEE98206E0F55632"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Loan security</header><text>Approval of a precision agriculture loan under this section shall require the borrower to provide loan security to the Secretary, in the form of—</text><paragraph id="H5731923E06B44D838657FD16A384C699"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a lien on the precision agriculture equipment being purchased; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C3750F71EA74BA09E4E68E4B0D91E55"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such other security as is acceptable to the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H696DA1C61E054AC28DD6E8A265B7CD1F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reporting</header><paragraph id="H30F5CDF50D064E588D398E3A166580C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition of recipient producer</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>recipient producer</term> means an eligible producer described in subsection (d) that received a precision agriculture loan under this section during the fiscal year covered by the applicable report prepared under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DC5ECCF8C7F42878D33179F476C6F37"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Preparation of report</header><text>For each fiscal year, the Secretary shall prepare a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="H8706D8B69537445B91313BEF32DDEE7A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>aggregate data based on a review of each outstanding loan made by the Secretary under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0BDE7BE9B3D04C74898B4FE5D7457E06"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of—</text><clause id="HC803A197385C4455A0AB437BAE5C5C21"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the United States and for each State and county (or equivalent jurisdiction) in the United States—</text><subclause id="H832217EA18EC44EDBEBDC33C21773D56"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the age of each recipient producer;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA2540B5B95A44B85B7D405B0B33A0E66"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the duration during which each recipient producer has engaged in agricultural production;</text></subclause><subclause id="HBED5AF2A99DF4650A3879B83A240DD2A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the size of the farm or ranch of each recipient producer;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC73BFFDD74044732810D8814D1479172"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the total amount provided as loans under this section for each category of equipment or technology described in subparagraphs (A) through (K) of subsection (a)(2) during the fiscal year covered by the report; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HF603AC38E5D6456E91B898C2F6CBB650"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the estimated input reduced or environmental benefits received per category of equipment or technology described in those subparagraphs with respect to which a loan was provided under this section during the fiscal year covered by the report or any prior fiscal year, including the estimated input reduced or environmental benefits received per category—</text><item id="HCD37AC1C5D66422AB531F043FB2AAA62"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>during the fiscal year covered by the report with respect to—</text><subitem id="H61ECBF22E1394C119D283535FD0C13B7"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>loans provided under this section during that fiscal year; and</text></subitem><subitem id="H1D3844ACA07A48F7849375D071D4C80F"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>loans provided under this section during that fiscal year or any prior fiscal year; and</text></subitem></item><item id="HC514480033CA42E2A3B29FBB803CBCA0"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in the aggregate with respect to all loans provided under this section during or prior to the fiscal year covered by the report; </text></item></subclause><subclause id="H7E87A8C63A0F40868E5965125CEFC30B"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>the race, ethnicity, and gender of each recipient producer; </text></subclause><subclause id="H2D831E2DF58A4F4A80DF785688E94300"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>the 1 or more agricultural commodities or types of enterprise for which each loan provided under this section during the fiscal year was provided;</text></subclause><subclause id="H4B12D38F20694B2FB6B895079A751E45"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>the amount of each loan provided under this section during the fiscal year; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD8E1171654244001A454B19BF8E78780"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>the default rate of the loans made under this section during—</text><item id="HE62F0964567A4F0A83E5031A3D2E12B3"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the fiscal year covered by the report;</text></item><item id="HF4B07716A0814C2994944D7F564B950C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>each preceding fiscal year; and</text></item><item id="HE4E1C10141B04A3CB30696A6467213B7"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in the aggregate with respect to all loans provided under this section during or prior to the fiscal year covered by the report; and</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H3026C16044C245C3B8295DD14BEDBA51"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for each State and county (or equivalent jurisdiction) in the United States, the number of outstanding loans made under this section, according to the loan size cohort.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD06A8A331C9446CBC34211D588762D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Submission of report</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H376D0A5714C743B295871722979235E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, submit the report described in paragraph (2) to—</text><clause id="H448C6309950B46AAB9D74150EE3BB2BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate;</text></clause><clause id="HED9F7E91B19246D59F35B5D2058E87E2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate;</text></clause><clause id="HDE3BB86BE7A64B05A1AD4CFE41213D11"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives; and</text></clause><clause id="H013F117953D343F8AB032FD643B4B2E5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8CC29B95E8043588B9F83CC12F0EE55"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date on which the report is submitted under subparagraph (A), make the report publicly available.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H59DDD4640125470C87479E91B1EA2DCA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

