<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2B59B012F2B942C79607F2F1E8F8C139" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4884 IH: Mental Health for Latinos Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4884</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to provide for a behavioral and mental health outreach and education strategy to reduce stigma associated with mental health among the Hispanic and Latino population, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H1780308090724F66BC1AB03CE15F01DF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HED163A96E1E14CB4894BEEAD53D638B9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mental Health for Latinos Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H885FAB4352EF41C4BB69310710E09A7B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Hispanic and Latino behavioral and mental health outreach and education strategy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part D of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290dd">42 U.S.C. 290dd et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H80253BDC420447CD9A3F27853D7906D6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H290514EC04744694B040811306E4ED40"><enum>553.</enum><header>Behavioral and mental health outreach and education strategy</header> 
<subsection id="H456DCA15BA2D4FE087149216081A226D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary, shall, in coordination with advocacy and behavioral and mental health organizations serving populations of Hispanic and Latino individuals or communities, develop and implement an outreach and education strategy to promote behavioral and mental health and reduce stigma associated with mental health conditions and substance abuse among the Hispanic and Latino populations. Such strategy shall—</text> <paragraph id="HC779FE612E0040FB8FBFF656A0B0A430"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be designed to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE804EC0208804951899EAE7EA1A4E8A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>meet the diverse cultural and language needs of the various Hispanic and Latino populations; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB346170FABED4066B42694DF142AC0BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be developmentally and age appropriate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E7F1CCC3FB14F32844ED2FFEA375495"><enum>(2)</enum><text>increase awareness of symptoms of mental illnesses common among such populations, taking into account differences within subgroups, such as gender, gender identity, age, sexual orientation, or ethnicity, of such populations;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF86F7CCE224D42A3BA983E72A4BFD206"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide information on evidence-based, culturally and linguistically appropriate and adapted interventions and treatments;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3A2204457BD14E2182C04E35E8BD0FB9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure full participation of, and engage, both consumers and community members in the development and implementation of materials; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCC21F39A954C405D9A0F1D7228A4E0AA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>seek to broaden the perspective among both individuals in these communities and stakeholders serving these communities to use a comprehensive public health approach to promoting behavioral health that addresses a holistic view of health by focusing on the intersection between behavioral and physical health; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6159B16F4CED4C6AB27D0CCDB543C606"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address the impact of the SARS–CoV–2 pandemic on the mental and behavioral health of the Hispanic and Latino populations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDC72C8F0C5734D029AA9241BB689FE36"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section and annually thereafter, the Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary, shall submit to Congress, and make publicly available, a report on the extent to which the strategy developed and implemented under subsection (a) improved behavioral and mental health outcomes associated with mental health conditions and substance abuse among Hispanic and Latino populations.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD34383A1503941BDA27CD47622FC049D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $1,000,000 for fiscal year 2024.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

