<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7D5C2F2814184F8DA4E3C36FCF90A271" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 691 IH: Sanctioning Iranian-Backed Militia Terrorists Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 691</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To impose sanctions with respect to Kata’ib Sayyid al-Shuhada.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3F3B87FF9B274F6AA24677A4F0FF3AD9" style="OLC"><section id="H2F4AF8F1F985444EAD2175BF2EBE6E7A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sanctioning Iranian-Backed Militia Terrorists Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF14CAD7C53A7465B95AB843E4E4C5895"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H6955F5BC84354B29B28BB22B6262BAA6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Kata’ib Sayyid al-Shuhada (KSS) is an Iranian-backed Iraqi militia founded in 2003 by Abu Mustafa al-Sheibani, who was sanctioned on January 9, 2008, by the Department of the Treasury <quote>for threatening the peace and stability of Iraq and the Government of Iraq</quote>. Sheibani led a network which according to the Department of the Treasury conducted improvised explosive device attacks against United States soldiers in Baghdad.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DA8E620FB4D40AFA675553129A98205"><enum>(2)</enum><text>KSS openly recognizes the Iranian Supreme Leader Ali Khamanei as its spiritual leader.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86D1355E9A2F4EB5AD06501D2BD7606B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>KSS is provided training, funding, and arms by Iran’s Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps (IRGC) and IRGC-Quds Forces and works closely with Kata’ib Hezbollah (KH), Lebanese Hezbollah, and Asa’ib Ahl al-Haq (AAH), all of which have been designated as Foreign Terrorist Organizations by the Department of State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BF1D88DFA9E4717AA78C2E0605575CE"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">KSS has fought under the command of former IRGC-Quds Forces commander Qassem Soleimani. The militia has members who operate as a unit of the Popular Mobilization Forces (PMF), which is a formal part of the Iraqi federal government under the authority of the Prime Minister of Iraq and which receives funding from the Iraqi federal government, including salaries. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA58DC7708FB545C29967DC9AC5B66691"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Since its founding KSS has deployed forces to Syria to engage in military operations supporting the Government of Syria, including offensives in Daraa, Quneitera, the Damascus suburbs, and the Aleppo countryside.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D26CA3B5FB5483896F8F7490A3987D8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 2015, KSS threatened to <quote>strike and destroy</quote> Saudi Arabia, saying in a statement: <quote>We in the Sayyid al Shuhada Battalion consider Saudi interests a legitimate and permissible target on all levels, and we will strike and destroy them whenever it pleases us.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4B513360C07490986256D135DF073CF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In August 2019, Abu Alaa al-Wala’i, a leader of KSS, said that <quote>All Americans will be held hostage by the resistance factions in the event of a war.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD96C7AAF21E4032B86535FF6DFF7320"><enum>(8)</enum><text>On February 14, 2020, the Department of State announced that sanctions were imposed on KSS pursuant to section 3 of the Iran, North Korea, and Syria Nonproliferation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note) for engaging in illicit arms transfers to or acquisition from Iran.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC080218A038465781C8E60A6423AB11"><enum>(9)</enum><text>On February 25, 2021, President Biden ordered airstrikes against infrastructure utilized by Iranian-backed militias in eastern Syria in response to attacks against United States personnel in Iraq. According to the Department of Defense's statement on February 25, 2021, <quote>the strikes destroyed multiple facilities located at a border control point used by a number of Iranian-backed militant groups, including Kait’ib Hezbollah (KH) and Kait’ib Sayyid al-Shuhada (KSS).</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HBFE3F2093DB549B2AA9B9FC55ED5AF87"><enum>3.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header><subsection id="H631DE9DD6A214457BF38DE563D3EDF6C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall impose the sanctions described in subsection (b) with respect to—</text><paragraph id="H6CB503C09E0E4BA39247ECF41EFB8261"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Kata’ib Sayyid al-Shuhada; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4ED7510C6604B73825F4FBC6CC12AA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any foreign person that is a member, agent, or affiliate of, or owned or controlled by, Kata’ib Sayyid al-Shuhada.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H30568B41A51F46529416927FE54E5B88"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this subsection are—</text><paragraph id="HE0930DABDCD04A14B37BE169D957C5A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>sanctions applicable with respect to a foreign person pursuant to section 7412(b) of the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8791">22 U.S.C. 8791</external-xref> note); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5346BA8BE29448BB8F6700A06A6CE1A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>sanctions applicable with respect to a foreign person pursuant to Executive Order 13224 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property and prohibiting transactions with persons who commit, threaten to commit, or support terrorism).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

