<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H43A1CEF0FA274D558E7DB3CBC7B677AD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4950 IH: Improving Medicaid Programs' Response to Overdose Victims and Enhancing Addiction Care Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4950</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XIX of the Social Security Act to encourage appropriate prescribing under Medicaid for victims of opioid overdose.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6616D0E2C76447CC9CA33E3600FFB4CB" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HF5FF62A831434F0992E54AEA8D688654"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Medicaid Programs' Response to Overdose Victims and Enhancing Addiction Care Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>IMPROVE Addiction Care Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD2CC7722E38C4000A11A296EE0F63F76"><enum>2.</enum><header>Encouraging appropriate prescribing under medicaid for victims of opioid overdose</header> <subsection id="HBE508C8E27BB44168BFC5D9088390870"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1927(g)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-8">42 U.S.C. 1396r–8(g)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1E4C70315D56486A9A0B56D980D2BB53"> 
<subparagraph id="H1327644824B848F3AFCAE4173D777FDE"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Additional drug use review requirements</header><text>As part of a State’s prospective and retrospective drug use review under subparagraphs (A) and (B), as applicable, the State shall, not later than 24 months after the date of enactment of this subparagraph, develop and implement, or review and update, protocols to, subject to any applicable State or Federal privacy or confidentiality protections that could preclude such protocols—</text> <clause id="HA489E943AED241B788F39AB4DE73AB60"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify individuals receiving benefits under this title who have experienced a nonfatal opioid-related overdose within a look-back period (to be determined by the Secretary except that such period shall not be less than 1 year and shall not exceed 5 years), to the extent that such data is available, and make a good faith effort to connect these individuals to treatment options and recovery support services that have been determined appropriate by the Secretary;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF544B95289A54BF796410D64001A2B69"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if an individual receiving benefits under this title experiences a fatal overdose that is opioid-related (without regard to whether such overdose was related to a covered outpatient drug), or, if specified by the Secretary, related to any other drug (including a drug that is not a covered outpatient drug), not later than 6 months after the date of such overdose—</text> <subclause id="HA921AB8B699341A495ABE29BED8391E0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>provide notice of such overdose to each provider that, during the period (to be established by the Secretary) preceding such overdose, prescribed opioids (or such other specified drug, if applicable) to such individual, to the extent that such data is available; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9DD6B277682C41A9854B111300814098"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provide each such provider with educational materials on prescribing opioids (or such other specified drugs, if applicable);</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H1770008144554E89A76EF319FC6EE3F7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ensure that a provider who is treating an individual receiving benefits under this title has notice of the individual's diagnosis or history of opioid use disorder, opioid poisoning diagnosis, history of nonfatal opioid-related overdose, or a diagnosis or history of a substance use disorder or overdose for such other specified drug, if applicable, to the extent such data is available; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H04D2F6AAE8D94B74AC23EF706001A20D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>perform ongoing retrospective drug utilization reviews and offer provider education that is informed by such reviews (which may include education provided under an educational outreach program established under subparagraph (D) or through an intervention described in paragraph (3)(C)(iii)) regarding appropriate prescribing practices for individuals receiving benefits under this title with a diagnosis or history of opioid use disorder, a history of nonfatal opioid-related overdose, an opioid poisoning diagnosis, or a diagnosis or history of a substance use disorder or overdose for such other specified drug, if applicable.</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">Nothing in this subparagraph shall be construed as requiring a State to develop and implement additional protocols if the State establishes to the satisfaction of the Secretary that the State has in place existing protocols meeting or exceeding the standards set forth in this subparagraph.</continuation-text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H0198F9D2C742469E920F058D9A6D8771"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical amendments</header><text>Section 1932(i) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396u-2">42 U.S.C. 1396u–2(i)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8BFF5DE42E6D460E963CD93F4E39E80A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>section 483.3(s)(4)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 438.3(s)(4)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE12F989E91954627B969180CDE193A66"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>483.3(s)(5)</quote> and inserting <quote>438.3(s)(5)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

