<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFB5D2C10346243938004962B1858AC77" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5484 IH: Green Ribbon Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5484</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Ms. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To strengthen and expand the Green Ribbon Schools Program at the Department of Education by boosting the capacity of participating States to expand the number of engaged schools, applicants, and nominees, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4C496CD8FEFD42FE8407A5632F0D527B" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HE5D9F5398F2B4F569BD0BE9A284099DC"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Green Ribbon Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H0B6A4BFF279F433D9C427FCB5299BD86"><enum>2.</enum><header>Green Ribbon Schools Program</header> <subsection id="HDD05DFB471BC4CCE8D5B02BCF2E64014"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section: </text>
<paragraph id="HB2966EA3F55849268D064731F406F331"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ESEA definitions</header><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, <term>Secretary</term>, and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2BAD8BA8544A4D1399BF535138D0BA2F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an elementary school, secondary school, school funded or operated by the Bureau of Indian Education, local educational agency, or institution of higher education. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H3027C88EBAF0408A9BED3EACE28F83C3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Environmentally literate</header><text>The term <term>environmentally literate</term>, when used with respect to an individual, means the capacity to—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H024A3B2AC7D74850BF4BC307DA0D42F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perceive and interpret the relative health of environmental systems and the interrelationships between natural, economic, and social systems and technology; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2498D4A6354543D4915D11797ED42360"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assess options and take appropriate action to maintain, restore, or improve the health of the environmental systems and promote sustainable development.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H90B03FD9847D44FC85DF325B376A5C7F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Green Ribbon pillars</header><text>The term <term>Green Ribbon pillars</term> means the following 3 interrelated aspirational goals:</text>
<subparagraph id="H3442D3E270984EA685BE6E105FCC83E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>100 percent of the graduates of the eligible entity or the schools served by the eligible entity are environmentally literate.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8F6094FE2B9F4BDEA120FF8F33E1CC9B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The environmental impacts of the eligible entity’s buildings, grounds, and operations are targeting significant emission reductions with a long-term goal of 100 percent reduction.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H435D39D150FA45E18F5EF45AC0A1B4A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The eligible entity has a net positive impact on the environmental health of its students and staff. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H611E45B8C1D54C5A8A6FBDC9343B1457"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Green Ribbon school award winner</header><text>The term <term>Green Ribbon School award winner</term> means an eligible entity that has received an award of recognition from the Department of Education for high performance in making progress toward all 3 of the Green Ribbon pillars, in accordance with subsection (b)(4).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6CFCE3D5F78A4730AB48E87B0099D004"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD1EC924847D14CDC81E6C8AAA1328323"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Green Ribbon School Program of the Department of Education</header> <paragraph id="HE1853095B3E143908879223680DD1D37"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct a program, which shall be known as the <quote>Green Ribbon Schools Program</quote>, to reach and engage more schools by—</text>
<subparagraph id="H45A5D37D3DDC443AB017F80B3D07EF8E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>encouraging eligible entities to implement the Green Ribbon pillars; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95A3A7F4F1E442AB8F81E10638EB22A2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recognizing high performance in the Green Ribbon pillars by eligible entities, through voluntary partnership with States;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9BCCCDE4B74B425C9B2CBA04185F4B62"><enum>(C)</enum><text>increasing the number of participating local educational agencies and schools that are receiving resources from the program, including those not pursuing an award on the date of enactment of this Act;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4A5BC9ECEE0441AE87326F29C51569AB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>engaging with public and private stakeholders to maximize positive impact; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF59CEAEE8DFB4748A62627AC7E542DD7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>supporting schools in implementing measures to reduce energy and water use and costs, increase resilience, increase environmental literacy, and improve indoor air and other conditions for health and wellness. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDC0ADA257E984EF3B4A3580685C7971A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Update</header> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H40FDF0330AB14E49B5FF90F9D1D93D54"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall conduct a review and update the criteria for the Green Ribbon school award winner program, including scoring, which shall include—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H324AB8016F42415F9A1A92B8C57E1AC2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensuring that health and wellness criteria align with programs of the Environmental Protection Agency and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and are associated with benefitting student health, thinking, and the ability to learn; </text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6E453BFE62974504B79A59ABB86B6A27"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensuring that environmental criteria emphasize the role of schools in mitigating and adapting to climate change, including school resiliency to natural disasters; and </text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDAA92735D58C4945821B1D1AAD0093BB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ensuring that environmental and sustainability literacy criteria encourage applicants to identify methods of assessment of student knowledge and skills and set goals for literacy among graduates. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA6C389F38A734B1B8437C0B86D040568"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Federal Register</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall publish in the Federal Register the final updated criteria for the Green Ribbon school award winner program and shall allow for, and address, any public comments related to the updated criteria. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA93C6368DCAE4DFB9CE9AF000BEEC7CA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grants and awards</header><text>In conducting the Green Ribbon Schools Program, the Secretary shall, from the amounts made available to carry out this Act—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H277E93CAB02B4731BE320262CE34408A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reserve not less than $250,000 for the Secretary of Interior to carry out the activities under subsection (c)(7) with respect to schools operated or funded by the Bureau of Indian Education;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17FB72C5CFF747A2A674A9011063EAD0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">award grants to State educational agencies under subsection (c); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEE2AC4FEBD7E451AA3D0AEB467CCCBC9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide an honorarium to each Green Ribbon School award winner in an amount equal to $10,000, subject to appropriations. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H507987ABB93C45618A30E37C0802C09A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Studies, research, and surveys</header><text>The Secretary may conduct studies, research, and surveys to inform the Green Ribbon Schools Program. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA6813DBD31A6445AA62928A38A7C7DC6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Green Ribbon school awards</header><text>Each year, regardless of whether funds are available for the honoraria described in paragraph (2)(C), the Secretary shall—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE7341B1210A646F299422107FFEA05C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a process through which—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HABAB32C3A3CD4820A0498444993DAB98"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">State educational agencies may nominate eligible entities for recognition of high performance in making progress toward all 3 of the Green Ribbon pillars; and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H22F48F5C28E74B5DA87E4F2FEB226613"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of the Interior, operating through the Bureau of Indian Education, may nominate eligible entities that are schools operated or funded by the Bureau for such recognition; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82ABF874CD4245C7B13A4627479E3A5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">award the Green Ribbon School award to nominated eligible entities that the Secretary determines have shown high performance in making progress toward all 3 of the Green Ribbon pillars.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE2B653A5C7A24343ABB5AB8BAA418052"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Secretary shall consult with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency and the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to align the Green Ribbon Schools Program with the science on school environments and school health cited by the Environmental Protection Agency and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H424C1E1643D34599B34DA37C8C266D94"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Reports</header> <subparagraph id="H0F8DD64C4BC9405B9A3C62BDB57A3F12"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Annual reports</header> <clause id="HEA34413D93934CE9A95773EFB8D5F610"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than November 1, 2023, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall publish a report describing the Green Ribbon Schools Program of the prior fiscal year. </text></clause>
<clause id="HB335E31395B44F00B760BA3D3C6BB1F5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Content of annual reports</header><text>Each annual report described in clause (i) shall—</text> <subclause id="HFA41BEDA7B5543ECB262F11738214021"><enum>(I)</enum><text>describe the activities and outcomes of the Department of Education and State grant award winners, including the uses of grant funds to reach and engage additional schools, and the successes and challenges of the Green Ribbon Schools Program; </text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3DA76105667340DF8F08CAC75ABFE35D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>describe the plan of State grant award winners to extend opportunities to become a Green Ribbon School award winner to schools that are eligible to receive funds under part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311 et seq.</external-xref>) or other schools that are low-income schools, schools in disadvantaged or rural or remote communities, or schools that serve a significant number of students with disabilities; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB6880BBD1BDB4F9F8D5C7ABB9A7DDFCF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>provide a proposed plan for the following year.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3C9E25ABF94D48E0A27C9EA48039DA08"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Biannual reports</header><text>Not later than November 1, 2024, and biannually thereafter, the Secretary shall publish a report describing key programs and policies of each State in supporting its schools in making progress toward all 3 of the Green Ribbon pillars. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCAA406EFC2794060B270E3D07860AB22"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State grant program</header> <paragraph id="H6B0A0FA59471492AB911D29A5269A286"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to State educational agencies, on a competitive basis, for the purpose of supporting and engaging eligible entities as green schools. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF1BB626779884F289C91940C8AA3CBA1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>A State educational agency that desires to receive a grant under this subsection shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may require, including an assurance that the agency will—</text> <subparagraph id="HE59F529CAD5849B9B55C50C1DFCEF182"><enum>(A)</enum><text>expend not less than 40 percent of the grant funds to support underresourced schools; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3E0247EA351A412782EB72086394CA8C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide documentation to the Secretary demonstrating compliance with the requirement under subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48EC9F2519734629BC9E445472BE4451"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In selecting grant recipients under this subsection, the Secretary shall consider the State educational agency’s proposed program or program expansion in terms of— </text>
<subparagraph id="H91D9F3B448054450B7BF416AFAB38BDA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the projected impact and proposed impact metrics;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H89F3FB63494D41B591FDC35038D0B86C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the incorporation of specific activities to ensure underresourced eligible entities benefit and have opportunities to participate;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD23FA7EE73A64EFCB6CF7FA0D741A09B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the extent to which stakeholders and partnerships are included;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFBE961ACD39D4FBBB86DE528964F1653"><enum>(D)</enum><text>innovative approaches to scaling green school practices and learning;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA1E5F900CD444A3F917ADA0A934E3274"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the engagement of past award winners in the program, including as mentors or advisors to other eligible entities; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB7C4892D9F9E4450AD5454C77B5F75C8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>other criteria as may be identified by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDD68C6E73B564C4191A4722FD3F28B7A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Amount of grants</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Secretary may determine the amount of each grant award, except that no grant award shall be for an amount that is less than $250,000 nor more than $1,000,000.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H858EA3CC6D0643B5A99B8388E218E03D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Time period</header><text>Grant funds awarded under this subsection shall be available for use by the grant awardee for not more than 3 years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H50353B13841F456FB407B8B0412E0275"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Allowed uses</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this subsection shall use the grant funds to increase and support eligible entities in becoming Green Ribbon School award winners, including by—</text> <subparagraph id="H2ECCF7C779A1400F84DD21780A676C88"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establishing State-level Green Ribbon awards and recognition events;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H312C2A64C55A4354839E8B1F6DF147D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>working in partnership with nonprofit green school organizations and other organizations, utilities, businesses, and other State and local governmental entities to inform, educate, and support eligible entities regarding actions to make progress toward all 3 of the Green Ribbon pillars;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC6A95C2580B14D8E8A50520048A49958"><enum>(C)</enum><text>using resources from the Department of Education and its green schools partners, as appropriate, to curate and disseminate resources about best green school practices and provide statewide training and professional development in the Green Ribbon pillars;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5D78F950B1744BEFB5CE991A1D199C5F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>utilizing innovative ways to promote—</text> <clause id="HB691E937A9C1454CB189A885E70C3100"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the implementation of green school practices; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H2BDEFB952D7344DB97EB6C4416859862"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Green Ribbon Schools Program and any State-level Green Ribbon schools program; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H720AFFC03A2F4C4DBB37191E8EE261F9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>providing statewide training and professional development in the Green Ribbon pillars.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H5EB6D804ED054126997CFC9B7CDCB3AE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Institute of Museum and Library Services Green Ribbon Award Program</header>
<subsection commented="no" id="HBB9A745E18FB4B158EFE4167D6CCF7C6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this section is to develop and implement a Green Ribbon award program for nonformal learning institutions at the Institute of Museum and Library Services in order to recognize and help advance excellence in the greening of nonformal learning institutions.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H65D68E413C9C4565AFE99F3018AD6020"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>nonformal learning institutions</term> includes public and private libraries, museums, arboretums, botanical gardens, nature centers, historical societies, historic preservation organizations, history museums, science and technology centers, planetariums, children’s museums, art museums, general museums, natural history museums, natural science museums, zoos, aquariums, and wildlife conservation centers. </text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HB357AE0483B445499944194EC17778A6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Consistent with section 209 of the Museum and Library Services Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9107">20 U.S.C. 9107</external-xref>), the Director of the Institute of Museum and Library Services shall establish an award program for nonformal learning institutions modeled on the Department of Education’s Green Ribbon Schools Program. The award program shall recognize and honor nonformal learning institutions that demonstrate high achievement in all 3 of the following goals: </text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H00FE0B9B53034A6C80B47353B457F4E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Ensuring that their visitors are exposed through multiple learning modes to locally relevant information to advance understanding of the interconnection of the natural environment, built environment, and quality of life.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H2DBA723F8A554B0EA4FFF4431E65B7C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Significantly reducing their net environmental and carbon footprints, while using their own built and natural environment as a learning laboratory and a model of best practice for their host community.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H28D14FA883CA4EBB8CCA91889501A65D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Ensuring their institution has a net positive environmental impact on visitor and staff health.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HBDE1554F31FE48559F44F3DFBC583A0D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Award</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Institute of Museum and Library Services shall provide each national award winner under this section with an honorarium of $10,000.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB9FC846BDF8943779C10F72949BB49BE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Director of the Institute of Museum and Library Services shall consult with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency and the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to align the award program under this section with the science on school health studied by the Environmental Protection Agency and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="HEA352E5CEF1B433DAC981262C5089F6F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Office of School Infrastructure and Sustainability within the Office of the Secretary of Education</header>
<subsection id="HFE6E583806794254B67647B2A6FE7102"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established within the Office of the Secretary of Education, the Office of School Infrastructure and Sustainability that shall be composed of 3 full-time employees.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7AC5A1782B794530A93751D5A35BB2D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The Office of School Infrastructure and Sustainability shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H13E5711CF8B64CF6AF838E4198EC0810"><enum>(1)</enum><text>direct content and programming of a technical assistance center for school infrastructure; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9A0175A0094D401C80170984C2683FEC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>liaise with partner Federal agencies that have programs, grants, and equities in school facilities, promote the National Clearinghouse's resources to schools, provide robust technical assistance to partner Federal agencies, local educational agencies, and State educational agencies, and oversee, promote, and expand the recognition award for the Green Ribbon Schools Program; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H97CEDA74ECA845A58058BC9BFCFAE289"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide technical assistance, training, and, subject to appropriations, grants to State educational agencies and local educational agencies on issues related to educational facility planning, design, financing, construction, improvement, operation, and maintenance, including green building design and operation practices consistent with a commitment to tackling the climate crisis; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6615737A604A4B4DADF4321105793B47"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop resources and assemble best practices on issues related to ensuring equitable access to healthy, educationally adequate, and environmentally and fiscally sustainable public school facilities and grounds; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H12D1E1A45E49429AAF9E9EA7C0E159A2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>recommend revisions to regulations of the Department of Education that pertain to school construction and renovation; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF13A7A5936CF43B1BFC329B2B1396939"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult with Federal agencies to ensure peer-reviewed recommendations and resources are incorporated into the work of the Office of School Infrastructure and Sustainability. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF0C3BDA68F8C445691DA960541B65EDA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriation</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $2,000,000 for fiscal year 2024.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HCA8B2D85437A4181B2956F8C4934BC0E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> <subsection id="H4BB8621343694F3FBD6E640473DD29D5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act (except for section 4) $10,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2029.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5417609ECC41432DB24331176ED38BE3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reservations</header><text>The Secretary—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H060187208C7A4D158D31DA4FA71DC780"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall reserve 10 percent of the amount appropriated under subsection (a) to carry out section 3; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE0CF4C20005A482DB34EC776715C441D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may reserve not more than 5 percent of the amount appropriated to carry out this Act for a fiscal year for administrative expenses. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

