<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFE5A5E2D3D414F1A9BF6909AAAEF24D5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5069 IH: To amend title 5, United States Code, to require Federal political appointees to sign a binding ethics pledge, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5069</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230728">July 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to require Federal political appointees to sign a binding ethics pledge, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H58B2E50023344FF69C36042208685AA1" style="OLC"><section id="H80C17E3AF2EC48298F165F5465644EE7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Ethics pledge requirement for senior Executive branch employees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/131">Chapter 131</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H04811860A30E4D08A84C45534920CCDF" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subchapter id="HE0AA990E3F934611A97D06CBBB98E0E7"><enum>IV</enum><header>Ethics Pledge</header><section id="H16CBE1FCC98541CA85E118BD3FF6A5DE"><enum>13151.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For the purposes of this subchapter, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="H6048377E1BEE4950975E19F432671760"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>executive agency</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 105, and includes the Executive Office of the President, the United States Postal Service, and Postal Regulatory Commission, but does not include the Government Accountability Office.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F919DB0481E461CA96C8FB4DA34A05E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>appointee</quote> means any full-time, noncareer Presidential or Vice-Presidential appointee, noncareer appointee in the Senior Executive Service (or other SES-type system), or appointee to a position that has been excepted from the competitive service by reason of being of a confidential or policymaking character (Schedule C and other positions excepted under comparable criteria) in an executive agency, but does not include any individual appointed as a member of the Senior Foreign Service or solely as a uniformed service commissioned officer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H876DC38B6BBA4FDC8DE6B260D74BC514"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>gift</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="H237CF2083D724DA78274FEF5D42786A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has the meaning given that term in section 2635.203(b) of title 5, Code of Federal Regulations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC70F3088B6DF4FF199B3434DFD2E3503"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes gifts that are solicited or accepted indirectly as defined at section 2635.203(f) of such title; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7551EB8FB19244F3B1C33AE2E5791257"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not include those items excluded by sections 2635.204(b), (c), (e)(1)–(3) and (j)–(l) of such title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H51622F5F0E92483BBCFD673C0C3E33A2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <quote>covered executive branch official</quote> and <quote>lobbyist</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 3 of the Lobbying Disclosure Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1602">2 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0FA0DDA958648CB9371A25C0B342068"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The term <quote>registered lobbyist or lobbying organization</quote> means a lobbyist or an organization filing a registration pursuant to section 4(a) of the Lobbying Disclosure Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1603">2 U.S.C. 1603(a)</external-xref>), and in the case of an organization filing such a registration, <quote>registered lobbyist</quote> includes each of the lobbyists identified therein.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8D54A2ACB374360B649E14CEB3B4217"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The term <quote>lobby</quote> and <quote>lobbied</quote> mean to act or have acted as a registered lobbyist.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CAE11F9ED854E7B98977E3075889862"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The term <quote>particular matter</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 207 of title 18 and section 2635.402(b)(3) of title 5, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9894BB7964A4570951356456FFDD825"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The term <quote>particular matter involving specific parties</quote> has the meaning set forth in section 2641.201(h) of title 5, Code of Federal Regulations, except that it shall include any meeting or other communication relating to the performance of one’s official duties with a former employer or former client, unless the communication applies to a particular matter of general applicability and participation in the meeting or other event is open to all interested parties.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7CCBD6DAD7540B1AAFAF7A725EF85A0"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The term <quote>former employer</quote> is any person for whom the appointee has within the 2 years prior to the date of his or her appointment served as an employee, officer, director, trustee, or general partner, except that <quote>former employer</quote> does not include any executive agency or other entity of the Federal Government, State or local government, the District of Columbia, Native American tribe, or any United States territory or possession.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03462D10A63149EFAA51749676537279"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The term <quote>former client</quote> is any person for whom the appointee served personally as agent, attorney, or consultant within the 2 years prior to the date of his or her appointment, but excluding instances where the service provided was limited to a speech or similar appearance. It does not include clients of the appointee’s former employer to whom the appointee did not personally provide services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1767C5D9EAA946D9987D8AF7F5D9AD86"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The term <quote>directly and substantially related to my former employer or former clients</quote> means matters in which the appointee’s former employer or a former client is a party or represents a party.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89BFB403755F4586AD9CDCB808942306"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The term <quote>participate</quote> means to participate personally and substantially.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3351E803D3074A5BA3571097069C869A"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>post-employment restrictions</quote> includes the provisions and exceptions in section 207(c) of title 18, and the implementing regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5E957D95275401BAAAC161349540E10"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Government official</quote> means any employee of the executive branch.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C5671C133014645AC82157986DAA683"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Administration</quote> means all terms of office of the incumbent President serving at the time of the appointment of an appointee covered by this subchapter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98A7428CBE704E33A5EBE9CBD0D4CB79"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The term <quote>pledge</quote> means the ethics pledge set forth in section 13152 of this subchapter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4359F5F06A24EC6BC0E9D44F51C565E"><enum>(17)</enum><text>All references to provisions of law and regulations shall refer to such provisions as in effect on the date of enactment of this subchapter.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H36BC3AD4FF734EB7A13A2A503FD0A192"><enum>13152.</enum><header>Ethics pledge</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Each appointee in every executive agency appointed on or after the date of enactment of this section shall sign, and upon signing shall be contractually committed to, the following pledge upon becoming an appointee:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC6C4AA3193F344C4813F1FD29CF14712" style="OLC"><section commented="no" id="H544DF8FEFD474F04BC0C4D11CAF782A8" section-type="undesignated-section"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As a condition, and in consideration, of my employment in the United States Government in an appointee position invested with the public trust, I commit myself to the following obligations, which I understand are binding on me and are enforceable under law: </text><paragraph id="HEABC01F2239F4CF5909B0EE21258D987"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">I will not, within 5 years after the termination of my employment as an appointee in any executive agency in which I am appointed to serve, engage in lobbying activities with respect to that agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7F9960913DF4F8EB20B76BD9C1DDA8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If, upon my departure from the Government, I am covered by the post-employment restrictions on communicating with employees of my former executive agency set forth in section 207(c) of title 18, United States Code, I agree that I will abide by those restrictions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE15FA944B684E69BF2A5D4C74A32D12"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to abiding by the limitations of paragraphs 1 and 2, I also agree, upon leaving Government service, not to engage in lobbying activities with respect to any covered executive branch official or noncareer Senior Executive Service appointee for the remainder of the Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8EB019ED17F4443997E5118A0208D17"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">I will not, at any time after the termination of my employment in the United States Government, engage in any activity on behalf of any foreign government or foreign political party which, were it undertaken on January 20, 2017, would require me to register under the Foreign Agents Registration Act of 1938, as amended. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04744A476A0D40B98A68A7E0A1E9ECED"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">I will not accept gifts from registered lobbyists or lobbying organizations for the duration of my service as an appointee.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H545143B54DD140C4BFE280F1E81C7DAA"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">I will not for a period of 2 years from the date of my appointment participate in any particular matter involving specific parties that is directly and substantially related to my former employer or former clients, including regulations and contracts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8133FD0312284B55948D7A93DDCD7785"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If I was a registered lobbyist within the 2 years before the date of my appointment, in addition to abiding by the limitations of paragraph 6, I will not for a period of 2 years after the date of my appointment participate in any particular matter on which I lobbied within the 2 years before the date of my appointment or participate in any particular matter on which I lobbied within the 2 years before the date of my appointment or participate in the specific issue area in which that particular matter falls.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C0A2F858011448ABAF86913FB5A99C9"><enum>(8)</enum><text>I agree that any hiring or other employment decisions I make will be based on the candidate’s qualifications, competence, and experience.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B2F966C41C44F78BEB052E47131864E"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">I understand that the obligations of this pledge are in addition to any statutory or other legal restrictions applicable to me by virtue of Government service.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H1FFF85AC2635425C815F59DF62C2614F"><enum>13153.</enum><header>Waiver</header><subsection id="H3C2C96CA4C944418896AC3A7246506B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Office of Management and Budget, in consultation with the Counsel to the President, may grant to any current or former appointee a written waiver of any restrictions contained in the pledge signed by such appointee if, and to the extent that, the Director certifies (in writing) that—</text><paragraph id="HF511BE2A1F46416BB78EFAF15835C0B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the literal application of the restriction is inconsistent with the purposes of the restriction; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B604065E82A4E03BB278873E0B54F42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>it is in the public interest to grant the waiver.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H56857EE2028E427CB2AEBD421D2382C7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Any waiver under this section shall take effect when the certification is signed by the Director.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9B9FB0B8BCFA4011912D636EB907C197"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public interest</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a)(2), the public interest shall include exigent circumstances relating to national security or to the economy. De minimis contact with an executive agency shall be cause for a waiver of the restrictions contained in paragraph 3 of the pledge.</text></subsection></section><section id="HFFC8B5A0EE834D2FB820F94ED1F071AE"><enum>13154.</enum><header>Administration</header><subsection id="HFBA87E3F82AA4727A1D11EC29D5F11C0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The head of each executive agency shall, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, establish such rules or procedures (conforming as nearly as practicable to the agency’s general ethics rules and procedures, including those relating to designated agency ethics officers) as are necessary or appropriate to ensure—</text><paragraph id="HB6BE52D64BAF477EBCEBECF6DE5362F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that every appointee in the agency signs the pledge upon assuming the appointed office or otherwise becoming an appointee;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7966FE52A0544C2A90620CCEE1CE27D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that compliance with paragraph 3 of the pledge is addressed in a written ethics agreement with each appointee to whom it applies, which agreement shall also be approved by the Counsel to the President prior to the appointee commencing work;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE308351514754097946B282C9C371875"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that spousal employment issues and other conflicts not expressly addressed by the pledge are addressed in ethics agreements with appointees or, where no such agreements are required, through ethics counseling; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89CB78FB483C417F82BB3784FE77891A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>compliance with this subchapter within the agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF183D20F84DD4F9A9C03A6B8C26E83FC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>EOP</header><text>With respect to the Executive Office of the President, the duties set forth in subsection (a) shall be the responsibility of the Counsel to the President.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD130A69D84924375BE89460E20C4436F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Director duties</header><text>The Director of the Office of Government Ethics shall—</text><paragraph id="H724850E7E2864CE2BBD53E93E3184C71"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure that the pledge and a copy of this subchapter are made available for use by agencies in fulfilling their duties under subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE7F693F9EA8477BA68CD94F97E5210C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in consultation with the Attorney General or the Counsel to the President, when appropriate, assist designated agency ethics officers in providing advice to current or former appointees regarding the application of the pledge;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5ED5CBD06CB431E8FAC0C7D848C07A3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in consultation with the Attorney General and the Counsel to the President, adopt such rules or procedures as are necessary or appropriate—</text><subparagraph id="H1463E64495D84E75A4139CC15E0F9B0F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to carry out the responsibilities assigned by this subsection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9254E42BD2894E0EA3AEDB482F8C4008"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to apply the lobbyist gift ban set forth in paragraph 1 of the pledge to all executive branch employees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A9413DA42DA43C19339277BFDF30033"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to authorize limited exceptions to the lobbyist gift ban for circumstances that do not implicate the purposes of the ban;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB312C11A5F949D58DAC0EB08A368F3C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to make clear that no person shall have violated the lobbyist gift ban if the person properly disposes of a gift as provided by section 2635.205 of title 5, Code of Federal Regulations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H782DD4D69D6D4CFC91390AD1B15BE391"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to ensure that existing rules and procedures for Government employees engaged in negotiations for future employment with private businesses that are affected by their official actions do not affect the integrity of the Government’s programs and operations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B77C347DC204613A06118C8AEEE5E38"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to ensure, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, that the requirement set forth in paragraph 6 of the pledge is honored by every employee of the executive branch;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HACE04A1837F646DF9B908EFD9257714C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in consultation with the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, report to the President on whether full compliance is being achieved with existing laws and regulations governing executive branch procurement lobbying disclosure and on steps the executive branch can take to expand to the fullest extent practicable disclosure of such executive branch procurement lobbying and of lobbying for presidential pardons, and to include in the report both immediate action the executive branch can take and, if necessary, recommendations for legislation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00C368DC4F284E6C834F352FFA5AE4BD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide an annual public report on the administration of the pledge and this subchapter.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2BD8F92837564FB599F94F86F8413F13"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Director of the Office of Government Ethics shall, in consultation with the Attorney General, the Counsel to the President, and the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, report to the President on steps the executive branch can take to expand to the fullest extent practicable the revolving door ban set forth in paragraph 5 of the pledge to all executive branch employees who are involved in the procurement process such that they may not for 2 years after leaving Government service lobby any Government official regarding a Government contract that was under their official responsibility in the last 2 years of their Government service, and to include in the report both immediate action the executive branch can take and, if necessary, recommendations for legislation.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFC9D4ABAF6FC401F95B30EE2320F29B2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Filing</header><text>All pledges signed by appointees, and all waiver certifications with respect thereto, shall be filed with the head of the appointee’s agency for permanent retention in the appointee’s official personnel folder or equivalent folder.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD988A3A6A4314F239A7AD03581923ED5"><enum>13155.</enum><header>Enforcement</header><subsection id="H2B7E9048C1744238AA9B507C709EF25F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The contractual, fiduciary, and ethical commitments in the pledge are solely enforceable by the United States pursuant to this section by any legally available means, including debarment proceedings within any affected executive agency or judicial civil proceedings for declaratory, injunctive, or monetary relief.</text></subsection><subsection id="H159D0285D8454BEFB14322734CC2A8F2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Violations</header><text>Any former appointee who is determined, after notice and hearing, by the duly designated authority within any agency, to have violated his or her pledge may be barred from lobbying any officer or employee of that agency for up to 5 years in addition to the time period covered by the pledge. The head of every executive agency shall, in consultation with the Director of the Office of Government Ethics, establish procedures to implement this subsection, which procedures shall include providing for fact-finding and investigation of possible violations of this subchapter and for referrals to the Attorney General for consideration pursuant to subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H87A4020DFC404E17A5726359CE69E4F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Investigation; civil action</header><text>The Attorney General is authorized—</text><paragraph id="HD3D8ECECA4CE43D0B6BAD4EB9434F94C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>upon receiving information regarding the possible breach of any commitment in a signed pledge, to request any appropriate Federal investigative authority to conduct such investigations as may be appropriate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE55E3C64E0BF4F61B33A103AAA18B17F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>upon determining that there is a reasonable basis to believe that a breach of a commitment has occurred or will occur or continue, if not enjoined, to commence a civil action against the former employee in any United States District Court with jurisdiction to consider the matter.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0CF84254DED5459FBBC451CABF7683F7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Relief</header><text>In any such civil action, the Attorney General is authorized to request any and all relief authorized by law, including—</text><paragraph id="H0E5AFD583D314F50850F3547E3ADC392"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such temporary restraining orders and preliminary and permanent injunctions as may be appropriate to restrain future, recurring, or continuing conduct by the former employee in breach of the commitments in the pledge he or she signed under this subchapter; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB306BFF2068842489ECA519C44253F50"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establishment of a constructive trust for the benefit of the United States, requiring an accounting and payment to the United States Treasury of all money and other things of value received by, or payable to, the former employee arising out of any breach or attempted breach of such pledge.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></subchapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

