<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB1A4EE97A1B7442889B7549561019E41" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6760 IH: No Tax Dollars for the United Nations Climate Agenda Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6760</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231213">December 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000546">Mr. Graves of Missouri</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001195">Mr. Smith of Missouri</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit United States contributions to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, and the Green Climate Fund.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H259DE0E8CA1F45168AF7C6EA2B233608" style="OLC"><section id="H838018FDB8924E978E00EEF706C2658D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Tax Dollars for the United Nations Climate Agenda Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HAF9AF3E1D82A46959E00CCD247A4A171"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on United States contributions to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, and the Green Climate Fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no funds made available to any Federal department or agency may be used to make assessed or voluntary contributions on behalf of the United States to or for the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC), or the Green Climate Fund.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

