<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF489D971CA494161ADF1697958B14174" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4407 IH: VOTERS Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4407</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to direct the Standards Board of the Election Assistance Commission to release voluntary considerations with respect to the administration of elections for Federal office.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HD5888FD91BDF4DC0BA04B358EB95462B" style="OLC">
<section id="H01C07E150FA846EE97A83347C9B3F2B2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Voluntarily Offered Tools for Election Reforms by States Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>VOTERS Act</quote>. </text></section> <section id="H075FB22617B0486EAFC79847FFA9A801"><enum>2.</enum><header>Election integrity voluntary considerations</header> <subsection id="H1A93212BFB2140BF8062A6151D489280"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle C of title II of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20981">52 U.S.C. 20981 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H52983B654A11411FADCE678EF1C7035E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating section 247 as section 248; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9238AA4864D74899B2F2085F7D02930B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 246 the following new section:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H35BEAB74C72549DD9EC55BAB95632310" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="H2EA9C56F5ACE42158015B228954E5173"><enum>247.</enum><header>Release of voluntary considerations by Standards Board with respect to election administration</header>
<subsection id="H8F1A2CC0CBE549A2A67666FF4217E11A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Standards Board shall draw from experiences in their home jurisdictions and information voluntarily provided by and between States on what has worked and not worked and release voluntary considerations with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HE5EDDD9E0E7E4439A8144704DB0125F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To consider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In releasing the voluntary considerations under subsection (a), the Standards Board shall examine and consolidate information provided by States and release considerations with respect to each of the following categories:</text>
<paragraph id="H5559659749AD442C87C3ACB3DCC4E938"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The process for the administration of ballots delivered by mail, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HBE7A54E392D94C668F5DD44F38B22F85"><enum>(A)</enum><text>deadlines for the return and receipt of such ballots to the appropriate election official;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H95D42F677158472E8DC05D8D4E78BECB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the design of such ballots, including the envelopes used to deliver the ballots;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA7FA7A820054B2ABAFBB41B0F15CF8A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the process for requesting and tracking the return of such ballots; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H507AC47BF26942A586C0C809E941368D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the processing of such ballots upon receipt by the appropriate election official, including the schedule for counting the ballots and the reporting of the unofficial results of such counting. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7BB7A23787AB48D395A777E0FFFFDCCB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The signature verification procedures used to verify the identity of voters in an election, which shall include an evaluation of human and machine methods of signature verification, an assessment of the training provided to individuals tasked to carry out such verification procedures, and the proposal of other less subjective methods of confirming the identity of a voter such as requiring the identification number of a valid government-issued photo identification or the last four digits of the voter’s social security number to be provided along with the voter’s signature. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3173C30BC22E42CB956688D28858C186"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The processes used to carry out maintenance of the official list of persons registered to vote in each State.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H588AAC87AEC34CC3A42B232E70B37D8C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Rules and requirements with respect to the access provided to election observers. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H809A933B69C546CFA7B6B78BF2B6FB51"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The processes used to ensure the timely and accurate reporting of the unofficial results of ballot counting in each polling place in a State and the reporting of the unofficial results of such counting. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCF717D5747F64FAAA802B5D7F73DC305"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The methods used to recruit poll workers and designate the location of polling places during a pandemic, natural disaster, or other emergency.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCB57E0888FD24B0DB546E1B26BE03E38"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The education of the public with respect to the certification and testing of voting machines prior to the use of such machines in an election for Federal office, including education with respect to how such machines are tested for accuracy and logic.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBD97DCD91DA2457A8B366706CFC43722"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The processes and procedures used to carry out a post-election audit.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0032C8DAA6284B29ABA5271F65F6850A"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The processes and procedures used to ensure a secure chain of custody with respect to ballots and election equipment.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H14B2855D64B1485CB5285EAA68B384B5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Release of voluntary considerations</header> <paragraph id="HC024965D3DA349E8B0B335F2F8900DE1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deadline for release</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than December 31, 2024, the Standards Board shall release voluntary considerations with respect to each of the categories described in subsection (b).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H867EF3BF59874F429EE84B21BCDE6688"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transmission and notification requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 days after the date the Standards Board releases voluntary considerations with respect to a category described in subsection (b), the Commission shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H73CF51B114184B67B99B9026BE22938A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transmit the considerations to the chief State election official of each State and the elected leadership of the legislature of each State, including the elected leadership of any committee of the legislature of a State with jurisdiction with respect to elections;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD305E56A489741CB862323F388D32898"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make the considerations available on a publicly accessible Government website; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB835C837C2AC462EAD798FADC80FB46E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">notify and transmit the considerations to the chair and ranking minority member of the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking minority member of the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFD94906FE18A4FAFA21FD4DE884806A6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of requirements payments for implementation of voluntary considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State may use a requirements payment provided under this Act to implement any of the voluntary considerations released under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC33E7E0085B746E58A452E44D2606A53"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed—</text>
<paragraph id="H0E4812CF4E4D4F8AA8A5490D1A555998"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to require compliance with the voluntary considerations released under subsection (a), including as a condition of the receipt of Federal funds; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4AB96C3180E44E978982C754E2E84111"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to treat the lack of compliance with such considerations as a violation of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 or to treat compliance with such considerations as a defense against an alleged violation of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HBDED1F0295C842C396A30A9914A2188A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8BBDA67862864A93BC302F790663DD05"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the item relating to section 247 as relating to section 248; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAAD906B05D8040F893FCCE12FEC12F98"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 246 the following new item:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H938642BF7CA640CE89B6F6A550E39EFE" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 247. Release of voluntary considerations by Standards Board with respect to election administration.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

