<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEFEF3F9DB0EF4C39B56BF550BE156A5B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6000 IH: Revoke Iranian Funding Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6000</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231019">October 19, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00"> Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To freeze $6,000,000,000 of Iranian funds held in Qatar, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H4AC65AB379334F419DE9AC5A3B682F73" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8B43DDD06D944AB1AD65FE613F0A9A33" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Revoke Iranian Funding Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4F28D314AFB04CAEBF73FB2D3DCB01F7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H07B7D84F584D47E8AB7A5F2C14415F0F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Iran, as documented by the report of the Department of State entitled, <quote>Country Reports on Terrorism 2021</quote>, is the leading state sponsor of terrorism in the world;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1539E260D55242A1B6891BE6151979D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Hamas has repeatedly carried out acts of terror against Israel, citizens of the United States, and innocent civilians, including the October 2023 assault against Israel that resulted in the brutal murder of innocent men, women, and children;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H93B69EED38A845BCBDE216D0D7414189"><enum>(3)</enum><text>given the fungible nature of money, funds released to Iran for so-called humanitarian purposes cannot be reliably prevented from funding future terrorist attacks, especially when the Government of Iran has explicitly acknowledged their willingness to use any and all monetary gains to support the ideology of their regime; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D46D92CD8D64FA9BDB390395421623E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in the face of this reality, the United States Government should consider every available tool to immediately restrict access by Iran to any and all funds that are used to finance international terrorism.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H47567E9AA49F49B78CB92BD7FA17BB8F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rescission of license authority with respect to Iranian accounts in Qatar</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective on the date of the enactment of this Act—</text> <paragraph id="H2739F3E735AA404F895C0EB34D850624"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Treasury shall rescind any general license, specific license, action letter, comfort letter, statement of licensing policy, answers to frequently asked questions, or other exemption from the imposition of sanctions under a covered provision of law purportedly for humanitarian purposes, such as the $6,000,000,000 transferred from South Korea in September 2023, with respect to accounts held by the Government of Iran or a covered person in Qatar issued before such date of enactment; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFCFFC6640CDA47EDA08EE54F75E296BE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any authority provided to the Secretary of the Treasury to issue, purportedly for humanitarian purposes, a general license, specific license, action letter, comfort letter, statement of licensing policy, answers to frequently asked questions, or other exemption from the imposition of sanctions under a covered provision of law with respect to accounts held by the Government or Iran or a covered person in Qatar is rescinded for the one-year period following the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDE1E882C2D3247C498E3869B9D5DE436"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rescission of waiver determination issued on September 8, 2023</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective on the date of the enactment of this Act, the waiver determination issued by the Secretary of State on September 8, 2023, under covered waiver authority and submitted to Congress on September 11, 2023, is rescinded.</text></section> 
<section id="H6CB134EF9E524358A1932D95B549F80F" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report and briefing on Iranian assets and licenses</header> 
<subsection id="H4B9901D23AEA46FBB6D491F802EE4341"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report and provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing—</text> <paragraph id="H21CF961052054D28A56AB8470DB7CD53"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifying—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF1629D9306BA48669113ABC44D7789FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all assets of the Government of Iran or covered persons valued at more than $5,000,000 and blocked by the United States pursuant to any provision of law; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFBC6DA5B7CA74CBD8E7F50AC051B1437"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for each such asset—</text> 
<clause id="H5346205344E34FA1A2E55D1F60DACFB3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the country in which the asset is held;</text></clause> <clause id="H119D116B3BE848899204D364D6005906"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the financial institution in which the asset is held; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H39CB7121E09344B4A0D0FC31DCACDDE7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the approximate value of the asset; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8C0A461843614AF7A84C10C798D2CF1D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>setting forth a list of all general licenses, specific licenses, action letters, comfort letters, statements of licensing policy, answers to frequently asked questions, or other exemptions issued by the Secretary with respect to sanctions relating to Iran that are in effect as of the date of the report.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H00BAFD82610A48B1940248CB5C9A2725" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0310057AE7F74353BC3C93130C5BD452"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assets</header><text>The report and briefing required by subsection (a)(1) shall be submitted or provided, as the case may be, in unclassified form. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDBC39DB605841928C7538DE84B00077"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exemptions</header><text>The report and briefing required by subsection (a)(2) shall be submitted or provided, as the case may be, in classified form.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H35E50AC56459404D99929373817A0F2F"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H18666A8B3EF84D3EACE9C9677F68C61A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFA4E2A64F37540E6A8FAF3858ADE4A17"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAE4B781B85734DEEA3976C987150BA2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4F92CD5228CE407592001C04B730B25C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered person</header><text>The term <term>covered person</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HA93E9915823C4B28B4E0115422C727F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual who is a citizen or national of Iran and is acting on behalf of the Government of Iran;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB11F933E596B48EE932843054BC32135"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of Iran or otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the Government of Iran; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F287AA9E00649CDBDE5134B6BAC45D6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an individual or entity that provides material, tactical, operational, developmental, or financial support to—</text> 
<clause id="H236CB0B5350C4EE9BA8159FBEDCCE592"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps;</text></clause> <clause id="HF1AAD5493F3C4B6299A11205DFA5E834"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any agency or instrumentality of the armed forces of Iran;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HADE174EAD0AC473CB6C4D3D3B5FC38BB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any agency or instrumentality related to the nuclear program of Iran; or</text></clause> <clause id="HC7A104CE901946E2B46FAE760CB0EC61" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any organization designated as a foreign terrorist organization under section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>), including Hamas, Hezbollah, Palestinian Islamic Jihad, al-Qa’ida, and al-Shabaab. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEC4ED9039D7F4F76933299939749E692"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered provision of law</header><text>The term <term>covered provision of law</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H6E0706BB7A6441F3A10AA1BF1E6850FB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 1245 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8513a">22 U.S.C. 8513a</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3DCFA98B18C0467DA582EE1C09E56C28"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 1244 or 1247 of the Iran Freedom and Counter-Proliferation Act of 2012 (22 U.S.C. 8803 and 8806).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H717528D7D88D43838E15505130945D88"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered waiver authority</header><text>The term <term>covered waiver authority</term> means the authority to issue a waiver of the requirement to impose sanctions under—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6A6EB7AE06564DB5B5BDDBD7919E61D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 1245(d)(5) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8513a">22 U.S.C. 8513a(d)(5)</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB6D09A6CD9E246D09D8678CEAE593760"><enum>(B)</enum><text>section 1244(i) or 1247(f) of the Iran Freedom and Counter-Proliferation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8803">22 U.S.C. 8803(i)</external-xref> and 8806(f)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


