<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE449AF2A9E9E4E41BA65818F452782DE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5562 IH: Fostering Success in Higher Education Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5562</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230919">September 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to provide formula grants to States to improve higher education opportunities for foster youth and homeless youth, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H133C36A245A9451C9DD7A9C496FD38FD" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H167C291AD72C41809336461E76EF4AED"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fostering Success in Higher Education Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0D25366669084019B3BE2F82696D63FB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Formula grants to States to improve higher education opportunities for foster youth and homeless youth</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title VII of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1133">20 U.S.C. 1133 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0FDAD4CBD21C4F6999CAD4BAD84E9BF2">
<part id="H96FA93E53C994AE9BCF33A2BA2EFC743"><enum>F</enum><header>Grants for improving access to and success in higher education for foster youth and homeless youth</header>
<section id="H6F130AC8DF904EF79B84BBD834AD8E02"><enum>791.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part:</text> <paragraph id="HA9523C5BCF3E4BE2996C05CB51EF0E8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Foster youth</header><text>The term <term>foster youth</term>—</text>
<subparagraph id="H22AE230357D7461EA7285866937798A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means an individual whose care and placement is the responsibility of the State or tribal agency that administers a State or tribal plan under part B or E of title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/621">42 U.S.C. 621 et seq.</external-xref>; 670 et seq.), without regard to whether foster care maintenance payments are made under section 472 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/672">42 U.S.C. 672</external-xref>) on behalf of the individual; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8C401EEC7D7D442CB0AF0F8146D204C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes any individual—</text>
<clause id="HC09AF6200AE54FFABE4550EB8507301E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whose care and placement was the responsibility of such a State or tribal agency when, or at any time after, the individual attained 13 years of age, without regard to whether foster care maintenance payments were made under section 472 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/672">42 U.S.C. 672</external-xref>) on behalf of the individual; and</text></clause> <clause id="H8ED1E39E1261445197DF5F02F4E03E8B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who is no longer under the care and responsibility of such a State or tribal agency, without regard to any subsequent adoption, guardianship arrangement, or other form of permanency option.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7EDE26CEF9AA42409EF9E01C9C2041E2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Homeless youth</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>homeless youth</term> has the meaning given the term <term>homeless children and youths</term> in section 725 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11434a">42 U.S.C. 11434a</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H593438C46E5146BE8A19D278A5EEEDD8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Indian Tribe; tribal organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>Indian Tribe</term> and <term>Tribal organization</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDC076A39D1AD40B98A797094ECE24A72"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States and the District of Columbia.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7D3BBB33AFD4459291C554EF2CAA31D1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Territory</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>territory</term> means the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, the Federated States of Micronesia, and the Republic of Palau.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H04144B97513A488BACEC8996A115C827"><enum>792.</enum><header>Formula grants to States to improve access to and success in higher education for foster youth and homeless youth</header>
<subsection id="H8498366386F948BB9F6B5D9C0FF91ECB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program established</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amount appropriated under subsection (h), the Secretary shall make allotments under subsection (b), to States having applications approved under subsection (c), to enable each State to—</text> <paragraph id="H71C8FF1E21CA4853910FF42D1153FABA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out the statewide transition initiative described in subsection (d); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H454E635E546344F0B0A95EBCD584B991"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make subgrants described in subsection (e).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF64137CD5F64425FADEB9E0E4B5E023B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Allotments</header> <paragraph id="H880B05FF04414BE7B60BCE5368F54425"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Formula</header> <subparagraph id="HD20B4CCA521A4B3FB477081100E82DA1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Reservation for Indian tribes and territories</header> <clause id="H25999FABAE954E4282AA65D5FF35CD20"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From the amount appropriated under subsection (h) for a fiscal year and subject to clause (ii), the Secretary shall reserve—</text>
<subclause id="H50207926C4C348B794DE39C0C2DC8919"><enum>(I)</enum><text>not more than 3 percent for grants to Indian Tribes, consortia of Indian Tribes, or Tribal organizations; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HD8C9F18356324019B94069A1E6D35E0D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not more than 2 percent for grants to territories.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HA9D09A6B4FE7420AAC65B76960A71D04"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this subparagraph, the Secretary—</text> <subclause id="HE9B9E80A886C4C5486343C8D23CE5D6D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall not award a grant under subclause (I) or (II) of clause (i) for a fiscal year for which no Indian Tribe (or consortium of Indian Tribes) or Tribal organization, or territory, respectively, submits a satisfactory application for a grant under such subclause;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H95A631F799F74995BD6497EC21BF37C9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shall require that any Indian Tribe, consortium, Tribal organization, or territory that receives a grant under this subparagraph provide an assurance of a partnership among relevant education, child welfare, and homeless agencies or organizations; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HD669B0262E6C4C02A57787275F76924D"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may determine any other requirements with respect to such grants (including the allocation, application, and use of fund requirements), which to the extent possible, shall be consistent with the requirements for States under this part, except that appropriate adjustments shall be made based on the needs and size of populations served by the Indian Tribe, consortium, Tribal organization, or territory applying for the grant.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2E4F91AE40D04EE49A1ED4A8D38B72CE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reservation for Department activities</header><text>From the amount appropriated under subsection (h) for a fiscal year, the Secretary may reserve—</text> <clause id="H84684E622A294143BB115D5898D7B549"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not more than 7 percent to—</text>
<subclause id="H338E731A9D7146489683B25F7C265D79"><enum>(I)</enum><text>provide technical assistance, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, to States carrying out activities under this section; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE87601C5D04943D2AC8F6B3F7FB2BCFC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>complete the evaluations required by subsection (g)(1); and</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H0123A2BAA32A494B91A5D5CC4C52ABF6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not more than 3 percent for administrative expenses.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H877342D0ADA14ED79686EBA77AFA05F1"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Allotments</header><text>From the amount appropriated under subsection (h) for a fiscal year and remaining after the Secretary reserves funds under subparagraphs (A) and (B), the Secretary shall allot to each State the greater of—</text>
<clause id="HC64C60B2EDF4455980D44A78589B7ADE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$500,000; or</text></clause> <clause id="H98A42D6F72F2465CB37DD471AE2EB1BC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount that bears the same proportion to the remaining appropriated amount for such fiscal year as the number of foster youth and homeless youth in the State bears to the number of foster youth and homeless youth in all States.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H81750B4E837A40BDBAF4F2B6551E31D0"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Ratable reduction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the amount appropriated under subsection (h) for a fiscal year and remaining after the Secretary reserves funds under subparagraphs (A) and (B) is less than the amount required to be allotted to States under subparagraph (C), then the amount of the allotment to each State shall be ratably reduced.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6730401FA39E43BCB54064061B3AFCF2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State Reservation</header><text>From the amounts awarded a State under paragraph (1)(C) for a fiscal year, the State may reserve not more than 5 percent for administrative expenses.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2641FF8688DF4A0E995D327091FA3E3A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Temporary ineligibility for subsequent payments</header>
<subparagraph id="H055E0F5ACAC346709FC140BB3A2915DE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall determine a State to be temporarily ineligible to receive a grant payment under this subsection for a fiscal year if—</text> <clause id="H8521DB90EC3645BABA1BE7050A3D2BD5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the State fails to submit an annual report under subsection (f) for the preceding fiscal year; or</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H1EB1EAD02EE045AFBF692E3DA8D7E09B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Secretary determines, based on information in such annual report, that the State is not effectively—</text> <subclause id="HBA9181538BBF41C1B24237F730E5717C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>meeting the outcomes described in the application of such State under subsection (c)(2)(C), and does not have a plan to improve the outcomes;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H72FA5683A5EC4BCB868A04A2F3C4317D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>monitoring and evaluating the activities under subsections (d) and (e); or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0AECFB4ABC9942D7A5372D8FB69C0D9E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>using funds as required under subsections (d) and (e).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H93A5B82CAB02480B8965C12CC9136D46"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reinstatement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary determines that a State is ineligible under subparagraph (A), the Secretary may enter into an agreement with the State setting forth the terms and conditions under which the State may regain eligibility to receive payments under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC126EFFBA2B04657B8056981A79929D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header> <paragraph id="H042675766E6C45598900133FD7A35246"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each fiscal year for which a State desires an allotment under subsection (b), the State shall submit an application to the Secretary—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3C3D8D355304DF886357375F33974D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2B8D35E7BEE34BAA9FF0BD2B5B89D16D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">containing the information described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H82B7F69F340C490B84C19D92D69105C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An application submitted under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H808B76191B3949ADACD3153712E51895"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A plan for how the State will carry out the activities under subsections (d) and (e).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6ADCC5D7B0114961AC4D4C2CA78C1C1B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the State’s capacity to carry out such activities.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0584AEB9844E4333864C296AF0051048"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of intended outcomes for such activities.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1189064337804A3EBCE5C8D86876E474"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A plan for how the State will monitor and evaluate such activities, including how the State will use data to continually update and improve such activities.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H51769CD9A1184D618318963AEB57DDA2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of how students will be identified and recruited for participation in the statewide transition initiative under subsection (d).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H449ADCC7F58C4817B5AF5371A2477C64"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An estimate of the number and characteristics of the populations targeted for participation in the statewide transition initiative under subsection (d), with attention to the diverse needs of homeless youth and foster youth in the State.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3DE7AACB66B042409ECDCB44987DB984"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of how the State will coordinate services provided under the grant with services provided to foster youth and homeless youth under the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11301">42 U.S.C. 11301 et seq.</external-xref>), the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, and the Runaway and Homeless Youth Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/11201">34 U.S.C. 11201 et seq.</external-xref>), and other services provided to foster youth and homeless youth by the State.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE2CCFCA3155048E8A31022D646073043"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assurance that the State will comply with subtitle B of title VII of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11431">42 U.S.C. 11431 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2A6FE11B8CB04BE6A081690C0684C5EF"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assurance that the State will partner with State educational agencies, local educational agencies, institutions of higher education, State and local child welfare authorities, and other relevant organizations that serve foster youth or homeless youth.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE40B764D0529448B82542CA4DF73B738"><enum>(J)</enum><text>An assurance that the State will submit the annual report required under subsection (f).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3D020EF8D7A74FA1B594BCAB45081B92"><enum>(K)</enum><text>A budgetary analysis of the use of funds awarded under this section.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H42BF6AD8EF4B429DA5C3C57D29280693"><enum>(L)</enum><text>Such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0D39B82E84AE4CE998CF4584674E5713"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Statewide transition initiative</header> <paragraph id="HA60906AACC4D4D18BDFE344CBF97BD57"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Subject to subsection (b)(2), and in consultation and coordination with the entities described in paragraph (2), a State receiving a grant award under this section shall use not less than 25 percent of the funds to—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD9A5AFD3B93C4FEFBBDB99E145F1A6E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide intensive outreach and support to foster youth and homeless youth to—</text> <clause id="H487448FBDD8B463EB80D0061114547E3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improve the understanding and preparation of foster youth and homeless youth for enrollment in institutions of higher education;</text></clause>
<clause id="HAE93849B414240BD93D9BCE6B4AD5FE4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>increase the number of applications to institutions of higher education submitted by foster youth and homeless youth; and</text></clause> <clause id="H4EFE0A690BA046489A712FED547AD380"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>increase the number of enrollments of foster youth and homeless youth at institutions of higher education;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB14FACA3FD6F420F967328B1ECA0B7E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide education to foster youth and homeless youth with respect to—</text> <clause id="H1EF1629885394E0C9A143460D9737427"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the benefits and opportunities of postsecondary education;</text></clause>
<clause id="HE944BA42180C40EAB5A883BBE4B8F4FE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>planning for postsecondary education;</text></clause> <clause id="H20FD865DFC594174A4A200F6081CD2D8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>financial aid opportunities for enrollment at an institution of higher education;</text></clause>
<clause id="H68DE3E13CD54428E9C8EC346E28BA931"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Federal and State services and benefits available to foster youth and homeless youth while enrolled at an institution of higher education, including health and mental health services;</text></clause> <clause id="H9290FD96B0804159908FDC40CD465675"><enum>(v)</enum><text>career exploration; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H55758CC15EEA40F89041E6AA25638889"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>financial literacy training, including security from identity theft;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC93C0BB4D0E8462AA468DE820E0797D2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>assist foster youth and homeless youth with submitting applications for—</text>
<clause id="H0EB2FF835CB441B9956B2717D85EF6A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>enrollment at an institution of higher education;</text></clause> <clause id="H55715916D44443D9A6F9796501D63390"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>financial aid for such enrollment; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HE68AC686CEA34F1DAF1F5AB88AA72708"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">scholarships available for such students, including under a State educational and training voucher program referred to in section 477(i) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/677">42 U.S.C. 677(i)</external-xref>); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8A7513A9572647F99D40AA35FACD0968"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide free programming, which may include free transportation to and from such programming, for foster youth and homeless youth to prepare such individuals socially and academically for the rigors of postsecondary education during the summer before such individuals first attend an institution of higher education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA9D48DD403BE4D90AE6305D5FCC1F905"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Required consultation and coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the activities described in paragraph (1), a State shall consult and coordinate with State educational agencies, local educational agencies, institutions of higher education, State and local child welfare authorities, and other relevant organizations that serve foster youth or homeless youth.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H408891AD26674E50B2A6A3601EBDA9AA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Subgrants To create institutions of excellence</header> <paragraph id="HDBDD26B85F5C4B7997634EA58790B0A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsection (b)(2), a State receiving a grant under this section shall, acting through the administering State agency, use not less than 70 percent of the funds to award, on a competitive basis, subgrants to eligible institutions to enable such institutions to become institutions of excellence by improving access, retention, and completion rates at eligible institutions for foster and homeless youth as described in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H44BB0678F91A4B2899E8BD8DB6D2E5BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header>
<subparagraph id="H993AEB27F1ED4977A09C7924AEC50C1F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible institution desiring a subgrant under this subsection shall submit an application to the State in which such eligible institution is located, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the State may require.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAC303DA21EC948E18ABB324C0B02BA34"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>Each State receiving an allotment under this section shall provide outreach and technical assistance to eligible institutions with respect to applications for subgrants under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC6407FA3FC1F40BDA36C5BE78524D1C1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible institution that receives a subgrant under this subsection shall use the subgrant funds to carry out the following activities with respect to homeless youth and foster youth:</text> <subparagraph id="H72B6C3A0857046D49E4701617E83B1E3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide flexibility and assistance in completing the application process to enroll at such institution.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFC9E70C914314514830A87ED7A599722"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Coordinate programs with relevant on- and off-campus stakeholders to increase the enrollment of such youth at the institution and align services at the institution for such youth.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4A67F1862D2C48F3A682240BC0A4ACF0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Adjust the cost of attendance for such youth at such eligible institution to include the cost of housing during periods of non-enrollment.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1FEAC91CFA6542F7A987C873672F46A0"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide institutional aid to such students to meet the cost of attendance that is not covered by other Federal or State educational grants.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3104AB7FE4FF45008BA6C9834D074FBF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Provide outreach to such students to ensure that such youth are aware of housing resources available during periods of non-enrollment.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDF4F2F9AF5574B35874455686B38929F"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsidize any fees for such students associated with orientation and offer free transportation to the orientation or move-in week at the eligible institution.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA02633F03DB34C53AA21DF7168E0F0C8"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Hire and provide training for at least one full-time staff member at the eligible institution to serve as a point of contact to provide case management services and monthly face-to-face meetings with students who are foster youth or homeless youth. Such individual shall have an advanced degree and at least two years of relevant experience.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7EE75BF55D00401B8445935F6339B2DF"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Establish or enhance campus support programs to provide such students with a wide-range of on-campus services, including—</text> <clause id="HFBB18E04B2004E5683B851A3A1E43261"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assistance with financial aid;</text></clause>
<clause id="HF3D16A30E0CD4C85A663C1E1F90E5E23"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>career advice; and</text></clause> <clause id="H6BD9D0BBD8094BB999745CB8694293CE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>leadership development.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4D3C8521455345D78A0131BECD0ED464"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Ensure the availability of robust health services (physical and mental) that meet the specific needs of foster youth and homeless youth.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4F161632188348B7A0E67FCDAD372C56"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish or expand early alert systems to identify and support such students who may be struggling academically.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC1057CA6051F4A598D4B8EB69D189AF6"><enum>(K)</enum><text>For each such student with reasonable, unanticipated expenses that would not be covered by the institutional aid provided under subparagraph (D) and that would be necessary for the student to persist in higher education during an academic year, provide the student with access to an emergency grant to help cover such expenses.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HADE88E740F644BD6B883FB2ED7B42228"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Collect, review, and monitor data for program improvement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HED8B3B59000345449DE1BFF084D56648"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reliance on institutional aid or emergency grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any institutional aid or emergency grant funds provided to a student under subparagraph (D) or (K) of paragraph (3) by an eligible institution during the period of the institution’s subgrant under this subsection shall continue to be provided during the student’s continuous enrollment at the institution, without regard to whether the subgrant period ends during such enrollment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9FD77F0DFFC849A4AEF1768471C7F076"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection:</text>
<subparagraph id="H51EB8422063B494482D41764E03CDBDE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Administering State agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>administering State agency</term> means a State agency—</text> <clause id="HEA8F3D9A93A142C185D39B158698D746"><enum>(i)</enum><text>designated by the Governor or executive of the State to administer the subgrants under this subsection; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H336B01891F58406B9802EA78D862A080"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that, with respect to such State, has jurisdiction over—</text> <subclause id="H4A52F5B23C73457CBD42E69796DA67CB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>foster youth;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HBCB666AA3BE1410F98F02FD49AFDD7E6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>homeless youth;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE62C0AFF2A494D638B0BE37BA445BC72"><enum>(III)</enum><text>elementary and secondary education; or</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HF2C286F1B76646FF86EDA3927BEFF7B7"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>higher education.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0B8D3242CBA04D11BF96B0859848CFA8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligible institution</header><text>The term <term>eligible institution</term> means an institution of higher education that—</text>
<clause id="H488D984CD44B4959ADD2C12B04CE1F41"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is in partnership with—</text> <subclause id="H9E16CE153230477FB845AA60F294B4AF"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the State child welfare agency that is responsible for the administration of the State plan under part B or E of title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/621">42 U.S.C. 621 et seq.</external-xref>; 670 et seq.); and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H34E56126262A4C59A1B8EFD1A2A20BDE"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an organization that serves homeless youth (such as a youth shelter or outreach program); and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H512883683A084E878E8648D83061E074"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may partner with any other provider, agency, official, or entity that serves foster youth and homeless youth, or former foster youth and homeless youth.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0F8B6DB1EBB045C893A43036E77D90F6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>State reports</header><text>For each year in which a State receives an allotment under subsection (b), the State shall prepare and submit a report to the Secretary that includes—</text> <paragraph id="H038594397C2C45DCA5F4F87A9CFE82FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>each activity or service that was carried out under this section;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7B98D7FE495D4E229FB93A1C9A3E65C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the cost of providing each such activity or service;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFDEDB6B860214D4E96910D05D44EACA5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of students who received each activity or service, disaggregated by demographics;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFC0D2E9B33844970917CFE8385EC41DF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>using qualitative and quantitative analysis, how the State—</text> <subparagraph id="H658B64A7AEB44EA69E8C5695E66F9BC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improved access to higher education for foster youth and homeless youth; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAB520806892549E18C234EB1000624E4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>measured youth satisfaction with activities carried out under this part;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE92B9B8248D44169F6EF9623981394A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an analysis of the implementation and progress of the statewide transition initiative under subsection (d), including challenges and changes made to the initiative throughout the preceding year;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6D7FC9F6D4DD4359B33F0DA89741C92C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>if, based on the analysis under paragraph (5), the State determines that the program is not on track to meet the intended outcomes described in the application of the State under subsection (c)(2)(C), a description of how the State plans to meet such intended outcomes; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9BC4A2D267AC49D3900377182C91DAB6"><enum>(7)</enum><text>information on the eligible institutions receiving subgrants, including how such institutions used subgrant funds to carry out the activities described in subsection (e)(3).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H34C465B23DA24851875BB7E421B51BE0"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Department activities</header>
<paragraph id="H58CA1CE63BDE45BF9A492E5DE016538D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Evaluations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date on which funds are first allotted under subsection (b), and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall evaluate recipients of allotments and subgrants under this section. The results of such evaluations shall be made publicly available on the website of the Department.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E1B8098B23940FA8AF0D9A0AF9AF797"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which funds are first allotted under subsection (b), and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit a report to Congress that includes—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0A0DE88447AF4739B2E1208EBA983834"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount of each allotment under subsection (b);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1B483C1C78BD4266A9FB09A6D90C8A9F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount of each subgrant under subsection (e); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H86B857343AB945538B111A3655B97613"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to the year for which such report is made, the results of the evaluations under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H641CA925DBE8468FA3946A5CC83C9362"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $150,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each of the 5 succeeding fiscal years.</text></subsection></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


