<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF7FBC8BECC8E4402957D49C4239382E1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6097 IH: To amend the Family Violence Prevention and Services Act to authorize grants to ensure access for victims of family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence to substance use disorder treatment that allows parents (or legal guardians) and their children, stepchildren, or other dependents to remain together throughout the course of treatment, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6097</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001214">Mr. Mrvan</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Family Violence Prevention and Services Act to authorize grants to ensure access for victims of family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence to substance use disorder treatment that allows parents (or legal guardians) and their children, stepchildren, or other dependents to remain together throughout the course of treatment, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE6177CC2087844F3B2679F291A2356C6" style="OLC"><section id="H10428BE6D8254EFE8C8073652C0F667E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Grants for safe recovery together</header><subsection id="H5B23F9A00DB641E3AE2526B60918D1EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Family Violence Prevention and Services Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10401">42 U.S.C. 10401 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H04E5C80C87A34B9A8494E2F2092D98DA" style="OLC"><section id="H8F1FFA3BD01E42CDB2168F72435FA35B"><enum>315.</enum><header>Grants for safe recovery together</header><subsection id="HDB12E4073B944387AA388D9A7B1C7A64"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Safe recovery together</header><paragraph id="H829AAE47BD724C13B147C357CF56D79B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the sums appropriated under section 303(e) and available to carry out this subsection for any fiscal year, the Secretary may award grants to eligible entities to develop, implement, and improve programs for ensuring access for victims of family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence to substance use disorder treatment that allows parents (or legal guardians) and their children, stepchildren, or other dependents to remain together throughout the course of treatment. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FA81848526C42149FD90402B996818A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an entity shall be—</text><subparagraph id="H804B1B0DDE014D70B1208804BBDAED20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A882569799445D7883CF3E178562DF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State Domestic Violence Coalition;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5E458E3D63945B692B9ECFCA618287C"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nonprofit entity, including a Tribal, culturally specific organization, or community-based organization, with a history of effective work in the fields of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence and substance use disorder treatment, prevention, and recovery support; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H067C992B71564DE681D1547F26AEAC11"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a local or State department (or other division) of health (including mental health, behavioral health, or substance abuse agencies), a State Domestic Violence Coalition or victim service provider, or any other nonprofit, nongovernmental organization with a history of effective work in the fields of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence and substance use disorder treatment, prevention, and recovery support. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H84BFCF397F4A4065BA125D42E477315B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an eligible entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D69B65F2DCD44D3BDD2475B27B463F7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><subparagraph id="H41A5698311B04108B8DA633DABFDCFB4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity receiving a grant under this subsection shall, directly or through subgrants or contracts, develop and implement a program for ensuring access for victims of family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence to substance use disorder treatment that allows parents (or legal guardians) and their children, stepchildren, or other dependents to remain together throughout the course of treatment by carrying out one or more of the authorized activities described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D4A796108C44D6AB342476ACB71FED7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Authorized activities described</header><text>The authorized activities described in this subparagraph include the following: </text><clause id="H70A8586A9F794BF5AFDD31B5EB0EE583"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The provision of residential and nonresidential substance use disorder treatment services.</text></clause><clause id="HF94E07FC14094470BD11265E8818E9FE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Notwithstanding section 308(d)(1), the provision or expansion of transitional housing, temporary rental assistance, and other supportive housing stability services, including direct cash assistance.</text></clause><clause id="HBD603BDC5EF241D993764DF7F6CD8CC7" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The provision of services that—</text><subclause id="H953AC728A15840D28B62CA777C7974EC"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support victims of family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence while receiving substance use disorder treatment services, including recovery and harm reduction; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA1124E79F9DD41CC855D3536C5A3F445"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enable parents (or legal guardians) and their children, stepchildren, or other dependents to remain together throughout the course of treatment, including—</text><item id="H6B36553C469E4CE0A9D14EB203DD96E0" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>supportive services, including advocacy, case management, and information and referral services;</text></item><item id="HF0F0E513792647DEA61D3C969D8B5A2F" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">health care services, including prenatal wellness services, and support services for pregnant and postpartum victims; and</text></item><item id="HF59D5382B6DC402DB58D59E91A5E30AC" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>services for children and youth that are exposed to family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence, including age-appropriate confidential counseling and supportive services.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="HAA1BFDD4BDC24C899B49C82BCA3FBD3C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The cultivation of partnerships between State, local, and Tribal policymakers in order to develop and implement service and policy changes for victims of family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence with substance use disorders that ensure the safety of victims, and reduce barriers for victims disproportionately affected by family violence.</text></clause><clause id="HA848A07D8A6347E6A34B48CAA422B5C8"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provision of training for staff associated with delivering services to ensure that each program developed using a grant received under this subsection includes procedures that protect the safety, privacy, and confidentiality of parents (or legal guardians) and their children, stepchildren, or other dependents in a manner consistent with subparagraph (F).</text></clause><clause id="HCB4BB39E2A2442AE98AFF98D2E465567"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Such other activities as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF622827AF4F649B9B885007EC8D469B4" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Advance notice of information disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the release of information is compelled by statutory or court mandate, an eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall—</text><clause id="H485EC896A15549B18C2BAD123AE7A643"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide advance notice to victims affected by the release of such information about the circumstances compelling the release of such information, such as mandatory reporting laws; and</text></clause><clause id="HFACE0615F65A4B809F0F599A91AD8D05"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>give victims the option to receive information and referrals without affirmatively disclosing abuse.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD3499E2B72741E9883894E4B2AE5EBB"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Administration and technical assistance</header><text>Each eligible entity that receives a grant under this subsection may use—</text><clause id="H56A45C3F64134FA38A06974CCCDE2FAE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">up to 6 percent of the grant amount to procure technical assistance, including technical assistance provided by the National Capacity Building Center to Prevent Substance Use Coercion established under subsection (b); and</text></clause><clause id="HB38637700B9548A799629A302BC382C5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>up to 5 percent of the grant amount for evaluation, monitoring, staff training, and other administrative costs under this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAD55117BA144CA9A8C193D60E1C49A2"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Reports and evaluations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this subsection shall submit to the Secretary at such time as shall be reasonably required by the Secretary, a report that—</text><clause id="H7C92BD05332443569DFAA248B0B0A47D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>describes the activities that have been carried out with such grant funds;</text></clause><clause id="HC24C10E0F70B46A88250ACEF183E7306"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes an evaluation of the effectiveness of such activities; and</text></clause><clause id="H6F19BCA876D249D1A9F476640C1D1256"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>provides such additional information as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBA1A9DFA7534D3C85D67A3B2C154F73" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Privacy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this subsection shall ensure that each program developed or implemented with such grant protects victim privacy, confidentiality, and safety in compliance with applicable confidentiality, privacy, and nondisclosure requirements of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5842DF4C601440A3BC2AF7837C2383B1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National Capacity Building Center to Prevent Substance Use Coercion</header><paragraph id="HF3520117742C4382A9A67D42FF6F960E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the sums appropriated under section 303(e) and available to carry out this subsection for any fiscal year, the Secretary may award a grant to an eligible entity for the establishment and maintenance of a National Capacity Building Center to Prevent Substance Use Coercion that will undertake the activities described in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD0A7F0F4C214190B314659C9F8EFFC7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an eligible entity—</text><subparagraph id="HEE9B2B0C31BE4510B8969EC6592523DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be a nonprofit private organization that focuses primarily on domestic violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0948C19F9986443D9B0048E96E319F06"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall provide documentation to the Secretary demonstrating experience working directly on issues of domestic violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1E2F4F2D5014D06B3BE6A079CFAD041"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall provide documentation to the Secretary demonstrating experience working directly on the intersection of domestic violence, substance use, and substance use coercion;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83E281AFBB7E494BB416B22DDEEB7BD4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall—</text><clause id="HE8B98C40C19C428386C4F805DFF66E3C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>include on the entity’s advisory board representatives who are from domestic violence service programs and who are geographically and culturally diverse; or</text></clause><clause id="H933CD480B4CF4A20936DEB4B42C1FD62"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">procure equivalent involvement of, and feedback from, individuals who have such qualifications, if the entity does not have an advisory board; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE1272594CC642259727CE1CB2C7EAC1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>shall demonstrate the strong support of domestic violence service programs from across the Nation for the entity’s demonstrated history in providing training and technical assistance on the intersection of domestic violence, substance misuse, and substance use coercion. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CA5DEC1BD0A40F184998F560F6D0A4C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Required uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The eligible entity awarded a grant under this subsection, through the National Capacity Building Center to Prevent Substance Use Coercion, shall use the grant—</text><subparagraph id="H9C2CEFC60FC140CABDB3A9523F6029C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to provide training and technical assistance to entities receiving grants under subsection (a) in the implementation of programs funded under such subsection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0ECB1FF4A597490D8FE7EBA47F4B02CF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to conduct evaluations of programs funded under subsection (a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7C42DB193BC4BBFAE75B2CDD9D9A0F8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to identify and disseminate best practices that emerge from programs funded under subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFDC610A092F443EAD02F80D6CC2E59C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to carry out such other activities as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3B8E4DA227F048838CC721A4FCF45165"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Federal administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the sums appropriated under section 303(e) for any fiscal year, not more than $4,000,000 for such fiscal year may be used by the Secretary for evaluation, monitoring, and other administrative expenses.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7F5A90A3FEF849D892F53CD0D1F58465"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB8097CFC76894C9B8EDD6F53C8F25885"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Substance use coercion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>substance use coercion</term> means any act, threatened act, or pattern of acts of physical or sexual violence, or any other form of abuse involving substance misuse through the use of force, threat, or coercion, that results in, or exacerbates, a substance use disorder, a substance-induced mental disorder, or any other form of substance dependance, directed against—</text><subparagraph id="H4F931D9440A143F6B13DFBD2AF4BF46D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a dating partner or other person similarly situated to a dating partner under the laws of the jurisdiction where such an act occurs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30610B8430644ED09CF7400BECDDD38A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a person who is cohabitating with or has cohabitated with the person committing such an act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5DE99E9105E2474794ECEA206022482E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a current or former spouse or other person similarly situated to a current or former spouse under the laws of the jurisdiction where such an act occurs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68EBC9FB94C34E8F85F78AD961017162"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a person who shares a child, stepchild, or other dependent in common with the person committing such an act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA32498FAFFA3445BB869249EBC6845CB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a person who is related by marriage, blood, or is otherwise legally related; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AC4FA0D8ECD4DE7A32BC5E7F29E22F1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other person who is protected from any such act under the domestic or family violence laws, policies, or regulations of the jurisdiction where the act occurs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9B7220910C843C2AB5DED2001410C93"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Victim</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>victim</term> means an individual against whom an act of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence is carried out.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H2D7557C800BE47E6AB299F37CB308E02"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>Section 303 of the Family Violence Prevention and Services Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10403">42 U.S.C. 10403</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HAE98097D369B451DAC70626823CB25F6" style="OLC"><subsection id="HAF7517D2C76F4DEB977400AEBE3F1E1E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Safe recovery together grants</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out section 315 $30,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

