<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H07070FD4602049ADB68116F5ED9154FE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 6303 IH: Strengthening American Nuclear Competitiveness Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6303</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231108">November 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To assess and improve the competitiveness of United States nuclear commerce, to expedite Department of Energy review of certain nuclear technology exports, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H65E69520D05446E7B85A50F766465C13" style="OLC"><section id="H6A3DA98D51AE499B9D101C87E587F727" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strengthening American Nuclear Competitiveness Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8609197B39194CB7BC2329AA682A3D7A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Competitiveness of nuclear commerce</header><subsection id="HB6872F0784E149AEAC242DE9C7C97CBF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy shall develop and submit to Congress a report on United States nuclear commerce.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE75617D6ED5A48FA8F967519013506FC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing the report required under subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy shall consult with—</text><paragraph id="H3C2531BD569C4D22AD9962CDE70A2EE0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of State;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35B54E364376420CBD7793D1C2E57764"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of Commerce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17BCAE16EB394189BA13F17F41825CC1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F15FB5E96424C44976462811CE7DFBB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Nuclear Regulatory Commission;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB25CC479DE21452FA5FD436A3FFEF1E5" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any other Federal agency or office the Secretary of Energy determines appropriate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE7F2E7F705C469D8BF61CF2D0BB8610" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the nuclear energy industry;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H991D74D3FC624C4DAA4F82298DE7A0F7" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>nongovernmental nuclear policy organizations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3C7F3062C0D482AA78173BDDDC17C32" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>other public stakeholders, as the Secretary of Energy determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF04B7A105CCC4377BC144BA8754F21A0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="HF38AB927874448CABD618EC20FAA13DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an assessment of—</text><subparagraph id="H99C9F14F9BB54FE1AD3863E11AA59374"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">legal and regulatory requirements and policies of, and commercial practices in, the United States with respect to the nuclear industry of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF360FF80691348089D30400DAD5E7C50"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the effects of such practices on such nuclear industry in domestic and foreign commerce; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31D705A1BDF74127A408D5C012FE61BF" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the role of emerging United States nuclear technologies and applications of such technologies, including nonelectric applications of those technologies, in domestic and foreign commerce; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDCF7CF7AA30A44DBBA8AC440C4DFC4EA" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effects of advanced manufacturing and construction methods for nuclear technologies on—</text><clause id="H4F0E093F99DF4AB2B49EA7A9FA67CC59"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the costs for deployment of such technologies; and</text></clause><clause id="H38B3B9C3B37D482D810AB8A68D3636E3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the competitiveness of the nuclear industry of the United States;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E36A575C7054892B72DB11D5D7513C5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a comparison of the matters assessed in paragraph (1) with respect to the United States to an assessment of such matters as they apply with respect to foreign countries, including Canada, the United Kingdom, France, Japan, the Republic of Korea, China, and the Russian Federation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D820506CCFE4FAF913AD1F8C23E66AD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommendations to improve the competitiveness of United States nuclear commerce; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE704B2937A1B4A4B96ECAE90835EB519" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommendations relating to the applicability of section 170 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2210">42 U.S.C. 2210</external-xref>) with respect to advanced nuclear technologies.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H639ED66495A44C86AB04CA916D3343D2" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Process for review and amendment of part 810 generally authorized destinations</header><subsection id="H8DEDD38BF4B34629BE90AF8C2C2266CA" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Identification and evaluation of factors</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall identify and evaluate factors, other than agreements for cooperation entered into in accordance with section 123 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2153">42 U.S.C. 2153</external-xref>), that may be used to determine a country’s generally authorized destination status under part 810 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations, and to list such country as a generally authorized destination in Appendix A to part 810 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations. </text></subsection><subsection id="H0713B5D2BF0F4F6092AED58BE1CCCE6E" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Process update</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy shall review and, as appropriate, update the Department of Energy’s process for determining a country’s generally authorized destination status under part 810 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations, and for listing such country as a generally authorized destination in Appendix A to part 810 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations, taking into consideration, and, as appropriate, incorporating factors identified and evaluated under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H2A70F8125E5A47E6864BB97577EFD49C" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Revisions to list</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, and at least once every 5 years thereafter, the Secretary of Energy shall, in accordance with any process updated pursuant to this section, review the list in Appendix A to part 810 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations, and amend such list as appropriate. </text></subsection></section><section id="H760D27DE9AB14DB2896415F2BF9F1869" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Licensing domestic nuclear projects in which United States allies invest</header><subsection id="HF8E1CCFAACB8425CA26C00C402AC277B" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The prohibitions against issuing certain licenses for utilization facilities to certain aliens, corporations, and other entities described in the second sentence of section 103 d. of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2133">42 U.S.C. 2133(d)</external-xref>) and the second sentence of section 104 d. of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2134">42 U.S.C. 2134(d)</external-xref>) shall not apply to an entity described in subsection (b) of this section if the Nuclear Regulatory Commission determines that issuance of the applicable license to that entity is not inimical to—</text><paragraph id="H632E9A9AD7704E4BB70A552349A6E17C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the common defense and security; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD404DDCB3E584DF681DC9BA4E107DB74" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the health and safety of the public.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0492CA7BEF5F401E8912301AA49E06EC" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Entities described</header><paragraph id="HBB3CCFE8C19B46EFBD4468C1C2C3A3F1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity referred to in subsection (a) is an alien, corporation, or other entity that is owned, controlled, or dominated by—</text><subparagraph id="HD38572D16F5A499A889CFD98E9A12D17" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the government of—</text><clause id="HA3F42D4E15C44B16A79A9984AD16475A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a country, other than a country described in paragraph (2), that is a member of the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development on the date of enactment of this Act; or</text></clause><clause id="H935E1CD1C6074A9996E7A138AE4CDAB1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Republic of India;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23FBBF7A56F14F9C9ECC024A755CF1FB" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a corporation that is incorporated in a country described in clause (i) or (ii) of subparagraph (A); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49D24D92AD834384B9444918AC12354B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an alien who is a citizen or national of a country described in clause (i) or (ii) of subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H71AA6BAE58074C569B8DA95185468F17" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A country described in this paragraph is a country—</text><subparagraph id="HCCB9DF508BBB444E9204B3D77AC5C526" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any department, agency, or instrumentality of the government of which, on the date of enactment of this Act, is subject to sanctions under section 231 of the Countering America’s Adversaries Through Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9525">22 U.S.C. 9525</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C53C9085F674A36847C76929026F397" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any citizen, national, or entity of which, as of the date of enactment of this Act, is included on the List of Specially Designated Nationals and Blocked Persons maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury pursuant to sanctions imposed under section 231 of the Countering America’s Adversaries Through Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9525">22 U.S.C. 9525</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A6FF5AC8876410793E491E6EC531F18" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text>Section 103 d. of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2133">42 U.S.C. 2133(d)</external-xref>) is amended, in the second sentence, by striking <quote>any any</quote> and inserting <quote>any</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H749EA0C828704D858296A347507AD698" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text>Nothing in this section affects the requirements of section 721 of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4565">50 U.S.C. 4565</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="HB7CF46A7BF9849EBB570ECADD586A8C6"><enum>5.</enum><header>Licensing considerations relating to use of nuclear energy for nonelectric applications</header><subsection id="H927432B369994E7E83DB712446608AB8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission (in this section referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>) shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report addressing any unique licensing issues or requirements relating to—</text><paragraph id="HBA10F1D1ACA6482EBBDFB91BC4ADC01C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the flexible operation of advanced nuclear reactors, such as ramping power output and switching between electricity generation and nonelectric applications;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8890F8F1DC91452587CF64C22BD994A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the use of advanced nuclear reactors exclusively for nonelectric applications; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H516AA852F7FF414EB1F1A45BE83B9D32"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the collocation of advanced nuclear reactors with industrial plants or other facilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD68E1F2E51B543CEA3AF13BB42982B4A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Stakeholder input</header><text>In developing the report under subsection (a), the Commission shall seek input from—</text><paragraph id="H65E15B904C9F4757BB1DC3F42B072741"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3B07DD7C2274CDFA457D3E5FFBB9E45"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the nuclear energy industry;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4B26072EF1241A787DDF8262B4ECB3C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>technology developers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E489C7BDE604D45901BF50CD935D9AD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the industrial, chemical, and medical sectors;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FB31A01040945D7A7F6D89B61486B21"><enum>(5)</enum><text>nongovernmental organizations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86F9FD6D0C3A4FE785341222DE3F969C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>other public stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC5A5E7D70BE74A51A521FA16972CC175"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall describe—</text><paragraph id="H2C8D8EBDEBD14DC19B7DA738E88C43B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any unique licensing issues or requirements relating to the matters described in paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a), including, with respect to the nonelectric applications referred to in paragraphs (1) and (2) of that subsection, any licensing issues or requirements relating to the use of nuclear energy—</text><subparagraph id="H22AF7F3DA9074504AAC953F817406596"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for hydrogen or other liquid and gaseous fuel or chemical production;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8CF27BEED7A4C7BBE07CBDE01B60EA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for water desalination and wastewater treatment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8619EE9D3FC1441490BB3843AEE3B85F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for heat used in industrial processes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00C1E66D50C84CEEAA64AE50528262E2"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for district heating;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7EAB408A83B4CEB8C9CD0283000425D" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in relation to energy storage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DCCF30D8F26497A88826FE2BEC013AC"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for industrial or medical isotope production; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBFCAB64C6F0464AB3E4883472F68976"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other applications, as identified by the Commission;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8DB4CFA9C1C4A89BC87692C3B5D3975"><enum>(2)</enum><text>options for addressing such issues or requirements—</text><subparagraph id="H49B6DC82456F408E8882E20198EBCB06"><enum>(A)</enum><text>within the existing regulatory framework;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EAD98F43A8D444F8A8702E493BA545E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through the technology-inclusive, regulatory framework to be established under section 103(a)(4) of the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2133">42 U.S.C. 2133</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/439">Public Law 115–439</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F7545EB6B1241E9BE1572BA112C4E8B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>through a new rulemaking;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HABEA651965FC43EE8A218D6892211BA4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the extent to which Commission action is needed to implement any matter described in the report; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07218132C52342259380664AAA9B2725"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cost estimates, proposed budgets, and proposed timeframes for implementing risk-informed and performance-based regulatory guidance for licensing advanced nuclear reactors for nonelectric applications.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H90177358D8214483BDD7B674C0F1D3EB"><enum>6.</enum><header>Report on advanced methods of manufacturing and construction for nuclear energy projects</header><subsection id="H79E31EFA1DE74230A9C73CCACFDD5C23"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission (in this section referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>) shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report on advanced methods of manufacturing and construction for nuclear energy projects.</text></subsection><subsection id="H742051F14A4A415EB8D0BB1548E84F0A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Stakeholder input</header><text>In developing the report under subsection (a), the Commission shall seek input from—</text><paragraph id="HCBA4FF8E10C24C9290F9081497D229F4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3355E5226F6477FA4FECCB24D823341"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the nuclear energy industry;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AA3F0121AC44B1983B5A27A0AE0FCA3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the National Laboratories;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2221A8FB5F147BF974D67916AACB796"><enum>(4)</enum><text>institutions of higher education;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23A4CEE9A95540E49DD65BCBB409807B" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>nuclear and manufacturing technology developers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H443FEE964E23475D8848BF43D99A5086"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the manufacturing and construction industries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A211C80275A424C937CEF3347D25771"><enum>(7)</enum><text>standards development organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H747B178B2F764B4085580586D7671BAD"><enum>(8)</enum><text>labor unions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB9A4241EB8E4B01ADB4EDD7A82AD6CC"><enum>(9)</enum><text>nongovernmental organizations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0DB6D9F428443BFABC9B5C559A1A2F4"><enum>(10)</enum><text>other public stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEAF1D8A9F4CD4E35831735BD4DE67381" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contents</header><paragraph id="H00506DE7AEA34A3288D071A757F86AB5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall—</text><subparagraph id="HB0E42B5DA3DE47A49B3AD78355456EC7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>examine any unique licensing issues or requirements relating to the use, for nuclear energy projects, of—</text><clause id="H97927B9C80A14E688C6C1719F74E90A8" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>advanced manufacturing techniques; and</text></clause><clause id="H75AC64202280489E870FD2CE7195CB3A" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>advanced construction techniques;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24B5CB200B22437F93A40BD091FF343E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>examine—</text><clause id="HAB332F1964F04520814EB41B33A8471D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the requirements for nuclear-grade components in manufacturing and construction for nuclear energy projects;</text></clause><clause id="HE1739B332DB145B6BA0098543DE4FF24" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>opportunities to use standard materials, parts, or components in manufacturing and construction for nuclear energy applications; and</text></clause><clause id="H1ECD2F306B824A7FA2FB247F75A68F3E" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>opportunities to use standard materials that are in compliance with existing codes and standards to provide acceptable approaches to support or encapsulate new materials that do not yet have applicable codes or standards; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E3E4BBB5CBB4E7288F66365914426A7" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identify safety aspects of advanced manufacturing processes and advanced construction techniques that are not addressed by existing codes and standards, so that generic guidance for nuclear energy projects may be updated or created as necessary by the Commission; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF01BC908B644BD4BD526914C315B63A" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>identify options for addressing the issues, requirements, and opportunities examined under subparagraphs (A) and (B)—</text><clause id="H6B5235B1EEBB44B3BC85306715CE0725" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>within the existing regulatory framework; or</text></clause><clause id="H08DB3139CF2B4B05BA7AFBE5EA863568" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>through a new rulemaking; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C56A675A65846D3B7F98EB0AD11AC65" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>describe the extent to which Commission action is needed to implement any matter described in the report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7123D8B9F73141C3A278D207F73F2DFE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cost estimates, budgets, and timeframes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report under subsection (a) shall include cost estimates, proposed budgets, and proposed timeframes for implementing risk-informed and performance-based regulatory guidance for advanced manufacturing and construction for nuclear energy projects.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H71C690B58A0A4D2D8B958F3BF704F061"><enum>7.</enum><header>Extension of the Price-Anderson Act</header><subsection id="HC0FBA7BFF9424AF7B1F7B5C6926C2612"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Extension</header><text>Section 170 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2210">42 U.S.C. 2210</external-xref>) (commonly known as the <quote>Price-Anderson Act</quote>) is amended by striking <quote>December 31, 2025</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>December 31, 2065</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H046C6E0D1BAF40F996DAF7495E09789F" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Liability</header><text>Section 170 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2210">42 U.S.C. 2210</external-xref>) (commonly known as the <quote>Price-Anderson Act</quote>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H52901CBB22CE46D9A4DB2C32B97607FD" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection d. (5), by striking <quote>$500,000,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$2,000,000,000</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6C05B214D5B4BB68CEBE5AA562A2E6C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection e. (4), by striking <quote>$500,000,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$2,000,000,000</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAB471F2A9F754E928947A20A44B43FC4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Section 170 p. of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2210">42 U.S.C. 2210(p)</external-xref>) (commonly known as the <quote>Price-Anderson Act</quote>) is amended by striking <quote>December 31, 2021</quote> and inserting <quote>December 31, 2061</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCDFD67CD52FF421B8A8999A7A872B4C6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition of nuclear incident</header><text>Section 11 q. of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2014">42 U.S.C. 2014(q)</external-xref>) is amended, in the second proviso, by striking <quote>if such occurrence</quote> and all that follows through <quote>United States:</quote> and inserting a colon.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6BDA3B7702904C22A8F82C1D63235E21"><enum>8.</enum><header>Risk pooling program assessment</header><subsection id="H7F3C444EC2EB49CDAA78ADE85248A5D5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall carry out a review of, and submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report on, the Secretary of Energy’s actions with respect to the program described in section 934(e) of the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/17373">42 U.S.C. 17373(e)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HF89C04129146461DBD65DFBD660798E9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report described in subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="H9D629764BCBD469BB2A8A393D550BCAC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an evaluation of the Secretary of Energy’s actions to determine the risk-informed assessment formula under section 934(e)(2)(C) of the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/17373">42 U.S.C. 17373(e)(2)(C)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB69BB8EA296149C4A06066A8BA4C48B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a review of the Secretary of Energy’s methodology to collect information to determine and implement the formula.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

