<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA2E0B86C2AB643EFBA25F27E5E6ECFC8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 854 IH: Captain James C. Edge Gold Star Spouse Equity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 854</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230206">February 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend titles 10 and 38, United States Code, to expand certain benefits for surviving spouses of members of the Armed Forces who die in line of duty, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFF7D6A7BAB7040E3AA99C08173C01CB5" style="OLC"><section id="HBB3B8795B32745E4B367CC21DA31F409" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Captain James C. Edge Gold Star Spouse Equity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H69C337D1419A4ECD9D97849761FFCC1B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Continued eligibility for Survivor Benefit Plan for certain surviving spouses who remarry</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1450(b)(2) of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H5FCFF88D7DCA404C9C7ABA5091C39A3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>An annuity</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="USC"><enum-in-header>(A)</enum-in-header></header-in-text> Subject to subparagraph (B), an annuity</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DF18EE5468A41BBAC6983EE25D4681C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5FA04EA147D04471841C95CC282758DD" style="USC"><subparagraph id="HEE1642F733A64AC69EB3F8AE983DCF6F" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not terminate payment of an annuity for a surviving spouse described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of section 1448(d)(1) solely because that surviving spouse remarries. In the case of a surviving spouse who remarried before reaching age 55 and before the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Captain James C. Edge Gold Star Spouse Equity Act</short-title>, the Secretary shall resume payment of the annuity to that surviving spouse for each month after the date of the enactment of that Act.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H3B392BD3FD1945EF934973CB40496D0E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Continued eligibility for dependency and indemnity compensation for surviving spouses who remarry</header><subsection id="HCD316463D1AE482ABDD5E675BECFF28C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 103(d) of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4777E84D69EE4A71AE14ECC9B59CCE66"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2)(B), by adding at the end the following: <quote>The remarriage of a surviving spouse shall not bar the furnishing of benefits under section 1311 of this title to the surviving spouse of a veteran.</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A735EB3077849AFA61F9DE012B65DEC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking subparagraph (A) and renumbering subparagraphs (B) through (E) as subparagraphs (A) through (D), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA6423A7302094A4B8BCA6E8C45D0BA86"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Resumption of payments to certain individuals previously denied dependency and indemnity compensation</header><text>Beginning on the first day of the first month after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall resume payment of dependency and indemnity compensation under section 1311 of such title to each living individual who—</text><paragraph id="H1CA93F5F89CC49678A95E3493351BC4C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is the surviving spouse of a veteran; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H82165772FBD447ACA6815E4922583E24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>remarried before—</text><subparagraph id="HFEEA24E3185D4816A3463A123F90C0E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reaching age 57; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H200CC3143BB440858A694CE5612846D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

