<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H76B4CF72C11546B98013EBDB786955C5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1438 IH: Think Tank Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1438</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230308">March 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require certain nonprofit and not-for-profit social welfare organizations to submit disclosure reports on foreign funding to the Attorney General; and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H51C8975F55EE4272BB1EF3F154BB0CAF" style="OLC"><section id="HA85142BBA95C4C81B34D18A3FE0A1E23" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Think Tank Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC225E6D1FCCE4C1BA5D49872C569F49D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HC9A9981F48414F2A8EA177D52C09FD35"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Think tanks have provided Congress and the Administration with a wealth of research and scholarship that largely has benefitted the American public by improving the drafting, enactment, and enforcement of U.S. policy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F7D0996142248B4B10D86FFC21A3009"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is broad bipartisan agreement that think tanks possess enormous influence on the passage and enforcement of policies, particularly those that relate to foreign policy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD63A45E273BC4D8B94FEE3EF280A6039"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In recent years, foreign funding of think tanks has increased substantially.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4B80CC30E574C9BA1D3C10530B75E2E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress, the Administration, and especially the American people have a right to know which think tanks receive foreign funds and to assess for themselves the extent that foreign influence should be considered when analyzing the credibility and value of research and scholarship produced by such organizations that receive foreign funds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA672C7B890E4F54855A0DF87AC70ACC"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The House has already recognized the national security issues inherent in undue foreign influence of entities with covert sources of foreign funding who testify before Congress. Since 2015, individuals who testify before the U.S. House of Representatives have been required to disclose relevant foreign funding sources directed to them or their employers in Truth in Testimony disclosure forms. (The original looser requirement was enacted in 1997).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4670AAA45B94222A24D94AA8EE01E22"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Over 30 years ago, Congress enacted section 117 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (HEA) in light of concerns about the growing financial relationship between U.S. universities and foreign sources. Congress balanced academic freedom and national security by mandating financial transparency through required reporting of contracts with and gifts from a foreign source.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B8B2E835A144E91BEECF9DFFAEFD7E6"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 117 does not prohibit institutions from taking foreign money; it mandates accurate and transparent disclosures of sources and amounts to the Department of Education. In 2019, the Department took concrete steps to enforce section 117 by ensuring the integrity of reporting requirements, confirming the correct reporting and categorization of donations, and prohibiting the use of domestic conduits and intermediaries to avoid the disclosures of foreign gifts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H285ABF8739C8463B8E68443A02C7DD3F"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Between 2011 and 2021, Russia has given at least $160 million to U.S. universities. China alone has given at least $2.7 billion during the same time frame. And during that span, the State of Qatar has given at least $5 billion to U.S. universities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19CF8B24035742BA9EC9A835BDF66A99"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each of these nations has a repressive and deeply troubling record on human rights, and all three have engaged in cyber espionage targeting Americans.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC438A5F4D3D5469B82E7BD5C8E9439FF"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Russia, China, and Qatar all pose grave threats to U.S. national security interests, yet they have successfully lavished billions of dollars to cultivate strong ties with institutions of higher education and research across the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3260C644F5C41588D80EF43D2E0558B"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is also evidence suggesting that Qatar encouraged and potentially facilitated U.S. universities receiving its largess to flout U.S. disclosure requirements under section 117 of the Higher Education Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H895932B604094E9FA0F47E8435498CBC"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Although the Center for International Policy conducted a study in 2020 that concluded that think tanks focused on Federal policy received at least $174 million in funding from foreign governmental entities between 2014 and 2018, there is currently no means to determine the actual level or extent of foreign influence on such think tanks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6FB77FCB0FC46758AA3A78014CE810C"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While the exact amount of foreign funding that U.S. based think tanks receive is unknown, it is clear that the foreign sources would not provide that level of funding unless it impacted think tanks' policy recommendations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8065A0FB31DB4EE58A16DE58C5AB7A08"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One prominent think tank, the East West Institute, received substantial funding from China’s People’s Liberation Army, which conducts cyber espionage attacks, including against Americans. After the East West Institute was dissolved in 2021, the Stimson Center took over several of the think tank's key programs involving China.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC40E64CA2554C4595510FD9BAF42058"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Stimson Center worked to significantly alter the Homeland and Cyber Threat Act (H.R. 1607, introduced into the 117th Congress on March 8, 2021). The HACT Act, which would provide an exception to the Foreign Sovereign Immunities Act of 1976 (FSIA) to allow U.S. persons harmed by foreign-government sponsored cyberattacks to bring civil claims for damages, passed in the last Congress with broad bipartisan support. The changes advocated by the Stimson Center would gut the bill and render it completely ineffective in holding foreign nations and their agents responsible for cyberattacks on and in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3D6A9FE2F8B4F8C8E371A0839BC2457"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One of the main sources of the Stimson Center’s funding is the State of Qatar, a major sponsor of terrorism worldwide and one of the most notorious sponsors of cyberattacks against U.S. entities. In 2019 alone, the Stimson Center took over $600,000 in contributions from the Government of Qatar.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D4DF1F5BAF847A192E285EC6BD981DA"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Brookings Institution has received at least $22 million from the State of Qatar from 2013 through 2021, but the exact amount has not been disclosed publicly.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC33B116291B4D189D949C4EB2473438"><enum>(18)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is also significant concern in Congress about potential contractual stipulations tied to foreign funding that could be leveraged by foreign powers to exert even greater influence over the research and policy recommendations of think tanks that the Federal Government and the American public would otherwise believe to be independent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H578FC454468C4DEC9DF9384930DE23F6"><enum>(19)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a 2007 “Establishment Agreement” between the Brookings Institution and Qatar’s Ministry of Foreign Affairs—which appears to have been in place in its original form through the end of 2021—the Doha “branch” of the Brookings Institution, called Brookings Doha Center, was effectively owned and controlled by the Emir of Qatar. Under the terms of the contract, the Brookings Institution’s role in the Doha Center was limited to that of a “Promoter”.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04AE497D9B7E454ABEECEFC0FBA9FCD2"><enum>(20)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As only revealed publicly in June 2022, the Brookings Doha Center was a separate and distinct legal entity, specifically a Private Foundation for the Public Benefit, the same incorporation status as the State of Qatar’s propaganda arm, Al Jazeera.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FA40F3AD6264C32AF9B19EC089B931D"><enum>(21)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Pursuant to the 2007 Establishment Agreement, the Director of the Brookings Doha Center was required to report directly to Qatar’s Ministry of Foreign Affairs, including to “engage in regular consultation … regarding the development and ongoing operations” and for prior approval of “programs that will be developed by the [Brookings Doha] Center”.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H056C504E2D55478E9367EB438B46F654"><enum>(22)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Brookings Doha Center was renamed the Middle East Council on Global Affairs, and evidence indicates that it is now entirely under the control of the Qatari Government. According to a January 2022 “Amendment” to the 2007 Articles of Incorporation, the Brookings Institution ceded the “Promoter” role for Brookings Doha Center to a senior employee of Qatar’s Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Majed Al-Ansari. This Amendment also called on the Middle East Council to assume control of intellectual property rights that had been under the “Brookings” brand, including the content from and followers of the “@BrookingsDoha” Twitter account.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5CEB3036318B421E82C3A32FFCDDCAF3"><enum>(23)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress currently is unable to determine what other agreements that the Brookings Institution or other influential think tanks have with foreign governmental entities, a void which has already been exploited by at least the State of Qatar in obtaining prior approval of budgets and research projects conducted under the branding of the Brookings Institution and the Brookings Doha Center in the aforementioned 2007 contract, or the transference of valuable intellectual property to the Qatari Government pursuant to the 2022 amendment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAF12138EE9643A18DBB283075E562E3"><enum>(24)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is broad bipartisan agreement that undue foreign influence obscured through the use of proxies—or hidden by the powerful brand of a highly respected think tank—threatens the national security interests of the United States. There is also broad agreement that transparency is the most important and effective tool for reducing the harm of foreign influence targeting U.S. public policy or public opinion.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC63887AEE3054635A3D01FFF5E1676EA"><enum>(25)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As such, this bill aims to provide critical transparency regarding the foreign funding provided to and the related contractual agreements with think tanks whose work includes influencing U.S. policies or public opinion.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HCC6F961F616C4F5BBF5A80713B14066D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Contemporaneous disclosure reports</header><subsection id="H402140C417B64EA68B98EB84E8202A0F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reporting conditions</header><paragraph id="H649493BB99A24CAF913527E19E891C67"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Gifts, donations, or contributions</header><subparagraph id="H5BEA2679CFDB43848EFBED02D5ACB38D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in section 6, a covered entity that receives a gift, donation, or contribution from a foreign principal during a calendar year in an aggregate amount of $10,000 or greater shall file a disclosure report with the Attorney General in accordance with subsection (b) not later than 90 days after each disclosure date.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3D89A2AA5C444D1480DE02EBCEEC15D3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Disclosure date defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>disclosure date</term> means—</text><clause id="HFC7C3FFA6A8B49C6B98ECD67A7061C3E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the first date during any calendar year by which a covered entity has received a gift, donation, or contribution from a foreign principal in an aggregate amount of $10,000 or greater; and</text></clause><clause id="H5E4CEE86B5AD4367ADA7465F6996A759"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other date during such calendar year by which a covered entity has received a gift, donation, or contribution from a foreign principal in an aggregate amount of $10,000 or greater since the most recent disclosure date for such calendar year.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H45B5B51566C44DB1BFF0AD88429606ED"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contract, memorandum of understanding, or agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in section 6, a covered entity that enters into or modifies a contract, memorandum of understanding, or agreement with a foreign principal shall file a disclosure report with the Attorney General in accordance with subsection (b) within 90 days of the formation or modification of such contract, memorandum, or agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H32B7619E6BCC4DB29E178012902D59A1" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of contemporaneous disclosure report</header><paragraph id="H158658A831A3456A81D6DFDA2057C05F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Gifts, donations, or contributions only</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under subsection (a)(1) shall detail the following:</text><subparagraph id="HD3B750A9BCAA437F838613BFAB8121FB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The identities of the foreign principal and the primary point of contact of the foreign principal for engaging with the covered entity, including the name and title of such point of contact.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37593394E57C4F6CA78D47DF904A2EA1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The date on which the foreign principal provided a gift, donation, or contribution to the covered entity.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74164D9EDE624B4E9CAA062859506B4B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The aggregate dollar amount of such gift, donation, or contribution attributable to a particular foreign principal.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1101B1AB2854ADEA3BD3B2F3ACE00C1" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of any conditions or restrictions regarding any of the disclosed gifts, donations, or contributions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD667E0FD53454D6F8FBBACFCAEDD38D7" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The aggregate amount of such gifts, donations, or contributions received from each foreign principal.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H332E84CFB7054876B42D3B549805A8C8" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A description of any decisions made because of the foreign principal to the structure of the organization or to the research, programs, or content intended to be or actually published, disseminated, or promoted by the covered entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H46A1F95F2914483E906F93743A5EB2BC" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contract, memorandum of understanding, or agreement only</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under subsection (a)(2) shall detail the following:</text><subparagraph id="HBE6ADBE9D4C84FFF91619EA586C4BEAB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The identities of the foreign principal and the primary point of contact of the foreign principal for engaging with the covered entity, including the name and title of such point of contact.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF84E4FFA89184DE69A258F271F3263DD" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The date on which the covered entity entered into or modified a contract, memorandum of understanding, or agreement with a foreign principal.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DABC253C97D44658D0A82EF8840BDBE" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Copies of all written contracts, agreements, or memoranda of understanding the covered entity entered into or modified with any foreign principal.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1FAE4D791D24C3B8DB5ECCBAB3E9324" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Copies of all internal and external documents, research materials and publications produced as a result of the contract, memorandum of understanding, or agreement.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC95DE8E990C42C5B2EEA71B6A690F0C" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of any decisions made because of the foreign principal to the structure of the organization or to the research, programs, or content intended to be or actually published, disseminated, or promoted by the covered entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2760E6A62A6B40C083BD4561D55D8612" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Initial disclosure reports</header><subsection id="H6E3D84E895D643148CB79F8AEBACF8FE" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered entity shall file an initial disclosure report, in accordance with subsections (b) or (c), with the Attorney General within 180 days of the date of enactment of this Act if, during the period beginning on January 1st of the most recent calendar year which ended before the date of enactment of this Act and ending on the effective date of this Act—</text><paragraph id="HBB7E97287D5440399E92C512B25E36A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such covered entity received a gift, donation, or contribution from a foreign principal in an aggregate amount of $10,000 or greater;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5436F4CE8544A9C818B47D1BBA98C91"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such covered entity entered into or modified a contract, memorandum of understanding, or agreement with a foreign principal; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BF19A4652464AAFB5BE135FEBD94D31" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such covered entity had previously entered into a contract, agreement or memorandum of understanding with a foreign principal that was still valid or enforceable on or after January 1 of the most recent calendar year which ended before the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDA525B2077A842ADA9E52D30BA11792B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prior gifts, donations, or contributions</header><text>The report required under subsection (a)(1) shall detail the following:</text><paragraph id="H362A9D4D940A4A828C110FFA8F133D75" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The name of the foreign principal.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1445D26E64C74E30BB0E21BA6837970C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The country of citizenship of the foreign principal.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B3690A164324FEBAB7DECCC43CEF35D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount and date of such gifts, donations, or contributions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5699321DCBF4A4E9095D9253631C7B9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The description of any conditions or restrictions attached to, or placed on, the gifts, donations, or contributions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2788F5B41D5841268894FF38B4227821" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of any decisions made because of the foreign principal to the structure of the organization or to the research, programs, or content intended to be or actually published, disseminated, or promoted by the covered entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H69009B67A9F24AA8A1B056BB1C2DB5AE" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Contract, memorandum of understanding, or agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under subsection (a)(2) shall detail the following:</text><paragraph id="H945E709D5E0046E1ACE6F14EF10ABE09" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The name of the foreign principal.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13E0DDE9132249868CF222C2C5B79B33"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The country of citizenship of the foreign principal.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6DBFD0153E44D64B89FF1A255875171" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Copies of each written contract, memorandum of understanding, or agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAAD7EF873766422D882D451830CCB1E3" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any modification of each such written contract, memorandum, or agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB0FCC4BDDE24EF692A80610D6620F1E" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The terms and conditions of each oral agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB4144F6B51B4661829A03A15DFC6E62" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any modification of each such oral agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42074E595B1046D480D3B82999D1E30D" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A comprehensive statement of—</text><subparagraph id="HA956BEDFA17E491CA0EE88FD21FF68BE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the nature and method of performance of each item described in paragraphs (3) through (6); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB67AB88A125A40AEBCD45708ABDAEFF7" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the actions taken by the covered entity at the request or suggestion of each such foreign principal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H27750844B6C84DA294A857643B7845DB" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A description of any decisions made because of the foreign principal to the structure of the organization or to the research, programs, or content intended to be or actually published, disseminated, or promoted by the covered entity.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC8BFFC0083E645C3A905B93385F46F9D" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>Briefings, testimony, or similar forms of presentation of research</header><subsection id="H416E92CAD97B4C0598929A0D05DEA8C4" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Labeling of written materials</header><text>If a covered entity provides a briefing, testimony, or similar form of presentation of research to a member or employee of Congress or an executive branch official, such covered entity shall identify prominently on any written materials the name of the relevant foreign principal and the country of citizenship, if the foreign principal is not a government, who provided funding for such briefing, testimony, or similar form of presentation of research.</text></subsection><subsection id="H118799C8422D4E96BC36CBE524E519A8" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Addendum to briefing, testimony, presentation</header><text>In the event that no written materials are provided, the covered entity shall convey the information required under subsection (a) in writing to the member or employee of Congress or executive branch official before or within 10 days after the briefing, testimony, or presentation.</text></subsection></section><section id="H34E7277582334A94B037EA202DBC050C"><enum>6.</enum><header>Relation to Other Reporting Requirements</header><subsection id="HA026C81D4E45446FA5018E8086C1ACD0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>State reports</header><paragraph id="HA217404C84584A3FA2EE6E228BEE8BA5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements of a covered entity</header><text>If a covered entity is within a State which has enacted requirements for public disclosure of gifts, donations, or contributions from or contracts or agreements with a foreign principal that are substantially similar to the requirements of this Act, a copy of the disclosure report filed with the State may be filed with the Attorney General in lieu of a report required under this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B72F0749D634CC7A4F6800A6A0EBFB4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements of the State</header><text>The State in which the covered entity is located shall provide to the Attorney General such assurances as the Attorney General may require to establish that the covered entity has met the requirements for public disclosure under State law if the State report is filed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3006D86709F646328BAD5C24EE438DCC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal reports</header><text>If a covered entity receives a gift, donation, or contribution from, or enters into a contract or agreement with, a foreign principal, if any other department, agency, or bureau of the executive branch requires a report containing requirements substantially similar to those required under this section, a copy of the report may be filed with the Attorney General in lieu of a report required under this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC23B54549A1347808532BFA46838B061"><enum>7.</enum><header>Administration and Enforcement</header><subsection id="H3F5B19943ADE4281A144ED5EB067BFBD" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Books and records</header><paragraph id="H7E40A1BBC9E04B12B1B52FD7329B38D3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Retention period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For a period of not less than 5 years, a covered entity shall retain the necessary materials required to comply with the requirements of this Act, including books of account, all communications with the foreign principal, and other records regarding its activities related to any contracts, memorandum of understandings, or agreements with or gifts, donations, or contributions from a foreign principal.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B44109CF0C9410F9C9926E42E0A83FC" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inspection</header><subparagraph id="H0B41F2241CD34F3783CC0DA2319E293B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Attorney General</header><text>Upon request of the Attorney General, each covered entity shall furnish to the Attorney General all information and records in its possession which the Attorney General may determine to be necessary to comply with the requirements under this Act.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01690E7EF7CD45C9AB4694FD7CE05B59" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon request of Congress or a committee of Congress, a covered entity shall furnish to Congress or the committee such information and records as Congress or the committee may request to determine the extent to which the covered entity is in compliance with the requirements of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0970BC3E8D443CCA60B35682205A74C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Any information or records furnished pursuant to paragraph (2)(A) shall be made available in the database required under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4338301104D4EC79B8BE6369B604366" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>It shall be unlawful for any person willfully to conceal, destroy, obliterate, mutilate, or falsify, or to attempt to conceal, destroy, obliterate, mutilate, or falsify, or to cause to be concealed, destroyed, obliterated, mutilated, or falsified, any books or records required to be kept under the provisions of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H45B1C738182C479C88F77BC9213BFC1F" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All disclosure reports required by this Act shall be made available to the public through a database maintained on the official website of the Department of Justice.</text></subsection><subsection id="H923CC4ACBF34478F9ABD468AC9AC6F9F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Civil monetary penalty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any covered entity that fails to comply with the requirements of this Act, including any rule or regulation promulgated thereunder, shall be subject, in addition to any other penalties that may be prescribed by law, to a civil money penalty of no less than $1,000 for each day of the failure described by this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA69C432F8F5A411BBD6C414958D9115D" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Civil action</header><paragraph id="H0CDAC0AC5F6547AC8E5E23AB5DC5023C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Court orders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever it appears that a covered entity has failed to comply with the requirements of this Act, including any rule or regulation promulgated under this Act, a civil action may be brought by the Attorney General in an appropriate district court of the United States, or the appropriate United States court of any territory or other place subject to the jurisdiction of the United States, to request such court to compel compliance with the requirements of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AA75007BC1842DE95B7A8A789E91A41" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Costs</header><text>For knowing or willful failure to comply with the requirements of this Act, including any rule or regulation promulgated thereunder, a covered entity shall pay to the Treasury of the United States the full costs to the United States of obtaining compliance, including all associated costs of investigation and enforcement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD2E05385D8EC40D9925BAE9ADCA3D11F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General may promulgate regulations to carry out this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3ABB451D15294374AE3688D2F6533740"><enum>8.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H4524E3178BFF475D97E055D587148571" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Conduct intending to directly or indirectly influence public policy or public opinion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>conduct intending to directly or indirectly influence public policy or public opinion</term> means, with respect to a covered entity, any activity that the covered entity engaging in believes will, or that the covered entity intends to, in any way influence any agency or official of the Government of the United States or any section of the public within the United States with reference to formulating, adopting, or changing the domestic or foreign policies of the United States or with reference to the political or public interests, policies, or relations of a government of a foreign country or a foreign political party.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3C965F968F149CA86D2CD40E6304B2E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contract</header><text>The term <term>contract</term> means any agreement for the acquisition by purchase, lease, or barter of property or services by the foreign principal, for the direct benefit or use of either of the parties.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69D2E59EA1264D38A0EBFAE74A6743D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Country of citizenship</header><text>The term <term>country of citizenship</term>, with respect to a foreign principal, includes—</text><subparagraph id="H3EDC8F504C494AA4A4D15B30F7CEB932"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the principal residence for a foreign principal who is a natural person; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA872BAA721D74B6788A7B5CA8283D498"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the country of incorporation or the principal place of business for a foreign principal which is a legal entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA78CE918BE3468D99A0E50D1281EAAE" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <term>covered entity</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H5203C1E898C949548B588FF5E49E368A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a nonprofit organization or a not-for-profit social welfare organization that—</text><clause id="HA7CF381AFDEC4F529FE11A8FE7423B0F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>spends more than 20 percent of its resources within any given calendar year on conduct intending to directly or indirectly influence public policy or public opinion; or</text></clause><clause id="HBFCD64A55A7842E684C503A41A071447" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is affiliated with or is a sub-unit of an <quote>institution</quote> subject to section 117 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1011f">20 U.S.C. 1011f</external-xref>) that—</text><subclause id="HEA0790DB6E0E4557AFA09255A68278F8" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engages in or publishes substantial policy-related research or scholarship; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H4A6303C124154DC597E378A75115EC8C" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hosts, sponsors, or otherwise promotes annual, or on a more frequent basis, events featuring reporters, journalists, or U.S. or foreign government officials; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H270BA26D16A543CE8639D89A6849905E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">excludes—</text><clause id="H4E0501F71D464ABFBFE8BD192973C82D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an <quote>institution</quote> subject to section 117 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1011f">20 U.S.C. 1011f</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="HC97FD3FDEAC64560BB2479D10CBEF3B0" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an entity organized and operated exclusively for religious purposes.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H67F10030AF0649B6834BBB518AF445D3" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Foreign principal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>foreign principal</term> includes—</text><subparagraph id="H29C8A183FAB7419A998BD3D26422C2FC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a government of a foreign country and a foreign political party;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1359C42B4A364EFC9A1F6AB118D9AB99" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a person outside of the United States, unless it is established that such person is an individual and a citizen of the United States, or that such person is not an individual and is organized under or created by the laws of the United States or of any State or other place subject to the jurisdiction of the United States and has its principal place of business within the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H69F219ED2DFA4C5BA5E0E9CB0C2D043C" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a partnership, association, corporation, organization, or other combination of persons organized under the laws of or having its principal place of business in a foreign country.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DA115276591473FBD58B0033D708DC8" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Gift, donation, or contribution</header><text>The term <term>gift, donation, or contribution</term> means any gift of money, property, or in-kind contribution given directly or indirectly to a covered entity by a foreign principal.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H227F7608EDB54C3CA8776D815CAE4AC8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Not-for-profit social welfare organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>not-for-profit social welfare organization</term> means an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(4)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from tax under section 501(a) of such code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2E0494E677D46C8914582362E532005" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>nonprofit organization</term> means an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from tax under section 501(a) of such code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF0F989711C24B22B14BE904E028758F"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Restricted or conditional gift or contract</header><text>The term <term>restricted or conditional gift or contract</term> means any endowment, gift, grant, contract, award, present, or property of any kind which includes provisions regarding—</text><subparagraph id="H332C9C1CDDF5498DB6677C5CD730DFCA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the employment, assignment, compensation, or termination of researchers, scholars, or experts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A82E07E1FA747429023E654FF69D38C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the earmarking of funds for departments, centers, research or lecture programs, or new positions for researchers, scholars, or experts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9183FE643F94CD5AA7BEB6D2679063F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the subject matter, nature, or contents of research, analysis or any information published or disseminated to U.S. government officials, the media, or the public; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CC9F8D5686744489DEC4840E9BEC577"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other condition or expectation regarding either the foreign principal’s ability to review in advance, approve, veto, or modify budgets, programs, events, or presentations, or the contents of information or materials to be published or disseminated.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H66B569283D234B758D04079DCACBEB83" commented="no"><enum>9.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall take effect on the date that is 120 days following the date of enactment.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

