<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H82162946E493492587ECF64895A9A80F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 6491 IH: Asset Seizure for Ukraine Reconstruction Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6491</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231128">November 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the seizure and forfeiture of assets of Russian kleptocrats, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8890348130B1414EA47E28B004AEF771" style="OLC"><section id="H1B7B6698A7524D94B722C52A183DE9DB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Asset Seizure for Ukraine Reconstruction Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H0B8E93BEB1D54D7EA91E92B4FE52BD8C"><enum>2.</enum><header>National emergency declaration relating to harmful activities of Russian Federation relating to Ukraine</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The procedures under section 3 shall apply if the President—<italic></italic></text><paragraph id="H326920DFA2A64881BAD88B49389F460E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">declares a national emergency under section 201 of the National Emergencies Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1621">50 U.S.C. 1621</external-xref>) with respect to actions of the Government of the Russian Federation or nationals of the Russian Federation that threaten the peace, security, stability, sovereignty, or territorial integrity of Ukraine; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C3E4F076E8A4AB8B14439A7F87E94ED"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">declares that the use of the procedures under section 3 are necessary as a response to the national emergency.</text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H07328620A4214E1792F6034F1D9253A9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Procedures</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H773F3AE8E2534228AC478A9933BC00AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Nonjudicial forfeiture</header><text>Property may be forfeited through nonjudicial civil forfeiture under section 609 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1609">19 U.S.C. 1609</external-xref>), without regard to limitation under section 607(a)(1) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1607">19 U.S.C. 1607(a)(1)</external-xref>), if—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE809FB893A4648B89D718D38F60F8D17"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the President makes the declaration described in section 2; and </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1A4FDAF1F88436BACFFEDB1120ACF52"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Attorney General, or a designee, makes the certification described in subsection (b) with respect to the property.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC57C8D5DC39453DB49B52FFD7DB80AF" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>After seizure of property and prior to forfeiture of the property under subsection (a), the Attorney General, or a designee, shall certify that, upon forfeiture, the property will be covered forfeited property (as defined in section 1708(c) of the Additional Ukraine Supplemental Appropriations Act, 2023 (division M of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>; 136 Stat. 5200), as amended by this Act). </text></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H029037F23B5241ACBB7DE52CAF41B2EC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Expansion of forfeited property available to remediate harms to Ukraine from Russian aggression</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0F5B4B2FD50A48C280A07DD9C4AD9CEB"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1708(c) of the Additional Ukraine Supplemental Appropriations Act, 2023 (division M of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>; 136 Stat. 5200) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3EB3616BED2E46739FA3F429153955CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>which property belonged</quote> and all that follows and inserting the following: ‘‘which property—</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H412BC9D8473B4A868FEE28FAD2B662BA"><subparagraph id="HEB0725EC0B414BB4AFAA4D91EC855324"><enum>(A)</enum><text>belonged to, was possessed by, or was controlled by a person the property or interests in property of which were blocked pursuant to any license, order, regulation, or prohibition imposed by the United States under the authority provided by the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) or any other provision of law, with respect to—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5CD347F6C22E44F69F9B2551897319BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Russian Federation; or </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H945BD220DF8E4C1DB3FEF69D9B6FA2C8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">actions or policies that undermine the democratic processes and institutions in Ukraine or threaten the peace, security, stability, sovereignty, or territorial integrity of Ukraine;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EE1F73BEBB1451E83164B57B33C993B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>was involved in an act in violation of or a conspiracy or scheme to violate—</text><clause id="H7A3598329A9646C7BA47D173C873CE13"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any license, order, regulation, or prohibition described in subparagraph (A); or</text></clause><clause id="H2A9F50794FBA45C8B717D7895FB7CA08"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any restriction on the export, reexport, or in-country transfer of items imposed by the United States under the Export Administration Regulations, or any restriction on the export, reexport, or retransfer of defense articles under the International Traffic in Arms Regulations under subchapter M of chapter I of title 22, Code of Federal Regulations, with respect to—</text><subclause id="H6B16285076514831BBAC1F1219E71364"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Russian Federation, Belarus, the Crimea region of Ukraine, or the so-called <quote>Donetsk People's Republic</quote> or <quote>Luhansk People’s Republic</quote> regions of Ukraine;</text></subclause><subclause id="HBB04EEF61C20410BAABB2BF345485266"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any person in any such country or region on a restricted parties list; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H817D7AA96E8748E99EFA86C7AA7C6A56"><enum>(III)</enum><text>any person located in any other country that has been added to a restricted parties list in connection with the malign conduct of the Russian Federation in Ukraine, including the annexation of the Crimea region of Ukraine in March 2014 and the invasion beginning in February 2022 of Ukraine, as substantially enabled by Belarus; or</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0004A4EA428743D8BC9C4AE07F9BAF32"><enum>(C)</enum><text>was involved in any related conspiracy, scheme, or other Federal offense arising from the actions of, or doing business with or acting on behalf of, the Russian Federation, Belarus, the Crimea region of Ukraine, or the so-called <quote>Donetsk People's Republic</quote> or <quote>Luhansk People’s Republic</quote> regions of Ukraine.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H089EBEB8E849421BB0F0EFE9B0A3B081"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE5D6F41BA6C34A47B9506667F0E6C2BE"><paragraph id="HC21D7AA62E9543C4A1798EDAC73102D4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>Export Administration Regulations</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1742 of the Export Control Reform Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4801">50 U.S.C. 4801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE046546E90C34EB39F6DC04AA4B7BE93"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>restricted parties list</term> means any of the following lists maintained by the Bureau of Industry and Security:</text><subparagraph id="H816C8C396A9E4B3885E8AC94E8A08CF5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Entity List set forth in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB294B2FDCC3042E3A5600DA63ED48BC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Denied Persons List maintained pursuant to section 764.3(a)(2) of the Export Administration Regulations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C5A1BCBE0EF4BBA9EFCA662F0049ADA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Unverified List set forth in Supplement No. 6 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFEB4A4DD95D74207A62BED2C036EDF69"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Extension of authority</header><text>Section 1708(d) of the Additional Ukraine Supplemental Appropriations Act, 2023 is amended by striking <quote>May 1, 2025</quote> and inserting <quote>the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Asset Seizure for Ukraine Reconstruction Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HDDB763CD16D9493893B7C5A00BF4D761"><enum>5.</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General and the Secretary of the Treasury may prescribe regulations to carry out this Act without regard to the requirements of section 553 of title 5, United States Code.</text></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H708DAFF7940F49D190C13432B1EE9194"><enum>6.</enum><header>Termination</header><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H2DB77164AC3C4CE790EEF4A0756FC8B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of this Act shall terminate on the date that is 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0F86B710E99C4130B3888CB355C576D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Savings provision</header><text>The termination of this Act under subsection (a) shall not—</text><paragraph id="H733DB0260C434B658F05C4130736C855"><enum>(1)</enum><text>terminate the applicability of the procedures under this Act to any property seized prior to the date of the termination under subsection (a); or </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E3CFC452FAC47DCA8E936C9F96F32F4" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>moot any legal action taken or pending legal proceeding not finally concluded or determined on that date. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

