<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H731F85A006ED43D3B47D850851C63D62" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5067 IH: Empowering Electric Grid Reliability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5067</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Energy to establish a task force to study and report on supply chains for local electric distribution grids in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H6A7DCFCA115E48F7A2F0B7E4BFB25E14" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1F493E91770242A3BE381A09A5E5A8B2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Empowering Electric Grid Reliability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE3A5BA13648B4761AE23D9FA4D01E563" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header> Task force study and report</header> <subsection id="H317892EECDF94A44A11C910F18B0D75C" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of task force</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy shall establish a task force—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCA597B70E58E46D4BC6C0C443F1E883C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to conduct a study on supply chains for essential components of local electric distribution grids, as identified by the Secretary of Energy, including substation transformers and equipment and downline facilities that deliver retail electric energy to homes and businesses; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF9BA8969661C452AB40F2C8F8CECED53" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on such study, in accordance with this section.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H72FF7A5774C54E449FB0557F564AA175" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study and report</header> 
<paragraph id="H80C0262298E44BAD8EB0A7EBEFA20E3D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The task force shall conduct a study that—</text> <subparagraph id="H391CE84CAAE64297AEADB693F316689D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies, with respect to each supply chain for an essential component of a local electric distribution grid, the goods and materials that are essential to such supply chain; </text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBF6A70EB60DE482B8911382A0F1A0330" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identifies the manufacturing or other capabilities necessary to produce the goods and materials identified under subparagraph (A), including emerging capabilities; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H86506CB8C2F2446EAA30B84CB7E3D464" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies, with respect to each supply chain for an essential component of a local electric distribution grid, the defense, intelligence, cyber, homeland security, health, climate, environmental, natural, market, economic, geopolitical, human-rights, or forced-labor risks or other contingencies that may disrupt, strain, compromise, or eliminate such supply chain and that are sufficiently likely to arise so as to require reasonable preparation for their occurrence, including risks—</text> 
<clause id="HDE9ED542CE864DAE80532CC52EBBC0E8" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>posed by the reliance of such supply chain on digital products that may be vulnerable to failures or exploitation; and</text></clause> <clause id="H1630D7B3DE4F4ED795757871C9F8B3A2" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>resulting from the elimination of, or failure to develop domestically, the capabilities identified under subparagraph (B);</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H54E19451C657434191E97CB6E73AD43C" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reviews the resilience and capacity of domestic supply chains for essential components of local electric distribution grids, and the industrial and agricultural base of the United States, to support national and economic security and emergency preparedness in the event any of the contingencies identified under subparagraph (C) occurs, including identification and review of—</text> <clause id="HD257F67FEDD448FCA45903BD6CFF8FE3" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the resilience and capacity of the manufacturing or other needed capabilities of the United States, including the ability to modernize to meet future needs; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H6C418A51AD6E4EE699D7C34D2C61465B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>gaps in domestic manufacturing capabilities, including nonexistent, extinct, threatened, or single-point-of-failure capabilities; </text></clause> <clause id="HD1AD7E765EDD434A99981E08B3423E58" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any supply chain for an essential component of a local electric distribution grid with a single point of failure, single or dual suppliers, or limited resilience, especially for subcontractors (as defined under section 44.101 of title 48, Code of Federal Regulations);</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2AEF8D2FC5D748BE953845BA72B2455B" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the location of key manufacturing and production assets, with any significant risks identified under subparagraph (C) posed by the assets’ physical location;</text></clause> <clause id="H0D0E285907CA4D42A588307F02343F37" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any exclusive or dominant supply of goods and materials identified under subparagraph (A) by or through nations that are, or are likely to become, unfriendly or unstable;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE9D6136A12A84B6A9F78420F7C49E4A3" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the availability of substitutes or alternative sources for goods and materials identified under subparagraph (A);</text></clause> <clause id="H3FA2581E789548B99223AE6A439E3D29" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">current domestic education and manufacturing workforce skills for each supply chain for an essential component of a local electric distribution grid, and identified gaps, opportunities, and potential best practices in meeting the future workforce needs for such supply chain;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9B6D9A0D7E334FA9A3DFE026CC1AC27D" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the need for research and development capacity to sustain leadership in the development of goods and materials identified under subparagraph (A); and</text></clause> <clause id="H8D1D9995FF644F908DF2CF8792964407" commented="no"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the role of transportation systems in supporting existing supply chains for essential components of local electric distribution grids and risks associated with those transportation systems;</text></clause> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF5F4C0E087F24FF7A5D0928A3B6B2A80" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">examines allied and partner actions regarding supply chains for essential components of local electric distribution grids, including with respect to the goods and materials identified under subparagraph (A), and possible avenues for international engagement; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H46E68539E5AD4743B857EDFF0426F627" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies a prioritization of the goods and materials identified under subparagraph (A) for the purpose of identifying policy recommendations that is based on—</text> 
<clause id="H93C7C1EE6059481EBD3D5FF267EC5007" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>statutory or regulatory requirements;</text></clause> <clause id="H1095E9299B1C428CB0E0E55EB142B971" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">importance to national security, emergency preparedness, and strengthening the resilience of supply chains for essential components of local electric distribution grids; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HEA252222FE6D4B19B1733BB59815BA0A" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the review conducted pursuant to subparagraph (D).</text></clause></subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HC35CA14513F74E64B6CFFE4A79512619" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 3 months after the task force is established, the task force shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the study conducted under paragraph (1) that includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H2309D5E69638499788608C9E3F76BDDB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specific policy recommendations for ensuring resilient supply chains for essential components of local electric distribution grids, including recommendations for—</text> <clause id="H36A804681E9945A2AD523300140DBC0E" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>sustainably reshoring such supply chains and developing domestic supplies for such supply chains; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H5E4EF1D1E12A40788008E66C4085BD7B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>cooperating with allies and partners to identify alternative supplies for such supply chains, including for goods and materials identified in the study under paragraph (1)(A);</text></clause> <clause id="HF3DECAB0CC4E49239F4085A6212D7D73" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">building redundancy into domestic supply chains for essential components of local electric distribution grids;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC3CAB68526334AF8A63F768BC800A23E" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensuring and enlarging stockpiles of goods and materials identified in the study under paragraph (1)(A); </text></clause> <clause id="H63AAF4E618294662A4160F1FCB483026" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing workforce capabilities for producing essential components of local electric distribution grids, including goods and materials identified in the study under paragraph (1)(A); </text></clause> 
<clause id="H2E206A07E59C45D7B4F11FD50349B5D1" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expanding research and development with respect to such supply chains; and</text></clause> <clause id="H67CBD5996B1C4B92808D0BDA2E5FA469" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">addressing risks due to vulnerabilities in digital products relied on by any such supply chain;</text></clause> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5F3D2C514DDC4BC7A66F164DA919F1AC" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any recommendations for executive, legislative, regulatory, and policy changes and any other actions to—</text> <clause id="HABBDFAEA5A4B49C398D5D790410BC781" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>strengthen the capabilities identified in the study under paragraph (1)(B); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB985BB5981FF477B8B852618E83E7BF7" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>prevent, avoid, or prepare for any of the contingencies identified in the study under paragraph (1)(C); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7A156E180AAF4BCD974B7D8E626591E5" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any recommendations for improving Government-wide efforts to strengthen supply chains for essential components of local electric distribution grids, including proposals for coordinating Government actions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA9CA494BB38E4FEBB54BB6CC785A0581" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HC40A1CAE7F79430FB030BA19D0A1D0A6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3222EDFA45A3465CB4A1D24AB89FEDBD" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H80CC93069BFB4DC4AC5E4DFB3E009CBA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6C65E9EF3B3B42779F4EFD177BDCA012" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H23ACE01EF51344469830A7B331E83DDC" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H949FBC992F8145A1BA2ADB4E9D1611C9" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA863218E0345400194A2CE7246E0AC67" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Supply chain</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>supply chain</term> includes, with respect to minerals, the exploration, mining, concentration, separation, alloying, recycling, and reprocessing of minerals. </text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9CE7A65CC47041E5A306131FBB565EF0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Task force</header><text>The term <term>task force</term> means the task force established under subsection (a). </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

