<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA175AF6F945A4A77A7FAD0BF24E980F0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1264 IH: Commonsense Reporting Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1264</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230228">February 28, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To streamline the employer reporting process and strengthen the eligibility verification process for the premium assistance tax credit and cost-sharing subsidy.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H0A6F2923F64B4029B2F8948AE504858D" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H73B3DD6378114F5D9362DBE2B74174F1"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Commonsense Reporting Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H8BD574E3845D4F9CAA3E7721DECFFA6E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9555EA291B02483EA1B1503D1D935901"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Department of the Treasury and the Internal Revenue Service should work together with other relevant departments and agencies to identify and implement methods to minimize compliance burdens on businesses, insurance carriers, and individuals.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6328264819E249F89212082F800C56C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Such collaboration should strike an appropriate balance between sufficient reporting to enforce the law and protecting the privacy of individuals.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H8F3F8F620BD8420CA5C628EBDAEE4334"><enum>3.</enum><header>Voluntary prospective reporting system</header> 
<subsection id="H0FB4E034FBBF46C68F37107E98A7123A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Labor, and the Administrator of the Small Business Administration, shall develop and implement guidance providing for a prospective reporting system meeting the requirements of subsection (b). Such system shall be available for use by employers on a voluntary basis beginning not later than January 1, 2024.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8B09AA83BB2A42BCAA92AF3000E5AF15"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The system created under subsection (a) shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB7408AE272294CB79D5F704D07D43387"><enum>(1)</enum><text>voluntary reporting by each participating employer that offers minimum essential coverage to its full-time employees and their dependents under an eligible employer-sponsored plan, not later than 45 days before the first day of the annual open enrollment period under section 1311(c)(6)(B) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18031">42 U.S.C. 18031(c)(6)(B)</external-xref>) for each calendar year, of—</text> <subparagraph id="H920CFC3B27C7458CAA9B17BD78B810D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the name and employer identification number for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6056">section 6056</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 of the employer;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H842E984D8763489AAC3ED7C97367D1EC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a certification of—</text> <clause id="H6648F18F11164709918C84A7B689A24C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>whether coverage meeting the definition of minimum essential coverage in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5000A">section 5000A(f)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is offered to the full-time employees (within the meaning of section 4980H of such Code) of the employer;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDA82EF04AE5040B9BC74B7611E2B5770"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether such coverage is offered to part-time employees of the employer;</text></clause> <clause id="H654EB0F63B814E3A9CB406ED5ECE08CB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>whether such coverage is offered to dependents of employees;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB184BE34006F42F7A7879AF2D816CCED"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>whether such coverage is offered to spouses of employees;</text></clause> <clause id="HECD324D2E152497CA1B3B94E0251B639"><enum>(v)</enum><text>whether such coverage meets the minimum value requirement of section 36B(c)(2)(C)(ii) of such Code;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3064899C9BB64D0B96B9FDBEF265B830"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>whether such coverage satisfies the requirements to qualify for one of the affordability safe harbors promulgated by the Secretary of the Treasury for purposes of section 4980H of such Code; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC6A3F5BC7E85490490067D0147901B42"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>whether the employer reasonably expects to be liable for any shared responsibility payment under section 4980H of such Code for such year;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3B786C4D772842CD8CAAAF1DB7DF49D4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the months during the prospective reporting period that such coverage is available to individuals described in clauses (i) through (iv) of subparagraph (B);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6D85EFBFC04248CB86DD741DF6A8DA03"><enum>(D)</enum><text>what waiting periods, if any, apply with respect to such coverage; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H47EC18BF64EC442AA12DEE3808A0654E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a list of all employer identification numbers of the employer for entities that employ employees within the employers control group under subsection (b), (c), (m), or (o) of section 414 of the Internal Revenue Code for 1986;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1C674331A7484DA4A37BD9A1F3EA62C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>processes necessary to ensure that Exchanges, the Federal Marketplace Data Services Hub, and the Internal Revenue Service can securely and confidentially access the information described in paragraph (1) as necessary to carry out their respective missions, and to provide to the Secretary of Health and Human Services additional information relating to eligibility determinations for advance payment of the premium tax credits under section 36B of such Code and the cost-sharing subsidies under section 1402 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18071">42 U.S.C. 18071</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H26FF0E2892994E81B25B3294648F9870"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a process to allow Exchanges to follow up with employers in order to obtain additional reasonably necessary information relating to an employee’s eligibility for such advance payment or such cost-sharing subsidies, and to allow an employee to receive notification of any problem in verifying such eligibility; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9460592C8FC041C8BA74610ABDB20F8D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a process to allow employers using the system to provide timely updates to the Federal Marketplace Data Services Hub regarding any cancellation of coverage or significant change in coverage for participating employees that would change the information reported under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCE377CE9234A478EB63D2D2507F19835"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Employer notification of employee enrollment in exchange plans</header><text>Subparagraph (J) of section 1311(d)(4) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18031">42 U.S.C. 18031(d)(4)(J)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>to each employer</quote> and all that follows through <quote>(and the effective date of such cessation); and</quote> and inserting</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3D96557057104DA1965CFC6CC8843475"><text>to each employer—</text> 
<clause id="HFC0CF0701DAB49079D2C69494C57634E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the name of each employee of the employer who enrolls in a qualified health plan for a plan year, or whose dependents enroll in such a plan, at the time of such enrollment; or</text></clause> <clause id="HE8B0D506BB4047CC8C8BFB9D5EC382FE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the name of each employee of the employer described in subparagraph (I)(ii) who ceases coverage under a qualified health plan during a plan year (and the effective date of such cessation); and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H690AC2369F75403B8F91E7B9FAEF9932"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exemption from reporting requirement under internal revenue code of 1986</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6056">Section 6056</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (f) as subsection (g) and by inserting after subsection (e) the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H818E2E2920574FA78B735295FCACF67A"> <subsection id="H064F098C2BBC48A9BE55BCF5A4C46C30"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>If, through the system created pursuant to section 3(a) of the Commonsense Reporting Act of 2023, an employer provides prospective reporting for any calendar year that meets the requirements of section 3(b)(1) of such Act, such employer shall be treated as satisfying the return requirements of subsections (a), (b), and (c) for such year. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDC63160D673C4FA78117EE53FE6D7FF5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Third-Party filing</header><text>An employer may contract with a third party to make the report under subsection (b)(1) without affecting the employer’s treatment as having satisfied the return requirements of subsections (a) and (b) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6056">section 6056</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF719FBED401746008EF391C7D21F542B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Access to the national directory of new hires</header><text>Subsection (i)(3) of section 453 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/653">42 U.S.C. 653</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>The Secretary of the Treasury and the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall have access to the information in the National Directory of New Hires for purposes of administering section 36B and 4980H of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and section 1402 of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18071">42 U.S.C. 18071</external-xref>). Subsection (k)(3) shall not apply to information received for purposes of the administration of such sections 36B and 4980H of such Code and section 1402 of such Act.</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H17454E1AF239449381824EBE15659BFF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Improving employee access to accurate EINS</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall develop and implement guidance for allowing any employee of an employer to receive, on request, the employer’s employer identification number for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6056">section 6056</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986. Employers shall provide the employer’s employer identification number for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6056">section 6056</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 on employee pay statements. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HA7D067FC88EA4C65A242F7CCD90B0222"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Funding for voluntary prospective reporting system</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, the Secretary of Labor, and the Administrator of the Small Business Administration such sums as are necessary to carry out this section. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HE0519C911E904089BD880A15AFC1C14F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Protection of dependent privacy</header> 
<subsection id="HD956ED5FBEB4498794D0D42024F1564C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (1) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6055">section 6055(b)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following flush sentence:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC0650DF54442408EA666B9FBA29E53C6"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (B)(i), in the case of an individual other than the primary insured, if the health insurance issuer or the employer is unable to collect or maintain information on the TINs of such individuals (other than for purposes of this section), the Secretary may allow the individual’s full name and date of birth to be substituted for the name and TIN. In the event the Secretary allows the use of the individual’s full name and date of birth in lieu of the TIN, the Social Security Administration shall assist the Internal Revenue Service in providing data matches to determine the TIN associated with the name and date of birth provided by the Internal Revenue Service with respect to such individual.</text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD8F20BD1DF994172B753B9E6723DDEA3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to returns the due date for which is after the date that is 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H87983E02A19245B8ABABE0320CBC6E8B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Electronic statements</header> <subsection id="HCE0EE947D817414495BCB6D9E9147682"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (c) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6056">section 6056</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3BE8AB0EE83E4A41A71191F9C4FFF858"> 
<paragraph id="H42306ED0D894445D8ABBBF3E73EF099E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Electronic delivery</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual shall be deemed to have consented to receive the statement under this subsection in electronic form if such individual has affirmatively consented at any prior time, to the person who is the employer of the individual during the calendar year to which the statement relates, to receive such statement in electronic form. The preceding sentence shall not apply if the individual revokes consent in writing with respect to the statement under this subsection.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HF9089D46FDF64D27B40B116C052D85BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statements relating to health insurance coverage</header><text>Subsection (c) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6055">section 6055</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4AED225DDF134036B440288E24687DA8"> 
<paragraph id="H095809267C6E4DF7A9710F4F6D102D75"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Electronic delivery</header><text>An individual shall be deemed to have consented to receive the statement under this subsection in electronic form if such individual has affirmatively consented at any prior time, to the person required to make such statement (such as the provider of the individual’s health coverage), to receive in electronic form any private health information (such as electronic health records), unless the individual revokes such consent in writing.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H73B9F01371C340958F7F05D1115D39FA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to statements the due date for which is after December 31, 2023.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HE0D78D66F8DF49D883B1277971384293"><enum>6.</enum><header>Time for appeal</header> 
<subsection id="HAABBFD84DFC24D3BBD06FA768FFEB278"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4980H">Section 4980H(d)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H219F38EDFB9045DD882956566A90D5A3"> <paragraph id="H31C0C95FA882467FB290B1FE080C9D51"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Time for appeal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall allow an applicable large employer 90 days from the date of the first letter which allows the employer an opportunity for administrative review of a proposed employer shared responsibility payment under this section by the Internal Revenue Service Independent Office of Appeals to appeal the proposed assessment of such payment before issuing the notice and demand for payment under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA52AA937C0B14B21A439D960A63DE5EA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall apply to assessments in taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section> <section commented="no" id="HB14B7FE3B176482E8D675D80EAA74062"><enum>7.</enum><header>Statute of limitations on penalty assessment</header> <subsection commented="no" id="HA9173645FD384D0A993BD30F658C496B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4980H">Section 4980H(d)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended by section 6, is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4CE5775D75A74148A9F56871BA6DD3B2"> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HD87A45D13476422DA63C853DFB5100E5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Statute of limitations on penalty assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to an assessment of an assessable payment under paragraph (1), the statutory period for such assessment shall expire at the end of the 3-year period beginning on the date the employer files the return under section 6056 for the calendar year with respect to which such payment is determined.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H809E7CC489484659B297094F07638054"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall apply to proposed assessments with respect to which a letter described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4980H">section 4980H(d)(4)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by this section) is issued in taxable years beginning after the date which is 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H857F01EF8AF34A8F86C9F998A9B69333"><enum>8.</enum><header>GAO studies</header> 
<subsection id="H69A8683DC7104F0BB9DE9A329209C721"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study of first years of employer reporting</header> 
<paragraph id="H3098656765EE4F608EC3CD3778D387EB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study that evaluates, with respect to the period beginning on January 1, 2015, and ending on December 31, 2022—</text> <subparagraph id="H704ABA1A62664FD18E435786240528C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the notification of employers by Exchanges established under title I of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/148">Public Law 111–148</external-xref>) that a full-time employee of the employer has been determined eligible for advance payment of premium tax credits under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/36B">section 36B</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 or cost-sharing subsidies under section 1402 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18071">42 U.S.C. 18071</external-xref>), including information regarding—</text> 
<clause id="HE07F7DA64276405297EC06891F3930E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the data elements included in the employer notification;</text></clause> <clause id="H02BAF1F68FBA4DE29DDFC696228E85A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the process by which the notification forms were developed and sent to employers, including whether the process provided for a formal notice and comment period;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7F13403026E24CB6928CBDD8CEF24D5E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>whether employers report that such notifications provided sufficient and relevant information for them to make appropriate decisions about whether to utilize the appeals process;</text></clause> <clause id="HC2E7B820D2974AD3BBBAEC5AA658C8E5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total number of notifications sent to employers and the timeline of when such notifications were sent;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE2569AF6C2F447298DD5A7AAC1CDCFCB"><enum>(v)</enum><text>differences in the notification process between the marketplace facilitated by the Federal Government and the State-Based Marketplaces; and</text></clause> <clause id="H551894913D0D4478BC2FF8F5E43F6B30"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>challenges that have arisen in the notification process, and recommendations to address these challenges; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5D70777073844F57A3ABE4819121CB5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the extent to which the Secretary of Health and Human Services has established a separate appeals process for employers who received such a notification to challenge the eligibility determination, as required by section 1411(f)(2) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18081">42 U.S.C. 18081(f)(2)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0AA8FA6AF2B149D2A897CBF5CE4CC66D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the Committees on Finance and Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committees on Ways and Means, Energy and Commerce, and Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives a report on the results of the study conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD1130CA8D5BE48E19E73B618AFFCCA36"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study of prospective reporting system</header> 
<paragraph id="H9C2DA6D97B6E46E8A351710439343F28"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study that evaluates, with respect to the period beginning on January 1, 2024, and ending on December 31, 2024, the functionality of the prospective reporting system established pursuant to section 3, including the accuracy of information collected, the number of employers electing to report under such system, and any challenges that have arisen in implementing such system.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H876F510D758B4F6BAD34687F1ACC4A61"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than July 1, 2025, the Comptroller General shall submit to the Committees on Finance and Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committees on Ways and Means, Energy and Commerce, and Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives a report on the results of the study conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section commented="no" id="H2D81B50AE3F74126AE185F4AD657CEF7"><enum>9.</enum><header>Tax compliance</header> 
<subsection id="H05DFF5338EC243198111E79312996787"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6724">Section 6724(d)(1)(B)(xxv)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting <quote>or, in the case of an employer to which section 6056(f) applies, section 3(b)(1) of the <short-title>Commonsense Reporting Act of 2023</short-title></quote> before <quote>, or</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBE397ECC0C10406BAD2C85E1CC7C0C92"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to returns required to be filed after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


