<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HC2A7AD00E9154249B111EB1DB3A7E54B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1567 RH: Accurately Counting Risk Elimination Solutions Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 149</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1567</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–186, Part I]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230310">March 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="N000189">Mr. Newhouse</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HII00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on March 10, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require that the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of the Interior submit accurate reports regarding hazardous fuels reduction activities, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HII00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H0E1C1132A37345E995DBFAD85F88D223"><section id="HBA553A6E5C0A446BAFB09EFB29FDFC1D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Accurately Counting Risk Elimination Solutions Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ACRES Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H8095BA067A314F6EA5A3B42A3B58B340"><enum>2.</enum><header>Accurate Hazardous Fuels Reduction Reports</header><subsection id="HA3AF891123EF4D09A839E85AF6085248"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Inclusion of Hazardous Fuels Reduction Report in Materials Submitted in Support of the President’s Budget</header><paragraph id="HB4DB38EBA3774365B1566CDA2122096C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning with the first fiscal year that begins after the date of the enactment of this Act, and each fiscal year thereafter, the Secretary concerned shall include in the materials submitted in support of the President’s budget pursuant to section 1105 of title 31, United States Code, a report on the number of acres of Federal land on which the Secretary concerned carried out hazardous fuels reduction activities during the preceding fiscal year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4376C9FEF80409F941178F52C438FA9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>For purposes of the report required under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned shall—</text><subparagraph id="H5ABF602025494E42AAA8D559FDDB79A1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in determining the number of acres of Federal land on which the Secretary concerned carried out hazardous fuels reduction activities during the period covered by the report—</text><clause id="HE05AB7CCF1074836A48F062F085B0966"><enum>(i)</enum><text>record acres of Federal land on which hazardous fuels reduction activities were completed during such period; and</text></clause><clause id="H99A6DF7EC207422F9BDECC675B79B0D4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>record each acre described in clause (i) once in the report, regardless of whether multiple hazardous fuels reduction activities were carried out on such acre during such period; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3578CE34336647A485E970806D5314F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to the acres of Federal land recorded in the report, include information on—</text><clause id="H93BDF747D8E449E7AEC905FAB63AB273"><enum>(i)</enum><text>which such acres are located in the wildland-urban interface;</text></clause><clause id="H9A7D12BCD8FA49FDB3335127D25D18E3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the level of wildfire risk (high, moderate, or low) on the first and last day of the period covered by the report;</text></clause><clause id="H54B802A664454ABE81DB968ACA8323C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the types of hazardous fuels activities completed for such acres, delineating between whether such activities were conducted—</text><subclause id="H85A2EB1AE06F41D281C4B97324580E35"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in a wildfire managed for resource benefits; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H936F74810D7C430296FD0C5023BE72A6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>through a planned project;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H76716D56D8F24F7898EBE1C07EC5D847"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the cost per acre of hazardous fuels activities carried out during the period covered by the report;</text></clause><clause id="HB125C28CE96D4A25990B10576FABE40B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the region or system unit in which the acres are located; and</text></clause><clause id="H5612D04FCE6F4F2585C28C57853FF951"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the hazardous fuels reduction activities on reducing the risk of wildfire.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE34EF57203684FBBB2FD9A6BC6BC1BDC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Transparency</header><text>The Secretary concerned shall make each report submitted under paragraph (1) publicly available on the website of the Department of Agriculture and the Department of the Interior, as applicable.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H323B2FD3A6874215AAF813EC6D6976D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Accurate data collection</header><paragraph id="H66B169756F60417BBFE08A3C18EDA323"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall implement standardized procedures for tracking data related to hazardous fuels reduction activities carried out by the Secretary concerned.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB0E8F35F5794ED7ACF95B5DB831615B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The standardized procedures required under paragraph (1) shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H0698D0820C1F4348B7BBE4A7CD5FF801"><enum>(A)</enum><text>regular, standardized data reviews of the accuracy and timely input of data used to track hazardous fuels reduction activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAC13E2E248241DA9C91528D8E51546E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>verification methods that validate whether such data accurately correlates to the hazardous fuels reduction activities carried out by the Secretary concerned;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6A1F10A20904ECCA543B470B6A8322B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an analysis of the short- and long-term effectiveness of the hazardous fuels reduction activities on reducing the risk of wildfire; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA315F4B4E424AE89FF983DC81A56E99"><enum>(D)</enum><text>for hazardous fuels reduction activities that occur partially within the wildland-urban interface, methods to distinguish which acres are located within the wildland-urban interface and which acres are located outside the wildland-urban interface.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EDFC226135E44B0AB321FE08654744B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 weeks after implementing the standardized procedures required under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned shall submit to Congress a report that describes—</text><subparagraph id="H748B23025E0546CBAA9D7D2140D34BA6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such standardized procedures; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF10D5721E29442AA90A6BA06726330F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>program and policy recommendations to Congress to address any limitations in tracking data related to hazardous fuels reduction activities under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H99EE9312D32A4436A3BC9BA26169CBBB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>GAO study</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text><paragraph id="H1942EE97B06A4E22B8F2F596F693FA5F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a study on the implementation of this Act, including any limitations with respect to—</text><subparagraph id="H5F08D863E9A749D884D62AB636CBDD61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reporting hazardous fuels reduction activities under subsection (a); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9A8C1094A7E4DE2BD23E7C53A0F77D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>tracking data related to hazardous fuels reduction activities under subsection (b); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H668E227DF8CE491DAC2330BC297FCEDC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to Congress a report that describes the results of the study under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D7DB578CA6C488AA4437B6EC6F083F7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HC11778BCC19D4DD1A5C1D82F9B91187E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hazardous fuels reduction activity</header><text>The term <term>hazardous fuels reduction activity</term>—</text><subparagraph id="HE1553572E7D24B35A02F153151B325C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any vegetation management activity to reduce the risk of wildfire, including mechanical treatments and prescribed burning; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21E93727DF4E444B9A4EB5D45A474379"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include the awarding of contracts to conduct hazardous fuels reduction activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1A336E29DD242039A4131CA4BB9798A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal lands</header><text>The term <quote>Federal lands</quote> means lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Agriculture. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6772794B19FF4D69822574204569EFF0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary concerned</header><text>The term <term>Secretary concerned</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H34D482915531415096BE870A797A4ADE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture, with respect to National Forest System lands; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF985974054534CA391ABCF50AAB4FB23"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior, with respect to public lands and units of the National Park System.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H60B98FC73BE54567A94B2D00CBB628B6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Wildland-urban interface</header><text>The term <term>wildland-urban interface</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6511">16 U.S.C. 6511</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HII00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

