<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H53468184108740E1A098FEF5A1196B17" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1577 IH: BUILDER Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1577</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230314">March 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 to clarify ambiguous provisions, reflect modern technologies, optimize interagency coordination, and facilitate a more efficient, effective, and timely environmental review process.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1D4F45F8B9794A4EA147772EEE194493" style="OLC"><section id="H0E7ED85A71BC4DC2A9B699B72B44DD75" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>BUILDER Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Building United States Infrastructure through Limited Delays and Efficient Reviews Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H783B8A6297CE4CE780CB7B80CC0DF448"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Environmental Policy Act of 1969</header><subsection id="H5768FEA567144F1EAD5134B14EC6919C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Paragraph (2) of section 102</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 102(2) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H43A252AEC064459FAA3021583D212DE9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>insure</quote> and inserting <quote>ensure</quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2697C7E6513C48C58B1D49F8E59EBD03"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>insure</quote> and inserting <quote>ensure</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE836EF79B64F4870BAF9FDD490BF8586"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text><subparagraph id="HB6702E63BF22431F98C5B11E37FC90E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>consistent with the provisions of this Act and except as provided by other provisions of law,</quote> before <quote>include in every</quote>; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE84358F43C184139B5FB46A9E9DE651D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking clauses (i) through (v) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA1A7D0E980F74073A9C28D671B91FAFF" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="HE0485897C16C4387B5BC6715E43BEF87" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reasonably foreseeable environmental effects with a reasonably close causal relationship to the proposed agency action;</text></clause><clause id="H08FB253F3E494390B3D4A3596EF60B37" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any reasonably foreseeable adverse environmental effects which cannot be avoided should the proposal be implemented;</text></clause><clause id="H8E910D90C09E4A30826FA816D711D3D9" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a reasonable number of alternatives to the proposed agency action, including an analysis of any negative environmental impacts of not implementing the proposed agency action in the case of a no action alternative, that are technically and economically feasible, are within the jurisdiction of the agency, meet the purpose and need of the proposal, and, where applicable, meet the goals of the applicant;</text></clause><clause id="H7E96273F4A3E454A980C074C872A9700" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the relationship between local short-term uses of man's environment and the maintenance and enhancement of long-term productivity; and</text></clause><clause id="H1A4D4B0A0981475CA176CB8548011C8C" indent="up1"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any irreversible and irretrievable commitments of Federal resources which would be involved in the proposed agency action should it be implemented.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07905C80926F43D790A746152874939E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>the responsible Federal official</quote> and inserting <quote>the head of the lead agency</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B373245BC144DCA8D00552DBEB78DCD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>Any</quote> and inserting <quote>any</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2073E24F1D9D4B3E84A884AFA05E4B1C" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (D) through (I) as subparagraphs (F) through (K), respectively;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72C7F1FD234641FE80D1B1BD38A264B8" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8774526A3A0E45A7ADEFD1EF2134C7B1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H051EDEBEC9AF4F3EB188981295744065" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure the professional integrity, including scientific integrity, of the discussion and analysis in an environmental document;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D4AD7D1802C47A2A0E5661FFB234D0F" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make use of reliable existing data and resources in carrying out this Act;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E1CEFD592BB484EAADEA2B7C198705C" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (G), as redesignated, to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE595AD7E57EE44D1AA6370AFA3587C4C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H120DEB25A5B74485977B129CC4A5692B" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consistent with the provisions of this Act, study, develop, and describe technically and economically feasible alternatives within the jurisdiction and authority of the agency;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HD81BC7F4AECC40FDBE73461DC50E3BE5"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (H), as amended, by inserting <quote>consistent with the provisions of this Act,</quote> before <quote>recognize</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEB94FB24AC0C409091665CCE7E72B8F0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>New sections</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title I of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0A4D2A90DB7C48F4A682957F4062947F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HFAAF2488B4B74DD0AA6E14F7F6C2D60A"><enum>106.</enum><header>Procedure for determination of level of review</header><subsection id="HBA12363555564949A92153FCA3921605"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Threshold determinations</header><text>An agency is not required to prepare an environmental document with respect to a proposed agency action if—</text><paragraph id="HA7399FE269304FF182F0CE6C925325EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the proposed agency action is not a final agency action within the meaning of such term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BE6FC55614F4E5BB3C16542EC4E0057" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the proposed agency action is covered by a categorical exclusion established by the agency, another Federal agency, or another provision of law;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7E1549D1F764598A8B31E4C1E1F8B34"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the preparation of such document would clearly and fundamentally conflict with the requirements of another provision of law;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3140D4E997741A087C50E7983A6F69C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the proposed agency action is, in whole or in part, a nondiscretionary action with respect to which such agency does not have authority to take environmental factors into consideration in determining whether to take the proposed action;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1A8BC7009BB497BB7BD82AA67ED1C9C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the proposed agency action is a rulemaking that is subject to section 553 of title 5, United States Code; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDDE4D1E988E41B38022B3A564969065"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the proposed agency action is an action for which such agency’s compliance with another statute’s requirements serve the same or similar function as the requirements of this Act with respect to such action.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA65D7AA2D01C4D79AB646F7071B6ACA8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Levels of review</header><paragraph id="H87F75A0BCDCE4DEDA143DDE433E24A7A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Environmental impact statement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An agency shall issue an environmental impact statement with respect to a proposed agency action that has a significant effect on the quality of the human environment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C48ECF57F544E7AB9E3D41BA954DF86"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Environmental assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An agency shall prepare an environmental assessment with respect to a proposed agency action that is not likely to have a significant effect on the quality of the human environment, or if the significance of such effect is unknown, unless the agency finds that a categorical exclusion established by the agency, another Federal agency, or another provision of law applies. Such environmental assessment shall be a concise public document prepared by a Federal agency to set forth the basis of such agency’s finding of no significant impact.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H268CE578F3B44BA4990CBF52706EFA2D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sources of information</header><text>In making a determination under this subsection, an agency—</text><subparagraph id="H9FDA8247A79945C0B4CF30E7AA767B32"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may make use of any reliable data source; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA3DFBD7878945B9B63A785141FB0A92"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not required to undertake new scientific or technical research.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC52583D8A10841AF81980171F63BE85D"><enum>107.</enum><header>Timely and unified Federal reviews</header><subsection id="H7B3B12B6160D4D0D9C31B1CE9C022F6F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Lead agency</header><paragraph id="H415912E92DFE4A3095A822EB4F38ED7F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Designation</header><subparagraph id="H7EDE488ABFEB4678AF0492ACB64E668A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If there are two or more involved Federal agencies, such agencies shall determine, by letter or memorandum, which agency shall be the lead agency based on consideration of the following factors:</text><clause id="H0BF04D7AD9E44C6CB40AA0BBBE6D20C8" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Magnitude of agency’s involvement.</text></clause><clause id="HDD567931447C44869749EF41112BAFD6" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Project approval or disapproval authority.</text></clause><clause id="HB7C0013C9BD94905ABD4F98109017FC1" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Expertise concerning the action’s environmental effects.</text></clause><clause id="HE55CD4B045DF49F5A945D09BC0F10479" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Duration of agency’s involvement.</text></clause><clause id="H165F722E2B7B41298EFE5D7761F9CBDD" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Sequence of agency’s involvement.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7198BE80E716460FB599FAF44FAF8147" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Joint lead agencies</header><text>In making a determination under subparagraph (A), the involved Federal agencies may, in addition to a Federal agency, appoint such Federal, State, Tribal, or local agencies as joint lead agencies as the involved Federal agencies shall determine appropriate. Joint lead agencies shall jointly fulfill the role described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20EECC25420C481B8A2E6F313BEE782B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Mineral projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This paragraph shall not apply with respect to a mineral exploration or mine permit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD118ECE99894DEE84843D7A42525069"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Role</header><text>A lead agency shall, with respect to a proposed agency action—</text><subparagraph id="H1D9F58EA573A4D21B9A2A8299E04AB25"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supervise the preparation of an environmental document if, with respect to such proposed agency action, there is more than one involved Federal agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC25E6B92813B4D7C9864CF32F2DBD963"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">request the participation of each cooperating agency at the earliest practicable time;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A66B1ECD98A48E993DA04FA38429202"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in preparing an environmental document, give consideration to any analysis or proposal created by a cooperating agency with jurisdiction by law or a cooperating agency with special expertise;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD01EB2C8841C47FBB623EAF299A40E6A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>develop a schedule, in consultation with each involved cooperating agency, the applicant, and such other entities as the lead agency determines appropriate, for completion of any environmental review, permit, or authorization required to carry out the proposed agency action;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7FCAE0F227C45BB8F35B1BB36792A08"><enum>(E)</enum><text>if the lead agency determines that a review, permit, or authorization will not be completed in accordance with the schedule developed under subparagraph (D), notify the agency responsible for issuing such review, permit, or authorization of the discrepancy and request that such agency take such measures as such agency determines appropriate to comply with such schedule; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC7202F0D4154FD187B8974CE0F023FC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>meet with a cooperating agency that requests such a meeting.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H44DC2DDD20604C6E98A026EC51F64F5A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cooperating agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The lead agency may, with respect to a proposed agency action, designate any involved Federal agency or a State, Tribal, or local agency as a cooperating agency. A cooperating agency may, not later than a date specified by the lead agency, submit comments to the lead agency. Such comments shall be limited to matters relating to the proposed agency action with respect to which such agency has special expertise or jurisdiction by law with respect to an environmental issue.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H328DCF4F7E1247BD80FBE5AD0A0B7444"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Request for designation</header><text>Any Federal, State, Tribal, or local agency or person that is substantially affected by the lack of a designation of a lead agency with respect to a proposed agency action under paragraph (1) may submit a written request for such a designation to an involved Federal agency. An agency that receives a request under this paragraph shall transmit such request to each involved Federal agency and to the Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED2E81F98FD343E2B1D3CB5388B59F9C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Council designation</header><subparagraph id="H60231A3C918A422DA07ABFE6F0C757BE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Request</header><text>Not earlier than 45 days after the date on which a request is submitted under paragraph (4), if no designation has been made under paragraph (1), a Federal, State, Tribal, or local agency or person that is substantially affected by the lack of a designation of a lead agency may request that the Council designate a lead agency. Such request shall consist of—</text><clause id="H8CF8C19E3A5C42769040BB23F3B8E48C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a precise description of the nature and extent of the proposed agency action; and</text></clause><clause id="H41193D928D5540E1893DCA9B3CA92812"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a detailed statement with respect to each involved Federal agency and each factor listed in paragraph (1) regarding which agency should serve as lead agency.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB8A2B5D3BAA4A3183A730EB009AF56C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Transmission</header><text>The Council shall transmit a request received under subparagraph (A) to each involved Federal agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7A9F1FAE90B47CCBA6C758D523B11E4"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Response</header><text>An involved Federal agency may, not later than 20 days after the date of the submission of a request under subparagraph (A), submit to the Council a response to such request.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28A51BB5BAE849A39D2B72261E688425"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>Not later than 40 days after the date of the submission of a request under subparagraph (A), the Council shall designate the lead agency with respect to the relevant proposed agency action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCAF7E5E128C047F7B1EA985A18AC7CFE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>One document</header><paragraph id="H111FA2682C104A13BE380D7C55E3E7CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Document</header><text>To the extent practicable, if there are 2 or more involved Federal agencies with respect to a proposed agency action and the lead agency has determined that an environmental document is required, such requirement shall be deemed satisfied with respect to all involved Federal agencies if the lead agency issues such an environmental document.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D063597C88C428081300DC078AD451D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consideration timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing an environmental document for a proposed agency action, no involved Federal agency shall be required to consider any information that becomes available after the sooner of, as applicable—</text><subparagraph id="HE74F29A835624459BCF99EDDFC6734B1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">receipt of a complete application with respect to such proposed agency action; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD05C4A5B992F403A991517F7F80F481C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">publication of a notice of intent or decision to prepare an environmental impact statement for such proposed agency action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8B2C13A973547BD812A8752FA1F715B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Scope of review</header><text>In developing an environmental document for a proposed agency action, the lead agency and any other involved Federal agencies shall only consider the effects of the proposed agency action that—</text><subparagraph id="H5FDA9ADE06FB401CA8E97010EDFCBD2A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>occur on Federal land; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD449DE2370E453A951837DFDFBFC806" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are subject to Federal control and responsibility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA27FECB9D5D34B4591CA76BB0162D650"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Request for public comment</header><text>Each notice of intent to prepare an environmental impact statement under section 102 shall include a request for public comment on alternatives or impacts and on relevant information, studies, or analyses with respect to the proposed agency action.</text></subsection><subsection id="H574CE83258514CF4AF1BA03B85071710"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Statement of purpose and need</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each environmental impact statement shall include a statement of purpose and need that briefly summarizes the underlying purpose and need for the proposed agency action. </text></subsection><subsection id="H63B5FC76B34C486CBF7735746547EB32"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Estimated total cost</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The cover sheet for each environmental impact statement shall include a statement of the estimated total cost of preparing such environmental impact statement, including the costs of agency full-time equivalent personnel hours, contractor costs, and other direct costs.</text></subsection><subsection id="H10E2AD9611C44B7E8651FDE3A3E56860" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Page limits</header><paragraph id="H0BF20B7053E94A879D45C5B9327F32D0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Environmental impact statements</header><subparagraph id="H0EC62D714F7A4C088EBA97F2D8A2874F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), an environmental impact statement shall not exceed 150 pages, not including any citations or appendices.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFA0478E8FCD4A989264F36B011FAB8E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extraordinary complexity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An environmental impact statement for a proposed agency action of extraordinary complexity shall not exceed 300 pages, not including any citations or appendices. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3D1A02E984E453FAB9ECBE35A4E949B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Environmental assessments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An environmental assessment shall not exceed 75 pages, not including any citations or appendices.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB186401A4EF746B192C75B3A7D5AAE97"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Sponsor preparation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A lead agency shall allow a project sponsor to prepare an environmental assessment or an environmental impact statement upon request of the project sponsor. Such agency may provide such sponsor with appropriate guidance and assist in the preparation. The lead agency shall independently evaluate the environmental document and shall take responsibility for the contents upon adoption.</text></subsection><subsection id="H42953F813435496DBDB62237FADD4C78"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><paragraph id="H430799856AE544D5A9152EFB44815348"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), with respect to a proposed agency action, a lead agency shall complete, as applicable—</text><subparagraph id="H5ACA948176094045AFBA303AABAD4859" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the environmental impact statement not later than the date that is 2 years after the sooner of, as applicable—</text><clause id="H55F9F656571F4ABEB985C35FC2DD2A07" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which such agency determines that section 102(2)(C) requires the issuance of an environmental impact statement with respect to such action; </text></clause><clause id="HCAA8283E9EE54D3E9774C175D9209BD3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which such agency notifies the applicant that the application to establish a right-of-way for such action is complete; and</text></clause><clause id="H2E781A3726DA497F9A465B24D368FE42" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which such agency issues a notice of intent to prepare the environmental impact statement for such action; and </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE0B7E8DEC9A4638A4D2DBE98770EDF4" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the environmental assessment not later than the date that is 1 year after the sooner of, as applicable—</text><clause id="H0E1D17C43D2642FAADFF6B69FF5D1328" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the date on which such agency determines that section 106(b)(2) requires the preparation of an environmental assessment with respect to such action;</text></clause><clause id="H1A53BB2D0772440CB940038062F743A6" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which such agency notifies the applicant that the application to establish a right-of-way for such action is complete; and </text></clause><clause id="H09A70802CA404613A9796D0CE56D5285" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which such agency issues a notice of intent to prepare the environmental assessment for such action.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEF51A8AD0C24C5DBD798FC9D8E165ED" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Delay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A lead agency that determines it is not able to meet the deadline described in paragraph (1) may extend such deadline with the approval of the applicant. If the applicant approves such an extension, the lead agency shall establish a new deadline that provides only so much additional time as is necessary to complete such environmental impact statement or environmental assessment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DFBDC482DA8481380364407885D4676"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Expenditures for delay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a lead agency is unable to meet the deadline described in paragraph (1) or extended under paragraph (2), the lead agency must pay $100 per day, to the extent funding is provided in advance in an appropriations Act, out of the office of the head of the department of the lead agency to the applicant starting on the first day immediately following the deadline described in paragraph (1) or extended under paragraph (2) up until the date that an applicant approves a new deadline. This paragraph does not apply when the lead agency misses a deadline solely due to delays caused by litigation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDA55FD6A531F422ABD34E40D1E58B8C4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H3F0284DB8F124EEA80F755D4D8813C4B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of each lead agency shall annually submit to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report that—</text><subparagraph id="HA31FD6859EA6454FB819A59550A4F707"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifies any environmental assessment and environmental impact statement that such lead agency did not complete by the deadline described in subsection (h); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9673607706F34CEF9E916B5C53F1744C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides an explanation for any failure to meet such deadline.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DFB151576024C26B9BD030A5AE5F8D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report submitted under paragraph (1) shall identify, as applicable—</text><subparagraph id="H3062C9CC2EAB44EFB6B87EAE64DE8CD8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the office, bureau, division, unit, or other entity within the Federal agency responsible for each such environmental assessment and environmental impact statement;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81A19A439B1842BE92F2E729CE2FBF13"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date on which—</text><clause id="HE1F4884F4C3C40959D246DA0EB052B71"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such lead agency notified the applicant that the application to establish a right-of-way for the major Federal action is complete;</text></clause><clause id="H471CF46E43AD4DD894C3981130E856D5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such lead agency began the scoping for the major Federal action; or</text></clause><clause id="HEF3E1B4D8B00436484E1C4E01A4D1AC2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such lead agency issued a notice of intent to prepare the environmental assessment or environmental impact statement for the major Federal action; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H695E2CB5D9BA4EE1B65E813844208EEE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>when such environmental assessment and environmental impact statement is expected to be complete.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HEC3E54C71B6042148310F01D5BD16133"><enum>108.</enum><header>Judicial review</header><subsection id="HCE9699C8C18A4285A0221EC3D97CC4E2" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitations on claims</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a claim arising under Federal law seeking judicial review of compliance with this Act, of a determination made under this Act, or of Federal action resulting from a determination made under this Act, shall be barred unless—</text><paragraph id="HCF3FEF61C1A5450E87258CAE413EA2C6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of a claim pertaining to a proposed agency action for which—</text><subparagraph id="HA33CE082B7A14593B8DBFF7D73FECD7F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an environmental document was prepared and an opportunity for comment was provided;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7DA25959EB674DD1BC25BB00315E85A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the claim is filed by a party that participated in the administrative proceedings regarding such environmental document; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63A12E4D57AE4798BE6AC5CF69ECBA28" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the claim—</text><clause id="HF4AFB3FD2F2541FD8F2FAD518E7216FC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is filed by a party that submitted a comment during the public comment period for such administrative proceedings and such comment was sufficiently detailed to put the lead agency on notice of the issue upon which the party seeks judicial review; and</text></clause><clause id="H34CB40887F0F43B6B2248B7E7636EF2C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is related to such comment;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D5348F98B1A4092A4813AD25B2583C4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>except as provided in subsection (b), such claim is filed not later than 120 days after the date of publication of a notice in the Federal Register of agency intent to carry out the proposed agency action;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F0BE59F8F5443FBAE9B2C7EE622AF03"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such claim is filed after the issuance of a record of decision or other final agency action with respect to the relevant proposed agency action;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5EA24EF6944426BB527DEDF66C2C338"><enum>(4)</enum><text>such claim does not challenge the establishment or use of a categorical exclusion under section 102; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0258A58A6A9E429BB823FDC8FA579AB7"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such claim concerns—</text><subparagraph id="H4435ED22F9F04AB89E816025BD27F560"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an alternative included in the environmental document; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFED348C2322945EE84FAEAC632FAB702"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an environmental effect considered in the environmental document.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9789958CB70A44B3A661B6042BA3EB84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Supplemental environmental impact statement</header><paragraph id="H2B4DD39C684C4828A5BBE935CF4BFFD3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Separate final agency action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The issuance of a Federal action resulting from a final supplemental environmental impact statement shall be considered a final agency action for the purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, separate from the issuance of any previous environmental impact statement with respect to the same proposed agency action.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45663530FDC54A4EBBA7EF6BA37596A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for filing a claim</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A claim seeking judicial review of a Federal action resulting from a final supplemental environmental review issued under section 102(2)(C) shall be barred unless—</text><subparagraph id="HA0F0F17C0F51477EB5DDD6F93ED84819"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such claim is filed within 120 days of the date on which a notice of the Federal agency action resulting from a final supplemental environmental impact statement is issued; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5180CB8261E44C38A226981AC6990BE3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such claim is based on information contained in such supplemental environmental impact statement that was not contained in a previous environmental document pertaining to the same proposed agency action.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9262C9BC9BCA484197F38845B1B9B327"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on injunctive relief</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a violation of this Act shall not constitute the basis for injunctive relief.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1B11AD7EBF0744EC88649F6E9A45692B" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to create a right of judicial review or place any limit on filing a claim with respect to the violation of the terms of a permit, license, or approval.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0BCC6F4245A945E9AEBE32E86FE2D994" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Remand</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no proposed agency action for which an environmental document is required shall be vacated or otherwise limited, delayed, or enjoined unless a court concludes allowing such proposed action will pose a risk of an imminent and substantial environmental harm and there is no other equitable remedy available as a matter of law.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2E122E0D322E4050989D52ED68C2C0A3"><enum>109.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title:</text><paragraph id="HB7CDA3E2F4FD4EC694934BB6BDE6A32D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Categorical exclusion</header><text>The term <term>categorical exclusion</term> means a category of actions that a Federal agency has determined normally does not significantly affect the quality of the human environment within the meaning of section 102(2)(C).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0AAB41669834FC6A72AE7D9F0EE0D90"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cooperating agency</header><text>The term <term>cooperating agency</term> means any Federal, State, Tribal, or local agency that has been designated as a cooperating agency under section 107(a)(3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18B84B668C2646A7847F0A6925EEF8C1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Council</header><text>The term <term>Council</term> means the Council on Environmental Quality established in title II.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C1D1094C285483B9462CD47909E31A7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Environmental assessment</header><text>The term <term>environmental assessment</term> means an environmental assessment prepared under section 106(b)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1883009CCDD4BB491F378DD768EB6FD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Environmental document</header><text>The term <term>environmental document</term> means an environmental impact statement, an environmental assessment, or a finding of no significant impact.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CAF1E595685489ABEB16FF2A5BEEF06"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Environmental impact statement</header><text>The term <term>environmental impact statement</term> means a detailed written statement that is required by section 102(2)(C).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9898815C6AD43EE8C8338CE7EA28E23"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Finding of no significant impact</header><text>The term <term>finding of no significant impact</term> means a determination by a Federal agency that a proposed agency action does not require the issuance of an environmental impact statement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72DC2ABB52214F87896D9AB2CB5723F0"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Involved Federal agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>involved Federal agency</term> means an agency that, with respect to a proposed agency action—</text><subparagraph id="H1910CDA30EFF41D3BA3985A1F7B17FD0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>proposed such action; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3663A7260A1B478D83F9822E675A156C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is involved in such action because such action is directly related, through functional interdependence or geographic proximity, to an action such agency has taken or has proposed to take.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B7655EB39A44A7EA32B8C5337A55354" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Lead agency</header><subparagraph id="H9FBF85597E0941BF8B8A98509010F3D7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the term <term>lead agency</term> means, with respect to a proposed agency action—</text><clause id="HABAFB4E87A97482C9107DEDC5C40AF84" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the agency that proposed such action; or</text></clause><clause id="HBBA9B9F12A4046FC8E60F690AB051651" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if there are 2 or more involved Federal agencies with respect to such action, the agency designated under section 107(a)(1).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB28E61D4908A4042BF2A271E4B488E33"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Specification for mineral exploration or mine permits</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a proposed mineral exploration or mine permit, the term <term>lead agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 40206(a) of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H265E4CB772B54FC29833E6DD882F577C" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Major Federal action</header><subparagraph id="H75B12C81782F489C9788A5E97270595F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>major Federal action</term> means an action that the agency carrying out such action determines is subject to substantial Federal control and responsibility.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE273AE5CF3C48A6BFEBD4F7977B6F5A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>The term <term>major Federal action</term> does not include—</text><clause id="H2D526D9E73B04E57AE00836E93C55DAD" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a non-Federal action—</text><subclause id="H27F2E20B3A1A4CB9A1C9D98B63B1B450"><enum>(I)</enum><text>with no or minimal Federal funding;</text></subclause><subclause id="H3AF315D2715F48D8BE735C26D4273705"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with no or minimal Federal involvement where a Federal agency cannot control the outcome of the project; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H524473B883254F1883684845F281104C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>that does not include Federal land;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H292BCB1F852645B582BA0EC8D53BCF2C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>funding assistance solely in the form of general revenue sharing funds which do not provide Federal agency compliance or enforcement responsibility over the subsequent use of such funds;</text></clause><clause id="HA87E3268815842CDB6A9AB9199920E38" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>loans, loan guarantees, or other forms of financial assistance where a Federal agency does not exercise sufficient control and responsibility over the effect of the action;</text></clause><clause id="H737EBB7FBDA34D508083BFF7A4BBEAFC" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>farm ownership and operating loan guarantees by the Farm Service Agency pursuant to sections 305 and 311 through 319 of the Consolidated Farmers Home Administration Act of 1961 (7 U.S.C. 1925 and 1941 through 1949);</text></clause><clause id="H4E006F1AE957449F9AAD007BBD243A5A" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>business loan guarantees provided by the Small Business Administration pursuant to section 7(a) or (b) and of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/636">15 U.S.C. 636(a)</external-xref>), or title V of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/695">15 U.S.C. 695 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H0D482BA1DD9F499FA09B20D09B5B3B17" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>bringing judicial or administrative civil or criminal enforcement actions; or</text></clause><clause id="H1619637AE5804237AE121095EF20547C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">extraterritorial activities or decisions, which means agency activities or decisions with effects located entirely outside of the jurisdiction of the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD3060D817394B679AA993F53C4DEDF5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Additional exclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An agency action may not be determined to be a major Federal action on the basis of—</text><clause id="H010BE53326B64D3DA44E2C41342E9944"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an interstate effect of the action or related project; or</text></clause><clause id="H34BFA7F783814810957BB90C2E447F06"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the provision of Federal funds for the action or related project.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H47ACBA8909184AA7800E7E5E96A4FDC8"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Mineral exploration or mine permit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>mineral exploration or mine permit</term> has the meaning given such term in section 40206(a) of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD209E83D0CD94886BA6A85303271D914"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Proposal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>proposal</term> means a proposed action at a stage when an agency has a goal, is actively preparing to make a decision on one or more alternative means of accomplishing that goal, and can meaningfully evaluate its effects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E5E56F598CB4FD78C179848E6B7ED26" commented="no"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Reasonably foreseeable</header><text>The term <term>reasonably foreseeable</term> means likely to occur—</text><subparagraph id="H42248B778EDF466A9504C81A68A2A374" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 10 years after the lead agency begins preparing the environmental document; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H863ADE96F8E143C1A99289B5D25668DA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in an area directly affected by the proposed agency action such that an individual of ordinary prudence would take such occurrence into account in reaching a decision.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07E41D6920EC4790B92B29319A3FAA58"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Special expertise</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>special expertise</term> means statutory responsibility, agency mission, or related program experience.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HA8B8D3AB9255413583928445469CAC9B" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>E–NEPA</header><subsection id="HC3E94D0534884A06A64F2E49AAE8398C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Permitting portal study</header><text>The Council on Environmental Quality shall conduct a study and submit a report to Congress within 1 year of the enactment of this Act on the potential to create an online permitting portal for permits that require review under section 102(2)(C) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(C)</external-xref>) that would—</text><paragraph id="HCE4EBC77540A4E3397AA01B360973F63"><enum>(1)</enum><text>allow applicants to—</text><subparagraph id="HFC476754EB2F477EB2F86DB772363DBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit required documents or materials for their application in one unified portal;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H683470591F2F4324B3C60272EB3CCBA5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>upload additional documents as required by the applicable agency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC530EA44E7C54942BAC7B83EC896C80D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>track the progress of individual applications; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E2BCDE978F34DD49D4EA34E4ECB39BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>enhance interagency coordination in consultation by—</text><subparagraph id="H51E926F46BA04FBB88DD242123810042"><enum>(A)</enum><text>allowing for comments in one unified portal;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H933B59E2B351444D9911E69BCECC4791"><enum>(B)</enum><text>centralizing data necessary for reviews; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD07CC8E0842641939644FEEA09361B6A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>streamlining communications between other agencies and the applicant; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H625666BCCD92499A8F0AAC1D6CB6091F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>boost transparency in agency decisionmaking.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0173D46255464D508F0C57A0E4E4F057"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $500,000 for the Council on Environmental Quality to carry out the study directed by this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

