<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0D452422A7D74FD4BF4E09A42D741000" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4401 IH: Restoring Earned Veterans Benefits Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4401</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to establish the timing of the resumption of payment of compensation or pension, after discontinuance by reason of receipt of active service pay.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H60D4F44AD27648BA9B1D1FF2A8D7FCCD" style="OLC"><section id="H6F09F020F30649C9A3012E9AF6083F48" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restoring Earned Veterans Benefits Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H59A0F5582E35441CACB0A199CBE2F9AD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Payment of certain veterans compensation after discontinuance by reason of receipt of active service pay</header><subsection id="H53C9B1C09D0445BD9D3FE910EC1BFABC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Timing of resumption of payment</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id42d0c56def0242d39cfd20b34e6b62b9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id47D1098D1DE14FDA8031511E1AEF9D5C"><section id="idbb5649a87bd7442a9f5f075ac55a1904"><enum>5114.</enum><header>Resumption of period of payment after discontinuance by reason of receipt of active service pay</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Payment of compensation or pension, discontinued by reason of receipt of active service pay (pursuant to subsection (c) of section 5304 of this title), shall resume on the first day after the period of active service. The Secretary may resume such payment if the veteran has not filed a claim for such payment if the Secretary determines that the record contains sufficient evidence to re-establish the entitlement of the veteran to such benefit. </text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="id0f12f63d55474e5dbe220469669eaaee"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 5113 the following new item: </text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id1F0FAF7B942B4025B9798BDE65DE85F2" style="USC"><toc><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">5114. Resumption of period of payment after discontinuance by reason of receipt of active service pay.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id23944e05bc8c479fa7a703bfbb693ac6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation plan</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretaries of Veterans Affairs and Defense shall jointly implement a plan to—</text><paragraph id="iddb663c3e260745759aebee0b7f07dd6c"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to improve the process by which the Secretary of Defense notifies the Secretary of Veterans Affairs of the end of a period of active service by a veteran who was in receipt of compensation or pension benefits under title 38, United States Code, immediately before such period; and </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id9c32f789597e46cca5a8fc0e84a63de3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to ensure timely resumption of payment in accordance with section 5114 of such title, as added by subsection (a). </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill>


