<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H62F2C09D732C4746B15C286605D0C778" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3416 IH: Youth Workforce Readiness Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3416</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001090">Mr. Harder of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a competitive grant program to support out-of-school-time youth workforce readiness programs, providing employability skills development, career exploration, employment readiness training, mentoring, work-based learning, and workforce opportunities for eligible youth.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB85CD6D03769406087E072355A69FCAF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5C8610ADEB3D4C4782BE88A58012D6A7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Youth Workforce Readiness Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAB8782C20E2A4BBC8CC48C0B1E735E55"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to establish or expand activities to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4B540B745CB54CF6AB8AFDA58593C217"><enum>(1)</enum><text>increase access and opportunities for youth to obtain the education and training that youth need to succeed in the labor market;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC4B5CFBF319A4B38927C4F03F9851BFB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support engagement in and the integration of programs and activities offered during out-of-school-time hours through the workforce investment, education, and economic development systems;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H46F3D2C417A64CDCAD4D5E9EBAF4EA33"><enum>(3)</enum><text>improve the quality of the workforce and meet the skill requirements of employers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9D3C04B7F123436A9993041CA99F9FBB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>engage employers in addressing the training, skill, and employment needs of youth and youth jobseekers, and fostering opportunities for connection and economic mobility; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF927072A2633408B8B36A3F7F3F7C9EF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>include younger youth in the education and workforce investment activities in an age and developmentally appropriate manner.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H5D2A77C3819A406080491444E6173E1C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H3A81D3479E9C4812A16FC3A428B2E5C7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community-based organization</header><text>The term <term>community-based organization</term> means a youth-serving private nonprofit organization (which may include a faith-based organization) that—</text> <subparagraph id="H1E5F68063B04464886E266435545EC06"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is representative of a community or a significant segment of a community;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB2F9718098F14F00B1542F585ACE22FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has demonstrated expertise and effectiveness in workforce development; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8810A2E94D364C3F9BA3BF737DB3AF23"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has demonstrated expertise—</text> 
<clause id="H9887284F92634BCDADD53A5A4DC77B28"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the planning and delivery of education, training, and related activities that are included in a career pathway;</text></clause> <clause id="H25319C85A6F94A40BEADF9D51AC7BC9C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in forging coordination and cooperation between educators and other members of the community; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H56C3C7615E9F45EFA2DA083A0B43DB57"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in development and implementation of data systems that measure the progress of students and outcomes of career pathways.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD8B497A2209547D385B58AEFDEFCAFAD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered partnership</header><text>The term <term>covered partnership</term> means a partnership between—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H110180C364834A0A91376513D547D3F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a community-based organization; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBB35B81D04BA4B66883A0F9017F40161"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an industry or sector partnership, a local educational agency, and another public entity or private employer, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1EACAAA9C6F0478DA5D2E4124F931B7E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible youth</header><text>The term <term>eligible youth</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>), except that the individual involved shall be—</text> <subparagraph id="HDC3DA30E09EC45F5BBEDE84745F712BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not younger than age 6; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE44D052F5BB84174A706DDC584CE4736"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not older than age 18 (or age 19 if enrolled in secondary school).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3846EE747EA640F0A7CA26A29E596327"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Industry or sector partnership</header><text>The term <term>industry or sector partnership</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H30E3B78B928646E19F2FCA60D715AE03"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an industry or sector partnership, as defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAB840FDF800C4CC99E6BA126AC233761"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a collaborative that meets the requirements of paragraph (26) of that section 3 but also includes—</text> 
<clause id="H89709220219549AC96A068556F1FA18E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an Indian tribe or tribal organization (as such terms are defined in section 166(b) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3221">29 U.S.C. 3221(b)</external-xref>)), as appropriate; or</text></clause> <clause id="HD79D03213207490CBB684A028CCE5E86"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a community-based organization.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6E19983D349B4433B535C4EEBA652FBC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Out-of-school-time</header><text>The term <term>out-of-school-time</term>, used with respect to a program described in section 7, means a supervised program regularly attended by eligible youth, that fosters learning and development during out-of-school-time hours, which includes hours before school, after school, during summer vacation or another school holiday, or on a Saturday or Sunday.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABC08A04E4654C5389A03F0AEE7C678F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2A6E9D00FB6745E986D0D8CC3E943E19"><enum>(7)</enum><header>WIOA definitions</header><text>The terms <term>career pathway</term>, <term>customized training</term>, <term>in-demand industry sector or occupation</term>, <term>local area</term>, <term>local board</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, and <term>recognized postsecondary credential</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9679E748D04D42DEA002ABAD2DFAF6F2"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Workforce readiness program</header><text>The term <term>workforce readiness program</term> means an out-of-school-time program that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1DD0B29956ED4EEAAA7223624C62B30F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>meets the requirements of section 7;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9DAFEC63677849AA9C848C140489D478"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is offered by a community-based organization of an eligible entity or a related covered partnership; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0735AB8360F84DCE90FABDF386E1FB11"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is intended to help prepare eligible youth for the workforce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="HD4F65EC82B1F4451877939D6AA4EA9BE"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grant program establishment</header> <subsection id="H8EEC73C59D93439FA61F6CBA4AAC4464"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>Using the amounts made available under section 9, the Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB5B347E19D0A4D3087329BFDB6B3A3DC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>General use of funds</header><text>The Secretary shall award the grants, on a competitive basis, to assist eligible entities in planning, developing, and implementing nationwide, comprehensive workforce readiness programs, that are—</text> <paragraph id="H13FF6499E32E4E54A83500AAADF1FC85"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in out-of-school-time programs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDB50C351A27F493582AE613B6A781A61"><enum>(2)</enum><text>carried out by community-based organizations of the eligible entity or related covered partnerships; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDFBEFC0EE9F043A3BCAFAFC0048C9655"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for eligible youth.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H9FF5E1D59D7346C19F424364742B380B"><enum>(c)</enum><header> Periods of grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award the grants for periods of not less than 3 years and not more than 5 years.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H15ABCB29E210403E94AEAC0EDE23E298"><enum>5.</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under section 4, an entity shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9B4B745500A2411A8B91EA4554D995CB"><enum>(1)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H48D24118A30A476C854EA9801E899536"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be a national youth-serving organization with active chapters, affiliates, or subgrant recipients, that are community-based organizations (including such organizations that are facility-based organizations) in not fewer than 35 States; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H58ABD05CB6DD4C63A74653144F08A2CE" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide programming focused on youth workforce readiness in an out-of-school-time program; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6CFD779E98D14CE288E92E729659E319"><enum>(2)</enum><text>obtain approval of an application under section 6.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HABB9FA7603294FCDA0BDEE9ED1A6FD2B"><enum>6.</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under section 4, an entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H46B899103B574FB7B39E5EE0ECCAA344"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of how the entity will implement a youth workforce readiness program in a manner that ensures an equitable geographic distribution of program activities, including an equitable distribution between urban and rural communities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD2C7A4CC242E42F399CDA499B49E8B0C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the proposed program activities to be funded and their locations;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H145C3B0F0E96430691ECA828F07FEEA8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of populations of eligible youth to be served, including populations living in or from underserved communities or communities with employment disparities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEA8BF299B4FF47A6B92D9D4D1618A09E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a description of the effective strategies, best practices, or evidence-based practices the workforce readiness program will use;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B32E31CA9E044ED942734B11A32F192"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an assurance that the program will take place in safe and easily accessible facilities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H46F7E86678FC47A98E2583E03373D473"><enum>(6)</enum><text>a demonstration of how, in implementing the proposed program activities, the entity will coordinate activities with Federal, State, and local programs and make the most effective use of public resources;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCB1A48AF387E4C36AC808E252E80A618"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a description of—</text> <subparagraph id="H261DCC05C4B248DCB5E9F2CCA95487CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the community-based organizations or the covered partnerships through which the entity will implement the program; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H85409926693B4EFA951B1695567212F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if a covered partnership will assist in implementing the program, the collaboration and coordination activities that the community-based organization in the partnership has carried out or will carry out with other entities in the partnership, related to that implementation;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H938F18162A42480F8EA5D571847A899D"><enum>(8)</enum><text>if the program includes an opportunity to earn a recognized postsecondary credential, a description of the activities leading to the credential;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9163C1E457884CB4900300D5EE076070"><enum>(9)</enum><text>an assurance that funds provided under this Act will be used to supplement and not supplant other Federal, State, or local funds expended to provide youth programs or workforce readiness programs; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4EC106B2A11F4914B1B81CD1BFFA1AC7"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a budget detailing program activities and administrative costs.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H911E3E1E07324F2A9BC254E42B7E63E3"><enum>7.</enum><header>Program activities</header> 
<subsection id="H9DD04DDCB48848FD9CFA1282423F958D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that receives a grant under section 4 shall use the grant funds—</text> <paragraph id="HB065425EA61D476FBC9C9D3B3E1F6E4E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>if the entity seeks to implement the workforce readiness program through a covered partnership, to establish the partnership; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H09D49D8555C9463A8946F471F7123AAF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to carry out the development and implementation of a youth workforce readiness program—</text> <subparagraph id="H84DF4E7EAB044043908219B45631AA90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that includes services to help prepare eligible youth who are not younger than age 15 for the workforce, which services shall include—</text> 
<clause id="HC2205F11F3A24E228C3082DC26E0A625"><enum>(i)</enum><text>support for the use of career pathways;</text></clause> <clause id="HC355592FE8864028BBC04ED6D156AA8D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>paid and unpaid work experiences that have as a component academic and occupational education, which may include—</text> 
<subclause id="HCCC32035B3D8465BB71054A9595A8AE3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>summer employment opportunities and other employment opportunities available throughout the school year;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF7931CA198E947A6A076CC5ABDBA5DCE"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pre-apprenticeship and apprenticeship programs registered under the National Apprenticeship Act;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H5E2E9B847885435DB7BFCAAEFF1E9E6B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>internships and job shadowing; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H42258E8796D142D4BD57FB3062ED0F95"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>on-the-job training opportunities;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H317933A51EBF490F9DC14F9530070318"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>work-based learning (as defined in section 3 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>)) that provides opportunities for the application of employability skills, and hands-on work experiences through covered partnerships;</text></clause> <clause id="H1464FDC954C94CA287AEFDEB4EFF5FE3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>occupational skill training, which shall include priority consideration for training programs that lead to recognized postsecondary credentials that are aligned with in-demand industry sectors or occupations in the local area involved, if the local board determines that the programs meet the quality criteria described in section 123 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3153">29 U.S.C. 3153</external-xref>);</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2B6989F0668B465CAD8D327EEA79809B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the provision of customized training;</text></clause> <clause id="H9B46DEC7FCB74DD58AF37595DE956B06"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>education offered concurrently with and in the same context as workforce readiness activities and training for a specific occupation or occupational cluster; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF8A5FD784E75467A9D393C8677F13D69"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>activities that help youth prepare for and transition to postsecondary education and training;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDC6023E9644F4D1287B78A056A14C4DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that includes services to help prepare eligible youth for the workforce, which services shall include—</text> 
<clause id="H8E733D266F9342D38C9B7674ED509096"><enum>(i)</enum><text>leadership development opportunities, which may include community service and peer-centered activities encouraging responsibility and other positive social and civic behaviors, as appropriate;</text></clause> <clause id="HD51A264B55F3449FB1F15DDAC2E87FB5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>workforce or workforce readiness opportunities;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HEE09F6F5B0B14EEAAC110EB19FAEC3D0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>supportive services;</text></clause> <clause id="HE4F5DDDDCE0A48858D733B3886B6251A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>adult mentoring for the period of participation and a subsequent period, for a total of not less than 12 months;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6252925A666740F0B541FC36BC5CBD3E"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">comprehensive guidance and counseling, which may include drug and alcohol abuse, prevention services, counseling and referral, as appropriate;</text></clause> <clause id="H4A770C3058104482B730C91544257BB4"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>financial literacy education;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8580B5A8F00A43F28F86B8CDDFB6968B"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>entrepreneurial skills training;</text></clause> <clause id="H46B06FD9C90145429C34283FCAC60022"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>services that provide labor market and employment information about in-demand industry sectors or occupations available in the local area, such as career awareness, career counseling, and career exploration services;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HAFFABC1CB25D43828D6A28C396B9F8BF"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>activities to develop fundamental workforce readiness skills, or to develop employability skills (such as communication, creativity, collaboration, and critical thinking) that support social-emotional development through every developmental stage, in both formal and informal learning experiences;</text></clause> <clause id="H85C774ABB78B4D3A8F7176F6063D34A8"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">academic counseling to support workforce readiness; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9E401B475FA74E6B92D197F5F27BE744"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>career exposure, through mentoring and targeted programming, offered by local industry or sector partnerships, to provide career assessments and education and career planning; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8100D621F75C42688E862780EF0AFC4A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that may include—</text> 
<clause id="HB183D3FE29D24512B5D28CD1B9F3798E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the provision of professional development (as defined in section 3 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>)) for training educators and other providers of educational services who participate in the workforce readiness program; and</text></clause> <clause id="H0ED6FC7F3C2B40D099856EA53457CC12"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>developing assets and resources that assist an employer or groups of employers or sectors in working with eligible youth.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE0CF27859EF042F893789FBFCDA820E2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><text>The eligible entity may use the grant funds, with the approval of the Secretary, to award subgrants to eligible organizations to carry out activities through a youth workforce readiness program.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H09743673D9E347258859AE1333E8F937"><enum>8.</enum><header>Evaluation and reporting</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1EAAD1051DCD46EAA5AE986781609A00"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measures of effectiveness</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC13AD8FDE8454CCBB3194A37B4AB9B10"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that implements a youth workforce readiness program under this Act shall—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4E7BF3A13F8E4EF9A48E2685045F3155"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that the program is—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3BE103FDBD1B41AB8594BBABE5479773"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">based upon an assessment of objective data regarding the need for such a program in the communities served; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H19384EFE66BE434D846D864E4946EABD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluated on an established set of performance measures aimed at ensuring the availability of high-quality opportunities by measuring eligible youth success; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7194DBA915234E2892B9C3946DA0FA98"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collect the data necessary for the measures of eligible youth success described in subparagraph (A)(ii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2B46617D6E5F4C9ABE23F2ACF6B29FD0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Measures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The performance measures (including indicators) that will be used to evaluate the youth workforce readiness programs—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6446732E1BB34BAC990ABCAEED859EE5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall be aligned with the regular academic program of the school of and the academic needs of participating eligible youth; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H175C152D3B5946F6A35E6B2C299EAED2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall include performance measures that—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3A4F309FF7644FDD905635114AD361F9"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are able to track the success (such as improvement over time) of eligible youth; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H061BAE72ECDF410AB2D66177E93C0F75"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include assessment results and other indicators of eligible youth success, such as improved attendance during the school day, better classroom grades, regular (or consistent) program attendance, and on-time advancement to the next grade level; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E6DF166781E4059A720B4AB07D1FF8E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for high school students, may include indicators such as achievement of career competencies, or successful completion of internships, apprenticeships, or work-based learning opportunities, or high school graduation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8C76AF255FD44E7BB153972B26F2B0F7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Periodic evaluation</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDD7D4E7F1DD04824841C0A14E92548F9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct a periodic evaluation of the eligible entity, to assess the progress of the entity's youth workforce readiness program toward ensuring high-quality opportunities by measuring eligible youth success.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H60EDC1D0574D49E8B48EC89CF945F02D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of results</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The results of evaluations under paragraph (1) shall be—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H92142FB5D15C479F815B98F08A595C36"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">used to refine, improve, and strengthen the program, and to refine the performance measures; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H937A54D545E14290B37AB0CC0FCE8194"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">used by the Secretary to determine whether a grant for a program is eligible to be renewed under section 4.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H358C3319406E45698402E968C88DA55F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>The Secretary shall submit a report containing the results of the evaluation to the appropriate committees of Congress, and make the report available to the public.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HC984687C5F3E4B678FAF197FBC670A91"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></section> 
<section id="H2709F075FA3E44C68F1ADC3BC9758302"><enum>10.</enum><header>Reestablishment of youth councils</header> 
<subsection id="HBA75CF79C43A405B898190FC6610096F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 107 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3122">29 U.S.C. 3122</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HA11F0F4BF5774639BE723EC0DA48C8E2" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HA27F61CBBA554C92A917C13AB7C82620"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Youth council</header> <paragraph id="H3E577993BFF74DE0AA45688F466BAA4A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There shall be established, as a subgroup within each local board, a youth council appointed by the local board, in cooperation with the chief elected official for the local area.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF26E6CD5E31C45E7BED57F558AFD5B77"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The membership of each youth council shall include representatives with special interest or professional expertise with youth workforce development programs, activities related to youth workforce readiness, youth workforce investment activities, local labor or joint labor-management organizations, and education related representatives—</text> <subparagraph id="HE461C4C3AFA44A2084E22AEB333E9A86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>membership may include—</text> 
<clause id="H8F379584F6FC4192A783125FA9D5D8D5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>members of the local board with special interest or expertise in youth workforce readiness or youth workforce development;</text></clause> <clause id="HA81A31AC78134CE095191F3381560134"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>local labor or joint labor-management organizations with a special interest or expertise in youth workforce readiness or youth workforce development; representatives of the workforce, in the local area, with a special interest or expertise in youth workforce readiness or youth workforce development;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H49B10DA1A6B34995AFDA842E26E6B4A6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>representatives of entities administering education and training activities, including career and technical education activities, in the local area, with special interest or expertise in youth workforce readiness or youth workforce development;</text></clause> <clause id="HA763862275E141A9AD66E1FD9621F0F9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>representatives of youth service agencies, including juvenile justice, local law enforcement agencies, and representatives of local public housing authorities;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HAA1E0BC5869444569CD8E66572CCA0C5"><enum>(v)</enum><text>parents of eligible youth, and current or former youth program participants;</text></clause> <clause id="H014C1738BDE140DE82302B82D47A490E"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>representatives of vulnerable populations (including foster youth, minority youth, and youth with disabilities);</text></clause> 
<clause id="H5A461832B45A42DA89BC28E48EDAEFCF"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>community representatives, employers of eligible youth, and workplace learning advisors, with experience relating to youth workforce activities; and</text></clause> <clause id="H3E79CBC37E62426DB6A50E616B431617"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>representatives of the Job Corps; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD14A5EA3B9264573B3454A4E806F577D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include such other individuals as the chairperson of the local board, in cooperation with the chief elected official, determines to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4FBD7905A6F54E0C8C1D4943F1B71D7D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Relationship to local board</header><text>Members of the youth council who are not otherwise members of the local board shall be voting members of the youth council and nonvoting members of the board.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC18D9188A0844FA8ACE84DC6F375D6CA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The duties of the youth council shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="HBD2770EB91064FF5928A2AB5A76196B8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>representing the interests of youth before the local board;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA4C3BCD4DA4F48678B428FD7E545D2DC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>collaborating with the local board to ensure programs address youth workforce development and youth workforce readiness; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5CCBE3EB57DA49308787D057273DB614"><enum>(C)</enum><text>advising the local board on the inclusion and incorporation of the local youth workforce in decisions, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7151CFAEA1E84B12B084D25F20C44DB9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State plans</header><text>Section 102(b)(2)(C) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3112">29 U.S.C. 3112(b)(2)(C)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H30FB176129984255902B0FE2762E3932"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (vii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0FDC5F1020EA4BA6B6E98113B5027133"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating clause (viii) as clause (ix); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0DB39C78E74747BD8EC5D77404087E6B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (vii) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0F21317D0DDC4D708385C1603186B1E2"> 
<clause id="H58B14765CC8041F5A003FCA330EDBFD9"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>how the local boards in the State are incorporating the recommendations of the youth councils within the local boards; and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBF5746993ACC4CD0A2DED6192DDFC417"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Local plans</header><text>Section 108(b) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3123">29 U.S.C. 3123(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H45DFFC8CF334414598A77C09E227AFC7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (21), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB7B4AC81D849465A821AC8AEE8ED253D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (22) as paragraph (23); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC53E2F71636E4E5FA9A0626C4E115597"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (21) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H163CC567F11F4507A9073A39975DB6EC"> <paragraph id="HF8265236E178484F9D618354E39C0658"><enum>(22)</enum><text>how the local board is incorporating the recommendations of the youth council within the local board; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H75B8811944AB4F0AAFFA228EC041EB25"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>Section 116(d) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3141">29 U.S.C. 3141(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H093BBB9E3C8740A098E6C195D6D448BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAA75A193FD26490B881321409E206072"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (K), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD39CBBBE6DDD44BEB321A5DF7E2805A0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (L) as subparagraph (M); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3E1BBEC29827457D890ECE326CA9C033"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (K) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCAD84D321E9341C8AA3D1C4BD4A6BD97"> <subparagraph id="H29131491E9074FA2889C22249C09E124"><enum>(L)</enum><text>information on the activities carried out in the State on the recommendation of youth councils in the State; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC99F1B1ADD148E7B93A83CF8BB953B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <subparagraph id="H8BF6CA461D48446AA28FC02370CBA657"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>(L)</quote> and inserting <quote>(M)</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9D0A6B6040BB4CEE9887FC38FB35C721"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H56B0DF3A907745D4B65B9895C7673D94"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (C) as subparagraph (D); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7CD548E3174C43F5A9D57668B16153E8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (B) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E7C9A3B38DF4D3685E6E531142B70AA"> <subparagraph id="H8C601ECD8BC0446D813B3F21077C1AE8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>information on the activities carried out in the local area on the recommendation of the youth council within the local board; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

