<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD82ACDE48CFB4944AA5CC231F29B9691" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1658 IH: Manage VA Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1658</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230317">March 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to establish in the Department of Veterans Affairs an Under Secretary for Management, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H966B1C54D17C4C1C9DAD6C81DBE59979" style="OLC"><section id="H538F8BC8A39E484BA4F21935F1777804" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Manage VA Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HFB0C4006446A471CB16965AE404D796F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Under Secretary of Management of Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H6A7DD6AE47F94AFB878F1A3D13F975A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/3">Chapter 3</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/307">section 307</external-xref> the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H261AA153FC914BE48CC24997DEB76DEE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HEAC8CF3CCB18427BBEDB92DD4775C3AC"><enum>307A.</enum><header>Under Secretary for Management</header><subsection id="HDCAA4EB4E3E14A008705394360A3FEF8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is in the Department an Under Secretary for Management, who is appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate. The Under Secretary for Management shall report directly to the Deputy Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H322A8200AA6842999D45FF6E7EBC60B0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary for Management shall serve as the Chief Management Officer of the Department and principal advisor to the Secretary on matters related to the management of the Department, including management integration and transformation in support of Veterans Affairs operations and programs. The Secretary shall carry out the following responsibilities through the Under Secretary for Management:</text><paragraph id="HB0202A39865247468FD76D014EB28A32"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The budget, appropriations, expenditures of funds, accounting, and finance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF48CE1084E74406A0F53B45E48D9454"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Procurement, including infrastructure, property, equipment, and other material resources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E64CAE8DF144F9C95C3C781FF776269"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Human resources and personnel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H15D1FCBA4E2C4D6B8DFFB467716C352D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Information technology, including policies and directives to standardize information technology systems across the components of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B70031D9A764B80929C1C79623B6EF4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Strategic management planning and annual performance planning and identification and tracking of performance measures relating to the responsibilities of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACC22737234140E781EF9386EF823B57"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The management integration and transformation within each functional management discipline of the Department, including information technology, financial management, acquisition management, and human capital management, to ensure an efficient and orderly consolidation of functions and personnel in the Department, including—</text><subparagraph id="HA9879936F6464F9EB308CE832F7244D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the development of centralized data sources and connectivity of information systems, to the greatest extent practicable, to enhance program visibility, transparency, effectiveness and coordination;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF2DCB60DDE04033A6010766D571F0E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the development of standardized and automated management information to manage and oversee programs and make informed decisions to improve the efficiency of the Department;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA922D1D11D0B490ABAF8263C635FEEF6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the development of effective program management and regular oversight mechanisms, including clear roles and processes for program governance, sharing of best practices, and access to timely, reliable, and evaluated data on all acquisitions and investments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65B6CCF5A7E742DA9C5575556C8FE5B6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the overall supervision, including the conduct of internal audits and management analyses, of the programs and activities of the Department, including establishment of oversight procedures to ensure a full and effective review of the efforts by components of the Department to implement policies and procedures of the Department for management integration and transformation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H39A464310D2742D79B790789E7C02F51"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The development of a transition and succession plan, before December 1 of each year in which a Presidential election is held, to guide the transition of Department functions to a new Presidential administration, and making such plan available to the next Secretary and Under Secretary for Management and to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA85CB522A6F64900BAE43AF0FF167314"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Reporting to the Government Accountability Office every six months to demonstrate measurable, sustainable progress made in implementing the corrective action plans of the Department to address the designation of acquisition management on the bi-annual high-risk list of the Government Accountability Office, until the Comptroller General of the United States submits to the appropriate congressional committees written notification of removal of the high-risk designation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA3383D6B84443938F7E12CDB30B63CF"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The management of the Office of Enterprise Integration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H486CCCB8EFC0474AAB12984C5E2D0F00"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The supervision of the Director of Construction and Facilities, who shall report directly to the Under Secretary for Management.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6D54BD755274726B0300AD209A8236B"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Any other management duties that the Secretary may designate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HAD3E9E0FCD7845B8AF968842D563EE66"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 307 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HE593B375BAE143BABA7B479307F1BF93" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">307A. Under Secretary for Management.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H6E1DC079A5E1434B893BDA043907AC3D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deadline for appointment</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall appoint an individual to serve as the Under Secretary of Veterans Affairs for Management by not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

