<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1F29974400C5423B9FCFB5E9A3E44B1F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3310 IH: Kira Johnson Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3310</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. Garc&#237;a of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001214">Mr. Mrvan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Vel&#225;zquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To end preventable maternal mortality and severe maternal morbidity in the United States and close disparities in maternal health outcomes, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8B78732E421F4DE1AA1BC882A1721FA3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4045D33931E843EBA5C99761560BCE5F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Kira Johnson Act</short-title></quote>. </text> </section> <section id="HA39ACC064D53421FB980FEB86911221D" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sustained funding for community-based organizations to advance maternal health equity</header> <subsection id="H3D0DCA7763C0462184E7AFC07557389B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall award grants to eligible entities to establish or expand programs to advance maternal health equity.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H55BBC7E57CDD4843A8DD1B41820684B4" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the 1-year period described in subsection (d), the Secretary shall commence awarding the grants authorized by subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD8DFAA3C3C5842E9850FF1AA2BA8FF2D" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to seek a grant under this section, an entity shall be a community-based organization offering programs and resources aligned with evidence-based practices for improving maternal health outcomes for demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEF8D44B8F9874B9092CFA612DC3B2416" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Outreach and technical assistance period</header><text>During the 1-year period beginning on the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H99A043FB16484B6C80F760E06DA480F5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct outreach to encourage eligible entities to apply for grants under this section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE833916A5B21402E890F018EC0919D58" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to eligible entities on best practices for applying for grants under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDADD0BF25605428FA5DE51AF2593A760" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Special consideration</header> <paragraph id="H4F26B5FBB4CE450DBB2471A060B67343" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>In conducting outreach under subsection (d), the Secretary shall give special consideration to eligible entities that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H856C22C1C0004C62AEE43E9996405CB1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are based in, and provide support for, communities with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes, to the extent such data are available;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H460D5D9DBE9144D5BBF4DA3E8F5B9D22" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are led by individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H145A1A83385A4ED5A0795A4EB543B202"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer programs and resources that are aligned with evidence-based practices for improving maternal health outcomes for individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9607A9A405B64FCE8655ECF9789B467B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Awards</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give special consideration to eligible entities that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H608F6EEB0E3C405E9C777749FD5419E8" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are described in subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) of paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H88F5B5679EDF4469B31F26D5A3E952B0" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer programs and resources designed in consultation with and intended for individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA48F14A1AC0D45099C7FFD5913F5BBF9" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>offer programs and resources in the communities in which the respective eligible entities are located that—</text> <clause id="H6EBD5B28253141F5BC4A803AB17126A9" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote maternal mental health and maternal substance use disorder treatments and supports that are aligned with evidence-based practices for improving maternal mental and behavioral health outcomes for individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H93626DA785C94FFBADBB67DCD6590527" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address social determinants of maternal health;</text></clause> <clause id="HC99DB21CCD9B4DD68BF84DC6595D3405" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote evidence-based health literacy and pregnancy, childbirth, and parenting education;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H14CABE1097D341CDAAF42203F42E832C" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide support from perinatal health workers;</text></clause> <clause id="H65835B10F4FA4DD0864631C901BC0012"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide culturally and linguistically congruent training to perinatal health workers;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9DA6E77E97EC4232AE6FF2718B262206"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct or support research on maternal health issues disproportionately impacting individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></clause> <clause id="HFDD9498AB0DF41B3962C278D9EFD178D"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer group prenatal care or group postpartum care;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HAEA6FCE62BBC440AB273612AB6241BC5"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate mutual aid efforts during infant formula shortages, including community milk depots, donor human milk banks and exchanges, and forums for community outreach and education;</text></clause> <clause id="H29643A361644409CABD1E774E8AD45F5"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>provide support to individuals or family members of individuals who suffered a pregnancy loss, pregnancy-associated death, or pregnancy-related death; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H52398539F64E47FEA5444DB498236439"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">operate midwifery practices that provide culturally and linguistically congruent maternal health care and support, including for the purposes of—</text> <subclause id="HF57693CEDB89445F809F256577032F9B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>supporting additional education, training, and certification programs, including support for distance learning;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HB5E07B7CC2704014BB74C5BDC9FC7522"><enum>(II)</enum><text>providing financial support to current and future midwives to address education costs, debts, and other needs;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HDF90CB18D33A4A5E8F16C04FC151147E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>clinical site investments;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HBE86EED4415D4366B3BDA7EAA1D32D77"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>supporting preceptor development trainings;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H307E82AA942D469694D6729B0B95AE76"><enum>(V)</enum><text>expanding the midwifery practice; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H6277FD7F134544CB9500BA6DC75506C8"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>related needs identified by the midwifery practice and described in the practice’s application; and</text></subclause></clause> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEA97823FCC574F828763F7FA3B1A7F01" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have developed other programs and resources that address community-specific needs for pregnant and postpartum individuals and are aligned with evidence-based practices for improving maternal health outcomes for individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H97D21F95FFDE4EDE88D8AA34E95382CE" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall provide to grant recipients under this section technical assistance on—</text> <paragraph id="H482E2261DA83415BA72EC662B5035302" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">capacity building to establish or expand programs to advance maternal health equity;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H85F8DDA480CB44E2BB49ADE1FB160D5D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>best practices in data collection, measurement, evaluation, and reporting; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HACAC3468F1C8470586E4756438947B01" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">planning for sustaining programs to advance maternal health equity after the period of the grant.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA091AD210B2345BDAA3A98F834019ED4" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the end of fiscal year 2028, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress an evaluation of the grant program under this section that—</text> <paragraph id="HDF53533CBEB24BC2B37ECE5BF2F3D26D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assesses the effectiveness of outreach efforts during the application process in diversifying the pool of grant recipients;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H127E97B5A9E048A1A7F55736809D21AA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">makes recommendations for future outreach efforts to diversify the pool of grant recipients for Department of Health and Human Services grant programs and funding opportunities related to maternal health;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3EE56984B34A4A23A58B2939F2A0CBB8" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assesses the effectiveness of programs funded by grants under this section in improving maternal health outcomes for individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes, to the extent practicable; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H867573D1A151409091C9A4BD047A9069" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">makes recommendations for future Department of Health and Human Services grant programs and funding opportunities that deliver funding to community-based organizations that provide programs and resources that are aligned with evidence-based practices for improving maternal health outcomes for individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB114C5740D844178AEA3D60EE852EC17" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H5093F9A1442A427DB2E025199A2BD311"><enum>3.</enum><header>Respectful maternity care training for all employees in maternity care settings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title VII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/293">42 U.S.C. 293 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3276C33F648A40D38AE368B5A62FFDD6" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="HCFEF12AF70294D398BB6AACA57BF67BB"><enum>742.</enum><header>Respectful maternity care training for all employees in maternity care settings</header> <subsection id="H6E447BD363734BBF99D5D16F20996F93"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants for programs to reduce and prevent bias, racism, and discrimination in maternity care settings and to advance respectful, culturally and linguistically congruent, trauma-informed care.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA10B2DE0A9BB404FB1955C5758C9A847"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Special consideration</header><text>In awarding grants under subsection (a), the Secretary shall give special consideration to applications for programs that would—</text> <paragraph id="H55192E0A78E042FF831C6DBF511CA160"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">apply to all maternity care providers and any employees who interact with pregnant and postpartum individuals in the provider setting, including front desk employees, sonographers, schedulers, health care professionals, hospital or health system administrators, security staff, and other employees;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8C2FABCD084A40F2BC447D0DAC94DB75"><enum>(2)</enum><text>emphasize periodic, as opposed to one-time, trainings for all birthing professionals and employees described in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8765724F4CCC424ABE9A18CFC9C19B92"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address implicit bias, racism, and cultural humility;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCDCD8CF1DC31427E9426A52EAF2E1028"><enum>(4)</enum><text>be delivered in ongoing education settings for providers maintaining their licenses, with a preference for trainings that provide continuing education units;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3DF9D65DBD8C4D5E92F42FC22232B215"><enum>(5)</enum><text>include trauma-informed care best practices and an emphasis on shared decision making between providers and patients;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H64BAB84BB0574FA78AECA4013EC916CB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>include antiracism training and programs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H641D3E2D89714AC7A7A700D41F6F780F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>be delivered in undergraduate programs that funnel into health professions schools;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0B5A17D5E9F547B09D1BB1E23FFF8241"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be delivered in settings that apply to providers of the special supplemental nutrition program for women, infants, and children under section 17 of the Child Nutrition Act of 1966;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCADAE6054E274DB7ACEE7A1DCA1FE3A9"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">integrate bias training in obstetric emergency simulation trainings or related trainings;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H77921D6B0AC14104A4761799B8AD7B54"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include training for emergency department employees and emergency medical technicians on recognizing warning signs for severe pregnancy-related complications;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1FD13DB677344E28918B1D1AD44ABCD2"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer training to all maternity care providers on the value of racially, ethnically, and professionally diverse maternity care teams to provide culturally and linguistically congruent care; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC798D3C80E634426A9CDA77AF4C1A87B"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be based on one or more programs designed by a historically Black college or university or other minority-serving institution.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC9A19423BE9E44C9BAC6FA68F52F8507"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To seek a grant under subsection (a), an entity shall submit an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H41D828556AE842CBA0DBE06BED941BB4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each recipient of a grant under this section shall annually submit to the Secretary a report on the status of activities conducted using the grant, including, as applicable, a description of the impact of training provided through the grant on patient outcomes and patient experience for pregnant and postpartum individuals from racial and ethnic minority groups and their families.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2BAB411CBC24455B8A838DB671D28992"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>Based on the annual reports submitted pursuant to subsection (d), the Secretary—</text> 
<paragraph id="H66A54903989F4D45B4B43E7C56C24A98"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall produce an annual report on the findings resulting from programs funded through this section;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H90D41F6A2C9245AFADD2B45812033145"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall disseminate such report to all recipients of grants under this section and to the public; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H805FF3C899504CEA804D4976A738A098"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may include in such report findings on best practices for improving patient outcomes and patient experience for pregnant and postpartum individuals from racial and ethnic minority groups and their families in maternity care settings.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB169871518134942AF403BE6130DD9A6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H919D619683D342B4B18600C85D71A80F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>postpartum</term> means the 1-year period beginning on the last day of an individual’s pregnancy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H735E0482D63D4BF081070E135A538F7C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>culturally and linguistically congruent</term> means in agreement with the preferred cultural values, beliefs, worldview, language, and practices of the health care consumer and other stakeholders.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD9DA4144FCCA4A7088CD8EB607F7419F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>racial and ethnic minority group</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1707(g)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6333FF03502F4AD2A3BA35BB45BE311F" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H1CBF5A598D2F48DF930BC4FA5381B5C8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Study on reducing and preventing bias, racism, and discrimination in maternity care settings</header> 
<subsection id="HD62BA45975E146AEB01A98273517AF9C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall seek to enter into an agreement, not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, with the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (referred to in this section as the <quote>National Academies</quote>) under which the National Academies agree to—</text> <paragraph id="H849A1C6D4D5E49D5A32DFCF012E882B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct a study on the design and implementation of programs to reduce and prevent bias, racism, and discrimination in maternity care settings and to advance respectful, culturally and linguistically congruent, trauma-informed care; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE500DADE33164605BD76B976D92733E8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 24 months after the date of enactment of this Act—</text> <subparagraph id="H00070B07A06A4EF3BC69B16C34BAD09E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>complete the study; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H164304FD54BD479A912EF25812E72D42"><enum>(B)</enum><text>transmit a report on the results of the study to the Congress.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3E5C4F37B71042D1B3A27D10135B34EB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Possible topics</header><text>The agreement entered into pursuant to subsection (a) may provide for the study of any of the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HF6E8D0CAE8B7433DA511852ADABFE34D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The development of a scorecard or other evaluation standards for programs designed to reduce and prevent bias, racism, and discrimination in maternity care settings to assess the effectiveness of such programs in improving patient outcomes and patient experience for pregnant and postpartum individuals from racial and ethnic minority groups and their families.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6B552156CE5C4FB1BAD76E7526181E02"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Determination of the types and frequency of training to reduce and prevent bias, racism, and discrimination in maternity care settings that are demonstrated to improve patient outcomes or patient experience for pregnant and postpartum individuals from racial and ethnic minority groups and their families.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H0EC2E5EAFD394247AA6E17FFA4953CEE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Respectful maternity care compliance program</header> 
<subsection id="H3D48E7C88A734F1BB985C01DCCED2758"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall award grants to accredited hospitals, health systems, and other maternity care settings to establish as an integral part of quality implementation initiatives within one or more hospitals or other birth settings a respectful maternity care compliance program.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC282AEA548814C7AB9CAFA8BAFF7BE8C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Program requirements</header><text>A respectful maternity care compliance program funded through a grant under this section shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H47722456B93042EAA32B4B78909ADA24"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">institutionalize mechanisms to allow patients receiving maternity care services, the families of such patients, or perinatal health workers supporting such patients to report instances of racism or evidence of bias on the basis of race, ethnicity, or another protected class;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H882DE4C1B98A48369DF0924833D97851"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">institutionalize response mechanisms through which representatives of the program can directly follow up with the patient, if possible, and the patient’s family in a timely manner; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFB6DEEF5BC4442FFAAA27BE1CAE58634"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prepare and make publicly available a hospital- or health system-wide strategy to reduce bias on the basis of race, ethnicity, or another protected class in the delivery of maternity care that includes—</text> <subparagraph id="H825289EDF7654195A83439315480E620"><enum>(A)</enum><text>information on the training programs to reduce and prevent bias, racism, and discrimination on the basis of race, ethnicity, or another protected class for all employees in maternity care settings;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8437F81EF8164AF4B4E9E94F9BC260B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information on the number of cases reported to the compliance program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5E391187B4694842BCC89199469FBC16"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the development of methods to routinely assess the extent to which bias, racism, or discrimination on the basis of race, ethnicity, or another protected class is present in the delivery of maternity care to patients from racial and ethnic minority groups;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB499311DBEB49C88F23FF9C8D07ABEE"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop mechanisms to routinely collect and publicly report hospital-level data related to patient-reported experience of care; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H95971001DB8F432AB07CEB079C551B91"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide annual reports to the Secretary with information about each case reported to the compliance program over the course of the year containing such information as the Secretary may require, such as—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0A6FBBBEC78B4E6C9665529B0BE93583"><enum>(A)</enum><text>deidentified demographic information on the patient in the case, such as race, ethnicity, gender identity, and primary language;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3FD59A0B33464FB4BB6B978040C99E2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the content of the report from the patient or the family of the patient to the compliance program; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDD3D0FA1123C4760AFE668B2E5079F5B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the response from the compliance program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0FA347548DC240ECA8F60C9181A45D92"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent applicable, institutional changes made as a result of the case.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA5C8C3DA14FA429DA92FE45B6853A031"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Secretary requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="H6E3185910AC0462A9715B0FCF2B97DEA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Processes</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish processes for—</text> <subparagraph id="H7FDD5356A0A240AAA5B40C0E3570607C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disseminating best practices for establishing and implementing a respectful maternity care compliance program within a hospital or other birth setting;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H196FD76BC532454F8E1D4F7542A96B62"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promoting coordination and collaboration between hospitals, health systems, and other maternity care delivery settings on the establishment and implementation of respectful maternity care compliance programs; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H40413D15D13647C598C418F4FD642F07"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluating the effectiveness of respectful maternity care compliance programs on maternal health outcomes and patient and family experiences, especially for patients from racial and ethnic minority groups and their families.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5FEB47AE1EAE4513A8E99302EC4A2CCF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Study</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE687CF13F10A4EB98C961E184C9180E2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall, through a contract with an independent research organization, conduct a study on strategies to address—</text> <clause id="H1F838CAC9A324A308FB227E92372FB28"><enum>(i)</enum><text>racism or bias on the basis of race, ethnicity, or another protected class in the delivery of maternity care services; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8ADECD22BD7A475997C229A9A431D214"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>successful implementation of respectful care initiatives.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD08815CA95BA4500A36CA02406EDD082"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Components of study</header><text>The study shall include the following:</text> 
<clause id="H301FE479D248435FA2299E9EDF1E15FD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>An assessment of the reports submitted to the Secretary from the respectful maternity care compliance programs pursuant to subsection (b)(5).</text></clause> <clause id="HA623CCBBE54B4A58ABB093F088DF25C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Based on such assessment, recommendations for potential accountability mechanisms related to cases of racism or bias on the basis of race, ethnicity, or another protected class in the delivery of maternity care services at hospitals and other birth settings. Such recommendations shall take into consideration medical and nonmedical factors that contribute to adverse patient experiences and maternal health outcomes.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H082D245F7FFC4449B22FE1FBD468644B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to the Congress and make publicly available a report on the results of the study under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCA1E714ADA31453CBC81AB4FE8B0C0E2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2186ECA98B4446BB82D49001BDCCD8CA"><enum>6.</enum><header>GAO report</header> 
<subsection id="HF307D609AA30499A863089CA3CB0B3E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act and annually thereafter, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Congress and make publicly available a report on the establishment of respectful maternity care compliance programs within hospitals, health systems, and other maternity care settings.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H682A29F5B9BF4C40AC94C6C2CEB50AA6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters included</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H93B720224C9648DBBECCE909FCC677B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Information regarding the extent to which hospitals, health systems, and other maternity care settings have elected to establish respectful maternity care compliance programs, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H8DAD3ECD49B145C8AC091B658930D400"><enum>(A)</enum><text>which hospitals and other birth settings elect to establish compliance programs and when such programs are established;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2C265A58CA1D48ABA171092BC9B11E28"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent practicable, impacts of the establishment of such programs on maternal health outcomes and patient and family experiences in the hospitals and other birth settings that have established such programs, especially for patients from racial and ethnic minority groups and their families;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0F04F7E90BB8455AAE7FEEB6FA8C7C58"><enum>(C)</enum><text>information on geographic areas, and types of hospitals or other birth settings, where respectful maternity care compliance programs are not being established and information on factors contributing to decisions to not establish such programs; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H69D58E3DA3C04F70954B57B0CE774FAB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommendations for establishing respectful maternity care compliance programs in geographic areas, and types of hospitals or other birth settings, where such programs are not being established.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE1EFDD25479843038290416C0EEBC1E0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Whether the funding made available to carry out this section has been sufficient and, if applicable, recommendations for additional appropriations to carry out this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAD5FAFD617834045928BB6CBE27B8452"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Such other information as the Comptroller General determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H3FDA1C12FEED415B88C8F350500EF3E7"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H16E3AAD39E844534A7D26A73A506BFB9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Culturally and linguistically congruent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>culturally and linguistically congruent</term>, with respect to care or maternity care, means care that is in agreement with the preferred cultural values, beliefs, worldview, language, and practices of the health care consumer and other stakeholders.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDC29363B802B4A14977F757336889780"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maternal mortality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternal mortality</term> means a death occurring during or within a 1-year period after pregnancy, caused by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications, including a suicide, overdose, or other death resulting from a mental health or substance use disorder attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE7C9EED8279C48DE968CFDC4F3BFE6B0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Perinatal health worker</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>perinatal health worker</term> means a nonclinical health worker focused on maternal or perinatal health, such as a doula, community health worker, peer supporter, lactation educator or counselor, nutritionist or dietitian, childbirth educator, social worker, home visitor, patient navigator or coordinator, or language interpreter.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6F553B1D5B384DEE8C563DD9F8A0659D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Postpartum</header><text>The term <term>postpartum</term> refers to the 1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy of an individual.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8980BF9DAEA849C297550AEAFEEC6049"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Pregnancy-associated death</header><text>The term <term>pregnancy-associated death</term> means a death of a pregnant or postpartum individual, by any cause, that occurs during, or within 1 year following, the individual’s pregnancy, regardless of the outcome, duration, or site of the pregnancy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3C1B2109743A41B8B6CDF188B9EA9A56"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Pregnancy-related death</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>pregnancy-related death</term> means a death of a pregnant or postpartum individual that occurs during, or within 1 year following, the individual’s pregnancy, from a pregnancy complication, a chain of events initiated by pregnancy, or the aggravation of an unrelated condition by the physiologic effects of pregnancy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H53111023092E4A4A8F2726B9C676A12F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Racial and ethnic minority group</header><text>The term <term>racial and ethnic minority group</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1707(g)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300u-6">42 U.S.C. 300u–6(g)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H08F8B16E7FD6447ABA01C20057307078"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Severe maternal morbidity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>severe maternal morbidity</term> means a health condition, including mental health conditions and substance use disorders, attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy or childbirth that results in significant short-term or long-term consequences to the health of the individual who was pregnant.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30873716C5354E3F92C6FC413D19EFE7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Social determinants of maternal health</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>social determinants of maternal health</term> means nonclinical factors that impact maternal health outcomes.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

