<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H745E15F341DA49EDA3B403CDB0EBB055" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 622 IH: Restoring Equal and Accountable Legislators in the House Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 622</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230130">January 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To increase the number of Members of the House of Representatives, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H68F31C9A6AA540159BC6CB76B3FD32F0" style="OLC"><section id="HD417295F989B44BC8B046F0F05CAFC27" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restoring Equal and Accountable Legislators in the House Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>REAL House Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA27492C995BB4669BCFF36B771B6E71E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increase in number of Representatives</header><subsection id="HAC3C3D15F6064C808B8E5F312821B844"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 22 of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial census and to provide for apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a</external-xref>), is amended—</text><paragraph id="H5E85BA16F877495181D03884C99FA1D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>the then existing number of Representatives</quote> and inserting <quote>the applicable number of Representatives determined under subsection (d)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A209011E9E5481EAFB93EA98A49FAE6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6FB88E53EDAF45F69AE169619BD8E218" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HF9AFA48A5BA9436A8B9BDCB2660665AE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Determination of applicable number of Representatives</header><paragraph id="H1B1365AB1D9F422CB96C6902ADDA4B14"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial number for 2030 census</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of the regular decennial census conducted for 2030, the applicable number of Representatives determined under this subsection is 585.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CB8F7AB845F4F0BB81A78F29EFC927A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Number for subsequent censuses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of the regular decennial census conducted for 2040 and each subsequent regular decennial census, the applicable number of Representatives determined under this subsection is the number equal to the sum of—</text><subparagraph id="H153492F405AE4DD092C1412BE4CADF72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the applicable number of Representatives determined under this subsection for the previous regular decennial census; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H983BE6E00561482EA8715463C2BFC79A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the hold harmless number described in paragraph (3),</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">rounded to the nearest odd number.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC75D0D67351C4A288E4F705475930417"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Hold harmless number</header><subparagraph id="H6A8555559AAB465E8D58F102939D3DF1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (B), the term <term>hold harmless number</term> means, with respect to a regular decennial census, the number of additional Representatives which would be required to ensure that, after the apportionment of the applicable number of Representatives determined under this subsection for that regular decennial census, the number of Representatives received by each State would not be fewer than the number of Representatives to which that State was entitled under the statement required by subsection (a) for the previous decennial census.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16AD8D89B5DE4D9FAE3125421F507693"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limit</header><text>The hold harmless number with respect to a regular decennial census may not exceed 10.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD13393A46F7A4F55AADD933D0C4F1DD8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective Date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsection (c), the amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to the regular decennial census conducted for 2030 and each subsequent decennial census.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD45D699EACF64FE49644E56AFE6F707A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study of facility needs and logistical issues</header><subsection id="H229EFBF0AE8242FD9DC9627F361D42B5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study relating to expansion of number of Members</header><paragraph id="HBE9A7CE75D4D411D8793F7B4FDA501F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Architect of the Capitol, in consultation with the Administrator of General Services and such other persons as the Architect considers appropriate, shall conduct a study of the facility needs and other logistical issues involved in expanding the number of Members of the House of Representatives as determined by the regular decennial census conducted for 2030, as provided in this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2883602AEF5C437DB2EBE6A36826889D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than December 31, 2025, the Architect of the Capitol shall submit a report to the Speaker of the House of Representatives on the study conducted under paragraph (1), and shall include in the report such recommendations as the Architect considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H03DE0BD905D944A5905F12B4E3E15D81"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study prior to each subsequent reapportionment</header><paragraph id="H76BA156FC98F485D9C954417F8A4F92D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After each regular decennial census, the Architect of the Capitol, in consultation with the Administrator of General Services and such other persons as the Architect considers appropriate, shall conduct a study of the facility needs and other logistical issues involved in setting the number of Members of the House of Representatives, as determined by such census, at the applicable number of Representatives under section 22(d) of the Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide for the fifteenth and subsequent decennial census and to provide for apportionment of Representatives in Congress</quote>, approved June 18, 1929 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/2a">2 U.S.C. 2a(d)</external-xref>), as amended by this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H233170BE81F241BFB52528D5B78AB62E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than January 1 of the year immediately preceding the first year of a Congress for which the number of Representatives is set at the applicable number of Representatives under section 22(d) of such Act, as determined by the regular decennial census, the Architect of the Capitol shall submit a report to the Speaker of the House of Representatives on the study conducted under paragraph (1), and shall include in the report such recommendations as the Architect considers appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB84404DC8393480D8E3C7DD919B6D3BD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This subsection shall apply with respect to the regular decennial census conducted for 2030 and each subsequent regular decennial census.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

