<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H16C4D3EDCFCB4FA0803681D7911F8093" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3443 IH: Foster Youth Mentoring Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3443</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To support the establishment or expansion and operation of programs using a network of public and private community entities to provide mentoring for children and youth with experience in foster care.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HD29F62484BEE4A43BCFC45307282EFEE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7316A04F0D98404F991B28203E2DF078" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Foster Youth Mentoring Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H368988EBDBFD412BA5974F4D69775C3A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text> 
<paragraph id="H5D95B89D18E6450A9B7E8EC5592E29DD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Positive relationships are important for children and youth. An estimated 20 percent of youth do not have caring adults in their lives—representing 8,500,000 youth. Children who have a positive caring relationship with an adult can also benefit from additional positive relationships.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD389780BF2674179850D40DECAA3DB69"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Research shows that mentors make a difference in young people’s lives. At-risk youth who have mentors are 55 percent more likely to enroll in college. Students who meet regularly with their mentors are 52 percent less likely than their peers to skip a day of school. Youth who have mentors are also 130 percent more likely to hold a leadership position.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H889D0BE0D4D541F48D5A15FED94ACBC3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Young people that have mentors have improved relationships with adults, fewer disciplinary referrals, and more confidence to achieve their goals.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE09B1B9BF39C4DD78A00E572AE693978"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In 2017, 442,995 youth were in foster care. Of those youth 70,858 were between the ages of 10 and 13, and 101,983 were between the ages of 14 and 20.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE22377DCB55F452A9AB3EE3E6412DC50"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Mentoring programs that serve foster youth are unique and require additional considerations, including specialized training and support necessary to provide for consistent, long-term relationships for children in foster care.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD66A26B2822C455898AD41A8C58772CB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Mentoring programs can be used as an effective preventative or intervention strategy to support positive outcomes for foster youth.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H033ACB3BA0BF4321A7993CDE8602FFC8"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Mentoring programs targeting at-risk youth, community-based programs, and programs lasting 1 year or more are more frequently found to be effective.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAEED7B1F22D846D6863C4D28BF9BAECC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Increasing evidence is showing that peer mentoring and support can be very effective in engaging young people. Alumni of and youth in foster care have noted the importance of the support and service delivery by individuals with lived experience, including peers.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H722A2A325309447FABB0CBB46E78F365"><enum>3.</enum><header>Programs for mentoring children in foster care</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart 2 of part B of title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/629">42 U.S.C. 629 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HFA1AFD7918A14133B0D5BD354720CE97" style="OLC"> <section id="H4797F9BA2A7A44D280BA7D52705E5E4C"><enum>439A.</enum><header>Programs for mentoring children in foster care and youth with experience in foster care</header> <subsection id="H925EA3ADDB68408D8FDE0A43C898CF7F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>It is the purpose of this section to authorize the Secretary to make grants to eligible applicants to support the establishment or expansion and operation of programs using a network of public and private community entities to provide mentoring for children in foster care and children with experience in foster care.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB2C608DF01BD4776815C05D47B311D5F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H770B6DE7DE124E7E8DF1CDAB733D3F8A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Children in foster care</header><text>The term <term>children in foster care</term> means children who have been removed from the custody of their biological or adoptive parents by a State or tribal child welfare agency.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE21CCB0D42E34A0BAEBE9F15FEA7402A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Children with experience in foster care</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>children with experience in foster care</term> means children, youth, and adults who have not attained 26 years of age and who, at any time, were removed from the custody of their biological or adoptive parents by a State or tribal child welfare agency.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEEF3697E460647DA85A0C095287E8DDE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Mentoring</header><text>The term <term>mentoring</term> means a structured, managed program—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5AE50E388B7944B6BB1301C7EF10BD3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in which children and youth are appropriately matched with screened and trained adult or peer volunteers for consistent relationships;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4DBA5775C7D84B2B9B4271406FE219C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that can include direct one-on-one, group, or peer mentoring services that focus on 1 or more of—</text> 
<clause id="HE23009D252CB4169AB0D5E3A4F0645EE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>academic support;</text></clause> <clause id="HCE0D62ADE96E44AEB9B05FC3BED1D7BA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>enrichment;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H36EE7F02CB7043779B716F0943BF23A6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>educational success;</text></clause> <clause id="H987BE2F50E3A47A0B9898EE2A2D72EFF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>minimizing risk behaviors; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8EFD2A4F33754C11A5FBE16C781919C1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>promoting social skills and healthy relationships;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H832C2CF3CE314B82AD479DCD75C2632E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>that involves meetings, events, and activities on a regular basis designed to last at least 1 year; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF1D0C356CBF54B3D896F3DD182BB6B1A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>that is intended to meet, in part, the social and emotional development of the child or youth, the need of the child or youth for involvement with a caring and supportive adult, and the need of the child or youth for positive role models, connections, and normalcy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF6F298AFCB37415BB6C1D124999EED95"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC9979F812EE1438291BA488C484D307D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H897568A502F443379992E3A9CC6D6660"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State child welfare agency;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H188D9827306D47199D8CB1576E6C95E3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a local educational agency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H35B939D119864E6B854B988A13A6C5F3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an Indian tribe or a tribal organization; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H864352BBCD65426FA1A091116BBD451E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a faith-based organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFC8D16117349436997DA19E0E592DD23"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grant program</header> <paragraph id="H1A8DB76C64ED4E06B12DCBF21291A441"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a program to award grants to eligible entities to support the establishment or expansion and operation of programs using networks of public and private community entities to provide mentoring for children in foster care and children with experience in foster care.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H37616289E44C42F9B19DCBDE3C225B06"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application requirements</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under paragraph (1), an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application containing the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H807713A24D9F459CB10071649E5C0F66"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Program design</header><text>A description of the proposed program to be carried out using amounts provided under this grant, including—</text> 
<clause id="H7FC02959A510436090F824EE918195BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">targeted outcomes, mentee age and eligibility, mentor type, setting, duration, and meeting frequency;</text></clause> <clause id="H69E128241D5941B7BB8041BEA9A43CE4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of mentor-child matches proposed to be established and maintained annually under the program;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4637808B97204B39A8334668D9B52FCE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the capacity and expertise of the program to serve children and youth in a way that is responsive to children and youth of color, expectant and parenting youth, indigenous youth, youth who are lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgendered, or queer, and youth with disabilities;</text></clause> <clause id="HBC880B1319A340A1BA76D8F5717926B7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">actions taken to ensure that the design of the program reflects input from young people, including children with experience in foster care; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H224FEA1B98094C4D9F8697FC1752C454"><enum>(v)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H37B2CAD038B24291A7A14725565E0900"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Recruitment</header><text>An assurance that the program will engage in recruitment strategies for mentors that—</text> 
<clause id="HEDFAED454D5C4BADB80B0B308AB2B5D3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>realistically portray the benefits, practices, supports, and challenges of participating in the program; and</text></clause> <clause id="HECF4836817024901B79A1BA6BF549DBC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">seek to recruit mentors who reflect the race, ethnicity, and various identities of children in foster care and children with experience in foster care.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H94665869D3FB45049E1895CFA478490B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Training</header><text>An assurance that all mentors covered under the program will receive intensive and ongoing training in the following areas:</text> <clause id="HFE51239AA122412BBCA369D967FBCB8F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Child and adolescent development, including the importance of bonding.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H43DFB750CDCF402391C7FD14615114EF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Family dynamics, including the effects of domestic violence and trauma.</text></clause> <clause id="H8E5DBB23962149B49BB8329B719228D6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Understanding the education rights of foster children and youth, including those related to post-secondary education.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1FEB021C9D654D9580BD202F0EB5D85D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The challenges of and approaches to support the transition to adulthood.</text></clause> <clause id="H48B93296FA6846889ADE1EBA456EDE91"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Cultural competence practices and relationship-building strategies.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4E766B6AEB9F4FE2A663F45444A50427"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Positive youth development and authentic engagement practices.</text></clause> <clause id="H670B859BC5544BD483ABF72A324C6C8F"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Recognizing and reporting child abuse and neglect.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H63BBABE6325B4F5BA2ACE48D2A7D1CD0"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Confidentiality requirements for working with children in foster care.</text></clause> <clause id="H317E76B9429B44A2A26D645721D13B2D"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Working in coordination with the child welfare system.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0FEF279884E8422888A40433DACA7A75"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other matters related to working with children in foster care and children with experience in foster care.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5642479CCDF144F08F4A9DC62FD89B85"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Screening</header><text>An assurance that all mentors covered under the program are appropriately screened and have demonstrated a willingness to comply with all aspects of the mentoring program, including—</text> 
<clause id="HBC9D1CE359C64F3BB47A3E474A870075"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a written screening plan that includes all of the policies and procedures used to screen and select mentors, including eligibility requirements and preferences for such applicants;</text></clause> <clause id="H5301C9F7DF824FB5B408A73CFF94ADA3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a description of the methods to be used to conduct criminal background checks on all prospective mentors, and the methods in place to exclude mentors with convictions for crimes against children and mentors with convictions occurring within the past 10 years that are directly related to child safety; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HED3016EBB0D24E0BBC28A90FF65F762F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the methods to be used to ensure that the mentors are willing and able to serve as a mentor on a long-term, consistent basis as defined in the application.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H49BC93E52A55465CA25EDB69F6D1B6EB"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Community consultation and engagement; coordination with other programs</header><text>A demonstration that, in developing and implementing the program, the eligible entity will—</text> 
<clause id="HB3D397C1BC3F4DB8A21197AF075DC4BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consult with and actively engage—</text> <subclause id="H80BE724843714ED3A82B91CBF465BF17"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">children in foster care and children with experience in foster care;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H90BEEE8CC6644135B4BD51DC3C0AEEB0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>public and private community entities, including religious organizations and Indian tribal organizations and urban Indian organizations; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H547E725BA34D45A9BCFCB308A867F43F"><enum>(III)</enum><text>family members of children and youth who may be potential clients of the program;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H23399C2092BF4C29B2647B7BD77765F0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>coordinate the mentoring program and the activities of the eligible entity with other Federal, State, and local programs serving children and youth; and</text></clause> <clause id="H4C741A081D06423A901C20D1917FE632"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>consult and coordinate with appropriate Federal, State, and local corrections, workforce development, education, and substance abuse and mental health agencies.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFEA1F23BAE8243B3A255FDE5B8FBAFB4"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Equal access for local service providers</header><text>An assurance that public and private entities and nonprofit community organizations, including religious organizations and Indian organizations, will be eligible to participate on an equal basis.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6634CD0F516442F1B133363DC20EE7BB"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Records, reports, and audits</header><text>An agreement that the eligible entity will maintain such records, make such reports, and cooperate with such reviews or audits as the Secretary may find necessary for purposes of oversight of project activities and expenditures.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H14C83B35EA164AD9B690D377011F65BE"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>An agreement that the eligible entity will cooperate fully with the ongoing and final evaluation of the program under the plan by the Secretary, by means including providing the Secretary access to the program, the staff of the program, program-related records and documents, and each public or private community entity receiving funding under the plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HADE089E1E68B4497981F8BB2B91C23E9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations in awarding grants</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall take into consideration—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAA3D66DC4B4046B18212022944AEBB8E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how, and the degree to which, children in foster care and children with experience in foster care are consulted and engaged in the development, design, and implementation of the program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H617F44E8995C4E0AAC5AAFFFD31ADB60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the feasibility and strength of a plan to recruit and support transition-aged foster youth;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC2DC74B96D1F4507AD0CA8CA73BFE915"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the overall qualifications and capacity of the eligible entity and its partners to effectively carry out a mentoring program under this subsection;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H238D3099AF9A485F86BC124B16F2B2CE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the level and quality of training provided to mentors under the program;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H093A5C8C0B8C4535BABADB25FB31A0F4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>evidence of coordination of the program with the social services and education programs of the State or political subdivision;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HED3125973F7E4B678F2FD8BA1B0D5A4E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the ability of the eligible entity to provide supervision and support for mentors under the program and the youth served by such mentors;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6B6E014EFBBE47B28AC00D259BF25DFF"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the number of children and youth in foster care served by the State or political subdivision; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H414CC000A46244F8BD132EF73844FFB7"><enum>(H)</enum><text>any other factors that the Secretary determines to be significant with respect to the need for, or the potential success of, carrying out a mentoring program under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H25993E095852474A9677103B6B33E614"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this subsection may use such funds to—</text> <subparagraph id="H12327A8155AD41DA826249317C719B50"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop and carry out a training program and ongoing support for mentors;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H06631DA44A4F4D38B963758C99823720"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recruit mentors for children and youth in foster care;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H46831DD8158D44A69AD2D58A027B6E12"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compensate mentors including peer mentors;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA49AF908FF784C6F8F32A6098DF15F29"><enum>(D)</enum><text>pay for costs related to mentee participation in the program; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1B2BE19C8A045D38D06256FFFAE196F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>provide activities that will help the development of a child in foster care who is participating in the program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD2CA50A56D97430C896BD475B174D902"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall scale grants to account for the annual budget and capacity of the eligible entity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H767F23AAFDE54899A9BA48FA09DF6DA1"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to Congress a report that includes the following with respect to the year involved:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H98B13BED056E454E838DDCBD9A524DE3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A description of the number of programs receiving grant awards under this subsection.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDC7FB9D36F684A59B45494B46C2117FB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of mentors who participate in programs described in subparagraph (A), including the overall number, average length of participation, and demographics.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA37578E93BED4B43B7CB56F8CDBD16B3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of—</text> <clause id="H14D31C122AE244DBB0BDFF25EC20B303"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of children in foster care who participated in mentoring programs funded by the grant funds under this subsection;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBE20A06A849D4421946D6EBD9F3AC999"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>data on the academic achievement of the children in mentoring programs funded by the grant funds under this subsection; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBBE45A3E7A814AD49FE8D83014EE0E1D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of children in foster care on waiting lists for such mentoring programs, including successful transition into post-secondary education where applicable.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE10FACF85B9146D092F12D614A577BF5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any other information that the Secretary determines to be relevant to the evaluation of the program under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4BFD63858E4C44C381E7D5B273324AD8"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBAA3CB65E4EB49B7AE4A915DEB382392"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 and 2025; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H08956C2EA03C41C481C463F87D76558B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such sums as may be necessary for each succeeding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


