<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF25BF0D24037455C8FF0DB8D2510422B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5229 IH: Theater Air and Missile Defense Sufficiency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5229</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to conduct a study, and submit to Congress a report, on the defense of Department of Defense facilities and forces in the European and Indo-Pacific regions from missile and air attack.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBD950200C2194D478D6872C193B8DF0C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE6E5C955136D4502AF7F877A788EB751" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Theater Air and Missile Defense Sufficiency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H6E2AE78E6E9A458588FFD219AA92ABAB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on defense of Department of Defense facilities and forces in European and Indo-Pacific regions from missile and air attack</header> <subsection id="H05D4267CDDE34A8EA629D997F53F6B2F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall conduct a study to determine whether the Department of Defense has sufficient forces, systems, and capabilities to defend Department of Defense military facilities and deployed forces in the European and Indo-Pacific regions from hypersonic-, ballistic-, cruise-missile and air attack, or to otherwise defeat such attacks.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H916D0143B61344DF8EE9D9714119CF2E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="H98FD41BF766D4D978C3A0BC77CD460E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than June 30, 2024, the Secretary shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report on the findings of the study required by subsection (a). Such report shall include a specific and detailed plan for ensuring the ability of the Department of Defense to defend Department of Defense military facilities and deployed forces in the European and Indo-Pacific regions from hypersonic-, ballistic-, cruise-missile and air attack through 2030.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7BCB08D02D5D4D0DA4FEBC56E1F73FA2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form of report</header><text>The report required by this subsection shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2E3B2F7200E14DD19CD7855EF96CCA0F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>Not later than 14 days after the date of the submission of the report required by paragraph (1), the Secretary shall make an unclassified summary of the report available to the public on an appropriate internet website of the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

