<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF0309F92BA17436EB625E0504024A06D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4852 IH: IDs for an Inclusive Democracy Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4852</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Commissioner of the Social Security Administration to produce and make available at no cost to certain individuals in the United States an identification for the purpose of allowing such individuals to meet certain identification requirements, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H19DF7959BCBA4A55B9E7BE27F61CF618" style="OLC"><section id="H8904735F973C43F9AEC41195E513D124" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>IDs for an Inclusive Democracy Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA8AA8E4788434AF39146ECD880797D89"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal identification cards</header><subsection id="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commissioner of the Social Security Administration shall produce and make available at no cost to individuals in the United States who submit an application under <internal-xref idref="HF12B87C26597415799E6D75BC5770079" legis-path="2.(f)">subsection (f)</internal-xref> an identification pursuant to the requirements in the report issued by the Task Force on Federal Identification Cards under <internal-xref idref="H88DF88ADE76D43919FC8FBB8204F2134" legis-path="3.(i)">section 3(i)</internal-xref> that can be presented by such individuals to satisfy certain identification requirements.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA17FA1D9BE1A4E07B4A72BDF5D6F21C4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of identification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to an individual, the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> shall be deemed sufficient to satisfy identification requirements to the same extent and for the same purposes that any driver’s license or identification card issued by a State is accepted to satisfy such requirements.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF334E36297C5465E8BA471FFDB0ABED1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Content of identification</header><text>With respect to an individual, the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> shall include—</text><paragraph id="H8C43884AB1354C48848FC98119F84F89"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the full name of the individual;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E9FA37C6CFB4602B210DB3B6B5748D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date of birth of the individual;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC80B40344EE146E9874503BDCFDCC9EA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the gender of the individual, which shall include an option for male, female, and X (representing an unspecified or other gender identity), as attested by the individual;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9835858E90824555A9CDF25687738EC4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a photograph of the individual;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7601724968C34B2680CE21C43D0D010D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a unique identification number;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD13E647730A147F7A4CDB2EEABF51F06"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the date the identification was issued to the individual; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F593FE5199E4039AF6FFCA8AA37C5B3"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the date on which the identification is no longer valid.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H59F3FFD8CE3E4A4B892F9C44360E5772"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Security features of identification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> shall include—</text><paragraph id="HE1CE1ACDF6F94E25BFF9EECD9F2BF930"><enum>(1)</enum><text>physical security features to make the identification resistant to tampering, counterfeiting, duplicating, and fraudulent use; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB299144C22764AEAA72891FCA8655648"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">common machine-readable identity information based on defined minimum data elements as determined by the Task Force on Federal Identification Cards established under <internal-xref idref="H1E7E213F313141959B8DCF2B6AB6618B" legis-path="3.(a)">section 3(a)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H89B6661BE118405A9D368F3149177189"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Period of validity of identification</header><paragraph id="HA606186957EA48108243D14FC56A1FC6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in <internal-xref idref="HA3C6588F01A44271A9585B5D8DBF090D" legis-path="2.(e)(2)">paragraph (2)</internal-xref>, with respect to an individual, the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> shall be valid for the 10-year period which begins on the date the identification is issued by the Commissioner of the Social Security Administration to the individual.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3C6588F01A44271A9585B5D8DBF090D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Special rule for certain individuals</header><text>Notwithstanding <internal-xref idref="HA606186957EA48108243D14FC56A1FC6" legis-path="2.(e)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref>, in the case of an individual with a valid identification—</text><subparagraph id="H66484BEF5B2046919110920AB6D4CE66"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who is under the age of 18, such identification shall only be valid during the period beginning on the date the identification is issued to the individual and ending on the date the individual reaches the age of 18, after which the individual may submit an application for a renewal under <internal-xref idref="HA24600FA6229476EBCD1AD0EB9C5BB92" legis-path="2.(f)(2)">subsection (f)(2)</internal-xref>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75B8E956AE104B87A4B726249304A8CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who reaches 65 years of age or older during the period the identification is valid, the identification of such individual shall be deemed valid upon the expiration of the 10-year validity period for such identification without requiring a renewal of such identification.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF12B87C26597415799E6D75BC5770079"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Eligibility requirements</header><paragraph id="H2D0E1CE0E7574D77A8D323683C7B03CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To receive an identification under this section, an individual who is at least 14 years of age or older shall submit an application at such time and containing such information as the Task Force on Federal Identification Cards established under <internal-xref idref="H1E7E213F313141959B8DCF2B6AB6618B" legis-path="3.(a)">section 3(a)</internal-xref> determines appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA24600FA6229476EBCD1AD0EB9C5BB92"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Renewal application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To receive a renewal of the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>, an individual shall submit an application at such time and containing such information as the Task Force on Federal Identification Cards established under <internal-xref idref="H1E7E213F313141959B8DCF2B6AB6618B" legis-path="3.(a)">section 3(a)</internal-xref> determines appropriate, except that an individual shall not be required to provide documents that include the personally identifiable information of such individual unless any of such personally identifiable information has changed with respect to the most recent application submitted by the individual.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H00F8148962C240159704511045ACCD3F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Public education campaign</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months before the date the identification is made available to individuals under <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>, the Commissioner of the Social Security Administration shall develop and implement a campaign to educate the public with respect to the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>, including how an individual can receive and use such an identification to satisfy certain identification requirements.</text></subsection><subsection id="H354F9278945E42B2A142B2E528CC1BCE"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Postal Service application process</header><paragraph id="HED1469EDED8C4165B882D6EE154ACEB8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Postmaster General of the United States Postal Service shall, in consultation with the Commissioner of the Social Security Administration, develop and implement a process pursuant to the requirements of <internal-xref idref="H08AF13B490474CC499CE5D649E45F7E4" legis-path="2.(h)(2)">paragraph (2)</internal-xref> that enables individuals to apply for the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> through the United States Postal Service, including a process with respect to an application for a first-time identification and a renewal of such identification, which shall be modeled after the process with respect to applications for a passport through the Postal Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08AF13B490474CC499CE5D649E45F7E4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Process requirements</header><text>The process developed under <internal-xref idref="HED1469EDED8C4165B882D6EE154ACEB8" legis-path="2.(h)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref> shall include, with respect to an individual, an option to—</text><subparagraph id="HEB601C4707E1494595B86F9C41BAF1CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>receive full service at a post office location, including by providing photography services at no cost to the individual;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46BC570332104D5FA14E19CB466A74C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit an application online through the website of the Postal Service;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BB3C8F734EA4805AB2249CFEFA16675"><enum>(C)</enum><text>mail a written application described in <internal-xref idref="HF12B87C26597415799E6D75BC5770079" legis-path="2.(f)">subsection (f)</internal-xref> through the mail service of the Postal Service at no cost to the individual; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF49D0BE94F847A0897CB3347ED2204A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>with respect to an approved identification of an individual, receive such identification through mail service to the individual’s address or a post office location, at the option of the individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H95918D5919274946B442BEE7765C81C5" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>State defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the United States Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text></subsection></section><section id="HBF616C114EDD49CDB908B87CDE438081" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>3.</enum><header>Task Force on Federal Identification Cards</header><subsection id="H1E7E213F313141959B8DCF2B6AB6618B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established a Task Force on Federal Identification Cards (in this section referred to as the <quote>Task Force</quote>) for the purpose of determining the requirements to produce and make available the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">section 2(a)</internal-xref>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HCF76CD0E15064FEB855B5BCC5EF88D43"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall be composed of at least 9 members as follows:</text><paragraph id="HE8FF7A77EAF94694AC9F89C3109E0573"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Commissioner of the Social Security Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8C0E641E60C4C1DBB6FE68BDA04F6F7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from the Election Assistance Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3841D12ECF0746EB8466BD0ACD79D3FA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from the Domestic Policy Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61A200C9428D45C2A0F1D4A27996F340"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At least 1 representative from the United States Postal Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H093E08674433456AA7BA16526F5EFFBD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6097FD2168DF400292A5A27BC9F801AA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from the Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C199C9DD8704C5091196281713206F7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from the Department of Education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3EF4B3236F3A4F53A2AF2CB100A30EF4"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At least 1 representative from the Department of Labor.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4707638AC02D4D5598D700C909356D6E"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At least 1 representative from the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB03CC23AFAD54806830886618521A63C"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner of the Social Security Administration, in collaboration with the representatives described in paragraphs (2) through (9), may appoint such other individuals with relevant expertise or experience as the Task Force shall determine appropriate and the Task Force shall, with respect to any such appointees, make efforts to ensure that populations that have been disproportionately affected by the lack of access to identification are represented. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1340038A1628437A8C9E9DF78A1BEFDA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deadline for appointment</header><text>All appointments to the Task Force shall be made not later than 8 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6B5525B6DDF64B588978AEF200BD5DBC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Any vacancy in the Task Force shall be filled in the same manner as the original appointment.</text></subsection><subsection id="H394C817B5D7F447BB9B318AA94E1B37C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prohibition on compensation of Federal employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of the Task Force who are full-time officers or employees of the United States may not receive additional pay, allowances, or benefits by reason of their service on the Task Force.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1F19DCE801904EE593DEFCA118DF8C8E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in <internal-xref idref="H394C817B5D7F447BB9B318AA94E1B37C" legis-path="3.(e)">subsection (e)</internal-xref>, each member shall receive travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H07CB332841FF4A778904C8F1651288F2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Support staff; administrative services</header><paragraph id="HEA931D9653774B1592956A6253379B74"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Support staff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner of the Social Security Administration, any representatives from the Election Assistance Commission, and any representatives from the Domestic Policy Council shall provide support staff for the Task Force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5231C669B80F4CE9A51D2E2BA1BD64D9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon the request of the Task Force, the Commissioner of the Social Security Administration, any representatives from the Election Assistance Commission, and any representatives from the Domestic Policy Council shall provide any information, administrative services, and supplies that such Commissioner and representatives jointly consider necessary for the Task Force to carry out its duties under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H286883761A5A406386FD5B4ECCA302B5"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of Federal Advisory Committee Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) shall not apply to the Task Force.</text></subsection><subsection id="H88DF88ADE76D43919FC8FBB8204F2134"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Report on requirements for producing and making identifications available</header><paragraph id="H91F7FC2D65534618BAC5CAD5326CC30D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Task Force shall issue a report regarding the requirements to produce and make available the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">section 2(a)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBD8F8F84DDF44B9A58FBBD3A46539BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibiting unauthorized disclosure of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Task Force shall include in the report issued under this subsection a requirement that the Commissioner of Social Security and the Postmaster General shall establish procedures to prevent the unauthorized disclosure of any information obtained with respect to individuals who seek assistance in obtaining the identification described in section 2(a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H310A47B9B08040F3B5678234B7860184"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Development of voluntary best practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Task Force shall develop and publish recommendations for voluntary best practices for nonprofit organizations and entities that provide services to vulnerable populations with respect to how such organizations and entities can assist individuals to obtain the identification described in <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">section 2(a)</internal-xref>, which shall include—</text><paragraph id="HE75B859705C24A819A87233F11DC3F8E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>recommendations with respect to how such organizations and entities can provide full service to individuals to obtain such identification; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F9802490B5B40B9AF7286E3398FEF68"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations to minimize the barriers faced by such individuals, including individuals from groups which have been disproportionately affected by the lack of access to identification, in obtaining documentation of the information necessary to obtain the identification.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCFB9E39CF8C04A20BF36A4C7535F91DD"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Task Force shall terminate on the date the identification is made available to individuals under <internal-xref idref="H84113955B2774B0592FACB6815721E0D" legis-path="2.(a)">section 2(a)</internal-xref>.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB4C48694F6D94595B5CAEAEF2EB23646"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

