<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7558DB4B997B4B6982C1232A5A683D67" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5342 IH: Equal Treatment of Public Servants Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5342</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230905">September 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000375">Mr. Arrington</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000377">Ms. Granger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001224">Mr. Moran</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001199">Mr. Smucker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title II of the Social Security Act to replace the windfall elimination provision with a formula equalizing benefits for certain individuals with noncovered employment, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H324F5126AB0F4D5BB6A4AFD127FA9207" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H911DF9CE4C424C9EB86B8BD3744592FD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Equal Treatment of Public Servants Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H15DC72924EC54783BD636FAC36A24E30"><enum>2.</enum><header>Replacement of the windfall elimination provision with a formula equalizing benefits for certain individuals with noncovered employment</header> <subsection id="HDDBA634F58BA418F92CBFE5621BB30CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 215(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/415">42 U.S.C. 415(a)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after paragraph (7) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA52880DC92344E3DAA1F8BE7CA6A5412" style="traditional"> 
<paragraph id="HAA3210DFB46B4D1588D0C11AF35C1346" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3194916FEA214650B5D3790407DD3CC3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an individual whose primary insurance amount would be computed under paragraph (1) of this subsection—</text> <clause id="H7A44131E33EC4081A0884FFB59D8F7D2" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who first becomes eligible for an old-age or disability insurance benefit after 2067,</text></clause> 
<clause id="HEB2B8ABEA5534366BC33C5E0FB9CA244" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>who subsequently becomes entitled to such benefit, and</text></clause> <clause id="H26CCA8601CAB4AD19E3018484CEF8410" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>who has earnings derived from noncovered service performed in a year after 1977,</text></clause></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph" indent="subsection">the primary insurance amount of such individual shall be the amount computed or recomputed under this paragraph. </continuation-text> 
<subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF7AA745D0FE54F1B964F4702F00DC238" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The primary insurance amount of an individual described in subparagraph (A), as computed or recomputed under this paragraph, shall be the product derived by multiplying—</text> <clause id="HDF1E77F8461F4954810B5F2B9F24443A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the individual’s primary insurance amount, as determined under paragraph (1) of this subsection and subparagraph (C) of this paragraph, by</text></clause> 
<clause id="H786714CA4126478AA6280CFCF5909BE4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a fraction—</text> <subclause id="HA0B879A69B8140BC8AFE57204894E4CB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the numerator of which is the individual’s average indexed monthly earnings (determined without regard to subparagraph (C)), and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H26E8E810EB8142A78D70C468B3281702"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the denominator of which is an amount equal to the individual’s average indexed monthly earnings (as determined under subparagraph (C)),</text></subclause></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph" indent="subsection">rounded, if not a multiple of $0.10, to the next lower multiple of $0.10. </continuation-text></subparagraph> <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H224FC53D482F41669FB88D936C08AF3F" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4D9CA99E46C947338DDDB9BEAB8BFECD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>For purposes of determining an individual’s primary insurance amount pursuant to clauses (i) and (ii)(II) of subparagraph (B), the individual’s average indexed monthly earnings shall be determined by treating all recorded noncovered earnings (as defined in clause (ii)(I)) derived by the individual from noncovered service performed in each year after 1977 as <term>wages</term> (as defined in section 209 for purposes of this title), which shall be treated as included in the individual’s adjusted total covered earnings (as defined in clause (ii)(II)) for such calendar year together with amounts consisting of <term>wages</term> (as so defined without regard to this subparagraph) paid during such calendar year and self-employment income (as defined in section 211(b)) for taxable years ending with or during such calendar year.</text></clause> 
<clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD238E72DAC014C1C9A491653E03ED4D8" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>For purposes of this subparagraph:</text> <subclause id="HD3A57E26A6104382A46F7C5D580C007D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The term <term>recorded noncovered earnings</term> means earnings derived from noncovered service (other than noncovered service as a member of a uniformed service (as defined in section 210(m)) for which satisfactory evidence is determined by the Commissioner to be available in the records of the Commissioner.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H94412296DAD844C1A413ABB7E27BEF78"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The term <term>adjusted total covered earnings</term> means, in connection with an individual for any calendar year, the sum of the wages paid to the individual during such calendar year (as adjusted under subsection (b)(3)) plus the self-employment income derived by the individual during any taxable year ending with or during such calendar year (as adjusted under subsection (b)(3)).</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HD4FCC64C1FF64D8AB25C2CCC63E2ACA4" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner of Social Security shall provide by regulation or other public guidance for methods for determining whether satisfactory evidence is available in the records of the Commissioner for earnings for noncovered service (other than noncovered service as a member of a uniformed service (as defined in section 210(m))) to be treated as recorded noncovered earnings. Such methods shall provide for reliance on earnings information which is provided to the Commissioner by employers and which, as determined by the Commissioner, constitute a reasonable basis for treatment of earnings for noncovered service as recorded noncovered earnings. In making determinations under this clause, the Commissioner shall also take into account any documentary or other evidence of earnings derived from noncovered service by an individual which is provided by the individual to the Commissioner and which the Commissioner considers appropriate as a reasonable basis for treatment of such earnings as recorded noncovered earnings.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H775FBE7D048E4F28A1CC72B154068153" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon the death of an individual whose primary insurance amount is computed or recomputed under this paragraph, such primary insurance amount shall be computed or recomputed under paragraph (1) of this subsection.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6333C1B89F2145FFA18E1D9CA34A01F7" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any individual whose primary insurance amount would be computed under this paragraph who first becomes entitled after 1985 to a monthly periodic payment made by a foreign employer or foreign country that is based in whole or in part upon noncovered service, the primary insurance amount of such individual shall be computed or recomputed under paragraph (7) or paragraph (1), as applicable, for months beginning with the first month of the individual’s initial entitlement to such monthly periodic payment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1355E397C2D7424F9F0D22ADD73A33AA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Section 215(a)(7)(A) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/415">42 U.S.C. 415(a)(7)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H6E9892CFCFE3406DB6F86584590A1679"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H18F0A8E036A440A09EC55DC827C3CE5F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>after 1985</quote> and inserting <quote>after 1985 and before 2068</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAFC0C9A99D4D4814B28AFBBA2B64A772"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD7E6CF2A767B4CDDB7143B9C3DA92698"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (ii)—</text> <subparagraph id="H3AE86F816C5540DDB964F1F1697C1FCC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>after 1985</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>after 1985 and before 2068</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF963D47C831D4D6B9111078CB8927569"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBD5F22F81FA34B48AB72605D42FFFD2F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (ii) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H74CFF98EBF334DBB8375AB7DC8FA9F4D" style="OLC"> 
<clause id="H81DC97828C2F49FFAE5272429E913790" indent="up2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is an individual described in paragraph (8)(E),</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02192DC702D048A4B6BC0E1919C5E8CA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking <quote>hereafter in this paragraph and in subsection (d)(3)</quote> and inserting <quote>in this paragraph, paragraphs (8) and (9), and subsection (d)(3)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H68602C059D5045AC9D4893B5BECA2483"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to monthly insurance benefits payable on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H0B0F2EA2E55247D7A0646183788E8C21"><enum>3.</enum><header>Benefit calculation during transition period</header> <subsection id="H6461F19490A748C286A9A79BBA3E6EEF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 215(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/415">42 U.S.C. 415(a)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, is further amended by inserting after paragraph (8) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF85F6A68970F4028943BE9FDE426A69E" style="traditional"> 
<paragraph id="H8C43C18D90FD47E5A560D5D39817A3C5" indent="up1"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an individual whose primary insurance amount would be computed under paragraph (1) of this subsection—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H70AAACC0B7F34CF4900DDE081789D843"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who first becomes eligible for an old-age or disability insurance benefit after 2024 and before 2068,</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6C0B15ED9A6C4F0EA73A4460B9FF6583"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who subsequently becomes entitled to such benefit, and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF44A9AA9144E4BD1896933FBE8EF7817"><enum>(C)</enum><text>who has earnings derived from noncovered service performed in a year after 1977,</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subsection">the primary insurance amount of such individual shall be the higher of the amount computed or recomputed under paragraph (7) without regard to this paragraph or the amount that would be computed or recomputed under paragraph (8) if the individual were an individual described in subparagraph (A) of such paragraph.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE03FF81E807040E186B100CBBF9F3BD4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 215(a)(7)(A) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/415">42 U.S.C. 415(a)(7)(A)</external-xref>), as amended by section 2(b), is further amended by striking <quote>shall be computed or recomputed</quote> and inserting <quote>shall, subject to paragraph (9), be computed or recomputed</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H0D3F11A2B94F428D84BCD365CDA3BD1D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to monthly insurance benefits payable on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H545636D2B263442EBFFE542965B7A705"><enum>4.</enum><header>Additional monthly payment for individuals whose benefit amount is reduced by the windfall elimination provision</header> 
<subsection id="HC5564D04898B4FF8B908475046485018"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 215(a) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/415">42 U.S.C. 415(a)</external-xref>), as amended by sections 2 and 3, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF1E9998664DD476DB6FACAE38A9AD4E7" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H718F462F06D341C780E380A9C79D8A1C" indent="up1"><enum>(10)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H185B26C98D0A459CA84BBB3B2E6E055F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For any month beginning at least 270 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Equal Treatment of Public Servants Act of 2023</short-title>, the Commissioner of Social Security shall, subject to subparagraphs (C) and (D), make an additional monthly payment of $100 to each individual who is an eligible individual for such month, and an additional monthly payment of $50 to each individual (other than an eligible individual) who is entitled to a benefit under section 202 for such month on the basis of the wages and self-employment income of such eligible individual.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEC4F9928EE1E4E9AB399DE6764CEADFA" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <quote>eligible individual</quote> for a month means an individual who—</text> <clause display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC3E8753162C6443791D3D133A7D1AA0F"><enum>(i)</enum> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2F5D969D6D9B4885B3B46CE6A9CC7D4A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>first becomes eligible for an old-age or disability insurance benefit under this title before 2025, or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HDE19915E8AED4495891967A52DF1C27F" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is an individual described in paragraph (8)(E), and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HEAC9E8B2A62E4EECA35B37061327E955"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is entitled to an old-age or disability insurance benefit under this title for such month based on a primary insurance amount that was computed or recomputed under paragraph (7) (and not subsequently recomputed under any other paragraph of this subsection).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H701EE7FCAEBB42F48DDF32C7C3E8B739" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any case in which this title provides that no monthly benefit under section 202 or 223 shall be paid to an individual for a month, no additional monthly payment shall be paid to the individual for such month. This subparagraph shall not apply in the case of an individual whose monthly benefit under section 202 or 223 is reduced, regardless of the amount of the reduction, based on the individual’s receipt of other income or benefits for such month or the application of section 203(a) or due to the adjustment or recovery of an overpayment under section 204.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD240D8AAD9804E82AEBB3656715FC9AE" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H277D089DB3CE4D488E2FB78F986965A4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>An individual is not entitled to receive more than one additional monthly payment for a month under this paragraph.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H79F9E8A5B78F4BCE88CD96DEE13ACC87" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>An eligible individual who is entitled to a benefit under section 202 on the basis of the wages and self-employment income of another eligible individual for a month shall receive an additional monthly payment under this paragraph in the amount of $100 for such month.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCD7A74A1610B4C8AA3D3A7B591BC283C" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Except for purposes of adjustment or recovery of an overpayment under section 204, an additional monthly payment under this paragraph shall not be subject to any reduction or deduction under this title.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H251DEA87256148CD918620BF9EA55BFF" indent="up1"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever benefit amounts under this title are increased by any percentage effective with any month as a result of a determination made under subsection (i), each of the dollar amounts in subparagraph (A) shall be increased by the same percentage for months beginning with such month.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H5EA38F32D5224195A543C2F992BAB61B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to monthly insurance benefits payable for months beginning at least 270 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H96663D75FEA945A596E39DE5E8A5A7CB"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reporting of noncovered earnings on social security account statements</header> 
<subsection id="HAF2D3C9DBD844CD89B750EBC70A60D5F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1143(a)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-13">42 U.S.C. 1320b–13(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H0A09B9E36C5A4D678E951E665902E97C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) through (E) as subparagraphs (C) through (F); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC18FED21556C4B30B5CDF26C1D57B061"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02D55AE896C54ABBBD8EE462D84B86B6" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H8B806A3B30994B2B84C9871242B5474C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount of earnings derived by the eligible individual from service performed after 1977 which did not constitute employment (as defined in section 210), not including service as a member of a uniformed service (as defined in section 210(m)), as shown by the records of the Commissioner at the date of the request;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB09B976EE87044BBB88C64F64DEDEC41"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to Social Security account statements issued on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HD875117491F64509A47D6F87D0D8D74C"><enum>6.</enum><header>Study on partnering with State and local pension systems</header> <subsection id="H00FA50D818B24D5488A38A363F39BE96"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header> <paragraph id="H0BE015B0F167481F9934A120327BFCAF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commissioner of Social Security shall study and test the administrative feasibility of partnering with State and local pension systems, or other governmental entities, to improve the collection and sharing of information relating to State and local noncovered pensions.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H367931946E04481E8336AD3852F61781"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination with State and local pension systems</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the study described in paragraph (1), the Commissioner shall coordinate with State and local pension systems that reflect the diversity of systems and individual experiences to explore the development of automated data exchange agreements that facilitate reporting of information relating to noncovered pensions.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFFB6899450594A9BB40ADAFF7C8DC134"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner of Social Security shall conclude the study described in subsection (a) not later than 4 years after the date of enactment of this Act. As soon as possible after conclusion of the study and not later than 4<fraction>1/2</fraction> years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Commissioner shall submit to the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Finance of the Senate a report on the results of the study. Such report shall include the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H80CF2EF861D74122B4C81C1F2CEDF00A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A discussion of how the automated data exchange agreements could be implemented to cover noncovered pensions nationally, including the range of implementation timelines across State and local pension systems, or with other governmental entities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H994395B7FEB04B7DB6640B107C7E4850"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An analysis of the barriers to developing automated data exchange agreements and lessons learned that can help address these barriers.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA405E74AED9B487780F4C40C17DCC283"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of alternative methods for obtaining information related to noncovered pensions, and an analysis of the barriers to obtaining noncovered pension data through such methods.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9E70BC82214C46EE984129E7368F194D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An explanation of how coverage information is obtained by the Social Security Administration when an individual purchases service credits to apply to a new covered or noncovered pension after moving from another covered or noncovered pension within the State or in another State.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H77898593A0A349E799FEDCDE883333BD"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An estimate of the total amount, as of the date of the enactment of this Act, of noncovered pensions not reported to the Social Security Administration as a result of noncompliance with voluntary reporting policies.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD79074966FC94057B2096262811BF6E3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State and local pension information To be requested by the Commissioner</header><text>Section 202 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/402">42 U.S.C. 402</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after subsection (l) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF6C1539F62184A3ABB6A715D444F3A46" style="traditional"> 
<subsection id="HB958576AE8D0461FBA8824657A1F4040"><enum>(m)</enum><header>State and local pension information To be requested by the Commissioner</header> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1CA002C0EFC43BDB271236A13231D7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commissioner may partner with States to request information, including the information specified in paragraph (2), with respect to any designated distribution (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/3405">section 3405(e)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) from an employer deferred compensation plan (as defined in section 3405(e)(5) of such Code) of the State (or political subdivision thereof) to a participant of such plan in any case in which any portion of such participant’s earnings for service under such plan did not constitute <quote>employment</quote> as defined in section 210 for purposes of this title.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA6086413DBC3467DAD97859F6DE84E22"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The information specified in this paragraph is the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H73FA367524504AF2A883B655A51F1804"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The name and Social Security account number of the participant receiving the designated distribution.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H67BF733D464A4583932985A8CCC8714F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The dollar amount of the designated distribution and the date paid.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD51BE72F286F4403AB4B12AA21C1A499"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The date on which the participant initially became eligible for a designated distribution under the plan and, if different, the date of payment of the initial designated distribution.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H266071B25FE34E9898CD8B05262D546A"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The dates of each period of service under the plan that did not constitute <quote>employment</quote> as defined in section 210 for purposes of this title, and the dates of any other period of service under the plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H522C3DFF213441D0B3D593E18768C86A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="HDA816C67001B4E5FA82CC71B44F1E31F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>noncovered pension</quote> means a pension any part of which is based on noncovered service (within the meaning of section 215(a)(7) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/415">42 U.S.C. 415(a)(7)</external-xref>)); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H98D4BD536B8848358FA695B1D1D34A11"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>covered pension</quote> means any other pension.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

