<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAA7FDD3E65494BD0B6B4F340E3D30531" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3998 IH: Jackie Walorski Enhancing Necessary Data on Illegal School Bus Passing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3998</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Y000067">Mr. Yakym</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a program to monitor and gather data on incidents of illegal passing of stopped school buses, develop a national public safety messaging campaign, training materials, and model legislation to reduce such incidents, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H29AE921FD85246E6A771A68611775B32" style="OLC"><section id="HBC55D7E3430342899F3E81ADA2D2AEF8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Jackie Walorski Enhancing Necessary Data on Illegal School Bus Passing Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H57F0A06E4BE84A70AD15271CACF5EB09" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Program on illegal passing incidents</header><subsection id="H7F1421C4B39E4B41B204BF4FB0018C5F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration shall establish a program to provide grants to eligible entities to carry out a demonstration project to monitor and collect data on incidents of illegal passing of stopped school buses.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC360BE79A0E4BE1AE6CBC50CB742587"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>Upon the establishment of the program under subsection (a), the Administrator shall solicit applications, in such form and requiring such information as the Administrator determines is appropriate, from eligible entities to participate in the program.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFF41961F8521444DA944D7D6A5AE69C0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection</header><paragraph id="HFB68DFE5A0B84C70A88455A1BDDE97F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the deadline for submitting applications under subsection (b), as determined by the Administrator, the Administrator shall provide grants to not more than 12 eligible entities to carry out a demonstration project under the program established under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10ECC49F37AF49788EBB675C56ED212B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In selecting eligible entities to receive a grant under this section, the Administrator shall—</text><subparagraph id="H6343C16B54BA409D99D5A86AF343F972"><enum>(A)</enum><text>select entities located in—</text><clause id="H828001BB9B2D4ABB819E8E3E05694D94"><enum>(i)</enum><text>urban, rural, and suburban communities; and</text></clause><clause id="HB93F43847A6446A8A00F85525189A59E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">geographic areas that account for varying weather patterns;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBD7BAAF3C2746CB9B9608FEE4AD22B0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that a range of socioeconomic and demographic backgrounds are represented across the selected entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22FD7472C6584E7C9E2BC5EC9C0E4614"><enum>(C)</enum><text>select at least 1 entity that has publicly operated school bus fleets;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CD331D546A540508F3FD669AF51EF7D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>select at least 1 entity that has privately operated school bus fleets;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H526B82CD51124720AC50AD0E557C2A24"><enum>(E)</enum><text>select entities that have the ability to work cooperatively with local law enforcement to carry out a project described in subsection (d);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B152D02E3594F8999B59B4E025807BD"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">select at least 1 entity that is a tribal educational agency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE31F695E90FA4680A9841680150795D6"><enum>(G)</enum><text>select—</text><clause id="H5B92118AF1514D18BE4496BC7B7DC46B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 1 entity that has in place a local campaign to combat incidents of illegal passing of stopped school buses;</text></clause><clause id="H8A166FF1A13849C8A123ADCAD2D12921"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>at least 1 entity that has in place countermeasures to stop such incidents; and</text></clause><clause id="HFD8ACD0671D3448B83CF2DE240AE7796"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>at least 1 entity that does not have in place such a campaign or such countermeasures. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0A20205A06F644C493E303CC3B534427"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Demonstration projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of a grant under this section shall use such grant to carry out a project to monitor and collect data on incidents of illegal passing of stopped school buses, including a description of—</text><paragraph id="HBECA045754A0432DAB20D11BABABB9BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of incidents that occur each day;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF001F79BD834D54A903BF6161A3F7C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>traffic patterns or characteristics of locations in which such incidents occur, including—</text><subparagraph id="HB371CBAEB1E347C2A9B3E130F0F6B2A1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">road conditions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85C5D207E4B14A77BBB333665AD286DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>time and location of such incidents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2C18D986CC34715BE1E654DCC0BBACF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>lighting and weather conditions at the time such incidents occurred; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H782D269B99BC4A1892F14BD7CEBA0504"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the side of the school bus on which such incidents occurred;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3D6743A628F4E14B4F865396D439A3B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the drivers involved in such incidents, including—</text><subparagraph id="H65374E57DA234C969E099F18B4FA4B40"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the age and sex of the driver;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA6BC925FE154A1A96FE4C6BF1D22485"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of whether any law enforcement action was taken against the driver and, if so, a summary of such action;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50805D600B454907A0133685213ADF4B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether a driver has a record of traffic citations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40DC6ADAD52248039E698CE10C58EFF4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>whether distracted driving was involved in such incidents; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5B0BEAEB4D04BB797B777F1281CEB08"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other information the Administrator determines is able to be collected in order to prepare the public safety messaging campaign required under section 3.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC98F44B7A0AA4D14B8313060EFF4D3AB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to Administrator</header><text>Upon completion of a demonstration project carried out with a grant provided under this section, a grant recipient shall submit to the Administrator a report containing the data collected during such project.</text></subsection><subsection id="H70E0F10408AB4BB8ABE28A8B42D3F0D1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the Administrator provides grants to eligible entities under subsection (c)(1), the Administrator shall prepare a report describing the findings of the demonstration projects carried out with such grants and submit such report to Congress.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3EB4DD35069C4633901DBFF5D96242C1" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definition of eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means a local educational agency (as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary And Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>) or a tribal educational agency (as defined in section 6132(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7452">20 U.S.C. 7452(b)</external-xref>)). </text></subsection></section><section id="H0E5222652AD249248E64BE3D667201FA"><enum>3.</enum><header>National public safety messaging campaign</header><subsection id="HA05AE0918731476EA13C5DBECFAD82D5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Administrator submits the report required under section 2(f), the Administrator shall produce and distribute a national public safety messaging campaign to increase awareness and education about the dangers of illegal passing of stopped school buses. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC5236A34B5154CD7A642CA5F9CCAFA19"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In producing and distributing the national public safety messaging campaign under subsection (a), the Administrator shall—</text><paragraph id="H97C87F15C56C40BE950F016717C18F08"><enum>(1)</enum><text>incorporate the findings contained in the report submitted under subsection (2)(f) in the campaign, including distributing the campaign to targeted sectors of the public based on such report; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EAC6BFD1867444D8CFEFA7C41ECC91B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that the campaign includes radio, television, and social media advertising and is not limited to only digital downloads or regional distribution; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9E0356764B5418FB3B4773C4F6B8EC7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to television advertising, seek advertising time on key national broadcasts with a wide audience.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H81C7DA66B1D440B381B6FA4063FE4811"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date on which the Administrator submits the report required under section 2(f), the Administrator shall modify educational materials created for traffic safety resource prosecutors and State agencies responsible for administering driver’s license laws to include more data on the dangers of illegal passing of stopped school buses and emphasize the importance of strong enforcement of laws prohibiting the passing of stopped school buses.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB4C05FEB8228473B871973CA7AB18D46"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Pupil transportation safety</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall include in the next scheduled edition of the biennial highway safety countermeasure guide published by the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration that is provided to State highway safety offices information about pupil transportation safety and effective countermeasures to address illegal passing of stopped school buses.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB3E4FE9A4BE94146B7190C485C93B44F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Model legislation</header><subsection id="H3312F320297C4F278E05F2754E40735E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the Secretary of Transportation completes the review of illegal passing laws conducted pursuant to section 24110(a) of the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/23/402">23 U.S.C. 402</external-xref> note), the Secretary shall, in consultation with the National Conference of State Legislatures, develop model legislation to address incidents of illegal passing of stopped school buses.</text></subsection><subsection id="H33C03D4E791B4DB4B53CBBB66AC9E959"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The model legislation developed under subsection (a) shall require that a citation for the illegal passing of a stopped school bus be classified as a moving violation.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

