<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H49CAEE0BE8D045AFB258AB717E3F1D3E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3738 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to establish in the Department of Veterans Affairs the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3738</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to establish in the Department of Veterans Affairs the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H3F846767D8A24E3CA30675B617343CFB" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF9E281DB23F4132BF32582BD40232F9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration</header> 
<subsection id="HE83948971BE54399955CDFDD0C81B32B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration</header> 
<paragraph id="HB8C700C791D2487A931A53DAB62BFE42"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part V of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new chapter:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1C9D11845EE942248F1C6AADD0A459F4" style="USC"> <chapter id="H57D4A67CC8FD4D0384B051BA53D2A903"><enum>80</enum><header>Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration</header> <toc container-level="chapter-container" idref="H57D4A67CC8FD4D0384B051BA53D2A903" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration"> <toc-entry idref="HF96857BDEE5547D9ADC80ECFCD7C59CC" level="section">Sec. </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="HF96857BDEE5547D9ADC80ECFCD7C59CC" level="section">8001. Organization of Administration. </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="H30F9CE7E785F4D17823819F4C83B52E2" level="section">8002. Functions of Administration. </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="H9E38BB713220460A9BA8ACE7D7940D33" level="section">8003. Annual report to Congress.</toc-entry></toc> <section id="HF96857BDEE5547D9ADC80ECFCD7C59CC"><enum>8001.</enum><header>Organization of Administration</header> <subsection id="HC1A69C3762E64C0AB09A4153AE0C1ADD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is in the Department of Veterans Affairs a Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration. The primary function of the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration is the administration of the programs of the Department that provide assistance related to economic opportunity to veterans and their dependents and survivors.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HA5F84217C4DF4F6D8B36A1D668D8BD68"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Under Secretary for Economic Opportunity and Transition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration is under the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition, who is directly responsible to the Secretary for the operations of the Administration.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H30F9CE7E785F4D17823819F4C83B52E2"><enum>8002.</enum><header>Functions of Administration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration is responsible for the administration of the following programs of the Department:</text> 
<paragraph id="H75A9AEEE3E914B1895936E02507A6C79"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Vocational rehabilitation and employment programs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H331275CCFCC54F1AAB97D38DDA540408"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Educational assistance programs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H07790456271B4723AAD04C7A6C52BFC0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Veterans’ housing loan and related programs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HF6AF83EDBD234CCF9009B7EBABF169EA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The verification of small businesses owned and controlled by veterans pursuant to subsection (f) of section 8127 of this title, including the administration of the database of veteran-owned businesses described in such subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8B00DDA9A7C44138765B3F5040AE7D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Transition Assistance Program under section 1144 of title 10.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H890BB23E618D4236BD82F6CCA4CC620E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any other program of the Department that the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H9E38BB713220460A9BA8ACE7D7940D33"><enum>8003.</enum><header>Annual report to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall include in the annual report to the Congress required by section 529 of this title a report on the programs administered by the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition. Each such report shall include the following with respect to each such program during the fiscal year covered by that report:</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H3EF56DFA3DEE442F96ADE17FDA63EEDB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of claims received.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H30E128DC36014240B316368A59915D56"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of claims decided.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HCA275CAE1700464794F24F3D091CE889"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The average processing time for a claim.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB512EECDF784B8EA52C8DC33696C679"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of successful outcomes (as determined by the Secretary).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H98F2E21C537F4ADB9DFB55513EE9BF41"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of full-time equivalent employees.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5A4DAF776B304FFABD784CD88D5954FE"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amounts expended for information technology.</text></paragraph></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H17C1EE3FC22C45228F0C7C040F3A775F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><text>The tables of chapters at the beginning of title 38, United States Code, and of part V of title 38, United States Code, are each amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 79 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3CD7608DC03544B796806CADCC21FF5C" style="USC"> 
<toc> 
<multi-column-toc-entry bold="on" level="section"><toc-enum>80. </toc-enum><level-header level="section">Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration</level-header><target>8001</target></multi-column-toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5D39983CAB8D4F90A5EF26E1DBD64705"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/80">Chapter 80</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), shall take effect on October 1, 2024.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA1BC1F253C984715879A1A4D3D9F5D7C" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Full-Time employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For fiscal years 2024 and 2025, the total number of full-time equivalent employees authorized for the Veterans Benefits Administration and the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration, as established under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/80">chapter 80</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), may not exceed—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9B90CCA102F14418B818552ABD999966" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>34,228 in fiscal year 2024; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3775AAFDE0A24BD184C9177D2CD65CD5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>35,417 in fiscal year 2025.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5BAAFEE4BE04434F8704C34EA400BF42"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Labor rights</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any labor rights, inclusion in the bargaining unit, and collective bargaining agreement that affects an employee of the Department of Veterans Affairs who is transferred to the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration, as established under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/80">chapter 80</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), shall apply in the same manner to such employee after such transfer.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H6FEFBB8F52B14E1888E19F49D2AD1530"><enum>2.</enum><header>Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition</header> <subsection id="HA524864C8DE64652A15D7B4C5309EB66"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Under Secretary</header> <paragraph id="HE5E0B1C647E54B539E28272C76D88FFE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/3">Chapter 3</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/306">section 306</external-xref> the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD2677ADA635450C88A8230F2ADA50F4" style="USC"> 
<section id="H1B436F54C05446449A0F57B38016772D"><enum>306A.</enum><header>Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition</header> 
<subsection id="H0CA44FF519754F98B755223E29DA11FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Under Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is in the Department an Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition, who is appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate. The Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition shall be appointed without regard to political affiliation or activity and solely on the basis of demonstrated ability in—</text> <paragraph id="H16C67DB625EA41018F46FBCA358A164C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>information technology; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE4D49D89CFFD442DA1BBB58CA67A2B6C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the administration of programs within the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration or programs of similar content and scope.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF65EDA6FC2C54CD3BB84BEAB1306F396"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition is the head of, and is directly responsible to the Secretary for the operations of, the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6B8E30DB43F04E669578E9635CAA6AC1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Vacancies</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD53AA343A0AF4EBE9D54E77323659050"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Whenever a vacancy in the position of Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition occurs or is anticipated, the Secretary shall establish a commission to recommend individuals to the President for appointment to the position.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4203A6EFD67F4AD9860FA7FB232EE7FA" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A commission established under this subsection shall be composed of the following members appointed by the Secretary:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9666B1A5698C4FA4902CB35E06B1208A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Three persons representing education and training, vocational rehabilitation, employment, real estate, mortgage finance and related industries, and survivor benefits activities affected by the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7DB7D67745A24D7C9968C3A59FE1CBED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Two persons representing veterans served by the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5E42CDBA92764DE0BE16EB395CB19536"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Two persons who have experience in the management of private sector benefits programs of similar content and scope to the economic opportunity and transition programs of the Department.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H583F0B7429E344C19EBDEDBA20735857"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Deputy Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H67A39E8D6EE643E79D4544E0FF73BDF7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The chairman of the Veterans’ Advisory Committee on Education formed under section 3692 of this title.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0494C3DABC6D46C696DB43D32CBEC06A"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One person who has held the position of Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition, if the Secretary determines that it is desirable for such person to be a member of the commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8C564377ED22450D94BE502EEDABC272" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A commission established under this subsection shall recommend at least three individuals for appointment to the position of Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition. The commission shall submit all recommendations to the Secretary. The Secretary shall forward the recommendations to the President and the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives with any comments the Secretary considers appropriate. Thereafter, the President may request the commission to recommend additional individuals for appointment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6F73C070AC0D4E64BACDF3E97142A739" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary or Deputy Assistant Secretary of Veterans Affairs who performs personnel management and labor relations functions shall serve as the executive secretary of a commission established under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF3C09A9C797749658660DACF18ADC100"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 306 the following new item:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H020AFA93CA1A45C489010244DC8E84CD" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">306A. Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3FD1E956E64043098F9020AEE2D77922"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Title 38, United States Code, is further amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H68645C94FEDA42F089308C399FD7C282"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 306(c)(2), by striking subparagraphs (A) and (E) and redesignating subparagraphs (B), (C), (D), and (F), as subparagraphs (A) through (D), respectively;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5A1D9BE2B0AE4ED194B6D3212B4BBCA4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 317(d)(2), by inserting after <quote>Under Secretary for Benefits,</quote> the following: <quote>the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition,</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H008BB364C1AE4D838B0D02730D113DF9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 318(d)(2), by inserting after <quote>Under Secretary for Benefits,</quote> the following: <quote>the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition,</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A69690909454F88A9DCF83F22D0E74D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 516(e)(2)(C), by striking <quote>Health and the Under Secretary for Benefits</quote> and inserting <quote>Health, the Under Secretary for Benefits, and the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAE287A538D5F4DFFABC43E75CF1FB99B"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 541(a)(2)(B), by striking <quote>Health and the Under Secretary for Benefits</quote> and inserting <quote>Health, the Under Secretary for Benefits, and the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE8647F88940B4FFAB36DECA4291CBEEC"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 542(a)(2)(B)(iii), by striking <quote>Health and the Under Secretary for Benefits</quote> and inserting <quote>Health, the Under Secretary for Benefits, and the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBCE1457223C049D9B88F03286138E94D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 544(a)(2)(B)(vi), by striking <quote>Health and the Under Secretary for Benefits</quote> and inserting <quote>Health, the Under Secretary for Benefits, and the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H590CDCE109C846B2AD6736AA2D3CC586"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 709(c)(2)(A), by inserting after <quote>Under Secretary for Benefits,</quote> the following: <quote>the Under Secretary for Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition,</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7F01EA7817944F4BA6D1321D01B8E687"><enum>(9)</enum><text>in section 7701(a), by inserting after <quote>assistance</quote> the following: <quote>, other than assistance related to Economic Opportunity and Transition,</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H57C22B72B8084B5ABB5F0D1713913563"><enum>(10)</enum><text>in section 7703, by striking paragraphs (2) and (3) and redesignating paragraphs (4) and (5) as paragraphs (2) and (3), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD693C3D44D244081B6D3DE9C87F1199F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Section 306A of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), and the amendments made by this section, shall take effect on October 1, 2024.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HB3C0C506689D47B79EC9ED570427FFB3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Transfer of services</header> <subsection id="H464C8A4A1AAD4D74AD4D0F64F750932E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on the progress toward establishing the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration, as established under section 8001 of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 4, and the transition of the provision of services to veterans by such Administration.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2EE1D97DB8F046B8ADA9EFAE0029DC18"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may not transfer the function of providing any services to veterans to the Veterans Economic Opportunity and Transition Administration, as established under section 8001 of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 4 until the Secretary submits to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives certification that—</text> <paragraph id="H684453E8EB2F4FF2A816EFCCB3B06A2F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the transition of the provision of services to such Administration will not negatively affect the provision of such services to veterans; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D88C5C18C43459990D141865BB3C1EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such services are ready to be transferred.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4325001D34FF4A6A90D9FD59A93DAA04"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deadline for certification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives the certification required by subsection (b)—</text> 
<paragraph id="H463A189B6E3C4294AAC0901899F2169C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>no earlier than April 1, 2024; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBDEEBE441F544FBB80D3AA214FBD6C46"><enum>(2)</enum><text>no later than September 1, 2024.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCB8945D3014A4F31B37907553B6C2E4F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Failure To certify</header><text>If the Secretary fails to submit the certification required by subsection (b) by the date specified in subsection (c)(2), the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a report that includes—</text> <paragraph id="HC52B49E311D64E7D825F0DC21DD86723"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the reason why the certification was not made by such date; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H15A047FA29BF45B7B0C733EC22DCB247"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the estimated date when the certification will be made.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

