<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1952610A115E423BA27DAB299774C853" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6282 IH: Humane Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6282</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231107">November 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000136">Mr. Vasquez</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a report on detainees in U.S. Customs and Border Protection, U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement, or the Office of Refugee Resettlement (ORR) custody, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H68A342367E3C4E4ABF711C19E2BD5C04" style="OLC"><section id="HDA63C4CD057A4FDDA5E0046BE7C4B427" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Humane Accountability Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H158FF6F288644498B4D4C60B5DDC0A10"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on DHS and HHS detainees</header><subsection id="HA05BCF34E7A04283A04C634DE448AC65"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security and the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall jointly submit to Congress and the Comptroller General of the United States a report regarding detainees in U.S. Customs and Border Protection (CBP), U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE), or the Office of Refugee Resettlement (ORR) custody, as the case may be. Such report shall include information relating to the following:</text><paragraph id="HD6DBD84CCD33481D9800C7A4568F407E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>All instances of assault or abuse while in custody either by an officer, staff, or other detainee that requires medical attention.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8713DBCD0F35411E8653CC962B8E4A4A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>All reports of sexual assault on detainees while in custody, as well as any findings from subsequent investigations into each such assault.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H503FCE5ACF7D4A08AB9AFE4C95F4D78F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All instances of detainee death while in custody.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H996B4AFFF8F8408A8D2818E8FAA87D82"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The frequency and topic of complaints submitted by detainees or their families regarding abuse, sexual assault, staff neglect, staff retaliation, lack of proper resources or amenities, lack of access to legal counsel, or death to authorities at detention centers, as well as any action taken by such authorities to address and remedy such complaints.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3ED06CA60A0C451B817A4E744629B0EE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>GAO recommendations</header><text>Not later than 90 days after receipt of the report required under subsection (a), the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a list of recommendations to address the instances, reports, and complaints included in such report.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

