<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF30DE669693D4180868CF7F2E79DBAC4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5659 IH: Stop Funding Our Adversaries’ Research Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5659</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit Federal research agencies from carrying out certain activities with certain countries, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H67CC95B7C86347B5BC8671D7B1CDEFC9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H21CF2865970C4FDF92FE081E3DB905B6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Funding Our Adversaries’ Research Act</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="H3EE94F896F964439A37A3340D218DBF3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal research agencies carrying out certain activities with certain countries</header> <subsection id="H20807DC74B794D78B8BA23B49FEBCC8E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No funds appropriated or otherwise made available may be used by any Federal research agency (as such term is defined in section 10001 of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18901">42 U.S.C. 18901</external-xref>)) to conduct research, develop, design, plan, promulgate, implement, or execute a policy, program, order, or contract of any kind with the government, or any agency or instrumentality of such government, of a country of concern, or an entity organized under the laws of such a country, unless any such activity is specifically authorized by an Act of Congress enacted after the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H99FE64F0D12A44D48806C606CBE37C90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>country of concern</quote> means the People’s Republic of China (including the Special Administrative Regions of China, including Hong Kong and Macau), Russia, Iran, North Korea, Cuba, and Venezuela.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

