<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4F8E3375D1AD485C8D6D17AE07EE456B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3976 IH: To amend the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 to authorize grants to Indian Tribes to further achievement of Tribal coastal zone objectives, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3976</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 to authorize grants to Indian Tribes to further achievement of Tribal coastal zone objectives, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDC5207759EC94E1E8A06E28CB9861119" style="OLC"><section id="H014AC6AFB1074E1883A93EF364DB45E8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Grants for tribal coastal zone objectives</header><subsection id="H3E5A01A807B44C7182020F4EB8622437"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text>The Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1451">16 U.S.C. 1451 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 309 the following:</text><quoted-block id="H08083DC5E4C542828382A3C3BBAF0517" style="OLC"><section id="H094A1D0B76D84E128052C04005DA654E"><enum>309A.</enum><header>Grants for tribal coastal zone objectives</header><subsection id="HBB897DF685DD41BDB5EAF4236054D0FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text>The Secretary may award competitive grants to—</text><paragraph id="H91D56CE7C20142C2B72E57470593B847"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Tribal Governments to further achievement of the Tribal coastal zone objectives of such governments; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H588E7825851F43CE9874E5DFC2E54D16"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Native Hawaiian organizations, to further achievement of the coastal zone objectives identified in the corresponding approved management program as specified in section 306(d).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDA5F15E84209400D9E457ABA9F51477D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Cost share</header><text>The Federal share of the cost of any activity carried out with a grant under this section shall be 100 percent of such cost.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE4BEF04D22C14194808CDCD37DB239FF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>The Secretary may not award a grant under this section unless the Secretary determines that—</text><paragraph id="H6599CC14FF4E4EFFB79F5E8FE913D5A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the activities to be carried out with the grant are compatible with this title; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACE316F9533A4025BF44DBD7F4DFF6B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the potential grant recipient has consulted with the affected coastal state regarding the objectives and purposes of the grant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8CC491353C944E07838A5E259B607FAA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorized objectives and purposes</header><text>Amounts awarded through a grant under this section shall be used for 1 or more of the objectives and purposes authorized under subsections (b) and (c), respectively, of section 306A, with respect to the grant recipient and the corresponding coastal zone. In applying section 306A(b) under this subsection, a reference in that section to a provision shall be considered to be a corresponding provision or policy for an Indian Tribe or Native Hawaiian organization, as the case may be.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1191BC9CBE4F4ADF97D49ED794009117"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $5,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2028, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection><subsection id="H69955B20F40B44329D8737C1F67B3378"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HAD16CBA283614E3AB8656BE8D6B1208B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Indian land</header><text>The term <quote>Indian land</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2601 of the Energy Policy Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/3501">25 U.S.C. 3501</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF818A50791548148D500395A3579300"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Native Hawaiian organization</header><text>The term <quote>Native Hawaiian organization</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the NATIVE Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4352">25 U.S.C. 4352</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00CC60394561477BAFB241A98BB2C6B4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Tribal coastal zone</header><text>The term <quote>Tribal coastal zone</quote> means any Indian land of a Tribal Government that is within the coastal zone.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FABAAD92DA240CD9E1642B8DD0A9171"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Tribal coastal zone objective</header><text>The term <quote>Tribal coastal zone objective</quote> means, with respect to a Tribal Government and its Tribal coastal zone, any of the following objectives:</text><subparagraph id="HF40F450791944542A3886E91DC8C7E79"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Protection, restoration, or preservation of areas in the Tribal coastal zone of such Tribal Government that hold—</text><clause id="HA1542D9075D547BAB90FDCDAC62E4E74"><enum>(i)</enum><text>important ecological, cultural, or sacred significance for such Tribal Government; or</text></clause><clause id="H2234A41ECDA14DFABF97EC258AF885E2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>traditional, historic, and esthetic values essential to such Tribal Government.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67DDEDD7EE3E426D95E379CDE7E8BFD2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Preparing and implementing a special area management plan and technical planning for important coastal areas.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C66B70E114A4C83B17EB9632E50D341"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Taking any coastal or shoreline stabilization measure, including any mitigation measure, for the purpose of public safety, public access, or cultural or historical preservation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HADA8BF6768FA4C5D96EE9FA2C2B83C9F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary, acting through the Under Secretary, shall issue guidance for the program established under section 309A of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972, as added by subsection (a), including the criteria for awarding grants under such program, which guidance shall be established in consultation with Tribal Governments (as defined in section 304 of that Act) and Native Hawaiian organizations (as defined in section 309A(f) of that Act).</text></subsection><subsection id="H2D0DD752609944D190E023C0C0681B96"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of State grants To fulfill tribal objectives</header><text>Section 306A(c)(2) of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1455a">16 U.S.C. 1455a(c)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H9407D7811F1C4890B529B9B938EE2A29"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF85C1D82E65D429BAA76D799A3E07F5E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A4AA61BE10A45FBA2800D5AC10D4C4C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H7892C03EB9214243A9D99965B9310C89" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HB0FE8E9EF79A4ADD8B425972ACAD4BEE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>fulfilling any Tribal coastal zone objective (as that term is defined in section 309A) or coastal zone objective described in section 309A(a)(2).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96DDB66A11034904A3B312DED433593A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Other programs not affected</header><text>Nothing in this section, including the amendments made by this section, may be construed to affect the ability of a Tribal Government or Native Hawaiian government to apply for or receive assistance under, or participate in any program authorized by, the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1451">16 U.S.C. 1451 et seq.</external-xref>) or other related Federal laws.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

