<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H24EC113C4EAF42FA94D07C63D64737F4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1653 IH: Promoting Accountability and Security in Transitions Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1653</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230317">March 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, to ensure Presidential records are preserved, duly created when non-official electronic messaging accounts are used, and made available to the public and the next administration in a timely fashion to advance national security and accountability, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H846055638AD24AC890952A091FCF90D6" style="OLC"><section id="HFB7757DCF717498BBA665644D1CC2009" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Accountability and Security in Transitions Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PAST Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1EDEF6F2EE5E40048C3AA24D5E12E9EA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The sense of Congress is the following:</text><paragraph id="H9085903EDF16446289F680954D1D349C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The preservation of Presidential records (as defined in section 2201 of title 44, United States Code) is a legal obligation for every Presidential administration, as Presidential records are the most important and widely used source for studying how the executive branch of the Federal Government works, how it has changed over time, and how it might evolve to serve the needs of a new era.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61B622D067C6495FB9B69BF9DBDA87F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The preservation of Presidential records is therefore vital for— </text><subparagraph id="H1D453EE19AD548D98B8E6877E036B097"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the public to be able to understand and learn from the past; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E3FF009AAAD4E9A8EC5D957B142BC01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>future policymaking to build on the past administration’s successes and experience; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82921B7E50E04EE091967C7FBA937CE5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensuring accountability for results, performance, and conduct; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4DF1C80889C475BAF77831C463B8ADA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other purposes that serve to strengthen American democracy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCC89A2A58E3436D83AED4C82254F784"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any effort to destroy, alter, or remove Presidential records in violation of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code— </text><subparagraph id="H4A138A38FC2B4A4E9730992B299F9244"><enum>(A)</enum><text>threatens the values described in paragraph (2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA7401A95954450DB5BA4CB09678B202"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may subject a person engaging in such efforts to other criminal penalties under section 641 or 2071 of title 18, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB37E2EABEF1461482D5CE1ABD8301D8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The lawful disposal of Presidential records that no longer have administrative, historical, informational, or evidentiary value must follow a process as described in section 2203 of title 44, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBDF26A793D5A4EA69C3DCCBBE0A753E7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>What constitutes a Presidential record is determined solely by whether the record relates to the <quote>carrying out of constitutional, statutory, or other official or ceremonial duties of the President</quote>, as indicated in the definition of the term <quote>Presidential records</quote> in section 2201 of title 44, United States Code, and by the content of the information contained in the record.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38897D8B818044AFBB1D60B66A9C7782"><enum>(6)</enum><text>For communication between agencies and the Executive Office of the President, the copy of the record belonging to the agency is retained as an agency record pursuant to section 3301 of title 44, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE0004B8F31B4E878E2D18F06BB0747F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Consistent with section 2203 of title 44, United States Code, any Presidential records created with non-official electronic media shall be <quote>preserved</quote>, which includes a comprehensive documentation of all records and associated metadata and attachments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H206E7EAFC3CE464494F99E338579D1DD"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Applications or software with an automatic deleting functionality are antithetical to the legal and historical obligations described under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H045C8FB6292E412B9BD64ACAEF33A164"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Periods of Presidential transition are moments where the national security of the United States is most vulnerable, necessitating an early, good faith, and consistent commitment by the outgoing administration to ensure continuity of operations as it relates to national security and protecting critical infrastructure, among other reasons.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17FAE2EA13FE49959F1FF8C949FB1995"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Agencies and the Executive Office of the President are required by law to cooperate with the Archivist of the United States and the Federal Transition Coordinator of the General Service Administration, who is tasked with ensuring agencies comply with all statutory requirements relating to transition planning under section 4(c) of the Presidential Transition Act of 1963 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/3/102">3 U.S.C. 102</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H229869904DB14FA89370CEFEB2308B79"><enum>(11)</enum><text>During a Presidential transition, Presidential records, which contain valuable information regarding agreements or negotiations with foreign governments and international organizations and the actions and beliefs of foreign nations or actors are of enormous value to the national security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8FB4F1413804B03983A5050600A67A5"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Any effort to delay briefings, coordination, and sharing information regarding key national security relationships, threats, and operations with an incoming administration or the destruction, removal, or alteration of Presidential records that attest to the information described in this section could pose a grave danger to the national security. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E86A797EE81497A89007383215CE7DE"><enum>(13)</enum><text>An expeditious ascertainment of the plausible President-elect and Vice-President-elect by the Administrator of General Services plays a vital role in ensuring continuity of Government and protecting national security such that the risk of redundant expenditure is overwhelmed by the advantages of an early access to transition resources to allow for transition planning. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H080436C19FDC4DEAB7A7060B4CCCEDBE"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The National Archives and Records Administration plays an essential role in ensuring the official proceedings of Government are documented to improve democracy in the United States, protect national security, provide continuity of Government during a transition, and promote accountability for actions taking during a Presidency. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E1AC7B2041C446CBBE3971C6326EB01"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The robust funding of the National Archives and Records Administration and protection of its officers and employees from political interference is a national imperative and must be a priority for Congress. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H9FEEAAEE85AA4BD38F6310543DABD1A9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2201 of title 44, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3B5EEF1B6451477ABF21ADF4FB256D9A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>, and includes the metadata associated with all such material</quote> before the period; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3DF611BF3B4487A8E7F3D8FE0FB41BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2A29FA694C414A8B8E71DDC0660D4552"><paragraph id="HDFAD219821E347CEA606DE98FA181102" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>electronic messaging account</term> includes electronic mail, chat or instant messaging, text messaging, voicemail messaging, and other messaging platforms or apps, such as social media or mobile applications, among other applications. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17F9C26816FF44B7ABBC8D8BFF03EA8A"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>official electronic messaging account</term> includes electronic messaging accounts provided by an executive agency or the Executive Office of the President.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3570B1820FC2405A8511F64CCE5C41E0"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>dispose</term>, with respect to documentary material, means to remove, deface, alter, corrupt, delete, erase, or otherwise destroy the documentary material.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H1544FDA7AC8945AD89A652F36ADFA54A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Management and custody of Presidential records</header><subsection id="H28B645B60A2F4A80A60A1BAF908FE66A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2203 of title 44, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H75916EB068034142B90D745E9F8E78B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (e), (f), and (g) as subsections (g), (h), and (i), respectively; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE17D1480C53E4988BBF0A7A5A73DCD20"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (d) as subsection (e); </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE804958A0C50424CBF6CBC74E6659822"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking subsection (c) and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H76576AFBF9C14407828DACB34747F8D6"><subsection id="HC4640CD01363416D8D5E29050F98AF09"><enum>(c)</enum><text>The President shall obtain the advice of the Archivist in applying standards, procedures, and techniques designed to— </text><paragraph id="H9B72315C357D4DE894E19E8B61AF9F51"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improve the management of records; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H540F4256087A45D8A01E2A9E18524B3D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promote the maintenance and security of records determined appropriate for preservation; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE9436651A604A4CB88BEBB06FDDC08B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>facilitate the segregation and disposal of records of temporary value.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H73D8979DFEDD4B8296F31D23D5430D1D"><enum>(d)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H12CBED6D4FD741E88A51CD81BDDF259E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the President’s term of office, if the President wishes to dispose of those Presidential records of such President that no longer have administrative, historical, informational, or evidentiary value— </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E5F18B843FE41C190CB47F83E3D9FDB" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the President shall request, in writing, the views of the Archivist concerning the proposed disposal of such Presidential records; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" indent="up1" id="H774CE0DD0F294252B56056A91F73FB70"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Archivist shall indicate, in writing, whether the Archivist intends to take any action under subsection (g) of this section with respect to the Presidential records.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="H31015EC212E24718A10910A9ED7D5899"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 5 business days after the date on which the Archivist provides a written indication under paragraph (1)(B), the Archivist shall make publicly available on a website any communications received or sent by the Archivist regarding the potential disposal of Presidential records under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A00C782A3AB49978852FD6B0F7EB1B2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (e), as so redesignated—</text><subparagraph id="HB50ECA1C667843AC8E94B86B6333C94A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsection (c)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (d)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H593D10CC49C84D3E9EC3972F0E68A0FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsection (e)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (g)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H99CD85EF25D442278F2186DFC134C0D8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (e), as so redesignated, the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFD4D03E06EE544029C3B9982E0F724BD"><subsection id="HBECF8E3D1830429FB46A9126718EEC76"><enum>(f)</enum><text>In January of each even-numbered year, the Archivist shall, in coordination with the Office of Administration of the Executive Office of the President, submit to the Chairman and Ranking Member of each committee of jurisdiction of either House of Congress, of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, and of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and to the President a report that—</text><paragraph id="H3E7E492FAC4E44D09B7A660D9CE88B42"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is based on inspections conducted by the Archivist, in coordination with the Office of Administration of the Executive Office of the President, of the Presidential records management programs of the Executive Office of the President; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9CCD61F697B44F8A919B890F0311F50"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluates—</text><subparagraph id="HCF656005C58346EA9FD82F48AA6CBF0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the records management activities and training conducted and standard operating procedures and guidance issued pursuant to this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B78E86923984D26A12EE1965DE70B55"><enum>(B)</enum><text>responses to any recommendations resulting from inspections or studies conducted under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H48A6AB1B1C414D759C12CBA0807CA981"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="HADDDBBD831EE46328183A6829CB175B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Section 2105(a)(2) of title 44, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>paragraph (f)(2)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (i)(2)</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5628C0F9F2643F4BF60CD13A7AFD22F"><enum>(2)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">Chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HE94EA2FBC73F45EFA88150D6497E5DFE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in section 2204(b)(2)(A), by striking <quote>section 2203(d)(1)</quote> and inserting <quote>2203(i)(1)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25C3B95D634F4C0A8BF9E580F3FD3547"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 2206(1), by striking <quote>section 2203(f)(3)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 2203(i)(4)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0D73578D9BD746F5B1A8D5F021D2A1D1"><enum>5.</enum><header>Restrictions on access to Presidential records</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2204 of title 44, United States Code, is amended— </text><paragraph id="H93951AD4B502434DAF19ACBD1941A0E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(3), by striking <quote>shall not be subject to judicial review, except as provided</quote> and inserting <quote>shall be subject to judicial review, including as provided</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10E461A350704F0E92DDDCA03493809E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (e)—</text><subparagraph id="H698DF441A045479CAD7046188E3334CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> before <quote>The United States</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D537C64AC874582BECBD57B34187C29"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAB89FC599F774295AF27B9EAE308F76C"><paragraph id="HBA6E6D284A5847779553830BC85BD614" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H59D15F7137384F8ABC8C58AAB4B793A7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A person seeking access to a Presidential record to which access is restricted under subsection (a) may file an action in the United States District Court for the District of Columbia seeking release of the Presidential record.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="HE0C1B42F712345C390A6EB1A12138698"><enum>(B)</enum><text>In an action filed under subparagraph (A), the court shall direct the release of a Presidential record, or a reasonably segregable portion thereof, if the court determines that the Presidential record, or the reasonably segregable portion thereof, is not within any of the categories specified in subsection (a) and there is not a valid claim of constitutionally based privilege against disclosure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HF94E254D9A594413BD0223BC674E0D93"><enum>6.</enum><header>Exceptions to restricted access</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2205(2)(C) of title 44, United States Code, is amended— </text><paragraph id="H95BCE57FC34D434FB869CE3412A13826"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>to any committee or subcommittee thereof</quote> and inserting <quote>upon request by the Chairman or Ranking Member of a committee or subcommittee thereof, to such Chairman or ranking member,</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD87A9551736742669549F1382C2C7E14"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>its business</quote> and inserting <quote>the business of the committee or subcommittee</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H063C95A8C3D74076902E19399D56BBF3"><enum>7.</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2206 of title 44, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H246CFDF44948457E8C5F049619F83FB2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(a)</quote> before <quote>The Archivist</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27EB522DA5454868AF57A209B6A5068B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a), as so designated—</text><subparagraph id="HCAD980AACFC248DFA5BCC0E28EB11CC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1307E18AAB2B44F89BEC1640BFDE3CD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking the period and inserting a semicolon; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H911EF39736314AC7808D614CD6B0477A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H77BE97A8F7CC4AA3A9C2EF7B8059301B"><paragraph id="H74CD6B70B5E04B319DE72C5FB9192A2D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provisions— </text><subparagraph id="H3A9A7AFBE58842C8948555C298C0B02E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for what constitutes official and non-official electronic messaging accounts; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0012A73DEC6B42C7B5BEB090EF3D933E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing procedures for documenting— </text><clause id="HBAEA5B5FD8884777BAEC72DF79397567"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Presidential records created on non-official electronic messaging accounts (including emerging technologies, applications, and platforms); and </text></clause><clause id="H8F471A06C7A3425C9952AD41467D6872"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>required metadata; </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB0320B0EC7244598199B3D68FA26557"><enum>(6)</enum><text>provisions for the preservation of digital media, including from social media accounts, that may appear to be personal records or private property but the preservation of which may be required under this chapter; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2E0314C7C3F431B954957179EC9598F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>provisions for the appropriate circumstances and controls for the use of messaging applications and software with automatic deleting or other similar functionalities.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8120383EF7D4F9CB0AFA38E2A3AAC62"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D9591240DFD449D8C64D2DFB5DC76ED"><subsection id="H1A170976C3874B9A8EFAFCA315546BC0"><enum>(b)</enum><text>The Archivist shall issue, and shall annually update, implementation guidance with respect to the regulations described in paragraphs (5) and (6) of subsection (a).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H1724D8BAD2E54F97BAF158F2AB108C3B"><enum>8.</enum><header>Disclosure requirement for official business conducted using non-official electronic messaging accounts</header><subsection id="H49A15913E6444A37892B07D95D7C6C90"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2209(a) of title 44, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC9068D4609EB40EF9F90FC599B6DAD91"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>create or send</quote> and inserting <quote>create, send, or receive</quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2901197C3FA140E7A427C7513B80D31A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1) and (2) as subparagraphs (A) and (B), respectively, and adjusting the margin accordingly; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00244747421546E3A8DE819937C3FDD3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The President,</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H664CE6B0B78C418EAA2576BACC091625"><paragraph id="H7DA46B5008BD492E87A1409CAFBC003B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>Not later than 90 days after assuming office, the President shall publicly release guidelines for officers and employees of the Executive Office of the President who create or receive documentary material that— </text><subparagraph id="H2D811081441245BAA9B909243939B484"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prohibit the use of non-official electronic messaging accounts that cannot be easily copied or forwarded to an official electronic messaging account for official business; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BD0B493AA9B468DB5DF329FAC411EAD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prohibit the use of messaging accounts or software with automatic deleting or other similar functionalities. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H783EEED410D8466887BC6B88DC378300"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements for use</header><text>The President,</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF2D376D4F47F45BABCBA63A5215B3A05"><enum>9.</enum><header>Presidential Transition Act of 1963</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Presidential Transition Act of 1963 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/3/102">3 U.S.C. 102</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H0BD876B533CD432C9282D65DA5A3EEB6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 3—</text><subparagraph id="H0F6A970BB23846FEBB860AC2D49F4A74"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(8)(A), by striking clause (v) and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5502DB02E1D748BC85C0C831D57E27FF"><clause id="H6F44D64ED164442D822F18AAF0711D32" indent="up3"><enum>(v)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0A00CA88F50843D5988445181F95D292"><enum>(I)</enum><item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA232DAF2B4824647B2414ECE5BC01239"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>Activities under this paragraph shall include the preparation of a detailed classified, compartmented summary by the relevant outgoing executive branch officials of— </text><subitem indent="up2" id="HF0AA9AAFA4C6478189C21B14D7A7AF59"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>specific strategic, tactical, and operational threats to national security; </text></subitem><subitem indent="up2" id="H9B6E453124144F1C8A984ADAAB1883CB"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>major military or covert operations; and </text></subitem><subitem indent="up2" id="HCFF3570966504CC29E9122FCF284CA04"><enum>(CC)</enum><text>pending decisions on possible uses of military force or covert actions.</text></subitem></item><item indent="up2" id="H70FCBB0E0087457BAE96E88E6343E096"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>The summary prepared under item (aa) shall be provided to the President-elect and members of office staff with appropriate clearances that are designated by the President-elect as soon as possible after the date of the general elections held to determine the electors of President and Vice President under section 1 or 2 of title 3, United States Code.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H28D34089854940DB910DEBB5F6B0DA3A" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The Archivist of the United States shall collaborate with the Federal Transition Coordinator and agencies, including the Executive Office of the President, to ensure that the President-elect and members of office staff with appropriate clearances that are designated by the President-elect can easily access national security information (including documents, videos, audio, and briefings) created by the previous administration after the inauguration of the President-elect.</text></subclause><subclause indent="up1" id="HACEE45E6B17A4CA7ABF89E613B9B1A5A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The Archivist of the United States shall submit to the Chairman and Ranking Member of each committee of jurisdiction of either House of Congress, of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, and of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives a report if the Archivist of the United States believes there appears to be noncompliance with the requirements under this clause.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FEADC734EED4B2F99D613F72AD47E48"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><clause id="H8386771236A34840BACDF994126CED91"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> before <quote>The terms</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HC6D914A306694B53832D850D10EB3E0A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H94C7D75740564D93A433911B102E5B72"><paragraph id="H699605A510FF47F4B8A0F4E66D503737" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9DCFA00993E34F13921453D8C04F34A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Not later than 6 days after the date of a general election described in paragraph (1), the Administrator shall make the ascertainment described in paragraph (1) without any interference or undue pressure from the President or a candidate for President, or any representative thereof, based on provisional results from State election officials and expert analysis of results. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph indent="up1" id="H0C05DA583B334912BA07F78FEE7B30EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Given the imperatives of an orderly transition, if there is a plausible chance that the apparent successful candidate for the office of President and Vice President, respectively, are not the incumbent, or if the incumbent was not a candidate, the Administrator shall provide a portion of the services and facilities authorized to be provided under this section to all parties with a plausible chance of being the successful candidate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEFB09E8BD2C4E9AAC297EC6B65258C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 4—</text><subparagraph id="H19AF4E1CFFCD480E89ACEF32A3664C60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><clause id="H72CE066CBCD349BBA767EE857A01BEDD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><subclause id="HC1F6819E78554ECFBB89BD9257C66DF5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></subclause><subclause id="HDE970074AFCF4FD5B91C460BA5B0DA49"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0B47497A02C34691860404768113DE94"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA9D0970543214C7890582B23BC1C1A24"><subparagraph id="H7C76BA2256B144D9BF31714B6E469BA7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>under the guidance of the Archivist of the United States, monitor compliance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, including the preservation of all records and prevention of any records from being disposed unless done in accordance with such chapter.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H5F8A32C781EF4E04B7DB45ADE1DAEF2B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><subclause id="H9224E0EC33DD4122913CDF1B4767DE79"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (C) and (D) as subparagraphs (D) and (E), respectively; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H69D60B90A0304403B12869060950636C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (B) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1AE1E133CE724B28A645DF205662BDD3"><subparagraph id="HE773483DB3724134A6BB4A2A48D77A26"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Archivist of the United States;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H2529FB8EB5FC4C6F97E48F0CA690F58D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1E9EBBD46B8425DA7E34248AE900EC2"><paragraph id="HDE531CBB3D0E45DC82999B805F722950"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Role of the Archivist</header><subparagraph id="H177F5B10FFDD48D78194D092C53CD4A1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days before the date of a Presidential election, the Archivist of the United States shall send a written communication to all officers and employees of the Executive Office of the President who create or receive documentary material (as defined under section 2201 of title 44, United States Code)— </text><clause id="HFA3045A6872944C1A34FC0BFB64A7129"><enum>(i)</enum><text>describing the requirements under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code; and </text></clause><clause id="HBAAC3D7F57A049C8848C5FECD6B152D6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establishing a timeline for cooperation with the Archivist of the United States to ensure an orderly and timely transition of records subject to such chapter if there is a Presidential transition.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC459576E3D1406EB1EA413953A509EF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reporting</header><clause id="H11B12BE3D303443D9B01DD8AA2E670A7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of a Presidential election which results in a Presidential transition, the Archivist of the United States, in coordination with the Federal Transition Coordinator, shall submit to the Chairman and Ranking Member of each committee of jurisdiction of either House of Congress, of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, and of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives a report discussing the status of the transition activities of the White House Transition Coordinating Council and identifying concerns, if any, regarding compliance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code.</text></clause><clause id="HADF621728F8F4947AC0A4B7A68B48E83"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Noncompliance</header><text>The Archivist of the United States shall submit to the Chairman and Ranking Member of each committee of jurisdiction of either House of Congress, of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, and of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives a report if the Archivist of the United States believes there appears to be noncompliance with the requirements or timeline described in subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD6800D2B60E4573B87D22C707CAD23E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(2)—</text><clause id="HE03BAADB43CA4E64B0AFBA5E03BF4CFE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></clause><clause id="H6B96BC82F22941A9BCCE8F2CF8972707"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HB6CEA34A86DB40F88187EDF4AF6EE371"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0C71E4B05E4C4BA0B635EB792C8C4696"><subparagraph id="H4CF3703708264E0AB102F6DC6BEE10E0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>under the guidance of the Archivist of the United States, monitor compliance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, including the preservation of all records and prevention of any records from being disposed unless done in accordance with such chapter.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3FA875DF59C4F299A93BCA99C166024"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (i) as subsection (j); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB6804D4D0644C46B523044907C8CD7F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (h) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H09CE71CC20A64E7284B09E96E24066CA"><subsection id="HE4CEC1214D8347DC8109EA8FFA8F81F8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Role of the Archivist</header><paragraph id="H7DEEE3FEF3C24C39BEE9A11ADE2E2234"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days before the date of a Presidential election, the Archivist of the United States shall send a written communication to the head of each agency—</text><subparagraph id="H45EC2E1709FC496C8A092BD449AFD3A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describing the requirements under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H653088AF4E264791A7560551ADBFA8FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing a timeline for cooperation with the Archivist of the United States to ensure an orderly and timely transition of records subject to such chapter if there is a Presidential transition.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CD061DE8B9842608596F75F289FD541"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reporting</header><subparagraph id="H0ED7A91109714D25A9C1530C937A4681"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of a Presidential election which results in a Presidential transition, the Archivist of the United States, in coordination with the Federal Transition Coordinator, shall submit to the Chairman and Ranking Member of each committee of jurisdiction of either House of Congress, of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, and of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives a report discussing the status of the transition activities of agencies and identifying concerns, if any, regarding compliance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB558646A8F65415499435E156BB45E8C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Noncompliance</header><text>The Archivist of the United States shall submit to the Chairman and Ranking Member of each committee of jurisdiction of either House of Congress, of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, and of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives a report if the Archivist of the United States believes there appears to be noncompliance with the requirements or timeline described in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H9AB9187B074B4306B7A01B9C6748E4E2"><enum>10.</enum><header>Former Presidents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Act entitled <quote>An Act to provide retirement, clerical assistants, and free mailing privileges to former Presidents of the United States, and for other purposes</quote>, approved August 25, 1958 (commonly known as the <quote>Former Presidents Act of 1958</quote>) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/3/102">3 U.S.C. 102</external-xref> note), is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HADF8A6867D6E4CA094D2680BEABF472D"><subsection id="H138B76E9C1964DEB8DAB1660391E3907"><enum>(h)</enum><text>If the Archivist of the United States determines that a former President did not comply with major requirements under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, or the Presidential Transition Act of 1963 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/3/102">3 U.S.C. 102</external-xref> note), the monetary amounts described in subsections (a) and (b) shall be withheld until the later of— </text><paragraph id="H4EC2BF0B75EE4D28A71DE877D7CB5717"><enum>(1)</enum><text>1 year after the date on which the Archivist makes that determination; or </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H46C07E8AC2334D5BA3DF38A4501846B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date on which the Archivist determines the former President has adequately complied with the requirements.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H0057998FE791473F851378AA7BC69E50"><enum>11.</enum><header>Presidential archival depository</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2112 of title 44, United States Code, is amended— </text><paragraph id="H8DDDDA4B9EA74C0A94401B6368073D9E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H3C675549E5274C56A17FFE9B39D79737"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>When the Archivist</quote> and inserting <quote>(1) Subject to paragraph (2), when the Archivist</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D1C639690F54A27A57BE4AD0F1FA076"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2B7ED162754546B8A72ADE9C4441E557"><paragraph id="HC0342D62824B498DAB1B21727A5F4499"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Archivist may not deposit papers, documents, or other historical materials accepted under section 2111 of this title or other Federal records appropriate for preservation in a Presidential archival depository relating to a former President under paragraph (1) until after the date on which the Archivist determines that the former President has adequately complied with the requirements under chapter 22 relating to Presidential records (as defined in section 2201).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H87376DE2787C437F846A94539583CA42"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (g), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H030A47733E9046729D842535E39B0B04"><paragraph id="H5A13A8D99DE94587BA317E5EBFE2039D" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4AB56B216D304DCEB5836EE66485A355"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Notwithstanding paragraphs (3), (4), and (5) (to the extent that such paragraphs are inconsistent with this paragraph), this subsection shall be administered in accordance with this paragraph with respect to any Presidential archival depository created as a depository for the papers, documents, and other historical materials and Presidential records pertaining to any President who takes any action, including destruction, alteration, concealment, or removal, that threatens or damages the integrity and statutory preservation requirements under chapter 22 for Presidential records (as defined in section 2201).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41F5CC85597A4AC0B0895094EB8D55CA" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For purposes of subparagraphs (A)(ii), (B)(i)(II), and (B)(ii)(II) of paragraph (3) the percentage of 100 percent shall apply instead of 60 or 20 percent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F39404C1E35413396253B262AE08A66"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3684C312E79542EB99CD4904F3653181"><subsection id="HFB7AF0CD4E084C999EF7E56D769BC388"><enum>(h)</enum><text>None of the funds in the account in the National Archives Trust Fund that may be expended for the benefit and in the interest of a Presidential archival depository relating to a former President may be used for the cost of digitizing records the former President wishes to deposit in and make available through the Presidential archival depository.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

