<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H529EFF53FBB341069872EC8504982EC3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4524 IH: Parity for Tribal Law Enforcement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4524</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230710">July 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000189">Mr. Newhouse</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001053">Mr. Cole</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001148">Mr. Simpson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000136">Mr. Vasquez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Indian Law Enforcement Reform Act to provide for advancements in public safety services to Indian communities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5A248D4C6D31459D8C3B2E729D30AB27" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA346D7D6E1664D3998732F13C2C4521E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Parity for Tribal Law Enforcement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF5FCE883B24F404EA2D6A53EA8EC3568"><enum>2.</enum><header>Tribal law enforcement officers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Indian Law Enforcement Reform Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2801">25 U.S.C. 2801 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 4 the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H11785B9B12134D2FB5A6E45738BC6CEE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H0A8F3B4808A2422EA785D9582DA801F2"><enum>4A.</enum><header>Tribal law enforcement officers</header> 
<subsection id="H401E954E14264E878C0B148AED618CA5"><enum>(a)</enum><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of Federal law, law enforcement officers of any Indian Tribe that has contracted or compacted any or all Federal law enforcement functions through the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5301">25 U.S.C. 5301 et seq.</external-xref>) shall have the authority to enforce Federal law within the area under the Tribe’s jurisdiction, if—</text> <paragraph id="HEBA7BAC3070F4035ACF581A0D9B58D56"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Tribal officers involved have—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFDD0D3B9F2A947D781B911E15B0B4302"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">completed training that is comparable to that of an employee of the Office of Justice Services of the Bureau of Indian Affairs who is providing the same services in Indian country, as determined by the Deputy Bureau Director of the Office of Justice Services of the Bureau of Indian Affairs or the Deputy Bureau Director’s designee;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H843D4DFCD17446FD8E74E718C28D5CF7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>passed an adjudicated background investigation equivalent to that of an employee of the Office of Justice Services of the Bureau of Indian Affairs who is providing the same services in Indian country; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEAEFA20FABFD48EF9C37BE2BF8F737F5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>received a certification from the Office of Justice Services of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, as described in subsection (c); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H83DFA69E302642E6B39964045C6E4093"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Tribe has adopted policies and procedures that meet or exceed those of the Office of Justice Services of the Bureau of Indian Affairs for the same program, service, function, or activity.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6508F6929FD04170A8F87B140BDFF333"><enum>(b)</enum><text>While acting under the authority granted by the Secretary through an Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5301">25 U.S.C. 5301 et seq.</external-xref>) contract or compact, a Tribal law enforcement officer shall be deemed to be a Federal law enforcement officer for the purposes of—</text> <paragraph id="H1C68D783B5BC4C53B5C860E8DF50CE95"><enum>(1)</enum><text>sections 111 and 1114 of title 18, United States Code;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2E82D887683C4355B567E234A44875D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consideration as an eligible officer under subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/81">chapter 81</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA1D8797F66944D83A566F14630786574"><enum>(3)</enum><text>subchapter III of chapter 83 and subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/84">chapter 84</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2515EB638ABF4C57A643050652CBDBB4"><enum>(4)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/171">chapter 171</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Federal Tort Claims Act</quote>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE28524E35ECE4B0AA3BB8CF1C3E5FDBE"><enum>(c)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H39562FC4357A4791A8470D9DAC8A6D9C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Not later than 24 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBCA149FED4B541CB9B36744BE228DEED" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop procedures for the credentialing of Tribal officers under this section, independent of section 5, to provide confirmation that Tribal officers meet minimum certification standards and training requirements for Indian country peace officers, as prescribed by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA66A1861B46F45B99029BC9BDE77A602" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promulgate guidance, in consultation with Indian Tribes, to otherwise implement the provisions of this section. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFAF51DDAD0F3402FB6B8157D7715C4F4" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tribal law enforcement officers who choose to attend a State or other equivalent training program approved by the Deputy Bureau Director of the Office of Justice Services of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, or the Deputy Bureau Director’s designee, rather than attend the Indian Police Academy, shall be required to attend the IPA Bridge Program, or an equivalent program, prior to receiving a certification under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H8B44AFEB3AFB429A92B3348508FBB9C4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Oversight, coordination, and accountability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General, acting through the Deputy Attorney General, shall coordinate and provide oversight for all Department of Justice activities, responsibilities, functions, and programs to ensure a coordinated approach for public safety in Indian communities, accountability, and compliance with Federal law, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF8E5CD36FC8D4DF0A8F881FE5C671A94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the timely submission of reports to Congress;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE255F94E3A5846468C2B7367FB14A3DB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>robust training, as required under Federal law and as needed or requested by Indian Tribes or Federal and State officials relating to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H11F3D730BC464EDB9CBD9F83FB87B9C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>public safety in Indian communities; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1115CD012DF947F9A930CE5A1CC87EEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>training outcomes demonstrating a better understanding of public safety approaches in Indian communities;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HECF8ACAB8F944F8CA4594B09FB9EDEF4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the updating and improvements to United States attorney operational plans;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8BFB1CF3FA3F462A9D5FF7B9D85B17DF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>comprehensive evaluation and analysis of data, including approaches to collecting better data, relating to public safety in Indian communities; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H61DCB8ABD61B491CBCC926679AC87266"><enum>(5)</enum><text>other duties or responsibilities as needed to improve public safety in Indian communities.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

