<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H640F62F7A071441485F9F1D470CA4ED3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5231 IH: Department of the Air Force Future Force Design Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5231</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Air Force to develop a force design for the Air Force and Space Force.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6D1F5024C54E4DFBA78C0585072FBFE6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H49B39AC01A194308AD99C2817DDE85B8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of the Air Force Future Force Design Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H6F338288EBF64E2580B64E22E24F49C7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Future force design of the Department of the Air Force</header> <subsection id="H5D2AC8263AC14C17A723485C3D05720D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB56F1087A063419F99DD215A0ACAB8C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Department of the Air Force has made significant progress in organizing, training, and equipping the Air Force and Space Force to address the needs of the Joint Force and align with the current National Defense Strategy and National Military Strategy; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6AF35CE32AAB47709124EB0E03A77674"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to be prepared to effectively deter and defeat a peer adversary, the Department must address force design requirements that will enable equipment modernization, organizational restructure, and capacity adjustments to meet the challenges presented by the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H55313934D23145DEAB0EA124A7438131"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Force design required</header><text>Not later than August 31, 2024, the Secretary of the Air Force shall develop a force design for the Air Force and Space Force projected through 2050.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2DA7CBE075CD4C0C860A71981F5A82A3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The force design under subsection (b) shall address—</text> 
<paragraph id="H10692D1E06794DA7BC176DCFF8424450"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the concepts, capabilities, and structural elements (including size and form) of the Air Force and Space Force that are necessary to ensure those forces effectively execute their core functions through 2050 in support of the National Defense Strategy and the National Military Strategy;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC49A0C47491648BAB96F771B25EC369C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>force structure, including the development of capabilities (including platforms and systems) at the right level of capacity to address the challenges outlined by the National Defense Strategy and National Military Strategy;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC349BD6FE44D48769D1BF48E5F70ACA5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>force composition, including recruitment and development of the human capital, effective distribution of forces in the total force and policies to increase career flexibility across the different components;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H42FFB5F4006048F391445631EE515B25"><enum>(4)</enum><text>organizational design, including development of potential models to increase agility and operational effectiveness across the Air Force and Space Force; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE7AAAE90AFF74D418E2B391DF50CEDD0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>such other matters as the Secretary of the Air Force determines to be relevant.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H36679EDB440142B38B38227FEF73D298"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Information to Congress</header><text>Not later than 60 days after completion of the force design required under subsection (b), the Secretary of the Air Force shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H750718E688424BB18AF40F656425696B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit a summary of the force design to the congressional defense committees; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE82414DAED84B9A845083D19B40B827"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide to the congressional defense committees a briefing on the force design.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H76ED3A034ED9494CA4AC1D8A7551AFD4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Congressional defense committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>congressional defense committees</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101(a)(16) of title 10, United States Code.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

