<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA5DFAC24085C4AD891174EDC4C816104" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1570 IH: Mental Health in International Development and Humanitarian Settings Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1570</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230310">March 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance mental health and psychosocial support within United States development and humanitarian assistance programs.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8319870E7805438A950D968448841FFF" style="OLC"><section id="H0268A353556F4F3A906CBC862377C3CB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mental Health in International Development and Humanitarian Settings Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MINDS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4031253DC0C648289372692E6376ADE7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; sense of Congress</header><subsection id="H629A381EE8934E91812AA6BEE06E4586"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H39AEFA7EBF04443FA6935B2661DDFC66"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the World Health Organization (WHO), an estimated 1,000,000,000 individuals worldwide have a mental health or substance use disorder, and The Lancet estimates that nearly 130,000,000 additional cases of major depressive and anxiety disorders globally in 2020 resulted from the COVID–19 pandemic.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0BC2337B2864D658F656223345121D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to WHO, depression is among the primary causes of illness and disability in adolescents. One-half of mental health disorders emerge by age 14, and 14 percent of children and adolescents worldwide experience mental health conditions, the majority of whom do not seek care, receive care, or have access to care. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H226D8325A77C4F09AAFD42878E60F778"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to the United Nations, more than 1 out of every 5 individuals in conflict-affected areas has a mental health disorder. Roughly 1,500,000,000, or 2 out of every 3 of the world’s children under 18 years of age live in countries affected by conflict, and more than 1 out of every 6 children live in conflict zones. A greater number of children live in areas affected by armed conflict and war now than at any other point this century. The mental health burden in conflict-affected contexts is twice the global average.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1B9EDDC98184238B015FC5F51C81735"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the World Health Organization, risk factors that increase susceptibility to mental health disorders include poverty and hunger, chronic health conditions, trauma or maltreatment, social exclusion and discrimination, and exposure to and displacement by war or conflict. These risk factors, along with demographic risk factors, manifest at all stages in life. Preliminary research already illustrates that the COVID–19 pandemic has increased communities’, families’, and individuals’ risk factors for multiple types of adversity and compounded preexisting conditions and vulnerabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DFC5CE6363A43BD9C0EA415C078E232"><enum>(5)</enum><text>According to a Lancet Commission report, allocations for mental health have never risen above 1 percent of health-related global development assistance. Estimates indicate that child and adolescent mental health receives just 0.1 percent of health-related global development assistance.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD9B91940096A4DB1BEA61188B3FAC8F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H286A46E4EAA3462A9DA1B644C74792C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>helping to ensure that individuals have the opportunity to thrive and reach their fullest potential is a critical component of effective and sustainable international development efforts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79A03D657D6C41D3A9E661A77F52F372"><enum>(2)</enum><text>mental health is integral and essential to overall health outcomes and other development objectives;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC08077D620B42F4B53680B8645978C4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>mental health is an issue of critical and growing importance for United States development and humanitarian assistance programs that requires coordinated efforts to ensure that programming funded by the United States Government is evidence-based, culturally competent, and trauma-informed;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FF8072A7F014D77B562E61262B6EFAD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the relevant United States Government development and humanitarian assistance strategies should include a mental health and psychosocial support component;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C4C2BA2AECC44DC8B269774D46F7F35"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the redesign of the United States Agency for International Development reflects the nexus between humanitarian and development interventions and should be applied to all mental health and psychosocial support efforts of United States development and humanitarian assistance programs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16EFE507E11B486093DD886DDE1098D7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>ongoing efforts to improve social service workforce development and local capacity building are essential to expanding mental health and psychosocial support activities across all United States development and humanitarian assistance programs.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0FC25F131EB248A78A02AD296649977C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Coordinator for mental health and psychosocial support</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 135 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2152f">22 U.S.C. 2152f</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H29EFB65AEBFC4ECD9BFEB2FEDF232275"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (f) as subsection (g); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74AAA6CF60214D9BBFA2994D63B833FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (e) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A5533F99599434F93E8A7917085500A"><subsection id="H82646B60B05E4F4DB569D8028FC40FC0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Coordinator for mental health and psychosocial support</header><paragraph id="H28C3BABE1866499E8F6064DF81BD77F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in consultation with the Secretary of State, is authorized to designate a Mental Health and Psychosocial Support Coordinator (referred to in this section as the <quote>MHPSS Coordinator</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8673BC5292B4C9DA576E308954F5210"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specific duties</header><text>The duties of the MHPSS Coordinator shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HBFD9D3F6CF2345098B948D7A40A97B69"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establishing and chairing the Mental Health and Psychosocial Support Working Group authorized under section 4 of the <short-title>Mental Health in International Development and Humanitarian Settings Act</short-title>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA40C65EEECF84962A6304E55F791858E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>guiding, overseeing, and directing mental health and psychosocial support programming and integration across United States development and humanitarian assistance programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64D13948AC2847FFBED816D10477B3A5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>serving as the main point of contact on mental health and psychosocial support in the Bureau for Global Health, Bureau for Humanitarian Assistance, regional bureaus, the Office of Education, the Inclusive Development Hub in the Bureau of Development, Democracy, and Innovation, and other bureaus as appropriate, the President’s Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief, and other interagency or presidential initiatives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5EB5408692B4594A7F94E35C24C575D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>promoting best practices, coordination, and reporting in mental health and psychosocial support programming across United States development and humanitarian assistance programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H968BFE7D21E94B16A2C38296E3F0D376"><enum>(E)</enum><text>providing direction, guidance, and oversight on the integration of mental health and psychosocial support in United States development and humanitarian assistance programs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1876932E003C4CE2B54C7E28755EEE80"><enum>(F)</enum><text>participating in the Advancing Protection and Care for Children in Adversity Interagency Working Group.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6EB8ADEB5254AFEB9DF47046FBB02E3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Focus populations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The MHPSS Coordinator should, as appropriate, prioritize populations with increased risk factors for developing mental health disorders, including—</text><subparagraph id="HDDDB981D4E9644D09DBF34D714EAF135"><enum>(A)</enum><text>adult caretakers and children, as well as families and adults who are long-term caretakers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0646C08E47D42CEB02AEEF97DA3A5E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>children and others who are separated from a family unit; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H447FCFA21F5B49EE803D65DAF856D85B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>other specific populations in need of mental health and psychosocial support, such as crisis affected communities, displaced populations, gender-based violence survivors, and individuals and households coping with the consequences of diseases, such as Ebola, HIV/AIDS, and COVID–19.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H9C8C9362DD4249F0B27E83DA1B7B42FF"><enum>4.</enum><header>Mental Health and Psychosocial Support Working Group</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Administrator, in cooperation with the Mental Health and Psychosocial Support Coordinator (designated pursuant to subsection (f) of section 135 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as added by section 3), shall establish the Mental Health and Psychosocial Support Working Group, which shall include senior representatives from the relevant USAID bureaus, the Department of State, and other Federal departments and agencies, as appropriate, to ensure continuity and integration of mental health and psychosocial support across United States development and humanitarian assistance programs.</text></section><section id="HA86F2520A0074E3AA791C9A8CD85BCCA"><enum>5.</enum><header>Integration of mental health and psychosocial support</header><subsection id="HA23B4E9619E642B7AE57BF019C9210B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text>It is the policy of the United States to integrate mental health and psychosocial support across all relevant United States development and humanitarian assistance programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5BDCBEA94A6E4B7999DFC7FECC76E8E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation of policy</header><text>The Administrator and the Secretary of State should—</text><paragraph id="HE2982D9BA85640F8B41671D28F4B2FA2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">require all USAID and Department of State regional bureaus and missions to advance the policy described in subsection (a) through relevant development and humanitarian assistance efforts, including by building local capacity to inform, design and implement mental health and psychosocial support programming;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C65ACFB565F47399F765D5AD1636066"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that all USAID and Department of State mental health and psychosocial support programming—</text><subparagraph id="H57108930758B45F194D820CA1BFA0626"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is evidence-based and culturally competent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8417F42856114B13A58F17DCE86F7F5B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>responds to all types of childhood adversity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF91EE5FC79DD4425B108FEA2866D6C0D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>includes trauma-specific interventions in accordance with the recognized principles of a trauma-informed approach, whenever applicable; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4DBDE68E18B4FEBBD904875B6DB6157"><enum>(3)</enum><text>integrate the principles of Advancing Protection and Care for Children in Adversity Strategy.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8741BA197A874A11BFDCEE5191D260F5"><enum>6.</enum><header>Consultation and reporting requirements</header><subsection id="HCB742A46A68F4B3298493BB26C8EF523"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator, in coordination with the Secretary of State, shall consult with the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate regarding—</text><paragraph id="H1472E58E69404FA6811860A51B374A77"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the progress made in carrying out section 5(b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CAB414B9E174FFCADC67B727C757848"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any barriers preventing the full integration of the strategy referred to in section 5(b)(3).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H45F04B72FB374E4296DA6781074938B4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for 5 fiscal years, the Administrator and the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Mental Health and Psychosocial Support Coordinator (designated pursuant to subsection (f) of section 135 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as added by section 3) and the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, as necessary and appropriate, shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on—</text><paragraph id="H592CF6CB86984C0BA3AD4BEE56C577DC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the amount of funding under United States development and humanitarian assistance programs obligated and expended during the most recently concluded fiscal year on mental health and psychosocial support programming;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B95A41BC5D94D15AD5EB6A55B8E2A0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>how USAID and the Department of State are working to integrate mental health and psychosocial programming, including child-specific programming, into their development and humanitarian assistance programs across relevant sectors, including health, education, nutrition, and protection;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38B25F045647440C9EA5A15957A1557D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the metrics of success of the Advancing Protection and Care for Children in Adversity Strategy and progress made towards achieving broader mental health outcomes; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE5CE494C88340A7B069832CA387D867"><enum>(4)</enum><text>where trauma-specific strategies are being implemented, and how best practices for trauma-informed programming are being shared across programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D76321AF8874387B2AB721D0CDEDDC3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>barriers preventing full integration of child mental health and psychosocial support into programs for children and youth and recommendations for modifications or expansion;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31A9710D2E63460FB26106E52CB3800C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>barriers to the expansion of mental health and psychosocial support programming in conflict and humanitarian settings and how such barriers are being addressed;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED8CA2087485411F86E92F5F78055BA1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the impact of the COVID–19 pandemic on mental health and psychosocial support programming; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77D1A159F74B4067A9096298E85306AA"><enum>(8)</enum><text>funding data, including a list of programs to which USAID and the Department of State have obligated funds during the most recently concluded fiscal year to improve access to, and the quality of, mental health and psychosocial support programming in development and humanitarian contexts.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H525B4AB7A16244DC9A9A62248AA15CD8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act, and the amendments made by this Act, shall terminate on the date that is 5 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section><section id="H7EC851B8B67E4BDEA2FD18818492A2F8"><enum>8.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HD75A7F277FDE48E382838AC042F7394A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of USAID.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE71473BADA14AFE86B81C8518DC298B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>USAID</header><text>The term <quote>USAID</quote> means the United States Agency for International Development. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

