<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEFE3F58A1B6E4B00B46BAC4FE7B902F0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5895 IH: To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to provide for additional uses of funds for grants to strengthen historically Black colleges and universities, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5895</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231006">October 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to provide for additional uses of funds for grants to strengthen historically Black colleges and universities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H15808B4885BF4E9DAD212CFC81A221ED" style="OLC"><section id="H3F0008516F3E4772B11DA7CD527A7972" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HED06E502DA3A49FE91337CBC9C25E176"><enum>(1)</enum><text>According to a 2021 study by Americans for the Arts, the arts are an invaluable aspect of American society, as they strengthen the economy, improve healthcare, spark creativity and innovation, and unify communities, with 73 percent of participants agreeing that the arts help them to better understand other cultures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF631491EBA5340FB976CAC3DC3E9635D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Many United States museums are grappling with diversity. Studies report that only 1.4 percent of artists featured in America’s top museums are black, only 4 percent of staff directors at top museums are Black, and that only 2.5 percent of Black Americans are owners of Arts-Entertainment business.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEA84CFDA0C6489B826684D19F851B42"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Historically Black Colleges and Universities, or HBCUs, are uniquely positioned to produce a diverse generation of art professionals and help bring much needed attention to works by Black artists. HBCUs have historically served as long-standing conservators and crucial supporters of Black art and for the teaching, supporting, and displaying of essential Black artists who may otherwise have remained unrecognized.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5D3E359F05C491586EE0DCCF1EDC837"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Arts programs and arts departments are expensive and have often fallen victim to funding shortfalls. In 2018, the College Art Association reported that at least 18 institutions of higher education planned to severely curtail or eliminate their arts departments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5FC0CB673744A8E98F453D7272EBD31"><enum>(5)</enum><text>HBCUs have also been underfunded by $12,600,000,000 compared to their predominantly White counterparts over the last 30 years. Some HBCUs have shrunk, consolidated, or cut their arts programs due to limited resources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75F6B474848B4C2297212A72197F92F1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An increased investment in HBCU arts, arts education, and culture programs can further help students of color access an affordable arts education and ensure the continued preparation, conservation, display, and study of works by Black artists.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF49D0F44F4AF4B97AC8B308966476063"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strengthening historically black colleges and universities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 323 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1062">20 U.S.C. 1062</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H6C31B508C0054ECC88B30DCBAC9E8E49"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a),</text><subparagraph id="HC3D1F377A922419BAD4C2F1DC99C7E3A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (14) and (15) as paragraphs (19) and (20), respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1122ACCEC4F47D6B46E1287F1114B47"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (13) the following:</text><quoted-block id="H6C88AF55C61646D2924085143EE1D191" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HDA0677F92C21433C85093CE668CA8410"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Providing financial and other assistance to students in arts, arts education, and cultural programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H341D9177A8084AB5A1D532AA79206814"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Establishing outreach programs and development offices for arts, arts education, and cultural departments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80A8C0FFB44343CD96C53ACD4AFF8A05"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Providing comprehensive wraparound services for arts, arts education, and cultural students, including faculty and peer mentorship, work-based learning opportunities, guidance counseling, and career advising.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DE082D1AB80491C829802E58BB55635"><enum>(17)</enum><text>Exhibiting, maintaining, monitoring, and protecting Black art collections in exhibition and in storage.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H920A2CBB06E943E3BDFD9B9C57B20941"><enum>(18)</enum><text>Providing well-paid apprenticeship, internship, and fellowship opportunities to students in arts, arts education, and cultural programs through partnerships with nonprofit arts, arts education, and cultural institutes.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE59F8206B0934D5F80B59D19AB6A72FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H6481110D49AC436A97BE8B99ACDBA071" style="OLC"><subsection id="HBD1E1EF079E34AEDA0EB9CC8A072B64B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>National Endowment for the Arts</header><text>An institution may enter into a partnership with the National Endowment for the Arts to carry out the activities described in paragraphs (14) through (18) of subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HEC65867E2B614ED09B9BE294E99D2E87"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>arts</quote> means art forms used for self-expression and interpretation, including performance, literary, visual, graphic, plastic, and decorative arts.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

