<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBEFC470CF6CD47B598FFDF10061756AB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3322 IH: Social Determinants for Moms Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3322</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001214">Mr. Mrvan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To address social determinants of maternal health to eliminate maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0571D348389943F6815254DDBDF1243B" style="OLC"><section id="H20E2051BA483490486FFF2A1F827BE0C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Social Determinants for Moms Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5C6A4EA6AA1C4504B2AB7871C93501E9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Task force to address the United States maternal health crisis</header><subsection id="H1C858C04DC7C4389BFE08321F093C73F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall convene a task force (in this section referred to as the <quote>Task Force</quote>) to develop strategies and coordinate efforts between Federal agencies and other stakeholders to eliminate preventable maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities in the United States, including actions to address clinical and nonclinical causes of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC78FA52FC4C547729284173827163FD0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ex officio members</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The ex officio members of the Task Force shall consist of the following:</text><paragraph id="HAC931A12B8064002A259B68BDE6858B0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD473BC84241341E6B5837ADDC3DA10BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4DE00877DF344C79D3D0F798195108B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB30148875EF34DE1961389F36AC5B1C2"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5C179952E46423D9A1EA8846F526C46"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35B4563A89D24929AF73B223FDFFEC4C"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7F54FA2BB5D4FE7938B220F24408A85"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary for the Administration for Children and Families (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D8E50DEE2F2426FAC236FF8B7AAFF0C"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H073D9C1A4080435681BC4CC30105BCFB"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Indian Health Service (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54CE3433EB874899BA4351C7557CB9E1"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institutes of Health (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D13283415034B2BAB1BF11C0BDC58D5"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC7D86CE49324A89BCCA8E525868C180"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Health Resources and Services Administration (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86A1FB5D388A46C7A1B8B2CB631CA9AC"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Deputy Assistant Secretary for Minority Health of the Department of Health and Human Services (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2952726F1FE4401AABED3852AABEADA5"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Deputy Assistant Secretary for Women’s Health of the Department of Health and Human Services (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD0AC9575BE64AC39B21DDC543F1126E"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC292C0DBC604E2297B55C8AB967A443"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office on Violence Against Women at the Department of Justice (or a designee thereof).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H965C1E47D30F486097A65A37B1134949"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appointed members</header><text>In addition to the ex officio members of the Task Force, the Secretary of Health and Human Services may appoint the following members of the Task Force:</text><paragraph id="H6D161BC961EF4B689EC5C3D000BF17C2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Representatives of patients, to include—</text><subparagraph id="H0EA3021F5E7A4B4C99018F11E73EE2CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a representative of patients who have suffered from severe maternal morbidity; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H469EEDECF2A147609FAAC56CB2AB7DA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a representative of patients who is a family member of an individual who suffered a pregnancy-related death.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H017B1D10CA774BF1820B183E1D1B5D63"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Leaders of community-based organizations that address maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health with a specific focus on racial and ethnic disparities. In appointing such leaders under this paragraph, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall give priority to individuals who are leaders of organizations led by individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00FE7F4C21834750BD89AC4CDEA9B5BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Perinatal health workers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H001E312834544D25B23DEBC9EA6CFA47"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A professionally and geographically diverse panel of maternity care providers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F60FFEE80B946F2873F0B1E1B4248FE"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other maternal health stakeholders outside of the Federal Government with expertise in maternal health, including social determinants of maternal health.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96375FACAA234424BB4427A024AF59A7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Chair</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall select the chair of the Task Force from among the members of the Task Force.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBC5D7427C9FF4C779775A5E73B7CF428"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Topics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing strategies coordinating efforts between Federal agencies and other stakeholders to eliminate preventable maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities in the United States under this section, the Task Force may address topics such as—</text><paragraph id="HCAF0D41433A2468F936A56A80D530700"><enum>(1)</enum><text>addressing barriers that prevent individuals from attending prenatal and postpartum appointments, accessing maternal health care services, or accessing services and resources related to social determinants of maternal health;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H404B52E250EF448DB4B5AE99FBC07FFF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>increasing access to safe, stable, affordable, and adequate housing for pregnant and postpartum individuals and their families;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5AB8A9328864F6D8CA6BA0047131E8B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>delivering healthy food, infant formula, clean water, diapers, or other perinatal necessities to pregnant and postpartum individuals located in areas that are food deserts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CFCE309A9024A4EB7E3A3D3D895258E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>addressing the impacts of water and air quality, exposure to extreme temperatures, environmental chemicals, environmental risks in the workplace and the home, and pollution levels, on maternal and infant health outcomes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1FF028DFDB84D86853ADCB265C32381"><enum>(5)</enum><text>offering free and accessible drop-in childcare services during prenatal and postpartum appointments;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FDBA3F5CFDD40A5B77B64EB7EB85560"><enum>(6)</enum><text>addressing the clinical and nonclinical needs of postpartum individuals and their families for the duration of the postpartum period;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7430591A027643738FB9F0040E384B2F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>engaging with nongovernmental entities to address social determinants of maternal health, including through public-private partnerships;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6DF5293F0184204B196DE934CB00780"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">addressing the impact of domestic or intimate partner violence on maternal health outcomes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6A38D2D3F3E4FDFA94F70ADF3A566E6"><enum>(9)</enum><text>other topics determined by the chair of the Task Force.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94D38F0DDD924E309DFEAF4E863C9D47"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, and every year thereafter, the Task Force shall submit to Congress and make publicly available on the website of the Department of Health and Human Services a report—</text><paragraph id="H09D7F663188C434DA218B5A676CAF328"><enum>(1)</enum><text>describing the Task Force’s efforts to develop strategies and coordinate efforts between Federal agencies and other stakeholders to eliminate preventable maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86F85FE1C32B4D23AE528F85B12E8130"><enum>(2)</enum><text>providing an overview of actions taken by each member of the Task Force listed under subsection (b) to eliminate preventable maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2E5F2E2EDA746A8B3DD541A4FF6DB9C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>providing recommendations on Federal funding amounts and authorities needed to implement strategies developed by the Task Force to eliminate preventable maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71668BDE21A24E7E803DD46DAEE2C1E6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>providing recommendations on actions that stakeholders outside of the Federal Government can take to eliminate preventable maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities in the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32192E387DC24205B90B8115035BFE41"><enum>(5)</enum><text>addressing other topics as determined by the chair of the Task Force.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC4A13E3251DB466C923A776E08199ECD"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1013 of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the Task Force with respect to termination.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3525077DC5D44DE690D8261D57902C86"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sustained funding to address social determinants of maternal health</header><subsection id="H7DEF1F10F73E4A7D9E0924DDA256E101"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall award grants to eligible entities to address social determinants of maternal health to eliminate maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, and maternal health disparities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE1E56D39DB7141E59DA407B3B452D88F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H570E016F1EA548D09EFE1E1C0376353E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a community-based organization, Indian Tribe or Tribal organization, or Urban Indian organization;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA7230D363E44D4EBD40309C66A50A2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a public health department or nonprofit organization working with an entity listed in paragraph (1); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FEAA7623C9749A0AA761A1956F8E25A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a consortium of entities listed in paragraph (1) or (2) that includes at minimum one entity listed in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA34D835D1074CE5A5F58DA8550FBA41"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may provide.</text></subsection><subsection id="H87933D0DAE474085B01EF462EB531DE9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under subsection (a), the Secretary shall give priority to an eligible entity that is operating in an area with—</text><paragraph id="H0DB7E81ADF4047089DC2FEE398AF91E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">high rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4278FF1206084475B3AD5FCADA0383F2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a high poverty rate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H048DAE95AC714D2E8FCB8AE3F75A0B9E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may use the grant to address social determinants of maternal health such as—</text><paragraph id="HF470B277AF46492C80CA907097B7B9B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>housing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9C353C043C04339BC5839FE6C6D1E4E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>transportation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D29D3C99B184F33B7959CEB49225918"><enum>(3)</enum><text>nutrition;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H168E419083564F719C3539F7D6B6029D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>employment, workplace conditions, and other economic factors;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE36E523CB91141958916201AE811F41F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>environmental conditions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0EBD36FB498E49CB986940E49C4A0D40"><enum>(6)</enum><text>intimate partner violence; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0F12BB6113D4BB8AA313506C83DF530"><enum>(7)</enum><text>other nonclinical factors that impact maternal health outcomes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB5EFD401D50940AAABCC6B1164CD4372"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide to grant recipients under this section technical assistance to plan for sustaining programs to address social determinants of maternal health after the period of the grant.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBA61472AEDBA42FBB0CA4EBB93EEA3E7"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reporting</header><paragraph id="HFC894E8B2A36495B8D56FECDA80986BA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grantees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after an eligible entity first receives a grant under this section, and annually thereafter, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary, and make publicly available, a report on the status of activities conducted using the grant. Each such report shall include data on the effects of such activities, disaggregated by race, ethnicity, gender, primary language, geography, socioeconomic status, and other relevant factors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D12528CECBA4DC9B4A26F9F7E266F4A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>Not later than the end of fiscal year 2028, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="HA99912B5CBD94494931862A80779A52C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a summary of the reports under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE2C9C169AFE43FA8A55A478212D46E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations for future Federal grant allocations to address social determinants of maternal health.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H466C67D29F074B11A8ACFE63905BAAFB" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC8F3763A087E41A1A1E6064D07770492" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H3B917AEBCFD54FF88449C4891A212698"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Maternal mortality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternal mortality</term> means a death occurring during or within a 1-year period after pregnancy, caused by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications, including a suicide, overdose, or other death resulting from a mental health or substance use disorder attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D1BE3B7EACE4A95A7D2B1327A2E9177"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maternity care provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternity care provider</term> means a health care provider who—</text><subparagraph id="H612F5900CD3C4FEEB9C543577270204E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a physician, a physician assistant, a midwife who meets, at a minimum, the international definition of a midwife and global standards for midwifery education as established by the International Confederation of Midwives, an advanced practice registered nurse, or a lactation consultant certified by the International Board of Lactation Consultant Examiners; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB96DDF41301407F99EF7FA9D7B790B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has a focus on maternal or perinatal health.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD19108EF7095456F844A75E6E4A99FDC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Perinatal health worker</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>perinatal health worker</term> means a nonclinical health worker focused on maternal or perinatal health, such as a doula, community health worker, peer supporter, lactation educator or counselor, nutritionist or dietitian, childbirth educator, social worker, home visitor, patient navigator or coordinator, or language interpreter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0855249CA674956B804349DEE10D358" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Postpartum and postpartum period</header><text>The terms <term>postpartum</term> and <term>postpartum period</term> refer to the 1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy of an individual.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF38A5953BD514787836B9587E457ACD6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Pregnancy-related death</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>pregnancy-related death</term> means a death of a pregnant or postpartum individual that occurs during, or within 1 year following, the individual’s pregnancy, from a pregnancy complication, a chain of events initiated by pregnancy, or the aggravation of an unrelated condition by the physiologic effects of pregnancy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F57A8FAA605485CB21C2FA2187A85BD"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Severe maternal morbidity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>severe maternal morbidity</term> means a health condition, including mental health conditions and substance use disorders, attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy or childbirth that results in significant short-term or long-term consequences to the health of the individual who was pregnant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DFB3B7C064C4743B6EDCA63FCE592B5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Social determinants of maternal health defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>social determinants of maternal health</term> means nonclinical factors that impact maternal health outcomes.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

