<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H53CC61F497E842029380F4655FEB8368" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4801 IH: Honoring Organizations Nationally for Ethics, Sustainability, and Trust Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4801</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Compassionate Capitalist Award to recognize organizations that substantially benefit the well-being of their employees, stakeholders, and communities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE890A1BB77404A8CA1CC744FD768D936" style="OLC"><section id="H2099D3266E2C41A08F58E6F3FF69EA5B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Honoring Organizations Nationally for Ethics, Sustainability, and Trust Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HONEST Enterprise Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H6C238CD1460A4AA89273FE55DABC5652"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of the Compassionate Capitalist Award</header><subsection id="H09143FFCABCC466292255B4229AFA6D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established the Compassionate Capitalist Award (in this section referred to as the <quote>award</quote>), which shall be evidenced by a certificate and a medal that—</text><paragraph id="H4FD00EB54F9E4D32A50A80F83BA2F1AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>bear the inscription the <quote>Compassionate Capitalist Award</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50EFFC03C27C48C0AC841721F97E494B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>incorporate such design and materials, and bear such additional inscriptions, as the Secretary of Commerce (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8831774B84BB436A9BFC8398A182CC2A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Presentation of award</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President or the Secretary shall annually present, with such ceremonies as the President or Secretary determines appropriate, the award to organizations nominated under <internal-xref idref="H1FF62BE276144F51A30FF94CF2969728" legis-path="2.(d)">subsection (d)</internal-xref> that the Secretary determines are deserving of recognition for substantially benefitting the well-being of their employees, stakeholders, and communities with respect to the following areas:</text><paragraph id="HC2D2B88CD8654DC8A348858DF4AA95C7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Environmental stewardship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The degree to which an organization has in place practices to manage the environmental impact of its operations, supply chain, and distribution channels, including with respect to air, water, land, biodiversity, and climate effects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H76E0BFB366BD4A059810A646F515415B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Governance</header><text>The mission, ethics, and transparency of an organization, including, if applicable, the organization’s corporate leadership structure and executive compensation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22B043A8853F4C66A6F0C703E2302121"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Social responsibility</header><text>The degree to which an organization contributes to the communities in which it operates and obtains resources from, including the organization’s practices with respect to diversity, equity, inclusion, civic engagement, charitable giving, and refraining from doing business with exploitative countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6876943713424D0B9F35030C1BD65AAC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Worker empowerment</header><text>The degree to which an organization contributes to the financial security, workplace safety, healthcare coverage, wellness, engagement, satisfaction, and career development of employees, and the degree to which an organization provides a fair and living wage.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C73C28393EF4185B4D272EFFF457158"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible organizations</header><paragraph id="H12E4EFD7C59643EA9FCE603718CC3436"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President or the Secretary shall present the award to at least one organization each year in each of the following categories:</text><subparagraph id="HF2D9E3A885744FE6A5F16F8ECA96E0DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Small businesses (at least 10 and fewer than 50 employees).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC25889B8929D4EF39A03E4B5BE7E16C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Midsized businesses (at least 50 and fewer than 250 employees).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA16A9B37B9C94A7386BDC03AF1FEC734"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Large businesses (at least 250 employees and fewer than 1,000 employees).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EE03F19AD824371B1EF82385BB86425"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Very large businesses (at least 1,000 employees).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1984C58242A84428AC1C7CECE0562396"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Total number of awards</header><text>Not more than 18 awards may be awarded each year. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H401E992CF4494A08862D8804092115FF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Notwithstanding <internal-xref idref="H12E4EFD7C59643EA9FCE603718CC3436" legis-path="2.(c)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref>, no award shall be awarded in a given category if the Secretary determines that no organization qualifies for the award with respect to such category.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1FF62BE276144F51A30FF94CF2969728"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Establishment of board of directors</header><paragraph id="H159678B291EA4C67AF9206C64B87FA61"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a board of directors to nominate organizations for the award and assist with administration of the award.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H314D24696D6E4EF3989D6BE50E67F437"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The board shall be composed of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H4B097832C55B43B288D4AA3A958446E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development, who shall serve as chairperson of the board.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA27431C02F924BC9AC0D93B8AA8C6CD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Wage and Hour Division of the Department of Labor, who shall serve as vice chairperson of the board.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3968EBE6582143C98788AABA28184066"><enum>(C)</enum><text>At least 6 individuals appointed by the Secretary of Commerce, who shall include—</text><clause id="H43A17328C20E493B97C12E255AC1E354"><enum>(i)</enum><text>2 individuals representing independent nonprofit entities that have demonstrated leadership and excellence in the field of standard setting and measurement with respect to stakeholder impact;</text></clause><clause id="H9CC3DB336BFF46B2AD8CF39584016386"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">2 individuals representing corporate business entities that have demonstrated a history of service to society; and</text></clause><clause id="H969184A4095D40B8AAF7B627C5FC954A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>2 individuals representing organized labor entities or worker advocacy organizations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H761492EFBE4A464EA6F0F19C823F8929"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Diversity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making appointments to the board, the Secretary shall take actions to ensure the diversity of the membership with respect to race, ethnicity, and gender. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92CD45CE9F474E96BB4A8F564A87297A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Evaluation tool</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The board shall seek to enter into agreements with appropriate entities to obtain an online evaluation tool that meets the requirements of <internal-xref idref="HBFF8241D8B7F4D229AAE9F17F0FEA32C" legis-path="2.(e)">subsection (e)</internal-xref> to assist the board in making nominations under <internal-xref idref="H159678B291EA4C67AF9206C64B87FA61" legis-path="2.(d)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H116C40B118A24A6CA913BDD407C64F8B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Additional verification</header><text>The board shall take actions to verify the accuracy of the facts presented by organizations seeking nomination for the award, including by soliciting employee feedback. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H76C95F59CEF047AD9993C4A20D289CF9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>The board shall annually submit to the Secretary a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="HE6B50B08CC334F969F6B49EF472F3CCD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>nominations for the award; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB68B456AB1C24287BC44856A3D603770"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of the process for presenting awards under this section, including recommendations for improving such process.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBFF8241D8B7F4D229AAE9F17F0FEA32C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluation tool requirements and analysis</header><paragraph id="HB69D6A65FAA84AA7854C0F76B590AC56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The evaluation tool described in <internal-xref idref="H92CD45CE9F474E96BB4A8F564A87297A" legis-path="2.(d)(4)">subsection (d)(4)</internal-xref> shall—</text><subparagraph id="H39D1B3B9C99840A0B177448C02761E29"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to producing the numerical scores described in <internal-xref idref="HF1AAF0AD1A7A4C4DA48F3770E66E8667" legis-path="2.(e)(1)(B)">subparagraph (B)</internal-xref>, use standards specific to the category of business an organization qualifies as under <internal-xref idref="H12E4EFD7C59643EA9FCE603718CC3436" legis-path="2.(c)(1)">subsection (c)(1)</internal-xref> that are developed in consultation with such organizations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1AAF0AD1A7A4C4DA48F3770E66E8667"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide for each organization considered for an award a numerical score with respect to each of the areas specified in <internal-xref idref="H8831774B84BB436A9BFC8398A182CC2A" legis-path="2.(b)">subsection (b)</internal-xref>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8B346C46C684DDE900306FB8E454F4A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for each organization considered for an award a total numerical score.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H246D0F3FFA0E4134AA4D59789AB65F4B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Analysis of results</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The board shall seek to enter into an agreement with an office of the Department of Commerce, or a contractor with the appropriate expertise, for such office or contractor to conduct analyses of the numerical scores described in <internal-xref idref="H92CD45CE9F474E96BB4A8F564A87297A" legis-path="2.(d)(4)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref> and report the results of such analyses in a standardized format to assist the board in making nominations under <internal-xref idref="H159678B291EA4C67AF9206C64B87FA61" legis-path="2.(d)(1)">subsection (d)(1).</internal-xref></text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H870140B815864893867A8F7364A7E754"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Award eligibility requirements</header><paragraph id="H7B9A5249E0754AC39391E0BA437EE68F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An organization may be considered for an award upon submitting to the Secretary an application in such form, at such time, and containing such information as the Secretary determines appropriate, including information necessary for purposes of the evaluation tool described in <internal-xref idref="H92CD45CE9F474E96BB4A8F564A87297A" legis-path="2.(d)(4)">subsection (d)(4)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61384AF8BCBE491F99AFB94462596D1A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may charge a fee to submit an application under <internal-xref idref="H7B9A5249E0754AC39391E0BA437EE68F" legis-path="2.(f)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref> and shall deposit any such fees into the account of the revolving fund established under <internal-xref idref="HBDC568C71E464413B757D9694829B47E" legis-path="2.(j)">subsection (j)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD31C37FA02244C46A3A9F18ABEA6778B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prior recipient qualification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An organization that has previously received the award is eligible to receive an additional award if at least 5 years have elapsed from the date such organization previously received the award.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19DDF41E6A204AACA48EDBD6B43470FC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Donor ineligibility</header><text>An organization that makes a gift described in <internal-xref idref="HBD21020552594E12B3463AD0FEB47D7F" legis-path="2.(i)">subsection (i)</internal-xref> is ineligible to receive an award after the date of such gift. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H91C953AFAB0A4A4BA48089559006B548"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Modification of areas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may, on the basis of recommendations made by the board and developed in consultation with the Climate and ESG Task Force in the Division of Enforcement of the Securities and Exchange Commission, make modifications to the areas specified in <internal-xref idref="H8831774B84BB436A9BFC8398A182CC2A" legis-path="2.(b)">subsection (b)</internal-xref>, which shall be effective 30 days after the date on which the Secretary submits a detailed description of such modifications to Congress.</text></subsection><subsection id="H87FD28CBCB624EC4ACDA088DF2EA5DA8"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Information transfer</header><text>The Secretary shall issue to each organization that applies for the award—</text><paragraph id="HC6F2BFF3D03C4FD8AB4F1D2166B3536A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the evaluation with respect to such organization; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H572E4C5F506945BDB044A88D479FF85E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>information with respect to the organizations to whom the award was presented and the practices that the Secretary used as a basis to present such award to such organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBD21020552594E12B3463AD0FEB47D7F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Solicitation of gifts</header><text>The Secretary may solicit and accept gifts from public and private entities to carry out this section and shall deposit any such gifts into the account of the revolving fund established under <internal-xref idref="HBDC568C71E464413B757D9694829B47E" legis-path="2.(j)">subsection (j)</internal-xref>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBDC568C71E464413B757D9694829B47E"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Revolving fund</header><paragraph id="H32D9C19B87B4419883C320A0D1430103"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Treasury a revolving fund to be known as the <quote>Compassionate Capitalist Award Fund</quote> (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Fund</quote>) to carry out this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AF55BFEFD734D7A8326BEC64F74C129"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Fund under this subsection shall consist of the following amounts:</text><subparagraph id="H84AAFC39DAC2437FAE4D562E8351F591"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts deposited by the Secretary under <internal-xref idref="H61384AF8BCBE491F99AFB94462596D1A" legis-path="2.(f)(2)">subsection (f)(2)</internal-xref>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14A76C1C0CC241EFB1193068065FD243"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Amounts deposited by the Secretary under <internal-xref idref="HBD21020552594E12B3463AD0FEB47D7F" legis-path="2.(i)">subsection (i)</internal-xref>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CDEB2FD47EB4E7087D7780E8F5A6351"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other amounts as may be appropriated under law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEEA081BB72546F488164D04A37B6A7C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of amounts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts in the account of the Fund under this subsection shall be available to the Secretary, without further appropriation, to carry out this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4F0A9FE147BD4FD48E21E1DC4E08F84C"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the President and Congress a report on the progress made with respect to the award and any recommendations relating to the process of presenting such award.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBDCC21E0471047F1AC1DBBAC9409DBB8"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Public availability of award information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish and maintain a publicly available Government website that includes, with respect to the awarding of awards each year, information concerning—</text><paragraph id="H6538AED53687435B9D4472C7108BD363"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the organizations nominated for an award under <internal-xref idref="H159678B291EA4C67AF9206C64B87FA61" legis-path="2.(d)(1)">subsection (d)(1)</internal-xref>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55D1DA1E18774C859021A5A565566668"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the process by which organizations nominated for an award are evaluated; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CE9CCA3D7424E50B2C8AB390870BA5A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the performance metrics which can be used to determine best practices for each category of business described in <internal-xref idref="H12E4EFD7C59643EA9FCE603718CC3436" legis-path="2.(c)(1)">subsection (c)(1)</internal-xref> in each area specified in <internal-xref idref="H8831774B84BB436A9BFC8398A182CC2A" legis-path="2.(b)">subsection (b)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

