<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1EC5C8C73A2040D49B3BDDCD8B0D9D2A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5014 IH: Employing Veterans to Feed America Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5014</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to submit to Congress a report on the Warrior Training Advancement Course, to direct the Secretary of Agriculture to administer a pilot program to employ veterans in positions that relate to agriculture, conservation, and nutrition activities of the Department of Agriculture, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2BD3398643D843C882C872E595A7D4B2" style="OLC"><section id="HD5776A58A0BC4B5BAA3167992969FB04" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Employing Veterans to Feed America Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H9B6995CB6CB8410B8ADB814F87DE3DA6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reporting on the Warrior Training Advancement Course of the Veterans Benefit Administration</header><subsection id="H40D3C3AE833840459F120F31EBDA3F85"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reports required</header><paragraph id="H3829E33FD48C46D585508CC4A28B42B1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than six months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on WARTAC.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A38E8823E1A4BDE859161FF56ADB306"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>One year after the submission under paragraph (1) and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to such Committees a report that contains the elements under paragraphs (1) and (3) of subsection (b) with regards to the preceding year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE12752277E0E413682A0E00F3B59C2F3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Subject to subsection (a)(2), the reports under this section shall include the following elements:</text><paragraph id="H06B91A055F3542248BC9CE934B627995"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text>With regards to best practices of WARTAC—</text><subparagraph id="HAB8F0DFD3CE746BB92C107565BDA0BB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how many covered members have applied to participate in WARTAC;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E1CEC2A5C0C4811A39FF49F5B7DB7B2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how many covered members have participated in WARTAC;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D0E4EB48EA8434C9522CF1E78A52D54"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how the Secretary provides training to covered members during TAP;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C1AC5D23A2B43F292B360FAF1866780"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how many covered members have completed WARTAC; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF608D9732F04DF8B65C973849A051DB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other information the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8F1899F81A0435BBB5F326C242C4379"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cost savings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With regards to cost savings of WARTAC—</text><subparagraph id="H5A87A254276C47B496C68B111A8C611B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how much money the Secretary determines WARTAC saves the United States each fiscal year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5DEB273FDEEF4F059853B34E6015D81B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how much money the Secretary determines WARTAC has saved the United States since its establishment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA07BDC35E6B141809B41855703FA1DDE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the determination of the Secretary whether other Federal agencies may save money by establishing a program similar to WARTAC.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC9F5099948041F28A494C5B47253417"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Hiring</header><text>With regards to hiring covered members who complete WARTAC—</text><subparagraph id="HD1E47A5A03964C279F8FBAD975296DF6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how the Secretary identifies positions in the Department of Veterans Affairs for which such covered members may qualify;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H662B0620B2E143C9919D3502CD174155"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the grades of such positions on the General Schedule under section 5332 of title 5, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC707DDF627AF4872BAF6CB7DA13FC780"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how many such covered members the Secretary has hired to such positions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HADDEA76CBB4E4826A13138595FC6F863"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>Not later than 30 days after submitting the report under subsection (a)(1), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall transmit a copy of the report under this section to each head of a Federal agency.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC4284F3565FA4E1996A94A5206BD2152"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HC8DF1C1078724913944EABAB5FB028C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered member</quote> means members of the Armed Forces participating in TAP.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4125D88762B42A7A5D217E4502C4012"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>TAP</quote> means the Transition Assistance Program of the Department of Defense under sections 1142 and 1144 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E5E53614B1344D8A2FAD1664EA16670"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>WARTAC</quote> means the Warrior Training Advancement Course of the Veterans Benefit Administration, in which the Secretary provides training to covered members so such covered members may qualify for certain employment in the Veterans Benefit Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1D8A6E456C1D40799FABE1D49DA6BBB9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Pilot program to employ veterans in positions relating to agriculture, conservation, and nutrition activities</header><subsection id="H4039B6E0709C4A60946A9CBC66ADDB1D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Best practices for other departments</header><text>The Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training, in consultation with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall establish guidelines containing best practices for departments and agencies of the Federal Government that carry out programs to employ veterans who are transitioning from service in the Armed Forces. Such guidelines shall include the findings of the report required under section 2.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9BE2506FE64347F4BDBBE228CFF0AD05"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><paragraph id="HB00D11A0F7604EFF8EBE6EEF460A9B71"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Agriculture, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall establish a pilot program under which veterans are employed by the Federal Government in positions that relate to the agriculture, conservation, and nutrition activities of the Department of Agriculture.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3CCDA0F24E04333AF748A329D0E1ABC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Positions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture shall—</text><subparagraph id="HCACC272421354935A07DF341543773FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify vacant positions in the Department of Agriculture that are appropriate to fill using the pilot program established under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FE189DCB7AC48B684B4EEF319B531D5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent practicable, fill such positions using the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD85658DCB32E4C3AAFC4F0F7E892DA94"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application of civil service laws</header><text>A veteran employed under the pilot program established under paragraph (1) shall be treated as an employee as defined by section 2105 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CB319C80B8C4EE5AE121A8A394F14FB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Briefings and reports</header><subparagraph id="H9A1D5A92DCA644ECBC4103A1EA5A1338" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture and the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training shall jointly provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing on the pilot program established under paragraph (1), including—</text><clause id="HB38A3970BB9A40A5A21C1542290F8410" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of how the pilot program will be carried out in a manner to reduce the unemployment of veterans; and</text></clause><clause id="H5C51DDE312204563807DB3D4AAE2C9EF" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any recommendations for legislative actions to improve the pilot program.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40A13BC9E35B4AF099A0CADE1E0B8882"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date on which the pilot program established under paragraph (1) commences, the Secretary of Agriculture and the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training shall jointly provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing on the implementation of the pilot program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H148E962190E746178C58273F900EBA03" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Final report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date on which the pilot program established under paragraph (1) is completed, the Secretary of Agriculture and the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training shall jointly submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the pilot program that includes the following:</text><clause id="H2255A063E1D5493DB8EC1E2A27D0285D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of veterans who applied to participate in the pilot program.</text></clause><clause id="H336B571459CA4B94AF65EF7C10806C84" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The number of such veterans employed under the pilot program.</text></clause><clause id="HDA7B226214D547EB9D4FD0C4AC55A307" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of veterans identified in clause (ii) who transitioned to full-time positions with the Federal Government after participating in the pilot program.</text></clause><clause id="HDACDB8D42864405EB5056BB133F9DBC5" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Any other information the Secretary and the Assistant Secretary determine appropriate with respect to measuring the effectiveness of the pilot program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HED592AB2413342E5B4E27E57FD8384EB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The authority to carry out a pilot program under this subsection shall terminate on the date that is two years after the date on which the pilot program commences.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6D3E2F5AAE26447996C2A26CEE1C414D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H41A8BF2D149A4C69A7B7F03C1A24F80F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs and the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E707451F05C47298B9430B82D89C9D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

