<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6AB389C494E54EFDBEA1A9DC0A56CFA5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2425 IH: Universal Full-Day Kindergarten Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2425</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to make allotments to States to carry out full-day kindergarten programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA932B2FB3DDA4E01B9AF391D6B7D0626" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA57591E013654307AB19EB493A7D8156" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Universal Full-Day Kindergarten Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H58A45391A81D4C21B10CD99C7F29E562"><enum>2.</enum><header>Full-day kindergarten grant program</header> <subsection id="HE811E6259C924424BB924353207CA9F9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a grant program to make grants in accordance with the formula described in subsection (b) to States to carry out full-day kindergarten programs.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H04C21BBBC15F4524A3443E49FB72C93D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Formula</header> 
<paragraph id="HCAAD2F6E28804D29B12835D39785A9D1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Secretarial reservations</header> 
<subparagraph id="H6EDA1341CBD14B418D0B1D25B4BE3927"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>From the amount appropriated under section 6 for a fiscal year, the Secretary shall reserve 2 percent of such amount for technical assistance (including capacity building) to States.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2C0E10849A3B44FFAE40A26E03C93754"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Secretary of the Interior</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amount appropriated under section 6 for a fiscal year, the Secretary shall reserve one-half of 1 percent for the Secretary of the Interior for programs under this Act in schools operated or funded by the Bureau of Indian Education, Indian tribes and tribal organizations, or consortia of Indian tribes and tribal organizations. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1DA742C31AEA46FC81EDD34D8B3C06C2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Outlying areas</header><text>From the amount appropriated under section 6 for a fiscal year, the Secretary shall reserve one-half of 1 percent for the outlying areas to be distributed among those outlying areas on the basis of their relative need, as determined by the Secretary, in accordance with the purpose of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBB05324AE338434EBA55760D17EC434E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State Allotments</header> <subparagraph id="H07D92A71532C4F8897285FC01E4B1B2D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the amount appropriated under section 6 for a fiscal year that remains after the Secretary makes the reservations under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall allot to each State with an approved State plan under section 3(a), an amount that bears the same relationship to the remainder as the amount the State received under subpart 2 of part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6331">20 U.S.C. 6331 et seq.</external-xref>) for the preceding fiscal year bears to the amount all States received under that subpart (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6331">20 U.S.C. 6331 et seq.</external-xref>) for the preceding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8A7B812D9A324B0BA08E18AE9B7E109D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum amount</header><text>No State receiving an allotment under this paragraph shall receive less than one-half of 1 percent of the total amount allotted under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9D56A5D87B1B465194D3FA39B5582E0F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Reallotment</header><text>If a State does not receive an allotment under this paragraph for a fiscal year, the Secretary shall reallot the amount of the State's allotment to the remaining States in accordance with this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4526D524C95E448EBD2AA46D7104AC2B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>State Reservations</header> 
<clause id="H8E4B5188B57846AA9B49E0AEF6A9C87B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State may reserve not more than 2 percent of the allotment received by State under this paragraph for administrative purposes, including the activities described in paragraphs (2) and (3) of section 3(a).</text></clause> <clause id="H326EC4AA6185445590FBD81E8D538798"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Local allocations</header><text>A State shall reserve not less than 98 percent of the allotment received by the State under this paragraph to make allocations to local educational agencies under paragraph (3).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD8DEB61F6027480089E7DB8688F7F72F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Allocations to local educational agencies</header> 
<subparagraph id="H02352533BEB046C694414E615A1D3546"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the funds reserved by a State under paragraph (2)(D), the State shall allocate to each local educational agency in the State that has an application approved by the State under section 3(b), an amount that bears the same relationship to the total amount of such reservation as the amount the local educational agency received under subpart 2 of part A of title I of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6331">20 U.S.C. 6331 et seq.</external-xref>) for the preceding fiscal year bears to the total amount received by all local educational agencies in the State under such subpart (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6331">20 U.S.C. 6331 et seq.</external-xref>) for the preceding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H54DCE6A6B25A484B872707C7D6CDD34F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum local educational agency allocation</header><text>No allocation to a local educational agency under this paragraph may be made in an amount that is less than $10,000, subject to subparagraph (D).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H562E86C980DA47EB9230DDD21756E007"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Consortia</header><text>Local educational agencies in a State may form a consortium with other surrounding local educational agencies and combine the funds each such agency in the consortium receives under this paragraph to jointly carry out the activities described in this section 4.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H86308729BCF843CD8532EFCB16330F23"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Ratable reduction</header><text>If the amount reserved by the State under paragraph (2)(D)(ii) is insufficient to make allocations to local educational agencies in an amount equal to the minimum allocation described in subparagraph (B), such allocations shall be ratably reduced.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H72CF49AB5CDD481D83E916AC440CCB5B"><enum>3.</enum><header>State plans; local applications<editorial></editorial></header> 
<subsection id="H03625E26C9184B698CFC2A4119F32F5A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>State plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to receive an allotment under this section for any fiscal year, a State shall submit a plan to the Secretary, at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may reasonably require. Each plan submitted by a State under this section shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H78ADC8B3780B4AD5B616409815E396B3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of how the State will use funds reserved under section 2(b)(2)(D)(i).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H765F6FA2981F4397AC205BE77C2D21C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of how the State will ensure that the allocations made to local educational agencies meet the requirements of section 2(b)(3).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8DD28A8510DD490F9EB8EB5DAD5F0E84"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Assurances that the State will—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H57E487C43E354E1A8150D98C6BC9B732"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review existing resources and full-day kindergarten programs across the State and coordinate such resources and programs with the State plan submitted under this subsection and the funds received under this Act;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5C3699A95D4B4995A209206D3339AF1B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>monitor the implementation of activities under this Act and provide technical assistance to local educational agencies in carrying out such activities; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB9841B7411A24DAB92E0ADE892BE5B95"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide for equitable access for all students to the activities supported under this Act, including aligning those activities with the requirements of other Federal laws.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1285D0F260B6464BB23C3A4B3F2AC1A3" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Local applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To receive an allocation under this Act, a local educational agency shall submit an application to the applicable State at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as may be required by such State.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HC94AC289567C482FB8333F7DB7C0682F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A local educational agency that receives an allocation under this section shall use the allocation to establish or maintain a full-day kindergarten program that— </text> <paragraph id="HE706E3156CF3470889249291008EE856"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a duration of at least 5 hours per school day;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5F1462CD16094EC5A417C991FDAE6B42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>permits children who are not younger than age 5 or older than age 6 to be enrolled in such program, except that a program that permits children who are not younger than age 4 or older than age 6 meets the requirements of this paragraph;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H663007ADD7FB4A408AEA9317C98747D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>does not require payment for participation in such program;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCE5A9379E332445EA3BFABB9CE402FDB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>is offered for the full school year;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6716ED65BCEF4A6BAB77F9F5F46CFD32"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is taught by teachers who meet the applicable professional qualifications (including licensure and certification requirements) for kindergarten teachers working in the geographic area in which the program is located;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD1264AD1A2334E4D8AB20BF71C72B59B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>includes academic standards that prepare students to meet grade-level benchmarks;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF526DC8F8CDF4CF19181C451EBA90130"><enum>(7)</enum><text>may include standards related to cognitive development, socio-emotional learning, physical and behavioral skills development, and recreational activity; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBD0EA9DFF2D2451C8866F2647049B748"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a case of a program supported by paraprofessionals, is supported by paraprofessionals who meet the applicable professional qualifications (including licensure and certification requirements) for paraprofessionals working in the geographic area in which the program is located.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HBC86FF10EFCC4D68BAB271ED9D6E84CC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall conduct a study and submit a report to Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCEF3B145B49D4820AD582C1DE13CFF94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>specifies the number of States, local educational agencies, Indian tribes, tribal organizations, and outlying areas that offer full-day kindergarten programs; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H063BBD44F72B4123B58786328176B933"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assesses the availability of such programs to individuals in each such entity.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H3BCA9E6DBF904A06AF3279AE8490C074"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></section> <section id="H3DE8541FA57A4304ACC4993C9AF6B949"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H90F60492B8894C7BAE8622C87623394D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <term>local educational agency</term> and <term>outlying area</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H209138D27CD940F2A9C4B92F599F6692"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H586C1FDE264043538B686E35FA869877" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the 50 States, the District of Columbia, and the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H53A064474A2149618108748B48356E52"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Tribe; Tribal Organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>Indian tribe</term> and <term>tribal organization</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 5212 of the Tribally Controlled Schools Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/2511">25 U.S.C. 2511</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

