<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2650753F500447B2BBA759982C715582" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3438 IH: Military Industrial National Defense Supply Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3438</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Defense report on the domestic content requirements major defense acquisition programs, to establish an enhanced domestic content requirement for certain procurements, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H960602FC406C4B6CA6C65B3EF5DEAA1A" style="OLC"><section id="H3EF4B57F906A4DF69E17C874F0881920" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Military Industrial National Defense Supply Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MINDS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD7EFB73343E94B699397759608EDA09D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Enhanced domestic content requirement for major defense acquisition programs</header><subsection id="H1227D984E2574E2EAA22860FD0539578"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assessment required</header><paragraph id="H7D6528CCC36C4B33B944F00C718B7B18"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report assessing the domestic source content of procurements carried out in connection with a major defense acquisition program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22E51672FD8243A38BFB49B50CDEE00E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information repository</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall establish an information repository for the collection and analysis of information related to domestic source content for products the Secretary deems critical, where such information can be used for continuous data analysis and program management activities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF826CBB92F7C49D1ACF758590822E717"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enhanced domestic content requirement</header><paragraph id="H1212BF663FE44ECAB106406E3A245C44"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/41/83">chapter 83</external-xref> of title 41, United States Code, manufactured articles, materials, or supplies procured in connection with a major defense acquisition program are manufactured substantially all from articles, materials, or supplies mined, produced, or manufactured in the United States if the cost of such component articles, materials, or supplies—</text><subparagraph id="H967621B6825A48FCAA001A4820E1937F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supplied not later than the date of the enactment of this Act, exceeds 60 percent of cost of the manufactured articles, materials, or supplies procured;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H582EA8F5F46E40B99CBF55BC14026701"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supplied during the period beginning January 1, 2024, and ending December 31, 2028, exceeds 65 percent of the cost of the manufactured articles, materials, or supplies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79B135C3F07849C39D7F85630E88AE6E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supplied on or after January 1, 2029, exceeds 75 percent of the cost of the manufactured articles, materials, or supplies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE958E362FEB4962BB205AD94BC0C1D6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusion for certain manufactured articles</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1) shall not apply to manufactured articles that consist wholly or predominantly of iron, steel, or a combination of iron and steel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10463BCB3276405FA7AB95A077138250"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rulemaking to create a fallback threshold</header><subparagraph id="H3014F08C9B5A4E78B6E477145430F0B0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall issue rules to determine the treatment of the lowest price offered for a foreign end product for which 55 percent or more of the component articles, materials, or supplies of such foreign end product are manufactured substantially all from articles, materials, or supplies mined, produced, or manufactured in the United States if—</text><clause id="HE0929101B3AE49788D70B15247A1D6BD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the application paragraph (1) results in an unreasonable cost; or</text></clause><clause id="H3C5CB5621E154635A24E5286FAFB673E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>no offers are submitted to supply manufactured articles, materials, or supplies manufactured substantially all from articles, materials, or supplies mined, produced, or manufactured in the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D1CFF4EBCD340D9AADE2C02A7507581"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rules issued under this paragraph shall cease to have force or effect on January 1, 2030.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D50F8324FC043AA9C64ABEC93F40733"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements of this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="HB2DECF7C18624E5A8E10E0612F5D21D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall apply to contracts entered into on or after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3EE9766D50B94E708DD4F7ECE053931D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not apply to a country that is a member of the national technology and industrial base (as defined by section 4801 of title 10, United States Code).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD9A2170F460B492A913A9A6499A78046"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Major defense acquisition program defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>major defense acquisition program</term> has the meaning given in section 4201 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

