<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBC4E1459CE0F46A0AAD9FB996A53190A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 598 IH: Earth Act to Stop Climate Pollution by 2030</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 598</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230127">January 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure 100 percent renewable electricity, zero emission vehicles, and regenerative agriculture by 2030 to address global warming caused by human activity.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H60D09CB61CCD44DD94CC84F65FB0995E" style="OLC"><section id="H45B49D6505624AF89D335B112C384B4E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Earth Act to Stop Climate Pollution by 2030</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB95BDC9D74DB48E38B2B387E0FF276F1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H8336E77767CF4E158F125C5ECDB5631F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Global climate change is an immediate threat to the national security, public health, and national economy of the United States as well as the legacy we will leave to our children.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H893DD36C6F074A318E7C670DBADB9909"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The most vulnerable communities, including communities of color, women, children, the elderly, persons with disabilities, low-income communities, and those with underlying health conditions, face even greater health risks as a result of climate change.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EF5D4882DD240D3B223B6CAFB17E92E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United States is already seeing climate change exacerbate extreme weather events, with—</text><subparagraph id="HD67A3F3B611D48C79D7CB299D0453768"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the year 2020 seeing the most active Atlantic hurricane season on record with 30 named storms and six major hurricanes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB907EBA5DD454C61AF2763169004F881"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the 2019 issuance of the first-ever Extreme Red Flag Warning for wildfires;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A5F200CEBBD4283B73204347501C13F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>hundreds of thousands of acres in the Western United States currently or recently experiencing devastating wildfires; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H611FC664A8684B1580880D577E719818"><enum>(D)</enum><text>communities around the country regularly facing <quote>100-Year Floods</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H04D62D4E12F04EC190278418B90A3E2D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The United Nations Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change 2016 Special Report on Climate Change and Land found that sustainable land management can contribute to reducing the negative impacts of multiple stressors, including climate change.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18B3E028C297430C8EFEC0E853B7DD73"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Environmental Protection Agency found that electricity, transportation, and agriculture accounted for more than 60 percent of greenhouse gas emissions in 2019.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6ABB74B53F8342BF9998D97A9FC7813B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The National Centers for Environmental Information found that, in 2021, there were 20 weather and climate disaster events with losses exceeding $1,000,000,000 each to affect the United States. These events resulted in the deaths of 688 people and had significant economic effects on the areas impacted. The 1980–2021 annual average is 7.4 events.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC56D496CA4514A4FBD5FF542A32BF4F0"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The total cost of United States billion-dollar disasters over the years 2016 through 2020 exceeds $600,000,000,000, with a 5-year annual cost average of $121,300,000,000. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H059C21352BD04139B38F27D47619DE0F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The IPCC released its Working Group I, 2021 report, which found that, unless immediate and broad reductions in greenhouse gas emissions are made by the international community, it will be impossible to limit global warming to 2 degrees Celsius, the warming level which the scientific community believes will precipitate catastrophic climate-related consequences and risks to human health, livelihoods, food security, human security, water supply, and economic growth will all increase.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55065F99B53D4522901039C93BA10F26"><enum>(9)</enum><text>In 2021, the Secretary of Energy, Jennifer Granholm, expressed that, by 2030, the clean energy sector will be a $230,000,000,000,000 global market for all technologies and products that reduce carbon pollution, spurring economic opportunity through job creation for people across the United States and the world.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70F02B8FF97048A4B3880168DB1AE0C8"><enum>(10)</enum><text>According to the Environmental Protection Agency, renewable energy reduces greenhouse gas emissions and air pollution associated with energy production.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1CD39EB2C0642B68148B6C250B1C70C"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The 2021 Department of Defense Climate Risk Analysis found that increasing temperatures, changing precipitation patterns, and more frequent, intense, and unpredictable extreme weather conditions caused by climate change are exacerbating existing security risks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FE087557B014428A4AF1DBD233AFB15"><enum>(12)</enum><text>In 2021, the Office of the Director of National Intelligence assessed that climate change will increasingly exacerbate risks to United States national security interests.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41F5F2F68D224B55B995C15066A3F88C"><enum>(13)</enum><text>In 2021, the President issued an Executive order directing the Federal Government to achieve 100 percent carbon pollution-free electricity on a net annual basis by 2030 and 100 percent zero-emission vehicle acquisitions by 2035.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84A3EA7BC1914FB6882CB20B3CD32091"><enum>(14)</enum><text>In 2021, United Nations Secretary-General, Antonio Guterres, described the urgency of addressing climate change by stating that <quote>the alarm bells are deafening, and the evidence is irrefutable: greenhouse gas emissions from fossil fuel burning and deforestation are choking our planet and putting billions of people at immediate risk. Global heating is affecting every region on Earth, with many of the changes becoming irreversible</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B502D6FF21B47BD847A507F63BF197B"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Sixth Assessment Report of the IPCC found that <quote>human-induced climate change, including more frequent and intense extreme events, has caused widespread adverse impacts and related losses and damages to nature and people, beyond natural climate variability</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D0CE666990A493AAD9A0D2B8BF60E51"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The IPCC notes that to avoid mounting loss of life, biodiversity, and infrastructure, we must have ambitious, accelerated action to adapt to climate change, while also making rapid, deep cuts in greenhouse gas emissions.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4F740D59E21C470C92C3535F8038A65A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Renewable energy</header><subsection id="HC64A3FAA8F4D49298AC14E7F91A3430A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Renewable energy standard</header><paragraph id="H3D43A74FE82449E88E4EF3C3080E38E5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Minimum annual percentage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The minimum annual percentage of the total quantity of electricity sold by a retail electric supplier that is required to be generated from renewable energy resources shall be—</text><subparagraph id="H81CC9F94B91D410EA4BB0BB932637506" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in each of 2027, 2028, and 2029, at least 80 percent; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H586A8FDCC2404E3DAAAB21ED8E075431" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in 2030, and in each year thereafter, 100 percent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0503B96AF80E47A68AA72FFB5E7994CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of Energy shall issue regulations to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H796994C54C41406196E428E6C3376E30"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Required submissions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The regulations issued under paragraph (2) shall require a retail electric supplier to submit to the Secretary of Energy, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the Secretary of Transportation—</text><subparagraph id="H21107E80ABDA40A791664017FEB68C26"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than one year after the date of enactment of this subsection, and annually thereafter, a plan to achieve compliance with such regulations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67DEF4311EF141709D4FA961996344EA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">beginning in 2028, and annually thereafter, by April 15, a report on compliance with this subsection for the preceding year, including evidentiary documentation regarding such compliance. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE4D8CFE4456457CAADF83B6B123928E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Grants for transition assistance</header><subparagraph id="HE35CC9AE95954CB68C33C8360FAA2DE3" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Secretary of Energy shall make competitive grants to retail electric suppliers to pay up to 50 percent of the costs of meeting the requirements under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA96CD59EF3BC4133B5DB50D535E2FA53" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this paragraph, the Secretary of Energy shall give priority to retail electric suppliers who display significant need, as determined by the Secretary, to finance their transition to renewable energy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFDD72AEA18C42B081FB23573CF5EEE0" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this paragraph, a retail electric supplier shall submit to the Secretary of Energy an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10BD86ECA88641E2991642020D283BFB" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Best practices report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of Energy shall develop and publish, including on the public website of the Department of Energy, a report on the best practices for retail electric suppliers for activities to transition to renewable energy consistent with this subsection, including how to apply for a grant under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H81FF80DFAE904C659F7FBC9D149B1C35"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Renewable energy sources</header><paragraph id="H09BC95C694EB4A2CA60CA58DB338D19D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of Energy shall issue regulations regarding the sourcing, recycling, and disposal of materials used to manufacture renewable energy sources, with goals of—</text><subparagraph id="H011CCD0135CC4BE8B66DC16BC9C9498B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>eliminating the use of rare earth metals in the manufacture of renewable energy sources; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB94810F3042E4125A735256A904D494E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensuring the recycling of all such materials.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC2F2245181E4370A5DFEB4E9741B0BB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Required submissions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this subsection, the regulations issued under paragraph (1) shall require entities subject to such regulations to submit to the Secretary of Energy documentation on compliance with such regulations, as the Secretary of Energy determines appropriate, including documentation regarding lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions with respect to the business operations of such entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8A7C36B3F144436E8D84E519C73C509E" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB3B30EB58F264A1A826B03A3F44D125F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Renewable energy</header><text>The term <term>renewable energy</term> means electric energy generated from a renewable energy resource.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D6D3B0185AA4001B0A67A5F89810CB3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Renewable energy resource</header><text>The term <term>renewable energy resource</term> means wind, solar, geothermal, tidal, wave, and existing hydropower sources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4778EE8F709464D946E7D7817B478F9" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Renewable energy source</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>renewable energy source</term> means any facility or equipment, including any component thereof, used to generate or store renewable energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39987C290C2C459D9243F93EDB6D7DCD" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Retail electric supplier</header><text>The term <term>retail electric supplier</term> means an entity operating in the United States or in a territory of the United States that sold not less than 1,000 megawatt hours to electric consumers for purposes other than resale during the preceding calendar year.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA727FF7A69C14677B3E9E77505463300"><enum>4.</enum><header>Zero emission vehicles</header><subsection id="H540B93974B4A414CBE49EED94B22E1C1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part A of title II of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7521">42 U.S.C. 7521 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H34096CEB86934812A67409E9811CDC9B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H6C748ECF8B0E42C493101DB89A3BA62F"><enum>220.</enum><header>Zero emission vehicle production</header><subsection id="HD87167184FDD44358839CC6695A43AC5" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Minimum annual percentage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The minimum annual percentage of the total quantity of new motor vehicles sold by a vehicle manufacturer that are zero emission vehicles shall be— </text><paragraph id="H1CDF96B3383544DDA4DA9C0583AFFFBE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in each of 2027, 2028, 2029, at least 80 percent; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CF028838FEB445497022C0A0AA43225" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in 2030, and in each year thereafter, 100 percent.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA7D5FF0EA89748F2B29A113D6419EF76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall issue regulations to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9B2208A7216B493DAA619E4667D52F13"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required submissions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The regulations issued under subsection (b) shall require a vehicle manufacturer to submit to the Environmental Protection Agency, the Department of Energy, and the Department of Transportation—</text><paragraph id="H6A6E311B316E43C38A793E9491CC9922"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than one year after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, a plan to achieve compliance with the requirements of this section, including the steps to be taken with respect to materials and supply chains; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B244273DEAB419498F62174DB325E5A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by April 15, and annually thereafter, a report on compliance with this section, including evidentiary documentation, regarding such compliance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0258B7BD00D4A16869512034927CD2F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">documentation regarding lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions of applicable new zero emission vehicles.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9E1BA905369545B2AE24CFA2BFD9BAF1" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grants for transition assistance</header><paragraph id="H0181742DCC00418598436949AE3F3715" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Transportation shall make competitive grants to vehicle manufacturers to pay up to 50 percent of the costs of meeting the requirements under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AD063EC8EA541008C4F2AF58D346547" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary of Transportation shall give priority to vehicle manufacturers who demonstrate significant financial need, as determined by the Secretary of Transportation, to meet the requirement of paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEF57AA0B8994CC6B3A30C3C919328A3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, a vehicle manufacturer shall submit to the Secretary of Transportation an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary of Transportation may require.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCDED711C2BC44AA6A6A1760ADA467156"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Administrator shall develop and publish, including on the public website of the Environmental Protection Agency, a report on—</text><paragraph id="H6A73DC03D7444ECAB54876402587C0E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>best practices for meeting the requirements of paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4EBBE05EAF1543D79AEAA390124776DD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>guidance on how to apply for a grant under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H85D09F04704843C780F6CCDDED67A8B6" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF80B67B738B24005BAF386B49AD1CC22" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Motor vehicle</header><text>The term <term>motor vehicle</term>, as defined by this part, includes the following:</text><subparagraph id="HA33FE1B9C38A4A0DAD96FA9A5686F05B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A light-duty vehicle that is capable of seating 12 passengers or less.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H630F0BADBBF647B78139B8B9D951DCD1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A light-duty truck which has a gross vehicle weight in excess of 6,000 pounds.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3E66DB8E37A49AB9540F1A4E96AAF15" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Heavy duty vehicle which has a gross vehicle weight in excess of 8,500 pounds.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H09864305B42242289B3F5971FF86B08F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Vehicle manufacturer</header><subparagraph id="H103FC818A04D4636B7ACC1F714A08112" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term ‘vehicle manufacturer’ means an entity that—</text><clause id="H7282F9AE7535429EB8FDD85F35F42077" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>engages in the manufacturing of new motor vehicles; and</text></clause><clause id="HA985E95D269D443DB8D9A780C5C5180D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>sells no fewer than 100 new motor vehicles to ultimate purchasers, either directly or through an affiliate, such as a dealer.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFFC5BB37D584BD4865EE6E283CD21D5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>The term ‘vehicle manufacturer’ does not include—</text><clause id="H31BDCD687D694D66B68346BC17886C8F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a motor vehicle parts supplier; or</text></clause><clause id="HC8E227844FBE47D1BAF192089AE910E8" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a dealer.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H241D02B7E3D945F2A68CCD1371F50A8B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Zero emission vehicle</header><text>The term <term>zero emission vehicle</term> means a motor vehicle, as defined by this subsection, that produces zero exhaust emissions of any criteria pollutant, precursor pollutant, or greenhouse gas in any mode of operation or condition.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HD1D3799C59984F968F3B5DD87EF21A27"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>The table of contents for the Clean Air Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 219 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8346E16D59D34538A11B29E779221AB1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 220. Zero emission vehicle production.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HEB8BE785CA1341DF9205BFC8895B66F9"><enum>5.</enum><header>Regenerative agricultural practices</header><subsection id="H0F96DED1F209419E967500A03954068B" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Minimum annual percentage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The minimum annual percentage of land and livestock managed with regenerative agricultural practices for a covered land or livestock corporation shall be—</text><paragraph id="H79EA25E3725C4564BFAA62D4644A81A7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in each of 2025 and 2026, at least 50 percent;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2BB0CC013EB440D9951F61E1C09A534" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in each of 2027, 2028, and 2029, at least 75 percent; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56CA49941D564A099B9022CA15F308B2" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in 2030, and each year thereafter, 100 percent.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAE9519C0BE0F40DFB556CCF227D42A70"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of Agriculture shall issue regulations to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4DD7A9A43EE94252B793021464CFBC07" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required submissions</header><text>The regulations issued under subsection (b) shall require a covered land or livestock corporation to submit to the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="H16B7EDB663EE42C59B1E9B286B886BDC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than one year after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, a plan to achieve compliance with the requirements of this section;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H364939A0F6DB4281AA85015715C30153" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>beginning in 2028, and annually thereafter, by April 15, a report on compliance with this section, including evidentiary documentation regarding such compliance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A5211AB46BF48BEB5E1FEC919E8D6E8" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>documentation regarding lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions of managing land and livestock with regenerative agricultural practices.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA0AB5A9477C4A64A5E6D22BB29EB13C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grants for transition assistance</header><paragraph id="H01D19658A4054364B98C4C38BC2963D5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall make competitive grants to covered land or livestock corporations to pay up to 50 percent of the costs needed to meet the requirements under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11783431C8CD494BAD51D2AC8CBA92CC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall give priority to a covered land or livestock corporation that displays significant need, as determined by the Secretary, to finance the transition to regenerative agricultural practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H151834B56F3A4C3D9E01A363B9160562"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, a covered land or livestock corporation shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBFB5520DCA1A437A8296CEBCD07559A5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Best practices report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall develop and publish, including on the public website of the Department of Agriculture, a report on the best practices for covered land or livestock corporations for regenerative agricultural practices consistent with this section, including how to apply for a grant under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA9622E59572144D49066DA8F27C54B59"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H386D743FC06A42CB900A214D1973E530"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered land or livestock corporation</header><text>The term <term>covered land or livestock corporation</term> means an entity or person that—</text><subparagraph id="H5BBEAA37F02440E3ABF87EC660549301"><enum>(A)</enum><text>owns, manages, or controls land or livestock, including through—</text><clause id="HC1569C0163044C308D14226515E552B3" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>farming, ranching, or other related agricultural operations; or</text></clause><clause id="H3F0A949DE1574EEE9A7B49CB08C61EA9" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>contracts with farmers or ranchers under which the farmers or ranchers purchase patented inputs or inputs otherwise owned by the entity or person to produce agricultural products to be acquired by such entity (or a subsidiary thereof); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H56DA32C2365D45B798CB7EBB8F585341"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is required to file an annual report under section 13 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m</external-xref>), or has issued securities under the Securities Exchange Act of 1933.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA058729317948FAB37679EBCC37E026"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regenerative agricultural practice</header><subparagraph id="H564804BC98354F4DB9409146FE62341C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>regenerative agricultural practice</term> means one of the following practices:</text><clause id="H2ABF64140BEC43B9BAA9F9F0117460D3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Alley cropping. </text></clause><clause id="H0968F32CF4E94809AC8CAD6C10A2E330"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Conservation cover. </text></clause><clause id="H025F0EC922B444B885E401735675AE1E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Conservation crop rotation. </text></clause><clause id="H3F281BACAA7D44F6AED10B31E66C936C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Establishment of contour buffer strips. </text></clause><clause id="H3C582CAD17674DC3A813D2828682A00B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Contour farming. </text></clause><clause id="H052A7E0B558A4C31B8AB1D26270D3AF0"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of cover crops. </text></clause><clause id="H25194F74953843DBBEE607DA5DCEDF30"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Critical area planting. </text></clause><clause id="H0BD28EC5FCEC469F9EADD0DCD71C1491"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of cross wind trap strips. </text></clause><clause id="H8BCE71F33F354ED7B3413CF6B0C11DC6"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of field borders. </text></clause><clause id="H6F35518A5067404AAB83971C00696C74"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of filter strips. </text></clause><clause id="HF27AC62D37E640439174814A277184A7"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Forage and biomass planting, including the use of native prairie and seed mixtures. </text></clause><clause id="HAD10C739A3D149868C23142992385405"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>Implementation of forest stand improvements. </text></clause><clause id="H23672D4BC70846E69D57018C729E4C31"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>Establishment of grassed waterways.</text></clause><clause id="HBD2696FE66354C94A28F9ABE5EC405CB"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>Hedgerow planting. </text></clause><clause id="H2E5308A28FAA4988A7D18142AC7A99DB"><enum>(xv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of herbaceous wind barriers. </text></clause><clause id="H1BD6B53FAC514E99900657D90AA21227"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>Multistory cropping. </text></clause><clause id="HDBE77780C31D4D5AB480BDF90C1AA695"><enum>(xvii)</enum><text>Nutrient management. </text></clause><clause id="H5A0E81501E244E5C9932659FE8843886"><enum>(xviii)</enum><text>Prescribed grazing. </text></clause><clause id="H73251025ACD64DE399921AF7F5F78411"><enum>(xix)</enum><text>Range planting. </text></clause><clause id="HF128EDCE58C2491F9001DBBEB77A301E"><enum>(xx)</enum><text>Residue and tillage management with no till. </text></clause><clause id="H3E307BFF5640415E9656C21D7D516DBD"><enum>(xxi)</enum><text>Residue and tillage management with reduced till. </text></clause><clause id="H6C9C5F85FDDF422DA0CD29596688E4E8"><enum>(xxii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of riparian forest buffers. </text></clause><clause id="H45FD7E21351442B384728170928FC8EF"><enum>(xxiii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of riparian herbaceous buffers. </text></clause><clause id="HD70608D4AB2A4492907482F4B55F447A"><enum>(xxiv)</enum><text>Silvopasture establishment. </text></clause><clause id="HE89CB8EA8BBF46CFAF27270A566BDC6B"><enum>(xxv)</enum><text>Stripcropping. </text></clause><clause id="H2E5F5ADAA7E24941BFF63FA3CEB7ABAF"><enum>(xxvi)</enum><text>Tree and shrub establishment. </text></clause><clause id="H264CD4CD50374E50B52F4EE4B61C73E0"><enum>(xxvii)</enum><text>Upland wildlife habitat restoration. </text></clause><clause id="HB9D5AE3A2FC14CDBBE057B0E95FF66D1"><enum>(xxviii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of vegetative barriers. </text></clause><clause id="H4A6B64A02F484028A45BE04B2B3AD05F"><enum>(xxix)</enum><text>Wetland restoration. </text></clause><clause id="HBC97091CF7F040F380D2272D031C8171"><enum>(xxx)</enum><text>Windbreak renovation. </text></clause><clause id="HF46BB37DD1D64BE4A6E62709C4B21FF2"><enum>(xxxi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of windbreaks and shelterbelts. </text></clause><clause id="HDFF422194472478590C90926E8223F7F"><enum>(xxxii)</enum><text>Woody residue treatment. </text></clause><clause id="HF41872D8B91A4675AA8FC6F666A13CCB" commented="no"><enum>(xxxiii)</enum><text>Any other highly effective and evidence-based vegetative or management practice, as determined by the Secretary, based on an annual review, that significantly reduces agricultural greenhouse gas emissions or assists producers in adapting to, or mitigating against, increasing weather volatility.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H804F6A157736465F906A331891F229A8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>In the case of covered land or livestock corporation raising ruminant livestock, the term <term>regenerative agricultural practice</term> includes the following practices:</text><clause id="HFB814B3F30564C7ABBB685C8A73DE216" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The practice of allowing such livestock to graze pasture during the grazing season at least 120 days per year. </text></clause><clause id="HD5E6BBE85DF54E009550B555E9DD78DA" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The practice of requiring such livestock to intake at least 30 percent dry matter from grazing pasture during the grazing season.</text></clause><clause id="HD25EF7FE317944BF9BE8E77062C9D1D6" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The practice of a producer creating a pasture management plan that manages pasture—</text><subclause id="H88505D3AD5DE4F5FBC74DFBA4D0AF5A0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>as a crop to meet the feed requirements for such livestock; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HF4547B9E2C0345FB8190C79223594513"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to protect soil and water quality.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0A54A9D067E54A488AEF88BDA32C41D7" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The practice of allowing such livestock to—</text><subclause id="H8E09F40F0FC04166BA937690B96E479A" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>display natural behaviors at all times, with access to pasture during the finishing phase;</text></subclause><subclause id="H2F111F2FEC684838909C4F16DCCE1AC6" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>have the living conditions and freedom to express normal behavior;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF215A733093A4B6791CED33137496C7D" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>have freedom from discomfort, fear, distress, hunger, pain, injury, or disease;</text></subclause><subclause id="H57FB4C94C9EA4ABB9D66E02C4D49C40E" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>not be placed in confined feeding operations; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD5CE39F1C770413FA318F267C6A8219F" commented="no"><enum>(V)</enum><text>have access to a suitable shelter.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H08C75D1C33DD4E8B9590D0BE422E2DF9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0C8C76D15AEB40F5AAA0BB8816D9A98E" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Greenhouse gas emissions reduction regulations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of Agriculture shall issue regulations that—</text><paragraph id="H16EEBAEEEB564E34AFA89E11674CBA3B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>require the reduction of greenhouse gas emissions resulting from the operations of a covered land or livestock corporation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5BA5ACC799184DBAAC02847A72373FAF" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include guidance on how to reduce greenhouse gas emissions through—</text><subparagraph id="HEFD215319C3F48DD9ECC4123A6220418" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reducing the use of synthetic fertilizers and pesticides;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC457BDDEDB14A6FBD33BA8787D79FB7" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>supporting the supply of organic fertilizers and pesticides;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F2BCA60C6BB47E895384F72315901DC" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>changing feed content for animals; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H025970EA11D9407E9C384604011344C6" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>general farming practices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H780DCF055EDE4878A4B645DB3A1E5603" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>food and animal transportation, packaging, and distribution;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3718C6E29C44A81AB039C37E7E8893C" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>minimizing food waste; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6042B64A53F74F4D9D4EE06E1CC40639" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>applying the National List of Allowed and Prohibited Substances, established in section 205.6 et seq. of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations), to regenerative agricultural practices, as defined in section 5.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H66748BA0D5824791BC0EDA7A99C743C8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Animal welfare</header><subsection id="H23617129044B451CB6E73610C97E015A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Animal welfare mandate</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of Agriculture shall issue regulations to ensure the well-being of covered animals.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1FCD74D13D564D84885E7DC7CDCEDB11"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Specifications</header><text>In issuing regulations with respect to the well-being of a covered animal, the Secretary of Agriculture shall—</text><paragraph id="H4779105E005C4811A8C4F8ED54B0824A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prohibit the use of antibiotics, hormones, implants, or other substances, except for purposes of disease treatment as prescribed by a veterinarian;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75F023E992124D649CC06575C3867641"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prohibit forms of permanent physical mutilation, including debeaking, beak or bill trimming, declawing, pinioning, wattle trimming, desnooding, detoeing, nose rings, and tusk removal;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72DE9AF6DA0649D2B2E01B7502BC4594"><enum>(3)</enum><text>ensure that such covered animal lives in a condition that allows the animal to socialize naturally, to engage in natural behaviors, to have freedom of movement, and to be reared with a mother and weaned at a natural time;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD105CFD3700745758332139575B9B679" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide for compliance oversight, independent inspections, and transparency of covered facilities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A6C590021AE425EBE97611E2AA65ED7" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>if a violation of requirements of this subsection is found during an independent inspection performed pursuant to paragraph (4), the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="HF09DCD7CC32A4C369D8366813922EE91" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish an online livestream video of such covered facilities that is limited in scope to such violation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H745EE1EB83C14BA2842A3317A7747486" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>grant the public access to such online livestream video.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF9ADBE6D211B448194B6196CFAF2BAE0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Agriculture shall submit to the appropriate committees a report detailing—</text><paragraph id="HAC61F543326F4E36AE760DDB119EE52B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the findings of animal welfare compliance, oversight, and independent inspections of covered facilities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA84862FE32441EE916D4FC00CE03C7B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations to Congress on additional actions necessary to ensure covered facilities are compliant with regulations set forth by this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB208A7519814A5DA5CB190C5CA32FAA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any other details as required by the Secretary. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6313EEF22FE543DA9CC4BA85F0909065"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H277417B8C37B45B987E5409A55AEBF08"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H8B724A96C868443C97F4D47671075E5F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Agriculture and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00D6A17EF7A24076B6EC4A7FDA0BEAED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2401BB47A78E43278B1CAB45C7A3423A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered animal</header><text>The term <term>covered animal</term> means an animal raised for human consumption or the production of dairy products, including—</text><subparagraph id="H13319CD1BC924DD6BF59B7BA2255F67F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">beef cattle;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6561369D56CD47A88C1526C377BD829D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>broiler chickens;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE52A2D65339F427DA9EE11C1E476FD8A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>laying hens;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C26203D073D409E82B6D1E252A8CF95"><enum>(D)</enum><text>dairy cows;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A1CACBBBF6B48A7B7ABC043AC1DCAA2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>sheep;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H675B7155823E4C3FBA0E770DDCE73DDE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>goats;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99661ABBD7414237BBAAF6BFDFAE16FD"><enum>(G)</enum><text>pigs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3ED116AE44DC43328153ABDEDCBA4A1F"><enum>(H)</enum><text>turkeys;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C5E6BEBE3D141BF8D07CC5C40515404"><enum>(I)</enum><text>bison;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H402C908A6CE04994A861ABE9B8749C3D"><enum>(J)</enum><text>waterfowl, including ducks and geese; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83B86B933FE544EBABCE9E5514EA5371"><enum>(K)</enum><text>any other animal raised for human consumption or the production of dairy products, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H584BF7A88AA342D9A4B2AE4F1726C415"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered facility</header><text>The term <term>covered facility</term> means a facility of a covered land or livestock corporation (as defined in section 5) that engages in animal raising, transport, slaughter, and processing. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H62897A2FB3BE4897B5E6624478268BEE" commented="no" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>8.</enum><header>Tax provisions relating to climate transition costs</header><subsection id="HF3467BA1238644B0A91A754B6DCAB842" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Qualified capital climate transition costs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/162">Section 162</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (s) as subsection (t) and by inserting after subsection (r) the following new subsection: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8ADFCF86713145ECB91A0C887B944271" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H5031B91A9D7E47A79B1A6F646F0EFD90" commented="no"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Qualified capital climate transition costs</header><paragraph id="HD7011C3093F84E77949FE33601B88161" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a retail electric supplier, vehicle manufacturer, or covered land or livestock corporation, the amount of any deduction allowed under subsection (a) with respect to qualified capital climate transitions costs (determined without regard to this subsection) shall be doubled. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC057A0C092A04E11845FF1E104220100" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified capital climate transition costs</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>qualified capital climate transition costs</term> means costs directly related to a transition to renewable energy sources, electric vehicle manufacturing, or regenerative agriculture, as such terms are defined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB5060393F1D4A2D866F6DE5D8F35A9E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section—</text><subparagraph id="H0E225C4814AA4E619AB4DB9D166AD981" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Covered land or livestock corporation</header><text>The term <term>covered land or livestock corporation</term> has the meaning given such term in section 5(f)(1) of the <short-title>Earth Act to Stop Climate Pollution by 2030</short-title>. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07AFB9E3D93F426A9F62901ACC991575" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Retail electric supplier</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>retail electric supplier</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3(c)(4) of the Earth Act to Stop Climate Pollution by 2030. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51697F0AC6794718AC3ED07DE4DF4C45" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Vehicle manufacturer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>vehicle manufacturer</term> has the meaning given such term in section 220(f)(2) of the Clean Air Act. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H00DB0519BA15440BB994555F630FDD9C" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified capital climate transition property</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/179">Section 179</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><paragraph id="HB122FE3501AA4768A77507B55A997876" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1), by striking <quote>The aggregate cost</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in subsection (f), the aggregate cost</quote>, </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB23EB27557C04F9D988FC2EFA9C25F15" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(1), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (B)(ii), by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (C) and inserting <quote>, and</quote>, and by adding at the end the following new subparagraph: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2CD381A2F0584C40981F24E30635B1F2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="HB0C28ABD666C4F3EA55C7063500898E6" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at the election of the taxpayer, qualified capital climate transition property (as defined in subsection (f). </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>, and </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H10FA0AED9073459EAA6C2C248C903185" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H52A8E9330985442D84FD7C0A50C1803A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H224972F3750D4B7F8FCAEC0701C7801E" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Qualified capital climate transition property</header><paragraph id="H2787CEBF91854AD7AAA2F2116728046C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>qualified capital climate transition property</term> means property directly related to a transition to renewable energy sources, zero emission vehicle manufacturing, or regenerative agriculture, as such terms are defined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD497EE1C21647FC8404D238AF2F3630" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish by regulation the aggregate cost which may be taken into account under subsection (a) with respect to qualified capital climate transition property. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FC3DACAA0CE466182983B9E016F83F7" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>The Secretary may issue such regulations or guidance as necessary to broadly define qualifying section 179 property based on the qualified capital climate transition costs that can be expected to be necessary in future taxable years. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0BFAC6C9C5A74A75B46EEF0332154115" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred in taxable years ending after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H0893FFF9B269486F8812BD11066A26BE"><enum>9.</enum><header>Support, oversight, and reporting</header><subsection id="H5DD01DCFA40D4A29B44003FAF13F8D58"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Support and oversight</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, the Secretary of Energy, and the Secretary of Agriculture shall provide direct oversight, facilitation, and support for the transitions to minimum annual percentages required under this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7E81F083763C434283F6939F926AA9C2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Combined reporting required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, by April 15, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, the Secretary of Energy, and the Secretary of Agriculture shall jointly submit to Congress a combined report on the transitions and the compliance of such transitions required under this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8102FCAD4903454F869AF9D7D7C9F637"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National Academy of Sciences recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this Act, the National Academy of Sciences shall prepare reports to assist all relevant entities with implementing the requirements of this Act and the amendments made by this Act, including staffing, supply chain, domestic production, raw materials, and the reuse and recycling of all elements utilized to create renewable energy.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD6B7BFEAAAA149CA8860BC8A3031C9A3"><enum>10.</enum><header>Disallowance of deductions for non-compliant businesses</header><subsection id="HF7D64349AB604EE09E848B57CB9AB1F2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part IX of subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (relating to items not deductible) is amended by adding at the end thereof the following new section: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6F7FC265FA34439DA9194647B02E7F27" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HB1C63FBE801D4D10AAD051963656C795"><enum>280I.</enum><header>Expenditures of non-compliant businesses</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No deduction shall be allowed for any amount paid or incurred during the taxable year in carrying on any trade or business if such trade or business (or the activities which comprise such trade or business) does not comply with the provisions of the <short-title>Earth Act to Stop Climate Pollution by 2030</short-title> at any time during such taxable year.</text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HD92E1FBC0FD945D59141F53C3222D52C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>The table of sections for part IX of the subchapter B of chapter 1 of such Code is amended by adding at the end thereof the following new item:</text><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 280I. Expenditures of non-compliant businesses. </toc-entry></toc></subsection><subsection id="H7B69202D435F40DBAEC0ECCCF7D08036"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred after the date of the enactment of this Act in taxable years ending after such date. </text></subsection></section><section id="H9DADFB909DDA493789BBCC7D61823AE8"><enum>11.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Should any provision in this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, be found to be unconstitutional by a court of law, such provision, or such amendment, shall be severed from the remainder of this Act, and such action shall not affect the enforceability of the remaining provisions of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

