<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF92491740DB744B9B81D8C1726D355C0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6263 IH: Earl N. Williams, Sr., First Chance Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6263</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231107">November 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to provide basic and emergency supplemental living assistance grants under the student support services program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H09B938DF84FF44CCBF2C07A4AAB5C495" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H785FA244164F44F38401F5FB9917FC12" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Earl N. Williams, Sr., First Chance Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H06B3C55AE05942388404BBDDFA39BEE2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Supplemental living assistance in the student support services program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 402D of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070a-14">20 U.S.C. 1070a–14</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H33FFAD7431DC4E83B4D90E2E69943338"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="HBA024712ABC1425D86CC578898B05131"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H836D3115237249B9A1F070F1D2B95574"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0062109AC8094AADA74CD2D21678E6A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAFBF19BA48324EBCA7246EF9CE2FA22D" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HC8F86AB51E31468A8CC7B8735879C63D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">basic and emergency supplemental living assistance grants in accordance with subsection (f).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB561CBB691634831BC16D7AEFF9A016B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6E0F9ECBCC764B4D96D3658C37BC494E" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HF861F2C17D1849DC93782A21E60032AA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Basic and emergency supplemental living assistance grants</header> 
<paragraph id="H00FC6AF9713C4462A5F39928A23D97B4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the activities required under subsection (b)(7) with a grant received under this section, the recipient of such grant shall provide basic and emergency supplemental living assistance grants to assist students who are current participants in the student support services program offered by the institution (in this subsection referred to as <quote>eligible students</quote>)—</text> <subparagraph id="HCDD4B871EC77479589BBD2AABA8A609F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of a basic supplemental living assistance grant, in covering reasonable, anticipated expenses necessary for the completion of an academic year of the students’ first undergraduate baccalaureate course of study; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H16FD95DDD99C441D9D680AC5520E30D7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of an emergency supplemental living assistance grant, in covering reasonable, unanticipated expenses necessary for the students to persist in college during such academic year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H261C506E5AA645EB9236F771E65552F3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount of grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The recipient may determine—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5147326D108D4970AFCF3A02065BC5A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the appropriate division of the funds between basic and emergency supplemental assistance grants, except that funds shall be provided for both basic and emergency grants;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5ECA66B634D849BFA163A16CB82845B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount of each such grant and the total grant funds that an eligible student may receive, except that the maximum amount that a student may receive in emergency supplemental assistance grants may not exceed—</text> 
<clause id="HAAC13E4426A24E27A4873E10F1C0AD2D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for academic year 2024–2025, $500; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD4BBC95A48CD494A8F152D4BDB8229C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for academic year 2025–2026 and each succeeding academic year, the maximum amount in emergency supplemental assistance grants that a student may receive for the preceding academic year, as determined under this subparagraph, increased by a percentage equal to the estimated percentage change increase in the Consumer Price Index (as determined by the Secretary, using the definition in section 478(f)); and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H613690A29D44486B970F10A707819629"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the anticipated and unanticipated expenses referred to in paragraph (1) that such grants will cover based on the needs of eligible students, which—</text> <clause id="HDEF333FC321741F697CF8E9A8CFE3C07"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may vary by factors including academic year, housing, parental status, location in urban or rural area, or other circumstances; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H531EA7655D4346B3A2D47EA1696BFF2F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for an individual student, may cover—</text> <subclause id="HD9F045FD78864DFCA78E1E6DA4D81045"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any component of the cost of attendance for the student;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H44303C1A89E74C96B0F9E0B503F8CED2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an allowance for actual or expected expenses incurred for dependent care that exceeds such expenses determined for the student under section 472(a)(9);</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB682DE104FAA4AD0917766CBFB10AAB1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an allowance for actual or expected expenses for transportation that exceeds such expenses determined for the student under section 472; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H748F35946E6942CDADC774EAB11BEA10"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">personal items or expenses not otherwise covered by the cost of attendance for the student.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA3A087BE554440F8917DCDA2A859B25"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Percentage of total funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The recipient may use not more than 2 percent of the funds awarded under this section for grants under this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4B5B968A3D9A4EB691F4778F99A74475"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Determination of need</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A grant provided to a student under this subsection shall not be considered in determining that student’s need for grant or work assistance under this title, except that in no case shall the total amount of student financial assistance awarded to a student under this title exceed that student’s cost of attendance by more than $500.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7BF5F8C51A68453F8FDBD6A3C9487E0A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making grants to students under this subsection, an institution shall ensure that adequate consultation takes place between the student support service program office and the institution’s financial aid office.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H18571D48B887455FAA28CDD895EFD6DF"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Funds received by a grant recipient that are used under this subsection shall be used to supplement, and not supplant, non-Federal funds expended for student support services programs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H6A913A4B5D05474FA111C9253E49044C"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For a fiscal year for which the funds allocated for projects authorized under this section from the amounts appropriated pursuant to the authority of section 402A(g) exceeds the funds allocated for such purpose for fiscal year 2024, not more than 2 percent of such excess funds may be made available for grants under this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE66E62943EE74E0B9568516A01B006BF"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>cost of attendance</term> has the meaning given the term in section 472.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HC691CE50FE124A889E4F371DF7524D78"><enum>3.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by section 2 shall take effect as if included in the FAFSA Simplification Act (title VII of division FF of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/260">Public Law 116–260</external-xref>) and subject to the effective date of section 701(b) of such Act, as amended by section 102(a) of the FAFSA Simplification Act Technical Corrections Act (division R of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>) (including the authorization provided under section 102(c)(1)(A) of such Act).</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

