<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H24EBEAC3D7C446F1BAC1A8094397781B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 864 IH: Securing Guam’s Shores Reimbursement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 864</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230207">February 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Homeland Security to make grants to the Territory of Guam for the purpose of reimbursing the territory for expenses related to security measures associated with aliens unlawfully entering the Territory, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H87A4F1E20C0D4E66BA4EA4BA9869F991" style="OLC"><section id="H698972999CAD475EB185159D2962C384" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Guam’s Shores Reimbursement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9548562163A340C597887677A2C436BB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Securing Guam’s shores reimbursement grant program</header><subsection id="HE4F90F5C420D40A498649BEC85708B40"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall make grants to the Territory of Guam for the purpose of reimbursing the Territory for expenses related to security measures associated with aliens unlawfully entering the Territory through the shores, which expenses may include additional wages for local law enforcement providing security for such shores.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9B1012D4122F40BBB47A0B3F931FC389"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under this section, the Governor of the Territory of Guam shall submit to the Secretary of Homeland Security an application in such form, at such time, and containing such information as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H215A4CEBB36A49B088FB237F1DABFD4E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>A grant under this section may not exceed $500,000 for any fiscal year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0386CA33CB6144318AD638491959CCBB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text>A grant under this section may not be used to reimburse nonprofit organizations, to fund legal representation, or to provide educational, housing, food, or healthcare resources to aliens who unlawfully entered the Territory of Guam through the shores.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9B2F6E3901E346A3B65AA572AFC7D5F6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter through 2033, the Secretary of Homeland Security, acting through the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="H8545361B7D8D487FAD02C4C503C93F9F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Information relating to the following:</text><subparagraph id="H2B8BDBAE36034D6C89F746861AEFB818"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The use of each grant made under subsection (a).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1291BA41B78044D6A923979D53C154EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The implementation of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EA48C7A384B435AADF68298301540DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Any recommendations of the Secretary for improving such implementation, including with respect to the amount of funding provided to the Territory of Guam pursuant to grant under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE2A31FAFBA240C7ACD4E548AE80743C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Conditional limitation on Secretary</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not obligate or expend any Federal funds for official travel, except for such travel to and from the Territory of Guam, if the following conditions are satisfied:</text><paragraph id="H8244AAE381C643DFACC15189436CF2A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Funds are appropriated or otherwise made available to carry out this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CB700282D4F43819D4856F662BDD9B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary does not implement this section before the date that is 180 days after the appropriation or availability, as the case may be, of such funds.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60FD0C1939A84A9AB9AAD7344EBF293B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>alien</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDDA185B40F944566A4509EDA1D86BAC2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $500,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

