<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA0C6786C78B942A987C44A52A790B559" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3679 IH: Healthy Air Travel Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3679</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Federal Aviation administration to develop an interagency task force to develop and implement a strategy to identify and advance research on communicable diseases in air travel, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H518C5494896541A4BF450B8011E95503" style="OLC">
<section id="H65443E935B3A40ABB8E1847B22878A25" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthy Air Travel Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HEC25A029E0034FB0B9CDD44F4A28FB12" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Interagency task force on communicable diseases in air travel</header> <subsection id="HDC00FFFEAE99477D8FF6C0C68ED09679"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, in coordination with the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall establish an interagency task force to develop and implement a strategy to identify and advance research on communicable diseases in air travel.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HAD76EA30BC8A4875B4D966857BC0ABD8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, in coordination with the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall select members of the task force established pursuant to subsection (a) from the Federal Aviation Administration, the Department of Homeland Security, and the Department of Health and Human Services and such other Federal departments or agencies as the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration considers appropriate. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H124924E81E6045C48862D778E007EA17"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header> <paragraph id="HEC16DD4BB6E5441180F47DCC9E7DE3AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>When developing a strategy under subsection (a), the task force established pursuant to such subsection shall consult with aviation industry, health experts, and labor stakeholders, including representatives of—</text>
<subparagraph id="H09E55E16BED047C18C6BAD71EE01EF63"><enum>(A)</enum><text>air carriers, which shall include domestic air carriers consisting of major air carriers, low-cost carriers, regional air carriers and cargo carriers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H83D79785B44A4A1896603A1D33ABD393"><enum>(B)</enum><text>airport operators, including with respect to large hub, medium hub, small hub, and nonhub commercial service airports;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF315E6905E9B4E649E14C0F3480DBFB3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>labor organizations that represent airline pilots, flight attendants, air carrier airport customer service representatives, and air carrier maintenance, repair, and overhaul workers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H785391BB0A2C4DC4BAEFED0D27FF6D47"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the labor organization certified under section 7111 of title 5, United States Code, as the exclusive bargaining representative of air traffic controllers of the Federal Aviation Administration;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H32DCD89354CC4CD7A4F7E62CEA76F2C2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the labor organization certified under such section as the exclusive bargaining representative of airway transportation systems specialists and aviation safety inspectors of the Federal Aviation Administration;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6A9D28987F77421196BD8D2AC88FEA6F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>trade associations representing air carriers and airports;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3D849034C306447EB1E4188C7B1ED764"><enum>(G)</enum><text>aircraft manufacturing companies;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8551EC4B9B54849A2E30B30AE144069"><enum>(H)</enum><text>public health and infectious disease experts and researchers;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC90C209725CB4F539096C0585567CB38"><enum>(I)</enum><text>scientists and engineers familiar with air travel;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC40F7CAA6F6043A789A19F49D52771CA"><enum>(J)</enum><text>general aviation; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4E23628F570C420382EDCD9DEA3A9C94"><enum>(K)</enum><text>such other stakeholders as the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B22B41C71AE4149AE222A0159A4EA10"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Balance of input</header><text>The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall ensure input from stakeholders under paragraph (1) is balanced between labor stakeholders and airline, airport, and manufacturer stakeholders. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2A74055F199345A98A50A58C60D3E6AE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements on agencies</header><text>The task force established pursuant to subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="HAFA4DBFABA8F45929DA89EF6BFC3F2A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine the resources needed by each department, agency, or administration of the Federal Government;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8AC8F07B7F5A4FD68F35FF9F1E2BF204"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify the responsibilities of each such department, agency, or administration; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50BEED5DF1FE4F97A392525D9ED53FF8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>catalog all interagency agreements related to this section for Congress.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3FFDCD78473141E88ED86DF9814E9FAB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Contents of strategy</header><text>The task force established under subsection (a) shall develop a strategy that, at a minimum—</text> <paragraph id="H1D74217C63B94FEDB2BCBDEAB78E890A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provides a holistic look at what is known about communicable diseases in air transportation;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFE0CB790D1F449FDA1C47AD994F19075"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifies any areas of needed research;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5AA94B3E993433790CAD0FBAF5E693B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">gives researchers access to relevant data, including deidentified health data, and to the extent practicable, gives researchers access to aircraft and airports;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDD7BF6BA59B14924967936F6B4517C2C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">incorporates, as appropriate, the considerations made by the Comptroller General of the United States to the Secretary of Transportation contained in the report titled <quote>Air Travel and Communicable Diseases: Federal Leadership Needed to Advance Research</quote>, issued in July 2022 (GAO–22–104579);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H768ABB1062C7456C832D5CF97A1B2BB9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>considers the latest peer-reviewed scientific studies that address communicable disease with respect to air transportation; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H15EB6FE9DF3A483B948A52EB77060D66"><enum>(6)</enum><text>considers funding constraints.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDEB175AD72BF4169A436319D72893365"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The task force established pursuant to subsection (A) shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the contents of the strategy developed under subsection (d) and that identifies what authorities, if any, the task force considers are needed by either the task force or the membership agencies of the task force to help ensure implementation of the strategy developed under subsection (d). </text></subsection>
<subsection id="H03A918C3300040839D919020DCE58E84"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H9543BE917A9F44B8BDBA89A65B68BDF4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Air transportation</header><text>The term <quote>air transportation</quote> means the movement of passengers and airline crew through airports, onto and off aircraft, and in the aircraft cabin. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA9A7CAFDF1DF40B988D4119B19E91DCA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Communicable disease</header><text>The term <quote>communicable disease</quote> means a communicable disease that has the potential to cause a future epidemic or pandemic of infectious disease that would constitute a public health emergency of international concern as declared, after the date of enactment of this Act, by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under section 319 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d">42 U.S.C. 247d</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

