<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8092DE5ECA6740DA9B324785491B21E8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5952 IH: Prohibit U.S. Funds to the Palestinian Authority Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5952</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231012">October 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit United States funds to the Palestinian Authority.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H40C5DE9B49664C3CB44BFAEB3628EA99" style="OLC"><section id="HBC8FA6AE2A3D48D093BE869488A97F19" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Prohibit U.S. Funds to the Palestinian Authority Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H210DDD68DE904828A2FAFABA5A4ED040"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on United States funds to the Palestinian Authority</header><subsection id="HCDF20F169679412BBADFBBD0381D96EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No funds available to any United States Government department or agency to carry out the provisions of chapter 4 of part II of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2346">22 U.S.C. 2346 et seq.</external-xref>) for any fiscal year may be obligated or expended with respect to providing funds to the Palestinian Authority unless with respect to such fiscal year—</text><paragraph id="H66FDA33260D647A48011BF504B73A2B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an independent audit of the budget of the Palestinian Authority is conducted by a United States nongovernmental or private organization or entity and the Secretary of State submits such audit to Congress; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C15D531D64B493FBE7C01590FA1E19F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of State certifies to Congress that the Palestinian Authority, at a minimum, meets the requirements of paragraphs (1) to (8) of subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0229037E91654BA992B86D9190E53B5F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements described in this subsection are that the Palestinian Authority—</text><paragraph id="H92187A4B59A3465C9899AE2B6D7A4EEF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>does not manipulate or inappropriately influence in any way the outcome of presidential or legislative elections in areas controlled by the Palestinian Authority; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0570B90E0D824552A34D2A31F10E698A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is advancing democratic ideals by actively promoting human rights and ending government corruption through increased efficiency and transparency in all government agencies and initiatives; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C9C1559B9674E6EB0017EF08C8828CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>regularly and strongly condemns terrorism; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7EEE5FBB51749E991CB17D0C1148CA5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>has taken, and plans to continue to take, tangible steps to disavow terrorism, dismantle terrorist infrastructures, confiscate unauthorized weapons, arrest and bring terrorists to justice, consolidate and control the Palestinian security organizations, and end the incitement to violence and hatred in the Palestinian media, educational institutions, mosques, and other institutions; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2AF16BC69304844B5227D87C547EAFF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>has ceased to participate in any economic, educational, cultural, or other boycott of Israel, its citizens, its products, or its services; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA35B52D35C024D47B0CB336E98382009"><enum>(6)</enum><text>recognizes Israel’s right to exist as a Jewish state and conducts diplomatic relations with the State of Israel in the same manner and to the same extent as it conducts diplomatic relations with any other country; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4618FC082AAE4DD39FEA654A9AEBAABF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>has either excluded Hamas from participating in a unity government or, if not, has required Hamas to explicitly and publicly support the requirements of paragraphs (1) to (7) of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB8FDAC66217B49C98886DE8EAFE0407E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section takes effect on the date of the enactment of this Act and applies with respect to funds available for fiscal year 2024 and subsequent fiscal years.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

