<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H1494E08EA6F644B797146F52EBE2410B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4467 RH: DHS Border Services Contracts Review Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 190</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4467</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–238]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on July 6, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Under Secretary for Management of the Department of Homeland Security to assess contracts for covered services performed by contractor personnel along the United States land border with Mexico, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HHM00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H53C18344B072456388C61585234B20E8"><section id="H4019C4DC1451427CBD6AB8FB79499663" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DHS Border Services Contracts Review Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF923D0E656454910830ED7AD9E7D4F57"><enum>2.</enum><header>Assessment of contracts for covered services by the Department of Homeland Security</header><subsection id="HBCBCFE20134643C28788965D25586A3D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H0B995683F76B48BE836B85C05E658BD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary for Management of the Department of Homeland Security, in consultation with appropriate officials of the Department, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report regarding active contracts for covered services of the Department awarded on or before—</text><subparagraph id="HCF5A2A47A20640C28CF611FBF5AE3A6C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>September 30, 2023, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C8488E8F6CD47FCA03F787C306F7DF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date of the enactment of this Act,</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">whichever occurs later.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF761F90F83F84CA19567E04C9B906E2A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF806BB43B71542B093125A71B06A8FF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The criteria used by the Department of Homeland Security to determine whether contractor personnel were necessary to assist the Department in carrying out its mission along the United States land border with Mexico.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E720ECB993341C09467CB2A60D7A877"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An analysis of the purpose, quantity, and location of contractor personnel to perform covered services of the Department with respect to effectively—</text><clause id="H50C2C9487E3743DB97E6A9EB1198B182"><enum>(i)</enum><text>addressing mission needs along such border; and</text></clause><clause id="H835B5982EAD141A7921E2C203AFA5767"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>enhancing the capability of Department personnel to perform primary mission responsibilities, including the number of Department personnel not removed from their primary mission responsibilities by reason of the performance of covered services by contractor personnel.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13132036F94B4F8BAF754A451433EA62"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An assessment with respect to the benefits of contractor personnel performing covered services, including whether the performance of such services by contractor personnel is more efficient or effective than the performance of such services by Department employees.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D8BF025ACAE47BF9FBA3E1D47820284"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An assessment of opportunities to increase the efficiency of the Department with respect to contracting, including whether Department-wide contract vehicles for covered services would be the most cost effective option for the performance of covered services. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D8A940CBFA5471F93F58528BC1DF9AC"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A strategy to improve the procurement and delivery of covered services through contracts during the five-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act to—</text><clause id="H7BFBC43AB7304ED9810F2292E956D26C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>achieve the best value for the Department through the use of full and open competition; and</text></clause><clause id="H5E0D789B72AC4FBBAAE68C07A6FF14FA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure no lapse in the performance of such services.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6469F07F9E54A42B10C8037A3628124"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Recommendations based on findings resulting from the analysis and assessments required in subparagraphs (B) through (D).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E22787C4C634A8390B87BF8C7077AF4"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other information relating to contracts for covered services that the Under Secretary for Management determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBA90FC5F0F604743BB9DB0673BF158AE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Implementation plan</header><paragraph id="HA1601BA9929E40F3AB593519092826EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary for Management shall submit with the report required under subsection (a) a plan to implement the recommendations and strategy contained in such report to enhance coordination, minimize overlap, and increase cost effectiveness among contracts for covered services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A3A2DC36CA1400188A74BE7B0AA8E07"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date on which the Under Secretary for Management submits the report required under subsection (a) and the plan required under paragraph (1) and every 180 days thereafter until such plan is fully implemented, the Under Secretary, or the designee of the Under Secretary, shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing with respect to the status of such implementation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7926817DB95C4109A9CB3FBDE62FD0BC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No funds are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section. This section shall be carried out using amounts otherwise authorized to be made available for such purposes.</text></subsection><subsection id="H33F03904B7D8416FA6629B77B41C639C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H4707CA299E0842378CE704E3C0D6DEA9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H6447DBB764984359B9AAABA5FF8E6D13"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H404C20C0B9DB4DDCBE64AB99FD3B41E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H737DA7CF00F84CA9B2054D99348CECBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contract for covered services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>contract for covered services</quote> means a contract (with a total contract value of $50,000,000 or more in 2023 constant dollars, inclusive of contract options) relating to the procurement of covered services for the Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC56A779DF154E3FBFBCD8B33FC3A005"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered services</quote> means, with respect to the United States land border with Mexico, any service, including related to border security, provided by a contractor to be used by the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

