<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H141D2F696BDC4865B9EF982EEE00FD21" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6835 IH: Care Across Generations Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6835</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001213">Mr. Steil</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Older Americans Act of 1965 to establish a grant program for multigenerational activities for long-term care facilities.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF571F40E94734227A677AD1C1E2EE291" style="OLC"><section id="HB19ACC8943684474A38ECFDD06CFB11F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Care Across Generations Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H44A6BABA76394F90B4FCB406DF377D09"><enum>2.</enum><header>Competitive grant program for the funding of multigenerational programs in long-term care facilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title IV of the Older Americans Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3032">42 U.S.C. 3032 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H69C503E113604ECA9F79B138BAE01464" style="OLC"><section id="H8AD5EB1469FD47CF97949AC0400A9688"><enum>423.</enum><header>Competitive grant program for the funding of multigenerational programs in long-term care facilities</header><subsection id="H203F460BDE6241FEA1055C25ED3F68D5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of grant program</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to—</text><paragraph id="H659EDB3B7F07486185E6A8FFD2513FDD"><enum>(1) </enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">operate a qualified child care facility within the long-term care facility or contract with a qualified child care facility; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H571D4FB8F4094B48BDE3F69913721721"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinate multigenerational activities between the integrated qualified child care facility and long-term care facility; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04BE83FC05304CADB7932EF289F88878"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">build a new, or expand an existing, long-term care facility operated by the eligible entity for any of the purposes described in paragraph (1) or (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7449FC56BAF8417B9A402F0F55CFCEB0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An entity seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Assistant Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Assistant Secretary may reasonably require; and in accordance the requirements specified in subsection (g).</text></subsection><subsection id="H7261EBA65EAF45D489246F95028F1D6D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Evaluation and report</header><paragraph id="H1DBDB995DBA4450FAEED10FE564D61BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall evaluate—</text><subparagraph id="H81AF96571F50444784C12DE1C750E5AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effectiveness of the entity in operating a qualified child care facility within an long-term care facility as required under subsection (a)(1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4641B57D61C4D6EBCA6BB3182A4F90B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the multigenerational activities coordinated under subsection (a)(2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD40C85BBE0154C168B040274E90C6464"><enum>(C) </enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the impact on older individuals and children of the 14 co-location and multigenerational activities carried out by the entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0430DB54BA3A4A4DAEA3987F0B9FEB1A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Each eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall, not later than 6 months after the expiration of the period for which the grant is in effect, submit a report to the Assistant Secretary containing the evaluation under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H722AE1FCBF0446ACA71DDC38D7D5BF04"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the Assistant Secretary receives all reports required under subsection (c)(2), the Assistant Secretary shall prepare and submit to the Committee on Education and Labor of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate a report that assesses the evaluations contained in the reports required under subsection (c)(2). The report required of the Assistant Secretary under this subsection shall include, at a minimum—</text><paragraph id="H958AED167BBC4305842BC1C16D49A7E3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the names and addresses of all eligible entities that received grants under this section;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5699774A4294675ABE41CF23668E336"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the methods such eligible entities used in operating qualified child care facilities within long-term care facilities as required under subsection (a)(1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CD681ECB6234D86BA284655FFCB712B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of the methods such eligible entities used in coordinating multigenerational activities required under subsection (a)(2);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84C184A9423B47CDA0C8019B871940AE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a strategy for disseminating the findings resulting from the projects carried out through grants under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7D2C821CC4F48388A25947349C211E1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any policy change recommendations relating to operating qualified child care facilities within long-term care facilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H04DCE31600B44AA99A6A672D94573A03"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>As used in this section:</text><paragraph id="HB29C80A4DB70481ABD2390A62AAAFFA7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means an organization operating an long-term care facility that submits an application meeting the requirements under subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81508977E2D24590B82B9230BB5C6C7C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Long-term care facility</header><text>The term <quote>long-term care facility</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H461FCF873AED481799A821E6EA83044B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any skilled nursing facility, as defined in section 1819(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395i-3">42 U.S.C. 1395i–3(a)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74962FF54D59456EAAFEEDFF4C65D328"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any nursing facility, as defined in section 1919(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r">42 U.S.C. 1396r(a)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04B3195710D94ADFAC16C09895239623"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a board and care facility; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB688CF74FD0F4449BBC1013DA8A56DDF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other adult care home, including an assisted living facility, similar to a facility or institution described in subparagraphs (A) through (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE56549EC3F3540008199749006ADCF54"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Multigenerational activity</header><text>The term <quote>multigenerational activity</quote> shall have the meaning given such term in section 417(h)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4271FA87E5F24C958F7620ED29672F71"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Qualified child care facility</header><text>The term <quote>qualified child care facility</quote> means a facility—</text><subparagraph id="H17D222ABBA3048729A08E135F36DD038"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the principal use of which is to provide child care assistance; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17085AE3A6984382AF2B403EE6A8D00D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that meets the requirements of all applicable laws and regulations of the State or local government in which the facility is located, including with respect to the licensing of the facility as a child care facility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H46A5B3D42AA4494597DA418A2DDEBDC7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Grant periods</header><text>Each grant awarded under subsection (a) shall be for a period of not less than 36 months.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7BC47B7E0E9446788C5DD2D6A2E12F25"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header><text>An application submitted by an eligible entity pursuant to subsection (b) shall include a certification that, for purposes of infection control and prevention, such entity—</text><paragraph id="HD334F88E25BD41F3BFE8C45243A9C559"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conducts a screening process for all visitors of such entity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEAC096C5DE704311B50C7826684E8814"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is in compliance with all applicable state and local sanitation and infection control requirements.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

