<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H69AC7233513843169AB9DB8BEC7B03DB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5302 IH: Michel O. Maceda Memorial Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5302</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230829">August 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. Gonz&#225;lez-Col&#243;n</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To designate the Air and Marine Operations Marine Unit of the U.S. Customs and Border Protection located at 101 Km 18.5 in Cabo Rojo, Puerto Rico, as the <quote>Michel O. Maceda Marine Unit</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2496420C0C8843258E74ABBABE1B7D2D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB216EA9E79134ECFABAD49CC82283B94" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Michel O. Maceda Memorial Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H335755FE498A441B852AFD2366554127"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6CD714DB4E2641E284476CAE34F64139"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Marine Interdiction Agent Michel O. Maceda served honorably in the United States Army as a wheeled vehicle mechanic prior to joining the United States Border Patrol as an Agent in Douglas, Arizona, in April 2016.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB365EED632C4935B3B38CC57C0456B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Agent Maceda became a Marine Interdiction Agent with U.S. Customs and Border Protection, Air and Marine Operations in Mayagüez, Puerto Rico, in 2021.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H69CBF1C792BD4785A7F7FF00221A2D35"><enum>(3)</enum><text>On November 17, 2022, Agent Maceda and 2 other agents were conducting a drug interdiction stop off the coast of Puerto Rico, during which the agents boarded the target vessel.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBD3A799898B442EA8B729C955164542"><enum>(4)</enum><text>During the stop, Agent Maceda was mortally wounded when 1 of the occupants of the vessel shot the boarding agents with a firearm.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H77527CA05E00481FBE626FD7C9A0E956"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Agent Maceda is survived by his daughter, brother, and parents.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H7CE5FE0D89E044E7BE72A5E292AD98B1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Air and Marine Operations Marine Unit of the U.S. Customs and Border Protection located at 101 Km 18.5 in Cabo Rojo, Puerto Rico, shall forever be known and designated as the <quote>Michel O. Maceda Marine Unit</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H64FC5BCD3D7847C59AE36E69B7E9598E"><enum>4.</enum><header>References</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Any reference in a law, map, regulation, document, paper, or other record of the United States to the marine unit referred to in section 3 shall be deemed to be a reference to the <quote>Michel O. Maceda Marine Unit</quote>.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

