<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3D8A1D9D38F846C9B9B89DB86460E865" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6136 IH: REO Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6136</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act to authorize the Reentry Employment Opportunities Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF99BAD3CF7C84067878C4018BB78C974" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H55FEC79119F74572A693F437974D828B"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>REO Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HE3B7BD1F1B5F4DDCA464D39113AD22EF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reentry Employment Opportunities Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subtitle D of title I of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3221">29 U.S.C. 3221 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H2BA6E7AE85804073A9C555D8B47D471E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating section 172 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3227">29 U.S.C. 3227</external-xref>) as section 173; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8F39AC9830C4861A46BDFCA764D6301"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 171 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3226">29 U.S.C. 3226</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H757CB16F41AB4ADF89879B5A57B70ADD"><section id="HEA02F28A979D4C8D8EF20F5651CEAB78"><enum>172.</enum><header>Reentry Employment Opportunities Program</header><subsection id="H6276F01ED4974FFB94CE64D99AB2CF8D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF1AE9E7AF81E430CB9B34050F4C02A4E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Correctional institution</header><text>The term <term>correctional institution</term> has the meaning given the term in section 225(e). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8FCB4574E614ED6803F2F078CAAC319"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible adult</header><text>The term <term>eligible adult</term> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="HB612C483CC5B41228156BD4D153232C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>on the date of the individual's enrollment—</text><clause id="HF9879F3EABEC4CB2893E1AD287625B04"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not younger than age 25; and</text></clause><clause id="H354088D351C1456BA09E3CEF0FE3B543"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is residing in or returning to the geographic area served; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4463503369940349FB20261D3331DE4"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9265E16196D14646B97465F19AED80E3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>before that date of enrollment—</text><subclause id="H3E0A3D62DE1847DDADA46A42689D7FC5" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>was released from incarceration in a correctional institution (including being enrolled in a work release center at the institution); or</text></subclause><subclause indent="up1" id="H4E48319F6BDC439F85343967FC8E41A2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>served an alternative sentence, or a sentence to a diversion program, ordered through the adult criminal justice system; or</text></subclause></clause><clause indent="up1" id="HAF603EF0BC6F490E8B273AC4965E5E1B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>on that date, is subject to the adult criminal justice system, including an individual who—</text><subclause id="H046F5735CEE84610AC2B85EAFAB7EB0E" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is incarcerated in a correctional institution (including being enrolled in a work release center at the institution), but is scheduled to be released within 6 months;</text></subclause><subclause id="H0CF0BE53F8974620A58BA0F342542810"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is residing in a residential reentry center; </text></subclause><subclause id="H34D1AB8229C44EC7BC08AAEF7C0F7A4C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is subject to electronic or home-based monitoring;</text></subclause><subclause id="H8EC903BAD55946DEAAB44D43E64331EB"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>is in the community on probation or parole; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HAB858D79A24F465BAC038A3A4DE556F8"><enum>(V)</enum><text>is serving an alternative sentence, or a sentence to a diversion program, ordered through that system. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H11C0215FD52144F39AA4BAA88DDF8EC3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible young adult</header><text>The term <term>eligible young adult</term> means an individual who, on the date of the individual's enrollment—</text><subparagraph id="H41F35BC7BEB142A7BB16C0F4C7517F18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is not younger than age 18 and not older than age 24;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7C111CF9225433DA617477F0D192888"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is residing in or returning to the geographic area served; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H928B69BE740945E48CB252E492ED5FCA"><enum>(C)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H22C8C96450BC49E683102F9A7F19C36C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is a school dropout (within the meaning of section 129(a)(1)(B)(iii)(I)) from a high school, except that not more than 10 percent of the individuals accepted to participate in a program under subsection (b) may be found eligible under this subparagraph solely on the basis of meeting the requirements of this clause; or</text></clause><clause id="H00760A9C57874598BF273C12715B901D" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is an individual who is, or has been, subject to the juvenile or adult criminal justice system, including an individual who—</text><subclause id="HD04CBF8F2557442AAD18B29F6E4AD059" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is or has been incarcerated in a correctional institution (including being enrolled in a work release center at the institution or in a detention facility for juveniles);</text></subclause><subclause id="H8C943348EAB74804A9F5B3A4C795CEE9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is or has been subject to that system due to having an out-of-home placement, or being on probation or parole; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H691018B86E4F42BDA365FD6C53F32C7B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is serving or has served an alternative sentence, or a sentence to a diversion program, ordered through that system. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4DF46045C4DE462E8A6109E36A245CBF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible youth</header><text>The term <term>eligible youth</term> means an individual who, on the date of the individual's enrollment—</text><subparagraph id="H7D308C6F3F1040518A29571D55F004AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is not younger than age 16 and not older than age 17;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5BCC33E27164780BC8635348827C871"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is residing in or returning to the geographic area served; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2F181E5147646E8A3A16987B37E0627"><enum>(C)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H09D0C77D7AD14EBEAFD6A9F194AD3A8B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is a school dropout (within the meaning of section 129(a)(1)(B)(iii)(I)) from a high school, except that not more than 10 percent of the individuals accepted to participate in a program under subsection (c) may be found eligible under this subparagraph solely on the basis of meeting the requirements of this clause; or</text></clause><clause id="H829AD6C764E04226875F923D90192334" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is an individual who is, or has been, subject to the juvenile justice system, including an individual who—</text><subclause id="H2CD09FDF4B524C728990FD43FAED0D62" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is or has been incarcerated in a correctional institution (including being enrolled in a work release center at the institution or in a detention facility for juveniles);</text></subclause><subclause id="H3A8C5B4DB4304B99AC7A18982DEA22FE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is or has been subject to that system due to having an out-of-home placement, or being on probation or parole; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H4A90233E763A4BFDA19044F369ACA48C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is serving or has served an alternative sentence, or a sentence to a diversion program, ordered through that system. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1DF7944670A4176A2A3D04F0B192430"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Enroll</header><text>The term <term>enroll</term> means receive confirmation that an individual, having applied to participate in a program under this section, has been accepted to the program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE828B053D3884B848168FBDC8AEB42F5"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Registered apprenticeship</header><text>The term <term>registered apprenticeship</term> means an apprenticeship registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; 50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H098866E47AA948F7AA0A833CBA685586"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Adult Reentry Employment Opportunities Program</header><paragraph id="H6080C8B9197049AFB1D3BEA779BF69F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and carry out an adult Reentry Employment Opportunities Program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BFD6C3B3B144489B705B72B1285B2B7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grants</header><subparagraph id="H1087BC912BAE4A59BB066C545A4814B9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Direct grants</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary may make direct grants to eligible entities to carry out projects described in paragraph (5), in geographic areas, for eligible adults and eligible young adults.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46B0D5A969794418A86483B209D0DCFA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grants through intermediaries</header><text>In any year for which the Secretary makes grants under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall make intermediary grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities who are national or regional intermediaries, who shall use the grant funds to make direct grants to eligible entities or to carry out projects described in subparagraph (A) in accordance with the provisions of this subsection. For purposes of this subsection, a reference to the Secretary shall include a reference to an intermediary who receives funds under this subparagraph to the extent that the intermediary uses the funds to make direct grants to eligible entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3930402A21C84BDF9A5E049794010CFE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a direct or intermediary grant under this subsection, an entity—</text><subparagraph id="H23A25108D7A441CE8B769D8B9DC8F693"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 that is exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20804054FE044877B24D1D7CA8222286"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be—</text><clause id="HF7C117A98B454354BA44A33419B73017"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an organization that serves women or a minority population;</text></clause><clause id="H6865C45A607F4BA0AE048C99EF34EBF5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a State or local government; or</text></clause><clause id="H368B14755FB54B6FA4DB55A6AACD5F64"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an entity (including an Indian tribe or an Alaska Native-controlled or Native Hawaiian-controlled organization) that is eligible for a grant under section 166 (including the regulations issued under that section); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H900F1EC8AE94463A93B6C4F6E52B54B2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>may be an organization that serves—</text><clause id="H0FE5FCE3511C4FCA84C0C7EFDAFB431C" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text> an urban county, meaning a county that is a Metropolitan Area, as designated by the Office of Management and Budget; or</text></clause><clause id="H17A2FDA73D394A51AC37B4E4C6E8169B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a rural county, meaning a county that is a Micropolitan Area, or neither a Metropolitan Area nor a Micropolitan Area, as so designated.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H60DE1EBFF4B648CEB56234A4D44E5260"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible to receive a direct grant or an intermediary grant under this subsection, an entity shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including, for a program that includes an industry-recognized credential, a description of the program leading to the credential.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2F396017709496EBA6376FC1D1E441B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An entity that receives, under this subsection, a direct grant to carry out a project described in paragraph (2) shall use the grant funds to carry out a project that provides opportunities in a pre-apprenticeship program, a registered apprenticeship program, an industry-recognized apprenticeship program, occupational skills education, on-the-job training, work experience, job referrals, basic skills remediation, educational services, behavioral health services, or work readiness activities, to eligible adults or eligible young adults. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A407F8A2EF44452B1B588C9284BCEB2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this subsection for fiscal year 2024 and each subsequent fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H339CA2F1058A4C4098B170ABF2E9FAE0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Youth Reentry Employment Opportunities Program</header><paragraph id="H2C83A39B8A7F408AB177DC27F0764116"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and carry out a youth Reentry Employment Opportunities Program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C2F79737D7C422CA304DF43AD83DAAA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grants</header><subparagraph id="H3326BF6685F144D6B999111647D3CFA9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Direct grants</header><text>In carrying out the program, the Secretary may make direct grants to eligible entities to carry out projects described in subsection (b)(5), in geographic areas, for eligible youth.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B77EEB948654B1EB3F0918FD79FE0D8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grants through intermediaries</header><text>In any year for which the Secretary makes grants under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall make intermediary grants as described in subsection (b)(2)(B), except that references in that subsection to eligible entities shall be treated as references to entities described in paragraph (3). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H94304C1C79BF4A7B82C4D1D27DF79479"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a direct or intermediary grant under this subsection, an entity may be an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 that is exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code or a State juvenile justice agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBC96AD002C24AB9BF4FAA684FB730A2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible to receive a direct grant or an intermediary grant under this subsection, an entity shall submit an application as described in subsection (b)(4).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8355FDF85AE4361ACA2E12701BFB75C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An entity that receives, under this subsection, a direct grant to carry out a project described in paragraph (2) shall use the grant funds as described in subsection (b)(5), for eligible youth. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F284E7C2964422F84825E0335507ED2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this subsection for fiscal year 2024 and each subsequent fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H00AC1EC110AF40F58EF6635A7427F6A4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall reserve and use not more than—</text><paragraph id="H646C17E28C564057BB589FA033640FB4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>2 percent of the funds appropriated under subsection (b)(6) for a fiscal year to provide technical assistance to recipients of grants under subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11BA7B7B95A746218A227DDCC58E8E3F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>2 percent of the funds appropriated under subsection (c)(6) for a fiscal year to provide technical assistance to recipients of grants under subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H047E0A078B5E411A9BECF115E4EC9CB7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Evaluation of the reentry projects</header><subsection id="HAA63C5F4F8CF4F2C8B823EC46EDB1315"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Chief Evaluation Officer shall evaluate the effectiveness of direct grants and intermediary grants used by the Department of Labor to support offender reentry and recidivism reduction through reentry projects at the Federal, State, local, and tribal levels. The Chief Evaluation Officer shall evaluate each of the following: </text><paragraph id="HB737CB867E66453F8505DA61419EADC6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The effectiveness of such projects in relation to their cost, including the extent to which the projects improve reentry outcomes, including employment, education, housing, and reductions in recidivism, of participants in comparison to comparably situated individuals who did not participate in such projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04EC2EC4EFF042E88255773A718D9806"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The effectiveness of project structures and mechanisms for delivery of services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4820C9CDAEB748049EDCFE3460979D85"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The impact of such projects on the communities and participants involved.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7BBCE4A6AD54D488C62525446D61FC5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The impact of such projects on related programs and activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C2E638A5A3846A7AB70978789081962"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The extent to which such projects meet the needs of various demographic groups.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BBC696CE62745398EBD2E4D5EAE69BA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The quality and effectiveness of technical assistance provided by the Department of Labor to grantees for implementing such projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5187E71F331947EC8EDC5CFDB9C14B32"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Such other factors as may be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H22507CBA37DF4CC3AA1E7A8051DDE6F3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Availability of funds for evaluation</header><text>Not more than 2.5 percent of any amounts appropriated for a fiscal year to carry out the reentry projects shall be reserved and made available to the Chief Evaluation Officer for such evaluation, including evaluating the processes, implementation, outcomes, costs, and effectiveness of the reentry projects in improving reentry and reducing recidivism. Such reserved funding may be used to provide support to recipients of direct grants and intermediary grants for reentry projects for supplemental data collection, analysis, and coordination associated with evaluation activities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEA58B9CF95A14E5E819B204022FAAC73"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Techniques</header><text>Evaluations conducted under this section shall use appropriate methodology and research designs. Impact evaluations conducted under this section shall include the use of intervention and control groups chosen by random assignment methods, to the extent possible.</text></subsection><subsection id="H94AE7AEEE0E244729FEEE7F38B0A6093"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Metrics and Outcomes for Evaluation</header><paragraph id="H61445AB5FF0A43979031EA1CAFA7F00D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Chief Evaluation Officer shall consult with relevant stakeholders and identify outcome measures, including measures for employment, housing, education, and public safety, that are to be achieved by reentry projects and the metrics by which the achievement of such outcomes shall be determined.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07F90EE74CCB4A7192D97357C4072E8B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the Chief Evaluation Officer identifies metrics and outcomes under paragraph (1), the Secretary of Labor shall publish such metrics and outcomes identified.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0705BE86706B4EC8BF4ED2E549134940"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Data collection</header><text>As a condition of receiving a direct grant or intermediary grant for a reentry project, grantees shall be required to collect and report to the Department of Labor data based upon the metrics identified under subsection (d). In accordance with applicable law, collection of individual-level data under a pledge of confidentiality shall be protected by the Chief Evaluation Officer in accordance with such pledge. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6C2C802FA8BD4C989D0AEA008A6779A3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Data accessibility</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Chief Evaluation Officer shall—</text><paragraph id="H0F89B1191B9A4D5EAAEDD7D8DEEA2B86"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make data collected during the course of evaluation under this section available in de-identified form in such a manner that reasonably protects a pledge of confidentiality to participants under subsection (e); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3F8646C61EE4C028CE9FFE9B0C600B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make identifiable data collected during the course of evaluation under this section available to qualified researchers for future research and evaluation, in accordance with applicable law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD0F396D99F9C41268939E570A2E53AA9"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Publication and reporting of evaluation findings</header><text>The Chief Evaluation Officer shall—</text><paragraph id="H3A5FA5CCD1EC48FE9AA18C28EFC3A919"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 365 days after the date on which the enrollment of participants in an impact evaluation is completed under this section, publish an interim report on such evaluation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA1EFD756531453C966F2C6915A08B05"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date on which any evaluation is completed under this section, publish and make publicly available such evaluation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D2837846D8B40B5A469EBCC1DE8CCFF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not later than 60 days after the completion date described in paragraph (2), submit a report to the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate on such evaluation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB725616AA55442CA7ACE2B51C85BB53" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HCFB87F0BEE8A4E2887BFBEE84D3631B7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chief Evaluation Officer</header><text>The term <term>Chief Evaluation Officer</term> means the head of the independent evaluation office located organizationally in the Office of the Assistant Secretary for Policy of the Department of Labor. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5FACC614B16B413EA210631C195AEE7C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reentry project</header><text>The term <term>reentry project</term> means a project funded under the reentry employment opportunities program carried out under section 172 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunities Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0CBAA39A6FF944DE9447DC081E661612"><enum>4.</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act is amended—</text><paragraph id="HCAA19D758F8C48B5985C28482A5FA2EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the item relating to section 172 as the item relating to section 173; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H93E920B0E7B048E6871CD81AC4828F1F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 171 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H077CBA596C0D421192D7AF07E2C75909" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 172. Reentry Employment Opportunities Program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

