<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFE545B4F9AD24AB8885D57B38F3D2049" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3433 IH: Give Kids a Chance Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3433</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001260">Mr. Buchanan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001058">Mr. Huizenga</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act with respect to molecularly targeted pediatric cancer investigations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H02054FC5496546E3B2D32F7A68A5878F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA2D873F056D34E29A0FBCDC509C359B1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Give Kids a Chance Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text> </section> <section id="H5B4742FED2D94E35BB1892AB8F8E05F0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Research into pediatric uses of drugs; additional authorities of Food and Drug Administration regarding molecularly targeted cancer drugs</header> <subsection id="H5837D461E7764A629BA35059598888B4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="H86CAA14FF11042CF92896C41CCB19452"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Additional active ingredient for application drug; limitation regarding novel-combination application drug</header><text>Section 505B(a)(3) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355c">21 U.S.C. 355c(a)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE9729BAB733346A1A579AAB49B6133A7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) and (C) as subparagraphs (C) and (D), respectively; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H314B729970DF469AB6DF35D830B5D0BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (A) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H772B2E3B9C10420499917A4357FDBBC7"> 
<subparagraph id="HDD9869D8FCD045C0A60B8B855690DD41"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1)(B), the investigation described in this paragraph is (as determined by the Secretary) a molecularly targeted pediatric cancer investigation of—</text> <clause id="H4E3DAD99CD664E5AB1515E216B9677BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the drug or biological product for which the application referred to in such paragraph is submitted; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB03E2F008B6F4B8F85444A09CB014671"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such drug or biological product in combination with—</text> <subclause id="H9310018157D04E98933BDD4079850203"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an active ingredient of a drug or biological product—</text> 
<item id="H5A6DC94A48AB4C34A33FD54B27F616A8"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>for which an approved application under section 505(j) under this Act or under section 351(k) of the Public Health Service Act is in effect; and</text></item> <item id="HABEBB3812D11465D9438541ABADD4176"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>that is determined by the Secretary to be the standard of care for treating a pediatric cancer; or</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H436A707242CB4244A474525116108A6F"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an active ingredient of a drug or biological product—</text> <item id="H387F3B25996741709378273E20472BBE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>for which an approved application under section 505(b) of this Act or section 351(a) of the Public Health Service Act to treat an adult cancer is in effect and is held by the same person submitting the application under paragraph (1)(B); and</text></item> 
<item id="H61331B9D1FE741FDBD97F1AA3889B812"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>that is directed at a molecular target that the Secretary determines to be substantially relevant to the growth or progression of a pediatric cancer. </text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB2B2EC7EFDC1401888DFD7D9BFE34B95"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header> <clause id="HD2E728D598D3460B97986B2A92D6414C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Design of investigation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A molecularly targeted pediatric cancer investigation referred to in subparagraph (A) shall be designed to yield clinically meaningful pediatric study data that is gathered using appropriate formulations for each age group for which the study is required, regarding dosing, safety, and preliminary efficacy to inform potential pediatric labeling.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA18C64C4BC4D4BDCB40784576B6986AD"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An investigation described in subparagraph (A)(ii) may be required only if the drug or biological product for which the application referred to in paragraph (1)(B) contains either—</text> <subclause id="H0A7666E7025543208B612BE28C36F383"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a single new active ingredient; or </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7421C92A70A04D83BB191550CB430F9E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>more than one active ingredient, if an application for the combination of active ingredients has not previously been approved but each active ingredient has been previously approved to treat an adult cancer. </text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H0F79757DE2C44D3CB51574487A4F3099"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Results of already-completed preclinical studies of application drug</header><text>The Secretary may require that reports on an investigation required pursuant to paragraph (1)(B) include the results of all preclinical studies on which the decision to conduct such investigation was based.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9CC964EB6494452B9215D9D9D40D2552"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Rule of construction regarding inactive ingredients</header><text>With respect to a combination of active ingredients referred to in subparagraph (A)(ii), such subparagraph shall not be construed as addressing the use of inactive ingredients with such combination.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE75A2A4910542FA93BB5E796E066D0F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination of applicable requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 505B(e)(1) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355c">21 U.S.C. 355c(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>The Secretary shall determine whether subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (a)(1) shall apply with respect to an application before the date on which the applicant is required to submit the initial pediatric study plan under paragraph (2)(A).</quote>. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2FF78A75630546E79BE9665A0C79659B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Clarifying applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><italic></italic>Section 505B(a)(1) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355c">21 U.S.C. 355c(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEF3806ECA5874BFCA11BF33198FCFF20" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H8254BFEF07DF412C911F983EF010EE64"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No application that is subject to the requirements of subparagraph (B) shall be subject to the requirements of subparagraph (A), and no application (or supplement to an application) that is subject to the requirements of subparagraph (A) shall be subject to the requirements of subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDC86C746FA1E4B7C9E2F39B5AC340B82"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Section 505B(a) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355c">21 U.S.C. 355c(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H6454CAE4D9324FECBBB767DA2F5E6EC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(C), as redesignated by paragraph (1)(A) of this subsection, by striking <quote>investigations described in this paragraph</quote> and inserting <quote>investigations referred to in subparagraph (A)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFD5C03D25DB640738DD19B488D233504"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(D), as redesignated by paragraph (1)(A) of this subsection, by striking <quote>the assessments under paragraph (2)(B)</quote> and inserting <quote>the assessments required under paragraph (1)(A)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC832A407C831480EBAAF9EA59201A942"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF590F990971E47D79370CBA823EA9F51"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this Act, issue draft guidance on the implementation of the requirements in subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H46E1217BB6D44E88A69F909FCA7E65AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than 12 months after closing the comment period on such draft guidance, finalize such guidance.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H26BB7E7F7CD34AFB95B96C89597BF0DB" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section apply with respect to any application under section 505(b) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(b)</external-xref>) and any application under section 351(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>), that is submitted on or after the date that is 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H955795F4B03A4EC59266621734C4455A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header> <paragraph id="HCB78DAA905E7484DA69CD9909E6319AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Secretary of Health and Human Services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate a report on the Secretary’s efforts, in coordination with industry, to ensure implementation of the amendments made by subsection (a).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4ABA6E02EC174521ACD2D0445A873484"><enum>(2)</enum><header>GAO study and report</header> 
<subparagraph id="HABA5608CB4A243A5B46AED08763EFAC3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Study</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study of the effectiveness of requiring assessments and investigations described in section 505B of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (21 U.S.C.355c), as amended by subsection (a), in the development of drugs and biological products for pediatric cancer indications.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H82485B1380CB4C8084307E4359277AC0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Not later than 7 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate a report containing the findings of the study conducted under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body></bill>

