<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB9DDAE0EFEAF42A1915F075619C14827" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5790 IH: To provide for the establishment of a task force to identify trade barriers to United States agricultural exports and carry out other related duties.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5790</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000491">Mr. Lucas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001189">Mr. Austin Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000388">Mr. Kelly of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000595">Ms. Letlow</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the establishment of a task force to identify trade barriers to United States agricultural exports and carry out other related duties.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD8330358E26F41619B54782416753892" style="OLC"><section id="H818F7ECDC9D34A5E8F08459BC9DB0461" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the “Prioritizing Offensive Agricultural Disputes and Enforcement Act”.</text></section><section id="HA349FED630244741B448D8E339939D01"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H4A7FE50B8FDE4B6395ADAF110D984809"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Agricultural competitiveness through access to international markets is a vital part of the United States economy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C3F0040388E4AD9B73350CD7B5D383C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A healthy, well-functioning rules-based trading system is the basis for the success of United States agricultural exports.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41EDE4A30F1F4B8BAF98E0ED360508C1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>When foreign governments erect trade barriers this makes it difficult for United States agricultural exporters to compete in the global marketplace while undermining the rules-based trading system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CABCBDD9E07426487D308787153A875"><enum>(4)</enum><text>These trade barriers can harm United States farmers, ranchers, workers, and businesses, and they can also lead to higher prices for consumers and a less resilient international trading system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC61C35FD44C44E6BA12E6335B2D6C721"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Dispute settlement is available through trade agreements with 163 other countries and there are protectionist trade barriers to United States agricultural exports in many of these countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDB1E421E3794362B7E0B171F0A05147"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Many of these barriers are systemically important. For example, India’s unrestrained use of price support programs violates its commitments under the World Trade Organization (WTO).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AE018C274E24373921BEBDFEC3B4B72"><enum>(7)</enum><text>India recognizes that its price support programs violate its WTO commitments, so instead of reforming its programs, it has repeatedly demanded a permanent exemption from disputes for these programs. Moreover, India has tried to prevent discussions at the WTO of any other significant agricultural trade issue unless it receives such a permanent exemption.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEDE0753E19B4F4698D386D004D9E267"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Government of India has repeatedly raised its minimum price supports, which has had negative effects on several commodity markets and most notably has led to its dominance of the global rice trade, with a 40-percent share of the global market since marketing year 2020 through 2021. India is also the world's largest producer of pulses and second largest producer of wheat, peanuts, and cotton.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD63F832E766E4309B33FF5B1192A27BE"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Trade Representative submitted a counter notification at the World Trade Organization in 2023 showing that price supports by the Government of India for rice increased from 78.6 percent of the value of production in marketing year 2014 through 2015 to 93.9 percent of the value of production in marketing year 2020 through 2021, compared to the limit at the World Trade Organization on increased price supports of 10 percent of the value of production. That counter notification also showed price supports by the Government of India for wheat increasing from 77.7 percent to 81.3 percent during the same period. Previous counter notifications have shown similar violations by the government of India for other commodities. For example, in the 2016/17 marketing year, the support level was 67.9 percent for cotton, 31.7 percent for chickpeas, 41 percent for lentils, and 47.4 percent for pulses overall. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB26F87D2AFBA44099C6D51E2C588C773"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Minor attempts to reform the Indian agriculture subsidy system in the marketing year 2020/2021 failed to produce results. The enacted reforms would not have changed the policies that violate WTO commitments but would have merely provided farmers with opportunities to sell their products outside of the government-run <quote>mandi</quote> system, but those were ultimately repealed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H126951CD4108426783F7C7CF979D8B35"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Dispute settlement is an effective way to provide a neutral assessment of compliance with trade agreement terms and empower internal reformers who recognize a problem but have not been able to overcome entrenched resistance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28BA766336DF49989C997F241B399B38"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Global agriculture is uniquely susceptible to trade barriers and requires special attention to resolve myriad systemic and economically significant trade violations that impede the development of a resilient, sustainable, and rules-based agricultural trading system.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H8976D29B8E4A49A9B743029644F2ADF4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H74CD82F1CD1C4ACFB7FFF99339C08A91"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the United States should accelerate efforts to address foreign trade barriers that harm United States agricultural exports;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6EE3A8727BB48C7BE9E750EA206DAB8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Office of the United States Trade Representative and the Department of Agriculture both have a critical role in developing agricultural trade disputes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79867B1D88CB4097A78A4888F3F72393"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Congress and the private sector have key roles to play in the development of disputes and agricultural trade enforcement strategy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E60CE6B990F45BC8CE849F367D91668"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in the case of India’s minimum price supports, the United States has exhausted other options available through the World Trade Organization short of requesting consultations under the Dispute Settlement Understanding (DSU);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD0BF886A5134F899AF8CF5DC6C4A547"><enum>(5)</enum><text>there should be a plan and definitive deadlines in place for a request for consultations and establishment of a panel under the DSU;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C0B6C0E4BA04D898039FE0F8EA97AFB"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Office of the United States Trade Representative and the Department of Agriculture should jointly develop a proactive enforcement strategy for addressing systemic and economically significant trade barriers in the agriculture sector, in consultation with Congress and the private sector; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB92066DFBEB849BBBFBC42BAB16B03BE"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Office of the United States Trade Representative is the lead agency for United States trade policy.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HBE7643A70BD24DE2B0D953D4E1E7079F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Agricultural Trade Enforcement Task Force</header><subsection id="HA64C11076FE84EB1994096960994EE92"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall establish a joint task force to be known as the <quote>Agricultural Trade Enforcement Task Force</quote> (referred to in this section as the “Task Force”). </text></subsection><subsection id="HB0EEFBE0B37344588C1ECA6F83C19FC4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><paragraph id="HD15A4C79370843A6AFEB340A95BF28E3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Task Force shall—</text><subparagraph id="H487F3AD75C2744B0859A82E4C71E8DB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify trade barriers to United States agricultural exports that are vulnerable to dispute settlement under the World Trade Organization (WTO) or other trade agreements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C5EA97CBE654682B706481B36A64AA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop and implement a strategy for enforcing violations of trade agreements related to these trade barriers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3EB17A35B66A4F63BC277C6686511962"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identify like-minded trading partners for specific trade barriers that could act as co-complainants or primary complainants on disputes that are systemically or economically important to the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF17EBFE6C8EB41F5BC5FE2452EC65482"><enum>(D)</enum><text>report quarterly to Congress on progress towards resolving cases or filing disputes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H840D83B5DB454F3B8EECC2834786E877"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out its duties under this subsection, the Task Force shall regularly consult, to the extent necessary and appropriate, with the following:</text><subparagraph id="H9D405D86B51243E6AEB02ACBC8165F43"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Relevant stakeholders in the private sector, including the agricultural trade advisory committees.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C40856085A34C54BD26DF45381F579D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Federal departments and agencies that are not represented on the Task Force.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EADFE0387D64441902B3E2640E5DE12"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Like-minded trading partners that are similarly concerned with trade barriers and are potential participants in the dispute settlement process.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H976CF39F949F4F37A9F881E5CAF5B4B2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph id="H3BF441A096B642C4BA0007CC2E5C1A07"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Task Force shall be comprised of the following members:</text><subparagraph id="HB49678C6B43D4349937568F6C8DB86FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>One or more employees of the Foreign Agricultural Service, who shall be appointed by the Under Secretary for Trade and Foreign Agricultural Affairs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42E3FB282F8D4141A3B418B7B9AE6927"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One of more employees of the Office of the United States Trade Representative, who shall be appointed jointly by the General Counsel for the Office of the United States Trade Representative and the Chief Agricultural Negotiator.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2D61941AED64BF5828C27BA99AD626B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>One or more employees of other Federal agencies as needed, who shall be appointed jointly by the officials specified in subparagraphs (A) and (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B77201E8CD34A6C961EE73592D5E107"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualification</header><text>Employees of the Federal agencies specified in subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C) of paragraph (1) may be appointed as members of the Task Force only if such employees have appropriate expertise in agricultural trade policy and trade enforcement. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H75A26CE053E54993980BEF37969E4E2F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H643C98AB59484C288457377F9B929114"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and on a quarterly basis thereafter, the Task Force shall submit to Congress a report on its progress in identifying and addressing trade barriers to United States agricultural exports. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0354B8486C846D0BAFEF9232FB9867E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matters to be included</header><text>The report required by this subsection shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="HBE85FA05462940E58002FF0AFE6A481D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A description of the systemic and economically significant trade barriers that have been identified.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4488AF7924CD499FB71BD22B26330198"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A justification for including the identified trade barriers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F8A96D46F324D01B38699193962D5F1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of the progress that has been made in developing dispute settlement cases and further information that is required.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11C05492752247EDAB5D4B8865E01991"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The current status of ongoing disputes at the WTO and implementation of panel, arbitration, or Appellate Body decisions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB26589A47CC4885B22D8E163A75B852"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional matters to be included in initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The initial report required by this subsection shall, in addition to the matters described in subparagraphs (A), (B), (C), and (D) of paragraph (2), include a plan to file a request under the WTO dispute settlement process for consultations to address India’s minimum price supports. The plan shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HEDF975BFFC364C6C8C2C1CAC9F617C24"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an identification of like-minded trading partners that could act as co-complainants or primary complainants with respect to the request;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D73DF631FF441089719CA4FFE580165"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of specific claims the United States intends to make with respect to the request; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52F7211014394E0D86D0F949F32E6D9B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a timeline to—</text><clause id="HDBD0F8527EB645C28503C3FB5FF181A6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>request consultations; and</text></clause><clause id="H1EB4C6FD576148D4B308559455968C27"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">request the establishment of a panel not later than 60 days after the date of the request for consultations if India does not provide assurances that it will address its minimum price supports.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5164B03C21FD45CFAE25D4DC77E17DAF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Congressional briefings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Trade Representative and the Secretary of Agriculture shall provide briefings on the Task Force to appropriate Members of Congress and congressional staff.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

