<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HECC49F2CD5754B5AB4DDCE1065BD8699" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6589 IH: Prevent the Financing of Terrorism Through the Drug Trade Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6589</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231205">December 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a report on terrorist financing in the Americas, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H23A71CD7BE10409E89BAD40CF40DD3FD" style="OLC"><section id="H2F7F7806A85145589EF6E0E4E6B16681" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the “<short-title>Prevent the Financing of Terrorism Through the Drug Trade Act</short-title>”. </text></section><section id="HCBDE3A115DB9451CBF4C87CFB5A64607"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on terrorist financing in the Americas</header><subsection id="H868685D10D464B47BDD85C64C3458308"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury shall submit to Congress a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="H9EF2BA7360444E74912500D3CCD8CF20"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of the major money making sources for terrorist financing by Hamas and Hezbollah in Mexico, Central America, South America, and the Caribbean.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H292CDE5F92734F02BF09CF753E87689A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of the amount of money held by Hamas and Hezbollah in Mexico, Central America, South America, and the Caribbean, including an identification of the countries in which it is being held.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H341BF8BB895B4190954AE8FFBE4237C9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An analysis of the extent to which Hamas and Hezbollah are linked to drug trafficking organizations in Mexico, Central America, South America, and the Caribbean and an analysis of the amount of their funds raised through the narcotics trade.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2D9F60C6FEC45699E45774347F3B117"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of United States and multilateral efforts to disrupt financing by Hamas and Hezbollah in Mexico, Central America, South America, and the Caribbean.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD31F8B624307475B97848A76720C062F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An evaluation of the United States efforts to disrupt financial flows from Mexico, Central America, South America, and the Caribbean to Hamas and Hezbollah.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC4F882EC956E47E4B63BA573D6A5C020"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National Terrorist Financing Risk Assessment report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall, in the next National Terrorist Financing Risk Assessment report issued by the Department of the Treasury on or after the date of the enactment of this Act—</text><paragraph id="HFAB91C20C687438BABF2D91B444B2DA9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify Hamas as a <quote>Primary Threat</quote> under the report’s section relating to <quote>Threats</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B45F5D26BAC4E33B11A7C73B01284CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include a full description of Hamas’s activities relating to terrorist financing under such section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

