<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA8AFB2075CAB4DBBB77B34D2663FE10F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5990 IH: Border Enforcement, Security, and Trade (BEST) Facilitation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5990</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231019">October 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to authorize Office of Field Operations positions, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H90BE567CA0B8471B992D458638A44EA6" style="OLC"><section id="HEF65F46861614F5FB03C417D16158A25" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Border Enforcement, Security, and Trade (BEST) Facilitation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC322411DEB694DD686BEFA9AC0736A30"><enum>2.</enum><header>New office of field operations positions authorized</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 411(g) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/211">6 U.S.C. 211(g)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H62509E3D12B2441394E6213782198C86" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H6D62942B1051425CBCB15BF62775A98A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Image technician positions</header><subparagraph id="HC0B98E72B0D748459B11C63D3C6D05BF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Image technician</header><clause id="H87DCCCC696414C01B11B451622FFD5F2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be in the Office of Field Operations, the position of Image Technician, who shall be appointed in accordance with the provisions under chapter 33 (relating to appointments in the competitive service) and chapters 51 and 53 (relating to classification and rates of pay) of title 5, United States Code.</text></clause><clause id="H643252D0E98148E2B62BB747555A6E9A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Duties</header><subclause id="H814E64A5FB8549D281D987E14FC76E6E"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Duties of an Image Technician shall include—</text><item id="H20D4A578C7D34BDEB30CF97AE7051571"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>reviewing non-intrusive inspection images of conveyances and containers entering or exiting the United States through a land, sea, or air port of entry or international rail crossing;</text></item><item id="H0EC124980C314E6F820FF0AA2E81C2E7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>assessing whether images of conveyances and containers appear to contain anomalies indicating the potential presence of contraband, persons unlawfully seeking to enter or exit the United States, or illicitly concealed merchandise, including illicit drugs and terrorist weapons;</text></item><item id="H092D9C82997E45DD8ADE9AFFB9331E10"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>recommend entry release or exit release for any conveyances and containers where the images do not include noticeable anomalies indicating the potential presence of contraband, persons seeking to unlawfully enter or exit the United States, or illicitly concealed merchandise, including illicit drugs or terrorist weapons, to the U.S. Customs and Border Protection Officer responsible for inspecting such conveyance or container.</text></item><item id="H56B0CFF4B69C4A0DAD9B317499F13220"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>recommend for further inspection any conveyances and containers where any image the Image Technician reasonably believes contains anomalies indicating the potential presence of contraband, persons seeking to unlawfully enter or exit the United States, or illicitly concealed merchandise, such as illicit drugs or terrorist weapons, to the U.S. Customs and Border Protection Officer who is responsible for inspecting such conveyance or container; and</text></item><item id="H2BDA4EB5889A4416B07E0EF902B077A7"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>referring to a Supervisory Image Technician any image of conveyances or containers that is difficult to review or assess due to poor image quality or other factors.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H829065AAD9AA45F89480F5B9F6AF4413" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>A U.S. Customs and Border Protection Officer shall retain the discretion and final decision-making authority to release conveyances or cargo for entry or exit or to refer such conveyance or cargo for further inspection. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H155C1ED433904420ADE3F91C2E463A1E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Supervisory image technician</header><clause id="HB0CBC2D0DF9E4AB786521362FD443574"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be in the Office of Field Operations, the position of Supervisory Image Technician, who shall be appointed in accordance with the provisions under chapter 33 (relating to appointments in the competitive service) and chapters 51 and 53 (relating to classification and rates of pay) of title 5, United States Code.</text></clause><clause id="H37C1C1A7E16F4BD1B501A5D0C2905BCC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Duties</header><subclause id="HCA5246C5728F4040B39827DF00050D36"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Duties of a Supervisory Image Technician shall include—</text><item id="H5EB32A11F8D04FCE8AC8C5AB19A0E810"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>carrying out all of the duties described in clauses (i) through (iv) of subparagraph (A);</text></item><item id="HE2EE28F537094531A1090D3D8DBEE2BD"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>reviewing and making a recommendation regarding images referred by an Image Technician pursuant to subparagraph (A)(v) to the U.S. Customs and Border Protection Officer who is responsible for inspecting such conveyance or container;</text></item><item id="HF47339E30E7C42C6B17E5BE4914279DA"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>receiving intelligence from the National Targeting Center regarding tactics, techniques, and procedures being used at ports of entry and in the border environment by malign actors to facilitate the unlawful entry or exit of contraband, persons, or illicitly concealed merchandise such as illicit drugs or terrorist weapons; and</text></item><item id="HFF5E525A85D84F27864E152466276291"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>reporting new information to the National Targeting Center regarding tactics, techniques, and procedures being used at ports of entry and in the border environment by malign actors to facilitate the unlawful entry or exit of contraband, persons, or concealed merchandise such as illicit drugs or terrorist weapons.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H85226307DDA744B18DFE33799E6D8A31" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A U.S. Customs and Border Protection Officer shall retain the discretion and final decision-making authority to release conveyances or cargo for entry or exit or to refer such conveyance or cargo for further inspection.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFAB633FCA17B4E63BBE528836A2A744F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Training requirements</header><text>All Image Technicians and Supervisory Image Technicians shall receive annual training and additional ad hoc training, to the extent necessary based on current trends, regarding—</text><clause id="HC9CF9485D7A348059817D4CD5EE3F6A8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>privacy, and civil rights and civil liberties, including the protections against unreasonable searches and seizures afforded by the Fourth Amendment to the United States Constitution;</text></clause><clause id="H080AFEFAE0F946A3997CB08117380D3D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>analyzing images generated by non-intrusive inspection technologies or any successor technologies deployed by U.S. Customs and Border Protection;</text></clause><clause id="H10EC0030ED284482BF22FDD54A2D0299"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identifying commodities and merchandise in images generated by non-intrusive inspection technologies or any successor technologies deployed by U.S. Customs and Border Protection;</text></clause><clause id="H18B4907942A949849BBAB0D6DB401406"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>identifying contraband, persons who are seeking to unlawfully enter or exit United States, or illicitly concealed merchandise such as illicit drugs or terrorist weapons in images generated by non-intrusive technologies or any successor technologies deployed by U.S. Customs and Border Protection;</text></clause><clause id="H16080F43CAB543D08D2AD3426A6D9C04"><enum>(v)</enum><text>tactics, techniques, and procedures being used at ports of entry and in the border environment by malign actors to facilitate the unlawful entry or exit of contraband, persons, or concealed merchandise such as illicit drugs or terrorist weapons; and</text></clause><clause id="H168771D8EBFD4859A07F3C0D640B9950"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>any other training that the Commissioner of the U.S. Customs and Border Protection determines to be relevant to the duties described in subparagraphs (B) or (D) of this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7970090B745644B9891DF653A0BB9E08"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Annual assessment</header><text>All Image Technicians and Supervisory Image Technicians shall receive annual testing with respect to their—</text><clause id="H2DE260FB299D4E65AEC0E7286898B876"><enum>(i)</enum><text>accuracy in image analysis;</text></clause><clause id="HF05C2D25DAAB42889EBA0A9DED501D65"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>timeliness in image analysis; and</text></clause><clause id="HA1B943CD36E1482786DC65E3F5D52230"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ability to ascertain tactics, techniques, and procedures being used at ports of entry and in the border environment by malign actors to facilitate the unlawful entry or exit of contraband, persons, or illicitly concealed merchandise such as illicit drugs or terrorist weapons.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H485166C404B14A279809A9960679CCF2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Workforce staffing model</header><subsection id="H01194425CFE84C6DA93EBA80281EE7D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Development</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection shall develop a workforce staffing model for Image Technicians and Supervisory Image Technicians described in section 211(g)(6) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002, as amended by section 2, based upon—</text><paragraph id="HEF9A90FD89C24FDA9CD58923773DAF14"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the deployment of non-intrusive inspection technologies at ports of entry and international rail crossings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5CA0A2A65004299A485FD9065018E9E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>border traffic patterns; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4EBB51D6E4EE4BDEA56DB6D23A4AD543"><enum>(3)</enum><text>scanning goals at each port of entry and international rail crossing.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF66245A8DFE542338D49C8B93CCBC2CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Validation</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the completion of the workforce staffing model described in subsection (a), the Comptroller General of the United States shall validate such workforce staffing model and transmit notification of such validation to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB994F2F844264461AA6BE1049CF16234"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Upon completion of the validation of the workforce staffing model pursuant to section 3(b), and quarterly thereafter, the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, in consultation with the Executive Assistant Commissioner, shall submit a report to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives that identifies—</text><paragraph id="HE7CA4C70CA01499CA1F5CC470B83A0C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of Image Technicians and Supervisory Image Technicians hired during the reporting period;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C950DEA33EA4CDAAEC91FDF637ED4B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of Image Technicians and Supervisory Image Technicians currently employed by the Office of Field Operations, disaggregated by port of entry or sector;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD46E474881EB426DB811C2811DA0E96A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the daily average number of images scanned by each Image Technician;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF538718698D34010867AD45A2A8E506B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>training methodologies utilized to train Image Technicians and Supervisory Image Technicians;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF02199E8BE7240008A0D3B8FB20F9032"><enum>(5)</enum><text>assessment passage rates of Image Technicians and Supervisory Image Technicians; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06ED46AB7197459FA3AE1300A15C43B5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the apparent impact of Image Technicians and Supervisory Image Technicians on interdiction rates at ports of entry and international rail crossings at which Image Technicians or Supervisory Image Technicians are stationed or from which Image Technicians or Supervisory Image Technicians review images, including—</text><subparagraph id="H743A965F921D49F5B80752B3DC708D18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>throughput increases or decreases at such ports of entry and international rail crossings;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5253CE1EE50644F7BD76404F68BB3DDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>increases or decreases in waiting times at such ports of entry and international rail crossings;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20E72959ED334B39A228A55B95FFE4CA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>average wait times at such ports of entry and international rail crossings; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA31B5141757C4569ADAFAEB265FC49E1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>increases or decreases of seizures of contraband, persons seeking to unlawfully enter or exit the United States, or illicitly concealed merchandise such as illicit drugs or terrorist weapons, broken down by type of seizure and port of entry or international rail crossing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

