<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7E7688F17689454EAA3868B4067C21D9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 831 IH: Medicare Medically Necessary Dental Care Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 831</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230206">February 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide for coverage under part B of the Medicare program for medically necessary dental procedures.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0EBF1C5ABD8C498EB62BBA6A6C758B0E" style="OLC"><section id="HF6120F65ED5943A2A8A0F20291C78378" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; findings</header><subsection id="H14BD2F75BD55450F9AFEF604BC28F365"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short Title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medicare Medically Necessary Dental Care Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5CAF29ADC23E47D5AA81763BCF80B16C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HE4DF3D16C417455B9E9EFF19F1DE1266"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Oral and general healths are inseparable, and good dental care is critical to our overall physical health and well-being.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01A629324DEA42F4A350C892756BE76D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A 1999 Institute of Medicine study found that the prevention and management of oral infection have significant health implications when such infection has the potential to increase morbidity in Medicare patients who are at risk of adverse outcomes from underlying health problems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4F58424166D48E684AAFE060A9F6D29"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Improved oral health care may reduce mortality and morbidity rates of Medicare patients suffering from head and neck cancer, leukemia, lymphoma, organ transplantation, and heart valve disease.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42318DCFD0DC4213A6BF75FD88EEB618"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Medicare program, from its inception, has excluded coverage for services in connection with the care, treatment, filling, removal, or replacement of teeth or structures directly supporting the teeth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BF74E64057B4AA9958626FEBB140A4F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services has approved coverage exceptions for limited dental services and proposed additional exceptions based on the argument that oral health services would reduce the risk of infection and other complications of medical care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H252086559D854320A7AF3526BF6E1EDE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Institute of Medicine study concluded that it is reasonable for Congress to update the statutory language relating to coverage of dental services for Medicare beneficiaries so that it clearly covers dental care that is effective in preventing or reducing oral and systemic complications associated with serious medical conditions and treatments.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4FD737565C1B47DF841276A72CA78F25"><enum>2.</enum><header>Medicare coverage of medically necessary dental procedures</header><subsection id="H6BD1AAA062204DB2A07A0E58D29B28D8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1862 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395y">42 U.S.C. 1395y</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8F377BB526F64CFE9D25D2C7E7D43888"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(12)—</text><subparagraph id="H4D007E9DF8DE47B98D200BA496765D13"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(A)</quote> after <quote>except that</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3EE4D97FCC04EA0A0995F58FE90C7DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>, and (B) payment may be made under part B for the provision of such dental services that are medically necessary as a direct result of, or will have a direct impact on, an underlying medical condition if the coverage of such services is medically necessary, as determined under subsection (p)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3F4252F9B4F45D8A51AE0D9862AE90E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="HB1173A409B724CCAB3C81B58072873F5" style="OLC"><subsection id="HB7D80CE444CD40439E393170CBE1BF64"><enum>(p)</enum><text>For purposes of subsection (a)(12)(B), dental services shall be considered to be medically necessary if furnished—</text><paragraph id="H7A7AB5C8CCA54B2599081965CD3717FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in conjunction with treatment of an individual with a prosthetic heart valve replacement or a diagnosis of cancer of the head or neck, lymphoma, leukemia, and organ transplantation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FC1E679E5DE4DB8866920F219350F32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not later than one year after the later of—</text><subparagraph id="H56CF1A9E5A514CEDAF6264EB6D6E5A9D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date of such diagnosis; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7318D6B3DAE47D7ADE6A7363C0BBE51"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date of the related surgical or medical treatment for that diagnosis.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7AFE2548838E4FAB96266C7065720929"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall apply to procedures performed on or after January 1, 2024.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

