<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H50F603B4EE5D413CBFD9664B0AECC043" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5389 IH: National Coverage Determination Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5389</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230912">September 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to ensure transparency in the national coverage determination process under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H341DEE5B8A444D1A9D57822DD2D56335" style="OLC"><section id="H978DFE794BDC472B9D90469B3173BA35" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Coverage Determination Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7EEAF0594D8949749C419129256F6535" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring transparency in the national coverage determination process under the Medicare program</header><subsection id="H3D1BEEFA9A97426CAC954C24D8826B2B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1862(l) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395y">42 U.S.C. 1395y(l)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H88CD07EBF472443AA19766269413A2EA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HC1C084F14399457BBDF8F511F6EE71AD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Transparency in national coverage determinations</header><subparagraph id="H526786117FDB4776AF7E1BD4B4432A52"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each document (whether physical or electronic) received by the Secretary on or after the date that is 30 days after the date of the enactment of this paragraph that identifies itself as a request for a national coverage determination, the Secretary shall, not later than 30 calendar days after receipt of such document—</text><clause id="H01144960E8834EFA94F13AE5832559BD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>determine whether such document is a complete, formal request for a national coverage determination (as described in the rule entitled <quote>Medicare Program; Revised Process for Making National Coverage Determinations</quote> (78 Fed. Reg. 48164) or a successor regulation); and</text></clause><clause id="H7602C00666F243DFB4A75066D09FCF56"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case that the Secretary finds that such document is not a complete, formal request for a national coverage determination, directly transmit to the entity submitting such document an explanation of such finding that includes a specification of each item of additional information needed to make such document a complete, formal request for a national coverage determination.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9092B653542547BA9E251EE38AAA599B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Resubmission of document</header><clause id="H3121D2A34B234F6DB11690A4CF790CD3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a document described in subparagraph (A) with respect to which the Secretary has made a finding described in clause (ii) of such subparagraph, the entity submitting such document may submit to the Secretary a revised document that includes the additional information specified in such clause with respect to such document. Such revised document shall be treated as a newly-received document for purposes of subparagraph (A).</text></clause><clause id="H1872161ED11F48FA89952EE94A1C4FCA"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall provide such technical assistance as is practicable in order to assist entities in submitting revised documents under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA319A07E5B994A23A7E1C1B5264350CF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make available on a publicly accessible website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services or other appropriate means each document that the Secretary has determined is a complete, formal request for a national coverage determination (as described in subparagraph (A)(i)) not later than 2 business days after the date of such determination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3545B4257C24479C96CF256EA36D754C"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Clarification on timing requirements for national coverage determinations</header><text>For purposes of paragraphs (2) and (3) and with respect to a request for a national coverage determination received on or after the date that is 30 days after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, the references to <quote>the date of the request</quote> and <quote>the date the request is made</quote> shall be treated as references to the date the request was received by the Secretary, regardless of whether the Secretary had determined that such request was a complete, formal request (as described in paragraph (7)(B)(i)) as of such date. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCE55A29046EF4285B659B9C5421271FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusion of certain time periods in annual reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1869(f)(7)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ff">42 U.S.C. 1395ff(f)(7)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>Each such report submitted on or after the date that is 30 days after the date of the enactment of this sentence shall include in such actual time periods with respect to such a request any intervening time between the receipt of such request by the Secretary and the Secretary’s determination that such request was a complete, formal request (as described in section 1861(l)(7)(B)(i)).</quote>. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

