<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H22E5B8D465BC442F84C7C810EAB3C78C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3948 IH: Care for COFA Veterans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3948</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000809">Mr. Womack</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To expand access to health care for veterans in the Freely Associated States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H09DE920D9D9249519A399B3F808C3545" style="OLC"><section id="HB6F5559283164633BDA8FA0CAA71BF68" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Care for COFA Veterans Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H62815513D9B640FA9A699DFC07FDB5E7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Expansion of existing authorities to provide health care to veterans in the Freely Associated States</header><subsection id="H3350CAC1F94D49298AE4B6AB21B58B7E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Health care abroad</header><text>Section 1724 of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7F953229F8944E0D829E8EF989376546"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>subsections (b) and (c)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsections (b), (c), and (f)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H683FFE257EC24D3D98C42105FE8EDB48"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA9840073E0DA4E3FAC661BEECCC2DEDA"><subsection id="HCFCA3E1DCD0F404FAF638A96B8B409D5"><enum>(f)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HEE00A490137F49E1829FF14BA1B95F6A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary may furnish hospital care and medical services in the Freely Associated States for any service-connected disability or non-service-connected disability.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51334BAB385645C28910CAED3CBD569A" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In furnishing care and services under paragraph (1), the Secretary may furnish such care and services through contracts or other agreements, through reimbursement, or through the direct provision of care by health care personnel of the Department.</text></paragraph><paragraph indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D06BE1B9F814FA5901EF3B59066D373"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>Freely Associated States</term> means the Republic of Palau, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, and the Federated States of Micronesia, which have each entered into a Compact of Free Association with the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H91720090DDA84AC6A67A8663B5CD19CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Beneficiary travel for treatment of service-Connected disabilities</header><text>Section 111 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCBE8AB3E5EF44566965ECF14377C57C8"><subsection id="HD7969DA35A064AE4AE2FB7AC5280DA1E"><enum>(h)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H661A0E72752B4DC38C36B0B36B3B10CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary may make payments provided for in this section to or for any person specified in subsection (b)(1)(A) for travel specified in that subsection to, from, or within the Freely Associated States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BAEA0F93CE94C4FBF8104631AD88CB1" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In this subsection, the term <term>Freely Associated States</term> means the Republic of Palau, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, and the Federated States of Micronesia, which have each entered into a Compact of Free Association with the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H9C3692F3B43448AB9E3B99FE58FB6E86"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Legal issues</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in consultation with the Secretary of State, shall work with the governments of the Freely Associated States to facilitate the furnishing of health services, including telehealth, under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to veterans in the Freely Associated States, such as by addressing—</text><paragraph id="HC96808B80943489AA410545035FE7DB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>licensure, certification, registration, and tort issues relating to health care personnel; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BF2E11E1D6E463A860E95C464B7E98B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>matters relating to deliveries of pharmaceutical products and medical surgical products, including deliveries of such products through the pharmacy of the Department of Veterans Affairs, to the Freely Associated States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4DA316DB72394B52BCEEC133E871C6CB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Outreach and assessment of options</header><text>During the one-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall—</text><paragraph id="HC5E576B139D04F649BE707C07AA2E16A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct robust outreach to and engage with each government of the Freely Associated States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H824A37A190D74FDFB6981ED13FE77A52"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assess options about the best way to furnish care under section 1724(f) of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEB162DD009974F84BDF1F566F14D138F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report on provision of health care to veterans in the Freely Associated States</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to Congress a report on the implementation of the authorities provided pursuant to the amendments made by this section and any additional authorities and resources needed by the Secretary to carry out those authorities, including to carry out the following:</text><paragraph id="H7816EB784BF54BBB91885AC387C70A24"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Reimbursement of care for non-service-connected disabilities in the Freely Associated States under section 1724(f) of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7259C68F04EB484EAAA22F717F918A96"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Contracts with local clinics and federally qualified health centers (as defined in section 1905(l)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(l)(2)(B)</external-xref>)) in the Freely Associated States to provide care and services such section 1724(f), as so added.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H666E8817BBCE40418F96810870E66AED"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Furnishing of telehealth services and technologies to veterans in the Freely Associated States by providers of the Department under such section 1724(f), as so added.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7065C505125C411DAD0D4CC9C76415C4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Payment under section 111(h) of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (b), for travel to, from, or within the Freely Associated States for veterans seeking health care for service-connected disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC47A3BB71EFC4020A057071B9AD49D7B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Construction of clinics in the Freely Associated States or leasing of space at military installations, embassy compounds, or consulate facilities to provide care under section 1724(f) of title 38, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4A0F2FB01494C359AF4EE31D9CF5C9C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Such other matters as the Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5AABC21E5ECB40C48A968C7E9B94417E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Freely Associated States defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Freely Associated States</term> means the Republic of Palau, the Republic of the Marshall Islands, and the Federated States of Micronesia, which have each entered into a Compact of Free Association with the United States.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

