<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE18B1204D6ED4939BC182B9868C78248" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1712 IH: Rural Health Innovation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1712</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230322">March 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to establish a rural health center innovation awards program and a rural health department enhancement program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB735C7576F7C4D31B64EB907C75E25AF" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H4D6AAA979289449DBE0A9658618D7366"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Health Innovation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD615809B4CD549CAAB1E23DE3808240B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Rural health center innovation awards program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart I of part D of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H374616CEDA3A4D6CB49E940C79595F4D">
<section id="HF1BDF8F3A56844D2B4F03DFC1ABD3527"><enum>330Q.</enum><header>Rural health center innovation awards program</header>
<subsection id="HC204F17A20BF4A2EA289BFCE54F5D919"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H38BB3CB7981D44A9A305EA113AEC4CF0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H8A02672B3FF146DE8952FFE119258449"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a Federally qualified health center;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H40B277A1C6EB4966A7F5ECAABDF1EA18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is a rural health clinic; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB7ADD7EB6686434FBD1DD2284B9D9A6E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>agrees (as a condition of receiving a grant under this section) to establish such a center or clinic, including a hospital that agrees (as such a condition) to convert to a Federally qualified health center or rural health clinic.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H68DBC75DCFE34B668ED87466BF3C7BF9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federally qualified health center</header><text>The term <term>Federally qualified health center</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1861(aa) of the Social Security Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD2FAB73A3C6A43ED9862AEF34A593395"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rural area</header><text>The term <term>rural area</term> means any area that is rural, within the meaning of such term as used by the Office of Rural Health Policy of the Health Resources and Services Administration for purposes of determining eligibility for grants or services, including any area that is rural within such meaning as used by such Office for fiscal year 2023 or any area that is rural within such meaning as amended for a subsequent fiscal year. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97C1BF6E29FE40C0B7F08EB6FCA6C46C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rural health clinic</header><text>The term <term>rural health clinic</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1861(aa) of the Social Security Act.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6966DFA6BE8E445BB61BC9D9740DDC3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header>
<paragraph id="HC55073B0945444CC944F340DCC6C466B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Office of Rural Health Policy of the Health Resources and Services Administration, shall establish a grant program to be known as the <quote>Rural Health Center Innovation Awards program</quote> to award grants to eligible entities that submit an application in accordance with subsection (c) to enable such entities to establish or maintain a Federally qualified health center or rural health clinic that—</text> <subparagraph id="HBFCEF56733BE4877BBA79B1ACD246359"><enum>(A)</enum><text>serves individuals in a rural area as a walk-in urgent care center and as a triage center or staging facility for necessary air or ambulance transport to an emergency department; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H02722ED67E7644D4A515CB314531C750"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text> <clause id="HA631250F55D449A29397DBE1A71AAE4F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>professional clinical staff, including physicians, physician interns, residents, nurse practitioners, physician assistants, nurse midwives, or other health care providers providing walk-in urgent care and emergency triage; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H26702BD726534818947F0D741954D9FB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>resources, including laboratories, x-ray machines, and cardiac monitors.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H27544AD62FDF4324B26B5787E47B6CD8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Permissible uses of funds</header><text>The funds of a grant awarded under this section may be used to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H8DD47C36463C454F85D32A85BD3075CB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>expand the hours of operation of a Federally qualified health center or rural health clinic;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC18BEA91D74F4A72AB704356FC82E52F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>pay for the costs of construction and renovation of a Federally qualified health center or rural health clinic; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H279040E2CE0C4E42A78F3A146429B96E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>carry out any other activity for the purposes described in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H588829DF45584C91BDC55E5D2D317F1D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications and selection</header> <paragraph id="H013012F5DF84423F89ADFB70152C5F4E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity seeking a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6BE8FEDD22014B7E9D9C539264B0AA17"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Start up centers and clinics</header><text>An application submitted under paragraph (1) by an eligible entity that is not a Federally qualified health center, or a rural health clinic, on the date on which the entity submits the application under paragraph (1) shall include in such application a demonstration of the costs of the equipment and staffing needed to establish the center or clinic.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE83440C2340F47AD8454A6D5661D2DFE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consideration of overlap</header><text>In the case an eligible entity submits an application under paragraph (1) that proposes to serve an area that is served by another eligible entity through a grant under this section, the Secretary may consider whether an award to the eligible entity serving such same area can be justified based on the unmet need for additional services in such area.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4072A460A8A342CDB3A414F23DA6D732"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting recipients of grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to an eligible entity that is operating as a Federally qualified health center, or a rural health clinic, on the date on which the entity submits the application under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H404C766F830C4A4385244D2122E65904"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant period and amounts</header> <paragraph id="H61B514F68E504788AE964A5C01609A13"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Period</header><text>Each grant awarded under this section shall be for a period of 5 years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H07B34B3B415B43C5B7D97955001D88C3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount</header>
<subparagraph id="H5732FE275B804CE2941FE41F2184FDE1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A grant awarded under this section to an eligible entity shall not exceed—</text> <clause id="HEA4204715E6F4AD3A3E9C1EEF22F1DC9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the first year of the grant—</text>
<subclause id="H6EE0F24D739B471980161F659E4B2837"><enum>(I)</enum><text>$500,000 if the entity is a Federally qualified health center, or a rural health clinic, on the date on which the award is made; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H5791959523EA47D0AD44E3B9CC349786"><enum>(II)</enum><text>$750,000 if the entity is using the grant to establish a Federally qualified health center or a rural health clinic; and</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HA9C9ACA56E8A411EBDB0D8A211A0D3DA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for each of the second through fifth years of the grant, $500,000.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7E2661B215A6420B86538FE62EACDD6C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In determining the amount of a grant under this section for an eligible entity for each year after the first year in which the grant is awarded, the Secretary shall, subject to subparagraph (A)(ii), consider the number of patients treated, and the type of treatment provided, by the entity in the prior year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2929A25E55A34829BBE86A239A17912C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting</header>
<paragraph id="H9B89FB3C41F3453EA669ECBA3FD5C8A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall report to the committees described in paragraph (2) on the grant program under this section, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HC8B3A163A50A4F838BC0C2344A12B06C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the success of the program, challenges with respect to the program, and any action for regulatory flexibility or legislative authority needed to improve the program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H59F33581EF144B2BB5C97DB7F0D716B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any savings to Federal health care programs;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H695A2AAE98F4478F9729BEF09C6B8C35"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any increase in access to care; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFD4EF74A17024741A2999AA4CACC1B5C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any increase in utilization of health services in rural areas.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF3E477DE353547D180CF503A1DFF84EE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Committees</header><text>The committees described in this paragraph are—</text>
<subparagraph id="H01DEBEBF2F6D441C8FF12B2665537BF1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions, and the Committee on Finance, of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBD46604B6646459E87B25F8A72C615FB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Commerce, and the Committee on Ways and Means, of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5C94A73CEAD940F38DE5716E6DD5A154"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>No entity receiving a grant under this section shall lose status as a Federally qualified health center, or a rural health clinic, on account of carrying out any activities under this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HEE565B3241EE4178A26A48460499D17A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="HD39BB0753D134B4FA8300DDF3267471A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rural health department enhancement program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart I of part D of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8DF396CE2B2F4F1EBE5CBDF4E3FDAD1E"> <section id="HB61A6F45C7F64357BADCC7B402FD6474"><enum>330R.</enum><header>Rural health department enhancement program</header> <subsection id="H02FC407304F9478B918C43A6523ED138"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H3D12A8F9E6574C6388DA76B3B030DD8B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Rural area</header><text>The term <term>rural area</term> has the meaning given the term in section 330Q(a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H033348BC8E8043D39E1A2AED61254D4C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rural health department</header><text>The term <term>rural health department</term> means a local public health department that is located in a rural area.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF56709EBB21F4570AA0E74111E1D2229"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Office of Rural Health Policy of the Health Resources and Services Administration, shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to rural health departments that submit an application in accordance with subsection (c) to enhance such departments and enable them to provide individuals in rural areas with emergency services, triage and transport to emergency departments, primary care services, and other services similar to services provided by emergency departments.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H95089F21F96C4BF09C5017BEE84DB803"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>A rural health department seeking a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require, including—</text>
<paragraph id="H8A52278A85754C09B22AB073DF1C14E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an indication of the estimated cost of the equipment and staffing needed by the department for the first year of the award to set up the activities and services under this section;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2D0064FFDE9D4340A3F0921C4F63F338"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a demonstration that the department has, on the date on which the application is submitted, a facility operating that is located in a rural area; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAE333BFD77F14C4886C27C369BFF511A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a demonstration that, on the date on which the application is submitted, the department—</text> <subparagraph id="H9CB61AD2451B4CFBA0A390B42788E554"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has a nursing staff and medical equipment; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H476308405AF44ADB9DA3E267CE9A1371"><enum>(B)</enum><text>agrees to use such staff and equipment towards providing the services and carrying out the activities under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1C30957F082B4CBDBE0C6E86B92F5FF8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grants</header> <paragraph id="H2E6567153D434B8DB3F5B78DC505CEEB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual awards</header><text>The funds awarded through a grant under this section to a rural health department shall be awarded on an annual basis for each of 5 years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HED955C86C0A441759A684251CD6F00DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maximum amounts</header><text>The funds awarded through a grant under this section to a rural health department shall be in an amount that for a year does not exceed $500,000.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB5F13E5FC8474364B70D120CCB8D7EB7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>The Secretary shall determine the amount awarded to a rural health department through a grant under this section for a year in accordance with the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="HE1542854BA9E42B4A6DEF19D0BBB4A8C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For the first year of the award, the amount shall be based on the amount the rural health department estimates for the cost of equipment and staffing needed to set up the activities and services supported under this section, as specified in the application under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3E00F4ECA2E1434B8C1AE8E1F95BB2FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For the second through fifth years of the award, the amount shall be based on the number of patients treated, and the type of treatment provided, by the department in the prior year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H50476269246E4A80855A9EE3924F80EF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of funds</header>
<paragraph id="H14EE4962CF11424C8F2116AF9B0B22EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A rural health department receiving a grant under this section shall use the funds awarded through the grant to provide the services and carry out the activities described in subsection (b) at a facility that is located in a rural area, including by—</text> <subparagraph id="HF98D9C08AEED4CA28BC02B107AFBF3C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>obtaining additional medical equipment and resources necessary for providing the services and activities described in subsection (b), such as laboratories, x-ray machines, and cardiac monitors;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H17ED72CB4C664EE2A2455E6E9A0BEA18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>hiring additional providers to provide the services and carry out the activities described in subsection (b), such as physician interns, residents, nurse practitioners, physician assistants, and nurse midwives, which hiring may be through a partnership described in paragraph (2)(A); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H01623238D96A4D50A085B5FDB0BF9732"><enum>(C)</enum><text>providing outreach to the community regarding the services and activities of the rural health department as supported under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9B698394372A4479812B9A7B9B077902"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitations</header>
<subparagraph id="HD09533A2D07A4472B3979D4B504058A9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text>Not more than 3 percent of the funds awarded through a grant under this section for a year may be used towards the rural health department entering into a partnership with an academic medical center to assist with the hiring described in paragraph (1)(B).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H595B3C0E9CA245BB9029CB093C173FC6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Community outreach</header><text>For each of the first 2 years of a grant awarded under this section, not more than 3 percent of the funds may be used by the rural health department receiving the grant for the outreach described in paragraph (1)(C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H38627A8840CF4486A7DC8023F3B8E2B9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

