<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H26B0D649B6B941D3867E34DD5A588135" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3848 IH: HOME Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3848</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230606">June 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To make certain improvements in the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs relating to homelessness, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEDF68C698D514BDAAF216778EF4C7D3E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC30FB84B3BFD4EE19FA99C003E6CDC12" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Housing our Military Veterans Effectively Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote>HOME Act of 2023</quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF4AB44A65D1046DAB011D3A5DB3827C0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Per diem payments provided by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for services furnished to homeless veterans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2012 of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H17E5B4057A0A4C6080298F5CD53E936B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="H1781565728664622B3D4C269D6C8E389"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B)—</text> 
<clause id="H00691A55FB214C0C96450E13874EAF68"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i)(II)(aa)(BB)—</text> <subclause id="HEBD9AFD5F898475DBE5629CBAE096C62"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>115 percent</quote> and inserting <quote>133 percent</quote>; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3FD15D63DCA14507B1D867DB81C94D97"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, plus a percentage increase to such rate equal to the percentage determined under section 3564(a) of this title</quote> after <quote>of that section</quote>;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H1E993EF3EC4A452D9AC6D46AD4BE30C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>150</quote> and inserting <quote>140</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF7F6F80565B64C129C57BBEE9B76BEF0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H7DD677CACED348E38F5DC4D21138AB85" style="OLC"> <clause id="HB393D636195E46328A819CDA8CF562BA" indent="up3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to clause (iv), the Secretary may waive the maximum rate for per diem payments under clause (i)(II)(aa)(BB) or (ii) and provide such payments at a rate that does not exceed 200 percent of the rate authorized for State homes for domiciliary care under subsection (a)(1)(A) of section 1741 of this title, as the Secretary may increase from time to time under subsection (c) of that section, if the Secretary—</text> 
<subclause id="HDA676AFCAF1F4AD6BA50E480B9227885"><enum>(I)</enum><text>determines that the grant recipient or eligible entity furnishes services to homeless veterans in—</text> <item id="H4C7F7A6402C44891A5EBF74CBDEBAE88"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a rural or highly rural area;</text></item> 
<item id="HC8E5EB9072E74D9CAB6312C9C7DAA907"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>an area with a high rate of suicide among veterans; or</text></item> <item id="HEEE1132AE41B417987A707C00EE736A4"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>an area with a high rate of homelessness among veterans; and</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE459415D6B0D4F81B5002DC3B1F1DD29"><enum>(II)</enum><text>notifies Congress of the need for such waiver.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H1B79A036534A402D8881F0307CAF8B81" indent="up3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not, pursuant to clause (iii), waive the maximum rate described in such clause for more than 10 percent of all grant recipients and eligible entities in a fiscal year.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAC8426648843497FBEFDBD4D994AB81B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H7B7FBD1D402A474AB64E655E8372CA43" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H36BFEEA8D36944C480B4C8E497AE3027" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not provide more than 10,500 payments under this section in a fiscal year.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBCA4869789AE48078B5E74519DD29618"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block id="H97F7BA030A884358A747C2CF2158B340" style="OLC"> <subsection id="HC506D40C1BCC4E8090AFD332F62950D9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports required</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of the HOME Act of 2023, and not less frequently than twice each year thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the rate for per diem payments under this section that includes, for each Veterans Integrated Service Network of the Department, the following data:</text> 
<paragraph id="H5CE6CE731AC740F790C6684DFA15D575"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The average rate for such a payment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H510F1EC0ACF54D6EA35CFDCFC7A1DE18"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A list of locations where the rate for such a payment is within 10 percent of the maximum rate for such a payment authorized under this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF85A937EDEB7409483C5952AE04581BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The average length of stay by a veteran participating in a program described in section 2011(a) of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="H77B4B8FC627F404DB62A617355F7969A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Modification of authority to enter into certain leases at the Department of Veterans Affairs West Los Angeles campus</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2 of West Los Angeles Leasing Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/226">Public Law 114–226</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC1EBB1865EBA4252BE7BDA5E2FF1C865"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (h)(1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H4F3B0BD313504203862398F12C6D5188"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>that is not in compliance with such laws</quote> both places it appears;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE262A18269694DBFB895F376208B1E53"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>certifies</quote> and inserting <quote>submits</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE83AB8114E4742C6A166A91BC6EBBF2C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>that all recommendations included in the audit report or evaluation have been implemented</quote> and inserting <quote>notice in writing of whether the Secretary concurred or did not concur with each recommendation included in the audit report or evaluation and, in the case of any nonconcurrence, the reasons for such nonconcurrence</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H446589C4D63D4C2CB5260175EE77EF8B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H6DB12E993FE64DEDB2C9859F86F32FB4" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="HAD063D2863CA428BB31701971AABBA70"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 1302 of title 40, United States Code, section 8122 of title 38, United States Code, or any other provision of law, consideration for a lease made pursuant to this Act may include consideration other than money.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H8456156C07F543469AEBFDD7545124D4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Temporary authorization for Secretary of Veterans Affairs to use of certain funds for improved flexibility in assistance to homeless veterans</header> 
<subsection id="H9850473CE2054301959C29C15B0B3E65"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs may use amounts appropriated or otherwise made available to the Department of Veterans Affairs to carry out section 2011, 2012, 2031, or 2061 of title 38, United States Code, to provide to a covered veteran, as the Secretary determines necessary—</text> <paragraph id="H878D0EFBE8F24577B392B00BE917A395"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assistance required for the safety and survival of the veteran (such as food, shelter, clothing, blankets, and hygiene items);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H571FBFE7391648FB9FFB0680E778DF75"><enum>(2)</enum><text>transportation required to support the stability and health of the veteran (such as transportation for appointments with service providers, the conduct of housing searches, and the obtainment of food and supplies);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H543E850A09A14E299C816C741FA8DFC0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>communications equipment and services (such as tablets, smartphones, disposable phones, and related service plans) required to support the stability and health of the veteran (such as through the maintenance of contact with service providers, prospective landlords, and family members); and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54BDD6365FEB40AC9C572A30B789EC22"><enum>(4)</enum><text>such other assistance as the Secretary determines necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAE0FF081ED3F49F38A9655EB6C2D7D9D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Homeless veterans on Department of Veterans Affairs land</header> <paragraph id="H6E87BEF544E540B3B1417C9D62C65B26" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may collaborate, to the extent practicable, with one or more organizations to manage the use of land of the Department of Veterans Affairs for homeless veterans for living and sleeping.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D33F5C652384519BED5C130FE3B4EB1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Forms of collaboration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Collaboration under paragraph (1) may include the provision by either the Secretary or the head of the organization concerned of food services and security for property, buildings, and other facilities owned or controlled by the Department of Veterans Affairs.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H93F73FF1790C4FDF8EDBB7534A2E95CF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes, with respect to the period covered by such report—</text> 
<paragraph id="H33A9296B300C4BF790F66541279296E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a statement, disaggregated by each medical center of the Department of Veterans Affairs, of the amount of funds under this section—</text> <subparagraph id="H031349F7EF4F4A498E696756B72AA5E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each such medical center requested from the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2F25CF5B7CD04838AAB717AADD8FF5AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to which the Secretary provided each such medical center;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB229EABC34E04ABDA0C10036A8B1983D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>data, disaggregated by each such medical center, relating to how each such medical center used amounts provided by the Secretary under this section;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB60409A303A1479D81B2FF1670195FD8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of covered veterans to which the Secretary provided assistance under this section;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5BB6E8D83C14400DB918F7E14BE1A536"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total amount of assistance the Secretary provided to covered veterans pursuant to subsection (a)(3) for communications equipment, broken down by the type of equipment provided;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE48B2372082347F9BEA03B9AF4BCF340"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the total amount of assistance the Secretary provided covered veterans pursuant to subsection (a)(2) for ridesharing;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02F2DCD497DA4156AE817E4DE0A2E243"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the number of covered veterans who received such assistance; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD07EFC9D448140D8B95489CCD718576B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a description, for each rideshare used by a covered veteran with such assistance, of the reasons such covered veteran used such rideshare.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H804A4BB8A9F84DA0A0D1813AB1F80E36"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority under this section shall terminate on September 30, 2024.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1611F5E29A0D4D58A0FB3A59F2B7A9B4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>covered veteran</quote> means—</text> <paragraph id="HE8AB929DD32446C1B584861322DD72AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a homeless veteran; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDD5110EE5DA0456C9C150DB405D07DF0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a veteran participating in the program carried out under section 8(o)(19) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)(19)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

