<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFEB6EE94144C4C25A7FCFD75E45C1C02" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4267 IH: Protect Our Civil Liberties Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4267</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230621">June 21, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence (Permanent Select)</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To repeal the USA PATRIOT Act and the FISA Amendments Act of 2008, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H541D58DF6E6145E29EDDF6C8AF9B220A" style="OLC">
<section id="H1F265F644BA44F62AF4617B7582D82CA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protect Our Civil Liberties Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H10BDD3C824C84F6DAF3AA2EC39AC3A57"><enum>2.</enum><header>Repeal of USA Patriot Act and destruction of certain information</header> <subsection id="H8B152AE816554920B9687DC345B35DA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text>The USA PATRIOT Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/56">Public Law 107–56</external-xref>) is repealed, and the provisions of law amended or repealed by such Act are restored or revived as if such Act had not been enacted.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H1DD87B121CBC435598AA8BD11EDB29BB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Destruction of certain information</header><text>The Director of National Intelligence and the Attorney General shall destroy any information collected under the USA PATRIOT Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/56">Public Law 107–56</external-xref>) and the amendments made by such Act, as in effect the day before the date of the enactment of this Act, concerning a United States person that is not related to an investigation that is actively ongoing on such date.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H775CABB6ED2248A88D1F566E0B2B8443"><enum>3.</enum><header>Repeal of the FISA Amendments Act of 2008 and destruction of certain information</header> <subsection id="H462CA7E125814E3E90FD5299A3DE6B2A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Repeal</header><text>The FISA Amendments Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/261">Public Law 110–261</external-xref>; 122 Stat. 2477) is repealed, and the provisions of law amended or repealed by such Act are restored or revived as if such Act had not been enacted.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HCE4FC8B6776048218A9BF075818733A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subsection (a) of this Act shall not apply to sections 103 and 110 of the FISA Amendments Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/261">Public Law 110–261</external-xref>; 122 Stat. 2477).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC6984903D2F044FEB91390636C9E1262"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Destruction of Certain information</header><text>The Director of National Intelligence and the Attorney General shall destroy any information collected under section 702 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1881a">50 U.S.C. 1881a</external-xref>), as in effect the day before the date of the enactment of this Act, concerning a United States person that is not related to an investigation that is actively ongoing on such date.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="HD7B92FE94F7B4431978E4F300EA0F1EE"><enum>4.</enum><header>Increase term length of judges on Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court; reappointment; appointment of special masters to advise courts</header>
<subsection id="HE9F2416B9A63443AA151454F382DFA5D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Terms; Reappointment</header><text>Section 103(d) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1803">50 U.S.C. 1803(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8AABDDB2D61248A89FCA120A543C5DCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>maximum of seven</quote> and inserting <quote>maximum of ten</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1445052868DA4A35BE22514A34A8550E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and shall not be eligible for redesignation</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1E89A6D95D1C4A8E9950B11479EFA8B4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Special Masters</header><text>Section 103(f) of such Act, as amended by section 3 of this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph: </text>
<quoted-block id="H04F11B9BDF8C47F38613008F5044FDCF">
<paragraph id="HB5FBDC5D3A604A09AA7A967C357293ED"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Special Masters</header>
<subparagraph id="H74208D2AD0AA4A00A05705E8263F6F7C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The courts established pursuant to subsections (a) and (b) may appoint one or more Special Masters to advise the courts on technical issues raised during proceedings before the courts. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H83C289A2B69A476987D99A298D6011BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text> In this paragraph, the term <term>Special Master</term> means an individual who has technological expertise in the subject matter of a proceeding before a court established pursuant to subsection (a) or (b). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
<section id="H845766A2C3B64462AA81A6A3D82DC429"><enum>5.</enum><header>Electronic surveillance of specified persons without regard to specific device</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Section 105(c)(2)(B) of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1805">50 U.S.C. 1805(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows: </text> <quoted-block id="H5EE331C749464D8C9320385918298356"> <subparagraph id="H4863DACC40B04489BCADEA09C88374C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that, upon the request of the applicant, any person or entity shall furnish the applicant forthwith all information, facilities, or technical assistance necessary to accomplish the electronic surveillance in such a manner as will protect its secrecy and produce a minimum of interference with the services that such carrier, landlord, custodian, or other person is providing that target of electronic surveillance; </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H5FE9EC41E4984C18BB1491ED817CF0B0"><enum>6.</enum><header>Additional provisions for collections under the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978</header>
<subsection id="H24E7A7F8473341C3A2B0086D7559F2F9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title VII of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by section 3 of this Act, is further amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block id="HA031099EB0004A2DBF22658450658435"> <title id="HDB05C229876B4D3E803CD139C961CA12"><enum>VII</enum><header>Additional provisions</header> <section id="HCB9AE2C55BDA452F8167F8C33AFB2680" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>701.</enum><header> Warrant requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, no information relating to a United States person may be acquired pursuant to this Act without a valid warrant based on probable cause. </text></section></title><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H25EE75C0AB3D47AFBAB0EDDD68B68668"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents amendments</header><text>The table of contents in the first section of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by section 3 of this Act, is further amended by striking the items relating to title VII and section 701 and inserting the following new items: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9825219B125348F1920D9EAB6A7BA535"> <toc> <toc-entry level="title" bold="off">TITLE VII—Additional Provisions </toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section" bold="off">701. Warrant requirement.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="HF26843C4E2034DD6B00AC7E5EF46F920"><enum>7.</enum><header>Prohibit government mandated “backdoors” into encryption and privacy technology of electronic devices and software</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Federal Government shall not mandate that the manufacturer of an electronic device or software for an electronic device build into such device or software a mechanism that allows the Federal Government to bypass the encryption or privacy technology of such device or software.</text></section>
<section id="HA8638AEA43504DC1A0896E2B5E1922BA"><enum>8.</enum><header>Mandate annual GAO compliance evaluations</header>
<subsection id="H9A8BBFEA34CC422FB7ADB81FA46EE08D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall annually evaluate compliance by the Federal Government with the provisions of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H26A2DFD05D194798B8E7A42A682A58C8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Comptroller General shall annually submit to Congress a report containing the results of the evaluation conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="HDF876345C0364DF1A81B7CAC87B4FF65"><enum>9.</enum><header>Prohibit retaliation for whistleblower complaints</header>
<subsection id="HDB6B15DA5CD4467192CEA426306AC797"><enum>(a)</enum><header> Authorization To report complaints or information</header><text>An employee of or contractor to an element of the intelligence community that has knowledge of the programs and activities authorized by the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) may submit a covered complaint—</text> <paragraph id="H3486B3F9DD094E5D9A53A0DE83C0A2D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the Comptroller General of the United States;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H66B8C09E496F4C3DA088320F0BB6B053"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB41A71D0A41545E38FF0006569405CF9"><enum>(3)</enum><text> to the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8A23B458EBDE4966A597C0E5EDF62FE5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in accordance with the process established under section 103H(k)(5) of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3033">50 U.S.C. 3033(k)(5)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA8C6D7BD4A344B4C990B0DB157839039"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Investigations and reports to Congress</header><text>The Comptroller General shall investigate a covered complaint submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1) and shall submit to Congress a report containing the results of the investigation.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HF9B594F69FD24A859B13BD51166A16FD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered complaint defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered complaint</term> means a complaint or information concerning programs and activities authorized by the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1801">50 U.S.C. 1801 et seq.</external-xref>) that an employee or contractor reasonably believes is evidence of—</text> <paragraph id="H9FFAF29930F94A9AA3CE58B8FBC05BEE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a violation of any law, rule, or regulation; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H83F345E608314CF1B2FD7FC52F2E76A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>gross mismanagement, a gross waste of funds, an abuse of authority, or a substantial and specific danger to public health or safety. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HA186F883E52A4A72800B7EB8A175CBA0"><enum>10.</enum><header>Prohibit interference with reporting of waste, fraud, abuse, or criminal behavior</header> <subsection id="H1CF78A1F4CE8441C9F98119E2923A9C8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no officer or employee of an element of the intelligence community shall take any retaliatory action against an employee of or contractor to an element of the intelligence community who seeks to disclose or discloses covered information to—</text>
<paragraph id="HAFDB36B4218140BFB6723838C7190369"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Comptroller General;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H097FB8544D2749B4A4CE78383B5944F3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7F41C6822DC8480F92D1D902C793FFB7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate; or </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48CF18201BF943F88A5D2EF3CF7198D5"><enum>(4)</enum><text> the Office of the Inspector General of the Intelligence Community.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEC561CE1D4E04404BD98A600E93459C8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrative sanctions</header><text>An officer or employee of an element of the intelligence community who violates subsection (a) shall be subject to administrative sanctions, up to and including termination. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H6DD05CA1007941CBB92E317E0DF0C585"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H638B8935D9F049A8BAAA0FF929416CBC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered information</header><text>The term <term>covered information</term> means any information (including classified or sensitive information) that an employee or contractor reasonably believes is evidence of—</text> <subparagraph id="H1DD155C1AD6E42CF8DDB3B7DB3F30F39"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a violation of any law, rule, or regulation; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0993D48911AA4BBAB3CF066B95F66F98"><enum>(B)</enum><text> gross mismanagement, a gross waste of funds, an abuse of authority, or a substantial and specific danger to public health or safety. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B318DC0850A43B796E08E0DC781DA7B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Intelligence community</header><text>The term <term>intelligence community</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H2694B9F4B50341DC831498B11D935B95"><enum>11.</enum><header>Prohibit targeting United States persons under Executive Order 12333 without a warrant</header>
<subsection id="H213A81653AC4476686F1826901E4B325"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on targeting of United States persons without a warrant</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no United States person may be the target of an acquisition under Executive Order 12333 without a valid warrant based on probable cause.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6C7D58547F784FA7884974EABD76ED49"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Audit of compliance with prohibition</header> <paragraph id="HC472CE5311614682B337832B684ED6B8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Audit</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall annually conduct an audit of intelligence collection under Executive Order 12333 to ensure compliance with the requirement under subsection (a). </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA884683E9AD24350A64CDB05FF80379F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Comptroller General shall annually submit to Congress a report containing the results of each audit conducted under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7F3D2EE77201424CA0BE97DA64900AE1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Destruction of certain information</header><text>The Director of National Intelligence and the Attorney General shall destroy any information collected under Executive Order 12333 without a valid warrant based on probable cause concerning a United States person that is not related to an investigation that is actively ongoing on the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


