<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB609969468E84BDAABBD873EA4A18CC4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 425 IH: History and Tradition Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 425</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230120">January 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Revised Statutes of the United States to prevent the use of the legal system in a manner that extorts money from State and local governments, and the Federal Government, and inhibits such governments’ constitutional actions under the first, tenth, and fourteenth amendments.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H73BC8C3FFA664E6294CDC0A28192C52E" style="OLC"><section id="HF338AE9F92874A9789EEE0B129B4DD99" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>History and Tradition Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H0242B4F3D949460CAA4D79EB0E234F2F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Limitations on certain lawsuits against State and local officials</header><subsection id="HE796310A7B38411595C151E81DD783FD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Civil action for deprivation of rights</header><text>Section 1979 of the Revised Statutes of the United States (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1983">42 U.S.C. 1983</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD135C51D2A9E4B3AACD03531C59C5372"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC"><enum-in-header>(a)</enum-in-header></header-in-text></quote> before the first sentence; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7574B266422406CBEE0FBD383ECFDB3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HA3F7AD4BBFE8482B9C56AF817CBC0C99" style="OLC"><subsection id="HB1D1214F75384911BBF5A5070D7E33AC"><enum>(b)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The remedies with respect to a claim under this section are limited to injunctive and declaratory relief where the deprivation consists of a violation of a prohibition in the Constitution against the establishment of religion, including, but not limited to, a violation resulting from—</text><paragraph id="H1F98AF8D65AB447999A97FACE696A572"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any monument, memorial, statue, or other figure containing religious words, imagery, or symbolism;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6535BBC9A28D41E2A16A87ED35AF26B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a public building containing religious words, imagery, or symbolism;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8A28BCA00324FB2A7F3E8C1AA00944F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the presence of religious words, imagery, or symbolism in the official seals and flags of the several States and the political subdivision thereof; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C381257956B49A788E9628066AEAE38"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">religious expression in the context of the proceedings of any deliberative body or division of any State or deliberative body or division of the several States.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H535A65031052446A89B3A5D5E5DD6FAD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Attorney’s fees</header><text>Section 722(b) of the Revised Statutes of the United States (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1988">42 U.S.C. 1988(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>However, no fees shall be awarded under this subsection with respect to a claim described in subsection (b) of section nineteen hundred and seventy nine.</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="HAC3B32C9D70D46D59C29CF5EC46B5EEB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Limitations on certain lawsuits against the United States and Federal officials</header><subsection id="H5E1431D1600A4C189F7BF547CFB2C2C4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a court shall not award reasonable fees and expenses of attorneys to the prevailing party on a claim of injury consisting of the violation of a prohibition in the Constitution against the establishment of religion brought against the United States or any agency or any official of the United States acting in his or her official capacity in any court having jurisdiction over such claim, and the remedies with respect to such a claim shall be limited to injunctive and declaratory relief.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7453F97436C849189BC9F15A395E4B48"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>As used in this section, the term <term>a claim of injury consisting of the violation of a prohibition in the Constitution against the establishment of religion</term> includes, but is not limited to, a claim of injury resulting from—</text><paragraph id="HB484541041564E85AA68F63C1165C5C3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any monument, memorial, statue, or other figure containing religious words, imagery, or symbolism;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CEF9C30545D4F0789CAC9DFBF91B172"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a Federal building containing religious words, imagery, or symbolism;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD9AE26839BC43B59633D0351B9903C6"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the presence of religious words, imagery, or symbolism in the official seal of the United States and in its currency and official Pledge; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H233DE959BDCF45ADB0D1DB4F80A60696"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">religious expression in the context of the proceedings of any deliberative body or division of the legislative or executive branches of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5B3B631EDD3547EBA1A90082C2257028"><enum>4.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act and the amendments made by this Act take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act and apply to any case that—</text><paragraph id="H1B49F5098BB6460A8ADAA812C6555BDA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is pending on such date of enactment; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6C37E8FC7C841CCB95096A53F56308A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is commenced on or after such date of enactment.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

