<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Referred-in-Senate" dms-id="H8DB132BE3C304A768E1EEEE31EBA88F1" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3581 : Caregiver Outreach and Program Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IIB</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3581</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20231205">December 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received; read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSVA00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to modify the family caregiver program of the Department of Veterans Affairs to include services related to mental health and neurological disorders, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" style="OLC" id="HA49A6670DD674D9880519CDED0E9F39C"><pagebreak></pagebreak><section id="H24B6FDA4251B45C780D19BA1A8A6D132" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Caregiver Outreach and Program Enhancement Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COPE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H97A17061D3374988A875A4F42FD042EB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority for Secretary of Veterans Affairs to award grants to entities to improve provision of mental health support to family caregivers of veterans</header><subsection id="H0BF7F1E6FB4B497CA49E8D7E13DAED2C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/17">chapter 17</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBFBF901B68904931BD798976FB775473"><section id="HF08C19C443BA4921860A41445A130F13"><enum>1720K.</enum><header>Grants to provide mental health support to family caregivers of veterans</header><subsection id="HC0BB600694474B989DEF06DC000E7178"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The Secretary may award grants to carry out, coordinate, improve, or otherwise enhance mental health counseling, treatment, or support to the family caregivers of veterans participating in the family caregiver program.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC105849730904CDC89E69BCE0D32BB47"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE5BC99A1A5724AF1A3D4584CFFA7FA40"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To be eligible for a grant under this section, an entity shall submit to the Secretary an application therefor at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1779FE3DD38747819BEC814049B1F15F" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each application submitted under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="HC48616AF173946FEAE6E7F1BEB8CA5FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A detailed plan for the use of the grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23821684E51444F2A0FF145C7C54F09C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the programs or efforts through which the entity will meet the outcome measures developed by the Secretary under subsection (g).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D68D52D49614DC59C8A902B8AAB04A7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of how the entity will distribute grant amounts equitably among areas with varying levels of urbanization.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F2D061CE8354DA38B31164FC2E61422"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A plan for how the grant will be used to meet the unique needs of veterans residing in rural areas, American Indian or Alaska Native veterans, elderly veterans, women veterans, and veterans from other underserved communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C485AF5C9994EB6AEFDADC1F641DB36"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>The Secretary shall seek to ensure that grants awarded under this section are equitably distributed among entities located in States with varying levels of urbanization.</text></subsection><subsection id="H21639BC9B0CF40D88A2507775F3F607D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary shall prioritize awarding grants under this section that will serve the following areas:</text><paragraph id="H36C15740F14449DBB0D2B749FFB1F9A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Areas with high rates of veterans enrolled in the family caregiver program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97CA7422DECF4A22820612BA76AA277B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Areas with high rates of—</text><subparagraph id="HEA69889517F84CFCAD096350C4762D8B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>suicide among veterans; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA179A1D4CF2C42579B9ABC9332441841"><enum>(B)</enum><text>referrals to the Veterans Crisis Line.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF177A4CE5B3D465199B07F5FB132E5DC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Required activities</header><text>Any grant awarded under this section shall be used—</text><paragraph id="H519B870CF73F40659EFFB880F47542BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to expand existing programs, activities, and services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04C15AEA816740318A16411CCB4805BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to establish new or additional programs, activities, and services; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H251BD3D9A09C4B99AEBD829E86A9504D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for travel and transportation to facilitate carrying out paragraph (1) or (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBDDEF6C0A9B04D9997EC9EB8988E940D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Outcome measures</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9860BEDA7C484374827C79897E4708AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall develop and provide to each entity that receives a grant under this section written guidance on the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF46E1D7C30554C58A9B11382E8F4F136" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Outcome measures.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H822EA1A1B48F4F779A6CA947CAB38248" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Policies of the Department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA10BC7F37D384D1E88AA28B35EFD432F" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In developing outcome measures under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consider the following goals:</text><subparagraph id="H594F97B92053488B8831EA11E199B5AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Increasing the utilization of mental health services among family caregivers of veterans participating in the family caregiver program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AFEEC72249B47559F34CE9140CBB3B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Reducing barriers to mental health services among family caregivers of veterans participating in such program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE85E8B1ED3CD49109D1A4AE9E7099215"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Tracking requirements</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H65C12F4FE513436F91746DDCAC4A3B1D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall establish appropriate tracking requirements with respect to the entities receiving a grant under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE36E65695C524F3280A0C135FBF2E660" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Not less frequently than annually, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on such tracking requirements.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4CDFF1D4921941BF88F724C73F745F06"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Performance review</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H10C3D27D01314BC0B116B5094461FF4A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review the performance of each entity that receives a grant under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06D32F0E1686455FA631918E8A6C9012" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make information regarding such performance publicly available.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9CF7E00131D44CE5ADA569C4F8769824"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Remediation plan</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H32BDF6E9091644969E8107E17BB2BA82"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of an entity that receives a grant under this section and does not meet the outcome measures developed by the Secretary under subsection (g), the Secretary shall require the entity to submit to the Secretary a remediation plan under which the entity shall describe how and when it plans to meet such outcome measures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEACEA95F1A3345C5B67B6657D5B49BB7" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary may not award a subsequent grant under this section to an entity described in paragraph (1) unless the Secretary approves the remediation plan submitted by the entity under such paragraph.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H99CE0D24912E419E99D67A8E2B561589"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>The amount of a grant awarded under this section may not exceed 10 percent of amounts made available for grants under this section for the fiscal year in which the grant is awarded.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1FF5F2B291FD467BAFD21CF8E66366E6"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Any grant awarded under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant funding that is otherwise available through the Department to provide mental health support among family caregivers of veterans participating in the family caregiver program.</text></subsection><subsection id="H00DF451CA5EA49D08560EF882786C45F"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Outreach to family caregivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include, in the outreach materials regularly mailed to a family caregiver who participates in the family caregiver program, notice of mental health support provided by recipients of grants under this section that are located in the relevant Veterans Integrated Service Network.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5233FCDB2A514FE282C7AA86F0C5877C"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Funding</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE77CA0AE39474854B6D140C2F60ACB83"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Amounts for the activities of the Department under this section shall be budgeted and appropriated through a separate appropriation account.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1699A11E153B44239712798651D4DF60" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the budget justification materials submitted to Congress in support of the budget of the Department for any fiscal year (as submitted with the budget of the President under section 1105(a) of title 31), the Secretary shall include a separate statement of the amount requested to be appropriated for that fiscal year for the account specified in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6181613874C34671B2C726B524A243BB"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary, for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026, $50,000,000 to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7ED68A27F7F644C1B1D69255E9841BC9"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA8FB9A6BA5CC4334B58ADB8706710C8A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The terms <term>caregiver</term> and <term>family caregiver</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 1720G of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12147D6E7438410C9EDAA173C5A168A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>family caregiver program</term> means the program of comprehensive assistance for family caregivers under section 1720G of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3C2F265F74E40FDBD549405811B1E7D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>Veterans Crisis Line</term> means the toll-free hotline for veterans established under section 1720F of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H49A3207EB5024579B890723AE9BC3487"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such subchapter is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HBA11FE72AFBE47219BABEBC74D0365CA" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HVR00"><toc changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HVR00"><toc-entry level="section" idref="HF08C19C443BA4921860A41445A130F13">1720K. Grants to provide mental health support to family caregivers of veterans.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HB5775D0AE4FC41E7863BE844BE76D58D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Contributions to local authorities to mitigate the risk of flooding on local property adjacent to medical facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H7629CEF65F5646729E26AD6B732189DF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 8108 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, or to mitigate the risk of flooding, including the risk of flooding associated with rising sea levels</quote> before the period at the end.</text></subsection><subsection id="H97395122923349C19DA94728C4D10307"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report that includes an assessment of—</text><paragraph id="H9313DD8EC6554926A1699FBCAA0A3701"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the extent to which each medical facility (as such term is defined in section 8101(3) of title 38, United States Code) is at risk of flooding, including the risk of flooding associated with rising sea levels; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H343A51823E2E4B119F07010795ED42FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whether additional resources are necessary to address the risk of flooding at each such facility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8BF98D011DB44D2090E221E894A12370"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for the Department of Veterans Affairs for each of fiscals year 2024 through 2028 $25,000,000 to carry out the amendment made by subsection (a). </text></subsection></section><section id="H3388EA7A097D4D57B7060E8E35A1ED4A"><enum>4.</enum><header>GAO report on mental health support for caregivers</header><subsection id="H0873460E1CF54AC2AAE33A1DB67EEA59"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the provision of mental health support to caregivers of veterans.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3C269CFEB4C944E0BBD495C2F7CF1980"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report submitted under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H0F4FC1CE21F74DE0A5C83C719B3E5506"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An assessment of the need for mental health support among caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H12145F37324D470588A531F4BE3994FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An assessment of options for mental health support in facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs and in the community for caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C3FC02A61214C6F8861849E5B54606A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An assessment of the availability and accessibility of mental health support in facilities of the Department and in the community for caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD24F950A89F146E19D02CAFC3DEF4ABF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An assessment of the awareness among caregivers of the availability of mental health support in facilities of the Department and in the community for caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F85543BC4BB400CA6FB6509E77574FA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An assessment of barriers to mental health support in facilities of the Department and in the community for caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFEA0CF27AB5A45278B02DF03C99E13AE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB947CD37903F4C8F9861189920D73092"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>caregiver</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1720G of title 38, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBEF600AC80774B9298ECB4140D5CB71F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>caregiver programs</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HE3E32189FB484F1BBEDABABE7D4DAFE9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the program of comprehensive assistance for family caregivers under subsection (a) of section 1720G of title 38, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9083BBBEEC7F4F0C98C7D7DA7426C7D8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the program of support services for caregivers under subsection (b) of such section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H516F6C6B65AF4529BC869B690CFDC252" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header>Annual review of security at covered facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="HD57881FB0EF941079F09A91B11D154B3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual survey</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for each of the following five years, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in coordination with the Director of the Office of Security and Law Enforcement of the Department of Veterans Affairs, shall conduct an annual survey of covered employees to collect information regarding security at each covered facility. Each annual survey shall include questions about—</text><paragraph id="HBB532283FCE84EAA9C6AD3C9CC0422B5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the type and frequency of criminal activity experienced at the covered facility during the 12 months prior to the date the covered employee completes the survey;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB21E7BE797C4C549AB02B92E2B902E1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of vacant positions for Department police officers at the covered facility and the number of days each vacant position has been vacant;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32EFB7D00B3348C2A15E21C8A8402709"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the availability and adequacy of covered equipment; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83417B55458D4F3A9DD15603949ACCAD"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the availability and adequacy of resources, classes, or other time set aside for training Department police officers who work at each covered facility about any skill or tactic related to law enforcement, including the proper use of force, firearms qualifications and training, procedures for responding to an active threat, and any other training required for Department police officers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D0035BFEF314DB1B2413FCAD71295A8"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any security weakness;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BE823418A47484E81FCF52815CB8D48"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an analysis of the relationship between the covered facility (including the Department police officers who work at the covered facility) and local law enforcement agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D239DA4196343B7A0318758B50ECB73"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">efforts by the personnel of the covered facility to address and reduce criminal activity at, or in close proximity to, the covered facility; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62C20FA07B8A4F2EB91DF83C8991CCC5"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations for the Secretary to better address and reduce criminal activity at, or in close proximity to, covered facilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCEC6C18E729F41839E60D8D0543BAFE6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for each of the following five years, the Secretary shall submit to each of the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the House of Representatives an annual report regarding security at covered facilities that includes—</text><paragraph id="H579594A87CF143EFA414346E8E22FA7A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the results of the annual survey described under subsection (a) for the year covered by the report;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D6F2D73C2B34AA4A2CC85A8B6B66E25"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an analysis, made in coordination with the Director of the Office of Security and Law Enforcement of such Department and each director and police chief of a Veterans Integrated Service Network, of the results of the annual survey described under subsection (a) for the year covered by the report;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E2F473E574249EBB13117C62E107A6C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a plan of action that describes how the Secretary plans to address any security weakness identified in the results of the annual survey and includes clearly-stated goals with measurable benchmarks for each goal and deadlines for each benchmark; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CDF399AE56748D3852CFD82EBB6A35C"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of each vacant position for police chief or deputy police chief at each covered facility, and the number of days the position has been vacant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H800ED0BF2EA342E6B08142195A352D87"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HBDB6804F72E04053A4635F413CBBAE72"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered equipment</term> means any item issued by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to a Department police officer (including batons, firearms, pepper spray, ballistic vests, body-worn cameras, and radios) for use in the provision of services under section 902 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27C6057AC6D045FA84A0E497BAF8BD74" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered employee</term> means any employee of the Department of Veterans Affairs who is employed at a covered facility as a police chief, a facility emergency management leader, a facility director, or a person carrying out the responsibilities of one of these positions in an acting capacity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51C01B0F9ACA4CFF8F4B779F26819158"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered facility</term> means any facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs where Department police officers have jurisdiction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FEDD453AC4C465E8789B7B302617086"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Department police officer</term> has the meaning given to such term as used in section 902 of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10FF675B56F44494B3786FF53E7C0F18"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>security weakness</term> means a deficiency in the facilities, staffing, or covered equipment at a covered facility that a covered employee of the covered facility determines presents a risk to the safety of visitors or staff, including an unsecured door, inoperable security camera, unsecured police operations room, a lack of security presence at an entrance to the covered facility, and a lack of security presence in an area of the covered facility or the grounds of the covered facility that the director of the covered facility determines requires an increased security presence.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2780371B67D6425A8A8C8E166B2BA2AE"><enum>6.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs housing loan fees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The loan fee table in section 3729(b)(2) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>November 14, 2031</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>March 12, 2032</quote>.</text></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20231204" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives December 4, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Kevin F. McCumber,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation></bill> 

