<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6E4A44201B1842C99FDB1FF5B6CF4D7E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6198 IH: Building Up Infrastructure for Local Departments Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6198</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000595">Ms. Letlow</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To support infrastructure investment in small law enforcement agencies and small fire departments.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H5585D615DBA24888A6E7C1ADB527FAB5" style="OLC">
<section id="HF7368255C18B4A21B2B84E70E15C561A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Building Up Infrastructure for Local Departments Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>BUILD Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H9C53E10F7B6D4FFCA6D6ABB54AA07B3A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Building up infrastructure for local departments grant program</header> <subsection id="H1E19AAD641B348B19F36D962AFDC6EE9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 is amended by adding at the end the following: </text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H77ED50334CC243D98B6328FE5AA06AE2" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<part id="H7DD4F162D84E40248F1AE00C85CE161B"><enum>PP</enum><header>Building Up Infrastructure for Local Departments Grant Program</header>
<section id="HDB28AB1A71074EBEA7825B698546A153"><enum>3061.</enum><header>Grant authorization</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General is authorized to make grants to State and local law enforcement agencies that serve jurisdictions with fewer than 50,000 residents for use in accordance with section 3062. </text></section> <section id="HC342C78EDA204B00947797F7209607FF"><enum>3062.</enum><header>Use of funds</header> <subsection id="HBF3D5292F3F745FB8D73FD5B346F9341"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds made available to a State or local law enforcement agency under this part shall be used for a project to modify, upgrade, or construct a facility of the law enforcement agency, which project shall have a substantial nexus to—</text>
<paragraph id="H95BF02860D4345C5860ACACD9CC88316"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the improvement of the provision of emergency services;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H55167743932B4B63992508B5D5F176B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the training and development of law enforcement officers;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H970976E32A8E4886B8CADA69C2630082"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the recruitment and retention of law enforcement officers; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF76174F9BEF472FB2EA5D4AA182DD2F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>community engagement; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H86142B17C407498393C332937000649A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the improvement of community safety. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0B03379ABE6F49B5B13D0B8042C8775B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>A portion of a project to modify, upgrade, or construct a facility of law enforcement agency that does not have a substantial nexus to any of paragraphs (1) through (5), such portion may not use funds made available under this part. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="H716F7890B1C3437E8B75AD263EF7FC5B"><enum>3063.</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The head of a State or local law enforcement agency seeking a grant under this part shall submit to the Attorney General at such time and containing such information as the Attorney General may reasonably require, including an estimate of the cost of the project for which the grant will be used, as well as a demonstration of financial need for the grant. </text></section> <section id="HB1C1BC38D971471AAF27FC0DA26F9940"><enum>3064.</enum><header>Duties of Attorney General</header> <subsection id="H72DC1AF861094A4ABBF8EC3C382CDF99"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this part, the Attorney General shall issue guidance to carry out the grant program under this part.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HA99DEE8DC09346558C8DC048CA7A76DB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Distribution of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall distribute information about the grant program under this part to eligible State and local law enforcement agencies.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC80291F99B0E4BE69F7C84B50519DFAA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Equitable distribution</header><text>In awarding grants under this part, the Attorney General shall ensure, to the extent practicable, an equitable geographic distribution among the regions of the United States.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H45FFDB6C045D4C86BDED34F52EDCD092"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>On the date that is 2 years after the date of enactment of this part, and biannually thereafter until the date that is 6 years after the date of enactment of this part, the Attorney General shall submit to Congress and make publicly available a report on the grant program under this part. </text></subsection></section> <section id="HCF4753830A7A480C8A1DF95EDAAA10B8"><enum>3065.</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A grant under this part may not exceed $4,000,000.</text></section>
<section id="H571F9C00FCC94BC690CD2BD9996C8E50"><enum>3066.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Attorney General to carry out this section $250,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026. </text></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HBE3813CF6B2D43F19FBA4047E292563C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header> <paragraph id="H65157B7FE6AD4A948A45566629F9D0DC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Attorney General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall periodically conduct and publish a study of the met and unmet construction and renovation needs of a national sample of law enforcement agencies. Such study may be conducted as a supplement to the Law Enforcement Management and Administrative Statistics program operated by the Bureau of Justice Statistics.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H82833600AD664CA794C02504D3EB61ED"><enum>(2)</enum><header>GAO</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study on the sufficiency of existing capital infrastructure for law enforcement agencies serving jurisdictions with fewer than 50,000 residents, including the met and unmet construction and renovation needs of such law enforcement agencies. Such report shall include projections relating to such needs over the following periods:</text> <subparagraph id="H48CCB83D61394D1FB56A48358358587B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>One to five years.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF5881E3EC128453280C50F715A74EED6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Five to ten years.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4617C14C26D3483C913CE4F76A167ED2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>More than ten years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HBE4424183AEB45D08747F295709020A8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Building up infrastructure for local departments—fire grant program</header>
<subsection id="HCBA82FD285484402A9E54E9086C84E63"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant authorization</header><text>The Administrator is authorized to make grants to entities described in subsection (b) to modify, upgrade, or construct fire department facilities.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC233B4EAEC4E45E2B1027B7E4D2139BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Entities described</header><text>Entities described in this subsection are career fire departments, combination fire departments, and volunteer fire departments which serve jurisdictions of 50,000 people or fewer.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H5CDB02EED2924C63A6291B7FB49B82AC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Distribution of information</header><text>The Administrator shall distribute to entities described in subsection (b) information regarding the grant program.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD3A86BC549C14E70A0D24309D4EF255D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An entity described in subsection (b) seeking a grant under this section shall submit to the Administrator an application at such time and containing such information as the Administrator may reasonably require, including the size of the jurisdiction served by such applicant, an estimate of the cost of the project for which the grant will be used, and a demonstration of financial need for the grant.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H0D622335A31B44BA9CB1603D369A5EE2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the purpose described in subsection (a), a recipient of a grant under this section may use funds received for the following:</text> <paragraph id="H2D77B8A8C91B4026AA21D3A71B0F1BF9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The improvement of the provision of emergency services, including either firefighting or affiliated EMS capabilities.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H802E6553176A4B6F9C8C4E7A5D6DB61F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The training and development of firefighting or EMS personnel.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CD70C524369458F8A3AC623080C7A3D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The recruitment and retention of such personnel, including by improving safety.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H68A75264D6B04AAC80306E5540AC079A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Community engagement.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H59A931F20C294D778B8467E5E74A5EB7" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The improvement of community safety.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA5EBAB6482ED45F1A9BE1B111B4A2461" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Equitable distribution</header><text>In awarding grants under this part, the Administrator shall ensure, to the extent practicable, an equitable geographic distribution among the regions of the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE7D890DBE49F4DE0AC122FBF58B8EE66" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>A grant under this section may not exceed $4,000,000.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H662F45B2601B4E59B464327F205641C2"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports on grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act and biennially thereafter for six years, the Administrator shall submit to Congress and make publicly available a report on grants made under this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H32C1E2DB41894447B474EE2714B01CA9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Reports on construction and renovation needs</header> <paragraph id="H3624F05DB02B43148FF7717E7B9669B0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>FEMA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the greatest extent possible, the Administrator shall periodically conduct and publish a study of the met and unmet construction and renovation needs of a national sample of career fire departments, combination fire departments, and volunteer fire departments.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8E263AB5D8864BB994A5F1233DC3750C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>GAO</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress and make publicly available a report on the sufficiency of existing capital infrastructure for career fire departments, combination fire departments, and volunteer fire departments nationwide serving jurisdictions with fewer than 50,000 residents, including the met and unmet construction and renovation needs and the provision of emergency services. Such report shall include projections relating to such needs and services over the following periods:</text> <subparagraph id="HB2F3A5609AF64365AC3B5719D3F72E78" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>One to five years.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H61E6171BE6474A719FF3ADA02C4C4A73" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Five to ten years.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF8AB4F271CC64AECB440B9C307A6D571" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>More than ten years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7FE1647B14334E2AB87D4B419F971B76"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator $250,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2026 to carry out this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC4A4722E622443C5BD3B1AD53C84C40B"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="HEE14EE4931E14573A3FB4AF1C2785358"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H577B14D411EE4014861F3CA2494625BA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Career fire department</header><text>The term <quote>career fire department</quote> means a fire department that has an all-paid force of firefighting personnel other than paid-on-call firefighters.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H554F5B4AD13B43AA9941D10A0ED3CE32"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Combination fire department</header><text>The term <quote>combination fire department</quote> means a fire department that has—</text> <subparagraph id="H3612D388C5EC4418AE5A6397FA0BDC1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paid firefighting personnel; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF3A5666CFD3E44579E48BC57CCC432CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>volunteer firefighting personnel.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01E85C4E57BF48C7A7E33F672EA7C79A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>EMS</header><text>The term <quote>EMS</quote> means emergency medical services. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7A45E9CBAD6C49EB942F15BC3A25D274"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Volunteer fire department</header><text>The term <quote>volunteer fire department</quote> means a fire department that has an all-volunteer force of firefighting personnel.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

