<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HDA68110B5695438EAAFEFC7972109F02" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>89 HR 1752 RH: Eliminating Barriers to Rural Internet Development Grant Eligibility Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 187</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1752</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–229, Part I]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000546">Mr. Graves of Missouri</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HPW00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name> and <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget </committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on March 23, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 to provide for a high-speed broadband deployment initiative.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HPW00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H555B2EFB6CE24CACA7CD36B930776395"><section id="H83935346B28B44BBA60637EAC15D9D7F"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Eliminating Barriers to Rural Internet Development Grant Eligibility Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>E-BRIDGE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFBF5172452B540ADA23AEF3461D47761"><enum>2.</enum><header>High-speed broadband deployment initiative</header><subsection id="H2B4BFFFC8D604774B60BFC5DD998446B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title II of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3141">42 U.S.C. 3141 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HC467024FB9AB4736B7F4F569EF0A88A1" style="OLC" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HPW00"><section id="H143318DA83674163ADD179347F8CD287"><enum>219.</enum><header>High-speed broadband deployment initiative</header><subsection id="HDBF9791FF6DB4F38AF21A56072C9A1EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA51FDF473DC647E5AC6BA5AAEEDAD78E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Broadband project</header><text>The term <quote>broadband project</quote> means, for the purpose of providing, extending, expanding, or improving high-speed broadband service to further the goals of this Act—</text><subparagraph id="H35487A49C4B54770A1476B0CB44BDB97"><enum>(A)</enum><text>planning, technical assistance, or training;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EEC4A78254D491BB91BB11A526A147F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the acquisition or development of land; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83379FF4FBE841A7975A1884BD7A2246"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the acquisition, design and engineering, construction, rehabilitation, alteration, expansion, or improvement of facilities, including related machinery, equipment, contractual rights, and intangible property.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H25EC2CFBDB7243EEADAA7555C3349B77"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible recipient</header><subparagraph id="H485B5F68E5F84B14B0B35C08131BAE1F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>eligible recipient</quote> means an eligible recipient.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDCEB49481ED4740951DA526AC97B953"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>The term <quote>eligible recipient</quote> includes—</text><clause id="H7D4CEE683F9D474088090153EFB493BA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a public-private partnership; and</text></clause><clause id="HE9400508F6284231AC20A248E80BE1EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a consortium formed for the purpose of providing, extending, expanding, or improving high-speed broadband service between 1 or more eligible recipients and 1 or more for-profit organizations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H549F8571A6364E17A95E92B0024FEDB5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>High-speed broadband</header><text>The term <quote>high-speed broadband</quote> means the provision of 2-way data transmission with sufficient downstream and upstream speeds to end users to permit effective participation in the economy and to support economic growth, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H09BBB057F822469FBA157650B0DB2C26"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Broadband projects</header><paragraph id="H4F8923849A0A418B802CD531AF8AD5FE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On the application of an eligible recipient, the Secretary may make grants under this title for broadband projects, which shall be subject to the provisions of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F5CD6B3BD4E4DD2A2313DC21E9DE722"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In reviewing applications submitted under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall take into consideration geographic diversity of grants allocated, including consideration of underserved markets, in addition to data requested in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H508E46A6C157499990C4F91CD5AB7FD8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Data requested</header><text>In reviewing an application submitted under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall request from the Federal Communications Commission, the Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration, the Secretary of Agriculture, and the Appalachian Regional Commission data on—</text><subparagraph id="H09E56D3DA05B49F5A7AA10D2274A9089"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the level and extent of broadband service that exists in the area proposed to be served; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EE43DF4B45B492BBB11AA0FCEE00BDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the level and extent of broadband service that will be deployed in the area proposed to be served pursuant to another Federal program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H234E5651ABFE4B5FAE133711A497EDDB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Interest in real or personal property</header><text>For any broadband project carried out by an eligible recipient that is a public-private partnership or consortium, the Secretary shall require that title to any real or personal property acquired or improved with grant funds, or if the recipient will not acquire title, another possessory interest acceptable to the Secretary, be vested in a public partner or eligible nonprofit organization or association for the useful life of the project, after which title may be transferred to any member of the public-private partnership or consortium in accordance with regulations promulgated by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3840FEC9ECB747A28E87994DB79D5A61"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Procurement</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no person or entity shall be disqualified from competing to provide goods or services related to a broadband project on the basis that the person or entity participated in the development of the broadband project or in the drafting of specifications, requirements, statements of work, or similar documents related to the goods or services to be provided.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9174347E814A4E28B4315F203D9C61CD"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Broadband project property</header><subparagraph id="HC2DA8F8E4E054BFC9A8991E9F23D5235"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may permit a recipient of a grant for a broadband project to grant an option to acquire real or personal property (including contractual rights and intangible property) related to that project to a third party on such terms as the Secretary determines to be appropriate, subject to the condition that the option may only be exercised after the Secretary releases the Federal interest in the property.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H923E0DA07D4242DDBAB22BD23BE47124"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment</header><text>The grant or exercise of an option described in subparagraph (A) shall not constitute a redistribution of grant funds under section 217.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H12476AF7FE8641FA9626142D1F20849D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Non-federal share</header><text>In determining the amount of the non-Federal share of the cost of a broadband project, the Secretary may provide credit toward the non-Federal share for the present value of allowable contributions over the useful life of the broadband project, subject to the condition that the Secretary may require such assurances of the value of the rights and of the commitment of the rights as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HFC5D9F5A033C4779B7884B6DF3E3470D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3121">42 U.S.C. 3121</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/89/136">Public Law 89–136</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 218 the following:</text><quoted-block id="H82AE7E257133467080EF448021A3798D" style="OLC" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HPW00"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HPW00"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 219. High-speed broadband deployment initiative.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H50B796B9788A43EE8B797DEB9ED61704"><enum>3.</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by this Act shall only apply to amounts appropriated on or after the date of enactment of this Act. </text></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HPW00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name> and <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget </committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

