<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEBFFBA3F583C4CDE82ACBD8D38742E58" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6626 IH: Saudi Arabia December 6, 2019, Anti-Terror and Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6626</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231206">December 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To take certain actions with respect to Saudi Arabia in response to the shootings that occurred at Naval Air Station Pensacola in Florida on December 6, 2019.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3B7EA978EE974573AB645312D7DA1BB0" style="OLC"><section id="HA614C0BD29774FB09618162228C94B7E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Saudi Arabia December 6, 2019, Anti-Terror and Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBD381ACF3F8A4B5281550418A05F39A6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H86AFD8A0692441BDB5662684769E59BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Trust between the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and the United States has been eroded by the devastating humanitarian costs of the war in Yemen, the kidnappings and shakedowns of royals and other businessmen in the Riyadh Ritz-Carlton, the murder of journalist Jamal Khashoggi, and the torture of women activists seeking equal rights.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6DCE6DD98F943CC8EA60C59B85C0F42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Fifteen of the September 11, 2001, attackers were Saudi citizens, nationals, or of Saudi descent and some of these individuals had direct assistance from the Saudi Government for training, logistical support, and radicalization.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A63B9027E32495ABC2482F9ECA25776"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Mohammed Alshamrani, a 21-year-old second lieutenant in the Royal Saudi Air Force who was radicalized by al-Qa`ida in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP) and Osama bin Laden’s teachings of Wahhabiism, fatally shot Cameron Walters, 21, Mohammed Sameh Haitham, 19, Joshua Kaleb Watson, 23, and wounded eight others, including two sheriff’s deputies, at Naval Air Station Pensacola in Florida on December 6, 2019, in an act of unprovoked and cowardly terror.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE3B3D2F880E45B38589AB6AB399B7EB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Al-Shamrani was a Trojan Horse sent by his country, Saudi Arabia, and the Saudi authorities were negligent in properly screening Al-Shamrani.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB037A5D479DC4F1485733A51B8C65161"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Saudi Government had an obligation to report Al-Shamrani’s anti-American social media posts prior to his enrollment in a joint military training program at Naval Air Station Pensacola.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91CDDEF5475841D6B9D1E240C800D55D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Saudi Government was derelict in monitoring and reporting Al-Shamrani’s radicalization, and on failed in their promise to compensate the victims of Al-Shamrani’s terrorist attack.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD6721C3BF66040D78DD873B6B2AE7A95"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibitions on assistance to Saudi Arabia</header><subsection id="H88B5826983B349158B1C0FA63DE35063"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>None of the funds available to the Department of Defense or any other Federal agency may be used to—</text><paragraph id="H408AE54FF796486FAE8A2DACBB48985C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support the Saudi-led coalition in Yemen or any other Saudi-led proxy wars; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1C6ACC5E8554948AFB827CEC9109B78"><enum>(2)</enum><text>carry out any military officer exchange programs with Saudi Arabia.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10EA0D02CF1E4E09A10316085EFA53FD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Export controls</header><text>Notwithstanding the Export Control Reform Act of 2018, the President shall prohibit the export of munitions containers, weapon support, support equipment, spare and repair parts, technical and logistical support services, and related elements of logistical and program support to Saudi Arabia.</text></subsection></section><section id="H44375DEE10F74129AD0BDE1387A39F9B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Compensation for victims</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 404(c) of the Justice for United States Victims of State Sponsored Terrorism Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20144">34 U.S.C. 20144</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC3219E00A7B04DFA80A72B86F892D312"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><subparagraph id="HADB5AA0F588945F49F9A9D052B63C4A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end and inserting;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD4CCE61B66B4393B8B2B4EC4CA062B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4F615C83B364C07A2E3B9BCD465F244"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end, the following:</text><quoted-block id="HEF5C9B696CA246808553F6CDDA90D7FE" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H9BEA718250194A3B97B33B16B0FB7C8C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>$10,000,000 for a victim as defined under 40 CFR § 170.305 (or an immediate family member of a victim if the victim is deceased, whether or not as direct result of the shooting) of the shooting by Mohammed Alshamrani at Naval Air Station Pensacola in Florida on December 6, 2019.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H880F211C526A4622AE713631FC2D2C6F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(A), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H2465109222BA488EBEC15D24E741A79B" style="OLC"><clause id="HBACB261F978B4C74BC0AAE36232D69B7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of the Saudi Arabia December 6, 2019, Anti-Terror and Accountability Act, for a claim described in paragraph (2)(D).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H2F41A7F9A7D34938A0EF9D8B087EE597"><enum>5.</enum><header>Funding for compensation for victims</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 404(e)(5) of the Justice for United States Victims of State Sponsored Terrorism Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20144">34 U.S.C. 20144(e)(5)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HBAD5302295024B8BB7473FC956F0D1B2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Fund</quote> and inserting <quote>Fund—</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05578F08844142FA9794D4E46BD198F3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>out of any</quote> and inserting <quote>(A) out of any</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5FE6DBF770944B6BC3A4ED52C9B5820"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end, the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block id="H3F4F222280744482AF159875CC12F4F8" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H231EBC51E84B487AA5ECF1271C5EC180"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$1,000,000,000 to be derived from unobligated balances of amounts appropriated for security assistance for Ukraine in fiscal year 2024 and to remain available until expended to carry out subsection (c)(2)(D) and for other purposes of the fund. Any unused funds are made available to all victim eligible for damages under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20144">34 U.S.C. 20144</external-xref>.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

