<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2AA730C1E2C34A748B938670E5DBBEA1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1183 IH: Asylum Reform and Border Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1183</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To modify the treatment of unaccompanied alien children who are in Federal custody by reason of their immigration status, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H57DD2DED5ED348D888806C56ADEB6B08" style="OLC"> 
<section commented="no" id="HF8B1AA28A9EC4DA292630D8CEFD1613C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Asylum Reform and Border Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAA76007880E44C9EACDEAB978886DC23"><enum>2.</enum><header>Clarification of intent regarding taxpayer-provided counsel</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 292 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1362">8 U.S.C. 1362</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD4685D406F8549229EDFF845EA3E4B3A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>In any removal proceedings before an immigration judge and in any appeal proceedings before the Attorney General from any such removal proceedings</quote> and inserting <quote>In any removal proceedings before an immigration judge, or any other immigration proceedings before the Attorney General, the Secretary of Homeland Security, or any appeal of such a proceeding</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB18157E7FE0348C18CAC51D661E5AD28"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(at no expense to the Government)</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8ECBE7D4505F453098FDB6BAEC24F8F0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H891A8618CBE94EAD9BA944C23B175DAF" style="OLC"> <quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="section">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, in no instance shall the Government bear any expense for counsel for any person in proceedings described in this section.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HE39359F637914C0B8949F283A8B9CE65"><enum>3.</enum><header>Credible fear interviews</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 235(b)(1)(B)(v) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)(B)(v)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>claim</quote> and all that follows and inserting <quote>claim, as determined pursuant to section 208(b)(1)(B)(iii) and such other facts as are known to the officer, that the alien could establish eligibility for asylum under section 208, and it is more probable than not that the statements made by, and on behalf of, the alien in support of the alien’s claim are true.</quote>.</text></section>
<section id="HE31FCAE780C845CF848BACE29392457C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Recording expedited removal and credible fear interviews</header>
<subsection id="H7C2B5E49BA854FA5AC0253DFE715EE61"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall establish quality assurance procedures and take steps to effectively ensure that questions by employees of the Department of Homeland Security exercising expedited removal authority under section 235(b) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)</external-xref>) are asked in a uniform manner, to the extent possible, and that both these questions and the answers provided in response to them are recorded in a uniform fashion.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H06F358D4697948E992887848E867F467"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Factors relating to sworn statements</header><text>Where practicable, any sworn or signed written statement taken of an alien as part of the record of a proceeding under section 235(b)(1)(A) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)(A)</external-xref>) shall be accompanied by a recording of the interview which served as the basis for that sworn statement.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H32D22E77FBB9426E88BD15F3D6456E62"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Interpreters</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that a competent interpreter, not affiliated with the government of the country from which the alien may claim asylum, is used when the interviewing officer does not speak a language understood by the alien.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6520CF86F4AD4786B5BC891B84BBD32C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Recordings in immigration proceedings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be an audio or audio visual recording of interviews of aliens subject to expedited removal. The recording shall be included in the record of proceeding and shall be considered as evidence in any further proceedings involving the alien.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HFEC7966114E24ACDA4ED5CE468F3B7A8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>No private right of action</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to create any right, benefit, trust, or responsibility, whether substantive or procedural, enforceable in law or equity by a party against the United States, its departments, agencies, instrumentalities, entities, officers, employees, or agents, or any person, nor does this section create any right of review in any administrative, judicial, or other proceeding.</text></subsection></section> <section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC937CBE29C7D405FBC2CA3A450174A4C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header>Parole reform</header> <subsection id="H41CDFD6BFDD14C758A12144F34CF9E73"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (5) of section 212(d) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(d)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block id="H455ED2A97E0A4C8080550B71714B715E" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="H34B05F49984F43AA933E427D5C418880"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Humanitarian and significant public interest parole</header>
<subparagraph id="H47E15F8E26244F3FAE7160AC0FA1EBD1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the provisions of this paragraph and section 214(f)(2), the Secretary of Homeland Security, in the sole discretion of the Secretary of Homeland Security, may on an individual case-by-case basis, and not according to eligibility criteria describing an entire class of potential parole recipients, parole an alien into the United States temporarily, under such conditions as the Secretary of Homeland Security may prescribe, only—</text> <clause id="HBFBC8E13FDFC452580D95239B2E13C0D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an alien not present in the United States for an urgent humanitarian reason (as described under subparagraph (B));</text></clause>
<clause id="HC9FD62B7ABE14097828849559A8AA954"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an alien not present in the United States for a reason deemed strictly in the significant public interest (as described under subparagraph (C)); or</text></clause> <clause id="H0BC072E5BAD944B0A2DEB49B733B3DA5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an alien who—</text>
<subclause id="H0E2B40358A204025BE4F922E64511D5D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is present in the United States without lawful immigration status;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE081CE7E93B24C9A859E8D3572A1DCCD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is the beneficiary of a pending or approved petition under section 203(a);</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H1C1E8A29D80B48B5B05C76DA0B991D4B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>is not otherwise inadmissible or deportable; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H95DF4D275CBF4591A9B7328D92D9E04E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>is the spouse or minor child of a member of the Armed Forces serving on active duty at the request of the member of the Armed Forces.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H296C12491FC8452B9B4057F9F31A0367"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Humanitarian parole</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may parole an alien based on an urgent humanitarian reason described in this subparagraph only if—</text> <clause id="HCEC1DAEB6E2942A4936B571E67782283"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the alien has a medical emergency and the alien cannot obtain necessary treatment in the foreign state in which the alien is residing or the medical emergency is life-threatening and there is insufficient time for the alien to be admitted through the normal visa process;</text></clause>
<clause id="H69917422228841499DFE4055E88D29C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the alien is the parent or legal guardian of an alien described in clause (i), if the alien described in clause (i) is a minor;</text></clause> <clause id="HE2E15B428EC34B4D9F2C376246A60300"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien is needed in the United States in order to donate an organ or other tissue for transplant into a close family member and there is insufficient time for the alien to be admitted through the normal visa process;</text></clause>
<clause id="HBFEDA1BEF705454D95798D031D0C578D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the alien has a close family member in the United States whose death is imminent and the alien could not arrive in the United States in time to see such family member alive if the alien were to be admitted through the normal visa process;</text></clause> <clause id="H8BE184C9D7BA41678DA7357DFFFD4565"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien is an adopted child with an urgent medical condition, who is in the legal custody of the petitioner for a final adoption-related visa, and whose medical treatment is required prior to the expected award of a final adoption-related visa;</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H183F38F585514E91B9E612087C3D0794"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the alien is a lawful applicant for adjustment of status under section 245; or</text></clause> <clause id="H459D773B8E3B4F3E88FD6A1C9AB032D8"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the alien was—</text>
<subclause id="H2E459D93D9F94222BDADD4B3EF128A95"><enum>(I)</enum><text>lawfully granted status under section 208;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H366A29C290034CCCB0803494E2F1D520"><enum>(II)</enum><text>lawfully admitted under section 207; or</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HD0283507FBC546158D9AFA1268A4B071"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">granted withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE927843A949A43CB8D47746637188709"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Significant public interest parole</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security may parole an alien based on a reason deemed strictly in the significant public interest described in this subparagraph only if the alien has assisted (or will assist, whether knowingly or not) the United States Government in a matter, such as a criminal investigation, espionage, or other similar law enforcement activity, including a civil litigation matter requiring the alien’s presence, and either the alien’s presence in the United States is required by the Government or the alien’s life would be threatened if the alien were not permitted to come to the United States. Only a matter described in this subparagraph shall qualify for purposes of this subparagraph, and no other matter may qualify.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4FE505B302E64A65836607D4E7102B65"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Limitation on the use of parole authority</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not use the parole authority under this paragraph—</text> <clause id="HFB160F01AE5241DBAFEDF01B86579FEC"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to circumvent immigration policy established by law to admit classes of aliens who do not qualify for admission; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HA6457EC6FF1149EF8A35B4AB10A7ED03"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to supplement established immigration categories without congressional approval.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD65903195CCE4D488DE4E2F77C3AA686"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Parole not an admission</header><text>Parole of an alien under this paragraph shall not be considered an admission of the alien into the United States. When the purposes of the parole of an alien have been served, as determined by the Secretary of Homeland Security, the alien shall immediately return or be returned to the custody from which the alien was paroled and the alien shall be considered for admission to the United States on the same basis as other similarly situated applicants for admission.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB342978C23B74A4A96B54DE94F0D94E0"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the end of each fiscal year, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit a report to the Committees on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Senate describing the number and categories of aliens paroled into the United States under this paragraph. Each such report shall contain information and data concerning the number and categories of aliens paroled, the duration of parole, and the current status of aliens paroled during the preceding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H3BCA691B161E4598A17F262916680DF6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the first day of the first month beginning more than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H0F2A4CA87B0B4923BC985017272CBC08"><enum>6.</enum><header>Modifications to preferential availability for asylum for unaccompanied alien minors</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 208(a)(2) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking subparagraph (E).</text></section> <section id="HDDD2846CC77D4548A3AA86B283A97F7A"><enum>7.</enum><header>Safe third country</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 208(a)(2)(A) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(a)(2)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD41CADD2C0874475ADC93CA8EBD9ED52"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Attorney General</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9EC7E6D815B24B71A9BC07C1C0BE4BB8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>removed, pursuant to a bilateral or multilateral agreement, to</quote> and inserting <quote>removed to</quote>.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H42F07D2A24D248FF9F671320D84E226E"><enum>8.</enum><header>Withholding of removal</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 241(b)(3) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1231">8 U.S.C. 1231(b)(3)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H702F73BBA2BF4C08ADAFDBD0BCBFEE14"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end of subparagraph (A) the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1EB22FCE0BAB447FA07227702610A7E3" style="OLC">
<quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subparagraph">The burden of proof shall be on the alien to establish that the alien's life or freedom would be threatened in that country, and that race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group, or political opinion would be at least one central reason for such threat.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAD6024AB702549F293215702ED3325D5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>In determining whether an alien has demonstrated that the alien's life or freedom would be threatened for a reason described in subparagraph (A),</quote> and inserting <quote>For purposes of this paragraph,</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> <section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B3C585EED4C40659D2B1F38F186CBA1" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>9.</enum><header>Firm resettlement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 208(b)(2)(A)(vi) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(b)(2)(A)(vi)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>States.</quote> and inserting <quote>States, which shall be considered demonstrated by evidence that the alien can live in such country (in any legal status) without fear of persecution.</quote>.</text></section>
<section id="H9B890CC9E44D496AAE6FE7E65B019B25"><enum>10.</enum><header>Termination of Asylum Status Pursuant to Return to Home Country</header>
<subsection id="HE4FF5F850FD140DE9847CA9D05C451F2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 208(c) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F5C1F6AA6C641C5881F6E7FC7AA4F49" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HCBA538B6CA7A453B985849CAB73E325A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Termination of status pursuant to return to home country</header> <subparagraph id="H7395ADF8A82544439DF945C29D3B4F79"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraphs (B) and (C), any alien who is granted asylum status under this Act, who, absent changed country conditions, subsequently returns to the country of such alien’s nationality or, in the case of an alien having no nationality, returns to any country in which such alien last habitually resided, and who applied for such status because of persecution or a well-founded fear of persecution in that country on account of race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group, or political opinion, shall have his or her status terminated.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBF5C789E6A1B43278510944C5A392078"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The Secretary has discretion to waive subparagraph (A) if it is established to the satisfaction of the Secretary that the alien had a compelling reason for the return. The waiver shall be sought prior to departure from the United States or upon return.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HE561A2A78D04401BA18C6AD768D5E11A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 208(c)(3) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(c)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after <quote>paragraph (2)</quote> the following: <quote>or (4)</quote>.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H820CF8D5FC194D72B8FB11A086CAB295"><enum>11.</enum><header>Notice concerning frivolous asylum applications</header>
<subsection id="H32E7CC84D3354D87A782B7C1064D1189"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 208(d)(4) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(d)(4)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8BA9AB0EC8CA41E09D528312C4CDAB22"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>the Secretary of Homeland Security or</quote> before <quote>the Attorney General</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFBE136F598104C0DBCF6A761205418FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>and of the consequences, under paragraph (6), of knowingly filing a frivolous application for asylum</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5C996C083EA6478CB56ABD130899B992"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCD6239B69BE2417B91374B0A364A91B2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HF61E44D5AEAF45ABAA7430C3942425EE" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H1F0A7EE3B7434E68B21CE09FC6149ACF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensure that a written warning appears on the asylum application advising the alien of the consequences of filing a frivolous application.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEA94A11DFE4946EEB0A916C6BB27F22B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4589971CFD0A47C9A6AD34918A5E8BAA" style="OLC"> <quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="paragraph">The written warning referred to in subparagraph (C) shall serve as notice to the alien of the consequences of filing a frivolous application.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H01AEFCEEDF6049AABDC418CE901E5FD7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 208(d)(6) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(d)(6)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H853434699BB846A1933E428746D81BB4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>If the Attorney General</quote> and inserting <quote>(A) <header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">In general.—</header-in-text>If the Department of Homeland Security or the Attorney General</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H89E16296FA3443949FED90A287441A17"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>paragraph (4)(A)</quote> in subparagraph (A) (as designated in paragraph (1) of this subsection) and inserting <quote>paragraph (4)(C)</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE97C3ECF7E23493CA13789FDCD02BD8C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H18ABB17B2E7240CBB02A93095C69A9AA" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H53C258C02FD24650AE0298693127D7CC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>An application may be found <quote>frivolous</quote> if it is determined—</text>
<clause id="H8ED40242026E497D9275D2C0D26976A5"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to be totally insufficient in substance such that it is clear that the applicant knowingly filed the application without intending to pursue the merits of his or her asylum claim solely—</text> <subclause id="H1D477418BA7E4EBDAC0C95AEEB75D99D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to delay removal from the United States;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H3B75C8952BC44B11AA3AF673541A7928"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to seek employment authorization as an applicant for asylum pursuant to regulations issued pursuant to paragraph (2); or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H09EDCCB30E8949A39AB0C88934A4B267"><enum>(III)</enum><text>for applicants whom have not yet had removal proceedings initiated against them under section 239, to seek issuance of a notice to appear in order to pursue cancellation of removal under section 240A(b); or</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H176ACB00934F4B6BB3A9AAC7E15F56B6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that any of its material elements is deliberately fabricated.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2240938743CF4BF0B36548D4FF8AEF09"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitation on determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A determination under subparagraph (B) shall only be made if the decision maker is satisfied that the applicant, during the course of the proceedings, has had sufficient opportunity to account for any discrepancies or implausible aspects of the claim. For purposes of this section, a finding that an alien filed a frivolous asylum application shall not preclude the alien from seeking withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" id="HE816AFA35A1343F5B1DB58B2D360523E"><enum>12.</enum><header>Termination of Asylum Status in Removal Proceedings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 208(c) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(c)</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended—</text> <paragraph id="HEBA8B1F27FBA41C29F12E2D58C2E1C03"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA8038DEC1D8C436889E9F65FCCE301D6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>the Secretary of Homeland Security or</quote> before <quote>the Attorney General</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBEEF152F55F84682AA39B3F4AA919369"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>, pursuant to a bilateral or multilateral agreement,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAD02D37E7D0C418183FEDCF3EF3FEE11"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD539AFAF484743909AC9CD5228702137" style="OLC"> <paragraph commented="no" id="HC7A3F461410449B29DD8AA6BDBA10BB4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Timing for Consideration of Termination of Asylum Status in Removal Proceedings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an alien's asylum status is subject to termination under paragraph (2) or (4), the immigration judge shall first determine whether the conditions specified under that paragraph have been met, and if so, terminate the alien’s asylum status before considering whether the alien is eligible for adjustment of status under section 209.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
<section commented="no" id="HAD676402F17949F890CA07D7869C9E6D"><enum>13.</enum><header>Limitation on Eligibility for Asylum Based on Generalized Violence</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 208(b)(2)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(b)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H51311D4EAE5F426FB6264203B8AE6A57" style="OLC"> <clause commented="no" id="H8048A5E67A2D4A07B3C1F06631FCFB1C"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Limitation on Eligibility Based on Generalized Violence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An alien is not eligible for asylum under this section, or withholding of removal under section 241, based on any of the following circumstances:</text>
<subclause commented="no" id="H333F12A6370A4382B7E46A2979379CB6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Being, or having been, a member of a criminal gang.</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="H918AF27FDFA045C98845F71178031611"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Participating, or having participated, in the activities of a criminal gang.</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" id="H96951A3807B042C6969EB2A394CC720E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Having been recruited into, or having a fear of being recruited into, membership of, or the activities of, a criminal gang.</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="HFD36F14FAFBD41DDBE32CB70C3B2253E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Having been, or having a fear of being, the victim of a crime committed by a member of a criminal gang, or otherwise having been, or having a fear of being, the victim of a crime in the alien’s home country, unless the main motivating factor for the commission of the crime, or the fear of being the victim of a crime, is related to the alien’s race, religion, national origin, or political opinion.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H38FEFB49E1C840D7BB40836C97107ECD"><enum>14.</enum><header>Membership in a particular social group defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H97F65FA5A0F0404AB86A4E7948FFE5F6" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HAB24367F3C16411D85EFADDC5216EAC0"><enum>(53)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>membership in a particular social group</term> means membership in a group that is—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCC12DFA952E84A5AB08719B79D01CE02"><enum>(A)</enum><text>composed of members who share a common immutable characteristic;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H748F641C06AE4C92AE239D308C509482"><enum>(B)</enum><text>defined with particularity; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4C65E410DA8F4442B00E6DDC7B12666F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>socially distinct within the society in question.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H56C3F5D9986540EDA8055FD7DBBCF6AD"><enum>15.</enum><header>Anti-fraud investigative work product</header> <subsection id="H0575E905B23B450C960176D8E63A8C4F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Asylum credibility determinations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 208(b)(1)(B)(iii) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(b)(1)(B)(iii)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after <quote>all relevant factors</quote> the following: <quote>, including statements made to, and investigative reports prepared by, immigration authorities and other government officials</quote>.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HF13D8A617B90439AA0E23BAEB5E93C8D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Relief for removal credibility determinations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 240(c)(4)(C) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a(c)(4)(C)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after <quote>all relevant factors</quote> the following: <quote>, including statements made to, and investigative reports prepared by, immigration authorities and other government officials</quote>.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H4DE68030D29940FBB1F0FEA0CE0DB67E"><enum>16.</enum><header>Clarification for conduct of rogue foreign officials</header> <subsection id="H2F3FC9B9C50B481BA18FC3341DFA7122"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Asylum applications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 208(b)(2)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(b)(2)(B)</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB619B73B082A4495BB992EE9461DCF12" style="OLC">
<clause id="H235007E23ACD41AB8E1074FFCFD0548C"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Rogue foreign government officials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The burden of proof under paragraph (1)(B) may not be established based on the conduct of rogue foreign government officials acting outside the scope of their official capacity.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H93898DB039644BDC8C9404D6C2CF18D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Countries to which an alien may be removed</header><text>Section 241(b)(3) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1231">8 U.S.C. 1231(b)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8C126881D15A40E9AF08B88ACC46A279" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="HDE4B1CE076F04D4FBC9CAAD44EEF7D66"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The burden of proof for relief under this paragraph may not be established based on the conduct of rogue foreign government officials acting outside the scope of their official capacity.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H3E61BFB4551E44669784F7CF87A28146"><enum>17.</enum><header>Technical amendments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 208 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H342CA76E6BAB4F699F3CB32A256F6A52"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HC9D3E3AEAF894E72AD6F04F4D0D77B5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(D), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4B52E792FB454027BD882811A1125DB9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H86BFFBB344274029B9C7C1FB1002C9BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(2), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote> each place such term appears;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H95D820DD10694F89B45F5FD582C73D6D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c)—</text> <subparagraph id="HFA39F4616B2348B9914D0137D5E4E8FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>Attorney General</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1DE0A4AFC5C04D62B82EF3ED70E59661"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE983EDB0CEA4444080DBC90744F1E441"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4ECA9B2AC06145129A8D248B9C3A12C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote> each place such term appears;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42195A33EE9C4A8B9417A27E2A0B8847"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>Attorney General</quote> and inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security</quote>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3416144DA0504071B553EEC8C8166448"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote> each place such term appears;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H97DB136A072E4C20869D51736295AD43"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)—</text>
<clause id="HE0CE45832C664C5799B3584F9AAF0859"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="HD89C782D92F641108C3C83D828B3D102"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF306C2D587A74BB9A06AF0AB622A6935"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (6), by inserting <quote>Secretary of Homeland Security or the</quote> before <quote>Attorney General</quote> each place such term appears.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

