<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFEFE636EEB114BD68D4F5478C20BBCA0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1158 IH: Elimination of Future Technology Delays Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1158</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Toxic Substances Control Act with respect to new critical energy resources, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC8813D2AEAEC47DCAB2EF2CCD1E4D79A" style="OLC"><section id="H4F66AE1FD6F34D469AFE45A700EDB0AC" commented="no" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Elimination of Future Technology Delays Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H964B5D2C28F942E3AD75CC8D0FAC342F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Chemical substance review for critical energy resources</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5(a) of the Toxic Substances Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/2604">15 U.S.C. 2604(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9271E42D99C643BBBC6288618A8F5F39" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H82A68E20C2DB4CEFBF6E6734360C29BD" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Critical energy resources</header><subparagraph id="HCDCC179C1E3F4E79BA98C79EECF2FFFC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Standard</header><text>For purposes of a determination under paragraph (3) with respect to a chemical substance that is a critical energy resource, the Administrator shall take into consideration economic, societal, and environmental costs and benefits, notwithstanding any requirement of this section to not take such factors into consideration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E2DAB150BB24BE8AF33D1173AFE9711" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Failure to render determination</header><clause id="HE609B9831FBA4E899E0FAB8DDF901730"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Actions authorized</header><text>If, with respect to a chemical substance that is a critical energy resource, the Administrator fails to make a determination on a notice under paragraph (3) by the end of the applicable review period and the notice has not been withdrawn by the submitter, the submitter may take the actions described in paragraph (1)(A) with respect to the chemical substance, and the Administrator shall be relieved of any requirement to make such determination.</text></clause><clause id="H6BB0A20EDF0D480BA4B9DC56D0BB8320"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Non-duplication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A refund of applicable fees under paragraph (4)(A) shall not be made if a submitter takes an action described in paragraph (1)(A) under this subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45BF1CD7008842B886942FE4BE151154" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Prerequisite for suggestion of withdrawal or suspension</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may not suggest to, or request of, a submitter of a notice under this subsection for a chemical substance that is a critical energy resource that such submitter withdraw such notice, or request a suspension of the running of the applicable review period with respect to such notice, unless the Administrator has—</text><clause id="HDB971B2196074E8288206F4CF4EBF9FD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>conducted a preliminary review of such notice; and</text></clause><clause id="H9E5FFFD271BD4F6FBD319BAD7E50AB1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provided to the submitter a draft of a determination under paragraph (3), including any supporting information.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H848405FA9E0D4EDE904B60AFA713F1E3" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>critical energy resource</term> means, as determined by the Secretary of Energy, any energy resource—</text><clause id="HD175A7A098E846B2B016BC3407BD58B8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is essential to the energy sector and energy systems of the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="H27A4CA40DA9D41C399D69026B29FA2E4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the supply chain of which is vulnerable to disruption.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

