<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5645270CBF704C70A2DB3AF312919F57" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1704 IH: Latin America and Caribbean Nearshoring Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1704</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230322">March 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To decrease dependency on People’s Republic of China manufacturing and decrease migration due to lost regional economic opportunities.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8BCF001559914CE0AE62CF4290DED585" style="OLC"><section id="H6D3D2ED5F4654AD693B945C432327951" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Latin America and Caribbean Nearshoring Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD21CFDC78AB84B25A044D5EC51D60631"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress; statement of policy</header><subsection id="HFEFBAC3A93DF4F6EB1128CA32F3DD97E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States has economic and national security interests in securing the critical mineral and energy supply chains of Latin American and Caribbean countries from control and influence by the People’s Republic of China.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4E4EA2A70E5243B6ABB6A048E9377C6A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text>It is the policy of the United States to—</text><paragraph id="HD98A56D9007E4A568AE43CC269A4443D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advance United States foreign policy and development goals by assisting Latin American and Caribbean countries to reduce their dependence on critical mineral and energy supply chains controlled or influenced by the People’s Republic of China;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A15DAE2A49E41D8AE285060CDF74581"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote private sector-led long-term economic development, economic competitiveness and promoting good governance, human rights, and the rule of law in Latin American and Caribbean countries, particularly in the areas of investment, sustainable development, commercial relations, anti-corruption activities, and infrastructure projects;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6299AB124DE04C12A2DEC8EBD3893A61"><enum>(3)</enum><text>encourage United States public and private sector investment in energy infrastructure projects of such countries to bridge the gap between energy security requirements and commercial demand in a way that is consistent with the region’s absorptive capacity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2A4A871B93342A79818949936931E25"><enum>(4)</enum><text>encourage United States public and private sector investment in critical mineral mining and refining of such countries; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48C94EE46B53407DBCF304D2EAC94378"><enum>(5)</enum><text>help facilitate the export of United States energy technology and expertise to global markets.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB81C1AAE798E44AFA7683437BB09FB72"><enum>3.</enum><header>Efforts of the Department of State and related agencies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of State, in coordination with the heads of United States agencies that operate under the foreign policy guidance of the Secretary of State, shall, as appropriate, prioritize and expedite the efforts of the Department of State and such agencies—</text><paragraph id="H4C74150FC34A4074A9195A3E64A39B80"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to support efforts of Latin American and Caribbean countries to secure their critical mineral and energy supply chains from control and influence by the People’s Republic of China; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF088FAD3CBCC446F9F4401CE35C20ED8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to otherwise carry out the policy described in section 2(b).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H9298873F50BB43B684619EB8E4AB2F83" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Assistance from the United States International Development Finance Corporation</header><subsection id="H286FE47B94D3428A903A6F51B75BA1BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States International Development Finance Corporation, in coordination with the Federal agencies and officials described in subsection (b), shall provide assistance under section 1421 of the Better Utilization of Investments Leading to Development Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9621">22 U.S.C. 9621</external-xref>) for each fiscal year beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act—</text><paragraph id="HD75E7B8AA54441E5B50C5C13FF4840C6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to support efforts of Latin American and Caribbean countries to secure their critical mineral and energy supply chains from control and influence by the People’s Republic of China; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F4F924E9B754E08A6CB410410676FFD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to otherwise carry out the policy described in section 2(b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H20588010D00F47A39CDF52D7AE1D3EFC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal agencies and officials described</header><text>The Federal agencies and officials described in this subsection include—</text><paragraph id="H88F820D1630D48B680BBAC904CE5278C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States Trade and Development Agency, the Export-Import Bank of the United States, the Millenium Challenge Corporation, the United States Army Corps of Engineers, and the United States Agency for International Development; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB07C58579A074A71A2C274A5394608B5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States Executive Directors of relevant international financial institutions, including the World Bank Group, the Inter-American Development Bank, and the International Monetary Fund.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H28D0ACD8CE384701B58D2CFB77E3E3EA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>In providing assistance described in subsection (a)—</text><paragraph id="H73EF526CA98E4FB0956362F5DF532F88"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States International Development Finance Corporation may provide support for projects in Latin American and Caribbean countries with upper-middle-income economies or high-income economies (as those terms are defined by the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development Association (collectively referred to as the <quote>World Bank</quote>)); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB646B22EE71C42509C6DC65D5315AB4E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the restriction under section 1412(c)(2) of the Better Utilization of Investments Leading to Development Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9612">22 U.S.C. 9612(c)(2)</external-xref>) shall not apply.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA4996773DB26400988BE14534A3D974C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the United States International Development Finance Corporation shall develop and submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a plan to streamline the provision of assistance described in subsection (a), including to expedite the approval process for the provision of such assistance.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD6F343649D0B48FBB5A9B70778BF7CF8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Agreements for cooperation pursuant to section 123 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954</header><subsection id="H5466DFD586E3488BB513E63556762138"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President is authorized to take action to initiate negotiations with any Latin American or Caribbean country to obtain an agreement for cooperation pursuant to section 123 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2153">42 U.S.C. 2153</external-xref>) to approve the sale of nuclear reactors to such country but only if—</text><paragraph id="HAC88BDDDB1324760827391A46A137C07"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the President determines that such sale will not threaten the national security of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C46BD8C2DCB42EB8A33F3BF007B4104"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the country meets the conditions described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9C94D6B788334A10AE36D57BD2AB1399"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical assistance and expertise</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in consultation with the Secretary of Energy and the United States International Development Finance Corporation, may provide technical assistance and expertise in electrical grid and energy efficiency improvements related to sales under subsection (a), as appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H60E7C7D790684A5A909F5E411F946ECE" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conditions described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The conditions described in this subsection are the following: </text><paragraph id="HB2FB0F9CE6F245D1944224D5816890F5" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The country is taking steps to reduce migration in violation of the Immigration and Nationality Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB91E3F2A33A347C69EE4B0AFFB850936" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The country is taking steps to reduce economic dependence on the People’s Republic of China. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A71FCC3A98348099A5B1D0209B4E79B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The country allows Taiwan to establish and maintain a commercial office in the country.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2CAF33EEFDA0400DA6DB2FD6EDF7C738" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Latin American or Caribbean country defined</header><subsection id="H16B2674C878B4E7FB3865D02DAE4C93D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act, the term <quote>Latin American or Caribbean country</quote>—</text><paragraph id="HD74C416EAD3148718F218FF8A632E493" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>means—</text><subparagraph id="H6A51EFC6086444D29652D469683E22FD" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a country in the Caribbean Sea, South America, or Central America; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1A2C0182D2143299A5F0B765A477D5F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Mexico; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C7DC2DC64FC46718D3C148AA8803A63" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>except as provided in subsection (b), does not include Cuba or Venezuela.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H54A94EF5448344609E10D457F88DEC94" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Latin American or Caribbean country</quote> shall include Cuba or Venezuela if the Secretary of State determines and certifies to Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H0BDE0E48EF9E43DC9A168EFA3E6506B4" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the government of such country—</text><subparagraph id="H31C41AB420C447C09EA4186564E9EBCC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has held free and fair presidential and legislative elections, as determined by independent international observers, and subsequent elections are scheduled;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C8BF55022E94ECAB9695EB2BD2C56DC" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>respects and upholds human rights;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71102097554B47438F2C2D8618D52BDC" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is taking significant steps to privatize its economy and institute a free market;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BB2900489324A04B46DED7A436F939A" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">permits the international community to provide humanitarian, governance, and economic development assistance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF1BB9B6DE1148CFBE6E44EF9398C085" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has freed all unlawfully detained United States citizens, legal permanent residents, and political prisoners; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59DCC4DB3BC847C887929235D9C55D6D" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>has expelled all security services from foreign adversaries from the country; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E2AB4E1C2924098ADD01CB79A0602D6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the prior authorities of such country have renounced their illegitimate claim to power.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

