<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3DD7DF329E5A41C2BEF3523AE6CB6C24" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3169 IH: Port Crane Security and Inspection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3169</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the inspection of certain foreign cranes before use at a United States port, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H933FA1B2C5474573BE461A50959782F4" style="OLC"><section id="H183239CF6311471AA5FCB203F03164A5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Port Crane Security and Inspection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB549B88A31734E64A1B89EBC38859F6A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Foreign crane inspection transportation and port security and maritime security enhancement</header><subsection id="H9779AF22F4FF41978C9A8788CC067A92"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to newly constructed foreign cranes procured for use at a United States port determined by the Secretary to be of high risk to port security or maritime transportation security and that connect to the internet, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall, acting through the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency, before such crane is placed into service at such port, inspect such crane for potential security risks or threats.</text></subsection><subsection id="H79A84FC95BBD4505A5E3E2A21833FED1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Security risks or threats assessments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H7E5E0DB16C654E65BD397551F5D72906"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assess the threat posed by security risks or threats of any existing or newly constructed foreign cranes in use at a United States port; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0AC8C58C5AF413CA3B2F78F5A2B7ADC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>take any crane that poses a security risk or threat offline until such crane can be certified as no longer being a risk or threat. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C02341586E946DFBA047EC07F9A6116"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall brief the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate regarding foreign crane security risks or threats posed by existing or newly constructed foreign cranes within United States ports.</text></subsection><subsection id="H66FEC398C65B4FF1AB89538652E222CF" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HC6F939A6D0E24ADFA164CC85A1F24D9A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered foreign country</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered foreign country</quote> means a country that—</text><subparagraph id="HFA52AA82E300481797E7A00A05C1C9F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the intelligence community has identified as a foreign adversary in its most recent Annual Threat Assessment; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52353D83E7924D78AF7BEA0D7B9543C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security, in coordination with the Director of National Intelligence, has identified as a foreign adversary that is not included in such Annual Threat Assessment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E2D49B3F4874A6F85FF03C51075AAAC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign crane</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>foreign crane</quote> means a crane for which any information technology and operational technology components in such crane that is connected into cyber infrastructure at a port located in the United States was, in whole or in part, manufactured by an entity that is operating under ownership, control, or influence of a covered foreign country. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1AB54EC176FC41659912200155334197" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>3.</enum><header>Foreign crane prohibition</header><subsection id="H29B4EA3D0546448B84EA8E31A37F97AC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a foreign crane—</text><paragraph id="H5038CA2ED4884D318F8B8538E21B466E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which a contract was entered into on or after the date of enactment of this Act may not be operated at a port located in the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D0A5B00FC7B4422ACE31D1524DF7EC3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">operated at a port located in the United States may not operate foreign software on any date after the date which is 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H12E4B01ECE65442FBF19AE92A1613549"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H0176D182D3034A11B0A356B486276136"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered foreign country</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered foreign country</quote> means a country that—</text><subparagraph id="HFD803836780A45A0AF9C0D6058EBAE64"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the intelligence community has identified as a foreign adversary in its most recent Annual Threat Assessment; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A3E53834BCE4858B3B4823522909CAD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security, in coordination with the Director of National Intelligence, has identified as a foreign adversary that is not included in such Annual Threat Assessment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAC03EB48A2C42E1965E5421769FD4D8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign crane</header><text>The term <quote>foreign crane</quote> means a crane for which any software or other technology in such crane that is connected into cyber infrastructure at a port located in the United States was, in whole or in part, manufactured by an entity that is owned or controlled by, is a subsidiary of, or is otherwise related legally or financially to a corporation based in a covered foreign country. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6F5ED4DC089489183BE1C8E87B53777"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign software</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>foreign software</quote> means software or other technology, in whole or in part, manufactured by a company wholly owned by a covered foreign country. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

