<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H66FC04E67E0C45CE92BC51B992FAE6DF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6477 IH: To amend the Immigration and Nationality Act to reform the process for inspection of applicants for admission.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6477</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231121">November 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001051">Mr. Carter of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000450">Ms. Foxx</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Immigration and Nationality Act to reform the process for inspection of applicants for admission.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCDEFFDF9AABD4C889BD2DFB4E2E1ABAE" style="OLC"> 
<title id="H2B6E87F8CC9F4AF49C94A65A5C419B1A"><enum>I</enum><header>Inspection of applicants for admission</header> 
<section id="HA60F69DB94384208B5CBC5064BB245BE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>101.</enum><header>Inspection of applicants for admission</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 235 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H124667E5DA2547848E62F4023CED31BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAE4B04DCC4E547DBB58D771D86DCE047"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <clause id="HEBC80CF1C99A425998F13DBA4599CF34"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subclause id="HCB7965337BF84EEA8451F4C145B982BB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clauses (i) and (ii), by striking <quote>section 212(a)(6)(C)</quote> inserting <quote>subparagraph (A) or (C) of section 212(a)(6)</quote>; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H8C153C6CF2BF44D1BE3ADD09DD7C994C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9B972D08842647DBA841C96C21153FD0" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="HB05A2F6B161946C3B2DB0B5616A754AF"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Ineligibility for parole</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An alien described in clause (i) or (ii) shall not be eligible for parole except as expressly authorized pursuant to section 212(d)(5), or for parole or release pursuant to section 236(a).</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause> <clause id="H63CB7F79EB9E4C459E3E3C197550D85F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text> 
<subclause id="HD3A5C1427BE545CE9B391C18410595E4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>asylum.</quote> and inserting <quote>asylum and shall not be released (including pursuant to parole or release pursuant to section 236(a) but excluding as expressly authorized pursuant to section 212(d)(5)) other than to be removed or returned to a country as described in paragraph (3).</quote>; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H790A6C89AE3B49E889D147F97263F7C4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (iii)(IV)—</text> 
<item id="HA6CE9FC124C947C2808BCD157095350D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the header by striking <quote><header-in-text level="subclause" style="OLC">detention</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subclause" style="OLC">detention, return, or removal</header-in-text></quote>; and </text></item> <item id="H8EFCAC48B1FC489A849F6988F5145E7C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>The alien shall not be released (including pursuant to parole or release pursuant to section 236(a) but excluding as expressly authorized pursuant to section 212(d)(5)) other than to be removed or returned to a country as described in paragraph (3).</quote>;</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0D35E6DA09474567869BAE66CF76690C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2)—</text> <clause id="H4A906AFCF71A4108BFA986C544C1560C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subclause id="H08599E50CB574F8EB601C77C67CA6CEE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Subject to subparagraphs (B) and (C),</quote> and inserting <quote>Subject to subparagraph (B) and paragraph (3),</quote>; and </text></subclause> <subclause id="HC9F3A02D61884A5A99EF1045AB41C816"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>The alien shall not be released (including pursuant to parole or release pursuant to section 236(a) but excluding as expressly authorized pursuant to section 212(d)(5)) other than to be removed or returned to a country as described in paragraph (3).</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H9155D3FDA5D640FCABBC506DDE6BFA0B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (C);</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA6A74EA2F06143FE9670EAC2C7F26F9A" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (5); and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H428AE73C6F7D4C98AB3BB520F9A45A75"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H13DAB441D43144028DCF5D2AD0AA4B91" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H49868D1A5DD243C582D8880ECD58A4B2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Return to foreign territory contiguous to the United States</header> <subparagraph id="H73951D84C9AA4E69AEA91FF573A9A1BD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security may return to a foreign territory contiguous to the United States any alien arriving on land from that territory (whether or not at a designated port of entry) pending a proceeding under section 240 or review of a determination under subsection (b)(1)(B)(iii)(III). </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA8C6214C6508475BB17BBAECAF0A7210"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Mandatory return</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If at any time the Secretary of Homeland Security cannot—</text> <clause id="H41F2BA21E5A141BBA460AFF966AA835D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>comply with its obligations to detain an alien as required under clauses (ii) and (iii)(IV) of subsection (b)(1)(B) and subsection (b)(2)(A); or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H541D74ACAA9F424997D33FC9C7BB8FB6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>remove an alien to a country described in section 208(a)(2)(A), </text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">the Secretary of Homeland Security shall, without exception, including pursuant to parole or release pursuant to section 236(a) but excluding as expressly authorized pursuant to section 212(d)(5), return to a foreign territory contiguous to the United States any alien arriving on land from that territory (whether or not at a designated port of entry) pending a proceeding under section 240 or review of a determination under subsection (b)(1)(B)(iii)(III).</continuation-text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA8DEE7C529E84B66B86690C56F139F65"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Enforcement by state attorneys general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The attorney general of a State, or other authorized State officer, alleging a violation of the detention, return, or removal requirements under paragraph (1), (2), or (3) that affects such State or its residents, may bring an action against the Secretary of Homeland Security on behalf of the residents of the State in an appropriate United States district court to obtain appropriate injunctive relief.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAD65A8342A6C466A9D1B221945D8D5FF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCAD41E81D6BE4C67AC94EC2F31A2E390" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H4168A36F0CFE46B28CF76FCF77DDBF7A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authority To prohibit introduction of certain aliens</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of Homeland Security determines, in his discretion, that the prohibition of the introduction of aliens who are inadmissible under subparagraph (A) or (C) of section 212(a)(6) or under section 212(a)(7) at an international land or maritime border of the United States is necessary to achieve operational control (as defined in section 2 of the Secure Fence Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1701">8 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note)) of such border, the Secretary may prohibit, in whole or in part, the introduction of such aliens at such border for such period of time as the Secretary determines is necessary for such purpose.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></title> 
<title id="H87C86073C08D443CA3D068B1213DDEF3"><enum>II</enum><header>Immigration Parole Reform</header> 
<section id="HDBE480536A10404498065EFE536E18A5" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>201.</enum><header>Immigration parole reform</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 212(d)(5) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(d)(5)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H065AA22837254333BE317C9761E3C922" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H501B9876AD5A4B67916538C873310ECE" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HFC0A8364F5A74CB5A8871681281D2F54"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraphs (B) and (C) and section 214(f), the Secretary of Homeland Security, in the discretion of the Secretary, may temporarily parole into the United States any alien applying for admission to the United States who is not present in the United States, under such conditions as the Secretary may prescribe, on a case-by-case basis, and not according to eligibility criteria describing an entire class of potential parole recipients, for urgent humanitarian reasons or significant public benefit. Parole granted under this subparagraph may not be regarded as an admission of the alien. When the purposes of such parole have been served in the opinion of the Secretary, the alien shall immediately return or be returned to the custody from which the alien was paroled. After such return, the case of the alien shall be dealt with in the same manner as the case of any other applicant for admission to the United States.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H36921AF0CD124A98AA4F7045B92DBD4F" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may grant parole to any alien who—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDC0451C08FE4D098AB34EBB81235734"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is present in the United States without lawful immigration status;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H291E0A7FCEBD45C48F9F0A29A8A0E3E2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is the beneficiary of an approved petition under section 203(a);</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFB1328351E6641BBB3B44AD3C8CB0AA7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is not otherwise inadmissible or removable; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H862F26E78EF04162B8737318D6E1D156"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>is the spouse or child of a member of the Armed Forces serving on active duty.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4F480700159241D8B0FC844B4B2B5113" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may grant parole to any alien—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9CB2D56BC1424CA294C5E296CABE78E5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>who is a national of the Republic of Cuba and is living in the Republic of Cuba;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCA1FEFD810A4BA0B2F3665A2D9D4250"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>who is the beneficiary of an approved petition under section 203(a);</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36228ED15BCD4222BABFFFE84BDCD0D3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for whom an immigrant visa is not immediately available;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAD7E12EF50D44483AA5A4E4E4EBF8ACA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>who meets all eligibility requirements for an immigrant visa;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F794150792F40F2A67B6254C76399F9"><enum>(v)</enum><text>who is not otherwise inadmissible; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD5D41C187EB24F9AAA3249F32279F367"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>who is receiving a grant of parole in furtherance of the commitment of the United States to the minimum level of annual legal migration of Cuban nationals to the United States specified in the U.S.-Cuba Joint Communiqué on Migration, done at New York September 9, 1994, and reaffirmed in the Cuba-United States: Joint Statement on Normalization of Migration, Building on the Agreement of September 9, 1994, done at New York May 2, 1995.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8C327DE64A194B7FB9472D1C0A5BA332" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security may grant parole to an alien who is returned to a contiguous country under section 235(b)(3) to allow the alien to attend the alien’s immigration hearing. The grant of parole shall not exceed the time required for the alien to be escorted to, and attend, the alien’s immigration hearing scheduled on the same calendar day as the grant, and to immediately thereafter be escorted back to the contiguous country. A grant of parole under this subparagraph shall not be considered for purposes of determining whether the alien is inadmissible under this Act.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H52FCB0ED53834E739231AFF443150273" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>For purposes of determining an alien’s eligibility for parole under subparagraph (A), an urgent humanitarian reason shall be limited to circumstances in which the alien establishes that—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1519BE50B04B466DB78CF400C3F766B0"><enum>(i)</enum> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9DEE6D37596B4EA4806386AFF4DFA498"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the alien has a medical emergency; and</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="HCB6D7DC3F82D42F0AB0192B8272116D9"><enum>(II)</enum> <item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H938EB439B5FE4F36BDD29365A4DAF0EF"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the alien cannot obtain necessary treatment in the foreign state in which the alien is residing; or</text></item> 
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="HA84AB5270C4342C2AEBED8CFCB8E491F"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the medical emergency is life-threatening and there is insufficient time for the alien to be admitted to the United States through the normal visa process;</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0284C88CD37D45CA85E9F3F218D86DD7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the alien is the parent or legal guardian of an alien described in clause (i) and the alien described in clause (i) is a minor;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75F610554F80482D859BDDE9D2EF3F3B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the alien is needed in the United States in order to donate an organ or other tissue for transplant and there is insufficient time for the alien to be admitted to the United States through the normal visa process;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0A945B7E5AAB457DA536C37797EC6553"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the alien has a close family member in the United States whose death is imminent and the alien could not arrive in the United States in time to see such family member alive if the alien were to be admitted to the United States through the normal visa process;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7A1ABED94AEB4B2983B053AC4823AB5D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the alien is seeking to attend the funeral of a close family member and the alien could not arrive in the United States in time to attend such funeral if the alien were to be admitted to the United States through the normal visa process;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD9BFC1DE97014CC6AA4CBF7EFAE8782F"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the alien is an adopted child with an urgent medical condition who is in the legal custody of the petitioner for a final adoption-related visa and whose medical treatment is required before the expected award of a final adoption-related visa; or</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA8AAA9F1BD94DD9BADB28347E7D94C5"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the alien is a lawful applicant for adjustment of status under section 245 and is returning to the United States after temporary travel abroad.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE18537C22072482CB77008DDB9DD805E" indent="up1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>For purposes of determining an alien's eligibility for parole under subparagraph (A), a significant public benefit may be determined to result from the parole of an alien only if—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF8C41A25CF4043E297965CBAD062249D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the alien has assisted (or will assist, whether knowingly or not) the United States Government in a law enforcement matter;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H852287B2D537441388658954D351A3F6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the alien’s presence is required by the Government in furtherance of such law enforcement matter; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAD11DA32A39A4EF6A14430A142163C37"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the alien is inadmissible, does not satisfy the eligibility requirements for admission as a nonimmigrant, or there is insufficient time for the alien to be admitted to the United States through the normal visa process.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6830AF00F4E741388A6FE57AEB35F793" indent="up1"><enum>(G)</enum><text>For purposes of determining an alien's eligibility for parole under subparagraph (A), the term <term>case-by-case basis</term> means that the facts in each individual case are considered and parole is not granted based on membership in a defined class of aliens to be granted parole. The fact that aliens are considered for or granted parole one-by-one and not as a group is not sufficient to establish that the parole decision is made on a <term>case-by-case basis</term>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H47E202FA14BE4BE1AFD612D4F8186329" indent="up1"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security may not use the parole authority under this paragraph to parole an alien into the United States for any reason or purpose other than those described in subparagraphs (B), (C), (D), (E), and (F).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5B7DC1538F1B4B06BA297E57E96A8C0B" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>An alien granted parole may not accept employment, except that an alien granted parole pursuant to subparagraph (B) or (C) is authorized to accept employment for the duration of the parole, as evidenced by an employment authorization document issued by the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H985C167A859D415AB90001E5A595C370" indent="up1"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Parole granted after a departure from the United States shall not be regarded as an admission of the alien. An alien granted parole, whether as an initial grant of parole or parole upon reentry into the United States, is not eligible to adjust status to lawful permanent residence or for any other immigration benefit if the immigration status the alien had at the time of departure did not authorize the alien to adjust status or to be eligible for such benefit.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4B769B73A77641549141A6108F4CAE38" indent="up1"><enum>(K)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1F9F14AD58F64C25B8B0D9999D72735B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Except as provided in clauses (ii) and (iii), parole shall be granted to an alien under this paragraph for the shorter of—</text> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="H1594E322B8384ABCB6D835CFBE224F80"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a period of sufficient length to accomplish the activity described in subparagraph (D), (E), or (F) for which the alien was granted parole; or </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1" id="H649E5AE3ABB34595BC83E28418018FC2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>1 year.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H1B500F47E69340B59A6E1FD76E4D409D" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Grants of parole pursuant to subparagraph (A) may be extended once, in the discretion of the Secretary, for an additional period that is the shorter of—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H87E4F651A61B49F4831FF35D00D1CDA4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the period that is necessary to accomplish the activity described in subparagraph (E) or (F) for which the alien was granted parole; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCFD4E6DD735B4C4AAC20294AAC968003"><enum>(II)</enum><text>1 year.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H2312161BE5784E1B9A17AB77EFE56F8E" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Aliens who have a pending application to adjust status to permanent residence under section 245 may request extensions of parole under this paragraph, in 1-year increments, until the application for adjustment has been adjudicated. Such parole shall terminate immediately upon the denial of such adjustment application.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H905FE6219ADA46FCBB047614622324C1" indent="up1"><enum>(L)</enum><text>Not later than 90 days after the last day of each fiscal year, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives</committee-name> and make available to the public, a report—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1EC16BDF85F049F8B260EB0E737B824E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identifying the total number of aliens paroled into the United States under this paragraph during the previous fiscal year; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H822B4FB495F94157930D13B2109A58E2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>containing information and data regarding all aliens paroled during such fiscal year, including—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB73DE2B77ACA407AB12B24E0C47CEF0C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the duration of parole;</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA447B5526F7E47C1AE0F3D42B2F0BF13"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the type of parole; and </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H06FABD0BD4824F41AC57A276EEB0F468"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the current status of the aliens so paroled.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H234330243CF74C439FBA7445BDEB0AF1"><enum>202.</enum><header>Implementation</header> 
<subsection id="H38001180427D453598E7F348669F7D8D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), this title and the amendments made by this title shall take effect on the date that is 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF147AD12E3DD4556A47C1CE2BC5252F9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (a), each of the following exceptions apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD9FEEADA068B49B088238EF01DB89297"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any application for parole or advance parole filed by an alien before the date of the enactment of this Act shall be adjudicated under the law that was in effect on the date on which the application was properly filed and any approved advance parole shall remain valid under the law that was in effect on the date on which the advance parole was approved.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H82F42B97844C428AB14B84C01D191C3E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Section 212(d)(5)(J) of the Immigration and Nationality Act, as added by section 201 of this Act, shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CBBB568092B4F1C9B5AF562BDC48786"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Aliens who were paroled into the United States pursuant to section 212(d)(5)(A) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(d)(5)(A)</external-xref>) before January 1, 2023, shall continue to be subject to the terms of parole that were in effect on the date on which their respective parole was approved.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HA402A6D871BD4312A268BF3FF3523CFD"><enum>203.</enum><header>Cause of action</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Any person, State, or local government that experiences financial harm in excess of $1,000 due to a failure of the Federal Government to lawfully apply the provisions of this title or the amendments made by this title shall have standing to bring a civil action against the Federal Government in an appropriate district court of the United States for appropriate relief.</text></section> 
<section id="HAE29091B8C774A6993E23BB6AA02D34D"><enum>204.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this title or any amendment by this title, or the application of such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance, is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this title and the application of such provision or amendment to any other person or circumstance shall not be affected.</text></section></title> </legis-body></bill>

