<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD3EBE3EF44FB40F7AED2164443BF7AEE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5034 IH: To designate the facility of the United States Postal Service located at 2119 Market Square in Christiansted, St. Croix, United States Virgin Islands, as the “Lieutenant General Samuel E. Ebbesen Post Office”.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5034</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000610">Ms. Plaskett</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To designate the facility of the United States Postal Service located at 2119 Market Square in Christiansted, St. Croix, United States Virgin Islands, as the <quote>Lieutenant General Samuel E. Ebbesen Post Office</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD09E12EA2A00410FBE8F77B8F9B392A9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9EEA699E46E745748DD55866633BF36F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Lieutenant General Samuel E. Ebbesen Post Office</header> 
<subsection id="H07174BE88ED449A8962016114E737AC6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The facility of the United States Postal Service located at 2119 Market Square in Christiansted, St. Croix, United States Virgin Islands, shall be known and designated as the <quote>Lieutenant General Samuel E. Ebbesen Post Office</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H7D5E265661D04C26A6FC834A69BA9D9F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>References</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any reference in a law, map, regulation, document, paper, or other record of the United States to the facility referred to in subsection (a) shall be deemed to be a reference to the <quote>Lieutenant General Samuel E. Ebbesen Post Office</quote>.</text> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

