<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H45AFFA80BE73450FB36373D838C0D7E5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4221 IH: Healthcare for Our Troops Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4221</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230620">June 20, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000388">Mr. Kelly of Mississippi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 10, United States Code, to eliminate certain healthcare charges for members of the Selected Reserve eligible for TRICARE Reserve Select, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HC2DBF1607752476EA6856B740134FE7C" style="OLC">
<section id="HABDB31F9D3E84F7F9E8F830EEE7FA0EF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthcare for Our Troops Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H33C996DCDFA346A99BE0A43CB48AC8B0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Elimination of certain healthcare charges for members of the Selected Reserve</header> <subsection id="H3368954594674744A99C5D3C229B6A9D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>TRICARE Reserve Select</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1076d of title 10, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H9A70E07CDD514749A8BE1A0EA63C21B1" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="HCF09D38E9EBF4068AF50A07F2E01F8F1"><enum>1076d.</enum><header>TRICARE program: TRICARE Reserve Select coverage for members of the Selected Reserve</header>
<subsection id="HE6A78953B7034C44915EF1B4EF2D9D05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Members of Selected Reserve</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H673B1017281B41AF85F49AB9ECB8EBCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve of a reserve component of the Armed Forces is eligible for health benefits under TRICARE Reserve Select as provided in this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAEEECBCC8B784448AF15DB5B6676036B" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligibility for TRICARE Reserve Select coverage of a member under this section shall terminate upon the termination of the service of that member in the Selected Reserve. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H39FC8191B0544D5EA5D38C90552465A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>TRICARE Reserve Select family coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While a member of a reserve component is covered by TRICARE Reserve Select under subsection (a), the members of the immediate family of such member are eligible for TRICARE Reserve Select coverage as dependents of the member. If a member of a reserve component dies while in a period of coverage under this section, the eligibility of the members of the immediate family of such member for TRICARE Reserve Select coverage shall continue for six months beyond the date of death of the member. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H21A3BA659FA84C048F935AA1E2A0F7FB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No premiums for individual coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member of a reserve component covered by TRICARE Reserve Select individual coverage shall pay no premium for such coverage.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE9435F716AF743C98DE218F8BF8A48C5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Premiums for family coverage</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HAE71B021CF994314940399AF7C9E4C8F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member of a reserve component covered by TRICARE Reserve Select under this section shall pay a premium for any member of the immediate family of such member covered under TRICARE Reserve Select family coverage. Such premium shall apply instead of any enrollment fees required under section 1075 of this title.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF3A521C6601142C2B24D2C60435DEE05" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall prescribe for the purposes of this section one premium for TRICARE Reserve Select family coverage of immediate family members of members of the reserve components, that shall apply uniformly to all such immediate family members.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3001EC76BF294733B69E9E15D962BBE1" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0715B531C9A645DABDBBF37CAA9F607D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The monthly amount of the premium in effect for a month for TRICARE Reserve Select family coverage under this section shall be the amount equal to 28 percent of the total monthly amount determined on an appropriate actuarial basis as being reasonable for that coverage.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5FBDD88E0B144D51AD3FF8A62A9C15E8" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The appropriate actuarial basis for purposes of subparagraph (A) shall be determined, for each calendar year after calendar year 2009, by utilizing the actual cost of providing benefits under this section to members’ dependents during the calendar years preceding such calendar year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H89DC32E8E4044713B07D0A3CD29E7E4D" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The premiums for TRICARE Reserve Select family coverage payable by a member of a reserve component under this subsection may be deducted and withheld from basic pay payable to the member under section 204 of title 37 or from compensation payable to the member under section 206 of such title. The Secretary shall prescribe the requirements and procedures applicable to the payment of premiums.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB498A63A006E43AD98F44B089DDC3D22" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts collected as premiums under this subsection shall be credited to the appropriation available for the Defense Health Program Account under section 1100 of this title, shall be merged with sums in such Account that are available for the fiscal year in which collected, and shall be available under subsection (b) of such section for such fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1B6D8A03123A41B8BA6C9E658D46FC9E" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Cost-Sharing amounts</header>
<paragraph id="HB4A9990902284D36B90CCA29B2F89C69" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Network individual coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), a beneficiary covered by TRICARE Reserve Select individual coverage shall pay no charge for any healthcare service to which the beneficiary is entitled pursuant to such coverage.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H27C9D0B54C4E4C4EA9694CB36C1F87D3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Out-of-network individual coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to out-of-network healthcare services, a beneficiary covered by TRICARE Reserve Select individual coverage shall be subject to the same out-of-network cost-sharing requirements as those to which beneficiaries described in section 1075(c)(1) of this title in the active-duty family member category are subject to for the corresponding year.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H827520B05928466B8C927C6D2DBC9C16" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Family coverage</header><text>A beneficiary covered by TRICARE Reserve Select family coverage shall be subject to the same cost-sharing requirements as those to which beneficiaries described in section 1075(c)(1) of this title in the active-duty family member category are subject to for the corresponding year.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD30B6CB945DB498495A2B83CA51199F3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the other administering Secretaries, shall prescribe regulations for the administration of this section.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H7E200D984564442FBCD57CD5DA6783DE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HE7893C6AA8474B9F85C5CC355BBFA17B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The terms <quote>active-duty family member category</quote>, <quote>network</quote>, and <quote>out-of-network</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 1075(h) of this title.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H508F7A858DD844179F12353B67C502A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>immediate family</quote>, with respect to a member of a reserve component, means any dependents of the member described in subparagraph (A), (D), or (I) of section 1072(2) of this title.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5CB1DE0C0A2A4FAEB9D59BEBE8A60F32"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>TRICARE Reserve Select</quote> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H3B53D7B5E23A40E0ADD1DE425F0A03D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">medical care at facilities of the uniformed services to which a dependent described in section 1076(a)(2) of this title is entitled; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9C207ECF41994861A6FEEFE1656DE0D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">health benefits under the TRICARE Select self-managed, preferred provider network option under section 1075 of this title made available to beneficiaries by reason of this section and subject to the cost-sharing requirements set forth in subsection (e) of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8F3F4BDBD0DF4B24A88910A55372CAC8"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>TRICARE Reserve Select family coverage</quote> means the coverage under TRICARE Reserve Select of any members of the immediate family of a member of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve of a reserve component, as described in subsection (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H76EFCF4537E945BE8EB81574C2601AFC"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>TRICARE Reserve Select individual coverage</quote> means the coverage under TRICARE Reserve Select of a member of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve of a reserve component, as described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="HA33598D05BC14B8F8491F0ABA9780D44"><enum>(b)</enum><header>TRICARE Dental for Selected Reserve</header><text>Section 1076a of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H55F09652ABDE444DB748AC94B5220C1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H776E7A55A948472AB91F94BCF4D809CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the heading of paragraph (1), by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="USC">selected reserve and</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE5ABD74B04E7418FADD3F52426DA9336"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H67B3E2AEAAC744339005500BF63E7AB2" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H34952FE699FC447E8C27C9A8AD4D5466"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Plan for Selected Reserve</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A dental benefits plan for members of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H893C4304575A47E3AB494A4474F36E45"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5BBF6A05553C494F9FBC46050B029E5F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (4); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB26BD1172BD7414B8583ECD970A9D527"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H4B1E3CE21EBF4F9FBD491C6D6EEB5964" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="HA9F6F9387DD44C44AE0303AA102B3AAE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>No premium plans</header>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE8E8430CE4D1402AB6E13BC6717923C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The dental insurance plan established under subsection (a)(5) is a no premium plan.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0DF54B0D5F734B18B73FB2F9EF736CC8" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Members enrolled in a no premium plan may not be charged a premium for benefits provided under the plan. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5FE10C46CEEE46A5B80AE59F758FBAC3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(2)(A), by striking <quote>a member of the Selected Reserve of the Ready Reserve or</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCECF4211459D4172943B5E1B7EF24ABF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (f) through (l) as subsections (g) through (m), respectively;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9FB8BADED56E4D0B890BAA8274D5D1D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (e) the following new subsection (f):</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H796DFD9806B7406EB4A94DABC6A6C250" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="HB46A1F594281477F88523D61D263FE8B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Copayments under no premium plans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member who receives dental care under a no premium plan referred to in subsection (d)(3) shall pay no charge for any care described in subsection (c).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9F1092FC12C749DA97A88A4F0D45F70D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in subsection (i), as redesignated by paragraph (4), by striking <quote>subsection (k)(2)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (l)(2)</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3727D89F7A1742C29F9E23D2E2A653C5" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Improvements to coverage for certain retirees</header> <paragraph id="H86A3ECCD72384E14A07B2CA743B8BF6E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adjustment of eligibility</header><text>Section 1074(b)(2) of title 10, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H7C784C43867D4DC8B224D68A099DC0A5" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="HF2D7544BA747476DA67AE975E7D1DBAC" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1) does not apply to a member or former member entitled to retired pay for non-regular service under chapter 1223 of this title who is under 60 years of age unless such member or former member is in receipt of such pay (or would be in receipt of such pay but for section 5304 or 5305 of title 38).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1F8ED618FFE34895B2BC50BDBEBD0A5E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>TRICARE Retired Reserve</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1076e(a)(1) of title 10, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>but is not age 60</quote> and inserting <quote>but is not age 60 and is not in receipt of such retired pay (or would be in receipt of such pay but for section 5304 or 5305 of title 38)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1E020268017B410BA03C3F28A7C8BA6E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conforming amendments to TRICARE Select</header><text>Section 1075 of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HFC7C9A0170424C08917379BB95AFF19D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by amending subsection (c)(3) to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H47D3F797670343E8A44BF6A1D77E91FE" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H158463423EEA40F1AA59AA3839CAAE83"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to beneficiaries in the reserve and young adult category—</text> <subparagraph id="HC9EEDA3312804707B03F3C4982CD8DEA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for beneficiaries covered by section 1076e or 1110b of this title, the cost-sharing requirements shall be calculated pursuant to subsection (d)(1) as if the beneficiary were in the active-duty family member category or the retired category, as applicable, except that the premiums calculated pursuant to section 1076e or 1110b of this title shall apply instead of any enrollment fee required under this section; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2DE30DDC4F7441B7B9CAA04E64A32F1D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for beneficiaries covered by section 1076d of this title, the cost-sharing requirements shall be calculated pursuant to section (e) of such section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB76324DCE2E9425F9259CD8A1553280D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall apply with respect to the provision of healthcare under the TRICARE program beginning on the date that is one year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H126BD5FCA5D049DCB97DE976D3466B15"><enum>3.</enum><header>Forms and study relating to improved coverage for members of the Selected Reserve</header>
<subsection id="HABDCA464E5F24B0F97DE0A81CB7C0E37"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Forms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall develop forms to be used by civilian healthcare providers under the purchased care component of the TRICARE Program for medical and dental care for members of the Selected Reserve eligible for TRICARE Reserve Select. Such forms shall include opportunities for the healthcare provider to indicate, with respect to the member, the following information:</text> <paragraph id="HD1833442EB3D4E0E9C232296B1B308BF" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Medical Readiness Classification.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9B566C36C8E646E599B385B04E0ED6D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Dental Readiness Classification.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD300028FC614F46AF603FFF5C20AB15"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Fitness for deployment.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H682B7D22E01145C7BF58C8552C2FA1EE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any other information the Secretary determines necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8375CA0EA32841539D0BBB413CDF51B1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study</header> <paragraph id="HD8EF40D6CD044234A24C52E1F020D9C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall conduct a study on—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9652C57A7BB34844BF2B7F7561C8E9BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the phasing out of mass medical events and periodic health assessments for members of the Selected Reserve eligible for TRICARE Reserve Select; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD816F46F5CF7421DB906ECC89F61C625"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the replacement of such events and processes with the new TRICARE Reserve Select coverage model under section 1076d of title 10, United States Code (as amended by section 1), and the use of forms by civilian healthcare providers as specified in subsection (a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF116E4CA7D2441419510E2E96BF0CE71"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report containing the findings of the study under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

