<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE57EEA1199E74A8AAFA35B173B6A15F5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1620 IH: Maximizing Opioid Recovery Emergency Savings Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1620</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230317">March 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001220">Mr. McGarvey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote affordable access to evidence-based opioid treatments under the Medicare program and require coverage of medication assisted treatment for opioid use disorders, opioid overdose reversal medications, and recovery support services by health plans without cost-sharing requirements.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H13EE93E701D64AAC930B7443DCCF49C6" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H2B883366BB9F4512B6521A67FEB53BDB"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Maximizing Opioid Recovery Emergency Savings Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MORE Savings Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HAD8E3BE00E1D49E7857A1A9A8BBD96FA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Testing of elimination of Medicare cost-sharing for evidence-based opioid treatments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1115A(b)(2) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1315a">42 U.S.C. 1315a(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H82759A47BE6441CB8A1709F916FDA640"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), in the last sentence, by inserting <quote>, and shall include the model described in subparagraph (D) (which shall be implemented by not later than six months after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Maximizing Opioid Recovery Emergency Savings Act)</short-title></quote> before the period at the end; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H307796FAA64A4CE585ACFD4123B20729"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA43BA939EB6742AD9AF0C810FA869EE1"><subparagraph id="HE5C3B59BDD3B4D5784C052452FA159E7"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Affordable access to evidence-based opioid treatments</header><clause id="HE956E930696A4695AB591FD965A58B95"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The model described in this subparagraph is a model that seeks to provide affordable access to evidence-based opioid treatments and community-based recovery support services by eliminating coinsurance, copayments, and deductibles otherwise applicable under parts B and D of title XVIII (including as such parts are applied under part C of such title) for the following items and services that are otherwise covered under such parts:</text><subclause id="HF966F12610B846EB91E0A61DE553448A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Drugs and biologicals prescribed or furnished to treat opioid use disorders or reverse overdose.</text></subclause><subclause id="HF18155406D984F22AEB1AF98998ABC4F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Behavioral health and community support services furnished for the treatment of opioid use disorders, including treatment of addiction in non-hospital residential facilities licensed to furnish such treatment.</text></subclause><subclause id="H9BC4EBFBFA4448F883441FC9433A7C46"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Recovery support services to maintain a healthy lifestyle following opioid misuse treatment, such as peer counseling and transportation.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9D8CB7B0547344D297B5286D699927DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Selection of sites</header><text>The CMI shall select 15 States in which to conduct the model under this subparagraph. A State shall meet each of the following criteria in order to be selected under the preceding sentence:</text><subclause id="HA1914FD47FE7494BAC73AFC242231BD9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The State has a high proportion of Medicare beneficiaries.</text></subclause><subclause id="H0D7EE6737A2E430889516CC3C05A8788"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The State has a high rate of overdose deaths due to opioids.</text></subclause><subclause id="H9E239BD3A9B142CD870B2DBE65124125"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The State has a significant percentage of rural areas.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H680196B5E2C4439D9F90979B3BD05276"><enum>(iii)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Termination and modification provision not applicable for first five years of the model</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of paragraph (3)(B) shall apply to the model under this subparagraph beginning on the date that is five years after such model is implemented, but shall not apply to such model prior to such date.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HB9EDFCB39EDA4660AFF19DFBA89DEF61"><enum>3.</enum><header>Coverage of opioid treatments</header><subsection id="H7C3215FBA8D14F0D83D31E0564008B7E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 2719A (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-19a">42 U.S.C. 300gg–19a</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFB0B02E9303D42539F243A48ABB5B110"><section id="HE9F64E1C32734F8E9F06717D78BA7CFE"><enum>2720.</enum><header>Coverage of opioid treatments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A group health plan and a health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage shall, at a minimum, provide coverage for and shall not impose any cost-sharing requirements for—</text><paragraph id="HC12AEF4C8B224A02A1ADB25EE69BE5E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prescription drugs for the treatment of opioid use disorders or to reverse overdose;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D7E2FBE492A482FBF98C8B033B14546"><enum>(2)</enum><text>behavioral health services for the treatment of opioid use disorders, including treatment of opioid use disorders in non-hospital residential facilities licensed to provide such treatment; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BD1C28C98C34CA7A4B01F56A5143A47"><enum>(3)</enum><text>community recovery support services that are provided in conjunction with, where appropriate, medication-assisted treatment for an opioid use disorder, such as peer counseling and transportation, to support the enrollee in maintaining a healthy lifestyle following opioid misuse treatment.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCC0A65946D3C47ABB25F7E8520BC6912"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply with respect to plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1CC641A2C6624BC29E0A54ACAD5AAAD4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Enhanced Federal match for medication-assisted treatment and recovery support services under Medicaid</header><subsection id="H95A1C63BDA744F6EB37F2B221A337F10"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1905(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Notwithstanding the first sentence of this subsection, during the portion of the period described in subsection (a)(29) that begins on the date of enactment of this sentence, the Federal medical assistance percentage shall be 90 percent with respect to amounts expended during such portion of such period by a State that is one of the 50 States or the District of Columbia as medical assistance for medication-assisted treatment (as defined in subsection (ee)(1)).</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD380D892454249439FFD9A14BF7EF218"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State option To provide recovery support services as part of medication-Assisted treatment</header><text>Section 1905(ee)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(ee)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H5F78AE71E7EC4F6680FF404A024E6669"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA020153734C4B64B9A7B3583AED9FA2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD54DE434300B405DB6065391C79CE93E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="H741C2A1F082C402885970ED8AB8F1988"><subparagraph id="H179ABFAE97144D3DA48ED0F20283895C"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at the option of a State, includes recovery support services, such as peer counseling and transportation, that are provided to an individual in conjunction with the provision of such drugs and biological products to support the individual in maintaining a healthy lifestyle following opioid misuse treatment.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

