<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB66CE3DB07AD4AD7825909AB212618A6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 151 IH: No Frivolous Application for Short-Barreled Shotguns Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 151</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="A000055">Mr. Aderholt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001039">Mrs. Cammack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001118">Mr. Cline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001052">Mr. Harris</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001212">Mr. Stauber</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000809">Mr. Womack</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to remove short-barreled shotguns from the definition of firearms for purposes of the National Firearms Act, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB29C56A3188D4CEDADDE40711A354755" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC71F0F5AA3904653AA3F4C1D2484EFC6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Frivolous Application for Short-Barreled Shotguns Act</short-title></quote> or as the <quote><short-title>NFA SBS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4B455766E0F34DBAAE2583C62156E191"><enum>2.</enum><header>Short-barreled shotguns</header> <subsection id="H7D187DFBD7C74A3E849F27AE833171E7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5845">Section 5845(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4EB44D2914E744BAB770A4376094C1A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(1) a shotgun having a barrel or barrels of less than 18 inches in length; (2) a weapon made from a shotgun if such weapon as modified has an overall length of less than 26 inches or a barrel or barrels of less than 18 inches in length; (3)</quote> and inserting <quote>(1)</quote>, and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H475D753264974FBCAD7A4713CBE1DB0B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraphs (4) through (8) as paragraphs (2) through (6), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H693612F9425F4354BD231DCFB58DC586"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Shotguns not treated as destructive devices</header><text>Section 5485(f) of such Code is amended by striking <quote>except a shotgun or shotgun shell which the Secretary finds is generally recognized as particularly suitable for sporting purposes</quote> and inserting <quote>except shotgun shells and any weapon that is designed to shoot shotgun shells</quote>. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H33CB2F7CBB4B43E4A9C3BB365C31056C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall apply to calendar quarters beginning more than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H45B7D0AE63054F37BF6CE9FC832EA13D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Elimination of disparate treatment of short-barreled shotguns used for lawful purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 922 of title 18, United States Code, is amended in each of subsections (a)(4) and (b)(4) by striking <quote>short-barreled shotgun,</quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD777B6C9AD9B4B6D8ECD2CC39D84FCF0"><enum>4.</enum><header>Treatment of short-barreled shotguns determined by reference to National Firearms Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5841">Section 5841</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H4A8D4FFA90EC418AAEEE59532ED1A085" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HFAF1A8BB73594221A6A289B948697CB0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Short-Barreled shotgun requirements determined by reference</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any short-barreled shotgun registration or licensing requirement under State or local law which is determined by reference to the National Firearms Act, any person who acquires or possesses such a shotgun in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, shall be treated as meeting any such registration or licensing requirement with respect to such shotgun.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H5D870ACBB94240E48FE2F1A44BC938B4"><enum>5.</enum><header>Preemption of certain State laws in relation to short-barreled shotguns</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 927 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Notwithstanding the preceding sentence, a law of a State or a political subdivision of a State that imposes a tax, other than a generally applicable sales or use tax, on making, transferring, using, possessing, or transporting a short-barreled shotgun in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, or imposes a marking, recordkeeping or registration requirement with respect to such a shotgun, shall have no force or effect.</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H6DCD7F67B4CB47C1A53003E4A8E2C6E2"><enum>6.</enum><header>Destruction of records</header> 
<subsection id="HB444A1BD237948C188FCC141DB1B80E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 365 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall destroy any registration of an applicable shotgun maintained in the National Firearms Registration and Transfer Record pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5841">section 5841</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, any application to transfer filed under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5812">section 5812</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 that identifies the transferee of an applicable shotgun, and any application filed under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5822">section 5822</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 that identifies the maker of an applicable shotgun.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H51C70075034047E88CB49BF3EB9D5D6F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicable shotgun</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>applicable shotgun</quote> means any shotgun—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1CD445437B734983A5A671AFC6C1BA92"><enum>(1)</enum><text>described in paragraph (1) or (2) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5845">section 5845(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as in effect on the day before the enactment of this Act), or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B52B41073F84140BF8297CE03DC7859"><enum>(2)</enum><text>treated as destructive device under 5845(f) of such Code (as in effect on the day before the enactment of this Act) and not so treated under such section as in effect immediately after such date.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

