<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCBA70B0A8EAF472C869CF1D9CB269744" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4746 IH: Tribal Access to Clean Water Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4746</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide access to reliable, clean, and drinkable water on Tribal lands, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE39439416C2D4370BD0B9CDC09D33D0F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB16AA017D1A242D6AB2D2995EE9CD80F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Tribal Access to Clean Water Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF26359B026F24E0780F8FA3EBC2FF906"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H15DC0DB1EE6143F1AFE82719302B36B5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Access to reliable, clean, and drinkable water is an essential human need and critical to the public health, well-being, educational attainment, and economic development of all communities in the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBBF09623753447D9ACCC758FA2325B29"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Many countries, along with the United Nations, have recognized the urgency of the need to access reliable, clean, and drinkable water by passing laws or resolutions relating to the human right to water and sanitation, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H94BED0926BC343C6915B8F3854CA3063"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recognizing these water and sanitation needs exist among Indigenous peoples; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H43436B72AC874AFAA048D2B012C52D19"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establishing aggressive targets for achieving universal access to those basic services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H49BB477B6B644F24BEE70044D05DED2D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In the United States, access to reliable, clean, and drinkable water has long been a significant problem in many Native communities, such that nearly half of all households in those communities do not have access to reliable water sources, clean drinking water, or basic sanitation, and are significantly more likely than White households to lack indoor plumbing.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H265AFF19A498409A91E29C9A20E24C83"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The trust responsibility of the Federal Government to Indian Tribes requires the Federal Government to ensure the survival and welfare of Indian Tribes, and the failure to provide basic water service cannot be reconciled with that trust responsibility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9D9E28FA109D4DCF8579F1D1B3A8CEBF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The COVID–19 pandemic had, and continues to have, a disproportionate impact on Native communities due to a multitude of factors, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H5F28176B1250458ABF7F049477793EED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>persistent economic disadvantages;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H52F606162FDB45B68240AE984BA78014"><enum>(B)</enum><text>racial inequity; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAAC6EFAB8E3E43D6B7E821FF11A9F0AE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>lack of public health infrastructure, including access to running water.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H06EA642D46E44FDD9D1F501FA04D02E2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>On January 27, 2021, President Biden issued Executive Order 14008 (86 Fed. Reg. 7619, February 1, 2021), which provides that it is the policy of the Biden Administration to secure environmental justice and spur economic opportunity for disadvantaged communities that have been historically marginalized and overburdened by pollution and underinvestment in housing, transportation, water and wastewater infrastructure, and health care.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H938514195E3D4B6FB42FEE9B6092C59A"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Through the bipartisan Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/58">Public Law 117–58</external-xref>; commonly referred to as the <quote>IIJA</quote>), Congress has provided funding for the Indian Health Service and the Environmental Protection Agency to support the construction and repair of Tribal clean water infrastructure, but inadequate resources are available to Tribes to assist them with accessing these construction and repair funding programs, and to support Tribes’ operation and maintenance of water infrastructure.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H015C3712B0FD4F2BA6E6DC7C5472D9A4"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Filling the gaps in funding described in paragraph (7) is necessary to successfully implement the historic investment in clean water infrastructure in Native communities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H20F71A78A8224BC6B085A827F955F8D7"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Technical assistance to Tribes is necessary to ensure that they—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8D359D4506084EF99E5FD6BAAAAA2A98"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are able to access and take advantage of the new construction funding made available through the IIJA;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9AFF5576FB724897A16E54F419E566F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop the managerial, financial, and regulatory framework necessary for a fully functional and self-sustaining utility; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEB588F5DB5104D0A8988C9EC9A5AC19A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>are able to engage appropriate outside consultants to assist as needed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAA2074384F774EF98BF4C2549C4E7334"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Advances in water technology, including treatment, sensors, and innovative pipeline materials, can assist in—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H17202758FD4F41A1B5177233B172CBB5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>accelerating efforts to provide universal access to reliable, clean, and drinkable water for all Native communities; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF95D0AACBA5D4D178655CFC879A1AF68"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enhancing resilience in the face of climate change.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBB7A9787036F43E59619FEACC19E2CD3"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The COVID–19 pandemic has been a stark reminder that access to reliable, clean, and drinkable water to support basic hygiene is a matter of life or death for all individuals in the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB628FBE74B974FEBBFD4C9BEF4ED3F37"><enum>(12)</enum><text>It is in the interest of the United States, and it is the policy of the United States, that all existing Native communities be provided with safe and adequate water supply systems as soon as practicable.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H51AFD44B492D43EC945D09F639047293"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Both appropriate funding at the level of unmet need and a <quote>whole of government</quote> approach among all Federal agencies are essential to provide a meaningful solution to the lack of access to clean water on Tribal lands.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H5A64EFD416484B1E9F5BED82B7BB5A80"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H0B1C1488E7144C9B8654943F57F77FEB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74E6C2CC39814DCBB5E5EF9D867EFE1C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Native community</header><text>The term <term>Native community</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF4A489B1AA19487BA488A7318C2D9058"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H094DC588E80F4B9A9F9109B0B2DA19A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a Native Hawaiian community.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H32AD05D17B2C4C53A091C6E34551D9CB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Native Hawaiian</header><text>The term <term>Native Hawaiian</term> has the meaning given that term in section 801 of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/4221">25 U.S.C. 4221</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8F3654212D1A4F8EBC40C6BC2358FC27"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The term <term>technical assistance</term> means the provision of governmental or private sector expertise—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD60595BEF41E4F0D9FEED8C724F1E0C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to facilitate Native community access to repair and construction funding for clean water facilities made available through the Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/58">Public Law 117–58</external-xref>; 135 Stat. 429) or the rural development mission area of the Department of Agriculture; and </text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H11519146D7794D269B05C539CEA739DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to support Native communities in developing the managerial, financial, and regulatory capacity necessary for a fully functional and self-sustaining utility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HBF1765C061E2465599727315524D4E4B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Department of agriculture rural development</header> 
<subsection id="HCD86E59A2CF046EE9AE41ED516EEDA1F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Extension of authority for grants and loans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the purposes for which loans and grants may be provided under sections 306C and 306D of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1926c">7 U.S.C. 1926c</external-xref>, 1926d), the Secretary of Agriculture (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) may make or insure loans and make grants to eligible entities described in subsection (c) for technical assistance. </text> </subsection> <subsection id="H666DE94E20CB470DB1A767CB463464E2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>In addition to amounts otherwise available, there are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9BFE1AB432194D7BB193768BC3C7BE77"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$100,000,000, to remain available until expended, to make or insure loans and make grants under sections 306C and 306D of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1926c">7 U.S.C. 1926c</external-xref>, 1926d), and for the additional purposes described in subsection (a), to eligible entities described in subsection (c) to provide for the development, use, and control of water (including the extension or improvement of existing water supply systems); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H926BC3BBC45E4DE4ABEB895FB106A143"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$30,000,000, to remain available until expended, for eligible entities described in subsection (c) to contract for technical assistance.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H264A9314EC4F4C11A70F7E1C6F359899"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity eligible to receive a grant or an award of financial or technical assistance using amounts appropriated under paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (b) or amounts otherwise available under sections 306C and 306D of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1926c">7 U.S.C. 1926c</external-xref>, 1926d) is—</text> <paragraph id="H25416F3E0A6A46378A9ACE2E7367A872"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a Native community; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H23A0B5D69C024D128C6C0A84C191FA9F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of a grant in accordance with section 306D of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act, a consortium formed pursuant to section 325 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/105/83">Public Law 105–83</external-xref> (111 Stat. 1597).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF4038619A1254CC3972FE731358CA93D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No matching contribution</header><text>The provision of funds made available under subsection (b) shall not be conditioned on any matching contribution otherwise required by any other provision of law (including regulations). </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3FEA937DADED488A82BECF36CE3BBFE2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Priority for funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making or insuring loans or making grants to eligible entities using amounts appropriated under subsection (b), the Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H7E2C41632E1942A4A953204CBA7D1664"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">treat members of an eligible entity in the same manner as individuals who reside in a colonia for purposes of subsections (a)(2)(B) and (c)(2) of section 306C of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1926c">7 U.S.C. 1926c</external-xref>); and </text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H492A0948CDF24BEFBDA1BA56770A588D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make or insure the loans or award the grants without requiring the eligible entity or the members of an eligible entity to demonstrate an inability to finance the proposed project—</text> <subparagraph id="HAB60795209B6476393DB6A263EEACA31"><enum>(A)</enum><text>from the resources of the eligible entity or members; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF3C7B14A6FA248D4A8A9D531DE633109"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through commercial credit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2C6EDA92006E4C80B650BD390CAA1D45"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Interagency collaboration</header><text>The Secretary shall consult with the Director of the Indian Health Service regarding agency collaboration, project prioritization, and staffing needs to ensure that funds made available under subsection (b) are used in the most effective manner to promote access to water and sanitation.</text></subsection> </section> 
<section id="H1C26FF53BC184D9B8CAA8BA466E2F229"><enum>5.</enum><header>Indian Health Service</header> 
<subsection id="HABCCB817723D400C974AA121482237D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of Secretary</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Director of the Indian Health Service.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9B4030C5078D42F4BEE72244AE7501D9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanitation facilities construction program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of section 7(a)(1) of the Act of August 5, 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2004a">42 U.S.C. 2004a(a)(1)</external-xref>), <quote>Indian homes, communities, and lands</quote> for which the Secretary has authority to <quote>construct, improve, extend, or otherwise provide and maintain, by contract or otherwise, essential sanitation facilities, including domestic and community water supplies and facilities, drainage facilities, and sewage-disposal and waste-disposal facilities</quote> shall include community structures that are essential to the life of the Native community and provide indispensable educational, economic, and community services, such as schools, hospitals, nursing homes, teachers’ homes, Tribal offices, and post offices.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H629941381FBE461E8958CC45921DC979"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary, in addition to amounts otherwise available, $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended, to construct, improve, extend, or otherwise provide and maintain, by contract or otherwise, essential sanitation facilities, including domestic and community water supplies and facilities, drainage facilities, and sewage- and waste-disposal facilities for community structures described in subsection (b).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H96D136ECC26B44779F25505B5C147AF2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical assistance funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to amounts otherwise available, there is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $30,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended, for Indian Tribes and Native communities to enter into contracts for—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9FDD28A208A64725B3979220F2C80D24"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">technical assistance; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H60065467AF4B47249771E828AAD9894E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for other activities authorized under section 302(b)(2) of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1632">25 U.S.C. 1632(b)(2)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF1E9838E194F4EB4A6DC0CEA3A10267B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Operation and maintenance funding</header> 
<paragraph id="H57A2DCFA67A94B98A9C7E0BF6918189D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may provide financial assistance for the operation and maintenance of water facilities serving Native communities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H80A983C6C9E8474D84776EE497D2289C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>In addition to amounts otherwise available, there is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended, for providing assistance for the operation and maintenance of water facilities serving Native communities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H58F98A86651944CCA98767003D221B0C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority for funding</header><text>In awarding funding under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall prioritize water facilities that the Secretary determines to be the most in need of assistance.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47B5D913CBC94411BBBF15EE95285072"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Future funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For not less than 5 years after the date on which a water facilities project described in paragraph (1) is completed, to the extent to which annual appropriations are available, the Secretary shall include the completed project as eligible for funding assistance for operation and maintenance of the water facility to ensure that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H21555BC63AC34FDF874E5B23A0DF0A5A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the investments in the water facilities are adequately maintained and operated for the health and welfare of Native communities served;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB7691DB9E5C34679A5C816F78AB5A957"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the infrastructure investment is protected; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCC86B1BA69814EC9A1EEA3D3D0353240"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the intended economic benefit is realized.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection></section> <section id="HECE254A343C3492ABF408935086BDA78"><enum>6.</enum><header>Bureau of Reclamation</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">In addition to amounts otherwise available, there is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary of the Interior $18,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended, for use, in accordance with section 201 of the Energy and Water Development Appropriations Act, 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/373d">43 U.S.C. 373d</external-xref>), for the Native American Affairs Technical Assistance Program of the Bureau of Reclamation for the fiscal year ending September 30, 2024.</text></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


