<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD9C8F476B2D04226811A366F4655C11A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3630 IH: Student Athlete Level Playing Field Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3630</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230524">May 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001126">Mr. Carey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit certain entities from barring a student athlete from participating in intercollegiate athletics as a result of such student athlete entering into an endorsement contract, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9874E8726C3E4C16BCA5228BCAFA9923" style="OLC"><section id="H08B567EEC0744080BB281F16C231F604" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H467DCBC1A5F748C48F4E45AA6A2A5E7C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Student Athlete Level Playing Field Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBA67B7A8EA5341C7B764DFB6E27D897B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H08B567EEC0744080BB281F16C231F604" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDA7A244BD90A425A80DB8656B8892552" level="section">Sec. 2. Ability of student athletes to enter agency and endorsement contracts.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCA78A5D82124493DB71B2A2E778BBD46" level="section">Sec. 3. Covered Athletic Organization Commission.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H19D56474117E47DC8D14DA51A454C590" level="section">Sec. 4. Institutions of higher education and student athletes who enter into endorsement contracts.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF7F3AF2CA7874ED3883893A84D3A69FC" level="section">Sec. 5. Prohibiting unfair or deceptive acts or practices against student athletes.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3C07F123F4F54CDF92D1833B25238133" level="section">Sec. 6. Registration of certain agents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF931D9695E0A4EFBA4E89AF6ADF1B83B" level="section">Sec. 7. State preemption.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4C8638BF1DC44CD78E14868AF617DA43" level="section">Sec. 8. Rules of construction.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA3B62A5F85284856AC20AC6EE1216EAA" level="section">Sec. 9. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7DFDAED6E97E42E5A390F6C3299A1AAD" level="section">Sec. 10. Definitions.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HDA7A244BD90A425A80DB8656B8892552"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ability of student athletes to enter agency and endorsement contracts</header><subsection id="H0B556DC2DC1D4FAD81CE696CEE208F91"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered athletic organization or institution of higher education may not prohibit a student athlete from participating in intercollegiate athletics as a result of such student athlete entering into an agency contract or an endorsement contract, or otherwise receiving consideration for the name, image, or likeness of such student athlete.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6FA8805E273242A7B64D73C12FF423E1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation on athletic departments</header><text>An agreement under which consideration is provided to a student athlete for use of the name, image, or likeness of the student athlete, including such an agreement between an institution of higher education and a student athlete, may not be negotiated, drafted, or funded by the athletic department of the institution of higher education of the student athlete or an institutional employee who reports to such athletic department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7A6C286A79BF4DAC9B26CB417A914261"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Insignia prohibitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A student athlete may be prohibited, by the institution of higher education of the student athlete, from wearing an item of clothing or gear with the insignia of an entity during an athletic competition or athletic-related event that is sponsored by the institution.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4AB12D54B0B442518C2A6BFAC47D655D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enforcement by Federal Trade Commission</header><paragraph id="HE45778B6AEA044A4990A96747739F303"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of subsection (a) shall be treated as a violation of a regulation under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F7408A36FF6442DBBE8E852A20E978E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Trade Commission shall enforce subsection (a) in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this Act. Any person who violates such subsection shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAEA1A0234C4A42EDA089A44436B9F552"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed to limit the authority of the Federal Trade Commission under any other provision of law.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HCA78A5D82124493DB71B2A2E778BBD46"><enum>3.</enum><header>Covered Athletic Organization Commission</header><subsection id="H0472640136E2462F96D4BC9878C2B20C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established the Covered Athletic Organization Commission (in this section referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>), the purpose of which shall be to make recommendations—</text><paragraph id="H10DD2933C3A947BCA9B2ABD64478E16A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to Congress and covered athletic organizations, on the implementation of name, image, and likeness rules;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF5594D7FFD24A14A0E5E766CA25CC12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to covered athletic organizations, on a process for certifying or recognizing credentialed athlete agents; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD471826E9314007886FAD32A5289067"><enum>(3)</enum><text>on the establishment of an independent dispute resolution process for disputes arising between a student athlete and a covered athletic organization or an institution of higher education.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF80443C2920A4CF489ECE306A00AB1F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph id="H339C3428352041CD97AD508DA45CD666"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall consist of 13 members appointed from among the following:</text><subparagraph id="H9FB3AA0644E0452482088B999D5D6C9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Representatives of institutions of higher education, including athletic directors and coaches.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6257D78BDD54782A3384E5EC1ADCA96"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Individuals who are current or former student athletes and who advocate for the interests of student athletes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FEF04AA941C4BD180032D2A826AA1FB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Administrators of covered athletic organizations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDAE93F6278548AEB424E1076F89ADC2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Professionals with expertise in sports marketing, contracting, and public relations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H657C04EE37E7433BAFAB23EF2FA68085"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Individuals—</text><clause id="H418E54FBB0434038BEB68AF8635158B5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with expertise in corporate governance; and</text></clause><clause id="H4B4C717587B241F0A6A0B50339B72AF5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>who are not associated with a covered athletic organization or institution of higher education.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC804A7ACAE534D788DCAA2383578DBF6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Student athlete advocates</header><text>At least 2 individuals described in paragraph (1)(B) shall be appointed to the Commission.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1BD8077BC2D74841A1A40EBBEFCE8E97"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appointment</header><paragraph id="HF004337004164FBAA2552E869C28CE94"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, 12 members of the Commission shall be appointed as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H23AF9CADE85148078BE509FE2D9472E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>3 members appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77725CA006EE45378BD8C7BE32E0B099"><enum>(B)</enum><text>3 members appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB719B18DBB9A4491A4C109E398841B1F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>3 members appointed by the majority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD86E8A37F8B64A64A700CD62095C9EE3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>3 members appointed by the minority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1EE064D139544D6821CA2E20064899D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chair</header><subparagraph id="HC0C15CC0C1934773B57D4BAEA249C039"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the appointment of the initial 12 members of the Commission under paragraph (1), 1 member shall be appointed to the Commission by such members, upon agreement of 8 such members on the individual to be appointed.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB66AE3F991A542659013818E1E0CE6A1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Result of inability to reach agreement</header><text>If agreement on an individual to be appointed as a member of the Commission under subparagraph (A) is not reached during the time period described in that subparagraph, the Speaker of the House of Representatives shall make the appointment of such member.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40A66E5293464D25935C3EC302F0900A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Position as chair of the Commission</header><text>The member appointed to the Commission under this paragraph shall be the chair of the Commission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H18BDCBF21C78443DB6C7041395B6ED7C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Diversity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable, the individuals making appointments under paragraphs (1) and (2) shall coordinate their appointments to ensure that the Commission reflects diversity with respect to gender, race, and sport of association, as applicable, and shall prioritize the appointment of members unaffiliated with a division or conference of a covered athletic organization.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEB12A081591F4B6E931D62A4B6ED3F1E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Meetings and quorum</header><paragraph id="H02CE6548C12D43F6A044CA7A4ED7B445"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Meeting at call of chair</header><text>Meetings of the Commission shall be held at the call of the chair of the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3632D2D9ABF3465F932BB27BA68C9011"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>A meeting of the Commission may only be held if there is a quorum of at least 7 members, including not fewer than 2 members who are individuals described in subsection (b)(1)(B).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H100154418E3E4308B967E2F710C03FC2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the Commission is constituted, and annually thereafter during the subsequent 2-year period, the Commission shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, and make available to the public, a report on the activities of the Commission that includes the recommendations made under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HEB8D41B01E904B9392FDBEE3C0696E9B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall terminate on the date that is 60 days after the date on which the Commission submits the final report required under subsection (e).</text></subsection></section><section id="H19D56474117E47DC8D14DA51A454C590"><enum>4.</enum><header>Institutions of higher education and student athletes who enter into endorsement contracts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 487(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1094">20 U.S.C. 1094(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6B323739DFA640308DB8FEEA6DF17C69" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H735C6E72D37C481FB24FDA2B6A9AD715"><enum>(30)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an institution that has a student attending the institution who is an athlete at the institution and who is entering into an endorsement contract (as defined in section 2 of the Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7801">15 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)) or an agency contract (as defined in section 10 of the Student Athlete Level Playing Field Act), such institution will not prohibit such student from entering into such contract, including through a rule, standard, or policy that affects the eligibility of such student to receive athletically related student aid (as defined in section 485(e) of this Act).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HF7F3AF2CA7874ED3883893A84D3A69FC"><enum>5.</enum><header>Prohibiting unfair or deceptive acts or practices against student athletes</header><subsection id="H36D920DB94114E00BE59057D43F322F5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibiting unfair or deceptive acts or practices by boosters</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7801">15 U.S.C. 7801 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC408D44BD4D44E95B45E95066CCD629E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 2—</text><subparagraph id="HFC86F6DC614142B3B2DC3B49D7C7B5EF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (4) through (9) as paragraphs (5) through (10), respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80BC940EE66346D884B6202164052633"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (3) the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8D0941592AB541B8BDE632D188A2F9C2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H3292A64B9E134DA08929BA2D9DE7F3CA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Booster</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>booster</term> means an individual (other than an individual who is related to an applicable student athlete) or an organization (including a sponsor) that provides substantial financial assistance or services to the athletic program of an educational institution or that promotes a team or athletic program of an educational institution for purposes of the substantial financial interest of the individual or organization.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DA50273D17248A78F7F19454D0505CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after section 3 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9B83944EA72F4784BF05E6149A1C5835" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HFD6EA91B29B34054B5F59D8972F70E81" commented="no"><enum>3A.</enum><header>Regulation of unfair or deceptive acts or practices in connection with contact between a booster and a student athlete</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is unlawful for a booster to directly or indirectly provide or offer to provide any funds or thing of value as an inducement for a student athlete to enroll at a specific educational institution or group of such institutions, including that a booster may not orally or in writing enter into a contract or agreement with a prospective student athlete to provide the prospective student athlete with consideration for the use of the name, image, or likeness of the prospective student athlete until the prospective student athlete enrolls full time at the relevant institution.</text></section><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EFE214DFB174DDCA9791481B1B3784F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 5(a)(1), by inserting <quote>or by the engagement of a booster in a practice that violates section 3A of this Act</quote> after <quote>section 3 of this Act</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6D7C883A4CE445BBA7E697AE3F2FD78A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility To compete as a student athlete after entering into an agency contract</header><paragraph id="H474B9D9A56E54266B3D680638034F9FF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3(b)(3) of the Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7802">15 U.S.C. 7802(b)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>boldface type stating:</quote> and all that follows through the end of the paragraph and inserting the following: <quote>boldface type stating: <quote>Notice to Student Athlete: If you agree orally or in writing to be represented by an agent now or in the future, both you and the agent you are agreeing to be represented by must notify the athletic director of the educational institution at which you are enrolled, or another individual responsible for the athletic programs at such educational institution, that you have entered into an agency contract. Such notification must be made within 72 hours after entering into the agreement or before the next athletic event in which you are eligible to participate, whichever occurs first.</quote>.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA610F40C03D1412DA357BA5BB5942E24"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clearinghouse</header><subparagraph id="HF6F230EA929243CDB5A7410100D8A34C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Trade Commission shall establish a clearinghouse for endorsement contracts entered into by student athletes and athlete agents who represent student athletes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8B99129BE504FF4918210635DA90FBA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Agreement disclosure required</header><clause id="H00FE18C3F6074714A20CDAB211861F81"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission shall require each student athlete and each athlete agent who represents student athletes to disclose to the clearinghouse established under subparagraph (A) each endorsement contract entered into by such student athlete or such agent with a value of more than $500.</text></clause><clause id="H641D89F0649140FA9528E4F709FF163F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>Disclosure of a contract under clause (i) shall be made not later than 72 hours after agreement on the contract.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H981EA2A853884348999F2984FB761659"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Notification of institutions</header><text>The Clearinghouse established under subparagraph (A) shall notify the relevant institution of higher education about each contract disclosed under this paragraph and shall make such disclosures available to the public on a regular basis.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6DE5C2DF2630451D97C024B2C5D4CB30"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report on claims filed pursuant to the Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7801">15 U.S.C. 7801 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by this Act, is further amended by inserting after section 6 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H32FF92E7F010420D9DD3AC464417A163" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H31C731AEF538424CB3614FD6AC73DBFA"><enum>6A.</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Commission shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report summarizing any investigations or enforcement actions brought by the Commission pursuant to this Act during the preceding 1-year period, including the number of complaints filed with the Commission pursuant to this Act during such period. </text></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H3C07F123F4F54CDF92D1833B25238133"><enum>6.</enum><header>Registration of certain agents</header><subsection id="HDC2C14FAECDD4A1B9E1532FF4A018B74"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Trade Commission shall establish a program to register athlete agents for student athletes.</text></subsection><subsection id="H91F73868A6D640BFBA5636594AD650C1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Registration required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon establishment of the program required under subsection (a), a person who enters into an agency contract with a student athlete shall register with the Federal Trade Commission as an athlete agent for student athletes.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAEDAB5CB22D9492EAF31DBAC8F0EB605"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No cost for registration</header><text>The Federal Trade Commission may not charge a fee in relation to a registration under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8B7BC5CB91C740FC8F5C02807A29D827"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enforcement by Federal Trade Commission</header><paragraph id="H7B8A6CBB34E247B78BDE6362E8EF9C8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of subsection (b) shall be treated as a violation of a regulation under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F4EA03109E342E985B31AD87C26857A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Trade Commission shall enforce subsection (b) in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the <act-name parsable-cite="FTCA">Federal Trade Commission Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this Act. Any person who violates such subsection shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66A8718F20E645218E2E2A5233E18CC7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section may be construed to limit the authority of the Federal Trade Commission under any other provision of law.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF931D9695E0A4EFBA4E89AF6ADF1B83B"><enum>7.</enum><header>State preemption</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No State may enforce a State law or regulation with respect to permitting or abridging the ability of a student athlete attending an institution of higher education to enter into an endorsement contract or agency contract pursuant to this Act or an amendment made by this Act.</text></section><section id="H4C8638BF1DC44CD78E14868AF617DA43"><enum>8.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><subsection id="HEFA6DB7753614DC6936500B89BA57A2E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Tax</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, may be construed to affect the treatment of qualified scholarships under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/117">section 117</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3CF03700249A46ECA48B2D61F9AF8AEB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nondiscrimination</header><text>Nothing in this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, may be construed to affect the rights of student athletes, or affect any program funded, under title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H3A9CF58E63E34D47B210C80A825A908F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Antitrust</header><text>Nothing in this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, may be construed to provide a cause of action pursuant to the Sherman Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1">15 U.S.C. 1 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H46C868E6A78944A28CBD293FB63FBEFF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Employee status</header><text>Nothing in this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, may be construed to affect the employment status of a student athlete who enters into an endorsement contract with respect to a covered athletic organization or an institution of higher education.</text></subsection></section><section id="HA3B62A5F85284856AC20AC6EE1216EAA"><enum>9.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HF2A246557E754584B36EED2E720B8CE4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">institutions of higher education and covered athletic organizations should develop a course or program to assist student athletes with financial literacy with respect to entering into endorsement contracts; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62DC1728B7A2419992926E1B2F74B89B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Federal Trade Commission should investigate each claim filed pursuant to the Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7801">15 U.S.C. 7801 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7DFDAED6E97E42E5A390F6C3299A1AAD"><enum>10.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H28087F73A73F4009B796D8E6B7D8F860"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency contract</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agency contract</term> means an oral or written agreement under which a student athlete authorizes a person to negotiate or solicit an endorsement contract on behalf of the student athlete.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD92114D1C7843D899A6F10D8AEEE67A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Athlete agent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>athlete agent</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2 of the Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7801">15 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD8A6D27E9674C43B5544E6BC9783DEA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered athletic organization</header><text>The term <term>covered athletic organization</term> means an athletic association, conference, or other organization with authority over intercollegiate athletics or that administers intercollegiate athletics.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36D518D460FB4F618B733914F6B04BA8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Endorsement contract</header><text>The term <term>endorsement contract</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7801">15 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA052FFF99A140A2B1315C44152EA033"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB49DF227FECB453DA1F19FA16014B371"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Student athlete</header><text>The term <term>student athlete</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2 of the Sports Agent Responsibility and Trust Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7801">15 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

