<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H88A7A3A8F07C4C8695855297E0573E4C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5800 IH: Oleksander’s Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5800</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H000874">Mr. Hoyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the imposition of sanctions to combat the mass abduction of Ukrainian children to Russia and areas of Ukraine that are temporarily occupied by Russian forces, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA46939B5B83949FDB60C8480EB478747" style="OLC"><section id="HC102875BEB0C4B0C95AB7B33623194C9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Oleksander Ivanov Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or <quote>Oleksander’s Act</quote>.</text></section><section id="HC5CB3FE8C1C34621A3BF29EBA0E45D49"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HC9AC8E1B0F62419E85B5B720375F5894"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On February 24, 2022, Russia, under the leadership of Vladimir Putin, launched a premeditated war against Ukraine in an attack on democracy and a grave violation of international law, global peace, and security. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7880CCCD66FC4682AA34DA95F6F48179"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), as of September 19, 2023, there were more than 5.8 million Ukrainian refugees recorded in Europe and more than 369,000 Ukrainian refugees recorded globally.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H118812680F7845EFAB5B14DAB3D3C23C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The unjust and brutal war has put millions of Ukrainian women and children at risk of trafficking, millions of children have been deprived of their education and are experiencing trauma, and according to a report by Yale University, more than 6,000 children are in Russians custody. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC49EABDC1A724B7F88D3242FF27D9FD9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to a report by Yale University Humanitarian Research Lab (Yale HRL), at least 6,000 children from Ukraine ages four months to 17 years have been held at camps and other facilities within Russia-occupied Crimea and mainland Russia since Russia’s full-scale invasion began. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4034881C17E247129720B63CC75A6C49"><enum>(5)</enum><text>There are at least 43 camps and facilities where the Russian government has interned Ukrainian children. Out of the various camps, 12 are situated near the Black Sea, 7 are found within Russian occupied Crimea, and 10 are grouped around the areas of Moscow, Kazan, and Yekaterinburg. In addition, 11 of these camps are positioned at distances exceeding 500 miles from Ukraine’s border with Russia, with two camps located in Siberia and one in the Far East of Russia. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4758EF406DE849089DCEB0C0A6288565"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Among the camps identified by Yale University Humanitarian Research Lab, at least 32 (78 percent) of the camps seem to be engaged in organized re-education initiatives that subject Ukrainian children to Russia-focused educational, cultural, patriotic, and/or military teachings. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H090933A4E7734110B24A8AEACD5C292F"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Yale University Humanitarian Research Lab identified two camps that housed children who were alleged to be orphans. Those children were later placed into Russian foster families. Specifically, 20 children from these camps were placed into families in Moscow and were enrolled in local schools in Moscow. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB5426248595419E92999FE48F33A050"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Ukrainian children have had their names and birthdates changed when adopted, making them difficult to trace. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0C7A7357C62451D9CE437775CEA2CCC"><enum>(9)</enum><text>This scheme is centrally coordinated by the Russian government and is comprised of actors from every level of government. According to the report by Yale HRL, there are several dozen federal, regional, and local officials that are engaged in politically justifying the program and at least 12 of these individuals are not on U.S. and/or international sanction lists. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9151F6276E0B485EA7A4DFBD2DD0AA1D"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In May 2022, President Putin signed a decree simplifying the procedure of obtaining Russian citizenship for purported Ukrainian orphans and children without parental care, thereby expediting the process of illegal adoption of deported Ukrainian children by Russian families. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H287F44A16C2C4AFDB18B28740A5AB2AC"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Forcibly transferring children of one group to another group is a violation of Article II(e) of the Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide 1948 and the Geneva Convention IV, including articles 24, 25, 50, 78, and 82. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H140C733A0FB9416183422D59EEBE2809"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The International Criminal Court has indicted Russian President Vladimir Putin and Russian Commissioner for Children’s Rights Maria Lvova-Belova for the war crime of unlawful deportation of population (children) and that of unlawful transfer of population (children) from occupied areas of Ukraine to the Russian Federation under articles 8(2)(a)(vii) and 8(2)(b)(viii) of the Rome Statute.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97F820CB34F94B79A1C788EE028CB8FE"><enum>(13)</enum><text>On August 24, 2023, the Biden Administration imposed financial blocking sanctions and pursuing visa restrictions pursuant to section 1(a)(iii)(A) of E.O. 14024 on 12 individuals and a Russian government-owned entity that <quote>played a role in forcibly deporting Ukrainian children from Russia-occupied areas of Ukraine to Russia, and/or transferring Ukrainian children within Russia-occupied areas of Ukraine.</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE806CE8B2734481B99474426AD4C706A"><enum>(14)</enum><text>As reported by the Ukrainian Ministry of Education, over 400 schools have been destroyed and an additional 2,600 schools are damaged across Ukraine. According to the United Nations Childrens Fund (UNICEF), the education of Ukrainian children is at risk, as 5.3 million children currently face barriers preventing their access to education, with 3.6 million children directly impacted by school closures. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FBB0846B82E4B85BAA553A2B52F408F"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reports by the United Nations Children’s Fund also indicate that the war is having a devastating impact on the mental health and well-being of Ukrainian children. Specifically, around 1.5 million children are at risk of depression, anxiety, post-traumatic stress disorder and other mental health issues with potential long-term effects and implications. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA747D43104C446891CDAD54E7D31BFC"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The war has also caused Ukrainian women and children to become more vulnerable to being trafficked. The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees reports that 90 percent of the 5.8 million refugees who have fled Ukraine for Europe are women and children. Reports have stated that traffickers patrol border entry points, train stations, and refugee centers with the purpose of attracting and exploiting refugees. Specifically, traffickers lure in refugees with promises of accommodation, transportation, and employment, sometimes disguising themselves as volunteers providing humanitarian assistance. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H04ED9CFD21F3435AB5AAC3F34A6C464E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States should—</text><paragraph id="H98A73F5121F34AD9BD0321DFEBA3E2B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support programs specifically for trauma treatment and healing, rehabilitation and where necessary prostheses, for Ukrainian children affected by the war against Ukraine launched by Russia including nationwide educational programs of psychological support to address trauma and stress for all Ukrainian children, integrated into school curriculum and offered through clinical and social services; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFFA5693D5354D078C174851EB1918F7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support programs to rebuild the education system in Ukraine and education for Ukrainian child refugees, in cooperation with other countries, international organizations, and civil society;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8456D4A2840549059D1B0709F8055DD0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support the development of a unified and consolidated searchable registry of missing Ukrainian children in order to facilitate identification of children and family reunification, which should ensure strict data protection and availability in the Ukrainian, Russian, and English languages;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63581939FE774696836E3C6B21338183"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure the public is made aware of the existence of, and how to use, such registry;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9FB89F57A704BBD999347B6F824950B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support the development of a unified central emergency call center hub linked to law enforcement in Ukraine and in other countries to enable reporting on and interventions on behalf of missing Ukrainian children and suspected cases of human trafficking and sexual exploitation, including online, of Ukrainian children;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52A29448D133454B86A55F8D380E4117"><enum>(6)</enum><text>support the development of an international mechanism to facilitate vetting of volunteers and other non-governmental front-line responders working with refugees or with victims of other major crises or natural disasters by law enforcement or other governmental authorities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4C13F29C1AA439393896A4130FFECBC"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support efforts (including the efforts described in paragraph (6)) to only allow appropriately vetted and credentialed individuals access to refugees;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E38ED665FC9419B8A63AF5A0B20E021"><enum>(8)</enum><text>continue to support efforts by the Government of Ukraine to increase collaboration with European counterparts on anti-trafficking investigations and increased awareness efforts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A33EB348BD94BA3B597E5D089648944"><enum>(9)</enum><text>support the development of robust child protective mechanisms for vulnerable children, including Ukrainian children, in Ukraine and in countries that have received Ukrainian refugees, that include social assistance and protection to help prevent human trafficking and sexual abuse of Ukrainian children; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8934074B1E04A5390D75AA2BE4A7B02"><enum>(10)</enum><text>work with Ukrainian authorities to ensure that law enforcement officials stationed at major border crossing points in Ukraine during a refugee crisis are appropriately trained to prevent human trafficking and support other measures to monitor for indications of human trafficking targeting refugees in areas surrounding border crossings. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H89AAB11151694C059F19C44153C1EAA4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sanctions authority</header><subsection id="HC27AC97E413947FF8110673632F948BA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may impose the sanctions described in subsection (b) with respect to any foreign person that the President, or Secretary of the Treasury (in consultation with the Secretary of State), determines is responsible for engaging in, or facilitating, any of the following:</text><paragraph id="HDBDBB571D211497B9B6E6BBDA803435F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The forced displacement, including mass abduction of Ukrainian children to Russia or Russian-controlled areas of Ukraine.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23B4BBC76E014E7685B9CA409EF31921"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The illegal forced assimilation, adoption, or placement in a foster home of Ukrainian children.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE05598627DB54A6888EB60305A65F25E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Involvement of any form in the trafficking of Ukrainians in Ukraine or Ukrainian refugees.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H246D908E47054B1C91345DF3BFC4783C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The sanctions described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H7D254EB4EF9345099A1789F7AAB33C7A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The blocking, in accordance with the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>), of all transactions in all property and interests in property of a foreign person described in subsection (a) if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34B1A827242A492588F675C31B5B2140"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visas, admission, or parole</header><subparagraph id="H28D4D5515E874FC3A9217CC4A7A69C0D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Visas, admission, or parole</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A foreign person described in subsection (a) may be—</text><clause id="HC244BCAD29734ADAA97BCC1F2DADA206"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States; </text></clause><clause id="H38CB6B5754FC4F4884528671B5EC6EE4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and </text></clause><clause id="H468FFB22B0A24377AD984A75B1A3EEA5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFDCC40A887E64773872A0F527F4E6A85"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Current visas revoked</header><clause id="HB5C975E60CA347268DC9F55E5AB7E3F2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A foreign person described in subsection (a) may be subject to revocation of any visa or other entry documentation regardless of when the visa or other entry documentation is or was issued.</text></clause><clause id="H772D53AFA67F4652BA0BFBF90FA56DCC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Immediate effect</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A revocation under clause (i) shall—</text><subclause id="H172C73EFED97438AA00C435BB9B6A36F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>take effect immediately; and </text></subclause><subclause id="H64462D8B32BE400892E8173A241025F0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>automatically cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the possession of the foreign person.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H80BCE2E37DF644DBAFBCA5A678B8C73F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exception To comply with international obligations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions under this section shall not apply with respect to a foreign person if admitting or paroling the person into the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9E25458FD32E44659737AC73F74BAFFD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority to impose sanctions under this section shall terminate on the date that is 6 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6E80288148F24EBB81D6FE61721B513B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees and the Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe (commonly referred to as the <quote>U.S. Helsinki Commission</quote>) a report on United States efforts for the reintegration of Ukrainian children affected by the war against Ukraine launched by Russia, including a description of any such efforts to support—</text><paragraph id="H1275710105694E84A83F3C073178E289"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the rebuilding and redevelopment of the Ukrainian education system; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A58CA11116845C8BCE8B6163AB4978C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the implementation of mental health programs to address trauma and family separations among such Ukrainian children.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB3EE9814E11D4CAAAC3183E432050E9F"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HB9E90BBB772A4578823C84AE7B83BF44"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69021EFFC8194F50ACA5FBCF3A3D6A35"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Child</header><text>The term <quote>child</quote> means an individual under the age of 18.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B85F579DC8B4906A94D753F1E80A2CA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Ukrainian child</header><text>The term <quote>Ukrainian child</quote> means a child born in Ukraine or an inhabitant of Ukraine, regardless of whether the child is subsequently trafficked or forced to assume Russian citizenship.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

