<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2BA1A4BE19184D6A899ECD8394AEA2B7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6456 IH: Confronting Police Violence Against Children Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6456</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231117">November 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the National Institute of Justice to collect, study, and analyze data on incidents in which children have been seriously harmed or killed by law enforcement officers who were acting in their capacity as law enforcement officers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE3365FBF40BD4BCE9F636E2F8211D3CD" style="OLC"><section id="HF8CA3E9A95384D47A3C17A345C65A4D2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Confronting Police Violence Against Children Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6CEB3B7CE830403FAEEED60D6DEAF03F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H90A00C9CC3364447B8BF0E026CE9CE41"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The duty of American law enforcement is to uphold the law and to serve and protect the public.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C149EB89E6D4597BFD6F3210A968650"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Many law enforcement officers are dedicated to public service and perform their duties diligently and responsibly, creating safer communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51A3F7B2ADB243DDAEBAC9972E5DCA09"><enum>(3)</enum><text>There have been multiple reports in recent years of children being seriously harmed or killed by law enforcement officers who were acting in their capacity as law enforcement officers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC244E4B83A1E4B88A5393A9FC390C39A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In 2014, 12-year-old Tamir Rice was shot and killed by a law enforcement officer in Ohio within seconds of the officer arriving on the scene.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07BB80E99AD34EC1B78D61B12EA31782"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In 2017, 17-year-old Armando Garcia-Muro was shot and killed by a ricocheting bullet, which was fired by a law enforcement officer at a dog in California. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD8970C1422D4299A64D03891BDD832E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 2018, 16-year-old Anthony Jacob <quote>AJ</quote> Weber was shot and killed by a law enforcement officer in California who fired several shots into his upper body.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF737E641FDC849F3B720FB95F9031FAF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In 2020, 16-year-old Eric Parsa, who had autism, died in Louisiana after being restrained face down on the pavement for over 9 minutes by multiple law enforcement officers, one of whom put him in a choke hold, while Parsa was experiencing a mental health crisis.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71204A38A78A4348BF822BAE06580E29"><enum>(8)</enum><text>In 2020, 13-year-old Linden Cameron, who has Asperger’s Syndrome, was shot by a law enforcement officer in Utah while experiencing a mental health crisis, after his mother dialed 911 for help.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFABC5195AE634FF6890274853B0E7F89"><enum>(9)</enum><text>In 2021, 1-year-old Legend Smalls was shot in the head by a law enforcement officer in Texas after the officer opened fire on a suspect who allegedly attempted to steal the vehicle in which Smalls was seated.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E12860A37F64557A0E585EB15ECB1A9"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In 2021, 13-year-old Adam Toledo was fatally shot by a law enforcement officer in Illinois while his hands were in the air.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84ECDA198DC44150828696D37D5578FF"><enum>(11)</enum><text>In 2021, 14-year-old Valentina Orellana-Peralta was shot and killed by a law enforcement officer in California.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE0009342DF74ADB99BC68C6BB664EC6"><enum>(12)</enum><text>In 2022, a 13-year-old boy identified as <quote>A.G.</quote> was shot by a law enforcement officer in Illinois causing a major spinal cord injury while his hands were in the air.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA417951F87EC48708BB6942E11130355"><enum>(13)</enum><text>In 2023, 11-year-old Aderrien Murry was shot in the chest by a law enforcement officer in Mississippi after he called the police to his home for help.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H003CA7A1660F491890219B11C5A722D5"><enum>(14)</enum><text>In 2023, 14-year-old Jor’Dell Richardson was fatally shot and killed by a law enforcement officer in Colorado. Jor’Dell Richardson begged to be taken to the hospital before he died.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78B7716AD48D4A50AF99C09BF9C6AC60"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Law enforcement officers lack the training and resources necessary to effectively address issues of mental health, and these issues may be more appropriately handled with assistance from mental health experts and social workers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20C0EAFBA09C4A74B65A754AD1147137"><enum>(16)</enum><text>Reports of incidents in which children are killed by law enforcement officers erode the trust of the American people in law enforcement officers and the agencies and systems they represent, and such reports therefore undermine the ability of law enforcement officers and agencies to carry out their mission of protecting the public.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBFB620B596149ABB7DB47CAE22FA611"><enum>(17)</enum><text>A thorough investigation of the circumstances surrounding incidents of children being seriously harmed or killed by law enforcement officers would help policymakers enact policies to address these tragic incidents of violence in order to protect children and improve the effectiveness of law enforcement. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H7ED0AB1FE32948DA8904557158589DE3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report and recommendations</header><subsection id="HCFD09F9FECD64987902E09055C6B9531"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Institute of Justice shall prepare and submit a report to Congress studying incidents in which children were seriously harmed or killed by Federal, State, Tribal, or local law enforcement officers who were acting in their official capacity as law enforcement officers (whether or not the officer was on duty) during the 15-year period prior to the date of enactment of this Act. </text></subsection><subsection id="H104017CF730649B6A35EBF9967B35F57"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Required review</header><text>In preparing the report required under this section, the Director shall, at a minimum, review and include in the report the following: </text><paragraph id="H13AA9F09DEFE4D7D85036D4230037421"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Demographic data and analysis pertaining to—</text><subparagraph id="H33411A006E224F4C93947BE682FED1CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the age of the victims;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D165F413F6D42B9B58027C75796A41B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the race and ethnicity of the victims;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AA8E701A3334E1E9B87ABB0FDEDF816"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the gender of the victims; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD14E9800EEA64716B04AFE918949C1D5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the socioeconomic status of the victims. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EC4B5A59D314819B3EAB4938BDA8CE7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Information and analysis pertaining to—</text><subparagraph id="HAADAED421D9646F89D5FF7F516B1849A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the officers who were responsible for each incident of serious harm or death were affiliated with Federal, State, Tribal, or local law enforcement agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H231E596D5E6742A88D073702F551B145"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the rank, years of experience, and amount of training the officers had at the time of the incidents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86FBD1946FBA421085CC4B1AECAE8317"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the incidents occurred in urban, suburban, rural, or tribal locations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DEBAF6C1EDD4703B46C65BE8BCF9017"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the circumstances surrounding the incidents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F3D761A29D14284B52A241F6B860240"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the seriousness of the harm suffered by the victims, including the extent to which the harm was fatal;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94D1B4636ABF42CE8A698A3AB103399B"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the victims had developmental, physical, or mental disabilities at the time of the incidents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BF47EFA8ECA47B4844A4951E00B1C07"><enum>(G)</enum><text>whether the victims were experiencing a mental health crisis at the time of the incidents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB3E01C8F19E446EAAF1965378D6D914"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the presence and use of recording devices by the law enforcement officers during the incidents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1FB07676A8B4C81B39B069385A9C1A6"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the presence and use of recording devices by bystanders during the incidents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB857553EE1DF46F7801D1E9BA634648C"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the incidents involved harm to or the death of other individuals, including other law enforcement officers, associates of the child, or members of the public, and if so, whose actions directly led to the additional deaths or harm;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E2D6D52E0704B29A4C0543C9E009AF1"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reports of excessive force having been used by the law enforcement officers prior to the incidents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86F3C8B761CA41568194F9A7CE083BF9"><enum>(L)</enum><text>whether the use of force by the law enforcement officers was determined to be justified and proportional, on what basis any such determination was made, and by whom; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H377BCECD47304F4CB5E896867DB0FB54"><enum>(M)</enum><text>the consequences faced by the law enforcement officers who were responsible for the harm or death. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H32323198644B4016A4D7F839A9F975C1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Required consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In preparing the report required under this section, the Director shall meet with, and consider any facts and analyses offered by, prosecutors, defense attorneys, family attorneys, judges, medical experts, non-profit organizations, victims service providers, culturally specific organizations, Federal, State, Tribal, and local courts, Federal, State, Tribal, and local law enforcement agencies, State and local elected officials, and individuals with academic expertise in the study of law enforcement.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC128DEC8F08B40A7B1A1F0AFD6C9FA0A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Findings and recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall include in the report required under this section recommendations regarding—</text><paragraph id="HBDEA7A6B04D64FB1802AED1EC4B0E8B2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">best practices or guidelines for law enforcement agencies to adopt in order to prevent the excessive use of force by law enforcement officers and protect children from the excessive use of force;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBF4DEA151EC495B920F40CDB565629E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the best practices to train and equip law enforcement officers to handle situations involving children, including—</text><subparagraph id="HBBFCD63234584EBD955539202AF141FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>children with physical and mental disabilities; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H445CB105F7E14587B01883D422C8EC34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>children experiencing mental health crises;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7902AAB869E44F283269CF9960AB377"><enum>(3)</enum><text>best practices to ensure that children described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (2) receive help from qualified professionals who are equipped to deescalate situations and provide the proper resources to families; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE9D8CF7EE0740D7BCF39A405AB50959"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal legislation to prevent the excessive use of force by law enforcement officers and protect children from the excessive use of force.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5551C808A4CC467284F6301BC8E4100D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>child</term> means an individual who is under 18 years of age. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

