<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE0CB2552E8544E1F9BAE29F11541405E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3718 IH: Department of Veterans Affairs Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Processing Claims Improvement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3718</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to take certain actions to improve the processing by the Department of Veterans Affairs of claims for disability compensation for post-traumatic stress disorder, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC7DFD2B51BC549FF9879A147D826208A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H186283A6C2174DA193C9C69BD779FDB8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Veterans Affairs Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Processing Claims Improvement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H817F004015154779BF19B0DA2126E6C3" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improving processing by Department of Veterans Affairs of disability claims for post-traumatic stress disorder</header> <subsection id="HFA3D9725003C4D4CBDC8FCF77DDA0162"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Training for claims processors who handle claims relating to post-Traumatic stress disorder</header> <paragraph id="H27B62ACC31F34DAD82E54D96D3BF61CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Update training programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall, acting through the Under Secretary for Benefits, update an ongoing, national training program for claims processors who review claims for compensation for service-connected post-traumatic stress disorder.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H48AB0DDB24B64C0FA22417CA4BAA431B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Participation required</header><text>Beginning on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall require that each claims processor described in paragraph (1) participates in the training established under paragraph (1) at least once each year beginning in the second year in which the claims processor carries out the duties of the claims processor for the Department.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4336D359E03347F2A78D5639077F58BE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Required elements</header><text>The training established under paragraph (1) shall include instruction on stressor development and verification. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HED1CF8A009444AAE89484AD8D2C12A3C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Standardization of training at regional offices</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary, acting through the Under Secretary, shall standardize the training provided at regional offices of the Veterans Benefits Administration to the employees of such regional offices.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDE5E468C81AA4D55A0ED8A0C76EADDB7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Formal process for conduct of annual analysis of trends</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary, acting through the Under Secretary, shall establish a formal process to analyze, on an annual basis, training needs based on identified processing error trends.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HA68576781C604C49A1B4DBA556EABBD0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Formal process for conduct of annual studies</header>
<paragraph id="HBC3B8EE9E1024443909C599CA9A6AC5A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary, acting through the Under Secretary, shall establish a formal process to conduct, on an annual basis, studies to help guide the national training program established under subsection (a)(1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6F3FE197C05E4C58BEA0627EF41FE534"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Each study conducted under paragraph (1) shall cover the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H815D11539BDE48D496B754DCEEDEA6FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Military post-traumatic stress disorder stressors.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H515B659D5F184DD19B4ECBB44FF4FC21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Decision-making claims for claims processors.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2EFC78E37F22486BAB58B1DFA64F2B2C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual updates to post-Traumatic stress disorder procedural guidance</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and not less frequently than once each year thereafter, the Secretary, acting through the Under Secretary, shall evaluate the guidance relating to post-traumatic stress disorder to determine if updates are warranted to provide claims processors of the Department with better resources regarding best practices for claims processing, including specific guidance regarding development of claims involving compensation for service-connected post-traumatic stress disorder.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

