<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H75D4111247CC4EC68E93E519653BCB4D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3168 IH: To establish a Joint Autonomy Office in the Department of Defense, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3168</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish a Joint Autonomy Office in the Department of Defense, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HC060F4EC4925434495E36BE0107731E7" style="OLC">
<section id="H586AB7F0D0C8496EB89057840A2765C1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of the Joint Autonomy Office</header>
<subsection id="H7FB1CF93BA974F7DAC4E6DCD6300AF06"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer, shall establish an Office in the Department of Defense to coordinate and accelerate the delivery of all-domain autonomous systems to operational users.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H501476519E594CFE9D77D7F34CCCC2BF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The office established under subsection (a) shall be known as the <quote>Joint Autonomy Office</quote> (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H0E4929E8A64D45B39BABF034A170D2A6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Head of Office</header><text>The head of the Office shall be a Director appointed by the Secretary of Defense from among individuals with management experience and technical expertise in all-domain autonomous system technologies.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H97927F185D624349898811EF6581C13B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The duties of the Joint Autonomy Office are following:</text>
<paragraph id="H4172C4E432A24FEC952B992D811B1BAD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Utilize commercial and defense best practices and existing investments in defense cloud infrastructure to accelerate the delivery of autonomous systems to the operational user.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEC94820986754C788A2BB9474321A404"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Implement an all-domain enterprise autonomous systems software development and testing platform across classification levels of the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H013FCCC9CED5453080E24FECCC2CE4EB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide access to defense programs with autonomy requirements to accelerate the development and testing of all-domain autonomous systems.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA9A856F07EF34453B5B0306035D59CBC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Implement an enterprise all-domain data acquisition and curation process to build, manage, and sustain datasets from all available autonomy programs of the Department in order to develop and test all-domain autonomous systems.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H483886CA4E2643BBB0386CD57A62329F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide access to existing and future service and joint autonomous system development and acquisition programs, including such programs as the Optionally Manned Fighting Vehicle, Robotic Combat Vehicles, Collaborative Combat Aircraft, and Large Unmanned Surface Vehicle, as development and testing datasets mature.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39BDECF108C048308211D2E6B590F6A5"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Accelerate the Department’s development and testing of all-domain autonomous system prototypes to scaled production in conjunction with service and joint autonomous system development and acquisition and the combatant commands.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF0E871B241FC4D1683B64BC262BE289D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Accelerate the Department’s development and operational test and evaluation of all-domain autonomous systems in conjunction with service and joint test community and the combatant commands.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4A90738A1BA84F1E88CAB95E85D009BE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Continuously solicit and utilize joint warfighter feedback on requirements and capability progress in the development process.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4B7CD1D313D1490F8A26229E143092B3"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Ensure that the development environments, generated data for autonomous system development, and any prototype all-domain autonomous system technologies, are designed to transition to full sustainment within the programs of the military departments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H60611A5976F34FF39C9A23C040FFDC0F"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Ensure that knowledge of proper autonomous system program design and execution, including software development, test, and acquisition best practices, is transitioned to service program executive offices with unmanned and autonomous system requirements.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4F46FECD87DE4705A6867599E1A6EF9F"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Carry out such other activities relating to the coordination, development, and delivery of autonomous systems as the Secretary of Defense determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3178A7D665DF47B4BF5B0D2301471D95"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Hiring authorities</header> <paragraph id="H9AE51714E60F498CA8B050657A4054F7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Highly qualified experts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Pursuant to the authority provided under section 9903 of title 5, United States Code, the Secretary of Defense may establish within the Office up to 12 Highly Qualified Expert positions to facilitate the rapid hiring of technical program managers with experience in the development, test, production, and delivery of all-domain autonomous systems. The Secretary may extend the term of each such Highly Qualified Expert for a period of not more than seven years.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H581FEBCDC3F3490395C9A7E18891360C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Excepted service hiring authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each position in the Joint Autonomy Office shall be a position in the excepted service, and the Secretary may appoint individuals to such positions in the same manner as provided under section 1599f of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7E9614A6FDB0462E8EDD4A5845BD4E46"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Data access and related authorities</header> <paragraph id="H6F18304E1C704F05A85DC1C90561C457"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Data access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall ensure that the Joint Autonomy Office—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF040AAB4F6594A1A9E4B0EA198224467"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subject to the implementation of the security protocols described in paragraph (2), has unlimited access to existing datasets within service and joint autonomous system, artificial intelligence, and legacy platform and sensor programs regardless of classification level; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4430A6C8A37348F885F92F429427EC0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has the authority to centralize access to such data and information, as required to carry out the duties of the Office.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H698154D810EE4A2FAE0D8A6FFA3A06D2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Security protocols</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall implement appropriate security protocols to protect any data and other information shared with or maintained by the Office under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H755CA927F45140AD844DD66313115773"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Contracting authorities and limitations</header> <paragraph id="H88979E3CE16B4621A14265FF87A1F835"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the Office—</text>
<subparagraph id="H835DEA1F834A4769B57D70B71137276B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subject to paragraph (2), may enter into contracts with private sector, non-Government entities, as appropriate, for the purposes of leveraging innovative commercial technologies to aid and facilitate the execution of the duties of the Office; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAAB25BA693A941769F502DC7325C8B9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall ensure that all programs administered by the Office are carried out in accordance with section 3453 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H491061B7DF36498C9040C22892E5ACFF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office may coordinate with other offices of the Department of Defense with contracting authority as required to carry out the duties described in subsection (d).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4FC734ED019244189A1E3838753E3EC4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Director of the Office shall ensure that the activities of the Office are conducted in accordance with Department of Defense policies and in coordination with the research and development programs of the Department.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H0B693E2525524E7CB8D7BC319F05C420"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall provide to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives a briefing on the status of the establishment of the Office under this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H601B265606CA4FB7B54B481B9973B5C6" commented="no"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Termination</header> <paragraph id="H9270B63B3906444D8BCAD9F27543EB21" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Office shall terminate on the date that is seven years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6FAEB611B53C4DB3937AC713D7DA8A3C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Extension</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may extend the termination date under paragraph (1) for one or more additional periods of seven years if—</text> <subparagraph id="H57F35CAE7A9C402E8458F6071BC8B3FC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>if the Secretary determines that such an extension is in the best interest of the Department of Defense; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H522B6FFE9538465BAF96469E418DF625" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submits to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives notice of the Secretary’s intent to make such an extension.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE40564FB0D6346AFAE62AF78B1B3A718"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H92C106AB132A427097CFC45FCA7E68F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>all-domain</term>, when used with respect to an autonomous system, means interoperability across one or more of the ground, aerial, maritime, and space domains.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF35CD4A65A742D98359118870956E0F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>autonomous system</term> means a system with the ability to conduct integrated sensing, perception, communication, decision-making, and action within specific boundaries and independently from a human operator’s instruction.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6718D623F997480BADCEE32EB62E8A95"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer</term> has the meaning given that term in section 846(b) of the James M. Inhofe National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/263">Public Law 117–263</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBAFA2ABFE07140789D759518CBA6C487"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>operational test and evaluation</term> has the meaning given that term in section 4171(h) of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H079EABC75E664A53B242583FDAD747E3"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Department of Defense $55,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HE5DD5A2D40A94AC78F6BDF02732A1557" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Framework for classification of autonomous capabilities</header> <subsection id="H7AF90056D08D4FF5ABE3E5BC4F2A667A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date on which Joint Autonomy Office is established pursuant to section 1, the Director of the Office, in consultation with the Under Secretary of Defense for Policy, the Under Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering, the commanders of the combatant commands, and the Secretaries of the military departments, shall establish a Department-wide classification framework for autonomous capabilities.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H4861686A6BBF465BAB262825C0A1E664"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the framework required under subsection (a) shall be to facilitate the development of a common understanding within the Department of Defense of autonomous capabilities and related operational requirements to better plan for, resource, and integrate appropriate autonomy-enabling hardware and software into current and future systems across the Department.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE5FB4CECB62B43B8BE40897563A0C479"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Autonomy classification framework</header><text>At a minimum, the framework required under subsection (a) shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H0E34292B64DD4A4E965987E9CC2D126D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include multiple levels of increasingly complex autonomous maneuver capability with a focus on classifying necessary levels of human supervision or control during operational use;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67C5026A2F2B4DF99BBBDE58B3526B27"><enum>(2)</enum><text>apply to current and future autonomous systems operating across land, air, maritime, and space domains;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9A0011EB1E544F09866F18E1D953B6C6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include estimates of costs necessary to achieve specific levels of autonomous capability; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H03AB2E1625A2476EBA26E600BB5DEF8B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>include—</text>
<subparagraph id="HEC41A104D5E54B4182100F8826157C95"><enum>(A)</enum><text>operational requirements including necessary levels of survivability in GPS- or communications-denied environments;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H630B6B25C6C747FF9A719F10957DB5A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>specific operational or engagement scenarios; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA4A8EA135CAD464FACDDC669365DEF92"><enum>(C)</enum><text>necessary levels of teaming with other autonomous systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE84C44C5588C4A66B552428045805CCB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Progress report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the establishment of the framework under subsection (a), the Director of the Joint Autonomy Office shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report that includes a description of the framework and the specific methodologies, criteria, and operational requirements used to develop the classifications under the framework.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HA0439E0BBF1D44A5A72CF1E0A4FA6F94"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Regular reassessment</header>
<paragraph id="H6E62E06EE69E4F4BBE596C9D7828E0E9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not less frequently than once every two years, Director of the Joint Autonomy Office shall reassess and update the classification framework required under subsection (a) to ensure the framework incorporates recent developments in technology, standards, and operational requirements relating to autonomous capabilities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A5D6596D96E462891225E2610EF0FCA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 30 days of the completion of each reassessment under paragraph (1), the Director of the Joint Autonomy Office shall provide to the congressional defense committees a briefing on the results of the reassessment and any resulting revisions to the classification framework under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6BF0E34EEF09448BB1317475241C5004"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the establishment of the framework under subsection (a), the Under Secretary of Defense for Policy shall issue instructions to the military services to implement such framework by operationalizing the use of the framework in the planning and budgeting processes of individual program offices.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HD8361C782D2C4E8AB94EEC33D413977F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Plan for integration of autonomous capabilities into systems of the Department of Defense</header> <subsection id="H3FCE7CB5B5DB4ED1981F602F77BF1F20"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date on which Joint Autonomy Office is established pursuant to section 1, the Director of the Joint Autonomy Office shall develop and implement a plan and procedures to standardize the planning, resourcing, and integration efforts with respect to autonomous capabilities for current and future systems across the Department.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HF161A76B924046889EA01867C3C640F3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The plan required under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H02BE496758BB4FB79232BFB045D77E73"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A Department-wide assessment of the status of efforts to resource and integrate autonomy software into current and future systems, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="HFDA5072EF51B42E9B90688DF4DC9C206"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the identification of current and future systems across the Department which can be integrated with autonomy software to enable continuous operational capability of such systems in GPS- or communications-denied environments, including those systems identified in the report required by section 246 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/81">Public Law 117–81</external-xref>; 135 Stat. 1622); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2797AF8C384244979352412B34ABE37A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of gaps in—</text>
<clause id="H15CBA39B79BB493090812DA272027A44"><enum>(i)</enum><text>program funding related to the acquisition of autonomy software;</text></clause> <clause id="HD191E2B5A8BB49E58993EFCCFAD8832A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>acquisition processes, including the planning, programming, budgeting, and execution process for acquiring and integrating autonomy-enabling capabilities across relevant programs of record;</text></clause>
<clause id="HB54D3D27B2F44A1791403C7A8098E0CB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>training capabilities;</text></clause> <clause id="H8539D50F7BAA480AA6EE6DE0EF0C3120"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>testing, evaluation, verification, and validation capabilities in all environments, including virtual and real world environments; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HEE6243A9FE8A48F1A8968104C86C0846"><enum>(v)</enum><text>efforts to test, resource, and scale commercially available technologies.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA718EC98B174959AF202DB9935051CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A plan to address, to the maximum extent practicable, the gaps assessed in paragraph (1), including—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB74DE075259547FAA6FF18BA17B3C55A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>updated procedures to plan for autonomy software costs at the onset of the acquisition life cycle;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H89ED3EB462504837A2585E2EAE5E0116"><enum>(B)</enum><text>plans to include in greater detail the projected autonomy software costs for applicable programs of record within period covered by the Future Years Defense Program; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H60ADA933169D4C798923E3FB97C2D1CD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>plans to standardize the acquisition of autonomy software for programs of record across the military services including the use of the capability classification framework required in section 2 of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H608DB171479A419889634638C3917A85"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Director of the Joint Autonomy Office shall develop the plan under subsection (a) in consultation with—</text>
<paragraph id="H2D721499DA3842C7BFD41221A30F460E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD6CEBA84AF7A401BA021031D470332B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Chief Digital and Artificial Intelligence Officer;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H76F7F31C90744AD085111C727304954D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Joint Chiefs of Staff;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23A52ECD7FAA4849BE55C37058377BE9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the senior acquisition executive of each military service;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H186F3423A5B144289085F2312F58BEA3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the commanders of the combatant commands; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE031BDF7A9443BCB9E7D161303A6B44"><enum>(6)</enum><text>such other organizations and elements of the Department of Defense as the Director determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7DF05BB156CA45D7B5E55A5CD11461BD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header>
<paragraph id="H47DA8B5A4F9446D384A8109C37D797DF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the completion of the plan under subsection (a), the Director of the Joint Autonomy Office shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report that describes the specific elements of the plan.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61F4AEAA50E5444A8DC279A393777375"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report under paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may contain a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


