<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA5EFEEA47E644B0C95EAA776CA02CA66" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2517 IH: Retirement Forfeiture for Members of Congress Turned Foreign Lobbyists Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2517</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230406">April 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that a former Member of Congress or former senior Congressional employee who receives compensation as a lobbyist representing a foreign principal shall not be eligible for retirement benefits or certain other Federal benefits.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA5AABF354AE64DBDB91072B2849FA67E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H21846D0AC14F4653AA1717B60A1DE92F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Retirement Forfeiture for Members of Congress Turned Foreign Lobbyists Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCAF6BA9122414C8B96172361E46A64C9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition relating to certain Federal benefits for a former Member of Congress or former senior Congressional employee who receives compensation as a lobbyist representing foreign principal</header> <subsection id="H5B9EDB78477E431CA7443D5C7051DD1F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered individual who is a registered lobbyist shall not be eligible for any covered benefits for any month—</text>
<paragraph id="H6894E56497C942C7A8EDA53C110F8143"><enum>(1)</enum><text>which begins after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC019D2829ACA4485842141693D8C9492"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in or for which such covered individual is—</text>
<subparagraph id="HEF55DF649DE446D4B42A705F1BF1B7B0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>employed as a lobbyist who represents a foreign principal; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC087DB3325DC42AF9CBD1E5BC6701C5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>entitled to compensation as a lobbyist who represents a foreign principal.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6E9378EF6C254A9CBDC3BA1F86FE4885"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <term>covered individual</term> means an individual who becomes a former Member of Congress or a former senior Congressional employee after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8FE813006F324D518429EA70B2FF0D0F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered benefits</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>covered benefits</term>, as used with respect to a covered individual, means any payment or other benefit which is payable, by virtue of service performed by such covered individual, under any of the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H87AAC5791CE74DF6AE3DC6A786B166A1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Civil Service Retirement System, including the Thrift Savings Plan.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4B5E82793D7F481FB32E201D286E675A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Federal Employees Retirement System, including the Thrift Savings Plan.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H381CF7EE338040B09EA4800EAD4D36F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Federal Employees Health Benefits Program, including enhanced dental benefits and enhanced vision benefits under chapters 89A and 89B, respectively, of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H03CED0C068CF45B388D0BB879F364F67"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Federal Employees’ Group Life Insurance Program.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE27D3A16DFEE412FA161670B67293A15"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text> <paragraph id="HD778274D18BB426BB8C2A4344C71FB66"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>Member of Congress</term> means a Senator, Member of the House of Representatives, or Delegate to the House of Representatives, and the Resident Commissioner from Puerto Rico;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA7464DAA15C94A1DA8D5AA41AEC25560"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>senior Congressional employee</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HEC6FE9EA519E41BF831E90202C86C814"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each officer or employee of the legislative branch (except any officer or employee of the Government Accountability Office) who, for at least 60 days, occupies a position for which the rate of basic pay is equal to or greater than 120 percent of the minimum rate of basic pay payable for GS–15 of the General Schedule;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8C774C98365548A4A5C3591F59E592B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each officer or employee of the Government Accountability Office who, for at least 60 consecutive days, occupies a position for which the rate of basic pay, minus the amount of locality pay that would have been authorized under section 5304 of title 5, United States Code (had the officer or employee been paid under the General Schedule), for the locality within which the position of such officer or employee is located (as determined by the Comptroller General), is equal to or greater than 120 percent of the minimum rate of basic pay payable for GS–15 of the General Schedule; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H40BE54D9C38C4F97B5473E3B0A6F60DF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at least one principal assistant designated for purposes of this paragraph by each Member who does not have an employee who occupies a position for which the rate of basic pay is equal to or greater than 120 percent of the minimum rate of basic pay payable for GS–15 of the General Schedule;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H57AA389E19DB42F4996233F3ABBDCB89"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>registered lobbyist</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HBD79109CE40740A0AE141284CE80C952"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a lobbyist registered or required to register, or on whose behalf a registration is filed or required to be filed, under section 4 of the Lobbying Disclosure Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1603">2 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H78A389DA9D2B46CD87991545000D136D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an individual registered or required to register as the agent of a foreign principal under the Foreign Agents Registration Act of 1938, as amended (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/611">22 U.S.C. 611 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H84405D63F6A64A3DBB55D650DE1569E0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>lobbyist</term> has the meaning given such term by section 3 of the Lobbying Disclosure Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1602">2 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAFB27D0B00614506BBA7FAC2517F1FB9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>foreign principal</term> has the meaning given such term by section 1(b) of the Foreign Agents Registration Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/611">22 U.S.C. 611(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7825BE90841C4BA6B9FAD151ED506CD0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be considered to prevent the payment of—</text>
<paragraph id="H789B27068DF246CA9C894A0D7173A841"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any lump-sum credit, as defined by section 8331(8) or 8401(19) of title 5, United States Code, to which an individual is entitled; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCDC4EDD73B2C4CBB8BB2CD98F2DBFCE9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any amount in the account of an individual in the Thrift Savings Fund which, as of the date on which paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (a) are first met with respect to such individual, is nonforfeitable.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7CCC013D03914AEB8AA412DC16447FE2"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Any regulations necessary to carry out this section may be prescribed—</text> <paragraph id="H13C33C3BB9CC47A2AC443115F07115F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>except as provided in paragraph (2), by the Director of the Office of Personnel Management; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDF6CE4D9DC6E4AA4BDC5E11B4FB58E6D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the extent that this Act relates to the Thrift Savings Plan, by the Executive Director (as defined by section 8401(13) of title 5, United States Code).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

