<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFAD99F531F054BDD8DB289DD473D98E4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4934 IH: To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a standardized training curriculum for military vehicle operations.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4934</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a standardized training curriculum for military vehicle operations.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC5047159006A4D9EB7BC83260C732A44" style="OLC"><section id="H565BB16A5A1A424E8913B6FF060F87F0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Military vehicle operator training program</header><subsection id="H98AF957774D3452483156D5C0F084A2D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of training curriculum</header><paragraph id="HEEDD347246EE42C0ABF41DD3EDA5A869"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall establish a standardized training curriculum for military vehicle operations, encompassing both classroom and practical training components.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DCA64DEA56A41B6BDE8A0060892AE6C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Development</header><text>The training curriculum under paragraph (1) shall be developed in collaboration with subject matter experts, experienced members of the Armed Forces, and relevant stakeholders, and shall cover essential topics such as vehicle dynamics, safety procedures, hazard recognition and avoidance, defensive driving techniques, and vehicle recovery methods.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14C639E8C2ED4746BA5AC2B536B54474"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall ensure that the training curriculum under paragraph (1) is regularly updated to incorporate emerging best practices and technological advancements in military vehicle operations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9C0245E92E374232AEAA0E154587C3EF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification program</header><paragraph id="HC805FB639F6243C4A8B298CF5015AB05"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall establish a certification program to validate the proficiency of members of the Armed Forces in military vehicle operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5F0C092C1D9472BA2FE5B7184EA4F88"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Design of program</header><text>The certification program shall be designed to ensure that all members of the Armed Forces, regardless of deployment status, receive adequate training in military vehicle operations before being assigned to operational duty.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4E264661AEE48EBB6C4DFEDD1F079EF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Assessments</header><text>The certification program shall include written exams, practical assessments, and evaluations of demonstrated competence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECB1EA7A5DC744CD9557F9499CF8C3C2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Notice of completion</header><text>Notice shall be issued to members of the Armed Forces who successfully complete the training program and meet the established proficiency criteria.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4C57E08D9F8644439E92BDC87811BC17"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><paragraph id="HFADE56035F864BA3A90F8F57EEFE1F76"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deadline for commencement</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall commence the development and implementation of the training curriculum under subsection (a) and the certification program under subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDCF6D22D25847E9A1C6E922AEE387E9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for full integration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than three years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the training curriculum under subsection (a) and the certification program under subsection (b) shall be fully integrated into military training programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA39485ED56364F7084D308CF6DDB6D53"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Training delivery methods</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the Secretary of Defense shall—</text><paragraph id="H9FC036F229174D1CA51EAAC7BA252CE6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop a comprehensive and interactive training methodology that combines traditional classroom instruction with hands-on, practical training exercises;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDFAA95935434DDFA177640CE0E81295"><enum>(2)</enum><text>encourage the use of modern training technologies, simulators, and realistic training environments to enhance effectiveness of the training program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H990577D0821248CF86E05C3B7E7EBBE3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>ensure that training materials are up-to-date, accessible, and tailored to the specific vehicle types and operational environments members of the Armed Forces are likely to encounter.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCA4376265FC54160AF178439EDB01B7C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Information collection and evaluations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the Secretary of Defense shall—</text><paragraph id="H42D389BE1D0341009266277908E69C29"><enum>(1)</enum><text>update reporting mechanisms used to collect and analyze data related to military vehicle incidents, including vehicle rollovers, and the causes of such incidents;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D4E5B560055487CB141E82BAF14B18E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>conduct regular evaluations of the effectiveness of the training under this section in reducing incidents and improving the proficiency of military vehicle operators; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H712E1B7BFDD248F6B4B0565A8539F4FC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promptly implement any recommendations for program improvements based on the results of such data and evaluations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

