<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEFD85340D7724A5B85E847331C58F613" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5106 IH: To direct the Secretary of Agriculture to publish criteria for the review of requests by certain meat or poultry establishments to operate at alternate inspection rates, to review and respond to such requests, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5106</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230801">August 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001116">Mr. Clyde</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000470">Mrs. Fischbach</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000603">Mr. Rouzer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Agriculture to publish criteria for the review of requests by certain meat or poultry establishments to operate at alternate inspection rates, to review and respond to such requests, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFD086293EDCB4052A67C9490622EF9C6" style="OLC"><section id="HBF38F4AB96B04212BD5127D0D1AA2CA2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Requests for alternate inspection rates of meat and poultry</header><subsection id="H0B8F196CC045427D959B4FDC7DE7965A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall—</text><paragraph id="HEBF12DB07B48401AAD0B6DF1BF67625D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>publish in the Federal Register food safety criteria that the Secretary shall consider in granting a request submitted by any establishment to operate at alternate inspection rates; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCE9D550109345079480927F3BFA4476"><enum>(2)</enum><text>begin reviewing and responding to such requests from such establishments.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H98E513FFA94C40739EDF40548CD52C66"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Response</header><paragraph id="H99B342413249453DBE8EF29E8C65D759"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which a request from an establishment to operate at alternate inspection rates is submitted, the Secretary shall respond—</text><subparagraph id="H081DF276C6A74949A1C5C04230F07F35"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of a request that the Secretary determines meets the food safety criteria referred to in subsection (a)(1), by approving such request; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88249DCE75E24B4DB9D5A9AD58A98FFA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a request that the Secretary determines does not meet the food safety criteria referred to in subsection (a)(1), by denying such request in writing and explaining in detail the reasons for such denial.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H77B1CC7270374CFAAF44BE1D646AC593"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Failure by Secretary to respond</header><text>In the case of a failure by the Secretary to respond to a request during the 90-day period referred to in paragraph (1), such request shall be deemed to have been approved by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0B7DD441D75F4BFE85B62231BF949008"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Continuation of operations at certain establishments</header><text>In the case of an establishment operating at alternate inspection rates as of the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall authorize such establishment to continue operating at such rates—</text><paragraph id="HBFAA4D42DC6F4B6ABAFF77AB0E353177"><enum>(1)</enum><text>so long as the establishment maintains effective process control; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E94A90D88F14FC197188DB6051E5A94"><enum>(2)</enum><text>until such date that the Secretary, under subsection (b)(1), approves or denies a request submitted by the establishment to operate at alternate inspection rates.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08AA15DC22984130B7F5A2A2FF3F037F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duration of approved requests</header><text>An establishment may continue to operate pursuant to the terms of a request approved under subsection (b)(1) so long as the establishment continues to meet the food safety criteria referred to in subsection (a)(1).</text></subsection><subsection id="H2C2B5EFD37564ECEB227178A16DDC4D1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Noncompliance and revocation</header><paragraph id="HDDE297BA29E24E5E94F875ACEE48830E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notice of noncompliance</header><text>The Secretary shall provide—</text><subparagraph id="H6D89D0B2841740F88CF5872BE98D6443" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of an establishment operating pursuant to the terms of a request approved under subsection (b)(1) that fails to meet the food safety criteria referred to in subsection (a)(1), written notice to such establishment describing the nature of such failure; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41CFD6E7982F45678835CA5A3802E5EE" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of an establishment continuing operations under subsection (c) that fails to adhere to the requirements of such subsection, written notice to such establishment describing the nature of such failure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1211DE3682714278B7FD437ED182BB3F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grace period; response to noncompliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the 180-day period beginning on the date on which an establishment receives a written notice of noncompliance under paragraph (1), if the Secretary determines the establishment has not remedied the failures described in such notice, the Secretary may—</text><subparagraph id="H779BCFEB87E641DDBC3228271BA2291A" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at the discretion of the Secretary, provide the establishment an additional opportunity to remedy the failures described in such notice; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00F7F7BA23DF43168F09289EB6A36E1A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>revoke the authority of the establishment to continue operating at alternate inspection rates and provide written notice to the establishment describing the basis for such revocation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA77F64BAF3B64DCCA79690EA3EEB209F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Timeline for adjusting inspection rates</header><subparagraph id="HC32A1696317A408296CE8B0917F913A9" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The written notice of revocation referred to in paragraph (2)(B) shall include a timeline for adjusting inspection rates at the establishment receiving such notice to inspection rates otherwise permitted under regulations implementing the post-mortem inspection requirements of the Federal Meat Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/601">21 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Poultry Products Inspection Act (21 U.S.C. et seq.), in effect as of the date of enactment of this Act (or successor regulations).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAACE1D4DF8504334BA4AED31FD29364B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimization of negative impacts</header><text>In establishing the timeline for adjusting inspection rates described in subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall—</text><clause id="H06EC971CF1044553A1058B27327D9BE7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consider potential effects on live animal production and sourcing; and</text></clause><clause id="H29FC614BF7C54FCE9136C90E74F11A2B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>consult with the establishment to which such rates shall apply to minimize negative impacts—</text><subclause id="H4ABAC092123443F9BDA6FD902952A4E0" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the ability of the establishment to fulfill any contractual obligations of the establishment in effect on the date on which such timeline is established;</text></subclause><subclause id="H085417CD83394EFC9C141E6A40C6D2AD" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>on animal producers or growers; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HB77ACAB3C79E47DB9FA4EE9311F72E57" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>on animal welfare.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H987F6B9810BC404783D19D2598B1B271" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>A revocation under paragraph (2)(B) shall not limit the ability of an establishment to apply and be approved for alternate inspection rates under subsection (b)(1), so long as the establishment otherwise meets the food safety criteria referred to in subsection (a)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H133329E91D514E59992E718F986292D3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H8ECB67658E1A43DF8D36A8246A6C7EBC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Alternate inspection rates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>alternate inspection rates</term> means any rate in excess of the maximum rates permissible under regulations implementing the post-mortem inspection requirements of the Federal Meat Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/601">21 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Poultry Products Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/451">21 U.S.C. 451 et seq.</external-xref>), in effect as of the date of enactment of this Act (or successor regulations).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA3316F211D14D2CA251C391D1194AB1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The term <term>establishment</term> means— </text><subparagraph id="HFB8220E45B664DD6A73FA9EF2147D857"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an official establishment that is subject to inspection under the Federal Meat Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/601">21 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96003AB81F694E709FFFBC5B4290CFBC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an official establishment that is subject to inspection under the Poultry Products Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/451">21 U.S.C. 451 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

