<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7FC9E38F3E7E4779A9619E34AAADB2C7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3008 IH: Drug Shortage Prevention Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3008</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230428">April 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000557">Mr. Larson of Connecticut</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act to provide for notification by manufacturers of critical essential medicines of increased demand of such drugs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H43EFDDEB9C6841F499351597787E6696" style="OLC"><section id="H3B69EBF5C33D4CE8845E2C84CB4D1DF3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Drug Shortage Prevention Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB4B8D0CA4F464D79B71EE5001C24A44E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improving notification procedures in case of increased demand for critical essential medicines</header><subsection id="H3AC993FAE4D644CBB7547A2AE46BD401"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 506C of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/356c">21 U.S.C. 356c</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD385368EE7B44181B161E9B673E4A231"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Discontinuance or interruption in the production of life-saving drugs</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">Notification of issues affecting domestic supply of critical essential medicines</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEDED83B383243688F7FD0F325A7DF0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subsections (a), (b), and (c), and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCCF9698C0A6A4E349C22C949962B4520" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H87E6A28172974AA3B8A5867F8CA1B69D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification required</header><paragraph id="H85BA1F8210FE457EB5DDEF7FCA67D26A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A manufacturer of a critical essential medicine shall notify the Secretary, in accordance with subsection (b), of—</text><subparagraph id="H9CF68966A2E84D36A9C7F465736A5889"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H39F1917FDFE6470D86119C423262E81D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a permanent discontinuance in the manufacture of the drug or an interruption of the manufacture of the drug that is likely to lead to a meaningful disruption in the supply of such drug in the United States; </text></clause><clause id="HF177FEF7CF2744A2BD6CB030AAC18539" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a permanent discontinuance in the manufacture of an active pharmaceutical ingredient, an excipient, or any other input in the final dosage form of such drug or an interruption in the manufacture of the active pharmaceutical ingredient, an excipient, or any other input in the final dosage form of such drug of such drug that is likely to lead to a meaningful disruption in the supply of the active pharmaceutical ingredient of such drug;</text></clause><clause id="HB29C8709041244F0A29389ADC1A371C7" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an increased demand (other than an anticipated seasonal surge) for such drug or an active pharmaceutical ingredient, an excipient, or any other input in the final dosage form of such drug that is likely to lead to a shortage of the drug or the active pharmaceutical ingredient, an excipient, or any other input in the final dosage form of such drug; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H531B8DD84AED49FC839D1AC05E9B743F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the reasons for such discontinuance, interruption, or increased demand.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF0D6B27CADF43679F37D577FDDDBD8B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Notification under this subsection with respect to a critical essential medicine shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HC27F9A0948BA404C84720232F738694F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to the reasons for the discontinuation, interruption, or increased demand referred to in paragraph (1)(C), if an active pharmaceutical ingredient, an excipient, or any other input in the final dosage form of such drug is a reason for, or risk factor in, such discontinuation, interruption, or increased demand, the source of the active pharmaceutical ingredient, excipient, or other input and any alternative sources for the an active pharmaceutical ingredient, an excipient, or any other input by the manufacturer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAF137B2CBBB496282CE67E21A480CB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether any associated device used for preparation or administration included in the drug is a reason for, or a risk factor in, such discontinuation, interruption, or increased demand; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55AAD1E4AFE747EE8D42D422BFF47546"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the expected duration of the interruption or increased demand; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE556F859A9A423097C0FC54AE590360"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H01C75821983D429C848E4C83CEF56F13"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timing</header><paragraph id="HF638CED468514CE3BAAD78C5E5E7DE16"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A notice required under subsection (a) shall be submitted to the Secretary—</text><subparagraph id="H5BC6CA01FF104319B9E753C0D30A53E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at least 6 months prior to the date of the discontinuance or interruption; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC714F3EFA8D54823BB83AAE01E931327"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of such a notice with respect to increased demand for a critical essential medicine, not later than 30 days after the submission of the initial notification under paragraph (2); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H946C5C1B15754562BDDA7BF39E2748ED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>if compliance with subparagraph (A) or (B) is not possible, as soon as practicable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD06D990AD5D43AF861E4D9FEFBEBC00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Initial notification with respect to increased demand</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case a notification required under subsection (a) with respect to increased demand for a critical essential medicine, the manufacturer of the drug involved shall submit to the Secretary an initial notification not later than 48 hours after the date on which there has been increased demand for the critical essential medicine for a period of at least 6 consecutive weeks. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H903DDB085CC346DB85E8B9370B2CE62D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>To the maximum extent practicable, the Secretary shall distribute, through such means as the Secretary deems appropriate, information on the discontinuance or interruption of the manufacture of, or the increased demand for, critical essential medicines to appropriate organizations, including physician, health provider, and patient organizations, as described in section 506E.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC031525A43341F2BD3218E5E7EC3582"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (g), in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>drug described in subsection (a)</quote> and inserting <quote>critical essential medicine</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3E547A127D24D74B5AE55F650665706"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (j), by striking <quote>drug described in subsection (a)</quote> and inserting <quote>critical essential medicine</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H71A34195FB0B49C084E373879C66E39A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application to nonprescription drugs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 506C(h) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/356c">21 U.S.C. 356c(h)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HDA9143643DAB462BB04C5B6DA1556D31"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) as paragraphs (2), (3), and (4), respectively; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7F75D1CF85F49839C5A524B6BAFA668"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A) (as so redesignated), by striking <quote>and that is subject to section 503(b)(1)</quote> and inserting <quote>, including a drug that is not subject to section 503(b)(1)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE999D880110746639011D949678200D9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting before paragraph (2) (as so redesignated) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H438D521AABCC4427BB86AD6301FE2AB4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HDB5335E68570432A9975DCD8BECCC8A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>critical essential medicine</quote> means a drug that—</text><subparagraph id="HC8F2563CA36C4764B65A5D1676D972D7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is—</text><clause id="HDC025392127247A1A1CBC94347F653CA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>life-supporting; </text></clause><clause id="H4060941E5E8643BABDC18E457E6A1C8E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>life-sustaining; or </text></clause><clause id="H1E19DC0090A84C349BB84390029050D6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>intended for use in the prevention or treatment of a debilitating disease or condition, including any such drug used in emergency medical care or during surgery or any such drug that is critical to the public health during a public health emergency declared by the Secretary under section 319 of the Public Health Service Act; and </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99E75F58CCD74A55AAC0AEB99F7FE0A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not a radio pharmaceutical drug product or any other product as designated by the Secretary;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFDB4EB7180F44C89B5982F958CE36E84"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall issue final regulations to implement the amendments made by subsections (a) and (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6A9AA8C5937F409C819818CEED369EE5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Guidance</header><paragraph id="H2C4A84F9724B41E881B2C5EDFD9222A0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall issue guidance on the requirements for notifications required to be submitted under section 506C of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/356c">21 U.S.C. 356c</external-xref>), as amended by subsections (a) and (b), with respect to increased demand for critical essential medicines (as defined in such section 506C). Such guidance shall specifically address—</text><subparagraph id="HB8F1BA91079F4BEA8617A4D232415943"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the ways in which manufacturers of critical essential medicines can improve demand predictability; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8546E3BCA9D43AC9BC6CB0ABDFB88C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">what information manufacturers of critical essential medicines should send to the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H391C1E797FF14603B4692F8064CDC1EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>what communications from the manufacturer the Secretary would request with respect to increases in demand following such notifications. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H60B013144C7148F8A9D65B9BD8D1D996"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing such guidance, the Secretary shall consult with relevant stakeholders, including manufacturers of critical essential medicines and local, State, or Federal public health officials. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AE6BCD75FEB40B9A33E09891998B56E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall issue—</text><subparagraph id="H3BD765BA72624F4CAF860DCC5A150549"><enum>(A)</enum><text>draft guidance under paragraph (1) not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA089CC81518E4906A2D81B3C1B55B965"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">final guidance under such paragraph not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

