<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD1F830C26B5B490A928B4E068C764481" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6455 IH: Climate Displaced Persons Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6455</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231117">November 17, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy, to authorize the admission of climate-displaced persons into the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HDD1960E2D1984C0293FC17582419378C" style="OLC">
<section id="H9251567C935E42509BD2FE7475760724" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H94300E65D11F4046AFE1FB70EF4621A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Climate Displaced Persons Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8827A507316D4BCC90F8699C93AF2DFA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text>
<toc>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H9251567C935E42509BD2FE7475760724">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF6CAA541CFA4470D97D2B37D4D36E1DF">Sec. 2. Findings; sense of Congress.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF472434389B94963ADA00D526F5EBE1D">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HE677779966954201B0D46341C1526F0B">Sec. 4. Required data collection and reporting.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HE76038BA0EDA46438BFBA0AA86020DB1">Sec. 5. Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HB51946CA0E6447BE9271D6AD0568F63B">Sec. 6. Training in climate change resilience.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HB710514FA4034E058A5292F3F22C364F">Sec. 7. Guidance on the humanitarian impacts of climate change.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H24557484E4F84B88ACC5AC2E870E3B02">Sec. 8. Admission of climate-displaced persons.</toc-entry>
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HA4F64F47B35E42B19EE51439B5C616B8">Sec. 9. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section>
<section id="HF6CAA541CFA4470D97D2B37D4D36E1DF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; sense of Congress</header>
<subsection id="H4888D0BA14024C1B899B307A5C56852B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text> <paragraph id="H962EDEE3ECC64E12BFFE32C34245B913"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the second study of the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), issued in February 2022, the IPCC stated, based on scientific evidence, that the Earth’s climate is now changing faster than at any point in human and recent geologic history.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0CB28E550532416B9996F05801D2F002"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Sixth Assessment Report of the IPCC and the Fourth National Climate Assessment, issued in November 2018, found that a changing climate is—</text> <subparagraph id="H5C5712FB0EB945D89B0F1F54DE17E265"><enum>(A)</enum><text>causing sea levels to rise;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H48BF1E32B79C440C994E1B2ADBE32302"><enum>(B)</enum><text>contributing to an increase in wildfires and temperature extremes in some parts of the world;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H01A839D7A62A44E48D37AD3CA619B851"><enum>(C)</enum><text>contributing to an increase in heavy precipitation in certain locations; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFE772939565D433DA617223FA6B716CE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>intensifying drought in many regions of the world.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4AE3A00D61B04F6285DBA7915B59277D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Forced displacement and forced migration are increasing in the context of environmental changes and climate-induced disruptions, including weather-related disasters, drought, food insecurity, and rising sea levels.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H65423F464CE14C66AE245330F6E5FA28"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In 2022, flooding events caused 6 out of 10 disaster displacements within countries, surpassing other types of disaster, according to the Internal Displacement Monitoring Centre. Such events include—</text> <subparagraph id="H7D7DA9CE72C5454EBDF096190837511C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the weather phenomena affected by El Niño and La Niña, which have recently led to record levels of flood displacement in many countries, including Brazil, Nigeria, Sudan, South Sudan, and Somalia;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HADE18138870F47EBB2CF3FC41846EEA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>high-impact events, such as the August 2022 floods in Pakistan, which displaced millions of people; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5F285286BF8C4529ACEFA69845B45F13"><enum>(C)</enum><text>floods impacting the most marginalized communities, such as refugees, internally displaced persons, and returnee populations in northern South Sudan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H57BE1ADE6A9E4223BB600E3FFC244D46"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Sea level rise, both locally and globally, imperils low-lying communities around the world by threatening water supplies, accelerating coastal erosion and loss of arable land, and inundating coastal areas. This phenomenon affects—</text> <subparagraph id="H7B681394AE984291AB5DD922569E6BCC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>low-lying areas of countries, such as Bangladesh, are threatened with land erosion, land loss, salinization, and other effects of sea level rise and extreme weather events; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFD8AFE758F164B5CAAD2DF29666B2914"><enum>(B)</enum><text>small-island-developing states, which are particularly vulnerable to sea level rise, which threatens their entire economies and territoriality.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H57A6B025E16A43B5A2FCAE7FEEEBA100"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Climate change is intensifying drought events and conditions in both severity and duration, which imperils agriculture and other livelihoods and can force families and communities to relocate temporarily or permanently. Failed rainy seasons in the Horn of Africa have led to the worst drought conditions on record in Somalia, Ethiopia, and Kenya.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8018F940C60543159CA5CBDCACC2CB1A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A 2022 World Food Program report on the Dry Corridor, a strip of land located in Central America that includes Guatemala, El Salvador, Honduras, and Nicaragua, has found that in the region—</text> <subparagraph id="H6233FCCD4FFC47A6A46BC2F8B93E5D06"><enum>(A)</enum><text>temperatures have been rising, with climate change projections for the Dry Corridor estimating an increase in temperature of up to 5.4 degrees Fahrenheit by 2050 and 10.8 degrees Fahrenheit by 2100;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8B1AC943ABDC46479599BCE098108358"><enum>(B)</enum><text>rainfall has been dwindling and becoming violently sporadic, with long-term droughts projected to become more severe by 2100 and intensifying by 27 to 73 percent across all months;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDAFC83563F5B4B998E13593A3161B159"><enum>(C)</enum><text>crop failure is becoming rampant with the expected intensification of heat waves, which are expected to affect basic grains and coffee production due to forest fires, lags in sowing, and increased pests; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H23B9956DD8C44E04AFD1755E7D116B99"><enum>(D)</enum><text>approximately <fraction>2/3</fraction> of the rural population of the Dry Corridor live in poverty and roughly <fraction>3/4</fraction> of these people are living in extreme poverty with significant levels of malnutrition, with the average monthly income from farming and other livelihoods estimated at $177.60 per person, leaving little room to cover eventualities linked to droughts, pests, extreme weather events, or socioeconomic shocks.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0DC2ABB7D5334D399E3EAF7944987D5E"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Tropical storms, including hurricanes, cyclones, and typhoons, are extreme weather events fueled by climate change that can generate widespread destruction and displacement.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H40F15E60E7D14ABABB45672800D9FC20"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration reported that 30 tropical systems were reported during the 2020 Atlantic hurricane season, making 2020—</text> <subparagraph id="H8931A398D0CC4CEEB40378B48604EB35"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the highest-ever recorded Atlantic hurricane season;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCEB982152E894ABEBDC603FC2E7AD09F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the fifth consecutive year with an above-normal Atlantic hurricane season; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEF62183245604258BB5F9AF1211854D2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>1 of the 18 above-normal seasons during a 26-year span.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8E8A945CDDF344838F0F3752633367E7"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The negative effects of hurricanes on communities can linger for years, as demonstrated by the lasting impacts on parts of Central America caused by Hurricanes Eta and Iota, which both made landfall in the same area in November 2020.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB2EF7D52363148C08866FDEDD5A1A491"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Combinations of extreme heat and humidity may create wet-bulb temperatures that may render certain regions of the world uninhabitable in the coming decades.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4F996A4734BD4C81AFE860F94E3C7C2E"><enum>(12)</enum><text>In the second study of the Sixth Assessment Report, issued in February 2022, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change affirmed with high-confidence that societal adaptations in the near term can help reduce the risks of climate change throughout the 21st century.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H761D800AF46D438BA03D8AE680DD8BAE"><enum>(13)</enum><text>In the <quote>Synthesis Report: Climate Change 2023</quote>, the IPCC concluded—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6C02076E23049DBA74D1C10479188D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote>There is a rapidly closing window of opportunity to secure a livable and sustainable future for all</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDB53152368F5427989E22707C8331B92"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><quote>Deep, rapid and sustained mitigation and accelerated implementation of adaptation actions in this decade would reduce projected losses and damages for humans and ecosystems</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAE6D7027F9BB4D96A32A273E09827E3C"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The United States bears a disproportionate responsibility for climate change since an estimated <fraction>1/5</fraction> of all historical worldwide carbon dioxide emissions were released in the United States, which is greater than the amount of such emissions released in any other single country.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H79BB0D6E54874729A50135219F41D091"><enum>(15)</enum><text>In the <quote>Synthesis Report: Climate Change 2023</quote>, the IPCC concluded, with high confidence, <quote>Vulnerable communities who have historically contributed the least to current climate change are disproportionately affected.</quote></text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFCA73AA7EA69445EBFEED45CB02AD97E"><enum>(16)</enum><text>According to the United Nations Refugee Agency (UNHCR)—</text> <subparagraph id="H0041C259CBCF483AB0B1857E97A6296C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>70 percent of refugees originate from countries on the front lines of the climate crisis; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H347F93FA08F24269ADF59AE3DCA73075"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">climate change affects people inside their own countries; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF442B5EA5259415DA694C0C831CB9D4E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">climate change typically creates internal displacement before it begins displacing people across international borders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1C288C9231EB4908BB423B0B3A98968B"><enum>(17)</enum><text>The Global Compact on Refugees recognizes that <quote>climate, environmental degradation and natural disasters increasingly interact with the drivers of refugee movements.</quote></text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H54336D0E55B747FDA3984D7173EA3ECA"><enum>(18)</enum><text>The October 2021 White House Report on the Impact of Climate Change on Migration—</text>
<subparagraph id="H8CA77A705E5E441B87E18A9EA69D015D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recommends that Congress should explore <quote>the need for additional protections for individuals who can establish that they are fleeing serious, credible threats to their life or physical integrity as a result of climate change;</quote> and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF60E20D20CE24AB7912F708B811262B0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>states <quote>[t]he United States should identify ways to apply existing protection frameworks in the context of climate change-related displacement and to identify gaps where the United States should forge new legal pathways to protection.</quote></text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA4280E96A16740C883FFBBA98C51F9F3"><enum>(19)</enum><text>As noted in a March 2023 report by the U.S. Committee for Refugees and Immigrants' International Refugee Assistance Project and the Human Security Initiative, many asylum seekers have cited the destruction of their homes, agricultural lands, and businesses due to climate-related causes as contributing to their decisions to flee, as these climate-related environmental disasters exacerbated their conditions of marginalization. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F8A6E77EF03479B8A210B7BE8CC4FAB"><enum>(20)</enum><text>The United Nations Human Rights Council has recognized that climate change poses an existential threat that has already negatively affected the fulfillment of human rights, specifically noting that—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC3BB3EC896D54C51AE8F3F8DF58FB563"><enum>(A)</enum><text><quote>all States should, when taking action to address climate change, respect, promote and consider their respective obligations on human rights</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H49F3E494A0734E8D862FD71D8F3E11BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text><quote>the adverse effects of climate change are felt most acutely by those segments of the population that are already in vulnerable situations owing to factors such as geography, poverty, gender, age, indigenous or minority status, national or social origin, birth or other status and disability</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H269431A41CB34971B154328BBCE3B7A9"><enum>(21)</enum><text>The effects of climate change also exacerbate social, economic, and political tensions within and among nations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6EFDD6A3665B4F78AD69694ADD6359CD"><enum>(22)</enum><text>The UNHCR Global Trends Report 2020 found, <quote>95 percent of all conflict displacements in 2020 occurred in countries vulnerable or highly vulnerable to climate change. Disasters can also strike populations already uprooted by conflict, forcing them to flee multiple times, as was the case with [internally displaced persons] in Yemen, Syria and Somalia and refugees in Bangladesh.</quote></text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H32E33A6E7FC14C13A6B2D174C84A4E24"><enum>(23)</enum><text>Climate-vulnerable states experiencing protracted conflict, such as Afghanistan or Yemen, can be affected by multiple climate-related threats simultaneously, such as—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7E24C254326C4245AC80FA7C9F212626"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">drought and flooding events in Afghanistan; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HACC74146E12346638015B5B696BB1913"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">drought, desertification, and cyclones affecting Yemen.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3BD4B0EDF18A4AB0983D27BE39D00A3C"><enum>(24)</enum><text>In their 2022 report <quote>Migration as a Climate Adaptation Strategy</quote> USAID found—</text>
<subparagraph id="H21FE5209B4AC4C038C0DAF7E355BD111"><enum>(A)</enum><text><quote>Migration has the potential to serve as an important adaptation and risk management strategy for climate-impacted populations</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD608524AB00F434A8FA000DE8725299F"><enum>(B)</enum><text><quote>Migration is not an adaptation strategy available to everyone due to pre-existing vulnerabilities, a lack of resources, or systemic inequalities;</quote> and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H606D4B46D5C64343881032DCBCA8C28F"><enum>(C)</enum><text><quote>Voluntary and proactive migration can benefit migrants, their households, sending communities, and receiving communities. Benefits include livelihood diversification, increased income and remittances, and knowledge and skills transfer. Receiving communities can benefit from an increased labor pool and an influx of migrant spending and support services.</quote></text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E91FEA1837E40059AAC3DAC9B6BDC27"><enum>(25)</enum><text>The Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights has suggested that a person displaced across borders due to climate related events— </text>
<subparagraph id="HD271646F61ED4E65BC272EACAE05B37B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has the right to not be returned to a country where such person would have irreparable harm to their right to life;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6CE4311E372E48599E80A7657F32D243"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">should be considered a victim of forced displacement; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE263A7A6C2DC487C9DDBA33B2D6A1DFA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>should be granted at least a temporary stay in the country where they have found refuge.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H431075EB9EFD4706AB18D4925DC6A4A7"><enum>(26)</enum><text>Displaced individuals, including individuals affected by climate change, can seek protective stay in third countries through humanitarian pathways, family reunification processes, labor-based visas, and other complementary pathways with a humanitarian focus.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H29DAD32664B7428AB2A6E14997CFAFD2"><enum>(27)</enum><text>Recognizing the human rights implications of climate change, countries have begun to explore humanitarian pathways for those displaced by climate-related environmental disasters, such as the Kampala Ministerial Declaration on Migration, Environment and Climate Change and Argentina’s recently announced humanitarian visa program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H662F2EB0338F451A966A5CCE68556E0E"><enum>(28)</enum><text>A CARE International report, <quote>Evicted by Climate Change: Confronting the Gendered Impacts of Climate-Induced Displacement</quote>, which was published in July 2020, notes that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H508C1663E4CD4A959ACB9F6D02120591"><enum>(A)</enum><text><quote>the climate crisis exacerbates gender inequality and makes it harder to achieve gender justice</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H503ED409DC494B74ABA9DB186405D3CA"><enum>(B)</enum><text><quote>in 2018, more than half of the 41 million people internally displaced were women</quote>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB5E901965A5448399D4C74509F865737"><enum>(C)</enum><text><quote>[p]oor women and children are up to 14 times more likely to be killed than men by a climate-fueled disaster, such as a hurricane, typhoon, cyclone, or flood</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3EFC6CB8003648059BE806C045131113"><enum>(D)</enum><text><quote>[w]omen who are displaced by climate change related impacts often have less access to relief resources</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAD2A56FC1F8C472FAD859F7426D67E51"><enum>(29)</enum><text>Members of LGBTQ+ communities are disproportionately affected by institutional discrimination in the housing, employment, and health sectors, which reduces their capacity to cope with the impacts of climate change.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBD1D666349B4BE9BEC67E5992F74913"><enum>(30)</enum><text>Black immigrants and other immigrants of color face higher rates of displacement due to climate change, but are also more often discriminated against in immigration policies and systems.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1A10A8A1105B4587B155BEDCCA47E889"><enum>(31)</enum><text>A December 2019 Oxfam International report found that climate-related events forced an estimated 20,000,000 people from their homes every year during the previous decade. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4BF77847B5F348E3859A8EC290CD4204"><enum>(32)</enum><text>A 2021 national intelligence estimate from the National Intelligence Council, entitled <quote>Climate Change and International Responses Increasing Challenges to U.S. National Security Through 2040</quote>, predicted <quote>cross-border migration probably will increase as climate effects put added stress on internally displaced populations</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H98C5C5FEBBDB4B958DD823C73581A1D7"><enum>(33)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A 2022 study by the Loss and Damage Collaboration found that an estimated 189,000,000 people in low income countries are impacted by extreme weather events exacerbated by climate change every year.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF40B7D302E3F4216B1E4E384BE51F354"><enum>(34)</enum><text>An October 2023 United Nations International Children’s Emergency Fund study found that 43,100,000 children in 44 countries were displaced from 2016 to 2021 due to floods, storms, droughts, and wildfires.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE67AC7209562480B8183F6B85AC1684C"><enum>(35)</enum><text>Ecological Threat Register 2020, which was published by the Institute for Economics &amp; Peace—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32DF982B4FD0454DA153A2A49E9775B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">projects that climate-related threats will continue to cause significant displacement worldwide during the coming decades; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H13DC137863674F9A8FB65A29BFEAF003"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">stated that 19 countries, with a combined population of 2,100,000,000 people, are most at risk for displacement given population growth, water stress, food insecurity, droughts, floods, cyclones, and rising temperature and sea levels.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCB004EC9AB084C2AB92F16FB0ED2E155"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the United States should—</text>
<paragraph id="H9F221C9959E24304AF232AB214035082"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reduce its domestic greenhouse gas emissions on a scale and rate proportionate to its historical responsibility and in recognition of the urgency of the threat of climate change;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B07C7D3A43A4063A168F8437FC27483"><enum>(2)</enum><text>welcome the shared responsibility of climate change adaptation, global disaster risk reduction, resiliency building, and disaster response and recovery;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEF3748FF418848D5A9A33AB35EAB8674"><enum>(3)</enum><text>assist in providing durable solutions for climate-displaced persons;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HADB7B10DB9F7413394F8A3C3A1B60C9B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>aid other countries in their climate change mitigation efforts; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H31508E770A514CD99E810029D7240EDF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>work with the international community—</text> <subparagraph id="HB156B3BD0B60478AB88FD326675F4CA8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to establish a framework to share the responsibilities described in paragraphs (2) through (4); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H843FE38A60764C28AC366BAF214FCD26"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to ensure that the human rights of climate-displaced persons are acknowledged, respected, protected, and fulfilled.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HF472434389B94963ADA00D526F5EBE1D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions in the Immigration and Nationality Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HA6DB87201A644752815ED394CFAC88EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (8) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7D31D13AC4A14787A7A131B3335F8374"> <paragraph id="H63AF079142CB4F04B2DBB4672D4A6D7C" indent="up1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The term <term>climate-displaced person</term> means any person who—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A0699CDA266405B9BC445E2E5CDD07C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is compelled to leave his or her habitual home, either within his or her country of nationality or in another country, due to—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H350EEFD5156B40208378A24AD3B0CDFC"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a climate-related environmental disaster; or </text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE896B27DE7E34D6CBA97397BA46C248B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the interaction of a climate-related environmental disaster with other factors, including resource constraints, food insecurity, discrimination, persecution, or human rights abuses; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF2CA7F01DE4C4C91B6D962177860CBCA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is unable to otherwise access a durable solution, such as local integration or safe and voluntary returns to his or her habitual place of residence due to a climate-related environmental disaster that—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6CA0FA6AE2704433A5F3563C41DE5713"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has rendered his or her habitual place of residence uninhabitable; or </text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA30C313EC97142BEB4283E1D95EBD11C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has prevented safe integration or voluntary returns, including through targeted violence, discrimination, human rights abuses, food insecurity, and other forms of harm.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA9C6CF99A2E45BD90DBB4A37A3AB6D2"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>climate-related environmental disaster</term>—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H01F8B71C3D77495E99530095CD08B224"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means a hydro-meteorological or other climatic event related to the Earth’s climate that adversely affects persons’ lives, livelihoods, or living conditions; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE83A4379E20547CEB33DDC6228FF4FF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H10F277265C7C4E3CA250127CBDBF0F08"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sudden-onset hydro-meteorological events, including—</text>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H526C71938BBE48139256B07ACCBD41ED"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">flooding;</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96EAA52E4A8344098C7713C08FF09C87"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">windstorms;</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H560AD279A109421E96825F4758E3BFFB"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">heatwaves; </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H445C743192FD48D28640254A2358C7F1"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">extreme wet-bulb temperatures;</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA365186025124C8DAB19011453DB0DB5"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">violent storms, such as blizzards; and </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFCFF72BC63D54BADB37DF4A2D3124D93"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hurricanes, typhoons, or cyclones;</text></subclause></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H837CE2487AAE475588C9B72A2AFAF865"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sudden-onset events that are exacerbated by conditions related to climate change, including wildfires, mudslides, and avalanches;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9828BC158C114BC0A0D1AF643CB0B035"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">slow-onset events, including—</text>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A41EEABD6304603B19994C4A2456F82"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sea level rise or coastal inundation; </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD5D989FDCDC7434C8B1A125F94868F27"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">drought;</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5280348CAAE544329FFF709DE573126D"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">desertification; </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H754076E48180424098268338363A4C2E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">salinization; </text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD12B733AD1EC4D47B9BB7442878FE215"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ocean acidification; </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H77C55BD1664B4084B699F8A1E665072D"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">erosion; and</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0B3410F09DDF4EF08C34761E7A569C31"><enum>(VII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">permafrost thaw; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA09C02426C88410AAFC25989B1F41E5A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">slow- and sudden-onset events with a relationship to climate change that is subsequently attributed by further scientific research.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE549B55692DE4860826C1E020A096E97"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (34) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1DA35604D8A4490B9956D5CD8981FB89"> <paragraph id="HC819F822150F498FA95BF65BB94C29E3" indent="up1"><enum>(34)</enum><text>The term <term>designated application center</term> means any United States embassy or consulate or other facility delegated by the Secretary of State to accept applications for climate-displaced person status under section 244A.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
<section id="HE677779966954201B0D46341C1526F0B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Required data collection and reporting</header>
<subsection id="H0FCC5050B4794B97872385F503E09A3A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Data collection</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD3AB9147B4AF4BB4A08959E298F789CC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall ensure that the Department of Commerce, the Environmental Protection Agency, the Department of State, the United States Agency for International Development, the Office of the Director of National Intelligence, the Department of Defense, the Department of Homeland Security, and other relevant Federal agencies collect, maintain, and publish data on displacement caused by climate change. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3ABCF3953CB34B0EA38AF9CE80FCB1DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sources of the data described in paragraph (1) shall include information from—</text>
<subparagraph id="H84399FA2ADC046DB9D568184BAA5F6CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the International Organization for Migration;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCB8EB76418F84DDAAB35414A71BDD17C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the United Nations Refugee Agency (UNHCR);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4DB693310A514A6597E1905C93BB6B48"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the United Nations Children’s Fund; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7E8F85185B664FEE9F082449C0207236" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other international organizations that are collecting such data. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB64912035D934DD0934252751818EA1F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Data shall be collected, maintained, and published pursuant to paragraph (1) at sufficient levels of disaggregation to assess the disparities of the impacts of climate change on a variety of groups and populations, including disaggregation by race, ethnicity, pregnancy status, parental status, socioeconomic status, country of residence, and other relevant demographics to assess and ensure the equitable application of this Act and the amendments made by this Act. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H41263199B8D6420688F5B821ABE1F82A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Mitigation</header><text>The data described in this subsection shall be used to mitigate externally influenced disparities in other countries to the extent feasible.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H32EA730C7E7347628408B5A28F7DF85B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the President shall submit a report, in unclassified form, to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name> that—</text> <paragraph id="H9A7C7182DECB4CF1ABAB231ABE1DCB7A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>details the collection and analysis of the data described in subsection (a); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H55DC909927C14156A91F6D8BADA3ED37"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAF8C8C21C5C04B86ABBB55AA4AFB16D5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>List of climate-Vulnerable countries</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2525234F9D434626B2412CA01D94CC2C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 5 years thereafter, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Department of Homeland Security, the United States Agency for International Development, and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, shall compile a list of the 100 most climate-vulnerable countries and other administrative entities through notice and comment rulemaking.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCA236273C75B4280AB871A438C778FF3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Methodology</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In compiling the list of climate-vulnerable countries pursuant to paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC602BCABBB6F400384F746CF156B0263"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use the best available scientific resources, including relevant data—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF1BD9CF4B534372ADAED39BB87B8350"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">published by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6EB29CC4B081415A9595034FB7A0BFC1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">available through the World Bank's Climate Risk Country Profiles; and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H34BF2D27558B4A558BF28179A757766C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">available through the Notre Dame Global Adaptation Initiative (ND–GAIN) Country Index;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDEE3E8A4B7D465DB9F4D3E17B8BE859"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider the frequency and severity of climate-related environmental disasters;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82F769FE1549418292810A975B4A18A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider the impact of both slow- and sudden-onset climate-related environmental disasters;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H243FF2267CA344D0870904DB7AF491FA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>consider the interaction of these climate-related environmental disasters with each country's preparedness and resilience capacity, including physical and social infrastructure; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H24EFA403E05A4B15938090DCD89FDE80"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult with a committee of agency experts, including climate scientists, immigration and refugee lawyers, and adaptation specialists.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HE76038BA0EDA46438BFBA0AA86020DB1"><enum>5.</enum><header>Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 117 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151p">22 U.S.C. 2151p</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HA3988172EC8542EF93A5416EA691E322"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="H0BFC0D912A80456B8C99CF1AC2C87D7C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> after <quote>(b)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H763318753FD3421481C92698C7EE6C7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7E4E8947A22741A08A6949AC7BDEFD9C"> <paragraph id="HA26080AB398A4E708C5EE15C21C82256" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H49A26CB349A94C3C8AF65DC08C75847A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The President is authorized to furnish assistance to programs and initiatives, including multilateral initiatives and funds that—</text>
<clause indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H73D2AA4B17094320AB499476F612A679"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote resilience among communities facing harmful impacts from climate change;</text></clause> <clause indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4216429605AD4DA3AC7EDCA7218F3BAF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce the vulnerability of persons affected by climate change;</text></clause>
<clause indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H919D7164065B4DEBA1F37FEC6565B918"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address permanent loss and damage faced by affected marginalized communities;</text></clause> <clause indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA3EA98BC6DAA4C66B4FBDACEAA3DB792"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide support for community recovery, reconstruction, and rehabilitation after climate-related environmental disasters;</text></clause>
<clause indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8F921891B1A4496995D28A0C26598E4E"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote sustainable peace through cooperation on efforts to protect the earth against environmental threats and to address and minimize climate change; and</text></clause> <clause indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD7B08FED01434639AC0FAA813A319661"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support climate-resilient programming that promotes peacebuilding to avert conflict due to scarcity of resources caused by climate change, including scarcity of water, food, and grazing areas.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4FF56FCE03FD44648899273EE9782005" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>There shall be, in the Department of State, a Coordinator of Climate Change Resilience, who shall coordinate the assistance authorized under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H802A08C4667A4889923888A8071703BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H930DE0D39B5E4914BF3EDEDF7F72FB69">
<subsection id="HBDE06ED545554E76AE015DF6D853197C"><enum>(d)</enum>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4684FE1BA0374661B0845DF544303327"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary of State, in coordination with the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development (referred to in this subsection as <quote>USAID</quote>) and the Special Presidential Envoy for Climate, shall establish a 10-year, comprehensive, integrated strategy, which shall be known as the <quote>Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy</quote>, to mitigate the impacts of climate change on displacement and humanitarian emergencies.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H65103F4B1AEE49EDBC9D529DAD830E62" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H74890E5D8EA74E59B9DCAB2FE9A1B019"><enum>(A)</enum><text>focus on addressing slow-onset and rapid-onset effects of climate change;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB5672B2701084B99B0928A864AC88ED3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>consider the effects of climate change;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD2339A83E1F44423AF7BF340357D410C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>describe the key features of successful strategies to prevent such conditions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6762F702CE3B4E9086E7C29D40D4486C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>include specific objectives and multisectoral approaches to the effects of climate change;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6B4C4DB00D024D89BCDA14655AC602E4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>describe approaches that ensure national leadership, as appropriate, and substantively engage with civil society, local partners, and the affected communities, including marginalized populations and underserved populations, in the design, implementation, and monitoring of climate change programs to best safeguard the future of those subject to displacement;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDF424C76E515419787926E5681A84EBD"><enum>(F)</enum><text>assign roles for relevant Federal agencies to avoid duplication of efforts, while ensuring that—</text>
<clause id="H5CD1FA3612A54EDC9A26563849FD33B7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Department of State is responsible for—</text> <subclause id="H03B8554594A9420892FC8ADA0809491F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>leading the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H433B3A4268264ED69C2917A4DBB35E0C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>establishing United States foreign policy with respect to such strategy;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6E46D44184784CDCA43623D569DD95B2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>advancing diplomatic and political efforts with respect to such strategy;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H25896B5FFABB41F8B8631F21246D1B39"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>guiding security assistance and related civilian security efforts to mitigate climate change threats; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9D86E1C2AF6C44C49B3BB4EFEC155799"><enum>(V)</enum><text>providing overseas humanitarian assistance—</text>
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H77494D13A6CA430CB2D12D3B52C37384"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to respond to international displacement caused by climate change; and </text></item> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFF44D0DA50C14A48A821663A1810CF3B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to coordinate the pursuit of protection and durable solutions for climate-displaced persons, including resettlement into the United States;</text></item></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H20284B9AEC3943CD9C1B9E5837A68DDD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>USAID is—</text> <subclause id="H417A63EDE5CE4E48B7F383E525EDE587"><enum>(I)</enum><text>responsible for overseeing programs to prevent the effects of climate change; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H637CF5788ABE4933AEBC8EDD0414182F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the lead implementing agency for—</text> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFCEA11EE19054D9EB3C440CE6CB45BF0"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing overseas humanitarian assistance to respond to internal displacement and food insecurity caused by climate change; and </text></item>
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H67BF8F07309049D4B689DDCFCA552ECD"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing a related non-security program policy related to building resilience and achieving recovery; and</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="HCA29E08F658941A79C9A280235B8663C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>other Federal agencies support the activities of the Department of State and USAID, as appropriate, with the concurrence of the Secretary of State and the USAID Administrator;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H962F4FA2C57348BB80E1021A6A18F965"><enum>(G)</enum><text>describe programs that Federal agencies will undertake to achieve the stated objectives, including descriptions of existing programs and funding by fiscal year and account;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H396A2EBA350649FFAE4BFAD2155B7D9D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>identify mechanisms to improve coordination between the United States, foreign governments, and international organizations, including the World Bank, the United Nations, regional organizations, and private sector organizations;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEF7EA6FEBB68404899B7FAA92238902C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>address efforts to expand public-private partnerships and leverage private sector resources;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H738A5DA224B147469724E7DAFEC6F147"><enum>(J)</enum><text>describe the criteria, metrics, and mechanisms for monitoring and evaluating the programs and objectives in the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1AC3EED16C5948C4AF64E2D21A5CBBB0"><enum>(K)</enum><text>describe how the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy will ensure that programs are conflict-sensitive, country-led and context-specific; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE700EF636B6C43D38C79F4A0A755F5C3"><enum>(L)</enum><text>describe how the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy is a means for peacebuilding, and is incorporated into peacebuilding, and post-conflict plans and programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H446259A63DD049A28E44C84129B437FD" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Climate Displaced Persons Act</short-title>, and annually thereafter, the President shall submit a report to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name>, based in part on the information collected pursuant to this section, that details the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy. The report shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex, if necessary.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H056F404D27F14B13A4623005FA2BD81B" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Climate Displaced Persons Act</short-title>, the Secretary of State and the Coordinator of Global Climate Change Resilience shall brief the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives</committee-name> on the progress made towards implementing the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H815630379A8F48CE9DE68CBE4EDE08CC" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5D9B7926BD114040ADD4B1C98BF0DB61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Climate Displaced Persons Act</short-title>, and annually thereafter, the Comptroller General of the United States, in cooperation and consultation with the Secretary of State, shall publish a report evaluating the progress that the Federal Government has made toward incorporating climate change into policies of the Department of State and USAID and describing the resources that have been allocated for such purpose.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3F568548538040548277AA966F403111" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The report required under subparagraph (A) shall assess—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H873DBEE7B90741FFB2B8863F8325FDBE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the degree to which the Department of State and USAID are—</text> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H34AB3E8C0C5241C7816583967770F375"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing climate change risk assessments; and</text></subclause>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17E5CD3BE078476AB43E1AED5C17205F"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing guidance to missions on how to include climate change risks in their integrated country strategies;</text></subclause></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H268304FA9A224AFFAEAFF3566227D4AD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whether the Department of State and USAID have sufficient resources to fulfill the requirements described in paragraph (2); and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H83444B212C0E47919281E02E40802929"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any areas in which the Department of State and USAID may lack sufficient resources to fulfill the requirements described in paragraph (2).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HB51946CA0E6447BE9271D6AD0568F63B"><enum>6.</enum><header>Training in climate change resilience</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB4D3A821F794249882D949BF71F28BB"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Foreign Service officers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 708(a)(1) of the Foreign Service Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/4028">22 U.S.C. 4028(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HB1E41A963B8148C1A078B418BEED5D7E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD25F205944B6481EB8EF56C5B981B412"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBDF368D5EBF94A3698FA624F47ADB9E7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7E77575D3ECC4BA39F803421F1C43650"> <subparagraph id="H0BF6879D6C65495E837D8959FEB261BF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>for Foreign Service Officers who will be assigned to a country from which climate-displaced persons (as defined in section 101(a)(8) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(8)</external-xref>) have been displaced, instruction on climate displacement, including the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy established pursuant to section 117(d) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151p">22 U.S.C. 2151p(d)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H786E2919691E49A8817D966353F405EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>USCIS officers</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall require U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services officers who review applications for admission as a climate-displaced person (as defined in section 101(a)(8) of the Immigration and Nationality Act, as amended by section 3) to receive instruction on climate displacement, including the Global Climate Change Resilience Strategy established pursuant to section 117(d) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as added by section 5.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HB710514FA4034E058A5292F3F22C364F"><enum>7.</enum><header>Guidance on the humanitarian impacts of climate change</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of State shall provide guidance to each United States diplomatic mission, in accordance with Executive Order 13677 (79 Fed. Reg. 58229; relating to climate-resilient international development), to address the humanitarian impacts associated with climate change. </text></section>
<section id="H24557484E4F84B88ACC5AC2E870E3B02"><enum>8.</enum><header>Admission of climate-Displaced persons</header>
<subsection id="H2689C63B76E548DDA47E3B4C2B1FA305"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Admission of climate-Displaced persons</header>
<paragraph id="H3F14BA4C683B4C1A94AAAD27CCA0862B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Chapter 1 of title II of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 207 the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75ECCBCC676A4CDBBD26ABB2650625BF"> <section id="H14D9D8C524CA43AFB8B22766D0134D6E"><enum>207A.</enum><header>Climate-displaced persons</header> <subsection id="H5981C09434C445E9924ABC3155814DFE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Admission goal</header> <paragraph id="H0D0D14AFA6C44B4EAE60496D7F62EF3D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to the refugees admitted pursuant to section 207, the number of climate-displaced persons who may be admitted to the United States under this section in any fiscal year (beginning with fiscal year 2024) shall be not fewer than the greater of—</text>
<subparagraph id="H3D42CD30783D4381BB3672F4EAA80529"><enum>(A)</enum><text>100,000; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8E3D9AA345BB4BF7A4C7716212743A03"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number that the President determines pursuant to paragraph (2), before the beginning of each such fiscal year, after appropriate consultation with Congress, to be justified by—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H22929A29C3384BEAAC7AC85E8BB772E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the data collected through the process established pursuant to section 4 of the <short-title>Climate Displaced Persons Act</short-title>;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H49048D97CB134FD58BF1D1BF95F2A400"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other humanitarian concerns; or </text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H786BE53DCEBF4C9AA3A9DECA9B668A61"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other national interests.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF783DC6375914F57A1592252BCC8AB9D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of numerical adjustment</header><text>If a significant climate-related environmental disaster occurs in 1 or more of the climate-vulnerable countries included on the most recent list compiled pursuant to section 4(c) of the <short-title>Climate Displaced Persons Act</short-title> or if the President determines that the number of climate-displaced persons who should be admitted to the United States in a fiscal year based on humanitarian concerns or other national interests is greater than the number set forth in paragraph (1)(A), the President shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H8CD2AAB45D7D400F9503A70B88B57472"><enum>(A)</enum><text>set the admissions level for climate-displaced persons at the same time as the President determines the number of refugees who may be admitted in such fiscal year under section 207; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H29E2EDB730B04C709C1512D11A9A0F08"><enum>(B)</enum><text>follow all of the procedures relating to refugee admissions under section 207, including determinations of the President, after appropriate consultation with Congress, to fix the number of refugees to be admitted to the United States during the current period (not to exceed 12 months) in response to an emergency refugee situation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H09C532F1F1C44741B8856C6388CD9CFB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Equitable allocation</header><text>The President, in consultation with the Department of State, the Department of Homeland Security, the United States Agency for International Development, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and other relevant Federal agencies, shall establish a process by which admissions authorized under this section shall be allocated in an equitable manner, taking into consideration the list of 100 most climate-vulnerable countries and other administrative entities compiled pursuant to section 4(c) of the <short-title>Climate Displaced Persons Act</short-title> and the demographic data described in section 4(a) of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB0BF79944D03416B936DAA544E691817"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Admissibility; applications</header> <paragraph id="HFABE43F59C1843AC913188D22D3AEECE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header> <subparagraph id="HB5225F380ACD49038D064B2F34B3E07C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Admissibility</header><text>Subject to the numerical limitation set forth in subsection (a), the Secretary of Homeland Security, pursuant to such regulations as the Secretary may prescribe, may admit any climate-displaced person under this section who—</text>
<clause id="H0CEA0977387A45EBA2B6B0F3981DA5B9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is admissible;</text></clause> <clause id="H442B5F2F49994E268108486D8C2E79AC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not described in paragraph (2); and</text></clause>
<clause id="H26BB8E2792284B48A0F1D0B89D7D293B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is not described in section 208(b)(2).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2E2726DBB9314CD78F436AA75C951197"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>Any noncitizen described in subparagraph (A), regardless of such noncitizen’s immigration status, may apply for admission as a climate-displaced person if the noncitizen—</text>
<clause id="HAF058E9B4EB64D22962EC28366AAB2B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is physically present in the United States;</text></clause> <clause id="H0904AD5C6FFF49D18CD4B7CD6D4CC89D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>arrives in the United States (whether or not at a designated port of arrival and including a noncitizen who is brought to the United States after having been interdicted in international or United States waters); or</text></clause>
<clause id="HF6D3D08D4ACB4B0089BF039B9483556D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>applies at a designated application center.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H00DFC6C254674117AF18BBC1D43F76B1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (3), a noncitizen may not apply for status as a climate-displaced person if—</text>
<subparagraph id="H95AC19883D1542CAA20F90BB875355D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security determines that such noncitizen may be removed, pursuant to a bilateral or multilateral agreement, to a country (other than the country of the noncitizen’s nationality or, in the case of a noncitizen having no nationality, the country of the noncitizen’s last habitual residence) that is outside of the zone in which the sudden or progressive change in the environment obliged the noncitizen to leave their residence, provided that such determination does not violate the human rights obligations of the United States;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB4E5A5AA72A3404E964DB454ED34C7B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the application is not filed within 1 year after the date of the noncitizen’s arrival in the United States; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5EDCA020D85147CE9697A4981307EA8A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an earlier application by the noncitizen for climate-displaced person status has been denied.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5588722E5F9946D99BFFDB0D584B70B4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> <subparagraph id="H92FA5AB1F0E34416A0BFB28E72BE773E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Unaccompanied noncitizen children</header><text>Paragraph (2) shall not apply to an unaccompanied alien child (as defined in section 462(g) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/279">6 U.S.C. 279(g)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDA1157E79735402EABB638CA5606FB37"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Changed circumstances</header><text>Subparagraphs (B) and (C) of paragraph (2) shall not apply if the noncitizen demonstrates, to the satisfaction of the Secretary of Homeland Security, that—</text> <clause id="H40E77779CB6B48CBBFA252F559139E9C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>extraordinary circumstances prevented the noncitizen from filing an application within the period specified in paragraph (2)(B); or</text></clause>
<clause id="HE3E690A11F9D4D75B9FB8B6D0110E9E5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>changed circumstances materially affect the applicant’s eligibility for climate-displaced person status.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF8B86FE2731B40508D332C65BFD50C22"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Referrals authorized</header><text>The Secretary of State may accept applications submitted on behalf of eligible applicants for climate-displaced person status by qualified international agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFC4F5346AC0E4653A9627308AC8C4528"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each application submitted under this subsection shall contain such information as the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, determines to be necessary to determine whether the applicant is eligible for admission as a climate-displaced person.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5FB156B314BB4DE1B32ECC5C796935E7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Fees</header> <subparagraph id="HC6F98349739C49809820246130A948EE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), an applicant for climate-displaced person status shall not be charged a fee.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H42939F81485440B7AF8658950B043D1A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>If a noncitizen has applied for, and been denied, climate-displaced person status on 2 or more previous occasions, the Secretary of Homeland Security may charge a reasonable fee for a third application and any subsequent applications, which shall set at a level equal to the average cost of adjudicating such applications.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB82AE97194254F6B890CDDD724BD01C2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Treatment of climate-Displaced persons</header> <paragraph id="HADE27B5614B742B69770A9B4DA31A3A8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A noncitizen who qualifies for climate-displaced person status under this section shall be eligible for resettlement assistance, entitlement programs, and other benefits available to refugees and asylees admitted pursuant to section 207.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAD8014B06F1C4F4FA30CCD5212ACC236"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of children and spouse</header>
<subparagraph id="HCF051895DC4A43A6AC6092E2FFAB04E9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A spouse or a child (as defined in subparagraph (A), (B), (C), (D), or (E) of section 101(b)(1)) of a noncitizen who is granted climate-displaced person status under this section may, if not otherwise eligible for such status, be granted the same status as the climate-displaced person if accompanying, or following to join, such noncitizen.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H73320EF61B5B43E3BF9840B54336E57A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment of children</header><text>An unmarried noncitizen who seeks to accompany, or follow to join, a parent or guardian granted climate-displaced person status under this section, and who was younger than 21 years of age on the date on which such parent or guardian applied for such status, shall continue to be classified as a child for purposes of this subsection and section 209(b)(3), if the noncitizen reaches 21 years of age while such application is pending.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE56379549CBA475BAEF7469F2C2A8C4E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Defined term</header><text>In this section, the term <term>noncitizen</term> means any person who is not a citizen or national of the United States.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0C4B46183DEA4BFCAFEB9979C09F0F13"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents for the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> note) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 207 the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7AB53B915BA642B2A09CF721B28551D5">
<toc>
<toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 207A. Climate-displaced persons.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF4DAD79BA7984D6EAD93C6336110D001"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Adjustment of status</header><text>Section 209(a)(1) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1159">8 U.S.C. 1159(a)</external-xref>) is amended, in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or 207A</quote> after <quote>207</quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H03B254977B0F42D7A1914ABED8C4469F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Savings provision</header> <paragraph id="HE934FF9E33764D65ABB20453896DC857"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Nothing in section 207A of the Immigration and Nationality Act, as added by subsection (a)(1), may be construed to affect the United States commitment to the United States Refugee Admissions Program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H750A5D80D82349998ADB62AECC47CFA9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional protections</header><text>The protections described in such section 207A are in addition to the refugee admissions goal established by the Presidential determination described in subsection (a)(1)(B) of such section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HA4F64F47B35E42B19EE51439B5C616B8"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act. </text></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


