<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD7DFB199E24041ED886C5C80C3174D24" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4648 IH: To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to provide for duties of certain investment advisors, asset managers, and pension funds with respect to voting on shareholder proposals, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4648</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230714">July 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 to provide for duties of certain investment advisors, asset managers, and pension funds with respect to voting on shareholder proposals, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H84683DB074A54584B9B553BB52CADFFB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H037FD900E8B746DC99F6CBBCB5CE0CC7" commented="no" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Duties of investment advisors, asset managers, and pension funds</header> 
<subsection id="HE535CA6B9FD247BC88AF4F6FC05138FE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 13(f) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m(f)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD194BBA368804E41A200E442284AA122" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H48E0CCCCD6924836A3775D42739F5CED"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Disclosures by institutional investment managers in connection with proxy advisory firms</header> <subparagraph id="H9480F704F6704092AAE2DD446B911AC8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Every institutional investment manager which uses the mails, or any means or instrumentality of interstate commerce in the course of its business as an institutional investment manager, which engages a proxy advisory firm, and which exercises voting power with respect to accounts holding equity securities of a class described in subsection (d)(1) or otherwise becomes or is deemed to become a beneficial owner of any security of a class described in subsection (d)(1) upon the purchase or sale of a security-based swap that the Commission may define by rule, shall file an annual report with the Commission containing—</text> 
<clause id="H4C94ECDF09824A8E815633C6ABE2D4CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an explanation of how the institutional investment manager voted with respect to each shareholder proposal;</text></clause> <clause id="HC42A1F93CF3440F5BEF9CAABF888E427"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of votes cast on shareholder proposals that were consistent with proxy advisory firm recommendations, for each proxy advisory firm retained by the institutional investment manager;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1E34BC8D58BA4856BFAD426F0862AE06"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an explanation of—</text> <subclause id="H8089F82250CF46659E9EC2432005798C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>how the institutional investment manager took into consideration proxy advisory firm recommendations in making voting decisions, including the degree to which the institutional investment manager used those recommendations in making voting decisions;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8D561A2822994641A01F053AC0E98379"><enum>(II)</enum><text>how often the institutional investment manager voted consistent with a recommendation made by a proxy advisory firm, expressed as a percentage;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H57243291FB524F928280ADEF45A667E2"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how such votes are reconciled with the fiduciary duty of the institutional investment manager to vote in the best economic interests of shareholders;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H835B823A7E2C4E0289A7B6FC281FCE1B"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>how frequently votes were changed when an error occurred or due to new information from issuers; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6CCABBEB12864F97A5CD6F3D8D258183"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the degree to which investment professionals of the institutional investment manager were involved in proxy voting decisions; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HFF67759FF6D54D089E8BC9ECD96B4014"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a certification that the voting decisions of the institutional investment manager were based solely on the best economic interest of the shareholders on behalf of whom the institutional investment manager holds shares.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF672A8F7F011448E811CEE9ECDD823FB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements for larger institutional investment managers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every institutional investment manager described in subparagraph (A) that has an aggregate fair market value on the last trading day in any of the preceding twelve months of at least $100,000,000,000 shall—</text> 
<clause id="H5E13685837B44B8285BDBBEC51B0144D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in any materials provided to customers and related to customers voting their shares, clarify that shareholders are not required to vote on every proposal;</text></clause> <clause id="H180BB273929F49499175D8BB3F44EB30"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to each shareholder proposal for which the institutional investment manager votes (other than votes consistent with the recommendation of a board of directors composed of a majority of independent directors) perform an economic analysis before making such vote, to determine that the vote is in the best economic interest of the shareholders on behalf of whom the institutional investment manager holds shares; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE39FC8F8B18242A0893EC67BDA1BBBBA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include each economic analysis required under clause (ii) in the annual report required under subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC389EB642A84C568B547148F8CEDC20"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Certification requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report required under this paragraph shall be certified by the chief executive officer and chief financial officer of the institutional investment manager.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H811BB25DF1274B1FB7177FCDE319C24C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Best economic interest defined</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <quote>best economic interest</quote> means decisions that seek to maximize investment returns over a time horizon consistent with the investment objectives and risk management profile of the fund in which shareholders are invested. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HD6A68ED470DA4004B490F8300F645325"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proxy advisory firm defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78c">15 U.S.C. 78c(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6DE0CB9D391F4DB29F1B8578FE157C35" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H5836730E55724303A1582EAA22811A83"><enum>(82)</enum><header>Proxy advisory firm</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>proxy advisory firm</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H7F4D2089553440B89D1219201CF6B9BE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means any person who is primarily engaged in the business of providing proxy voting advice, research, analysis, ratings, or recommendations to clients, which conduct constitutes a solicitation within the meaning of section 14; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H74387F46B818406BBDB4842E2E4AEE1F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include any person that is exempt under law or regulation from the requirements otherwise applicable to persons engaged in such a solicitation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

