<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9EBD454D6F064F0D8CA97B2AB65A9BA8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5148 IH: To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a centralized database to record and maintain information relating to training performed by members of the Armed Forces.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5148</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230804">August 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a centralized database to record and maintain information relating to training performed by members of the Armed Forces.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3A5F3EA5496B4F8BA60816D6F53FF2A3" style="OLC">
<section id="H55A864DA615E4DB5A2986BB3948D9CEE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Military training and competency database</header> 
<subsection id="H7CC4EDBD504D4391ADC2D8BD462A0AAC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of database</header> 
<paragraph id="HC6AC8D0393A64F59B6EA02945E629130"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall establish—</text> <subparagraph id="H964B93D926F14D45B313E348A7029365"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a centralized database, to be known as the <quote>Military Training and Competency Database</quote> (referred to in this section as the <quote>Database</quote>), to record and maintain information relating to training performed by members of the Armed Forces; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3A4567F560D8473BA50C19574CEA6C78"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a process to make the information in the database available to States and potential employers to assist in determining if the training provided to a member or former member of the Armed Forces satisfies civilian licensing and certification requirements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4A1E1A77871E4D3FBFE7064315C291D3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The Database shall include following information for each member of the Armed Forces:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0B465769CD7F4D378F725E1DDBF2BA31"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Name, rank, and military service identification number.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H35A3FAD88F894FC9A30049537FADE7D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Branch of service and specialty.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1D76D36F77D3474BA0D1D2268E983452"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Details of completed training courses, certifications, and qualifications.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2FACDBC90FC9429CBAF15C6A73CDFA78"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any other information the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3E08CCE3145C4778A4ACAF7F59787909"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Availability of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall establish a process to make the information contained in the Database available to States and other employers upon request to assist such States and employers in verifying whether the training and qualifications of a member or former member of the Armed Forces satisfies relevant civilian licensing or certification requirements.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H81C3005AFC274E42953FB27BDB03A083"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Security and accessibility</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall ensure that the Database is secure, easily accessible, and regularly updated to reflect the training and qualifications acquired by members of the Armed Forces.</text></paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="HC0E4A0FFCC444038A72434240254B1ED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Competency reports</header> 
<paragraph id="H56AE4E40E9844FF8A5BBE3B1EA0413FC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Based on the information in the Database the Secretary of Defense shall provide to each member of the Armed Forces a document that outlines the training and qualifications acquired by a member while serving in the Armed Forces. Such document shall be known as a <quote>competency report</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE4AF88D9BF64DB69695203920AA2FDE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Format and contents</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall develop a standardized format for competency reports, which shall include, at a minimum, the following information:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0CE0056C1BAA4CFF9E3AB7CC20B8863C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Relevant personal details about the member.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE72682B4049747009D113694534C6AFB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Description of training courses, certifications, and qualifications obtained.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD117542C3731403292AE076B66580484"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Date and duration of each completed training.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H38BA29EE08D34D86B93285657945A7BB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Authorized signatures and other necessary authentication.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H278A6F2D9E364B889C006ACABF6B4757"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Competency reports shall be provided to members of the Armed Forces upon their separation or retirement from the Armed Forces.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6B535660C19A4CB79F3E5C53BF17BC00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation</header> <paragraph id="H6DCDAAE582B94EF4896CC5BD312D8F7F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall establish the necessary regulations, procedures, and timelines for the implementation of this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB0137E24B70D40F4833E8C8ECD99C558"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Resources</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall allocate sufficient resources to ensure the effective establishment, maintenance, and accessibility of the Database and the development and distribution of competency reports to members of the Armed Forces.</text></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="H3F7ED6AAE53545A1BA730B2E13B8E14D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report on the implementation and effectiveness of the Database and any recommendations of the Secretary for improving the Database. The report shall include feedback and recommendations from States and other employers regarding the usability and accuracy of the Database and the competency reports described in subsection (b).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H2EAEB45B086C49CFA713BD6254FC6544"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Congressional defense committees defined</header><text>In this Act, the term <term>congressional defense committees</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101(a)(16) of title 10, United States Code.</text> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

