<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDDDA115818BC44A49586BB3BBE6A3A3C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 863 IH: To amend title 18, United States Code, to prohibit a publishing house from knowingly furnishing sexually explicit material to a school or an educational agency, to prohibit Federal funds from being provided to a school that obtains or an educational agency that distributes sexually explicit material, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 863</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230207">February 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to prohibit a publishing house from knowingly furnishing sexually explicit material to a school or an educational agency, to prohibit Federal funds from being provided to a school that obtains or an educational agency that distributes sexually explicit material, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H013CBB210F6A4903AE98CC3E01A2B776" style="OLC"><section id="HE1F0F06286C44C498C053FF1C44F2CFD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Prohibition on knowingly furnishing sexually explicit material to a school or an educational agency</header><subsection id="HFE04EC9C20D64C2783312672C928C310"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition on knowingly furnishing sexually explicit material to a school or an educational agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/71">Chapter 71</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0243877EA57F434E8DD2D59BC292481B"><section id="H918ABA68138F4B59B6F52EE54F8B1944"><enum>1471.</enum><header>Furnishing of sexually explicit material to a school or an educational agency</header><subsection id="HC6175C5E3FA34E64A2594C048DD26189"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Offenses</header><paragraph id="HD02615A71012405A925B4BF244C37907"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Publishing house</header><text>Whoever, in or affecting interstate commerce, being a publishing house, knowingly furnishes an elementary school, a secondary school, a local educational agency, or a State educational agency with published material containing a sexually explicit visual depiction of any kind, including a picture, photograph, or drawing, shall be subject to a fine of not more than $500,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE151CD2CB8834042A5C93161DA5F77B9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>President, director, manager, or officer of a publishing house</header><subparagraph id="H22D313BC654446E3953AEA635DFE24BC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Whoever, in or affecting interstate commerce, being a president, director, manager, or officer of a publishing house, knowingly authorizes the furnishing of published material in violation of paragraph (1) shall be fined under this title, imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE20FA8D2BE4D457199E45CAD47A8CBB3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Affirmative defense</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be an affirmative defense to a charge of violating subparagraph (A) if the defendant proves, by a preponderance of the evidence, that an individual at a higher management level knowingly authorized the furnishing of the published material involved.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5EB9E5BAE5114F63AB9CD7AFF6043639"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Excepted material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prohibitions in subsection (a) do not apply with respect to material with serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific value.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF17B2F6F739F48E88ACC499DEF4D099B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H5EA9CBFADBF64200BEC48A99B8241750"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8959E043AA944D59ADA9EF5FBCF715B7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Published material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>published material</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H2995A36A71EE42EA903517535D112E3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any book, magazine, newspaper, or other printed material; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H039F7FE18126416A9B8BA60C410EB954"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes digital or electronic books.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CD8CA223C244C05A83361D00B76F013"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publishing house</header><text>The term <term>publishing house</term> means a for-profit entity that manufactures, distributes, or sells published material.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA025668BE3BF47519AE9C04B0289A006"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/71">chapter 71</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/18/1470">section 1470</external-xref> the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF4C73238D6924B93B5F9177438355092"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="item">1471. Furnishing of sexually explicit material to a school or an educational agency.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H08B75606BB194F7B8ACF49F0E7EA786D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal funds for school obtaining or educational agency distributing sexually explicit material</header><subsection id="HAB3505D07D9749F8AEC9CAC393013794"><enum>(a)</enum><header>No Federal funds for school obtaining sexually explicit material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds may be provided to an elementary school or a secondary school that knowingly obtains published material containing a sexually explicit visual depiction of any kind, including a picture, photograph, or drawing, until such time that the school relinquishes or destroys the published material.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA03804C882624660BA0C74117491E4A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No Federal funds for educational agency distributing sexually explicit material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds may be provided to a local educational agency or a State educational agency that knowingly distributes to an elementary school or a secondary school published material containing a sexually explicit visual depiction of any kind, including a picture, photograph, or drawing, until such time that the educational agency instructs the school to which the educational agency distributed the published material to either relinquish or destroy the material.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDE24724F970A453DA32ADB87F90C371B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Excepted material</header><text>The prohibitions in subsections (a) and (b) do not apply with respect to material with serious literary, artistic, political, or scientific value.</text></subsection><subsection id="H435EDE396A12495C8940F14BCE60DAF4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H0CA7A018E46242AB94E21E9308D51A41"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57FBA6559C3241A09CAB0A588E2C5F20"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Published material</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>published material</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H167068E986534604801F1EF139586D4F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any book, magazine, newspaper, or other printed material; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A2BE526691744A69AF964094CDA3A8F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes digital or electronic books.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

