<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBAFA369FD766472795D48EEA2B06F860" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3346 IH: Innovative Maternal Payment and Coverage To Save Moms Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3346</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230515">May 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001214">Mr. Mrvan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services to implement the Perinatal Care Alternative Payment Model Demonstration Project to test various payment models with respect to maternity care provided to pregnant and postpartum individuals, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H42872729D44840908372C85AF7AC14C4" style="OLC"><section id="HA7605497B6754EE3950BD97CB5567BD3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Innovative Maternal Payment and Coverage To Save Moms Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>IMPACT to Save Moms Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H381748AEEFD7413D9E0F44E03ADE155D" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>2.</enum><header>Perinatal Care Alternative Payment Model Demonstration Project</header><subsection id="HF17A54D9BB95435FB119DCB109EF100F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), acting through the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, shall establish and implement, in accordance with the requirements of this section, a demonstration project, to be known as the Perinatal Care Alternative Payment Model Demonstration Project (referred to in this section as the <quote>Demonstration Project</quote>), for purposes of allowing States to test payment models under their State plans under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) and State child health plans under title XXI of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>) with respect to maternity care provided to pregnant and postpartum individuals enrolled in such State plans and State child health plans.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEDC7D9C46BF04CE5AD096E3ADB1A5992"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In establishing the Demonstration Project, the Secretary shall coordinate with stakeholders such as—</text><paragraph id="H2AD86746A12E4E7FA5DEBB29D166EF75"><enum>(1)</enum><text>State Medicaid programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB7E51BB3B374E1C9439ECDDC1DBF1DB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maternity care providers and organizations representing maternity care providers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB65BDDCDC6E341F78B564688E8E7D52F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant organizations representing patients, with a particular focus on patients from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB62B2F6CF26E423CA95EADBEB4C1AB4E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">relevant community-based organizations, particularly organizations that seek to improve maternal health outcomes for individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H239F5AA783554119AA0FCC45E6865D5A"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perinatal health workers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA20CDAA7AB942AA8BD3511452E8490D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>relevant health insurance issuers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC964F15DC9AA4C8AB1DE8BDCBE988DBD"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hospitals, health systems, midwifery practices, freestanding birth centers (as such term is defined in paragraph (3)(B) of section 1905(l) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(l)</external-xref>)), Federally-qualified health centers (as such term is defined in paragraph (2)(B) of such section), and rural health clinics (as such term is defined in section 1861(aa) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395x">42 U.S.C. 1395x(aa)</external-xref>));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AC58BEB02C942598BF47A95C3AF58BD"><enum>(8)</enum><text>researchers and policy experts in fields related to maternity care payment models; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59969FA260AF46D6939385C8417F3FCD"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other stakeholders as the Secretary determines appropriate, with a particular focus on stakeholders from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA151656999EC405C9E41712718B9838C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing the Demonstration Project, the Secretary shall consider any alternative payment model that—</text><paragraph id="HF685BF470BAE4100A4CF6941B08865E4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is designed to improve maternal health outcomes for individuals from demographic groups with elevated rates of maternal mortality, severe maternal morbidity, maternal health disparities, or other adverse perinatal or childbirth outcomes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FD585AE52AF4EAE8E07116BB3A59156"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes methods for stratifying patients by pregnancy risk level and, as appropriate, adjusting payments under such model to take into account pregnancy risk level, including consideration of the appropriate transfer of patients by pregnancy risk level;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17F60471C5FC44D8ACC6FCCD51C62D15"><enum>(3)</enum><text>establishes evidence-based quality metrics for such payments;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C30D73E2D5F426FB3458BE0EA0EADA4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>includes consideration of nonhospital birth settings such as freestanding birth centers (as so defined);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDDF886C088C48D29D1B970519910427"><enum>(5)</enum><text>includes consideration of social determinants of maternal health; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFE24393C8F74659855F663E8169AD26"><enum>(6)</enum><text>includes diverse maternity care teams that include—</text><subparagraph id="H40C89DB8F3DB47B186F0B9F26CB5056B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maternity care providers, mental and behavioral health care providers acting in accordance with State law, and registered dietitians or nutrition professionals (as such term is defined in section 1395x(vv)(2) of title 42, United States Code)—</text><clause id="HE1756F11060C43B0BEB4BD624416213D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>from racially, ethnically, and professionally diverse backgrounds;</text></clause><clause id="HF07CC99D63FF42B7AD34CEB10F5D8FB8" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with experience practicing in racially and ethnically diverse communities; or</text></clause><clause id="HCCBB5B75206548C0A81B9D8FB8EC4CF1" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>who have undergone training on implicit bias and racism; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E1191C04F224D389F728EEA2E1AD48F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perinatal health workers; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4A805A45BD0408EA920DF4301AD4102"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes consideration of maternal mental health conditions and substance use disorders.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H844BB2444A474176B148828CDE4268F1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to participate in the Demonstration Project, a State shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBDD6C9F993324F7E8D84F2C141ECE478"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct an evaluation of the Demonstration Project to determine the impact of the Demonstration Project on—</text><paragraph id="H90E968B27AD44FCAB1895E4782E6FEF6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maternal health outcomes, with data stratified by race, ethnicity, primary language, socioeconomic status, geography, insurance type, and other factors as the Secretary determines appropriate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA677990749448A88A7BDF5767489F51"><enum>(2)</enum><text>spending on maternity care by States participating in the Demonstration Project;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3341AE6785554E738D2740218EDAAE71"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent practicable, qualitative and quantitative measures of patient experience; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA543638539694CD0BE66FFBA397E5D53"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other areas of assessment that the Secretary determines relevant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD369A22F156342808C21F5B7227A1309"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the completion or termination date of the Demonstration Project, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress, and make publicly available, a report containing—</text><paragraph id="H30A62FC3FA334AA883DA3DEC1E92B050"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of any evaluation conducted under subsection (e); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD92E12D0D2924EB28C9600E9DFEC41CD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a recommendation regarding whether the Demonstration Project should be continued after fiscal year 2028 and expanded on a national basis.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3B795E50C02A49B78F777320B28B8C73"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H0538ADF63A954510AA171C4F88FDCF09"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Alternative payment model</header><text>The term <term>alternative payment model</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1833(z)(3)(C) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(z)(3)(C)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF01501643FF4C4CB507202D23C67601"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maternal mortality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternal mortality</term> means a death occurring during or within a 1-year period after pregnancy, caused by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications, including a suicide, overdose, or other death resulting from a mental health or substance use disorder attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy-related or childbirth complications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD643D9587575497DAACC4996439101D3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maternity care provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>maternity care provider</term> means a health care provider who—</text><subparagraph id="H1104C880B2424FC685A7E872978F90BF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a physician, a physician assistant, a midwife who meets, at a minimum, the international definition of a midwife and global standards for midwifery education as established by the International Confederation of Midwives, an advanced practice registered nurse, or a lactation consultant certified by the International Board of Lactation Consultant Examiners; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C1338964F4F48BDAF12D30D7C310BCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has a focus on maternal or perinatal health.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7547ABCD7F749A4B4A6EFB68FFFAB04"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Perinatal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>perinatal</term> means the period beginning on the day an individual becomes pregnant and ending on the last day of the 1-year period beginning on the last day of such individual’s pregnancy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27A4000086BE4C3CBEC449DDC0970B11"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Perinatal health worker</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>perinatal health worker</term> means a nonclinical health worker focused on maternal or perinatal health, such as a doula, community health worker, peer supporter, lactation educator or counselor, nutritionist or dietitian, childbirth educator, social worker, home visitor, patient navigator or coordinator, or language interpreter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA11A9C9A45AD433FB201E346793A18B9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Postpartum and postpartum period</header><text>The terms <term>postpartum</term> and <term>postpartum period</term> refer to the 1-year period beginning on the last day of the pregnancy of an individual.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CE66F82BAF446ABAD4D4E1349CE6B51"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Severe maternal morbidity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>severe maternal morbidity</term> means a health condition, including mental health conditions and substance use disorders, attributed to or aggravated by pregnancy or childbirth that results in significant short-term or long-term consequences to the health of the individual who was pregnant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H445A28B7292D4E72838DCA0EBF9322D4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Social determinants of maternal health</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>social determinants of maternal health</term> means nonclinical factors that impact maternal health outcomes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2811BC790D174C1FB1A4F86FB1596391"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

