<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H99625A2C64E54FA9B6D609781D8DEC73" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6420 IH: Wy’East Tribal Resources Restoration Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6420</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231115">November 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Omnibus Public Land Management Act of 2009 to establish within the Mount Hood National Forest in the State of Oregon Indian Treaty Resources Emphasis Zones, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H05CC7D5236734FE8AF836E0A573F3D3E" style="OLC">
<section id="H6A478FD974C545ABBBFD8C80C16FEA01" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Wy’East Tribal Resources Restoration Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H1C9B87A9613C40489F6F7B2A21F4289C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Indian Treaty Resources Emphasis Zones, Mount Hood National Forest</header> <subsection id="HBD52D2EC54C04695A2F4B2B7F141B4D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subtitle C of title I of the Omnibus Public Land Management Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/11">Public Law 111–11</external-xref>; 123 Stat. 1007) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBAA14ADDC27C4D658F1326657C096E98">
<section id="H7C9F68F9CD3349DABAF166D1701598C5"><enum>1208.</enum><header>Indian Treaty Resources Emphasis Zones</header>
<subsection id="H4577CDA0999C493A809185D26EA11959"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H5FBBFD7F06B24DA5B2A470871319EAFA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>National Forest</header><text>The term <term>National Forest</term> means the Mount Hood National Forest in the State. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1828694FA0DF4886B6AAA129A0024474"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text>The term <term>Reservation</term> means the reservation of the Tribe.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5C7DA0C474004CFCB73645CBBC5419AA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Traditional ecological knowledge</header><text>The term <term>traditional ecological knowledge</term> means a body of observations, oral and written knowledge, practices, and beliefs that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0DEB215185E340FAA2C56A7DAE10D624"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promotes environmental sustainability and the responsible stewardship of natural resources through relationships between humans and environmental systems;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCF949A0B52DD4C3DBA7BC2BD3CCFE169"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is applied to phenomena across biological, physical, cultural, and spiritual systems;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H163F7D1E000C49C89AC464DF1B9C0647"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has evolved over millennia, continues to evolve, and includes insights based on evidence acquired through direct contact with the environment and long-term experiences, as well as extensive observations, lessons, and skills passed from generation to generation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1CA1AC14CD8B4FA5B9AD162E0B671BCE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is owned by Indigenous people, including Tribal Nations, Native Americans, Alaska Natives, Native Hawaiians, and other Indigenous people.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6E39A3B5D20B45C086A6F6C210FAB182"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Treaty</header><text>The term <term>Treaty</term> means the Treaty between the United States and the confederated tribes and bands of Indians in Middle Oregon, concluded at Wasco June 25, 1855 (12 Stat. 963).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE96D19C944974DEDA9A61511B66BA84E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Tribe</term> means the Confederated Tribes of the Warm Springs Reservation of Oregon.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H220F664294AE4AD2891E425274D08243"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Zone</header><text>The term <term>Zone</term> means an Indian Treaty Resources Emphasis Zone established under subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD2D8C26C376A4A7B8C86B946C931FCE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <paragraph id="H7BE48792C7FF4048BC2E7690A663DC66"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established within the area of the National Forest described in paragraph (3) 1 or more zones, each of which shall be known as an <quote>Indian Treaty Resources Emphasis Zone</quote>, consisting of any area within the National Forest with respect to which the Tribe and the Secretary enter into a memorandum of understanding under subsection (c)(1) to protect and enhance Treaty resources or to protect the Reservation from wildfire.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF5FE7803DE02485D9CE486C3E27DF70E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of a Zone are—</text> <subparagraph id="H7DB14AB439814E0DA702A42116395FE8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to meet the trust responsibility of the United States in protecting the exercise of off-Reservation Treaty rights reserved by the Treaty in the National Forest;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA9D582D510A643CDB9647A76D018F733"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to ensure that land and resource management priorities in the Zone maintain and enhance resources, activities, and access reserved by the Treaty;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB967AE00DA3A4491BB2195A4EA464AEC"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to protect Treaty rights and resources and the Reservation from wildfire, drought, and insect and disease outbreaks in the National Forest in line with the best available science, including traditional ecological knowledge;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD3ABD43E73D54C969B7A2FA25DF5F08D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to recognize and integrate traditional ecological knowledge as an important part of the best available science that is used in forest and resource management areas within the Zone;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H946F5EAF03D9479AA1A829BD2C5D8FB3"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to improve the technical understanding of Forest Service employees in the National Forest with respect to the trust responsibilities of the Federal Government (including the application of those responsibilities to ongoing forest management processes and practices);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7086EB4CC49F4436A75EAE37B7CACEC5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to enable a co-management strategy between the Forest Service and the Tribe; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H27AA9B99C04542CDA23F2249B96ABB1F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>to conserve other values within the Zone, including ecological, scenic, geological, climate, and indigenous cultural values.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA9C60A8B8EA64935AF25AF717088BEDF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Scope</header><text>This section shall apply to any area within the boundaries of the National Forest in which the Tribe retains Treaty rights.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFD17C5BC41FC4A4EAA68415DA04143CB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Management strategy</header> <paragraph id="H28E28532B4FF4631A110F7BB707C3798"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall seek to enter into a memorandum of understanding with the Tribe—</text>
<subparagraph id="H400C80AAEEF142EFBB907441BA4524B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in addition to the Tribal consultation process, to better fulfill the trust relationship between the United States and the Tribe by ensuring that the Forest Service includes the Tribe in the land and resource management decision-making process in a Zone to mitigate against adverse effects on Treaty rights and management of the resources on which the Treaty rights depend; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9BE1B09B63504B3895C3A3EF0F0592E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to cooperatively develop a management strategy for the 1 or more Zones, including guiding documents for the management of the National Forest and ecosystems for Treaty rights and resources within the Zones.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2E7677084570432DB9E1DFD1B89DDDC4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A memorandum of understanding entered into under paragraph (1) shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HEF149C79EA9B4F3A9DEF0F0F6CC1DA57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>include an assessment of wildfire risk to—</text>
<clause id="H891E4FAE56224B4BB369267C0FF45845"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Reservation from the National Forest; and</text></clause> <clause id="H3899081C108E4A8BB12BE8A6563CF3A5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Treaty and cultural resources within the National Forest;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9B765C5C37894D30A7120A6218C324D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide that forest restoration and management planning within a Zone includes, and is guided by, reserved Treaty rights, and the resources on which the Treaty rights depend;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2A62866BF93D4EDFAE521F536148FBD3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include requirements that no temporary or permanent road shall be constructed within a Zone, except as necessary—</text>
<clause commented="no" id="HD440919F3A8842828C2539A75154096C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to meet the requirements for the administration of a Zone; </text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H106C1F5921584C149679D059898828F0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to protect public health and safety;</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H5C0E52A0CCD14C74945FDAFF97E57297"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to respond to an emergency; or</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H87C9E65A490343229C8E9D008D42643A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>for the control of fire, insects, or diseases, subject to such terms and conditions as the Secretary determines to be appropriate; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4BD870A069A240F2A6FF9BB208068146"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, to meet the purposes of this section, provide for the retention of large trees, as appropriate for the historic forest structure or promotion of fire-resilient stands.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HDD3907C4230C46EFAC309B87027D9A40"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Road maintenance</header> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H3280F6A8EC9B4E50BD35A61E1C3038EB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to appropriations, the Secretary shall maintain existing roads determined by the Secretary, in consultation with the Tribe, to be necessary for authorized existing uses and the administration of a Zone. </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H18CD20A7D22447AA8666B01BA3E2F61F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion in memorandum of understanding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirement under this paragraph shall—</text> <clause commented="no" id="HD0F27D94F95545C5B5F7CA93B413807C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not expire; and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H88366F00CB324D06B7974EF16CAC3423"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be included in any memorandum of understanding entered into under paragraph (1).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB8348DA1B043411983F7CD1EE1BBA7D3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Withdrawal</header><text>Subject to valid existing rights, all public land within a Zone, and all land and interests in land acquired by the United States within a Zone, shall be withdrawn from—</text>
<subparagraph id="H279591328E754338BF5E7EAA2564239B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>all forms of entry, appropriation, or disposal under the public land laws;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBB87A77163E9496BBBA6EBE58233B670"><enum>(B)</enum><text>location, entry, and patent under the mining laws; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2F562DFAAD7D4D839A1B44807DF2B113"><enum>(C)</enum><text>operation of the mineral leasing, mineral materials, and geothermal leasing laws.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA78E1A9585342D7A313B6C76F429B91"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><text>To the maximum extent practicable, the Secretary shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="H08E3181688DE4C0E90F6C71C5AFC666C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, ratify a memorandum of understanding under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC47413F25E9D4B629028A9BBFEE182AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than the date that is 3 years after the date of enactment of this section, complete a management strategy for the 1 or more Zones.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H59224CC17F234D1083929EDFC2DE5121"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements for implementation</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretary shall, to the maximum extent practicable—</text> <paragraph id="HD4F3756C108348E2ADA1A1D38BBF4FCE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>use all existing authorities available to the Secretary, including, as applicable—</text>
<subparagraph id="H6E6412C48564407EBDFD38A8642AB2EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Tribal Forest Protection Act of 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/278">Public Law 108–278</external-xref>; 118 Stat. 868); </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4EB67B1595E1443ABD99B6A298462B5A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the good neighbor authority under section 8206 of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2113a">16 U.S.C. 2113a</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H17775DB330224B229FD6CDB0491F67EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>title XXVI of the Energy Policy Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/3501">25 U.S.C. 3501 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE911F99E57474CC7B54553B3A235377F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the stewardship end result contracting authority under section 604 of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591c">16 U.S.C. 6591c</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8BB0655C4600418C89CCAB669DA4DDD9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>section 102 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5321">25 U.S.C. 5321</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H58D390F5CD99464492E59649F587718E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the authority to enter into contracts with the Tribe to expedite projects, on request by the Tribe, under section 8703 of the Agriculture Improvement Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/3115b">25 U.S.C. 3115b</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H20E97E93A3764FBCB1610AC2B5EB0DE2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop a programmatic analysis for the management strategy for the 1 or more Zones under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6FF0947EE310450A920C6E278A4D36AD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>pursue a programmatic biological assessment to implement the actions analyzed under paragraph (2) under section 7 of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1536">16 U.S.C. 1536</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5F75CA92403D4689A4F2A1EF32C48A52"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure compliance with all applicable laws and regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1B9828FD9897448EB1D3AEB9C8EEFA30"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Review of MOU</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 5 years after the date on which a memorandum of understanding is entered into under subsection (c)(1), and not less frequently than once every 5 years thereafter, the Secretary shall, in coordination with the Tribe, review the accomplishments of the memorandum of understanding to determine if the memorandum of understanding shall be extended or modified.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H7DAE64C1C7334653BAF725195E01B769"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Funding agreement</header><text>The Secretary shall develop a funding agreement with the Tribe, including the use of appropriated funding, to ensure that the Tribe, in partnership with the Forest Service, has the capacity to participate in designing, implementing, and monitoring projects within a Zone.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB2D0A7E9A90E4522A042B52B99D4E418"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Monitoring</header> <paragraph id="H293384079BBD461D83C6E31225F05AAA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the Tribe under which the Tribe may, at the discretion of the Tribe—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF3E8CE711D764F4BB0CA0E5232228BB1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review and provide comments on any land management prescriptions developed by the Secretary for a Zone;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H13C9AEFC81CC4B6BB186E3814ED210B2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>monitor—</text>
<clause id="H6EEF6ED77B68427780D542DFA9FF5607"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the long-term effectiveness of restoration and management treatments of actions carried out in a Zone; and</text></clause> <clause id="H735A45F586CE4588B2C498B54D888824"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other action or lack of action that is detrimental to the purposes of a Zone; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFE63CA099E1C4AB7BF1FE85ADF07E365"><enum>(C)</enum><text>share any other information with the Forest Service that the Tribe determines to be necessary to further the purposes of a Zone.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB172E267462A4894A9EBA3D7E5D9431F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Management of cultural foods obligations</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H4ECEEBB9D83248FAB1A5F74966FE7D1B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the management plan described in section 1207(c) has not been developed and implemented as of the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H1F377912995B4BE0B735DB847099407E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>complete a management plan in accordance with that section not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H399E0D080D04479E9C64EF1A2652B895"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enter into a contract with the Tribe to draft a management plan described in that section pursuant to the authority of the Secretary under the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5301">25 U.S.C. 5301 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9177C58FD81742C1B0389CBE303B4854"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition of cultural foods</header><text>For purposes of the management plan described in paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consult with the Tribe to define the term <term>cultural foods</term>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H164BED5F24D046A4A0C7442C1597C6B5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text>The management plan described in paragraph (1) may be included in the management strategy for the 1 or more Zones developed under subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H584A16D995344D07A6D7C8B996373DBF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Land and resource management plan</header><text>Any revisions or amendments to the land and resource management plan applicable to the National Forest under the Forest and Rangeland Renewable Resources Planning Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1600">16 U.S.C. 1600 et seq.</external-xref>) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H6835079309014623B8ABF4DEFD2A9C88"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be made in consultation with the Tribe and other Indian Tribes with historical or legal interests in the National Forest; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5C9E6E17AE624AEAA05E1E05318CC9E1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be consistent with the management strategy for the 1 or more Zones; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H22E4A5B1EDFB4B4285BA84CC6239BD1E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>within the 1 or more Zones, protect Treaty rights and allow management of the resources on which the Treaty rights depend.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFB688B3D2F374C8F9CE46E49C1FD77BF"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Effect</header><text>Nothing in this section—</text> <paragraph id="H1739384877A64772B860758AB276BC2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>enlarges, establishes, or diminishes the current or future rights of any Indian Tribe, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H2D2CDBC5FB2448B2BD518CC9D542B54C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the exercise of hunting, fishing, gathering, and pasturing of livestock rights in usual and accustomed areas; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA98FAF6FED4E4B4787A8C220D6D35F3C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Indian hunting, fishing, or gathering activities conducted under an agreement with the State;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDE71DBFA71C44C0C8EC59B27CDE4A209"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides any Indian Tribe with exclusive use of any area within the National Forest; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H944AF8C69AB94B90AF017E0B94B4CC6C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>limits the Secretary from entering into a separate agreement with other Indian Tribes with treaty rights or a recognized legal interest in the National Forest.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H3E7FB7296D60413CB0BC8EEE39F45226"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Funding</header>
<paragraph id="HA83D7E79980F4E1C99100B4E66B2E646"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $3,500,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2846E330424C4E3E95BC0F98FA0EADFD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority to use other funds</header><text>Subject to the availability of funds, and based on priorities for the National Forest, the Secretary may use existing funds of the Forest Service and Forest Service program revenue generated from forest restoration activities to carry out the management strategy for the 1 or more Zones, in line with the purposes laid out in subsection(b)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H4ECE04EDAFFA486595EBA876A451F70A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of the Omnibus Public Land Management Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/11">Public Law 111–11</external-xref>; 123 Stat. 991) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 1207 the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9794EAE776DE47B1BCB17A628D2DF2EB"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 1208. Indian Treaty Resources Emphasis Zones.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

