<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6F4FAB067FEC4E9EB591237CEF547AEB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3577 IH: Medical and Health Stockpile Accountability Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3577</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response to establish an automated supply chain tracking application that provides near real-time insight into the amount of critical medical and health supplies available in the Strategic National Stockpile.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H360EB666863440BCB03B91329BBB4794" style="OLC"><section id="H62E2FDE32DF045FD84583C9A275464F1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medical and Health Stockpile Accountability Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3DF3609FC4144144905EBD92039EEE8F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Tracking and accountability of supplies in the national stockpile</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 319F–2 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d-6b">42 U.S.C. 247d–6b</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H43D200CF74C240E582421B3626C19694"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (h) as subsection (i); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2574D2143B1402B9A1A3CBC16472A66"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (g) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H13184D2BC087417EA06BF5BFE2F77E19"><subsection id="HBB2994455D6C433CB8EA50C8A6A5E26E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Tracking and accountability of supplies in the stockpile</header><paragraph id="HFFC24A10EEC340BAA08D44B302EFEE73"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Assistant Secretary</quote>) shall establish an automated supply chain tracking application that provides near real-time insight into the amount of critical medical and health supplies available in the stockpile under subsection (a), and available in the medical and health supply inventories of State, Tribal, territories, and local and private entities such as hospitals, manufacturers, and distributors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8310AA511B34975B885EA7B160CDE96"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Access and use of the application</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall establish rules for data access, and use of, the application established under paragraph (1). Such rules shall—</text><subparagraph id="H948297AF62E84DC1B50C16D689E72ED4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>require internal tracking, pursuant to subsection (d), of all supplies within the stockpile under subsection (a), in a manner that is visible to Federal entities identified by the Assistant Secretary;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B11292C56834142A4445A22B0943CC0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>allow for data access, by Federal entities during an emergency response, as determined by the Assistant Secretary, to the medical and health supply stockpiles of State, Tribal, territories, and local and private partners;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9760EB2D48E44B0EA71DFC99BF5D0FD1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>establish, after consultation with public and private partners, a national standard for collecting and reporting data related to products maintained in the stockpile, including—</text><clause id="HCCB8C75FC3E948A59BF6A81BEA3EBD73" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>data standards for category of products, nomenclature, and standards for coding of each product for entities to report product availability in their Federal, State, and local jurisdictions;</text></clause><clause id="H68A0746C665C440B9834FAB34F173BA7" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>application of the standard to Tribal and local stockpiles; and</text></clause><clause id="HB11AA28D70F8445182259290D08F4B1C" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a data dictionary defining terms, such as <quote>burn rate</quote>, <quote>calculation of supply-on-hand</quote>, and other appropriate terms;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E9EEE1CEAFC459A9DCA18CF7967DA16"><enum>(D)</enum><text>ensure clear and efficient mechanisms for health care entities, including hospitals, manufacturers, and distributors, to report data in an emergency that supports medical and health supply chain management and surge re-deployment, including detailed data regarding all relevant supplies secured and available;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3FA6F3A5312D44828ED08DCC7A21E03E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>allow access by the Administration for Strategic Preparedness and Response to data from different vendor management systems, through automated feeds from health care entities, eliminating manual reporting errors from health care entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA278EDADA0B45AA9B2126D14528B12B"><enum>(F)</enum><text>establish the parameters for permitted and prohibited government data access and uses;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFE0B25047B445C0A7270F9B515E529E"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that the Administration for Strategic Preparedness and Response protects any data from hospitals, manufacturers, and distributors that is shared through the application, including protection of confidential, proprietary, commercial, and trade secret information;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5B72B452DE54B8D910A8D2B22606C9B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>ensure that Federal data collection is for monitoring and dynamic allocation and will not be used to remove or reallocate inventory from organizations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H196F46EAB66F4506BAE2D35FEA56BDE1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>ensure that data will not be used by suppliers for commercial or contractual purposes;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCA83FC2B9B44AF4B9C59B666601AB39"><enum>(J)</enum><text>ensure that reported data will not be used to advantage or disadvantage any institution over another or to undermine the competitive marketplace; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0C10B7D5BB84A719379D4963CDC42AD"><enum>(K)</enum><text>ensure that the application interfaces, for tracking management purposes, with the National Disaster Recovery Framework of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, appropriate dashboards of the Department of Defense, and other appropriate Federal partners.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H473C796080A840DDB05E4BE483F0C437"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Participation by private entities</header><text>The application established under paragraph (1) shall support the voluntary sharing of data and accessing data by private health care supply chain entities, by allowing such entities to display near real-time data relating to inventory and time estimates for when inventories may be replenished.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6099701DC28E437985EF2E8CA947EEC9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Annual exercise</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary shall provide for an annual exercise hosted by the Administration for Strategic Preparedness and Response to test the effectiveness of the application established under paragraph (1), and to provide an opportunity to report, not later than 180 days after publication of the standards described in paragraph (2)(C), any inefficiencies or deficiencies in the application.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20535AAB70CE4A08A53CE9CD6D8AE556"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Program of support</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall establish a program to assist State, local, and private health care entities, such as rural, critical access, or community hospitals, that do not have an automated vendor management system in developing or obtaining such a system. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE9C2F312E454EE4A03EE25B1F0C6693"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Assistant Secretary for the acquisition and development of an application under this section, $250,000,000 to remain available for fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

