<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC2D5A3BA411C4756851C5D06B3550721" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6210 IH: To designate the General George C. Marshall House, in the Commonwealth of Virginia, as an affiliated area of the National Park System, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6210</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To designate the General George C. Marshall House, in the Commonwealth of Virginia, as an affiliated area of the National Park System, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0A609013A0EF411584227AD8D7F9392C" style="OLC"><section id="H3EEE3C29FBFD4C38A2C99602ED2BE2D1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of the General George C. Marshall House as an affiliated area</header><subsection id="H18806FAE1AD4441093E4DEAF6779027E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The General George C. Marshall House, in the Commonwealth of Virginia, is established as an affiliated area of the National Park System to promote public appreciation of the significant historic contributions made by United States military leader and statesman George Catlett Marshall, Jr. </text></subsection><subsection id="HB33A53B7BE6E4F3BB57B7508151C947D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Description of affiliated area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The affiliated area shall consist of the area generally depicted as the <quote>General George C. Marshall House Property, Leesburg, Virginia</quote> on the map titled <quote>General George C. Marshall House, Proposed Affiliated Area</quote>, numbered 999/189,974, and dated September 2023.</text></subsection><subsection id="H80E4C467F70845DBACC794B865AEEB30"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The affiliated area shall be managed in a manner consistent with—</text><paragraph id="H88426EBA657D4FDFA08E3A6A8871B7CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H336A3409A1F94858A0A8A00611573624"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any law generally applicable to units of the National Park System.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3B9B7D27A9804A7B96782EE21239D596"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Management entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The George C. Marshall International Center shall be the management entity for the affiliated area.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDD0DB3B967D44CF1B043F3F4532A99C6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Cooperative agreements</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) may provide technical assistance and enter into cooperative agreements with the management entity for the purpose of providing financial assistance for the marketing, marking, interpretation, and preservation of the affiliated area.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6D28C7B3844E44FCA74BC3E565CBD070"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limited role of the secretary</header><text>Nothing in this section authorizes the Secretary to acquire property at the affiliated area or to assume overall financial responsibility for the operation, maintenance, or management of the affiliated area.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2F6B5A0332D54FD7A03D97ADCAB31B2D"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Management plan</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date on which funds are made available to carry out this subsection, the Secretary, in consultation with the management entity, shall complete a management plan for the affiliated area in accordance with section 100502 of title 54, United States Code.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

