<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H866BBAB0EF564367A8CAA215F4617955" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6863 IH: Housing for Heroes Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6863</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that members of the Armed Forces, firefighters, and law enforcement officers shall be eligible for the Good Neighbor Next Door Sales Program of the Department of Housing and Urban Development, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2EF75A1607254354B68AEFEEA9E64D4A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H90B36BBAEFEA440F9D9D2FF5DA1734DE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Housing for Heroes Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text> </section> <section id="H78CAD75A9DBC4FDF93E4E91A56FC53EC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Eligibility of members of the Armed Forces, firefighters, and law enforcement officers for Good Neighbor Next Door Sales Program</header> <subsection id="H92A05B26DF94435C9562B54ED59CA0B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of the Armed Forces, firefighters, and law enforcement officers shall be eligible to purchase eligible properties under the Good Neighbor Next Door Sales Program of the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, as provided under subsection (b).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD906B9334FBC465A8B69E6DFFD1485D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible properties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 204 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1710">12 U.S.C. 1710</external-xref>), part 291 of the regulations of the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (24 C.F.R. part 291), or any other provision of law, regulation, guideline, order, or notice, in carrying out the Good Neighbor Next Door Sales Program for single-unit properties acquired by the Secretary, properties shall be made available for purchase under the Program by members of the Armed Forces, by firefighters, and by law enforcement officers without regard to whether or not they are located in a revitalization area.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5A7CE6B26F23464598FF1E830DDFCE8A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall amend the regulations of the Secretary as necessary to carry out subsections (a) and (b). </text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

