<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD782B9145E814154929198BE25DCB838" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3417 IH: Facilitating Accountability In Reimbursements Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3417</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure fair billing practices for items and services furnished by off-campus outpatient departments of a provider.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H29E8ED3DC5884DE9B043191497644763" style="OLC"><section id="HEE732E73A09646E68D0EBDA1AED2807E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Facilitating Accountability In Reimbursements Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FAIR Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HB2D18BAA5D1B4347AF16C6AA8B68F661" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring fair billing practices for items and services furnished by off-campus outpatient departments of a provider</header><subsection id="HEB0446DB9C1D45ED8FCED07BBBD9A359"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Separate NPIs for off-Campus outpatient departments of a provider</header><paragraph id="HC4E1F22486C3454199F611F493AEC819"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1173(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320d-2">42 U.S.C. 1320d–2(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD51524F784A14FC7A5B9956369777E8C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H85830EB05249471183C0C8F81019BAFD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Ensuring separate NPIs for off-campus outpatient departments of a provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The standards specified under paragraph (1) shall ensure that, not later than January 1, 2025, each off-campus outpatient department of a provider (as defined in section 1833(t)(21)(B)) is assigned a separate unique health identifier from such provider. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5097D74A21A4029A01C2510542E9D31"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Treatment of certain departments as subparts of a hospital</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2025, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall revise sections 162.408 and 162.410 of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations, to ensure that each off-campus outpatient department of a provider (as defined in section 1833(t)(21)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(t)(21)(B)</external-xref>)) is treated as a subpart (as described in such sections) of such provider and assigned a unique health identifier pursuant to section 1173(b)(3) of such Act (as added by paragraph (1)). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDC46758502DD435CAD1420E1B36D5867"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Off-Campus departments of a provider billing requirements</header><paragraph id="H94C8E28330704E53A752F03736DB37EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Medicare</header><subparagraph id="HFBCD8B284FBC4FD694177E8B5C94CE32"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1866(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc">42 U.S.C. 1395cc(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><clause id="H868E4679C7984119BDA53165321FEFE2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (X), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="H8AFD8854DFE24D2CBACB40E0614F35AC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (Y)(ii)(V), by striking the period and inserting <quote>, and</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HAD87CC1176A04FE68AD90F430AE0D614"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (Y) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H64D38B4374234C51AEFE6FAD0A1D51B9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H718A160815F04819B7E10939261E2C17" indent="up1"><enum>(Z)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a hospital with an off-campus outpatient department of a provider (as defined in section 1833(t)(21)(B)), with respect to items and services furnished at such department of a provider on or after January 1, 2025, to bill under this title (including under part C of this title) for such items and services using the unique health identifier established for such department of a provider pursuant to section 1173(b)(3) on a HIPAA X12 837P transaction or CMS 1500 form (or a successor transaction or form).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87BAA5C55F6A412CB69BD03C9DEC970B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Compliance reviews</header><text>In conducting any regular reviews of off-campus outpatient departments of a provider (as defined in section 1833(t)(21)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(t)(21)(B)</external-xref>)) for purposes of determining whether such departments are compliant with the requirements of section 413.65 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation), the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall prioritize reviewing such departments that, prior to billing for covered OPD services (as defined in section 1833(t) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395l">42 U.S.C. 1395l(t)</external-xref>)) under part B of title XVIII of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395j">42 U.S.C. 1395j et seq.</external-xref>), were furnishing items and services billed solely by individual practitioners or group practices under such part and that are not located in a rural area (as defined in section 1886(d)(2)(D) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww(d)(2)(D)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H02E6F2804E794B79A35A92F8C4A50DF7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other providers</header><text>Part E of title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-131">42 U.S.C. 300gg–131 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4A6003B53B7A43A39DB1BAAFF44B2E4D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H2BE5C76D40334535B6C7C669726AD1D2"><enum>2799B–10.</enum><header>Billing requirements for off-campus departments of a provider</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">A health care provider may not, with respect to items and services furnished to an individual at an off-campus outpatient department of a provider (as defined in section 1833(t)(21)(B) of the Social Security Act), submit a claim for such items and services to a group health plan or health insurance issuer, and may not hold such individual liable for such items and services, unless such items and services are billed—</text><paragraph id="H196B0468A24B4A1C91A97F4FDE9170C3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>using the separate unique health identifier established for such department pursuant to section 1173(b)(3) of such Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5777689280764376B3D3D6D7BF73D881"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on a HIPAA X12 837P transaction or CMS 1500 form (or a successor transaction or form).</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HA092F3AD3EA64A37B6EB887F8D64FF66"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by paragraph (1) shall apply with respect to claims submitted for items and services furnished on or after January 1, 2025.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

