<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H476B2F5FB0D04432BCFE59AE328BF752" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 839 IH: China Exchange Rate Transparency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 839</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230206">February 6, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the United States Executive Director at the International Monetary Fund to advocate for increased transparency with respect to exchange rate policies of the People’s Republic of China, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HF2359DA3C7E74B74A9895731A5BD3365" style="OLC">
<section id="HC3B88CB4628947BDA5F9A4A59CE52698" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>China Exchange Rate Transparency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF2E61F22AF4D4281BAC82A6C8938CD81"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text>
<paragraph id="HC6D8BA878013432CA276B474410AD456"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under Article IV of the Articles of Agreement of the International Monetary Fund (IMF), the People’s Republic of China has committed to orderly exchange rate arrangements, the avoidance of exchange rate manipulation, and cooperation with the IMF to ensure <quote>firm surveillance</quote> of the exchange rate policies of the People’s Republic of China. Pursuant to Article VIII of the Articles of Agreement of the IMF, the IMF may require the People’s Republic of China to furnish data on gold and foreign exchange holdings, including assets held by non-official agencies of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7528D4C88BC040D9A8948DE640B3F03E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In its November 2022 report, entitled <quote>Macroeconomic and Foreign Exchange Policies of Major Trading Partners of the United States</quote>, the Department of the Treasury concluded, <quote>China provides very limited transparency regarding key features of its exchange rate mechanism, including the policy objectives of its exchange rate management regime and its activities in the offshore RMB market.</quote>. The Department continued: <quote>China’s lack of transparency and use of a wide array of tools complicate Treasury’s ability to assess the degree to which official actions are designed to impact the exchange rate.</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA372AC1B164647B9930CDF01C148AF15"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In that report, the Department further noted that <quote>China’s failure to publish foreign exchange intervention and broader lack of transparency around key features of its exchange rate mechanism make it an outlier among major economies and warrants Treasury’s close monitoring.</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HD174FFD3EBD3479C96779EF568BFD787"><enum>3.</enum><header>Advocacy for increased exchange rate transparency from China</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall instruct the United States Executive Director at the International Monetary Fund (in this Act referred to as the <quote>IMF</quote>) to use the voice and vote of the United States to advocate for—</text>
<paragraph id="HA667E8E5D68A4D0C89C091052DB79D80"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increased transparency from the People’s Republic of China with respect to the exchange rate arrangements of the People’s Republic of China, including any indirect foreign exchange market intervention through Chinese financial institutions or State-owned enterprises;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7F1BBCD8685B46BAB290536FFC269F18"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compliance by the People’s Republic of China with information requests from the IMF regarding the exchange rate policies and holdings of the People’s Republic of China, consistent with the Articles of Agreement of the IMF;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H703F234E42904550827FF26C310BAAE4"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in connection with consultations with the People’s Republic of China under Article IV of the Articles of Agreement of the IMF, the publication of any significant divergences by the People’s Republic of China from the exchange rate policies of other issuers of currencies used in determining the value of Special Drawing Rights; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BC551835D334A13A562B59D6725FBB1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during governance reviews of the IMF, stronger consideration by IMF members and management of non-transparent exchange rate policies undertaken by the People’s Republic of China when evaluating quota and voting shares at the IMF.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H26E464A490C24F21BA8C897D236F6405"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall have no force or effect on or after the date that is 30 days after the earlier of—</text> <paragraph id="H1BDBB79EB08C45B0995A0E20EF63C8DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date that the United States Governor of the IMF reports to the Congress that the People’s Republic of China—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5084FCD84A0343A68295FB5A73426496" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is in substantial compliance with obligations of the People’s Republic of China under the Articles of Agreement of the IMF regarding orderly exchange rate arrangements; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEEC3F38C317F4B978810D0A5AA8F725D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has undertaken exchange rate policies consistent with those of other issuers of currencies used in determining the value of Special Drawing Rights; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5426EAC734DD4C129612909F5465CC35"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date that is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

