<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA24A4059FC9E4CB3B5BE2192B7F1191C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 6285 IH: Alaska’s Right to Produce Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6285</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231108">November 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001212">Mr. Stauber</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ratify and approve all authorizations, permits, verifications, extensions, biological opinions, incidental take statements, and any other approvals or orders issued pursuant to Federal law necessary for the establishment and administration of the Coastal Plain oil and gas leasing program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H840C90EF0D3F400A879D6FC0D7823847" style="OLC"><section id="HA5E3ADDC706E4FC489C30EFB8F6A8ED3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Alaska’s Right to Produce Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H724B2734A4224276818D5A9DDF4352AD" section-type="subsequent-section" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Congressional findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text><paragraph id="H1E0D09E090D1499393F899461FC33391" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress provided clear authorization and direction that the Secretary of the Interior <quote>shall establish and administer a competitive oil and gas program for the leasing, development, production, and transportation of oil and gas in and from the Coastal Plain</quote> in section 20001 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3143">16 U.S.C. 3143</external-xref> note) (commonly known as the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBA0B5E1A0E045E1920B6555AD040D3C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the timely administration of the Coastal Plain Oil and Gas Leasing Program is required and in the national and public interest;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20BED609F8EA4854A0595E6EADD1399D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Department of the Interior’s cancelling of the leases for the covered Coastal Plain lease tracts represents a major decision of economic and political significance that Congress did not delegate to the Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF3AFC0BE30442CFB1A9C55BA00F93B7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Naval Petroleum Reserves Production Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6501">42 U.S.C. 6501 et seq.</external-xref>) requires that the Bureau of Land Management—</text><subparagraph id="H8FB7C831DB4048E3A4823EC367D59FAE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>allow for the exploration, development, and production of petroleum products in the National Petroleum Reserve in Alaska; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AD0C35615AF49A5B366E410EA14165F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>equally balance, to the extent consistent with that Act, the protection of ecological and cultural values in the National Petroleum Reserve in Alaska; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C265DF576A8403499E0FAFB24F83DAE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the proposed rule of the Bureau of Land Management entitled <quote>Management and Protection of the National Petroleum Reserve in Alaska</quote> (88 Fed. Reg. 62025 (September 8, 2023)) fails to reflect the intent of Congress for the Naval Petroleum Reserves Production Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6501">42 U.S.C. 6501 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HDE88C7D09CFF4889BE2B1BFB4B0C85A6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HF368A66BFC6C4BE298C8813C4B792318"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coastal plain</header><text>The term <term>Coastal Plain</term> has the meaning given the term in section 20001(a) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3143">16 U.S.C. 3143</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC51FC09C83849B1A9E005D57A9065F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coastal plain oil and gas leasing program</header><text>The term <term>Coastal Plain oil and gas leasing program</term> means the program established under section 20001(b)(2)(A) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3143">16 U.S.C. 3143</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1E8E53216744A7C979AB15F06EF2745" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered Coastal Plain lease tract</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered Coastal Plain lease tract</term> means any of tracts 16, 17, 24, 26, 27, and 30 as listed in exhibit B of the document published by the Bureau of Land Management entitled <quote>Amendment to the Detailed Statement of Sale</quote> and dated December 18, 2020 (relating to oil and gas leasing within the Coastal Plain Alaska).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F41F2504D20481EA363E886BBE5B0CF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Record of decision</header><text>The term <term>Record of Decision</term> means the record of decision described in the notice of availability of the Bureau of Land Management entitled <quote>Notice of Availability of the Record of Decision for the Final Environmental Impact Statement for the Coastal Plain Oil and Gas Leasing Program, Alaska</quote> (85 Fed. Reg. 51754 (August 21, 2020)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E9CA47E8252488E96E3A092D6C5719B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H89F84F3E85634465BA7A544C2B181DC6" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Congressional approval of orders</header><subsection id="HBB4189B2AB9748AA866D27AC12445E3D" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Moratorium on Oil and Gas Leasing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any order or action by the President or the Secretary that has the effect of placing a moratorium on or otherwise suspending or pausing oil and gas leasing in the Coastal Plain shall have no force or effect.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2C790606B44D4C7A9DAB13B3868F621D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Approval and ratification of existing documentation and authorizations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, Congress—</text><paragraph id="HBA9390997E294303A3207253321B5332" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ratifies and approves all authorizations, permits, verifications, extensions, biological opinions, incidental take statements, and any other approvals or orders issued pursuant to Federal law, as described in the Record of Decision, necessary for the establishment and administration of the Coastal Plain Oil and Gas Leasing Program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H892E4DD462DC427690C4A82F824B20F0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">directs the Secretary, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and the heads of other as applicable Federal departments and agencies to process, reinstate, or continue to maintain such authorizations, permits, verifications, extensions, biological opinions, incidental take statements, and any other approvals or orders described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFE86FDAC8DAA45238D46A5CD6EFE1F42" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability of other law</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the authorizations, permits, verifications, extensions, biological opinions, incidental take statements, and any other approvals or orders described in subsection (b)(1) shall be considered to satisfy the requirements of—</text><paragraph id="H17A82EA347194363928EF34AC2340999" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>section 1002 of the Alaska National Interest Lands Conservation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3142">16 U.S.C. 3142</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF77200FBB4449368F22CC36D6A25B2D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>section 102(2)(c) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(c));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E8D7D71F9FE45A987E13CF3249C9688" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>section 20001 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3143">16 U.S.C. 3143</external-xref> note);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A077889EFAC4888A907F7335B9353D7" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B68EE37DE1A44ABA3BDB18650D94E10" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/7">chapter 7</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5A154A2A20FD4B52976AEEB0969563CD"><enum>5.</enum><header>Coastal Plain oil and gas leasing program</header><subsection id="H837BADA8E929444E81270E0BD2A977A7" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reissuance of canceled leases</header><paragraph id="HC991F8D5D621486E8F8B9E0B6C028ECC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Acceptance of bids</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall, without modification or delay—</text><subparagraph id="H5858F735808943F1BB8975A239020500" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">accept the highest valid bid for each covered Coastal Plain lease tract for which a valid bid was received on January 6, 2021, pursuant to the requirement to hold the first lease sale in the Coastal Plain oil and gas leasing program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E0997DCE4984367B75610A745447C58" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide the appropriate lease form to each winning bidder under subparagraph (A) to execute and return to the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H815ED2965ADD49B9ADC63FAD270C3E38" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Lease issuance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On receipt of an executed lease form under paragraph (1)(B) and payment in accordance with that lease of the rental for the first year, the balance of the bonus bid (unless deferred), and any required bond or security from the high bidder, the Secretary shall promptly issue to the high bidder a fully executed lease, in accordance with—</text><subparagraph id="H122690563251469B8EF936442AD78FA2" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the applicable regulations, as in effect on January 6, 2021; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H005F5B82D822497FA98E29302B1F6269" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the terms and conditions of the Record of Decision.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD887A96C4E644E6AB4D4DCA8E74485B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement for future leases</header><paragraph id="H4BD2E92D28864AB3B0DDA2517DB0E8CA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Second lease sale</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than December 22, 2024, the Secretary shall conduct the second lease sale required by section 20001(c)(1)(B)(ii)(II) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3143">16 U.S.C. 3143</external-xref> note) in accordance with the Record of Decision.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54EF44F3E8E347E885E6884EDD91553F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions for canceling a lease</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the President and the Secretary may not cancel a lease issued under the Coastal Plain oil and gas leasing program if the Secretary has previously opened bids for such a lease or disclosed the high bidder for any tract that was included in a lease sale under the Coastal Plain oil and gas leasing program unless the lessee is in violation of the terms of the lease and fails to cure the violation after a reasonable period of time.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60DBA3C8A3A24515A92054717159A418" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability of prior record of decision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law and with respect to reissuing leases under subsection (a), the Record of Decision shall be considered to satisfy the requirements of—</text><paragraph id="H4C3D22CB424444CBB7073A3C1D719224"><enum>(1)</enum><text>section 1002 of the Alaska National Interest Lands Conservation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3142">16 U.S.C. 3142</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5938A214299B4C61931973C5EDD991B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>section 102(2)(c) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (42 U.S.C. 4332(2)(c));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H078EA42152CE4B10AA5AFBA82C67F80D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>section 20001 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3143">16 U.S.C. 3143</external-xref> note);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74E19137757E4AC08412140D8D8A0261" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/93/205">Public Law 93–205</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1533">16 U.S.C. 1533</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED87FF1C9D864A8BAD5B36979BA15C65" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/7">chapter 7</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD2797FF7EA954E3F8BA7C82F1ED3BDAC" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Withdrawal of supplemental environmental impact statement</header><text>The Director of the Bureau of Land Management—</text><paragraph id="H588F83FFF9684BAE860BBBBE1BC6394A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall withdraw the notice of availability entitled <quote>Notice of Availability of the Draft Coastal Plain Oil and Gas Leasing Program Supplemental Environmental Impact Statement</quote> (88 Fed. Reg. 62104 (September 8, 2023)); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA5DC91DDD3947239F5A03F226CD9339" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may not take any action to finalize, implement, or enforce the supplemental environmental impact statement described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF600E7C597B94763801EE91D9E390EA1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Judicial review</header><paragraph id="H16D587906E9640D19B80FBE2F7DBB354"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Judicial preclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law and except as provided in paragraph (2), no court shall have jurisdiction to review any action taken by the Secretary, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, a State administrative agency, an Indian Tribe, or any other Federal agency acting pursuant to Federal law that grants an authorization, permit, verification, biological opinion, incidental take statement, or other approval described in section 4(b) for the Coastal Plain Oil and Gas Leasing Program, whether issued prior to, on, or after the date of enactment of this Act, and including any lawsuit or any other action pending in a court as of the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA43BDE6F868B4F5C82363C9507DBE30F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Forum exclusivity</header><text>The United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit shall have original and exclusive jurisdiction over any claim regarding—</text><subparagraph id="HCB749E8CFDE34E34982A769377461F05"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the validity of this section; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H944FF5755D474044AE4F67C1D47EEAA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the scope of authority conferred by this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H23EA8FB4B2F5434189A01623B8E0581F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Right to petition</header><subparagraph id="HC3C9A15BE03D489396FDEC3493E0BBA1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1), a lease holder may obtain a review of an alleged failure by an agency to act in accordance with section 20001 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3143">16 U.S.C. 3143</external-xref> note) or with any law pertaining to the grant of an authorization, permit, verification, biological opinion, incidental take statement, or other approval related to the lease holder’s lease by filing a written petition with a court of competent jurisdiction seeking an order under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB72198C301F4245AC6F38A6CBBB64DC" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Deadlines</header><text>If a court of competent jurisdiction finds that an agency has failed to act in accordance with section 20001 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3143">16 U.S.C. 3143</external-xref> note) or with any law pertaining to the grant of an authorization, permit, verification, biological opinion, incidental take statement, or other approval related to the lease holder’s lease, the court shall set a schedule and deadline for the agency to act as soon as practicable, which shall not exceed 90 days from the date on which the order of the court is issued, unless the court determines a longer time period is necessary to comply with applicable law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF8C96871040D44F4825525F58A4F4AF1"><enum>6.</enum><header>Nullification of certain Federal agency actions</header><subsection id="H45E958F7C5294EE98E3E052AF7541C53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>NPRA rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Bureau of Land Management—</text><paragraph id="HE2BD4258E2A8413BAB1FC9D525F50EED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall withdraw the proposed rule of the Bureau of Land Management entitled <quote>Management and Protection of the National Petroleum Reserve in Alaska</quote> (88 Fed. Reg. 62025 (September 8, 2023)); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H348B8526CBBE4AE3AA9AB67595B35CD7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may not take any action to finalize, implement, administer, or enforce the proposed rule described in paragraph (1) or any substantially similar rule.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4F7D5B01CDB84F0FB030A4601FC62818"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Executive order 13990</header><paragraph id="H3F3AE481D895483A8C90F5328F6523D0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4 of Executive Order 13990 (86 Fed. Reg. 7037; relating to protecting public health and the environment and restoring science to tackle the climate crisis) shall have no force or effect.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F9AAEBA2F0F434ABEB0C42A6B15D72A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds may be obligated or expended to carry out section 4 of the Executive Order described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3D7057449AFB414BA7E99C5B387FC499" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Secretarial order 3401</header><paragraph id="H52FC59BF2716442CAF9C00A2317BA904"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Secretarial Order 3401 (relating to the Comprehensive Analysis and Temporary Halt on all Activities in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge Relating to the Coastal Plain Oil and Gas Leasing Program), issued by the Secretary on June 1, 2021, shall have no force or effect.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3182A3ADDC7B46EDADBCB8BC98921173"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds may be obligated or expended to carry out the Secretarial Order described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

