<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6296CF1085A24A0D9638B1AEC157FFE1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6173 IH: Tech Safety for Victims of Domestic Violence, Dating Violence, Sexual Assault, and Stalking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6173</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a pilot program to address technology-related abuse in domestic violence cases.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF765258D782549E09903051A0B5A2590" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H51B8D4CFC9984AABB2E22E1E89100662"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Tech Safety for Victims of Domestic Violence, Dating Violence, Sexual Assault, and Stalking Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB082CB5B7561440790E27C3165637534"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H637DF3FCE09644F8A5629B2860F9E3E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the United States, 41 percent of women and 26 percent of men experience some form of sexual violence, physical violence, or stalking, or a combination thereof, by an intimate partner.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4AC33BF7E01D4E26AC16AE7137421B96"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Many victims of intimate partner violence also experience nonphysical forms of abuse.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H309478F1835448FCA49E4F74092B96CB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>With the proliferation of digital technology, technological abuse has become increasingly prevalent and pervasive among victims of intimate partner violence.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H335F0B399EA34C32A4C0B5F9D06C98D2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to a 2021 study by the National Network to End Domestic Violence, 97 percent of the programs providing support to victims of intimate partner violence have indicated that abusers are making use of technology to stalk, harass, or control victims.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H34C95DE29E624C8D8B6BD0C1262693FE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In the United States, 1 in 3 women under the age of 35 report being sexually harassed online, and over half of LGBTQ+ individuals report being the target of online abuse based on their sexual orientation or gender.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD11676D7DCA8448DACB1291BBD7F3E9A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Of victims who are stalked using technology—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H30281D8B173D4407AE11A4F5AED4B379"><enum>(A)</enum><text>67 percent received unwanted phone calls, voice messages, or text messages;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H94D96C5486B04B69934532FB6C61803B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>50 percent received unwanted emails or messages via the internet;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H03BDF0C4FA5E4B1DA585A75E36DDD6F6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>about 35 percent said their activities were monitored using social media;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H86FF78D7894C4B41946865AC161F0A42"><enum>(D)</enum><text>27 percent experienced the offender posting or threatening to post inappropriate, unwanted, or personal information about them on the internet; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBFAE8F73B56F4252BE1E8405B3FFA289"><enum>(E)</enum><text>19 percent said the offender spied on them or monitored their activities using technologies such as listening devices, cameras, or computer or cellphone monitoring software.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE9687DC38B514873BC4B77949AC4C150"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Technological abuse runs the gamut of technical sophistication, from the most basic social media platforms and phone-based apps to specialty stalkerware apps, demonstrating that technological abuse does not require huge financial resources or complex knowledge of technology.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4F01FC266EA7415083BFBA0E05EA95B3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Rapid advances in the technology and methods for technological abuse present challenges for advocates seeking to advise victims and prevent technological abuse.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48607FD84AE94E9580A96CA2405D527B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The integration of trained technology experts into survivor support networks has been successful in preventing and shielding survivors from technological abuse.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H7A1A4C3CE3E740A38625EFA395C037E3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H45E767AD114A43AA89AF271BDEDE0276"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Office on Violence Against Women.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0DAF33D92F05440394078D548C6A1DAC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible consortium</header><text>The term <term>eligible consortium</term> means an association—</text> <subparagraph id="H2BEA55FC3F3E476CA3F77FBE38E1A7F2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>between—</text> 
<clause id="H890129D904CA44B2B36D25FA94C1EA60"><enum>(i)</enum> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4217C2D95E1A494CBCF3BBAAFD18843F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>1 or more institutions of higher education that offers a masters, doctoral, or vocational program in information technology, cybersecurity, computer science, or other similar technological discipline; or</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="HFFBEC0782E1A42C282DCD7946E66D0A9" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>1 or more private or public sector partners in the community with a technical workforce and a plan for recruiting technologists or volunteers to work alongside a victim service provider (as defined in section 40002(a) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(a)</external-xref>); and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H16A7BFEB2BA74FC281C2D2ECE3DFFEEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 or more public or private domestic violence or sexual violence centers; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H268AC6AB94834759BE3F31B8A79D1F45"><enum>(B)</enum><text>which has a letter of support from the local, State, Tribal, or territorial government with jurisdiction over the area in which the activities to combat technological abuse will be implemented. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H33F30BF6EF294AA1B62CAC91F5198BBB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE249594063F047E39D860FE659C30000"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><text>The term <term>pilot program</term> means the pilot program established under section 4(a)(1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8F9E68F5D1B45FEBA0E52B04CA9131A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Technological abuse</header><text>The term <term>technological abuse</term> has the meaning given the term in section 40002(a)(40) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(a)(40)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD3E3917E944F41D69D6D0CBFFB565F9C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Pilot program to combat technological abuse</header> <subsection id="H7D9EF80EB5324338B3DBC7842092ACB3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Pilot program authorized</header> <paragraph id="H964CF38011764293BD20CFEE8D77C024"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director, in accordance with paragraph (2), shall establish a pilot program under which the Director may award grants to eligible consortia to combat technological abuse.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9641F3D2B6BF49EB955CB1E4B4C715FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In preparing to establish the pilot program—</text> <subparagraph id="HFE88975E97B744149729D25DC87F3EB9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Director shall consult with—</text> 
<clause id="H8059D4747822435C9AB2D243575C7A74"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary of Health and Human Services; </text></clause> <clause id="H4EC280307F3945B0AE251AF6B5E0CAC0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Secretary of Education; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFC3A80471592413397B83164F8900961"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Chairman of the Federal Communications Commission; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1D45D5512108460AAD957B3BDEEF2DBE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Director and the officers described in subparagraph (A) shall consult with relevant stakeholders, including—</text> 
<clause id="H08069D1AF1AD495FADE0CE41F3635C1F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>groups that work on reducing technological abuse; and</text></clause> <clause id="HB2ED8D655B6746BD9CFDCF74BE1F18A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>population specific and culturally specific victim service providers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0AEDD79B6D894CF9992A5F8C5C80CD07"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible consortium desiring a grant under this section shall submit to the Director an application at such time, in such manner, and containing or accompanied by such information, as the Director may reasonably require.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD84A8359834F4B178FA33C996A9BB03C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Grant limits</header> <subparagraph id="HA8F99EB3D7FE4F59820E2131535D0FF4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Award amount</header><text>A grant awarded under the pilot program shall be in an amount that is not more than $2,000,000.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H07658150FF5441159F60C1C8FA28D5EE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Number of recipients</header><text>Not more than 15 grants may be awarded under the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFBFB54766EB7427082278C1B16C5939B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Duration of pilot program</header><text>The pilot program shall terminate on the date that is 5 years after the date of the first award under the pilot program.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0225E36BB3DC4A79A389C1D3C393B406"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header><text>A recipient of a grant under this section may use the amounts received under the grant to combat technological abuse, including for—</text> <paragraph id="HA99D218A05384F19BD3E43067B0307E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text> the purchase of new technological devices for victims and survivors of technological abuse; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D168D5B6C3244F5A96B6E8542211328"><enum>(2)</enum><text> any other use, including the provision of victim services, that will reduce technological abuse or assist victims and survivors of technological abuse.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCD0CE554A36E43F1832C08E336919F6C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Pilot program review</header> <paragraph id="H018FECD7401443E88D0FBB730695DD94"><enum>(1)</enum><header>During pilot program</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of the first award under the pilot program, the Director shall submit to each committee of Congress with jurisdiction of the activities carried out under the pilot program a report—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD55E3F265D1E43979E86F09521CE3B1A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reviewing the efficacy of the pilot program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3F55E3AC4D3640E19F914A8F9C1ED1E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>indicating challenges to implementation and possible solutions; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H87A7CE2D5D4D4F89823E48F9A8BCEA2F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>including a recommendation relating to whether the pilot program should be turned into a permanent program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E5B9D8648304F1783518CB9801006E7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>After pilot program termination</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the pilot program terminates under subsection (a)(5), the Director shall submit to each committee of Congress with jurisdiction of the activities carried out under the pilot program a report reviewing the efficacy of the pilot program, including best practices and improvements needed to combat technological abuse.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBCBC5DDE00014DBF8C8A691D6F1D9A9A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H102D5FF60E3F40A5B35270A0DF999DE4"><enum>5.</enum><header>Grant program to provide education on technological abuse</header> <subsection id="HC5E6E8A830DE471F8FBEA129DD06F9EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program authorized</header><text>The Director in consultation with the Secretary of Education and the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall establish a program under which the Director may award grants to nonprofit organizations and institutions of higher education to develop and implement training and educational programs and technical assistance for organizations and individuals who provide support for victims of technological abuse.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA5F92F73713C41D1B09DC90314DB783B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Multiple grants</header><text>A recipient of a grant under section 4 is not barred from receiving a grant under this section. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HD91127EAA00743B48E1FF89E41E8F031"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header><text>A nonprofit organization or institution of higher education shall use the amounts received under a grant under this section to develop tools, curricula, and other materials.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H017AC781FFD04965AB076A9944332D41"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant program limits</header> 
<paragraph id="H03DA9A29ADDC4E65B97C00D2D52B58C6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>The Director may award a total of not more than $20,000,000 in grants under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H93D80EA2B42A40428B6D246936B8FF15"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Period of grants</header><text>The Director shall award grants under this section for a period of 5 years.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4058D71D5A4F49159EF24511F4EDB144"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

