<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2BBAB39A63C5488E98C9ADBC21053BFC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4915 IH: The Project Spectrum Authorization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4915</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 10, United States Code, to codify the program of the Office of Small Business Programs of the Department of Defense known as Project Spectrum, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3767D5EEE7684D3BBDA01DD828E28D7F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H923BAF6B1C4848A39E2F7ABBE8C85087" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>The Project Spectrum Authorization Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDADDE1D9AF1B445FBABF4027854AD106"><enum>2.</enum><header>Project Spectrum</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/19">Chapter 19</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by inserting before section 399 the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H0897A36450A24D9E83CB5EC2A156F91F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HE24A9755386949DE8D674B5B50FE2E0E"><enum>398b.</enum><header>Project Spectrum</header> 
<subsection id="H0584EFC0E1F14FFB8D0F3FF568AC4CCA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Project Spectrum; purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is within the Office of Small Business Programs of the Department of Defense a program known as <quote>Project Spectrum</quote>, the purpose of which is to provide to covered entities, through an online platform, digital resources and services that increase awareness about cybersecurity risks and help such covered entities to comply with the cybersecurity requirements of the defense acquisition system.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H73CE006A8BA1460792A8A5DED6C579E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Small Business Programs may establish eligibility requirements for the receipt by a covered entity of a given resource or service made available through Project Spectrum.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAC1049D0244543148BF6DE7725FD954A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To receive through Project Spectrum a resource or service for which the Director has established an eligibility requirement under subsection (b), a covered entity shall submit to the Director an application at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Director determines appropriate.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF3600557A4F042B5B798BD13FBD73CD8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Functions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out Project Spectrum, the Director shall maintain an online platform through which the Director shall make available to each covered entity that the Director determines to be eligible under subsection (b) with respect to a given resource or service, the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H8AF163C0E81C4CAEA270DC490EF87B86"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Educational materials regarding cybersecurity, including cybersecurity training courses and workforce development training.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H700038B28CA64D8B94D07E7578F620B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Guidance regarding best practices for cybersecurity matters, including guidance for developing internal cybersecurity policies and suggestions for procedures for reviewing any violation of such policies.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1FE118FD8D2C4171BC41D3A82B6A8477"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Assessments of the cybersecurity practices and cybersecurity systems used by a covered entity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8FF2EC11D3304B9E8FDC1FA1D040CDE1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A review and feasibility assessment of products, software, and data security tools available in the commercial marketplace.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H546616B6844048078FF4CC61199CC0B3"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cybersecurity services, including dashboard monitoring services, continuous threat monitoring services, software patching services, and patch testing services.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6CF6A4B1ABFB421488DE9761CD9989E1"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cybersecurity readiness checks.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE339EE8FCD4446B8997D187068D1BEA5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A platform for secure data collaboration between two or more employees of a covered entity and between multiple covered entities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2CE4B53FBB374EAC88E101FF699C5824"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Any additional resources or services, as determined by the Director.</text> </paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC7671B46F4D643A68B7F8FB69E901BE1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H8ED7F164ACB54247A70C331F8767C20C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>covered entity</term> means a supplier of the Department of Defense that is a small or medium business and registers to access the online platform of Project Spectrum.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1BE88B63DB06428D88308D3A3B102E1D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>defense acquisition system</quote> has the meaning given to such term in section 3001 of this title.</text></paragraph> </subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> </legis-body></bill>

