<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H74308C12F75F468689CFBFDA7A1CF55C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6411 IH: Innovative Materials for America’s Growth and Infrastructure Newly Expanded Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6411</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231114">November 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To encourage the research and use of innovative materials and associated techniques in the construction and preservation of the domestic transportation and water infrastructure system, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H375F685C02C54DFAB3F3017A6426A179" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H0E15820A45414F90AC8E6F5B35A287E0"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Innovative Materials for America’s Growth and Infrastructure Newly Expanded Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>IMAGINE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7EFAB3B68F6445D0A7FEE0141F256773"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="HC8EB7BC295DC4912BD56F456ECF801A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to encourage the research and use of innovative materials, in concert with traditional materials, and associated techniques in the construction and preservation of the domestic infrastructure network;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D5A16F26E3D4E2594922310AD8D36DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to accelerate the deployment and extend the service life, improve the performance, and reduce the cost of infrastructure projects; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AFAF20927C148C9B9A1EEC6E4365B79"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to improve the economy, resilience, maintainability, sustainability, and safety of the domestic infrastructure network.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7C4A7736B58B4AAD8F38A256F8A21972"><enum>3.</enum><header>Interagency innovative materials standards task force</header><subsection id="H57653D0EBE924804ACD910FEF6E7A70B" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of innovative material</header><text>In this section, the term <term>innovative material</term>, with respect to an infrastructure project, includes a material, or a combination or process for use of materials, that, as determined by the appropriate Secretary or agency head—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HD9AD32B34BFC4F86BE0F3C8F309CE66F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>enhances the overall service life, sustainability, and resiliency of the project; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H904231A1A66B43C3A178E6CB05737240"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides ancillary benefits relative to widely adopted state of practice technologies. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H185D040447E649E6B7C32D6467F56035"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purposes of this section are—</text><paragraph id="H32BAFADA437F43E59FEE0959778B9C62"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to encourage the research, design, and use of innovative materials, in concert with traditional materials, and associated techniques in the construction and preservation of the domestic infrastructure network;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F4823EBC22846058B2433BF6087D5FE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to accelerate the deployment, extend the service life, improve the performance, and reduce the cost of infrastructure projects; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17A34BCA4FD94BA1A36BB3FFDDAAFAF4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to improve the economy, resilience, maintainability, sustainability, and safety of the domestic infrastructure network.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE7C7FA50C70B41E9849A8CE2DD6CC5FE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Establishment</header><paragraph id="H1AA0556F30E548D4B64EF54795D7F648"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall establish an Interagency Innovative Materials Standards Task Force (referred to in this section as the <quote>Task Force</quote>) composed of the heads of Federal agencies responsible for significant civil infrastructure projects, including the Administrator of the Federal Highway Administration. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5000DC7930A42428831B51F654FFF0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text>The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall serve as Chairperson of the Task Force.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6700D5A6F7D249CE9E5A91EB9D7B41A8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Task Force shall coordinate and improve, with respect to infrastructure construction, retrofitting, rehabilitation, and other improvements—</text><paragraph id="HB11B2B5DA9AE4D9AAACEAD9CF8FB9FF0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Federal testing standards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78228814C3E745C4B75CFB1E32C2A79F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Federal design and use guidelines;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0C1D8B394834519806B1362F5933CED"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Federal regulations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF62E674E18EE47529819552F9D8A971D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>other applicable standards and performance and sustainability metrics.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0311FB3BCAE3445F8D2CC7390DFC684E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H8EA74ECA1BED4920B4238C0F58D44F01"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Task Force shall conduct, and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report that describes the results of, a study—</text><subparagraph id="H0F6D873D214B4403AE4104FB2B122749"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to assess the standards and performance metrics for the use of innovative materials in infrastructure projects;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCFE76BC91F6344F09A8CA7729AAF5789"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to identify any barriers, regulatory or otherwise, relating to the standards described in subparagraph (A) that preclude the use of certain products or associated techniques; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28D3574263F24BCF8CD307172C540DA8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to identify opportunities for the development of standardized designs and materials genome approaches that design and use innovative materials to reduce costs, improve performance and sustainability, and extend the service life of infrastructure assets.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E2D75B17DC745628BFAE6DDD1EB12CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The report under paragraph (1) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H57CE0501E602445294AF44868D58A4B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify any non-Federal entities or other organizations, including the American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials, that develop relevant standards; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD9A65AFEAD349A4B138F24AF1839336"><enum>(B)</enum><text>outline a strategy to improve coordination and information sharing between the entities described in subparagraph (A) and any relevant Federal agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE19D2FC2776D458E8D10A3DE4627F5BC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Improved coordination</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Task Force shall collaborate with any non-Federal entity identified under subsection (e)(2)(A)—</text><paragraph id="H32040FA53CD6474DB0F4C5BCB53D79C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to identify and carry out appropriate research, testing methods, and processes relating to the development and use of innovative materials;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E42721BD9D7457ABC412CFB794E9120"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to develop new methods and processes relating to the development and use of innovative materials, as the applicable agency head determines to be necessary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFAF7B7837AA402BA955ED0E6EA10634"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to contribute to the development of standards, performance metrics, and guidelines for the use of innovative materials and approaches in civil infrastructure projects;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65C5BD208BFA4CAB832CD8F6BC3EEFD1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to develop a plan for addressing potential barriers, regulatory or otherwise, identified in subsection (e)(1)(B); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19BA4DC833D54C1E84D99F2A06ABD15B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to develop a plan for the development of standardized designs that use innovative materials to reduce costs, improve performance and sustainability, and extend the service life of infrastructure assets.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H3DED38DD5E2F4370AC15D90630533475"><enum>4.</enum><header>Innovative material innovation hubs</header><subsection id="HB3B1605967FF4DDC87D93A060D03BE48"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF8D4434591254390819F128DBA1CF7C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hub</header><text>The term <term>Hub</term> means an Innovative Material Innovation Hub established under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BD242BD97B7412AA2F3D9A7C86CE216" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Innovative material</header><text>The term <term>innovative material</term>, with respect to an infrastructure project, includes a material, or a combination or process for use of materials, that, as determined by the Secretary—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H8D9E52429BB64D069A744ED3CA6A706B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enhances the overall service life, sustainability, and resiliency of the project; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1EDDE617AAF34F8494005F6B9B0680C7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides ancillary benefits relative to widely adopted state of practice technologies. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD64760677D3249E989FB2C195713C115"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualifying entity</header><text>The term <term>qualifying entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HB98972C3D5814ADB95E722CD6E5D8406"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an institution of higher education (as defined in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>));</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4584C81381FA4B7B81613336A08981FA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an appropriate Federal or State entity, including a federally funded research and development center of the Department of Transportation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H542A3F54D4D148A58C690639646CEE93"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a university transportation center under section 5505 of title 49, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA11E4ECD7A0343C58B70C8E71CEA01AE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a research and development entity in existence on the date of enactment of this Act focused on innovative materials that the Secretary determines to be similar in scope and intent to a Hub. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59D6027CDE354A249C6D78E644E2825F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H28746EDDE194493989A1B2CCA0A6606C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><paragraph id="HA7C64DD30A0C4A2F8DEDB7ACC919C5EB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a program to enhance the development of innovative materials in the United States by making awards to consortia for establishing and operating Innovative Material Innovation Hubs to conduct and support multidisciplinary, collaborative research, development, demonstration, standardized design development, and commercial application of innovative materials.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44944919D13842A99BCA88521140E605"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure the coordination of, and avoid duplication of, the activities of each Hub with the activities of—</text><subparagraph id="H954EC556D1FE42198D14FDEE09DFA050"><enum>(A)</enum><text>other research entities of the Department of Transportation, including the Federal Highway Administration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80D4C1E4693847B7A8B4D8DAB99DA670"><enum>(B)</enum><text>research entities of other Federal agencies, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H24235D58A0924C0483FB47D8F800D277"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Competitive selection process</header><paragraph id="HE63CA856DBD544A8BCB877980B745E40"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to receive an award for the establishment and operation of a Hub under subsection (b)(1), a consortium shall—</text><subparagraph id="H8349E68CFB7B45AEA5489A88E86F7040"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be composed of not fewer than 2 qualifying entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H570D440A0B0E47E1A5C27255EEA59970"><enum>(B)</enum><text>operate subject to a binding agreement, entered into by each member of the consortium, that documents—</text><clause id="HA2B8116B10F944D5BC750ACBB36BB080"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the proposed partnership agreement, including the governance and management structure of the Hub;</text></clause><clause id="HB6F0F00EB6454E49AC1CB12788951FD1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>measures the consortium will undertake to enable cost-effective implementation of activities under the program described in subsection (b)(1); and</text></clause><clause id="HCE6CD4E55B244C3BB280DABA0A623BC6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a proposed budget, including financial contributions from non-Federal sources; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A2F8F4184044C23BFA57733DF6C16C1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>operate as a nonprofit organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3950C07D2B654F4C972065E780724680"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application</header><subparagraph id="H20158A8038124F81910257A4867B33AB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A consortium seeking to establish and operate a Hub under subsection (b)(1) shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including a detailed description of—</text><clause id="H4EF181EA7D52440497BB9D1E3B37C54E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each element of the consortium agreement required under paragraph (1)(B); and</text></clause><clause id="H3DBAFC011E7F4B479143A12A0ACD560B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any existing facilities the consortium intends to use for Hub activities.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0769F8A5A72242439D196EEF4D89070A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>If the consortium members will not be located at 1 centralized location, the application under subparagraph (A) shall include a communications plan that ensures close coordination and integration of Hub activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF1219E09AA14A5EA47222559D96FBA1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Selection</header><subparagraph id="HA3DB9EDF66AC40A18AC7D6E2DA7DA066"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall select consortia for awards for the establishment and operation of Hubs through a competitive selection process.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H277AC6FAA4344184BD40C49A4784DD0F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In selecting consortia under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall consider—</text><clause id="HCC9F057C333A41E486B9D728B45C4EF7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any existing facilities a consortium has identified to be used for Hub activities;</text></clause><clause id="H6DD75DE6D7134F2683335C0E21F57C90"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>maintaining geographic diversity in locations of selected Hubs;</text></clause><clause id="H707F3D724CF04F6FA726DEE789792D05"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the demonstrated ability of the recipient to conduct and support multidisciplinary, collaborative research, development, demonstration, standardized design development, and commercial application of innovative materials;</text></clause><clause id="H0E7843AD051F496998883CE7EA9C6891"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the demonstrated research, technology transfer, and education resources available to the recipient to carry out this section;</text></clause><clause id="H868965DFF4114E948838F0FF4742DAC4"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the ability of the recipient to provide leadership in solving immediate and long-range national and regional transportation problems related to innovative materials;</text></clause><clause id="H5EB5106EAAC74EF49F1521CACCA3DB67"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the demonstrated ability of the recipient to disseminate results and spur the implementation of transportation research and education programs through national or statewide continuing education programs;</text></clause><clause id="H2C69DD6B1E5D4CAFB7D8D20C73D0E910"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the demonstrated commitment of the recipient to the use of peer review principles and other research best practices in the selection, management, and dissemination of research projects;</text></clause><clause id="H9D933155C3574145B13D59693729FD47"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>the performance metrics to be used in assessing the performance of the recipient in meeting the stated research, technology transfer, education, and outreach goals; and</text></clause><clause id="HA31D875849774D369D18BFD53080378F"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>the ability of the recipient to implement the proposed program in a cost-efficient manner, including through cost sharing and overall reduced overhead, facilities, and administrative costs.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB154560D7974182B24802222AAF6CA1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Transparency</header><subparagraph id="H0B9BA179C8624947B12AFCAC2AABE3DD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall provide to each applicant, on request, any materials, including copies of reviews (with any information that would identify a reviewer redacted), used in the evaluation process of the proposal of the applicant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CBC2BE7AFD84187850A753D7CD7F9AF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report the describes the overall review process under paragraph (2), given the considerations under paragraph (3)(B), that includes—</text><clause id="H2A55DD9AE4774D29803F8DC6B0D85882"><enum>(i)</enum><text>specific criteria of evaluation used in the review;</text></clause><clause id="H3D9E7FD8B4CA4B1A9C3FA63E5AD336C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>descriptions of the review process; and</text></clause><clause id="HD06E334D5CDF4199A936DBA71DD2CE19"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>explanations of the selected awards.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H75F68CA930584D28B2D86ED8C0DCF787"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="H624AC00E163C4FFEB1AC2DA713A54244"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as are necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F6088EA58BE430EB2D93EE9B6AD814C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>Amounts made available to carry out this section shall remain available for a period of 3 years after the last day of the fiscal year in which the amounts were made available. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H77DEA82A8F0A44B496735860BB25778C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Hub operations</header><paragraph id="H3DBC19E8894C4BA7A2C2CF8B2E0A64C8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each Hub shall conduct, or provide for, multidisciplinary, collaborative research, development, demonstration, and commercial application of innovative materials.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8546DCE7A9C42C1A2AE8C1D4A06C6DD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>Each Hub shall—</text><subparagraph id="HD01E3308555140D2ABC97CE88FF8C423"><enum>(A)</enum><text>encourage collaboration and communication among the member qualifying entities of the consortium, as described in subsection (c)(1), and awardees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H478F7A20AE4B4A1AAA1EC1859E4865C6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop and publish proposed plans and programs on a publicly accessible website;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6F3ADAE7F3B4FCEB387113F557C78F2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>submit to the Department of Transportation an annual report summarizing the activities of the Hub, including information—</text><clause id="H74D1D5F6EB99457F94DF2A6D8FB46017"><enum>(i)</enum><text>detailing organizational expenditures; and</text></clause><clause id="HA209E83D88FE4513AD71AF871E48444B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>describing each project undertaken by the Hub, as it relates to conducting and supporting multidisciplinary, collaborative research, development, demonstration, standardized design development, and commercial application of innovative materials; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB2A435AB33247778A600565587B7020"><enum>(D)</enum><text>monitor project implementation and coordination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE2BBB3C12174A189C3F623CFF033411"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conflicts of interest</header><text>Each Hub shall maintain conflict of interest procedures, consistent with the conflict of interest procedures of the Department of Transportation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7E89B4B20F649AD90477F57DF1FB6FA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prohibition on construction and renovation</header><subparagraph id="HDB8B68FD8C054DAE997646B404656B17"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No funds provided under this section may be used for construction or renovation of new buildings, test beds, or additional facilities for Hubs. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H755169EEF8524EBCA5D3FC0267157FAD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Non-Federal share</header><text>Construction of new buildings or facilities shall not be considered as part of the non-Federal share of a Hub cost-sharing agreement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H42EE4835D0C64B229873850EEAE267B3"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall administer this section in accordance with section 330 of title 49, United States Code. </text></subsection></section><section id="HFFEFF415737E453F95368924076D6A08"><enum>5.</enum><header>Turner-Fairbank Highway Research Center</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 503(b)(7) of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B5188D036AE49D5A736672CF392121B"><subparagraph id="HFCFE4FD989B04A1C9AE05BF73820D127"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Innovative materials</header><clause id="H2AC524008E624A27B14CE305BD56E0BB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definition of innovative material</header><text>In this subparagraph, the term <term>innovative material</term>, with respect to an infrastructure project, includes high performance asphalt mixtures and concrete formulations, geosynthetic materials, advanced insulating materials, advanced alloys and metals, reinforced polymer composites, advanced polymers, nanocellulose and wood-based composites, coatings, highly functional adhesives, or other corrosion prevention methods used in conjunction with those materials, and any other material or aggregate materials, as determined by the appropriate agency or department head.</text></clause><clause id="H4B2FBB1A2DC74852993A1499262C8D0C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Collaboration with States and Tribes</header><text>The Secretary shall expand the capacity of the Turner-Fairbank Highway Research Center to collaborate with relevant State and Tribal agencies—</text><subclause id="H146C2BA5E5F34211B5A9040D57D6138D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>with respect to the use of innovative materials in construction projects carried out by the State and Tribal agencies; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD50681EF7B4A4976AB3879F4BD89E634"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to understand and identify—</text><item id="HCC1B526810094D7E95426F73F549BC81"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the needs of the State and Tribal agencies; and</text></item><item id="H72B9890052464655BE2652E181DCBD89"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>innovative materials that may be further researched, developed, and used to meet those needs.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="HDE021B5B93EE45E98DC91CF9024A4F40"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>The collaboration described in clause (ii) may include—</text><subclause id="H7C43F0EEC2F2462AB3A32DAFA2AA7DC2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the development of new training for State and Tribal agencies; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H84C25049CAAD44DFB40FF4DA7F88CFA5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the expansion of technical training that involves State or Tribal departments of transportation in the development of new construction designs for innovative materials at the Turner-Fairbank Highway Research Center.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB7BFC63131B54E5FA367996A195F7418"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Priority research</header><text>The Turner-Fairbank Highway Research Center shall prioritize research relating to—</text><subclause id="H87749C7D67B743F4B676915F5ECFD2E7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the use of innovative materials in—</text><item id="H4FD323A12CB2485EB03C5FEBA58E01E2"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>bridges with a span equal to or greater than 50 feet;</text></item><item id="HFCC843E0D442422C8BAD965D0144CDC8"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>highway reconstruction and rehabilitation; and</text></item><item id="H686FD07762D84F799EBC3AC9EDFE6CE9"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>rural road infrastructure;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H2F09E3A5259A435EBC537DA29294B3D4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the development of standardized designs using innovative materials; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HFD8FD2D631624273B73A87EB8EF81AB3"><enum>(III)</enum><text>coastal resiliency.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HD8F65D315A454F6095FD5F6D7406BE47"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subparagraph $8,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H9AC60A60BB3042DB85D6D8155765AF29"><enum>6.</enum><header>Innovative Bridge Program</header><subsection id="HA0D76D18356F45DCB42891D0A8F04958"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of Administrator</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Federal Highway Administration.</text></subsection><subsection id="H73CA4EF856E043168FA3412F79AA3EFF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Administrator shall establish a grant program, to be known as the <quote>Innovative Bridge Program</quote>, to provide grants to State departments of transportation, Tribal governments, public toll authorities, and units of local government for—</text><paragraph id="H60C3999974F3445E9D5E1B50A9B36C12"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coastal or rural infrastructure bridge projects; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB5653861815400D833B0DFC68142F1F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>value engineering projects under subsection (g).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6984E4C6D28F49BEB21C7AFD4E4E77BB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under subsection (b), a State department of transportation, a unit of Tribal government, a public toll authority, or a unit of local government shall submit to the Administrator an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Administrator may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6A613FA3827748FD87A70C714F6D8177"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a coastal or rural infrastructure bridge project or a value engineering project shall—</text><paragraph id="HA57198AB91494968BC71391B7D6161BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be for the purpose of construction, preservation, rehabilitation, or reconstruction of a bridge with a span equal to or greater than 50 feet;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F39FEAE2A3242FB8DE0246FA3ABF4AE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be carried out in a manner so as to reduce traffic impact;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H773CA8A64B0A4E41B8FF3E96AB7AB282"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include multimodal transportation components, such as bicycle and pedestrian paths; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD5A41DEFE864B999357965C00CD571C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>use innovative materials that—</text><subparagraph id="H62EAE6E779814EF1985B8C97FB6EEA38"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are resistant to corrosion; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDC886AF8B7442738162A1937273297C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>extend the service life of the bridge.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF0B0867CC9FD48DAB32A2A0F2C9BCB5B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text>In providing grants under this section, the Administrator shall give preference to proposed projects that—</text><paragraph id="H8903A815D40044CCBD042B78331D09F7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>use materials that are domestically produced and sourced;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AA2C6C01D6F46B88E652B0B55466384"><enum>(2)</enum><text>use nontraditional production techniques, such as factory prefabrication;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H237F40DDD8A9433985123C57F08D04D7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include multimodal transportation components, such as bicycle and pedestrian paths; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF162DB520CAB441B8966A9A967AED9AF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>retrofit a bridge.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H19F708712BAD457CB01D90513719E7C2"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Special consideration for at-Risk areas</header><text>In providing grants under this section, the Administrator shall give special consideration to projects located in rural areas or areas prone to coastal or inland flooding due to severe storms (such as hurricanes or rain bursts), storm surges, or projected sea level rise during the projected lifetime of the project.</text></subsection><subsection id="H893F842A92414E02AF189712905DB43B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Value engineering using innovative materials</header><text>Of the amounts made available to carry out this section, the Administrator shall set aside $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to provide funding to 1 or more State departments of transportation or units of Tribal or local government that submit to the Administrator an application to carry out value engineering of a standard bridge design to enhance the performance of the bridge (including extending the service life of the bridge, increasing resistance to corrosion, and reducing construction and preservation costs) through the use of innovative materials.</text></subsection><subsection id="H614ADFD4CEF440BAAD174ED6B570E9D4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Recordkeeping; reports</header><paragraph id="H682CBF9F23754D99BF87B041C6582390"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recordkeeping</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall develop a project recordkeeping system that maintains comprehensive, current, and accurate information on each grant provided under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FB4C533959845F1965695808DFBA768"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the development of the recordkeeping system described in paragraph (1), and every 2 years thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate, and make publicly available, a report that describes, with respect to each project that receives a grant under this section—</text><subparagraph id="H65DEE8ADB5AF4791A16CAA64BA9E5800"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the status of the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B5EA6BE8F514DB89A2E044869A5D854"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the location of the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88444A77C9784267973CAD0BFAA81AB7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for each bridge involved in the project, the inventory number of the bridge in the National Bridge Inventory pursuant to section 144 of title 23, United States Code;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB727C763702418C8FAB60B4654B95EA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a detailed description of the scope of the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB81D151CA984DDCBB6CA48FD4303F13"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the amount of project costs paid by funds provided under this section and the total project costs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC4BCE1368694E53A29CA33AF69B9095"><enum>(F)</enum><text>for each bridge involved in the project, the bridge condition, operations, and performance of the bridge; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF0AFF78F2ED47E0AE06CB3DA6EE004A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>in every third report submitted under this paragraph, the results of the regular monitoring and evaluation of the maintenance demands, projects, needs, and costs of each bridge in the project during the previous 6 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBDBBA51BE47F46BD9511838D521BC318"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator to carry out this section $65,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1F4F9695C3314B73A80BEACB385582B3"><enum>7.</enum><header>Water Infrastructure Innovation Program</header><subsection id="H6E5454576B1544A59E86A19F976708FE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency (referred to in this section as the <quote>Administrator</quote>) shall establish a grant program, to be known as the <quote>Water Infrastructure Innovation Program</quote>, to provide grants for the design and installation of water infrastructure projects, including wastewater transport and treatment systems and drinking water treatment and distribution systems, that use innovative materials to reduce total costs, including operation and preservation expenses, and extend the service life of installed structures.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H0B85DF38A51F457BAC7FFAB2163A6CF5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an applicant shall submit to the Administrator an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Administrator may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H93072FF080174C5E92BB08016E092EDA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a water infrastructure project shall—</text><paragraph id="H8335EB53D1334599B1A21612F26EB323"><enum>(1)</enum><text>serve a community with a population between 3,301 and 99,999; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA2D1944EAAE4D91BD583650C4D3BE91"><enum>(2)</enum><text>use innovative materials that—</text><subparagraph id="H82E3DD07D2C94273A93086F7DB7180ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are resistant to degradation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA62D0C450CAF46FCB3E0E10F0BA5F158"><enum>(B)</enum><text>extend service life; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H89FAD4CFA9E74FEEAA214A4EE5DFE848"><enum>(C)</enum><text>provide long-term protection of water facilities and systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA22922D469F843218CCBC77CD19DD931"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Preference</header><text>In providing grants under this section, the Administrator shall give preference to proposed projects that use materials that are domestically produced and sourced.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0AB1A01FCB7444EEB675EAA51ED3DBD0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Special consideration for at-Risk areas</header><text>In providing grants under this section, the Administrator shall give special consideration to projects located in areas that are prone to saltwater intrusion or flooding due to severe storms, rain bursts, storm surges, or projected sea level rise during the projected lifetime of the project.</text></subsection><subsection id="H169272722AC349D6877AE4A2E3E76A5F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Recordkeeping; reports</header><paragraph id="HF992E4CDC94D478E8D1389D121C519EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recordkeeping</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall develop a project recordkeeping system that maintains comprehensive, current, and accurate information on each grant provided under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0879D309139748129641ECFF77BCBDF4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the development of the recordkeeping system described in paragraph (1), and every 2 years thereafter, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress, including the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate, and make publicly available a report describing, with respect to each project that receives a grant under this section—</text><subparagraph id="H7A0B72220146445A9BBA3009CC22AAB2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the status of the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF9825AC42E6E4F539295182AB749F7D8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the location of the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E77AADA5E3345488DE2ACB17CC4F56D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a detailed description of the scope of the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4549078D28B54AD6B86B8AEE27727379"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the amount of project costs paid by funds provided under this section and the total project costs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B187A13922145FC9376444FE5518250"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the condition, operations, and performance of the project; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5E6DD9CE0B82451EB546A34A4E04F868"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in every third report submitted under this paragraph, the results of the regular monitoring and evaluation of the maintenance demands, projects, needs, and costs of the project during the previous 6 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H179D1576B7D04507978079DC525A270B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator to carry out this section $65,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028. </text></subsection></section><section id="H2EEB4DA635CD4D629A66D0668A451F68" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>8.</enum><header>Innovative project delivery Federal share</header><subsection id="H80B54FE7652745C797674BC1E22CB459"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 120(c)(3)(B) of title 23, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HACFB22B63EA3464B8E55A97BEA04E0B0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking clauses (i) and (ii) and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB49E9A899AA8420592B7C87826788FB2" style="USC"><clause id="H1EAB315BDBEE4A44B62AB3AA34A9686D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prefabricated bridge elements and systems, innovative materials, and other technologies to reduce bridge construction time, extend service life, and reduce preservation costs, as compared to conventionally designed and constructed bridges;</text></clause><clause id="HAEBA30545611403994C739742C99AE3A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">innovative construction equipment, materials, techniques, or practices, including the use of in-place recycling technology, digital 3-dimensional modeling technologies, and advanced digital construction management systems;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FC6FAD83D114EA7AEF694AFC4AC4621"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (v), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H910997EADD2B426E830EE5930C5FF505"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating clause (vi) as clause (vii); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEAD37A9860704CE8A52D9489FC223EA9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (v) the following: </text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE4B124AAD5AB413B939AF5DC138E0672" style="USC"><clause id="H944D69EC5D414FF4914508530819F270"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">innovative pavement materials that demonstrate reductions in greenhouse gas emissions through sequestration or innovative manufacturing processes; or</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD1916A55233D4F9488DABF86B40E10EE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 107(a)(2) of title 23, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>subsection (c) of</quote>. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

