<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7B0BB2BD048A419EA93A61964212D479" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5582 IH: White Oak Resilience Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5582</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230920">September 20, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001220">Mr. McGarvey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To provide for white oak restoration, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H6C6E176EAADF4355A716B9AE95721E30" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H12598D13B9B94FA18D58C50A0154DE7C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>White Oak Resilience Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H243FC02B0F264440B79FF3E189991B6F"><enum>2.</enum><header>White Oak Restoration Initiative Coalition</header> <subsection id="H598696EE9DDE452FBB31E637DFBA10F3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The White Oak Restoration Initiative Coalition shall be established—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCD3187EDDA384B37BCBBE4F0D8AB45BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>as a voluntary collaborative group of public, State, private and non-governmental organizations to carry out the purposes described in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEFD26F819711421BA5FAD4B656899D63"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in accordance with the charter titled <quote>White Oak Initiative Coalition Charter</quote> adopted by the White Oak Initiative Board of Directors on March 21, 2023 (or a successor charter).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6D495CAFC63E45A589033E89D43BF434"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>In addition to the duties specified in the charter described in subsection (a)(2), the duties of the White Oak Restoration Initiative Coalition are—</text> <paragraph id="H4437FCD5CB9E445190FF0A1143B78339"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to coordinate public, State, local, private and non-governmental restoration of white oak in the United States; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDBDFCEB5BA6340158798B3C7C3E8F2E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to make program and policy recommendations with respect to—</text> <subparagraph id="H1BD8B78F9C704A44AC1EC5F7B46B67E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>changes necessary to address Federal and State policies that impede activities to improve the health, resiliency, and natural regeneration of white oak;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1DC1CBBCDC824F608BD2DA16A0034350"><enum>(B)</enum><text>adopting or modifying Federal and State policies to increase the pace and scale of white oak regeneration and resiliency of white oak;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEDCA3AFDF3FF46979775A7D0EBA02383"><enum>(C)</enum><text>options to enhance communication, coordination, and collaboration between forest land owners, particularly for cross-boundary projects, to improve the health, resiliency, and natural regeneration of white oak;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3B2C4085A8F745C28CA7E3B4C6C7828C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>research gaps that should be addressed to improve the best available science on white oak;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7C9014EF1F7D4CFD9DE6B8FF194BC9FE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>outreach to forest landowners with white oak or white oak regeneration potential; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF31FA7ED56A240799E9806D5E8265992"><enum>(F)</enum><text>options and policies necessary to improve the quality and quantity of white oak in tree nurseries.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H651C7493A17F4630A847C327DB8F1CA2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administrative support, technical services, and staff support</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Agriculture shall make such personnel available to the White Oak Restoration Initiative Coalition for administrative support, technical services, and development and dissemination of educational materials as the Secretaries determine necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF9E1BE289A3B42AFBE313EE1111BCE8E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of Federal Advisory Committee Act</header><text>Chapter 10 of part I of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the White Oak Restoration Initiative Coalition.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8FC09946585544CEADB626D8390896D8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Private funding of white oak restoration projects</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture may make funds available to the White Oak Restoration Initiative Coalition to carry out this section from the account established pursuant to section 1241(f) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3841">16 U.S.C. 3841(f)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HBDD1A80FCE534B70A79B2A1BD21CA5CC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Forest Service pilot program</header> 
<subsection id="HA212DB35B6AA4945B24AC45F57F69A09"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, shall establish and carry out 5 pilot projects in national forests to restore white oak in such forests through white oak restoration and natural regeneration practices.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2A1B2450E8CC4F89B091AF64D8BCBB01"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National forests reserved or withdrawn from the public domain</header><text>At least 3 pilot projects required under subsection (a) shall be carried out on national forests reserved or withdrawn from the public domain.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H35EC1E652D4444BB857BA55C9F3AB618"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority To enter into cooperative agreements</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture may enter into cooperative agreements to carry out the pilot projects required under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> <section id="H3871CA43FE1B44EEAFE07B57DA3B1092"><enum>4.</enum><header>Department of the Interior white oak review and restoration</header> <subsection id="H51F7223032A1453790A9FA62156F03CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assessment</header> <paragraph id="H1ED97ACA092B475D9DF72CE607CF67C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior shall carry out an assessment of land under the administrative jurisdiction of the Department of the Interior, including fish and wildlife refuges and abandoned mine land, to evaluate—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAE0185FC59F84D0683DC1A3372663B95"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether white oak is present on such land; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H79FE72479E4945AE9F9216690059257B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the potential to restore white oak forests on such land.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H027B49EF1D1945969C212952E9BB985E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of information</header><text>In carrying out the assessment under paragraph (1), the Secretary may use information from sources other than the Department of the Interior, including from the White Oak Initiative and the Forest Service.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H824097F0B7CB48AA92C1796E7FEDE24D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall submit to Congress, and make publicly available on the website of the Department of the Interior, a report regarding the results of the assessment carried out under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0B61C6DF3D8E42CB8C6DFEC627F667BB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Pilot projects</header><text>After the date on which the report required under subsection (a)(3) is submitted, the Secretary shall establish and carry out 5 pilot projects in different areas of land described in subsection (a)(1) to restore and naturally regenerate white oak.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H188088F2EDE6417A8DED247D9A5C2CCC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority To enter into cooperative agreements</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior may enter into cooperative agreements to carry out the pilot projects required under subsection (b).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H28497CFF1C2046688C604BA2E6824749" commented="no"><enum>5.</enum><header>White oak restoration fund</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 409 of the National Forest Foundation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/583j-7">16 U.S.C. 583j–7</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HCA81133F28C4479699E0FBB92DED3B2E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The activities</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HB46472D399EA4FE9A7E9069C40364242" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HAA48F3E8D8C845DC90E15FF6693BF7A9" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The activities</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H860C724B6EF0470EB755FB836C221D7E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HA060F2425EF54B468E57704B1529B975" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HD84D5C82CF8843C59E65DF06458E0347" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>White oak restoration fund</header> 
<paragraph id="H53BA6E2904D444A78839239189328A13" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Funds described in paragraph (2) shall be made available for activities—</text> <subparagraph id="H2AC623A2FC6847CEAA9AE723ED6056F2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>on national forests that are approved by the Secretary, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3E23600EF2714B3DBC75FCEE5A5C6ACC" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to—</text> <clause id="H058FE86AFD024199AC6020231438251E" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>re-establish white oak forests where appropriate;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H59F38F2296194521A7C5EE7649835D70" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>improve management of existing white oak forests to foster natural regeneration of white oak;</text></clause> <clause id="HDB13BAFA40EB47E4BB759FDBBEDBB83F" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>improve and expand white oak nursery stock; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0F82B6332074494DB8DFA26B4AA97AEC" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>adapt and improve white oak seedlings.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9FC8C7E4CA5F4834ACE9CBF94BCF0F91" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fund</header><text>The National Forest Foundation may accept gifts, devises, or bequests for the purposes of carrying out the activities specified in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2CE277C20D3D42D39A4F813DF1ADD800" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Summary</header><text>Beginning 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the National Forest Foundation shall include in the budget justification materials submitted to Congress in support of the budget of each such Foundation for each fiscal year (as submitted with the budget of the President under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code) a summary of the activities carried out under paragraph (1) and the funds accepted under paragraph (2) that includes—</text> <subparagraph id="HE10D534727A747919F44141AB9131845" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount—</text> 
<clause id="H032EEB591B334CCCABE2757E9A691CFA" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>accepted under paragraph (2) in the preceding fiscal year; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA41B8DA00E1A4893AABC7917F7FAEE07" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>described in clause (i) that is unobligated on the date of the report; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5593AE9DAD58402FB13956216F37C0FC" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the activities under paragraph (1) funded during the preceding fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HF2239215024D48478F441F8352DACA54"><enum>6.</enum><header>Civilian conservation centers reforestation activities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 147(d) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3197">29 U.S.C. 3197(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H757BA5E01DD646D3AA207A159E5CC0EA" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H1024DBE571F745FAB21F815215048FB2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Reforestation activities</header><text>Enrollees in Civilian Conservation Centers may provide assistance in carrying out reforestation of white oak and associated hardwood forest reforestation projects on National Forest System land in accordance with the land and resource management plan applicable to such land pursuant to section 6 of the Forest and Rangeland Renewable Resources Planning Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1604">16 U.S.C. 1604</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H1EE5A4EBC9024B39AC69736D0F9B1EC8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Tree nursery shortages</header> <subsection id="HCA6F79B657D54BB19038C295B53F1CB6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, shall develop and implement a national strategy to increase the capacity of Federal, State, Tribal, and private tree nurseries to address the nationwide shortage of tree seedlings.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H61233E6EC88A4399BC2EE809A184B2BE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The strategy required under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H40964DE6E6AD4BC2A355C644F0DD2C13"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be based on the best available science and data; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF1BA50E721B41DFBB04E6CFCDF356B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify and address—</text> <subparagraph id="HE685F6A820AC4E28A8C0723A0224FE31"><enum>(A)</enum><text>regional seedling shortages of bareroot and container tree seedlings;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0EBA545123D343758F844A3016D86A11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>regional reforestation opportunities and the seedling supply necessary to fulfill such opportunities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0229231B0CC348348BA1DB4E358815EC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>opportunities to enhance seedling diversity and close gaps in seed inventories; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5B2851B983C545A489D88D32C71C6323"><enum>(D)</enum><text>barriers to expanding, enhancing, or creating new infrastructure to increase nursery capacity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H86D8D5C69FDB417B9600141E74A886DE"><enum>8.</enum><header>White oak research</header> <subsection id="H7936292639B3411491AC212FB214B9E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture may enter into a memorandum of understanding with a covered land grant college to conduct research on—</text> 
<paragraph id="H74772D7B3BE241BA841ACBECADF1DF94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>white oak genes with resistance and stress tolerance;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEB34DE227DB34B99ABFAC51E3964D6D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>white oak trees that exhibit vigor for the purpose of increasing survival and growth;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1AAEFE54DA9F4A129A287345540BBD5B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>establishing a diverse white oak seed bank capable of responding to stressors;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H66C1FD8D0B17436F80117B85CEEF115D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>providing a sustainable supply of white oak seedlings and genetic resources;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EAF63E9B4554AA4AAF2A46D7C50D793"><enum>(5)</enum><text>reforestation of white oak through natural and artificial regeneration; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21C2603A42FC412F8ED873957591A69E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the best methods for reforesting abandoned mine land sites.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6CEB4967DBD14FE896133389E98164F6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consult</header><text>In carrying out the research under subsection (a), the covered land grant college that enters into the memorandum of understanding under such subsection may consult with such States, nonprofit organizations, institutions of higher education, and other scientific bodies, as the covered land grant college determines appropriate.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4CBCBF4D884E4AC798FCAAFE1E8A0E98"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered land grant college defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered land grant college</term> means an 1862 Institution, an 1890 Institution, or a 1994 Institution (as such terms are defined, respectively, in section 2 of the Agricultural Research, Extension, and Education Reform Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/7601">7 U.S.C. 7601</external-xref>)).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H65FDE5B8B98F4450ADC0D2E2619A6F18"><enum>9.</enum><header>USDA formal initiative</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Natural Resources Conservation Service, shall establish a formal initiative on white oak to—</text> <paragraph id="HEBB227DB9A4544D4BAB8BEEC8B5F8B42"><enum>(1)</enum><text>re-establish white oak forests where appropriate;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9E0B549499CA4434B62880762577245B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>improve management of existing white oak forests to foster natural regeneration of white oak;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B8D738607D64FD7A045CB8F79F09E1A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide technical assistance to private landowners to re-establish, improve management of, and naturally regenerate white oak;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7ECB42DA715E4ACBB827A6613985853F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>improve and expand white oak nursery stock; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A253C7A7BC34E08995569A2DAE1A510"><enum>(5)</enum><text>adapt and improve white oak seedlings.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H7B7DBA7D3BCA4D1E8228930D9003201E"><enum>10.</enum><header>Authorities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">To the maximum extent practicable, the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Agriculture shall use the authorities provided under this Act and the amendment made by this Act in combination with other authorities to carry out projects, including—</text> <paragraph id="H2B5BC3EA5BA84B50A965D443099C9EB6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>good neighbor agreements entered into under section 8206 of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/2113">16 U.S.C. 2113</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H13F8CA2085AE4E0B931E3800F2BDBF0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>stewardship contracting projects entered into under section 604 of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591">16 U.S.C. 6591</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

