<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEBD0D4A48F164480A22960104A3AB31D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3118 IH: Home Dialysis Risk Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3118</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230505">May 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide for Medicare coverage of monitoring devices to detect and alarm when a venous needle dislodgement occurs during home dialysis for hemodialysis patients.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7B76C8726AA64125A8C70398EC8FABB5" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDFDF1F4A38DA4F05A598D452EB00294E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Home Dialysis Risk Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5E264E884F3748FDBEEB557F9AA34E09"><enum>2.</enum><header>Providing for coverage of monitoring and alarm devices to detect venous needle dislodgement for hemodialysis patients</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1881(b)(14) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395rr">42 U.S.C. 1395rr(b)(14)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
<quoted-block id="H3D91E27256194181AC7D2CC3481362B1" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="H0E0D6AB007D84F0895FF4F14F997807B" indent="up2"><enum>(J)</enum>
<clause id="H2441D46FD1CA41ECA44825AB6BF75339" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>For home dialysis services and equipment furnished to new and respite individuals on or after the date that is 1 year after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph which are monitoring and alarm devices for venous needle dislodgement (as defined in clause (iii)(II)), the Secretary shall increase the single payment that would otherwise apply under this paragraph for such services by the amount determined under the payment system established under clause (ii). </text></clause> <clause id="HA8F5D423B51140F49F5E1F59DAD556C3" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The Secretary shall establish a prospective payment system through regulations to determine the amounts payable for monitoring and alarm devices and supplies to detect venous needle dislodgements for individuals receiving home dialysis. In establishing such system, the Secretary may consult with device manufacturers, health professionals, dialysis patients, private payers, and MA plans and may consider—</text>
<subclause id="H533679A1400241C0A4F701CC2014621D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the costs of furnishing the monitoring and alarm device and necessary supplies;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HCAB7784AB1D04106A105FFEE730A8BAD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>payment amounts for similar items and services under parts A and B; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H946FD9EABE434C38BA56D4E732486614"><enum>(III)</enum><text>payment amounts established by MA plans under part C, group health plans, and health insurance coverage offered by health insurance issuers.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HC773FDFC0CDB420099F833717AEF96C4" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>In this subparagraph:</text>
<subclause id="HEC080A91FC624866B47EDA418411A5BD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The term <term>new and respite individual</term> means an individual described in subsection (a) who is initiating home hemodialysis.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H54D939D1A38F42DCB003CD2CDB98A0A3"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>monitoring and alarm devices for venous needle dislodgement</term> means a blood loss detection solution specifically designed to detect blood leakage through core technology utilizing fiber optics. The detected blood triggers a visual and audible alarm.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HBD99123CCD364DFBB67559D6C223D4E6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The terms <term>group health plan</term>, <term>health insurance coverage</term>, and <term>health insurance issuer</term> have the meaning given such terms in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

