<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H02005CB657BC4DD98DC3B8C44E301E68" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5910 IH: Environmental Health Workforce Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5910</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231006">October 6, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To prioritize educating and training for existing and new environmental health professionals.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H0754650C65984246BECA9475F7997526" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HEB1BB3B2D6274E119FB9F3C8437D2AFC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Environmental Health Workforce Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB80AD3326D044210A92F268853567D11"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H4DEFEF41BC724F6E9F2001A4AD144B3A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The environmental health workforce is vital to protecting the health and safety of the public.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H66A7C040E7304AC88C81965EEBC71DB3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For years, State and local governmental public health agencies have reported substantial workforce losses and other challenges to the environmental health workforce.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H52F90E9E346F4134ABB0B7FF0EC96196"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the Association of State and Territorial Health Officials (ASTHO) and the National Association of County and City Health Officials (NACCHO), more than 50,600 State and local environmental health workforce jobs have been lost since 2008. This represents approximately 22 percent of the total State and local environmental health workforce.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F2359DD9FDB43C6817B6F7F0952CAB2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In the coming years, the retiring Baby Boomer Generation will lead to a further decrease in the environmental health workforce.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAABCBB7EE9A9402F8EF291E7009FF66F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the National Environmental Health Association, more than 67 percent of Tribal environmental health programs, 64 percent of State environmental health programs, and 60 percent of local environmental health programs report insufficient staffing capacity to respond to new issues presented by the COVID–19 pandemic. Industry workers also reported insufficient access to training and high levels of burnout.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9E4FDCFD829E4A2D86527BAA5FEC77EB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Currently, only 27 States require a credential for environmental health workers that is an impartial, third-party endorsement of an individual’s professional knowledge and experience.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBE7F9A1937CC49F5B71B59904C06AA6C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Educating and training existing and new environmental health professionals should be a national public health goal.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HDAADE51E267B4D3391ADDED8D39DAF9F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Model standards and guidelines for credentialing environmental health workers</header> <subsection id="H34C96BCDF3EC466B99FE4658933DC80B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, in coordination with appropriate national professional organizations, Federal, State, local, and tribal governmental agencies, and private-sector and nongovernmental entities, shall develop model standards and guidelines for credentialing environmental health workers.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H20E3041498D4454E9B24A5F76A6ECB8F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provision of standards and technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall provide to State, local, and tribal governments—</text> <paragraph id="H5E59F5FD741A47AABC908B4B9AEE8FC0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the model standards and guidelines developed under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF4963407F3CA44A6B5F529043C07950B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>technical assistance in credentialing environmental health workers.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section commented="no" id="H32287E34F070408C86F3891CA5F67855"><enum>4.</enum><header>Environmental Health Workforce Development Plan</header> <subsection commented="no" id="HE6FBD47E333A4E6C9CBE643DF368D238"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To ensure that programs and activities (including education, training, and payment programs) of the Department of Health and Human Services for developing the environmental health workforce meet national needs, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall develop a comprehensive and coordinated plan for such programs and activities that—</text> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HE435155020EB4DE3BBA2918EC39A9107"><enum>(1)</enum><text>includes performance measures to more clearly determine the extent to which these programs and activities are meeting the Department’s strategic goal of strengthening the environmental health workforce;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H2DB9F506A6894F0E9FE2538C390B8E40"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies and communicates to stakeholders any gaps between existing programs and activities and future environmental health workforce needs identified in workforce projections of the Health Resources and Services Administration;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H2D3BB4CD0E044818907F0616EBDC1748"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identifies actions needed to address such identified gaps; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H0A085EB645774B3791602C9FF9AAEDD8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identifies any additional statutory authority that is needed by the Department to implement such identified actions.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HF11305796B0746B09CF4EFAE9333902D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and to the Committees on Energy and Commerce and Education and Labor of the House of Representatives, the plan developed under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> <section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF1ADF7801F74877B296C43EBBE74F5C" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>5.</enum><header>Environmental health workforce development report</header> <subsection id="HE22098E08D824395BF0ED71412D48C9F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall examine and identify best practices in 6 States (as described in subsection (b)) related to training and credentialing requirements for environmental health workers and submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report that includes information concerning—</text> 
<paragraph id="HFEC8C3EF78FB46F0B1D7648D1449D1D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>types of environmental health workers employed at State, local, and city health departments and independent environmental health agencies;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H30D776E20BFE4B04B1CD7242D7C79E9C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>educational backgrounds of environmental health workers;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8C8BA73F61514EA3A3634BE724BB3360"><enum>(3)</enum><text>whether environmental health workers are credentialed or registered, and what type of credential or registration each worker has received;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5D2B06556DDC4A2E87E9ECBA59CE5AC5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>State requirements for continuing education for environmental health workers;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H53899A21427E4337B4C7FEA5315E4EA7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>whether State, local, and city health departments and independent environmental health agencies track continuing education units for their environmental health workers; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA127D088931E44C7BED60E46BF89116C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>how frequently any exam required to qualify environmental health workers is updated and reviewed to ensure that the exam is consistent with current law.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H246D7925FC3E4C99A1923DDC93D91CB2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Selection of States</header><text>The report described in subsection (a) shall be based upon the examination of such best practices with respect to 3 States that have credentialing requirements for environmental health workers (such as Maryland, Ohio, and Washington) and 3 States that do not have such requirements (such as Indiana, Iowa, and Pennsylvania).</text></subsection></section> <section id="HD468BA709A364141BC8B4B36BA9ED45E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Public service loan forgiveness</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 455(m) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1087e">20 U.S.C. 1087e(m)</external-xref>) is amended in paragraph (3)(B)—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD95D85513C5B4EB99F76B9D51999F150"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1B49697E54904FD597B77F2AB4327BD0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H89983EF03AE746B5AC0985F0A5BC70BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H18E406BF578248528DFC577EFDCD1E2C" style="OLC"> <clause id="HA912320307A04C8C9F73FD6C19586AA1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full-time job as an environmental health worker (as defined in section 7 of the <short-title>Environmental Health Workforce Act of 2023</short-title>) who is accredited, certified, or licensed in accordance with applicable law.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section commented="no" id="H2427F33C70B349C68F19B57A4ADD5068"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the terms <term>environmental health worker</term> and <term>environmental health workforce</term> refer to public health workers who investigate and assess hazardous environmental agents in various environmental settings and develop, promote, and enforce guidelines, policies, and interventions to control such hazards.</text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

