<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H231480293BBB4CF5A29C4A3C02E71DC0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1150 IH: John Lewis Civil Rights Fellowship Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1150</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the John Lewis Civil Rights Fellowship to fund international internships and research placements for early- to mid-career professionals to study nonviolent movements to establish and protect civil rights around the world.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6DF7A59CED3E4521963149F9C50C685E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1AC01EF5EC15406FA9FD53E34B033086" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>John Lewis Civil Rights Fellowship Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HD8D71DF28E2C4B9991E6F99E8A8196F6"><enum>2.</enum><header>John Lewis Civil Rights Fellowship Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Mutual Educational and Cultural Exchange Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2451">22 U.S.C. 2451 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21670E7D32F34936831026B06B74C0C1"> 
<section id="H437371D90A0F4CF0AEB80A44175DC03F"><enum>115.</enum><header>John Lewis Civil Rights Fellowship Program</header> 
<subsection id="H1802CE33094644C3A6DA0C537C3D2081"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established the John Lewis Civil Rights Fellowship Program (referred to in this section as the <quote>Fellowship Program</quote>) within the J. William Fulbright Educational Exchange Program.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H763CE9E0165E421287379C68E6E55594"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purposes of the Fellowship Program are—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA6808CC3352E4346BBA6EEB35D6EB3E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to honor the legacy of Representative John Lewis by promoting a greater understanding of the history and tenets of nonviolent civil rights movements; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H332A865AE86341E4B69BE009423B54C3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to advance foreign policy priorities of the United States by promoting studies, research, and international exchange in the subject of nonviolent movements that established and protected civil rights around the world.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1946FAC8ED4E43BFB3658BFEE1427220"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs (referred to in this section as the <quote>Bureau</quote>) shall administer the Fellowship Program in accordance with policy guidelines established by the Fulbright Foreign Scholarship Board, in consultation with the binational Fulbright Commissions and United States Embassies.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE0AC45A690484B2E91A3C6796A98C2AA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Selection of fellows</header> <paragraph id="H01CDF825656F44EABE41959848F377CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall annually select qualified individuals to participate in the Fellowship Program. The Bureau may determine the number of fellows selected each year, which, whenever feasible, shall be not fewer than 25. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3EB963FE3A53464B968AF3CE3BDC7151"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent practicable, the Bureau shall conduct outreach at institutions the Bureau determines are likely to produce a range of qualified applicants.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H832C3F7EEDA849D8BDB2700F5BD090A4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Fellowship orientation</header><text>The Bureau shall organize and administer a fellowship orientation that shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H26B9319A48E94AAD8F9D09293201908A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be held in Washington, DC, or at another location selected by the Bureau; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H561D897741694869BCBB77FF2B8CA269"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include programming to honor the legacy of Representative John Lewis; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0ECC8ED0B1A4498A9725BF0B0BA30799" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>be held on an annual basis.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC48D2690CD854A7F8499716805989026"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Structure</header> <paragraph id="H6E57364824CD45FB8EE874B2C46B8819"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Work plan</header><text>To carry out the purposes described in subsection (b)(2)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFFABFA070C2D49ABACEA25025C7D1FE8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each fellow selected pursuant to subsection (d) shall arrange an internship or research placement— </text> <clause id="H4A87D5BB462340E39FDEECCE6EAF0F86"><enum>(i)</enum><text>with a nongovernmental organization, academic institution, or other organization approved by the Bureau; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H839CB07DBF41480CAF7F8B18DD619108"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in a country with an operational Fulbright U.S. Student Program; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H337CC4BC8BDA41E6AFF1484E745F90B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Bureau shall, for each fellow, approve a work plan that identifies the target objectives for the fellow, including specific duties and responsibilities relating to those objectives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED0ED2E0730745F194F4A3DD845E132D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conferences; presentations</header><text>Each fellow shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HC01B5D48CB054831A9345602FE8FE425"><enum>(A)</enum><text>attend the fellowship orientation described in subsection (e);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0A4C54807674442DBC4378EDE870B2B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than the date that is 1 year after the end of the fellowship period, attend a fellowship summit organized and administered by the Bureau, which, whenever feasible, shall be held in a location of importance to the civil rights movement in the United States and may coincide with other events facilitated by the Bureau; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDB9027F258504152997DAFA71C41B36D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at such summit, give a presentation on lessons learned during the period of fellowship.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF901576D7B744C1985F3747F2FAE997"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fellowship period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each fellowship under this section shall continue for a period determined by the Bureau, which, whenever feasible, shall be not shorter than 10 months.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H37BE2E15596342A1A9F1A5C3108FC361"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Fellowship award</header><text>The Bureau shall provide each fellow under this section with an allowance that is equal to the amount needed for—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC9118E7CCCCC49D4B903AEF3D20DBACB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the fellow's reasonable costs during the fellowship period; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H74EC886C312E4F55BF7682F8B7B1D710"><enum>(2)</enum><text>travel and lodging expenses related to attending the orientation and summit required under subsection (e)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7525EECF936C4D0B917E8D92A8DA6F10"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of completion of the Fellowship Program by the initial cohort of fellows selected under subsection (d), and on an annual basis thereafter, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report providing information on the implementation of the Fellowship Program, including on—</text> <paragraph id="HC7F277A8AC3E44729B816642B0933178"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the demographics of the cohort of fellows who completed a fellowship during the preceding 1-year period;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9DA2DA48C2A449BABCFDBEC8C92DF05D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of internship and research placements, and research projects selected, under the Fellowship Program, including participant feedback on program implementation and feedback of the Department on lessons learned;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4B1169859C704F7B8D581826AFF5BAA3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a plan for factoring such lessons learned into future programming; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H56C3F4369E744005B1C44894692A5DFB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an analysis of trends relating to the diversity of the cohorts of fellows and the topics of projects completed over the course of the Fellowship Program.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HC0D3F6864E084BA690B29DD85FFA8C91"><enum>3.</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments to the Mutual Educational and Cultural Exchange Act of 1961A</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 112(a) of the Mutual Educational and Cultural Exchange Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2460">22 U.S.C. 2460(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H770F969AF04445438A3ADCDFD1167723"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (8), by striking <quote>; and </quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE14836C667B74970A8CDB3EF4FD17493"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDA31BE31360A409BA709387A3E63E408"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF56470AFEE14C59B5DC4D221DC4DB4C"> <paragraph id="HE49CA5E39AF24E6DB20E9428B594F850"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the John Lewis Civil Rights Fellowship Program established under section 115, which provides funding for international internships and research placements for early- to mid-career individuals from the United States to study nonviolent civil rights movements in self-arranged placements with universities or nongovernmental organizations in foreign countries. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H91004E3B1D33478D8068D927CD75738D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The authority to carry out the John Lewis Civil Rights Fellowship Program established under section 115 of the Mutual Educational and Cultural Exchange Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2451">22 U.S.C. 2451 et seq.</external-xref>), as added by section 2, shall expire on the date that is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

