<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA203928F3E29464189E9C60EF76514EC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5648 IH: Community Assistance for Recovery and Empowerment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5648</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Housing Act to authorize mortgage insurance for certain treatment facilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H58EAB863CB6844AEB17DFA01223BAD38" style="OLC"><section id="H2F19A46C9E3A435B84D4B64EE271A52C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Community Assistance for Recovery and Empowerment Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>CARE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC1879634990D43CC85155794EECDFCAC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Mortgage insurance for certain treatment facilities</header><subsection id="H957838632A794E67A67163E748C3A3C5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 232 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715w">12 U.S.C. 1715w</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HAF74AA8FD82442A4BF059CF0785BE81C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="HCB84AD8AF1AF4F87863378667C884DCC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (6)(C), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC79DBCD20404D3698CF73F594D1FC4B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking the final period and inserting a semicolon; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12170D73F4F0439D899DB7DF673D5E4E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1AB0A023EBA741839DCD0BB8F5F417F7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H82343CB73BDD4220A6655B36B72486A3"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>inpatient psychiatric treatment facility</quote> means a public facility, proprietary facility, or facility of a private nonprofit corporation or association that—</text><subparagraph id="H2F942CEB62D9441EB509DF79822425AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is licensed or regulated by the State (or, if there is no State law providing for such licensing or regulation by the State, by the municipality or other political subdivision in which the facility is located) for inpatient psychiatric treatment; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54ABFF9B64A047CC84F315ED3EDE7FD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has deemed status in the State pursuant to accreditation by the Joint Commission, the Commission on the Accreditation of Rehabilitation Facilities, or the Council on Accreditation; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0077A2066D74C16A6D12C202E9BD0AB"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>chemical dependence treatment facility</quote> means a public facility, proprietary facility, or facility of a private nonprofit corporation or association that—</text><subparagraph id="HA6393BA2A2F14359BE0C4AB8F904C1B8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is licensed or regulated by the State (or, if there is no State law providing for such licensing or regulation by the State, by the municipality or other political subdivision in which the facility is located) for chemical dependency treatment; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFED19753A300454F96CA87E982E8EAFF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has deemed status in the State pursuant to accreditation by the Joint Commission, the Commission on the Accreditation of Rehabilitation Facilities, or the Council on Accreditation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H64F337C1A4CE455C932FAB8A4B20EE08"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="H497C3D82B73D4AC2A9092C6B85BDC271"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, or intermediate care facility</quote> and inserting <quote>, intermediate care facility, inpatient psychiatric treatment facility, or chemical dependence treatment facility</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF894C84BDD5F4BCD97791520F11A8309"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>assisted living facility, or intermediate care facility</quote> and inserting <quote>assisted living facility, intermediate care facility, inpatient psychiatric treatment facility, or chemical dependence treatment facility</quote>; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6D3E4A2301814979B254F302F406D621"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>assisted living facility, and intermediate care facility</quote> and inserting <quote>assisted living facility, intermediate care facility, inpatient psychiatric treatment facility, and chemical dependence treatment facility</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4F1538180D574DE18713EFFBF49E22CA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of the Office of Psychiatric and Addiction Treatment Facilities</header><text>Section 4 of the Department of Housing and Urban Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3533">42 U.S.C. 3533</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFB91A34217884255A304DB4EA17CCE3B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HB13328B214204F37BDD37DC67A817A38"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Office of Psychiatric and Addiction Treatment Facilities</header><paragraph id="HCE28FF225A444FD0B45DCC0BFE2F1447"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established within the Federal Housing Administration the Office of Psychiatric and Addiction Treatment Facilities (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>Office</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEE673DD7BC6495FA57136477C7444E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assistant Director</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall appoint an Assistant Director, who shall—</text><subparagraph id="H30DA62A9A9DB43D6A45F489E9B4CDF0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>carry out the functions described in paragraph (3); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EC792C5918C47A89A480D4C18AB4879"><enum>(B)</enum><text>report directly to the Deputy Assistant Secretary for Healthcare Programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1261079B6A2B48EA978738383063869A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The Office shall oversee mortgage insurance that is authorized under section 232 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715w">12 U.S.C. 1715w</external-xref>) to be provided to an inpatient psychiatric treatment facility or a chemical dependence treatment facility (as such terms are defined in subsection (b) of such section).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HBD844129D6B0423990C09074FC6B8AEE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="H5DFF56E904594CD7AD491CCD2044D932"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Federal Housing Commissioner such sums as are necessary to carry out this section, including any costs related to—</text><subparagraph id="H920918CDF63346FCBD05C4D4944A3BD5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">hiring staff and temporary consultants;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D8AB14F8C12469FAB3A4DC1348BF91B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>developing policies, procedures, and underwriting models; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2964354713BA4CE492B723B73E52BE5E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>updating information management systems.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC22625C7ACC64CB09A8BCD0B00C84895"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In each fiscal year, the sum of any amounts appropriated pursuant to paragraph (1) and any amounts appropriated pursuant to section 519 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1735c">12 U.S.C. 1735c</external-xref>) with respect to the mortgage insurance programs described in section 232 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715w">12 U.S.C. 1715w</external-xref>) and section 242 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715z-7">12 U.S.C. 1715z–7</external-xref>) shall not exceed the amount that is the total amount generated through the collection of premiums associated with such programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD4311F3023A4C6892C3AFB79F3FA749"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the amount that is the total amount generated through the collection of premiums associated with the mortgage insurance programs described in section 232 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715w">12 U.S.C. 1715w</external-xref>) is less than the amount equal to the net present value of claims, nothing in this section may be construed to waive or eliminate the limitation described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7C6F3639C50347A99827D12585F5F6D0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Disaster preparedness and efficiency loans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 241 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715z-6">12 U.S.C. 1715z–6</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H16098EC3F8A7477F920D9AB1C8778049"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="HC483EFB9FB494F37BA528EB39ABDBBBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or other health facility</quote> and inserting <quote>or other health facility, including housing for employees or trainees of healthcare facilities insured under this title</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09C51437FB4D4FA1AC37A3008217D234"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, including floods, hurricanes, earthquakes, and other natural disasters</quote> after <quote>fire or other hazards</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H40D5ECF3AD0C4B56BAFA3D64DFF29EF0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1), by inserting <quote>or a group practice, medical practice facility, hospital, or other health care facility project approved by the Secretary under section 232 or section 242,</quote> after <quote>in a multifamily housing project</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD1D05EEB366342DA9661534A8744C1FB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall establish a negotiated rulemaking committee as provided for under section 561 of title 5, United States Code, to establish the procedures for implementation of this Act and the amendments made by this Act.</text></section><section id="H5FDF09A33E6F4C0ABA460ADF4A15B789"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header><subsection id="H48165E217F4040A18DC3D0D381E9C2D1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the end of the first fiscal year ending after the date of the enactment of this Act (and alternating fiscal years thereafter), the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall submit to the House Committee on Financial Services and the Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs a report in accordance with subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HA2904999587C447AB3E76F5EFC4DEA80"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required pursuant to subsection (a) shall include information on the operation of the mortgage insurance programs described in section 232 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715w">12 U.S.C. 1715w</external-xref>) and section 242 of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1715z-7">12 U.S.C. 1715z–7</external-xref>) for the 180-day period preceding the submission of such report, including the following information with respect to each such program: </text><paragraph id="H18408A7A88EF466E82D6020A854262A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of applications submitted to the program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71D7F0A21F8E49DABB039C8BC13BCB32"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The volume and value of loans issued under the program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1530427471564C7481DA3134F5A84B61"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The number and causes of defaults under the program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BD1EAC02C7A48E2B4B17EBDAC01F118"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The number of claims filed with respect to the program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24AF0DCD8B07430387DBE0B197CEFD39"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total premiums collected each year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0CF91ADDC5C4AF9B9EB3B87ED0EAC85"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The financial status of the program, including the credit subsidy level of the program during the period covered by the report, as determined by the Congressional Budget Office.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D4394509EDD4E76B35B6917469F515F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public inspection</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which a report is submitted pursuant to subsection (a), the Secretary shall make such report publicly available on the website of the Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

