<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4FF515B5374C46AC99F1E5CDD5C9024F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1313 IH: Transparency in CFPB Cost-Benefit Analysis Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1313</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230301">March 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000474">Mr. Flood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000294">Mr. Emmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000612">Mr. Rose</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001213">Mr. Steil</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000471">Mr. Fitzgerald</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001058">Mr. Huizenga</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001093">Mrs. Houchin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance rulemaking requirements for the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE22E77566B19417EABCF93E63BF5DCE5" style="OLC"><section id="H09E947081F4449DCA8E1BC27427CA988" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transparency in CFPB Cost-Benefit Analysis Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4BD12CBA5A7044EEAE99542E0251EECF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Transparency in cost-benefit analysis</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1022(b) of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5512">12 U.S.C. 5512(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5795E9FE55274349B041FEE522249219" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H3E3F47163B4E43C78B7403211493EB2E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Additional rulemaking requirements</header><subparagraph id="H81A2258184BE4079ABE892CFB3C2A3B1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each notice of proposed rulemaking issued by the Bureau shall be published in its entirety in the Federal Register and shall include—</text><clause id="H16DECBB483E34F4DA53E691772F37C54"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a statement of the need for the proposed regulation;</text></clause><clause id="HFEBCAB198BF64BB88FCAC38FA3CC9798"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an examination of why the Bureau must undertake the proposed regulation and why the private market, State, local, or tribal authorities cannot adequately address the problem;</text></clause><clause id="HB026D07BB0264F3E9CE2A794F488F8CD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an examination of whether the proposed regulation is duplicative, inconsistent, or incompatible with other Federal regulations and orders;</text></clause><clause id="H8D7175EEB35F431A975D9B6442C73DE9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>if the proposed regulation is found to be duplicative, inconsistent, or incompatible with other Federal regulations and orders, a discussion of—</text><subclause id="H0BBF121E2C9B4375AB0A1577D72D544C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>why the proposed regulation is justified;</text></subclause><subclause id="HBEF23E20F9934167AC211E06EC2A51B7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>how the proposed regulation can coexist with the existing regulations; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD0B5ADFEF0D940F0851EE03B3194D214"><enum>(III)</enum><text>how the Bureau plans to reduce the regulatory burden associated with the duplicative, inconsistent, or incompatible proposed regulation;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE686C7CF419644E4AF88C9D39405D98E"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a quantitative and qualitative assessment of all anticipated direct and indirect costs and benefits of the proposed regulation, including—</text><subclause id="H00B84DB7624648AF9A01BD70A9E7393E"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compliance costs for all regulated entities, including small businesses;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5C207FDC32D3486BAFD7A6D1F08EF705"><enum>(II)</enum><text>effects on economic activity, efficiency, competition and capital formation;</text></subclause><subclause id="HAFAF8EE1F5B4449ABE7774F3A918A280"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">regulatory and administrative costs of implementation; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H33320FCDF857474D9E12260851443EFF"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>costs imposed on State, local and tribal entities;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H3F888C95072E4BC4A3716D72466ECB66"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>an identification of reasonable alternatives to the regulation, including modification of an existing regulation;</text></clause><clause id="H1D846E5D064B4B4DAA943FD317CC5C3B"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>an analysis of the costs and benefits, both quantitative and qualitative, of any alternative identified pursuant to clause (v);</text></clause><clause id="HDA0D01E7841E40DB92B445EF6397B37F"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>if the Bureau determines the proposed regulation would increase costs for small businesses, then the Bureau shall consult the Office of Advocacy within the Small Business Administration to determine ways to minimize the effect of direct and indirect costs imposed on small businesses by the proposed regulation;</text></clause><clause id="H5868E86FC114478D99D00BB9B156E95D"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>if quantified net benefits of the proposed action do not outweigh the quantified net benefits of the alternatives, a justification of the regulation;</text></clause><clause id="H9288CE5E408F44BD838262049A69C9B2"><enum>(x)</enum><text>if quantified benefits identified pursuant to clause (iv) do not outweigh the quantified costs of the regulation, a justification of the regulation;</text></clause><clause id="H347EC291425E4D0A91A32E1CE733AD38"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>an assessment of how the burden imposed by the regulation will be distributed; including whether consumers, or small businesses will be disproportionately burdened; and</text></clause><clause id="HCE3532F3785C466586A0C09DFD1B866D"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>when feasible, and using appropriate statistical techniques, a probability distribution of the relevant outcomes of the proposed regulation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B4602F685E04445A30B9398C9DCB39E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Assumptions and studies used</header><text>With respect to the information required to be included under subparagraph (A), the Bureau will include—</text><clause id="HEF9922CEB2EE47A39CD22D2D3617F05E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a discussion of underlying assumptions used as a basis for such information; and</text></clause><clause id="H1361053812D649C7B88C93880FCD4D10"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of any studies or data used in preparing such information, and whether such studies were peer-reviewed. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

