<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1278315672634852A88A90DFB458BBB0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 475 IH: Witness Security and Protection Grant Program Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 475</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Attorney General to make competitive grants to State, Tribal, and local governments to establish and maintain witness protection and assistance programs.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H40E4A3990E034FB685BFB036D04A0DFC" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDA5FD825387941189571D10711366D39" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Witness Security and Protection Grant Program Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA83AEB341B7347018D3657CB922E9655"><enum>2.</enum><header>Witness protection grant program</header> <subsection id="H6277700A7ACD4501B70FD865422F5913"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text>
<paragraph id="HB910AC7AAF994CEEB69EB1691CDD8F94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>applicant</term> means a State, Tribal, or local government that applies for a grant under this section; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF5CE028AF452433BB83600C353383BF9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the terms <term>serious drug offense</term> and <term>serious violent felony</term> have the meaning given those terms in section 3559(c)(2) of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H82D5F4E112804A219C1EC3A6A4B2A647"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsection (j), the Attorney General shall make competitive grants to State, Tribal, and local governments to establish or maintain programs that provide protection or assistance to witnesses in court proceedings involving—</text> <paragraph id="H04473F18AD0845CA83D20935B68A4F18"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a homicide, serious violent felony, or serious drug offense; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2817DF63B53342B8A7E20164B0559980"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">gangs or organized crime.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H56B2311E354A4CB4A0FA9E40FF7D3F28"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In making grants under this section, the Attorney General shall evaluate applicants based upon the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H72772535078A440184FF3642B6F04D40"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The extent to which the applicant lacks infrastructure to support programs that provide protection or assistance to witnesses.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE9F6E8A42ECC450C818E2E3458F736CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The prevalence of witness intimidation in the jurisdiction of the applicant.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9630D1321DF04B96ACB86030EF7A024C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The percentage of cases not prosecuted by the applicant due to witness intimidation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H825249E892FB4A0C8CEE362F12A4962A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The number of homicides per capita committed in the jurisdiction of the applicant.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4980B8DE32784E4AA42EEF196EAF1A67"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The number of serious violent felonies or serious drug offenses per capita committed in the jurisdiction of the applicant.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H28F39CA39F1442F89F46B288B3B5CB59"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The extent to which organized crime is present in the jurisdiction of the applicant.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H287BCD94AA304D6CA741FA02B9C4DA23"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other criteria that the Attorney General determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HD449BDAB014142699ED72B3D79C91554"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From amounts made available under subsection (j) to carry out this section, the Attorney General, upon request of a recipient of a grant under this section, shall direct the appropriate offices within the Department of Justice to provide technical assistance to the recipient to the extent the Attorney General determines technical assistance is needed to establish or maintain a program that provides protection or assistance to witnesses.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDAB945D0DD9D4A0FBBC8B6F3D7B63328"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Best practices</header>
<paragraph id="HFDE895CF11CA47888542EE8850FFF1CC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report</header><text>A recipient of a grant under this section shall submit to the Attorney General a report, in such form and manner and containing such information as specified by the Attorney General, that evaluates each program established or maintained pursuant to the grant, including policies and procedures under the program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H27C72097394D47D0BE16284CC711013C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Development of Best Practices</header><text>Based on the reports submitted under paragraph (1), the Attorney General shall develop best practice models to assist State, Tribal, and local governments in addressing—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5DF19FED90DE43E5B746863AE7066340"><enum>(A)</enum><text>witness safety;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7514F0BDC3D4477BA662069C790C080A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>short-term and permanent witness relocation;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA3F3EBC3E94F466C9BD59C191AAD584C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>financial and housing assistance; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD79128332AC94B3B9A577313B61D3F9A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other services related to witness protection or assistance that the Attorney General determines necessary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7A04EFB23F134C1EB523556486055365"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Dissemination to States</header><text>Not later than 1 year after developing best practice models under paragraph (2), the Attorney General shall disseminate the models to State, Tribal, and local governments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7CB2C9860B1D4F0B8BBD1DF02EB81F9E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that State, Tribal, and local governments should use the best practice models developed and disseminated under this subsection to evaluate, improve, and develop witness protection or witness assistance programs as appropriate.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H7A5AABABFD89404B9D4D1BC725C8DBF1"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rule of construction relating to sensitive information</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to require the dissemination of any information that the Attorney General determines—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H20C195C4CC2A44DFB744E7FA2FF57629"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is law enforcement sensitive and should only be disclosed within the law enforcement community; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H0F7A75F520484430BCA903C542747CF5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>poses a threat to national security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HA56281A15A9D4724B1EF541475FB22ED"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Federal share</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H7E397D01DEA14670A25E2952867C9C0F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Federal share of the cost of a program carried out using a grant made under this section shall be not more than 75 percent.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="H5C2B40E1BDE8400E8415C18172ADB1FA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In-kind contributions</header>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HFD6AF878FA374716B1B2194A664AB802"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the non-Federal share for a program carried out using a grant made under this section may be in the form of in-kind contributions that are directly related to the purpose for which the grant was made.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3EB77782CEF74F4CAF82CEB87850CFB7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Maximum percentage</header><text>Not more than 50 percent of the non-Federal share for a program carried out using a grant made under this section may be in the form of in-kind contributions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="HA911B8973AF54287BF444D826C833980"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>Of amounts made available to carry out this section for a fiscal year, the Attorney General may use not more than 5 percent for administrative costs.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="HDFCF625D2B034838BFD777261ED9B613"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Geographic distribution</header><text>In making grants under this section, the Attorney General shall—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HFAA5CC0736DF4214B4359CD2D273D58A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the extent reasonable and practical, ensure an equitable geographical distribution throughout the United States of programs that provide protection or assistance to witnesses; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H5C1AA7F83DD5442CB31788F4B6465F64"><enum>(2)</enum><text>give due consideration to applicants from both urban and rural areas.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H25AA0BFEBC65486EB5EA930E19210725"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall submit a report to Congress—</text> <paragraph id="HA19FBE49C4B54E3DA3A8CE8431B13B18"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than December 31, 2024, on the implementation of this section, including any information on programs funded by grants made under this section; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H003EF335194942E699DDA8E7522A1D7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than December 31, 2028, on the programs funded by grants made under this section, including on best practice models developed under subsection (e)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H64A61471651C4028920A49FA42BC2BC1"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $30,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

