<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC09E5C73ABD4475AB48B66F1159EEB8A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3954 IH: Water and Agriculture Tax Reform Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3954</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000189">Mr. Newhouse</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to facilitate water leasing and water transfers to promote conservation and efficiency.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H590134C01082441CAE54B1E1A4756040" style="OLC"><section id="H01FFE3E3CADA4615A1B2D0C5D735C823" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Water and Agriculture Tax Reform Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFD03AF22D43C4406986FE90624C167F6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Facilitate water leasing and water transfers to promote conservation and efficiency</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8F4A8697C3BE4A71B181A1424A04887B"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (12) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBF10A212EDD8481EA2E910B2A7815C96" style="OLC"><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAEA9AAD95EFF4FC98E99DA39412696A0"><enum>(K)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Treatment of mutual ditch irrigation companies</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5CBA60B258C84BFAB185E85B4D9AB243"><enum>(i)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a mutual ditch or irrigation company or of a like organization to a mutual ditch or irrigation company, subparagraph (A) shall be applied without taking into account—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H76D19ED8C06441FFB1C7ABF8AEC5C637"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any income received or accrued from the sale, lease, or exchange of fee or other interests in real and personal property, including interests in water,</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4ED7576F0FA34C50B5EBE8152540FA1E"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any income received or accrued from the sale or exchange of stock in a mutual ditch or irrigation company (or in a like organization to a mutual ditch or irrigation company) or contract rights for the delivery or use of water, or</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82C71FEC7EBE418EB8A2E59F6E08AE33"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any income received or accrued from the investment of income described in subclause (I) or (II),</text></subclause><continuation-text commented="no" continuation-text-level="clause">except that any income described in subclause (I), (II), or (III) which is distributed or expended for expenses (other than for operations, maintenance, and capital improvements) of the mutual ditch or irrigation company or of the like organization to a mutual ditch or irrigation company (as the case may be) shall be treated as nonmember income in the year in which it is distributed or expended. For purposes of the preceding sentence, expenses (other than for operations, maintenance, and capital improvements) include expenses for the construction of conveyances designed to deliver water outside of the system of the mutual ditch or irrigation company or of the like organization. </continuation-text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B3654A03F30401CB265E245D1065674"><enum>(ii)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Treatment of organizational governance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a mutual ditch or irrigation company or of a like organization to a mutual ditch or irrigation company, where State law provides that such a company or organization may be organized in a manner that permits voting on a basis which is pro rata to share ownership on corporate governance matters, subparagraph (A) shall be applied without taking into account whether its member shareholders have one vote on corporate governance matters per share held in the corporation. Nothing in this clause shall be construed to create any inference about the requirements of this subsection for companies or organizations not included in this clause.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6E8D691A6F614C768BB69DDFEBD1FF65"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

