<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H39289929132343BB9B3F7389AB12A205" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5827 IH: Tenants’ Right to Organize Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5827</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230929">September 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote the establishment of resident organizations and provide additional amounts for tenant organizations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4FC6588D208E498DAA54A13A6D3DC3C0" style="OLC"><section id="HE96A53905E2B49278A4018FCD37CBECB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Tenants’ Right to Organize Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFA615747C33A499D9A87EDCA54CD53E2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of the Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that all members of a household receiving tenant-based rental assistance have the right to <quote>decent, safe, stable and sanitary housing</quote>.</text></section><section id="HCFAAEC688795426C82C2CC107B8144E8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Housing choice voucher tenant organizations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 8(o) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f(o)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H593A2EFC9D634E159A822F9DD2E8B787" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HD8812E63FB6A4A998BAA74F24B00977C"><enum>(23)</enum><header>Right to organize</header><subparagraph id="H387FD3E97BB94621BF68C856C89C3995"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tenants receiving tenant-based rental assistance have the right to establish, operate, and participate in a resident organization for the purpose of addressing issues related to their living environment, which includes the terms and conditions of their tenancy as well as activities related to housing and community development and may not be retaliated against for asserting these rights.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72DDE856253340D9BF19422B60597C74"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Required engagement</header><clause id="H40D791955B4C49E19CF92275029717AF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Public Housing Agencies</header><text>Each public housing agency shall—</text><subclause id="H2C9921A72B7F4E9A87212059F25FA6A4"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recognize legitimate tenant organizations;</text></subclause><subclause id="H35B9A8F3B5C244AD9D3C1956BE7E6199"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">solicit comments from all legitimate tenant organizations not less than once each year; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H6605964A812144CEAB11FAE702628266"><enum>(III)</enum><text>not later than 60 days after receiving a comment from a legitimate tenant organization, meaningfully respond in writing to such comment.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H797EA6255A4F408E862C89872E272AC0"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Owners of units</header><text>Each owner—</text><subclause id="H0AA0CE666CD9446EBC11965B458F0B59"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall recognize legitimate resident organizations; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H4D6DFBB2033840B3B216E1A4A0D0648C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>may not retaliate with respect to any tenant because of their association with a legitimate resident organization. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC4673223401496AB7CA5D55B41B25BC"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Protections</header><clause id="H1DF54E668FF84FD8A05C9C1D5F34F3A0"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each public housing agency and each owner may not interfere with the right of tenants to establish and operate a legitimate tenant organization.</text></clause><clause id="H6FF562EE33544B7C93667CAE0B147ED5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Protected activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each public housing agency and each owner shall allow tenants and tenant organizers to conduct the following activities related to the establishment or operation of a tenant organization: </text><subclause id="HA93615656541420EBDC1905FA3FD13A0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Distributing leaflets in lobby areas. </text></subclause><subclause id="H076B45C8AF3C45A198508877203DAFA9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Placing leaflets at or under tenants' doors.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6E60FD131D98457490709A7ECBDE1816"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Distributing leaflets in common areas.</text></subclause><subclause id="H13421CB92B354471BEFC7AC64E9333DC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Initiating contact with tenants.</text></subclause><subclause id="HB4D5ADF414474398A843BEB09EAA223B"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Conducting door-to-door surveys of tenants to ascertain interest in establishing a legitimate tenant organization and to offer information about tenant organizations.</text></subclause><subclause id="H5504D900626F48748BEAABD02700C970"><enum>(VI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Posting information on bulletin boards.</text></subclause><subclause id="HC09A5990C3D84C35BC05F69A5ED847FC"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>Assisting tenants to participate in tenant organization activities.</text></subclause><subclause id="HB1149781D7F24D229A2E93A1EAD97E6E"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>Convening regularly scheduled tenant organization meetings in a space on site and accessible to tenants, in a manner that is fully independent of management representatives. In order to preserve the independence of tenant organizations, management representatives may not attend such meetings unless invited by the tenant organization to specific meetings to discuss a specific issue or issues.</text></subclause><subclause id="HAC4EF69C0BC74298A672A291D34AFE7D"><enum>(IX)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other reasonable activities related to the establishment or operation of a tenant organization.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HD605379EA8284B82A8652116A690FC57"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Permission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A public housing agency or owner may not require tenants or tenant organizers to obtain prior permission before engaging in the activities permitted under this paragraph.</text></clause><clause id="HA43987E989E74AE9962F1787AC63C33E"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Presumption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a public housing agency or owner takes an adverse action against a tenant that is a member of a tenant organization there shall be a rebuttable presumption that such adverse action is an act of retaliation relating to the participation of the tenant in the tenant organization.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H079428A9F4524A3DB37E8C721780F187"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Enforcement protocol</header><clause id="H50C0AF691839468593281B9AC0C173AD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall, not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, establish a protocol for the enforcement of this paragraph and such protocol shall—</text><subclause id="HE8C9EEA282A64F11B050CBD3433F781F"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include an independent investigation of tenant and advocate allegations of abuse and retaliation;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD31D6028849E4E628D9BB9A7D1838217"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provide a mechanism for administrative complaints to be made and cataloged;</text></subclause><subclause id="HFC4EE56CC70946A38BAA13EB13CEC890"><enum>(III)</enum><text>keep tenants regularly informed about the progression of any complaint;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6B8779FAC8D247BE83591FB0753F094C"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prohibit the withholding of tenant-based rental assistance from any tenant that makes a complaint, until such complaint is closed; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9CB155B43CA442E28B7A178765091DFB"><enum>(V)</enum><text>provide confidentiality where necessary, including in cases where alleged abuse is extreme and targeted.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0423D0679A4D460B95A83D904770E129"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Delegation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing the enforcement protocol under clause (i), the Secretary may use subcontractors to preform enforcement activities. </text></clause><clause id="HB3D553407A5A4C6892473242B4B74016"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Secretary shall each quarter submit to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, a report with respect to the enforcement of this paragraph that—</text><subclause id="HE44BF3AC6B804BE49B65E4B347A52695"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides all data at both the property-level and jurisdiction-level; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7BE6591ED5BC40249413691C447638F4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>includes information with respect to—</text><item id="H382B55A0AD08463FA0F21F48A4FB5BDA"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the volume of outstanding complaints;</text></item><item id="H071A7C79B00A4138BE6CC8971BF4640B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the average response time for initial complaint; and</text></item><item id="H6C035C02B43D421CB580994BC13973C3"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the average time it takes to close a complaint.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H1FC1019610704E96B81EB2BC2A032311"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated, to the Secretary, such sums as are necessary to carry out this paragraph. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAAA968D3354647ECB2B796F00366C5E6"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Notice of right to organize</header><clause id="HD322708E1F5641648BD71A8C97D285F6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each public housing agency shall notify each tenant receiving tenant-based rental assistance of the right to organize described in subparagraph (A) annually during the recertification process. </text></clause><clause id="H0DA7C68BFA5B449692FD949750A3708F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Tenancy addendum</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall update the most recent Tenancy Addendum for the Section 8 Tenant-Based Assistance Housing Choice Voucher Program to describe the right to organize provided for in this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14089CE5061E4E98AFCE6C33BED0EFCC"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph:</text><clause id="HAFD689B750BB4F46A63A35F49D10E910"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Tenant organizer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>tenant organizer</quote> means a tenant or non-tenant who assists tenants in establishing and operating a tenant organization, and who is not an employee or representative of current or prospective owners, managers, or their agents.</text></clause><clause id="HB06A85D89070478F88B3878F92D4D5AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Legitimate tenant organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>legitimate tenant organization</quote> means an organization of 3 more tenants receiving tenant-based rental assistance that has been established for the purpose described in subparagraph (A).</text></clause><clause id="H7BB14FED624345599D5913E0B3479383"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Owner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term owner means a person who owns a dwelling unit occupied by a tenant that receives rental assistance.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HC5EECD09127C4634B649221AB3A2094D"><enum>4.</enum><header>LIHTC tenant organizations</header><subsection id="HB157DEAA9D1B45BB89486179B94381C2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/42">Section 42(g)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1891F89859114CE680C61515B887C1FA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HE563E1612DDD4BFEB99F68D2E6D69E26"><enum>(10)</enum><header>LIHTC tenant organizations</header><subparagraph id="H5BA41A0C1A23449F9335CA145755428A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Rights of tenants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tenants of rent-restricted units in any qualified low-income housing project shall have the same right as tenants described in section 8(o)(23)(A) of the United States Housing Act of 1937.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF80B346139D54009906F06E58F3D13AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Responsibilities of owners</header><clause id="HB6EFEF065B7841D2BE74DEA5E5BCBF1B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Each owner of qualified low-income housing project must meet the requirements in subparagraphs (B)(ii) and (C) of section 8(o)(23) of the United States Housing Act of 1937.</text></clause><clause id="HAEA04CA1502C422CBE2B049388060589" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an owner fails to meet the requirements referred to in clause (i) with respect to any qualified low-income housing project, the credits allowed under this section with respect to such project shall be disallowed or recaptured in an amount that is proportionate to the violation, as determined by the Secretary, but in no case less than 5 percent of the credits claimed during the taxable year during which the violation occurred.</text></clause><clause id="HE52D99980B6F4B428CEB30F0E373DC24" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any failure referred to in clause (ii) that occurs after the expiration of the project’s compliance period (as determined under subsection (i)(1)), the Secretary shall levy fines in accordance with a schedule determined by the Secretary that shall establish fines of not less than $500 per day for each day after the end of the correction period established by the Secretary. The Secretary shall establish such schedule not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act. The Secretary may delegate its duty to levy fines to the State housing credit agencies.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79CC3886B50F4641AE558EC40552C33F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Responsibilities of State Housing Agencies</header><clause id="HE13F5F53248F4E1F85F9FEB30326D8DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each State housing credit agency must meet the requirements which are the same as the requirements of subparagraphs (B)(i) and (C) of section 8(o)(23) of the United States Housing Act of 1937.</text></clause><clause id="HF6B5EB91F1BD49FA9A527F53BA2370F8" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a State housing credit agency fails to meet the requirements referred to in clause (i), there shall be a reduction in the State housing credit agency’s State housing credit ceiling (as calculated under subsection (h)(3)(C)) during the calendar year following a violation in an amount determined by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CBE8D82A24844B8883583F68A3A980B" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Establishment of private right to action</header><text>Individuals who meet the income limitation applicable to the building under this subsection (whether prospective, present, or former occupants of the building) may file an action at law or in equity, in Federal or State court, including for injunctive relief, to enforce the various provisions of this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEADA45A2E33B4E93AF92B62242497A44"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Enforcement protocol</header><text>The Secretary, after consultation with the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, shall—</text><clause id="HB9015262B34640A8A8A908C8A298B029"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a protocol for the enforcement of this paragraph which is the same as the protocol established under section 8(o)(23)(D)(i) of the United States Housing Act of 1937, except that, for purposes of this subparagraph, the reference in such section to <quote>tenant-based rental assistance</quote> shall be treated as a reference to the right of the tenant to occupy a rent-restricted unit and to any other right or privilege required to be provided to such tenant as a condition of the project being treated as a qualified low-income housing project, and</text></clause><clause id="H0975E325573F4712A223E4F57BCD67DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit each quarter to the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Finance of the Senate a report containing the information described in section 8(o)(23)(D)(ii) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 with respect to the enforcement of this paragraph with respect to qualified low-income housing projects.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21E63FDE86824D50A92F034F9881BBB3"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Notice of right to organize</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each State housing credit agency shall annually notify each owner and tenant of a rent-restricted unit of a qualified low-income housing project of the right to organize referred to in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HAC5A6973DE894CB3A903871891B60F77"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HC8DBCEE1B697440B95A333C6CD75A781"><enum>5.</enum><header>Funding for tenant and other participation and capacity building</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (3) of section 514(f) of the Multifamily Assisted Housing Reform and Affordability Act of 1997 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437f">42 U.S.C. 1437f</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HB79588433BAD49EB82942B2253C1D007"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subparagraph id="HA229B59D77C240999D46A66D56C3B3DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the first sentence—</text><clause id="H53805D7F40FA43E29E5EBA8DC2C24C05"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>not more than</quote> and inserting <quote>not less than</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H7366DDD072AD4DA9A6F899BD029F4454"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>of low-income housing for which project-based rental assistance is provided at below market rent levels and may not be renewed (including transfer of developments to tenant groups, nonprofit organizations, and public entities), for tenant services</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>and improvement of low-income housing for which project-based rental assistance, public housing subsidies, low-income housing tax credits, Federal or State subsidized loans, enhanced vouchers under section 8(t), or project-based vouchers under section 8(o) are provided or proposed</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HBCC06D23C0BD4ECFAC7CD47E0C07ABF1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the second parenthetical clause, by inserting before the closing parenthesis the following: <quote>, and predevelopment assistance to enable such transfers</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B6BAB943240410DB423EB40F9617B1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after the period at the end the following: <quote>For outreach and training of tenants and technical assistance, the Secretary shall implement a grant program utilizing performance-based outcome measures for eligible costs incurred. Recipients providing capacity building or technical assistance services to tenant groups shall be qualified nonprofit statewide, countywide, area-wide, or city-wide organizations with demonstrated experience including at least a two-year recent track record of organizing and providing assistance to tenants, and independence from the owner, a prospective purchaser, or their managing agents. The Secretary may provide assistance and training to grantees in administrative and fiscal management to ensure compliance with applicable Federal requirements. The Secretary shall expedite the provision of funding for the fiscal year in which the date of the enactment of this Act occurs and by entering into an interagency agreement for not less than $1,000,000 with the Corporation for National and Community Service to conduct a tenant outreach and training program to eligible housing under this subsection. The Secretary shall also make available flexible grants to qualified nonprofit organizations that do not own eligible multifamily properties, for tenant outreach in underserved areas, and to experienced national or regional nonprofit organizations to provide specialized training or support to grantees assisted under this section. Notwithstanding any other provision of law, funds authorized under this paragraph for any fiscal year shall be available for obligation in subsequent fiscal years. The Secretary shall require each recipient of amounts made available pursuant to this subparagraph to submit to the Secretary reports, on a quarterly basis, detailing the use of such funds and including such information as the Secretary shall require.</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HF5DAF1237C1349B99822975F46FF7B8C" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Clarification of tenant participation in multi-family projects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 202(a) of the Housing and Community Development Amendments of 1978 (12 U.S.C. 1715z–1b(a)) is amended by striking <quote>under section 1437f of title 42</quote> and inserting <quote>under section 1437f of title 42, including a project assisted under section 8(o)(13) of the Housing Act of 1937</quote>. </text></section><section id="H15A6F3EA390944CBAEB956033BBF0260"><enum>7.</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall, not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, issue a rule revising section 964.150 of title 24, Code of Federal Regulations, to permit housing agencies to fund $25 per unit per year for units represented by duly elected resident councils for resident services.</text></section><section id="H1FFAB8AEF6CF4B43A56793654C6476D3"><enum>8.</enum><header>Survey</header><subsection id="HCA9BB79D09EA44588065A4A628911D8A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall, not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, develop a resident survey protocol based on the National Standards for the Physical Inspection of Real Estate, that is designed to collect insights on resident experiences with the inspection process.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5415659BA8E94F3B8E840442A46ECC4D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of information</header><text>Information collected through the survey protocol developed pursuant to subsection (a) shall be used to—</text><paragraph id="H677139A0145C4B54954A8190A9FF70E7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify inspection-related challenges for residents; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7212712D45D741A283FB9B529CA7BA23"><enum>(2)</enum><text>improve the satisfaction of residents with respect to their housing conditions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D4E956CAA0346D3BD549338781BAF67"><enum>(3)</enum><text>ensure resident voices are heard; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06E61ACB5D1F4B2EB7D01251C62C1255"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide quality control.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

