<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9492EE6494EC474C88D937AC132F6F11" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 686 IH: Keep Huawei on the Entity List Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 686</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the continuation in effect of export controls with respect to Huawei Technologies Co. Ltd., and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB57688E54A444D558E431013556D12B3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H86804826EA694D3E8B61095878390661" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Keep Huawei on the Entity List Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HA42D527886574AB0B7B811B91B7D4A43"><enum>2.</enum><header>Continuation in effect of export controls with respect to Huawei Technologies Co. Ltd</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Commerce may not remove Huawei Technologies Co. Ltd., or its subsidiaries and affiliates, from the entity list or modify any of the licensing policies pursuant to its designation on the entity list, including the foreign direct product rule, unless the Secretary, with the concurrence of the End-User Review Committee by a unanimous vote of such Committee, certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that Huawei Technologies Co. Ltd., and its subsidiaries and affiliates—</text>
<paragraph id="H37CC6C34A1DC43E9BFA98D034D048B13"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have not engaged in activities that are contrary to United States national security or foreign policy interests and are unlikely to engage in such activities in the future; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC51DE9BA350E4A9593E8768297662E0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>are not owned, controlled, or influenced by the Communist Party of China.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HA4A266A6BFDA484BAFD34C91436331B3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Export controls with respect to Honor Device Co. Ltd</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce—</text> <paragraph id="H92E8C9C4F1BE444BB7C53C112C46E420"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall designate Honor Device Co. Ltd. for inclusion on the entity list; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H15C6BABA08BC44CD936A486D165EF5BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall publish a notification with respect to such designation in the Federal Register.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H3BA5B7ABC99C4D32A20EFDBF27980AE5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report</header> <subsection id="HDF9AFF7C22EB40EA8495978089FB0864"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and on a monthly basis thereafter, the Secretary of Commerce shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that—</text>
<paragraph id="H9FD29B40AFE94054A469F3B9F403937B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies and describes all license applications received by the Department of Commerce to export, reexport, or transfer (in-country) items subject to the Export Administration Regulations to—</text> <subparagraph id="HAB71CFE0C02E426588CAC3BD58D72A42"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Huawei Technologies Co. Ltd., or its subsidiaries and affiliates; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1CA54CAB6EAC4A018D418366057CB7AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Honor Device Co. Ltd; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6EA3934D8DC749EFA0D69A2A177129C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies whether such license applications were approved or denied.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA491C890B134487F94B699259FC376ED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HBB28DB86118B49EF86FA930A9F94FB54"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HEA872F56A0F84BA2BE68035BE9405C97"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB5020D9CA5FB4616A0FB34AF531223B7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>End-User Review Committee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>End-User Review Committee</term> means the End-User Review Committee described in Supplement No. 9 to part 748 of the Export Administration Regulations. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF2AE1A75C54D48178F2CBE949B65F9F3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Entity list</header><text>The term <term>entity list</term> means the list maintained by the Bureau of Industry and Security and set forth in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB64ACC8317A4887BE7DFE3C76A92060"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Export Administration Regulations</header><text>The term <term>Export Administration Regulations</term> means subchapter C of chapter VII of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

