<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H86DA57FBE0864C8584F66972452F61AB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 785 IH: To amend the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 to require paid rest breaks for certain construction employees, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 785</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 to require paid rest breaks for certain construction employees, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB3ACBC689AA0430F8606D7D7CD804612" style="OLC"><section id="H555270C8804A422AA97C0EFC3B1BE4BD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Paid rest breaks for certain construction employees</header><subsection id="H662B85C1496D4C9A88DFFCC515A4CF60"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Paid rest break</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Fair Labor Standards Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/201">29 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 7 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB00616866E734D37A3B989DF6747812B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HC53D6B6C12DC4D9899F0056BFC050FC3"><enum>8.</enum><header>Paid rest breaks for construction employees</header><subsection id="H273F5E9FE49642C1B41A670BDC53C685"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employer shall—</text><paragraph id="H8417F3CDB89C41548ADF2E84376C4922"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to each construction employee of such employer—</text><subparagraph id="H11D2657A73CB4E6D92620D1F7A58C9D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide at least one 15-minute paid rest break for every four hours of work to each such employee; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H654E28C092E64DF3AAE5C215015CBFFD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at the time of hiring, provide notice in the primary language of such employee, an explanation that—</text><clause id="HD589026BABD84E4CB48C6502D8A69E12"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such employee is entitled to the paid rest breaks described in subparagraph (A);</text></clause><clause id="HD081BBB27228429FBE93677A335A8FBE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>retaliation by such employer against such employee for requesting or taking such paid rest breaks is prohibited; and</text></clause><clause id="H5EC7FADA36B94B0D8758DBBC48B71B15"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>such employee has a right to file a complaint with the Secretary for any violation of this section by such employer; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EB632292F1D41119EA23B76B8801E39"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">display a sign, in a conspicuous and accessible location, at the place of business of such employer and at the applicable construction work site that includes, in both English and Spanish, the information described in paragraph (1)(B).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H99683E27397142BCA197CDF731B1D830"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Posted notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall issue regulations with respect to the design and content of the sign referred to in subsection (a)(2).</text></subsection><subsection id="HFA5F0EDF2E5C444A80FA39460BB0B013"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Retaliation prohibited</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employer may not take retaliatory personnel action or otherwise discriminate against a construction employee if such employee—</text><paragraph id="H7979DDFAB9AE47328807AB4E747980B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>requests or takes paid rest breaks in accordance with this section; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A881FF2A47048E1AAF29FCA5C8D5385"><enum>(2)</enum><text>files a complaint with the Secretary alleging a violation of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE3FE5975BD5E40C6B6C7B0FB4FA09AD5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Interaction with other laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to excuse noncompliance with any Federal or State law, municipal ordinance, or collective bargaining agreement requiring longer rest breaks than those required under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA08AE9760AD44C5B90F0F80F2E535CE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HDBB2C7274CCF452BBD3EB0CA0E25AD17" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>construction employee</quote> means an individual who is employed by an employer, or is hired as a contractor of such an employer, to perform general construction services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1311686F19644565897A38E11ABC6419"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>general construction services</quote> means the—</text><subparagraph id="H57F7BB9BBAD347569B90A94E80AFC8A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>erection of or preparation to erect a structure; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCA80786C5184E40A9910115C6AD2A1B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>remodeling, extension, repair, or demolition of a structure or other improvement of real property or a structure related to real property.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3658DC7209F4595AA6A095D293D4B0F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>rest break</quote> means a break from work during work hours, but does not include a regular meal break period provided to a construction employee by an employer. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCF43C7651CD44E37B77E70E784835667"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 16(b) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/216">29 U.S.C. 216(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding after the third sentence the following: <quote>If the Secretary makes a determination that an employer has violated section 8(a) of this Act, the Secretary may assess an administrative penalty to such employer if such employer fails to correct the violation not later than 30 days after the date on which such employer receives notice from the Secretary of such determination. Any employer that violates the provisions of section 8(c) of this Act shall be liable for such legal or equitable relief as may be appropriate, including without limitation employment, reinstatement, promotion, and the payment of wages lost and an additional equal amount as liquidated damages.</quote>.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

