<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF349514591E645AAA7C266061B991906" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 469 IH: Asylum Abuse Reduction Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 469</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require asylum officers at United States embassies and consulates to conduct credible fear screenings before aliens seeking asylum may be permitted to enter the United States to apply for asylum, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE313170650B545AAB75BB1A453B25BDD" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H7286B814A2C7446FA2191D30DA05DA51"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Asylum Abuse Reduction Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HCFA4F7392DDA42A9B89D23E73D9F0D36"><enum>2.</enum><header>Asylum interviews</header> <subsection id="H33C913FEC23347A3A1EAB794782B3CCA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Border crossings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 235(b)(1) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)</external-xref>), if an alien who is seeking asylum in the United States attempts to enter the United States from Canada or Mexico at a land port of entry without a valid visa or other appropriate entry document, the immigration officer who is inspecting the alien—</text>
<paragraph id="H10269D2132BD47E39C1A73597429329A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not admit or parole the alien into the United States; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF3920EE42B994E5C94F4C699BBD8BD6A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall advise the alien to schedule an asylum hearing with the most convenient United States embassy or consulate in Canada or Mexico.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H084C1E77F1714852B6740C68B557C5CF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Credible fear screenings</header><text>An alien described in subsection (a) may only be permitted to enter the United States to apply for asylum if an asylum officer stationed at a United States embassy or consulate—</text> <paragraph id="H159DF318A78541148E2C7C27836B658E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has conducted an in-person or telephonic interview with the alien; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0778AFC35F21414BA58E3329780781C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as a result of such interview, has concluded that the alien—</text> <subparagraph id="HA7D7CAB33DC843509AF00B2C5F0B1CF3"><enum>(A)</enum> <clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF8014B1472D74849BB4BA32A66380251"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has been persecuted in the alien’s country of nationality on account of the alien’s race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group, or political opinion; </text></clause>
<clause id="H9DC89903603749BCB00C9600B1FB90AC" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has a credible fear of persecution (as defined in section 235(b)(1)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)(B)</external-xref>)) if the alien returned to such country; or</text></clause> <clause indent="up1" commented="no" id="H6F800A6281954697A159011FB5D1A172"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>would be subject to torture by a government or public official acting under the color of law if the alien returned to his or her country of nationality; and </text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5F3CED97A2DC432FB05852121269EF68" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is otherwise eligible for asylum under section 208(a) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(a)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HDE6FFEC5D8D246EDACCEA00060B86E55"><enum>3.</enum><header>Asylum ineligibility</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 208(a)(2) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H6A686011E78445E3A72E58DD00E1963F" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="H606245A2F4534EDFB27C359C2DC55640"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Transit through third country</header>
<clause id="HDAF3EB857C9E4BC087701FA66E16DA55"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), paragraph (1) shall not apply to any alien who, on or after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, enters, attempts to enter, or arrives in the United States through the Southern land border after transiting through, on the way to the United States, one or more countries other than the country of citizenship, nationality, or last lawful habitual residence of the alien.</text></clause> <clause id="HC30AF971EBBE44508A7C9A4AF2F440C3"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply if—</text>
<subclause id="H4843AAEEB3AD4A2EACF95646AB384CA7"><enum>(I)</enum>
<item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H305369E283CA4CF4A421D819CB91B251"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the alien demonstrates that he or she applied for protection from persecution or torture in one or more countries (other than the country of citizenship, nationality, or last lawful habitual residence of the alien) through which the alien transited on the way to the United States; and</text></item> <item id="HE4BA32ED326242239DFED85C61416700" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the alien received a final judgment denying the alien protection in such country;</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="H29007C15B8CB4A15898EB44D76E1B3B9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the alien demonstrates that he or she is or has been subject to a severe form of trafficking in persons; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA545C487FDA140AA8FD66624326318F6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the one or more countries through which the alien transited on the way to the United States were not, at the time of the transit, parties to—</text>
<item id="H10646407095B4BE481504B2101FB04CB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees, done at Geneva July 28, 1951 (as made applicable by the Protocol Relating to the Status of Refugees, done at New York January 31, 1967 (19 UST 6223)); or</text></item> <item id="HCBE02826C5E9448D90DFD067C26ED6B7"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the Convention against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment, done at New York December 10, 1984.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H427448A916964C34B9C3E130858FE688" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Internal relocation</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to an alien interviewed by an asylum officer under section 2(b) of the <short-title>Asylum Abuse Reduction Act</short-title> if the asylum officer makes a determination that the alien may avoid purported persecution or torture in the alien's country of nationality by relocating to another part of such country.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H400C332D601A48CC88A61DA43313BFE5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Criminal bench warrants</header> <subsection id="H04BEC458300F4E4A84AB4D5A5E8A25D8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Issuance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal judicial district shall appoint at least 1 magistrate or district court judge who, upon a showing of probable cause, shall issue a warrant of arrest for a violation of section 243(a)(1) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1253">8 U.S.C. 1253(a)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H3BA972A439104CAB93F9095407FA400C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Probable cause</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An order of removal issued under any provision of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>) that has been in existence 90 days or more shall constitute prima facie evidence of probable cause to issue a warrant under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> <section id="H1AAE12A6AA8B48F2A5D7706A460F2AC2"><enum>5.</enum><header>Inapplicability of Flores settlement agreement to aliens subject to detention</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The stipulated settlement agreement filed in the United States District Court for the Central District of California on January 17, 1997 (CV 85–4544–RJK) (commonly known as the <quote>Flores settlement agreement</quote>), shall not apply to the detention and custody of aliens subject to detention in the United States under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

