<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8655BE1606234F59BE56EDCC82891C87" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6583 IH: Refuge System Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6583</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231204">December 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the United States Fish and Wildlife Service to seek compensation for injuries to trust resources and to use funds received as that compensation to restore, replace, or acquire equivalent resources, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE1CD3C5F8DFE4BD096F1D046B8B0EDDE" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H299DC6F862444E228A2F386E98599DAD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Refuge System Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB809401BB9BD4592A7ABFC5FE8035D5D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HFD4921E14FC14423A98EDD4AB262A558"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Damages</header><text>The term <term>damages</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H8FC52BA6177F499BA8459ACF4D2B1C66"><enum>(A)</enum><text>compensation for—</text> 
<clause id="H8BBE8A4AE9714D27862D7E7AC6E3C25A"><enum>(i)</enum> 
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H86AED45771D041E89B69A73908553BAC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the cost of replacing, restoring, or acquiring the equivalent of a system resource; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H09E53709177B41FEB5566E4F1C4C9B8F" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the value of any significant loss of use of a system resource, pending—</text> 
<item id="HC5C7F7E320D54260AD5E395E9FD07EDB"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>restoration or replacement of the system resource; or</text></item> <item id="HBC8A034DF0DE41AE8F2AFDD7C6AB6697"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the acquisition of an equivalent resource; or</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H4C4245A8C15449FD88603A0EDD780E54"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the value of a system resource, if the system resource cannot be replaced or restored; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H0B58F2343DB5435BA963BB00A8335DF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the cost of any relevant damage assessment carried out pursuant to section 4(c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7660A22BA0AB43488AE49B345C2C9A66"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Response cost</header><text>The term <term>response cost</term> means the cost of any action carried out by the Secretary—</text> <subparagraph id="H3B81501688844796BFC380A7EE2C451C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to prevent, minimize, or abate the destruction or loss of, or injury to, a system resource;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEAB893D5C83A412F9C9F9351834EB02D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to abate or minimize the imminent risk of any destruction, loss, or injury described in subparagraph (A); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5D2C9271B8FE4E5798312D2621A43DBF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to monitor the ongoing effects of any incident causing any destruction, loss, or injury described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A73B51973A5425B90BCF754DB471B7A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE9EB15BB8828492ABAFF16731D4ED743"><enum>(4)</enum><header>System resource</header><text>The term <term>system resource</term> means any living, nonliving, historical, cultural, or archeological resource that is located within the boundaries of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H71875BCE8FCA4A63B3F5685A12341902"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a unit of the National Wildlife Refuge System;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDF8FEA5D41C145E081D55FA614CE2000"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a unit of the National Fish Hatchery System; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H73F7AAF179DD4B4F98DBD62DBE78616A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other land or water managed by the Director of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, including any land or water managed cooperatively with any other Federal or State agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H81C2D72FE9BE43C4B45231B083C1557C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Actions</header> <subsection id="H29F14864BC9147C3876A815DE109410A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General, at the request of the Secretary, may bring in the district court of the United States of appropriate jurisdiction—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7713669FE7CC4FFD863FE5DA6F5263F3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a civil action against any individual or entity that—</text> <subparagraph id="HCF8F234ABDF74E979390B1066B06BEDF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>destroys, causes the loss of, or injures any system resource; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H80AEFEE2F0D14805A8810E956B4B7D0D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>causes the Secretary to carry out any action to prevent, minimize, or abate the destruction or loss of, or injury or risk to, any system resource; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF8659F83E16D456A9473959D27FE5AD9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an in rem action against any instrumentality (including a vessel, vehicle, aircraft, or other equipment or mechanism) that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9DAFC333952347A5AA9A7E60C0083D40"><enum>(A)</enum><text>destroys, causes the loss of, or injures any system resource; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD4D9EAE9A4DB4D9A85B23504207EF16C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>causes the Secretary to carry out any action to prevent, minimize, or abate destruction or loss of, or injury or risk to, a system resource.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBBD36BEF23084922A5BC1177789730EF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Affirmative defenses</header><text>It shall be an affirmative defense in an action under subsection (a) that—</text> <paragraph id="H6059A6288C14443A97D57C7AE16724F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the applicable destruction or loss of, or injury to, the system resource was caused by an otherwise legal act or omission that occurred outside of the boundaries of the system resource;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E7FF44FFE8B4EEBB67B1E0633A46CFE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the applicable destruction or loss of, or injury to, the system resource was caused by an activity performed in accordance with Federal, State, or local law, regulation, or court order;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB3627D183BD04344B8DC53D2A073489E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the applicable destruction or loss of, or injury to, the system resource was caused solely by an act of God or an act of war;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H533B607337A24B87BC1F16B58C8EB712"><enum>(4)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H18599D27B6F5401CA4AB68F700E3CABD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the applicable individual, entity, or instrumentality exercised due care; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H310E228068F74DB296CF02BD689107CB" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the applicable destruction or loss of, or injury to, the system resource was caused solely by an act or omission of a third party, other than an employee or agent of the individual, entity, or instrumentality; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3502819B9299491088F35327052D56A3"><enum>(5)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H2A5C338AE4B14C56B22C8B7110159C31"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the applicable destruction or loss of, or injury to, the system resource was caused by an individual, entity, or instrumentality, including an employee or agent of the individual, entity, or instrumentality, acting in physical self-defense or defense of others against physical harm; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F40759A8A8746E09A2B069B4A3A2F9F" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the physical defense was—</text> 
<clause id="HFF294D33C9D64FDF8155439D25B081F9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reasonably necessary;</text></clause> <clause id="HDB06D65D5B6A42EAB4E01904C53C3071"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>without reasonable alternative; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H494B20DD4DE14640B840F683532241B2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>not excessive under the circumstances.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H138F57D7651D4C458D2BF063C8215D9A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Damages</header><text>In an action under subsection (a), the court may award response costs and damages resulting from the applicable destruction or loss of, or injury to, the system resource.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0D65F3DF83984756BA847A9407CF0B2F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>De minimis threshold</header><text>The Secretary may not make a request to the Attorney General under subsection (a) if the amount that could be awarded under subsection (c) relating to the cause of action would not exceed $5,000.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA4CE8674EDED49D69E59ACB97805C02D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administrative actions for response costs and damages</header> <paragraph id="HAF7762EF0EDF474A86FC7969811A0A57"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Action by Secretary</header> <subparagraph id="H5AE93AC12E044E148CB2FC4F2D8728B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), the Secretary, after making a finding described in subparagraph (B), may consider, compromise, and settle a claim for response costs and damages if the claim has not been referred to the Attorney General under subsection (a).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1964175A60B9449AA621F47642787444"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Description of findings</header><text>A finding referred to in subparagraph (A) is a finding that—</text> <clause id="HF37777269BB04257AAE44B25AFF1FB96"><enum>(i)</enum><text>destruction or loss of, or injury to, a system resource has occurred; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDCE8B3930CB64ACAAA12C67BBD0CFDAB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that destruction, loss, or injury would occur absent an action by the Secretary to prevent, minimize, or abate the destruction, loss, or injury.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB9D35F9CA7674157A4214E1EDD54C30C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In any case in which the total amount to be recovered in an action under subsection (a) may exceed $500,000 (excluding interest), a claim may be compromised and settled under paragraph (1) only with the prior written approval of the Attorney General.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4AEFC580A61C403E8D786ADBC5EC92E9"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Response actions, assessments of damages, and injunctive relief</header> 
<paragraph id="H772E123CD32540FCAD4FD84CD823AAD0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may carry out any necessary action (including making a request to the Attorney General to seek injunctive relief)—</text> <subparagraph id="H7073C9C786A7400C9C4A52F258055E1B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to prevent, minimize, or abate the destruction or loss of, or injury to, a system resource; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7691C24CB3674E8FBE039DCB0CD1DA4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to abate or minimize the imminent risk of that destruction, loss, or injury.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67475CFC83CA42DC8A88BCCA02BC96BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assessment and monitoring</header> <subparagraph id="H102BEBF84AEA4A95AAD1698B20C79E9B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may assess and monitor the destruction or loss of, or injury to, any system resource for purposes of paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H544A96DCD7DF4ED58FE71122CA4BF7DE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Judicial review</header><text>Any determination or assessment of damage to a system resource carried out under subparagraph (A) shall be subject to judicial review under subchapter II of chapter 5, and chapter 7, of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Administrative Procedure Act</quote>), on the basis of the administrative record developed by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCF079B98B2E142A8B34D34440CD20CC0"><enum>(g)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Scope</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The liability established by this section shall be in addition to any other liability arising under Federal or State law.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H86FA55F3EA004EB5914CF0B5D86B6B16"><enum>4.</enum><header>Use of recovered amounts</header> 
<subsection id="H5029878111C040478C7098444F423D68"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts of the response costs and damages recovered by the Secretary under this Act and any amounts recovered by the Federal Government under any provision of Federal, State, or local law or otherwise as a result of the destruction or loss of, or injury to, any system resource shall be credited as discretionary offsetting collections to the Construction account of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service for use in accordance with subsection (b), and shall be made available for such purposes only to the extent and in the amounts provided in advance in appropriations Acts.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HAAE09AE8AC034DFD907F2FD46101F7CB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use</header><text>The Secretary may only use amounts made available under subsection (a)—</text> 
<paragraph id="H22A169FF4C674B56A5930AE3942E1892"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to reimburse expenditures incurred for—</text> <subparagraph id="H99C02832479141B59920F18A075C41F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>response costs;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF81B4F15E4A348668D9E71649D459574"><enum>(B)</enum><text>damage assessments;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD2772048FB6C46618345B29A0F6204B2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>remediation action planning costs; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H92F9010BCDDA4E16B344FF39B50AC1E4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other activities the Secretary determines to be necessary to respond to, assess, and remediate damages to a system resource;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H539F32C39B494D548993306DD9861AC1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to restore, replace, or acquire the equivalent of a system resource that was destroyed, lost, or injured; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3FDD1D0CAB6D4C6484CDBE39C365BEAA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to monitor and study the recovery of a system resource that was destroyed, lost, or injured.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBCFE6C194FB640BEA7AFC64A5F945FB9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Allocation</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2FF2B04C8D854317A2E5FF5E984C815A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>allocate for use under subsection (b) the amount of response costs and damages recovered with respect to each system resource and made available under subsection (a) to the unit, land, or water described in section 2(4) within which the system resource was located at the time of the destruction, loss, or injury; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4D5F5E36005849F283361E1F2D429B48"><enum>(2)</enum><text>after the allocation under paragraph (1), allocate any remaining amounts for such use under subsection (b) as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H7A3E0FC9014D442795F6D7E719AF4C78"><enum>5.</enum><header>Donations</header> 
<subsection id="HC7D4EE6990774C59B9CF711FF60E2759"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Acceptance of monetary donations and services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsection (b), the Secretary may accept donations of money or services to meet expected, immediate, or ongoing response costs and damages.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFDF8008621DC4C52A1E4A7CA6A6C3ECE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of monetary donations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts accepted under subsection (a) shall be credited as discretionary offsetting collections to the Construction account of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service for meeting such expected, immediate, or ongoing response costs and damages, and shall be made available for such purposes only to the extent and in the amounts provided in advance in appropriations Acts.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H266FFB9285D44426B0F4095D0CCE6322"><enum>6.</enum><header>Statutory Construction with Respect to Alaska</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any conflict arises between any provision of this Act and any provision of the Alaska National Interest Lands Conservation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3101">16 U.S.C. 3101 et seq.</external-xref>), then the provision in such Act shall control.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

