<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H05D3D3F9F6E34C14A41AB472C3FA686C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1211 IH: Student Loan Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1211</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230227">February 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the mass cancellation of student loans.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA593AC4121A44FA1A10143814B7758D5" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4ECE664FEF704FB4BDD0820914C593AA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Student Loan Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF68B076327874E789C9081770E1C2CE2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HCC67BD30E249444EBA951D9FBF2BB63C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Statutory authority has not been provided to the executive branch of the Federal Government to cancel student loans on a mass scale.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H255C20F1D8DC454498087F2C78A342E7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>It is unfair for taxpayers who paid student loans or did not attend college to pay for those who chose to take student loans. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H3101224296FB4626A0E382CA98C072B7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on mass cancellation of student loans</header> 
<subsection id="HE690207854D047AA88AB0D34CECCDBE8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header> 
<paragraph id="H3ACA60FFA91D4E0BAF7478223CBE6208"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Education, the Secretary of the Treasury, or the Attorney General shall not take any action to cancel or forgive the outstanding balances, or portion of balances, of covered loans, except as provided in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5FC71D3139A2406A9F69C0EA97FFBE7F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>The prohibition described in paragraph (1) shall not apply to targeted Federal student loan forgiveness, cancellation, or repayment programs carried out under the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>), under final regulations as in effect on March 12, 2020.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H32C0B2CC32BE435586610064404A72F3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered loan</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="HB60CB060852547EDA936DF93923AB9FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a loan made, insured, or guaranteed under part B, D, or E of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1071">20 U.S.C. 1071 et seq.</external-xref>; 1087a et seq.; 1087aa et seq.) before, on, or after the date of enactment of this Act; or </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEF3765FD4404435C903E6B4B1D7F6DC2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a loan under the Health Education Assistance Loan Program under title VII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/292">42 U.S.C. 292 et seq.</external-xref>) made before, on, or after the date of enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H57DDCB959CDD403AB122EFCBFE5B802F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Secretary of Education, the Secretary of the Treasury, or the Attorney General may not implement, or publish in any form, any regulation, or take any action, that modifies, alters, amends, cancels, discharges, forgives, or defers the repayment of any student debt not expressly permitted within statute or regulation as in effect on March 12, 2020, regarding covered loans, except to the extent that such regulation or action reflects the clear and unequivocal intent of Congress in legislation. </text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


