<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAF990AF3A22B483395DFDBEBDDAB7597" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4812 IH: Food for Thought Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4812</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to authorize the Secretary of Education to make grants to institutions of higher education to provide free meals to low-income students through existing on-campus meal programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD0993FD8759143AD9F1DD715FEB5A68F" style="OLC"><section id="H49AEB384E2614D7AB24F6EA2F34C64AB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Food for Thought Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H152BDEC6385B44B59C087E8A362DC51E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Free meals for low-income college students</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after subpart 7 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE55F309A10664AEE86F1895213DA1BB5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subpart id="H8AF2BD835C1A4F4BAC5777E66C8B806F"><enum>8</enum><header>Meals for low-Income students</header><section id="H0756FB3FF53F449A8C4FDAA0722E293D"><enum>420A.</enum><header>Free meals for low-income students</header><subsection id="HC2154802DEFE4CC4884B853E33CD537E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>From amounts made available under subsection (j), the Secretary is authorized to award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to provide free meals to low-income students through on-campus meal programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1C20CE4707604CF0874A363498AF471C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications</header><paragraph id="HD4B7A6ACFEF74D7DA9782F3C713E598C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity desiring to receive an award under subsection (a) shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. Such application shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H5433D112C1934853B1ED5F2FD285647C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a plan for identifying eligible students and conducting outreach; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H885E85650F654D8C8B5397906A56671D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assurance that the eligible entity will—</text><clause id="H8D71DCD0A6D84A1D98D45A3736661A33"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct outreach to students with respect to the grant program under this section, encourage student participation in such program, and inform students of—</text><subclause id="H1B4136C7B03340DE884037438EBB5918"><enum>(I)</enum><text>their potential eligibility for participation in other Federal, State, and local benefit and support programs, including means-tested Federal benefits programs such as SNAP; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H197D323E2ECD4DA48EC235D7701F5DE0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the processes for obtaining more information, confirming eligibility, and accessing benefits under such programs;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFEBB2FFAADFF4D83BC391D711D0A8163"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>evaluate institutional policies relating to the purchase of on-campus meal plans and whether such policies create barriers to enrollment and persistence for low-income students;</text></clause><clause id="H8E21BF4190DD4ECBABE73ABB3B11CAD7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identify ways to mitigate any institutional policies that are found, through the evaluation described in clause (ii), to create barriers described in such clause; and</text></clause><clause id="H7AB9D09F6BE54E1EA9328CEAD77E65FD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in the case of an eligible entity that is a consortia of eligible institutions of higher education that includes eligible institutions that do not have on-campus meal programs, provide an explanation with respect to how the eligible entity will ensure that low-income students attending such institutions will be able to easily access free meals provided under this section.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H268A62F84E464229B24CB71D5788EB0A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to—</text><subparagraph id="H20EF6791D839443483855E1077A91E44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an eligible entity that is an eligible institution of higher education that is—</text><clause id="HC0B28F1E4A724AA2B25180334F121B15"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a community college;</text></clause><clause id="H06B5133529D3455495BA252E0972CE9C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a minority-serving institution described in section 371(a); or</text></clause><clause id="H126EAF2C127C4DD8BAC97ADCED44F734"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>located in an area served by a local educational agency that is eligible for special assistance payments under section 11(a)(1) of the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1759a">42 U.S.C. 1759a(a)(1)</external-xref>); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H742D2904725949038DF76B9BCBDA3757"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an eligible entity that is a consortia of eligible institutions of higher education, in which at least 50 percent of such institutions meet at least 1 of the requirements under clauses (i) through (iii) of subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8602CB7763994D88BB3F2D732575B62F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mandatory activities</header><paragraph id="H25011A9A97CA47659B0BFDFE4A5C162E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use such grant funds to provide, through on-campus meal programs, not fewer than 1, and not more than 10, free meals per week to each low-income student selected by such entity to participate in the program under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D016F38845D4A08B8AFB35B4CA70F14"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting low-income students to participate in the program under this section, an eligible entity shall give priority to—</text><subparagraph id="H09DBE5056DC749EE99455EF2827A9528"><enum>(A)</enum><text>students with the greatest financial need; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE31C3685F5D44BA08BF56BA4DF4A551C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>students who indicate that they are experiencing food insecurity, housing insecurity, homelessness, or other insecurity with respect to basic needs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1D016BDD2D854171AD35533A8D4FBA20"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Permissible activities</header><text>In addition to the mandatory activities in subsection (c), an eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may use not more than 10 percent of such grant funds to—</text><paragraph id="H19E6DF20C2ED426B81E71D56AC08B0AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>facilitate the enrollment of on-campus vendors as authorized retailers in SNAP; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D73A3E86A9046ED92DBB92D19C0524D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support the operation of an on-campus food pantry; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H467A404942644B0996D3AFE428D02620"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">purchase food infrastructure equipment, including microwaves, refrigerators, and other such equipment determined by the Secretary to be necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2ABE6A82B85C4100BA521CA49099098D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>Not more than 5 percent of the grant funds provided to an eligible entity under this section for any fiscal year may be used for administrative purposes.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD165AD4A1E1C4A5A8D799E4E3836437D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Grant period</header><text>Grants awarded to eligible entities under this section shall be for a period of 5 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8D25897D658147F2AB6917F536FCFBF6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Campus meal program</header><text>Eligible entities receiving grants under this section may contract with third-party food service vendors to provide on-campus meals.</text></subsection><subsection id="H330E31DBDA5940678E7172CC10F87B2F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HFCF2F1DE466A4554A8FE750767159529"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Recipient reports</header><subparagraph id="HA55FC0F8F45948029A991A66E90E0C6C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>At the end of the 5-year grant period, an eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary a report on—</text><clause id="H554697B195FB4CBAA6059A4D9131198F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>how such entity used the grant funds, including the shares of such funds used for each of the activities described in subsections (c), (d)(1), and (d)(2); and</text></clause><clause id="H2BCDA4585DF44FE0A8E34CEBE8E3A727"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the success rates of students who participated in the grant program under this section (using benchmarks such as persistence, coursework completion, transfer, and completion rates).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H35A01EEED1E245C5BFC67C8053DB0789"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text>The information reported in subparagraph (A)(ii) shall be disaggregated, where possible, by—</text><clause id="H01536C6203214B8D9475E7E4F35C22B2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>race;</text></clause><clause id="H41EC2E837E1E40FFA793B2B6FD6FB364"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ethnicity;</text></clause><clause id="H96F81D999E8B4C10B5EB57DD317E6829"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Pell recipient status;</text></clause><clause id="HDC2F18CA5B194E04AEB398F673B88A80"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>income;</text></clause><clause id="H8AC267D5190040A9B96BA7A865B880E6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>gender; and</text></clause><clause id="H232C670B355849C5AEFC98B5221F6045"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>age.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D0A52BC22C245FDB0A3557EA26CB279"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary report</header><subparagraph id="H8B251AA222A448899329F316711C62A1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the Secretary receives the reports required under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit a report to Congress on the overall impact of the program under this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB88ED49D037842768FA5FB632E5650ED"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text>The information described in subparagraph (A) shall be disaggregated, where possible, by—</text><clause id="HAB7DCA621D0241AF97B5DDF859A16853"><enum>(i)</enum><text>sectors and types of institutions;</text></clause><clause id="H506A318A95204606B613AD5AC575BA9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether an institution is a minority-serving institution described in section 371(a); and</text></clause><clause id="HF435FF6975F740DEBC866F869488B0DC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>whether an institution has an open admissions policy.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H202D1C1C3F0B4F52AAF79A8D6F5691CA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that an eligible entity awarded a grant under this section should, to the extent practicable—</text><paragraph id="H76EE35804F5A46B3924ED0EAA36C2908"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure meals served pursuant to a grant under this section are consistent with the nutritional requirements and goals of the most recent Dietary Guidelines for Americans published under section 301 of the National Nutrition Monitoring and Related Research Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/5341">7 U.S.C. 5341</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H753A80083D0E47A8B352AD347C0EE093"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure access to vegetarian meals, vegan meals, culturally and religiously appropriate meals, and meals that accommodate common food allergies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EF2DAF04D7848F5BB77DCBC538BE93D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>build and encourage the use of on-campus food pantries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F23F386A0F346C7A6B52E16E82C69DC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>encourage on-campus vendors to increase the use of climate-friendly options; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B7B73080AC34535B9A29C317EC24DFA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>buy products to reduce the greenhouse gas emissions associated with providing free meals to students and purchasing food infrastructure equipment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3662DEBB022E405C80790ABC8D54503D"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary for fiscal year 2023 and each of the 5 succeeding fiscal years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0D6F9DB935054343BE2D3465BF3CE4C5"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HCAB6C411CE7C40B28344B34ECAED4478"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community college</header><text>The term <quote>community college</quote> means a public institution of higher education at which the highest degree that is predominantly awarded to students is an associate’s degree, including 2-year Tribal Colleges or Universities under section 316 and public 2-year institutions of higher education operated by a State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEACF35F164F42AB93D43A916DC1F872"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H09D9F80A76724EF4A0AE76531EEACCE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an eligible institution of higher education that has an on-campus meal program that is provided through an institutionally owned or operated food service or one or more third-party food service vendors; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC07F4706AD048A497B71B3933503931"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a consortia of eligible institutions of higher education, of which at least one has an on-campus meal program that is provided through an institutionally owned or operated food service or one or more third-party food service vendors, provided that such an eligible institution with an on-campus meal program is geographically accessible to the students of the eligible institutions that do not have on-campus meal programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5039008DA01B4AB4AACFB23FAAC47781"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible institution of higher education</header><text>The term <quote>eligible institution of higher education</quote> means an institution of higher education under section 101 or 102(a)(1)(B) in which at least 30 percent of the undergraduate students enrolled at such institution are eligible to receive a Federal Pell Grant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36173D7FA49F4732994112631E600C31"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Snap</header><text>The term <quote>SNAP</quote> means the supplemental nutrition assistance program (as defined in section 3(t) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2012">7 U.S.C. 2012(t)</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></subpart><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

