<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H52D8DA54171543D7B0D6898A2BEBB710" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6080 IH: Fixing Gaps in Hurricane Preparedness Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6080</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to carry out research and development to improve the understanding of how the public receives, interprets, and responds to and values hurricane forecasts and warnings, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H86DEC8A631D94C1B838BF9B94B2A8E64" style="OLC"><section id="H9DB1F37E3494403E9A3798A3E412E839" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fixing Gaps in Hurricane Preparedness Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBB11124AEB634C15BC8CB82D7E6C525F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Hurricane social, behavioral, and economic sciences</header><subsection id="H4DDC4D1441DC475083937570BEFC07A1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (in this section referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote>), in consultation with the Director of the National Science Foundation, shall carry out research and development to improve the understanding of how the public receives, interprets, and responds to and values hurricane forecasts and warnings.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA0337832BF2F408F842E9F3213DA6D45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Research and development</header><text>In conducting the research and development in accordance with subsection (a), the Administrator shall—</text><paragraph id="HBB27E38CA4154F6FA152D285F079718A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct a comprehensive review of what is known about how the public receives, interprets, and responds to and makes decisions regarding hurricane forecasts and warnings, including—</text><subparagraph id="H071F9A440FE54A279C883F753A428BF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how the connections between weather observations, downstream models, and processes affect the decision tools or products derived from such hurricane forecasts and warnings;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0EE53BEEBE0429E82387C38A43CE5C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how such hurricane forecasts and warnings generated by decision tools and products are used by emergency managers, governments, and other users to benefit the public and stakeholder groups;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C6D5EC3CD684F5FB0750C6F76498FBA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how past experiences with hurricanes impacts decision making;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA48D2B4EC984D2980E7E30D75FDD2F5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>how the source of such hurricane forecasts and warnings affects interpretation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC224FEEBD99E43969043AB15AFAD6F7E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>how tropical cyclone warnings and watches are received and interpreted;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15B06B9C7D904AA3A178E6F3EC0ACAB8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>how understanding of and response to such hurricane forecasts and warnings vary across demographic groups, including the elderly, people with disabilities, and other vulnerable populations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A797707772E48F8B286992D1A782084"><enum>(G)</enum><text>language barriers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25E7BE46C52C43BAACF1A6EEE8E784AC"><enum>(H)</enum><text>how understanding and response to such hurricane forecasts and warnings varies across geographic areas, including rural, urban, and suburban.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H87C16A98515046348ABEBC1E96E7FBF0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify data gaps based on the review conducted pursuant to paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA855467120274FF582C5ECF06C092B18"><enum>(3)</enum><text>taking into the account the data gaps identified pursuant to paragraph (2), carry out social and behavioral research, including data collection, to improve the understanding of how the public, including vulnerable populations, receive, interpret, and respond to hurricane forecasts and warnings and to inform evidence-based updates to existing hurricane forecasts and warnings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02C1E760E8784DE9929AACBE471BDAF5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>carry out research, including data collection, to evaluate and quantify the economic value of extending lead times of tropical cyclone warnings and watches, including to vulnerable populations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA4B7E2E65854587B468C03E64BE9534" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identify affected populations and gather data to conduct baseline assessments;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47B9EB5FA5DB4590897A99875AE23DDB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>conduct retrospective assessments of previous hurricane forecasts and warnings and improvements to better understand the key components of the value of the forecasts and warnings provided;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27E4156B004846B3A7E93339173A5198"><enum>(7)</enum><text>conduct ex ante assessments based on potential forecasts and warnings improvements and expected actions or behavior changes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF027B069BF844C76BFB65876B74D6B8C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>conduct cost benefit analysis of forecasts and warnings improvement alternatives;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23DDA827DBF14372A2E78D4B8464011E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>conduct risk assessments for pre-, during, and post-storm periods in regions and communities with significant elderly populations, including retirement communities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6D8001C1AD44A27AE918CC3C85310B5"><enum>(10)</enum><text>establish policies and procedures for the collection, archiving, and stewardship of data on community response, including the response of vulnerable populations, to high-impact tropical systems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6FE9D1B1C754C2B9EEB78D1D66B4C06"><enum>(11)</enum><text>integrate and consider research and development described in this subsection in the development or enhancement of hurricane products, information, and services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2CDFFCDE600411082F71270E0187CBD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Pilot study</header><paragraph id="H4A46FDABA9FE4BD38977714BEC6D92D8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days, the Administrator shall seek to enter into an agreement with an appropriate entity, as determined by the Administrator, to conduct a pilot study using a mixed methods approach, such as surveys, focus groups, and interviews, to gather information from hurricane prone population areas regarding their levels of preparedness for hurricanes. The surveys shall evaluate the following:</text><subparagraph id="HDB64FA7106DB46F7B3F9AAB4FA54182D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Possession of disaster supplies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF2D98333D10431A9B27A2919E8A376A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Evacuation decisions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51D8D295D96E4E00ADE36F79E00522B1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Levels of trust of tropical cyclone information from various sources.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDCE7F97070D4BD2916B8E1251F4C882"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Access to tropical cyclone warnings in a survey participant’s first language.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC75BDEB19D684D2FB992878F64A3E82C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Determination regarding a survey participant’s reasoning that may hinder the ability of such a participant to evacuate or willingness to evacuate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0AE505CDF7444B4D9214403ACE58F55C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Any additional information the Administrator determines necessary. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0146691C169F477FA64FDA8F6B896749"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The pilot study described in paragraph (1) shall define its methodology and be made publicly available on a website of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

