<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-HEY23655-JL3-2H-S25"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 3368 IH: Reimburse Veterans for Domiciliary Care Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date></dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3368</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action><action-date>May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to publish a rule to implement the requirement that the Secretary be permitted to waive the limitation in law on reimbursement of veterans receiving domiciliary care in State homes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5A02660486824D509CFD7D498FCB6DA2"><section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reimburse Veterans for Domiciliary Care Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id5c42e43b0eb74365ab2cfab9df7a5920"><enum>2.</enum><header>Publication of rule for waiver on limitation of payments to State homes for domiciliary care provided to veterans</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="id73c05df02ad14925892c44bcb44be71b"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Proposed rule</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall prescribe and publish in the Federal Register a proposed rule implementing the requirement under section 3007(a) of the Johnny Isakson and David P. Roe, M.D. Veterans Health Care and Benefits Improvement Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/315">Public Law 116–315</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/1741">38 U.S.C. 1741</external-xref> note).</text></subsection><subsection id="idc61c26084593413caf87b40f982e5030"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Final rule</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the publication of the initial rule required under subsection (a), or the date that is 260 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, whichever occurs first, the Secretary shall prescribe and publish in the Federal Register a final rule implementing the requirement specified in such subsection.</text></subsection><subsection id="id0ca34a2639b04e3f8adc87f2858582bd"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Retroactive payments</header><text>In prescribing the proposed rule under subsection (a) and the final rule under subsection (b), the Secretary shall ensure that the authority of the Secretary to provide payments to State homes (as defined in section 101(19) of title 38, United States Code) pursuant to any such rule is retroactive to January 5, 2021.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

