<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H68A52873D7D74E62B845A8F5A4E1351E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 983 IH: Second Chance at Life Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 983</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230210">February 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000459">Mr. Fleischmann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000298">Mr. Estes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001082">Mr. Hern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure that a woman seeking a chemical abortion is informed that it may be possible to reverse the intended effects of the abortion if the woman changes her mind, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HABC560D43F2D4CC6A82A74B986C46772" style="OLC"><section id="HEACF539E92FE441DA399EFB3C3BFA0C2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Second Chance at Life Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HEEA62B67836549A89B9FA8C1A6844D50"><enum>2.</enum><header>Abortion pill reversal informed consent</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/201">42 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H4D11982FAB4D48D2A8486353AD8FFC68" style="OLC"><title id="H08B39FABB4A34C66B597F2EFDEEBD1CE"><enum>XXXIV</enum><header>Abortion pill reversal informed consent</header><section id="H43E354267A774A7BA216EF8055F319E1"><enum>3401.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title:</text><paragraph id="HD822CE74A5A140A8A2837A88F99FE37F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Abortion provider</header><text>The term <term>abortion provider</term> means any person licensed to perform a chemical abortion under applicable Federal and State laws.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A28FA1A32BB496DAD6795F9EC93FCFB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chemical abortion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>chemical abortion</term> means the use or prescription of an abortion-inducing drug dispensed with the intent to cause the death of the unborn child.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C89006BAF1543A5A58A575156B351B1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Unborn child</header><text>The term <term>unborn child</term> means a member of the species homo sapiens, at any stage of development prior to birth.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HA80DC4E850C94400BD93011F8CA31453"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Woman</header><text>The term <term>woman</term> means a female human being whether or not she has reached the age of majority.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H513F3C7C95F74C79BA92ECE1E6800D44"><enum>3402.</enum><header>Abortion pill reversal informed consent</header><subsection id="HD34F045EF2444E0791DD67357D189EAC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement of compliance by providers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective 30 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Second Chance at Life Act of 2023</short-title>, any abortion provider in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, who knowingly performs any chemical abortion, shall comply with the requirements of this title.</text></subsection><subsection id="H499649BF472D4181A0F5E6267177DE87"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Informed consent</header><text>Except in the case of a medical emergency described in section 3403, a chemical abortion involving the two drug process of dispensing mifepristone first and then misoprostol shall not be performed or induced or attempted to be performed or induced without the following:</text><paragraph id="H69911A92D362490A8B5AF558B014DACF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The woman is informed, by telephone or in person, by the physician who is to perform the chemical abortion, by a referring physician, or by an agent of either physician at least 24 hours before the chemical abortion, that—</text><subparagraph id="HFE6C25B61F074C02B3ED7A6072292CE0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">it may be possible to reverse the intended effects of a mifepristone-induced chemical abortion if the woman changes her mind but that time is of the essence; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H601284A877274B9E9C1D24AEBCBD33F6"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information on and assistance with reversing the effects of a mifepristone-induced chemical abortion is available on the website of the Department of Health and Human Services required by section 3405(b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5143C5E580F64168A89D5378A61D4309"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the first drug involved in the two drug process is dispensed in a mifepristone-induced chemical abortion, the physician shall provide written medical discharge instructions to the pregnant woman which must include the statement:</text><quoted-block id="HAFD65B0DFE2649C0A1545C8A3D34A360" style="OLC"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Recent developing research has indicated that mifepristone alone is not always effective in ending a pregnancy. It may be possible to avoid, cease, or even to reverse the intended effects of a mifepristone-induced chemical abortion if the second pill has not been taken. Please consult with a health care professional immediately.</text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1D29D0D2D4974222B270F167CF66B57D"><enum>3403.</enum><header>Exception for medical emergencies</header><subsection id="HA49BE339115F4456B286324431E7ACE7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provisions of section 3402 shall not apply in the case where a woman suffers from a physical disorder, physical injury, or physical illness that would, as certified by a physician, place the woman in danger of death unless an abortion is performed, including a life-endangering physical condition caused by or arising from the pregnancy itself.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2C0F5F36A75D4C61A22BCA8841171AE6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Upon a determination by an abortion provider under subsection (a) that an abortion is necessary to save the life of a mother, such provider shall include in the medical file of the pregnant woman a truthful and accurate certification of the specific medical circumstances that support such determination.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD53BC2EBE59C4D76B128971AB05343ED"><enum>3404.</enum><header>Sign posting</header><subsection id="HB2FB46D70E5B430ABA1D5955BE037B69"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Posting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any private office, freestanding surgical outpatient clinic or other facility, or clinic in which chemical abortions, other than abortions necessary in the case of a medical emergency described in section 3403, are performed shall conspicuously post a sign (in a location as described in subsection (c) so as to be clearly visible to patients) which reads:</text><quoted-block id="HF321BE4F7D6446F4886296E6FAA3E112" style="OLC"><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Research has indicated that mifepristone alone is not always effective in ending a pregnancy and that its effects can be blocked or reversed if the second pill has not yet been taken. If you change your mind prior to taking the second pill and desire to attempt to save your pregnancy, consult with a health care professional immediately.</text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HD83FB90BA578450DAD5FE94A166707D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Lettering; size</header><text>The sign required by subsection (a) shall be printed with lettering that is—</text><paragraph id="HC47E02154F7C46DD8CC026C4C37F9487"><enum>(1)</enum><text>legible; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B3DE1180E7B439FAA3C5C3C4D9B4BAA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>at least three quarters of an inch boldfaced type.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H31219E3D40C64E74A3A1DE8F2AB1A733"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Locations</header><text>A facility in which chemical abortions are performed that is a private office or a freestanding surgical outpatient clinic shall post the sign required by subsection (a) in each patient waiting room and patient consultation room used by patients on whom chemical abortions are performed. A hospital or any other facility in which chemical abortions are performed that is not a private office or freestanding surgical outpatient clinic shall post the required sign in each patient admission area used by patients on whom chemical abortions are performed.</text></subsection></section><section id="H7D2D9C2C2A1A458CAE2741A260AC2090"><enum>3405.</enum><header>Printed information and website</header><subsection id="H508658E099CA4951827E586766C42CF8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall publish, in English and in each language which is the primary language of 2 percent or more of the population of any State, and shall cause to be available on the website required by subsection (b), the following printed materials in such a way as to ensure that the information is easily comprehensible:</text><paragraph id="H1737910D2D414526BD64D92F97B0EBF3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Materials designed to inform the woman of the possibility of reversing the effects of a chemical abortion utilizing mifepristone if she changes her mind.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DE0D091696448CDABE7B2BE2AA93FC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Materials on the assistance and resources that may be available to help reverse the effects of a chemical abortion.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H35B8E19922D5468C8EBC7163F0330113"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Website</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Second Chance at Life Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall develop and maintain a website to provide the information described in subsection (a) in accordance with the following:</text><paragraph id="HECF5A016895343F5A303610B3309ED7B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>No information regarding who uses the website shall be collected or maintained.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BB905821B9240C6A56618EDA44329A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary shall monitor on a regular basis the website to prevent and correct tampering.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E825E8D92A4443089715DF001D65BD9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The website shall be maintained at a minimum resolution of 70 DPI (dots per inch).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC18D6FBD84B481FB34CEEF95EE87253"><enum>(4)</enum><text>All pictures appearing on the website shall be a minimum of 200x300 pixels.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB144123F19784295ABFD7610C93D20CA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>All letters on the website shall be a minimum of 12 point font.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00F685A8CCD04FF2BD8F5AB79CBC20B9"><enum>(6)</enum><text>All information and pictures on the website shall be accessible with an industry standard browser, requiring no additional plug-ins.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H0FB9831990BD498AAE676DFB31625C79"><enum>3406.</enum><header>Civil remedies</header><subsection commented="no" id="HBD29B303BE1941D2A7AD51DE188AD5EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Civil suits for violation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), any of the following parties may bring a civil action before the appropriate Federal district court for actual and punitive damages against an abortion provider who knowingly or recklessly performed or attempted to perform a chemical abortion in violation of this title:</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H57A06E75A7A8429981A8428A8EDD9E29"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A person upon whom such a chemical abortion has been performed or attempted.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H715C3D5AB18F4D5181FC1F58514E7574"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A father of an unborn child who is the subject of such a chemical abortion.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HDF7AF847E8F947BB96A406E2922249A9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A parent of a person upon whom such a chemical abortion has been performed or attempted if such person had not attained 18 years of age at the time of such abortion or if such person died as the result of such abortion.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF100C20B39AD41EC9ACCDEBD524FB1B9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Barring suit</header><text>A plaintiff may not bring a civil action under subsection (a) if a chemical abortion is performed or attempted with respect to a pregnancy that is the result of the plaintiff’s criminal conduct.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H9844096D19AB430990EC9A7F7FC3BD40"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Attorney’s fee</header><text>If a party described in paragraph (1), (2), or (3) of subsection (a) is the prevailing party in an action under this section, the court shall award a reasonable attorney’s fee to such party. If a defendant is the prevailing party in an action under this section, and the court finds that such action was frivolous or brought in bad faith, the court shall award a reasonable attorney’s fee to the defendant.</text></subsection></section></title><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H3163D87639D9427BB6628619386298E4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Preemption</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act or the amendment made by this Act shall be construed to preempt any provision of State law to the extent that such State law establishes, implements, or continues in effect disclosure requirements regarding abortion or penalties for failure to comply with such requirements that are more extensive than those provided under the amendment made by this Act.</text></section><section id="HA7B8242507024DA0811D111CDDFB32B8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, or any application thereof, is found to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act and any application thereof shall not be affected by such finding.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

