<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H821F7DCE2A0D4911AB74AD688C2F0C44" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4543 IH: American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Timely Reporting of Election Results Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4543</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to establish certain requirements for the timely processing and reporting of results with respect to a District of Columbia election, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HA6F3DE2D33F8409FBCE730DA77A2EDDD" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1B11101E6C2049E5BC1BB4E35D48FA96" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Timely Reporting of Election Results Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HFA1FE80F5501430AA1DD1F973BC93906" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirements for processing and reporting results with respect to District of Columbia elections</header> <subsection id="H4BA909E4B08C42D58651BF29119CE557"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H82FBFBB9437749929249E4789B563044"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 304 and 305 as sections 305 and 306, respectively; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2761C25B4A4149CDA43C943F70D58410"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 303 the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD8B37328B22F4BE9A800D9CFB1BDD1EF" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H6A6BDABEFC084E9E9648B1A1C6343DDF"><enum>304.</enum><header>Timely processing and reporting of results with respect to a District of Columbia election</header> 
<subsection id="H117700FA0B5F4E77A0142426476FDDAD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Time for processing ballots and reporting results</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The District of Columbia shall begin processing ballots received by mail in a District of Columbia election as soon as such ballots are received and shall ensure to the greatest extent practicable that the results of such District of Columbia election are reported to the public not later than 10:00 am on the date following the date of the election, but in no case shall such ballots be tabulated or such results be reported earlier than the closing of polls on the date of the election.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H972799B78A7448FC875D7927382E3A61"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement To publish number of voted ballots on election day</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The District of Columbia shall, as soon as practicable after the closing of polls on the date of a District of Columbia election, make available on a publicly accessible website the total number of voted ballots in the possession of election officials in the District of Columbia as of the time of the closing of polls on the date of such election, which shall include, as of such time—</text> 
<paragraph id="HB66825B9FA754FC89E0A72C04808633A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of voted ballots delivered by mail;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5791A84C3F014E88AF5EC4178019678B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of ballots requested for such election by individuals who are entitled to vote by absentee ballot under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20301">52 U.S.C. 20301 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC794BA094EB247BEA072666B4BC0F497"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of voted ballots for such election received from individuals who are entitled to vote by absentee ballot under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20301">52 U.S.C. 20301 et seq.</external-xref>), including from individuals who, under such Act, voted by absentee ballot without requesting such a ballot. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2F8414D7E984466BA076429B47248854"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements To ensure bipartisan election administration activity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a District of Columbia election, District of Columbia election officials shall ensure that all activities are carried out in a bipartisan manner, which shall include a requirement that, in the case of an election worker who enters a room which contains ballots, voting equipment, or non-voting equipment as any part of the election worker’s duties to carry out such election, the election worker is accompanied by an individual registered to vote with respect to a different political party than such election worker, as determined pursuant to the voting registration records of the District of Columbia. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H720AC8E39C134D438A3778DFB553EC3A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>District of Columbia election defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>District of Columbia election</term> means any election for public office in the District of Columbia, including an election for Federal office, and any ballot initiative or referendum. </text></subsection> </section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0F95942F4A71466081B38818CAD2D885"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>303, and 304</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0837B8D3E36F412097120031988A64EA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H9161DD4AFC594E9AB24F274373630B5E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the items relating to sections 304 and 305 as relating to sections 305 and 306, respectively; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC05315A267B64C21BC481DBBE5AB30A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 303 the following new item:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H049A7277854047CF9C9C848B4C98B18D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">Sec. 304. Timely processing and reporting of results with respect to a District of Columbia election.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

