<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE8AED0F66C9D4F2E90FDDE097C439FC0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1127 IH: United States-Taiwan Advanced Research Partnership Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1127</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To allow for cooperative research activities between the Department of Homeland Security and Taiwan to strengthen preparedness against cyber threats and enhance capabilities in cybersecurity, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H296088AF34E547B6B2F631988E764188" style="OLC">
<section id="HA1A3A9394043439DB5C6D8B01B99080B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>United States-Taiwan Advanced Research Partnership Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4A01D9673F504B72971A720BDB31CBBB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Cooperative Homeland Security research and antiterrorism programs relating to cybersecurity</header> <subsection id="H7956F755064D464CACDFD207192755A0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of the international cooperative activities authorized under section 317 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/195c">6 U.S.C. 195c</external-xref>), the Under Secretary for Science and Technology of the Department of Homeland Security, in coordination with the Secretary of State and other appropriate Federal officials, may enter into cooperative research activities with Taiwan to strengthen preparedness against cyber threats and enhance capabilities in cybersecurity.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H0E6058B4FB564CD78083714D2C698087"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this section, the Under Secretary for Science and Technology of the Department of Homeland Security shall submit to Congress a report consisting of a status update on the progress of forming, executing, or implementing agreements with Taiwan for cooperative activities to strengthen preparedness against cyber threats and enhance capabilities in cybersecurity. Such report shall also detail any administrative, legal, or diplomatic challenges or resource constraints relating to such agreements or activities, as the case may be.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8D0D56A99AC0450E92C369B983A5B08B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No additional funds are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


