<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5D6BF90EEFFE4FEA9052F4149ECE5939" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4674 IH: Advanced Nuclear Feasibility Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4674</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230717">July 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a competitive grant program to fund feasibility studies for advanced nuclear reactors, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB4724833B9F547358BF3EB378AB394F3" style="OLC"><section id="H7BA0C7D2CCB44A309FF03C86F7D958A8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advanced Nuclear Feasibility Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HAC0CD292BD654F8C88264948D6B025DF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that Congress—</text><paragraph id="H780B1A038F01454EBA6B9D77DD4E7501"><enum>(1)</enum><text>recognizes the importance of developing, licensing, and deploying innovative nuclear energy technology, such as advanced nuclear reactors;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14C6B0DEE0694EFCB9A8122AB9EBFBE8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>acknowledges the vast deployment potential of advanced nuclear technology over the next several decades;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD79C1F27C104729851017ECC426970F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>understands the immensely beneficial impact of building and deploying advanced nuclear reactors; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8052FF5550664EE4B0675828E4268F33"><enum>(4)</enum><text>seeks to provide Federal support in promoting the use of nuclear energy throughout the United States.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H826D58B35671473684538F3A30000C57" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Advanced nuclear reactor feasibility study grant program</header><subsection id="H9E6D8078097F40A8B6C1B4038455948D" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a program to award grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities to conduct feasibility studies for the siting, construction, and operation of advanced nuclear reactors. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC3F3E8BED82C4159B2F4058F0ABDC868" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><paragraph id="HF039EA3FBFA846A2A0FC38E8EB61B59F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under the program, an applicant shall be—</text><subparagraph id="H2B4165BB713D4ADDBD704C30D16E329A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an institution of higher education located in a State or territory described in paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7F5303866344C2D9E05B5C6F3361407" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a private individual or company, including the owner or operator of an airport, port, or hospital, located in a State or territory described in paragraph (2); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CAF7527EC724BDCBBF411BDA80674CE" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a State or local government of a State or territory described in paragraph (2), including a State or local government that owns or operates an airport, port, or hospital.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2281F488BAB847FCA7160381BCFAD8B0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>States and territories</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State or territory described in this paragraph is a State, or territory of the United States, that has in effect a plan relating to advancing the deployment of advanced nuclear reactors, as the Secretary determines appropriate. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HED3BB4F4E3414F7FAE8A08F0389A0D6D" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph id="HE4DC020E475948079EBC9B01BE713DAA" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under the program, an eligible entity shall submit an application to the Secretary, not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including, at a minimum, information described in paragraph (2)(A).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AFB7B3EBB464F81B6401E2EBDA16C6F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information</header><text>An application under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="HD1D9C339C44B4197B97C5A936EFEEC6C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall include a description of—</text><clause id="H432B41E7D44849C4BF64FDA159A5A7FE" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the background for the feasibility study that is to be conducted for the siting, construction, and operation of an advanced nuclear reactor; and</text></clause><clause id="H062DBE1A224D4FD28E1605E842C6261B" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>organizational responsibilities for conducting such feasibility study; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02836EBBCB1E4EDBAEE94DE169B41F88" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include—</text><clause id="H5454ABE80A984E1F9E7F74AE54A97C89" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a plan for conducting such feasibility study, including a plan—</text><subclause id="H100AC6017B5041B688ACFD6239A2003C" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to conduct an analysis of—</text><item id="H9B037BD448414F46A98DB1D4A6165744" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the demand for electricity in the region of the proposed site of the advanced nuclear reactor and supporting facilities; </text></item><item id="H09C76324257146AAA3C026C6956718FF" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the transmission capacity and transmission facilities and systems in such region; and</text></item><item id="H8F5EF5FF84734ECD8109EE0856A69258" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the structure of the market for electricity in such region;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H2584E3BEDD7248C7B3A67DD0EC27BC9A" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to conduct an analysis of how the construction and operation of the advanced nuclear reactor at such proposed site would impact—</text><item id="HFCA1D6B6082147E3B502476D524CEA1A" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the overall demand for electricity in such region;</text></item><item id="HF65EC05009FA44C0ADC516A65B0FFD83" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the transmission capacity and transmission facilities and systems in such region; and</text></item><item id="H714F271E1F254DFA87A70FAB3A3A75BF" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the market for electricity in such region;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HBDF00BA99B524150967250A591340D65" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to conduct an analysis regarding the proposed site of the advanced nuclear reactor and supporting facilities, including preliminary site layout and site preparation and potential effects of the advanced nuclear reactor and supporting facilities on the applicable region, including population distribution and the current uses of land and water;</text></subclause><subclause id="HDC715A555C684FB59FA8559FED25703A" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to conduct an analysis of the environmental impacts of siting, construction, and operation of the advanced nuclear reactor at the proposed site, including—</text><item id="H2777D36924AA4BEAA2C9B48C67B2F794" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a comparison of the environmental impacts of siting, constructing, and operating the advanced nuclear reactor at such proposed site to siting, constructing, and operating the advanced nuclear reactor at other sites with similar characteristics in the applicable region;</text></item><item id="H92EF9A379144413382CE4D22D7B67E07" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>impacts on cooling water demand; and </text></item><item id="HA21320319D1742F9A09A6F04773527C0" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>an overview of the environmental protection requirements in the applicable region;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HEBA822024D264CF39D14912978FEAA81" commented="no"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for how to approach the licensing process and authorization requirements for the siting, construction, and operation of the advanced nuclear reactor; </text></subclause><subclause id="H6F3CA21E2B694AF7BC8A3FEE4EF08CAF" commented="no"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>to conduct an analysis of how the applicable project to site, construct, and operate the advanced nuclear reactor would be implemented, including analysis of potential contractual approaches, procurement plans, project schedules, project management, and risk management plans;</text></subclause><subclause id="H902221B1ECFD40A391F796A13BB389F2" commented="no"><enum>(VII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to conduct an analysis of organizational requirements and responsibilities for each phase of the applicable project to site, construct, and operate the advanced nuclear reactor, including requirements and responsibilities relating to human resources and training, including workforce logistics and staffing requirements for construction, commissioning, operation, and maintenance of the advanced nuclear reactor, including education and other training requirements; </text></subclause><subclause id="H0512F939FD234959A8AAC5E913E381C9" commented="no"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to conduct an analysis of the economic feasibility of the applicable project to site, construct, and operate the advanced nuclear reactor, including a cost-benefit analysis; </text></subclause><subclause id="H8B6D4AB4FD2142F7BC071494984077B1" commented="no"><enum>(IX)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for developing plans for emergency preparedness and coordination for the proposed site of the advanced nuclear reactor and supporting facilities, including on-site emergency planning and coordination with off-site emergency response organizations;</text></subclause><subclause id="H58C9D6D17352436AB20CEF77D113A588" commented="no"><enum>(X)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to conduct an analysis of cogeneration opportunities on the proposed site of the advanced nuclear reactor and supporting facilities; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HABD363F836134BBF9F1A5946CF681F48" commented="no"><enum>(XI)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to conduct a decommissioning analysis for the advanced nuclear reactor, including the cost of decommissioning the advanced nuclear reactor, decommissioning phases for the advanced nuclear reactor, and the environmental impact of decommissioning the advanced nuclear reactor; and </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB86C9C2E159D4ABB9E95C4A6EEF4A942" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the stakeholders that may be involved in the applicable project to site, construct, and operate the advanced nuclear reactor.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H63C8621E9F434BCA9FE81B30CF2054BE" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Distribution</header><paragraph id="HBB5D83E2898D46CCACEB36B8975E22B6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Announcement</header><text>Not later than 270 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall announce on the website of the Department of Energy each eligible entity selected to receive a grant under the program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5E399FEE4A64A96B59AAD2B9DE5FEFD" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Geographic distribution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under the program, the Secretary shall, to the extent practicable, award a grant to at least—</text><subparagraph id="HEE393746B3F04BCBA90FC1269C92EAF6" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>one eligible entity in each State described in subsection (b)(2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H964DDB26923849A0B3CC947BBFB7E110" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>one eligible entity in a territory described in subsection (b)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD63CA5C8433049C394E51FAEBA5FB615" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations and priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under the program, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H904354990A1945F4B7FE08DE674E40FE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">take into consideration the totality and thoroughness of the information included in the application from an eligible entity, including information described in subsection (c)(2)(B)(i) regarding a plan for conducting a feasibility study; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA199E91F7CD5497B95553464B463FE43" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>give priority to an eligible entity that certifies that the eligible entity will, after the competition of the feasibility study for which a grant is awarded, commence, if appropriate, other pre-licensing application activities for the applicable advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB47B5E471B62491D8755F96F43C9BEE4" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Feasibility study report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the selection of the eligible entities to be awarded grants under the program, the Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that describes—</text><paragraph id="HA187A9A859FC441A891B274CF190B8F1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the eligible entities that were selected;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E24320AF89042BAA4E0A29FAB07962C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the reasoning for selection of such eligible entities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AA5D7309FA0478C95966570DC663C95" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a summary of each feasibility study to be conducted using a grant awarded under the program, including the amount requested for the feasibility study;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A195C4B31D247FC90AEBA69F924D1EF" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an anticipated timeline for each resulting feasibility study; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F1B8804DAD44A35AC4676997D555A6E" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>any other information the Secretary determines necessary.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB742F9C0AE31499988891F6E8C11D1AE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Use of existing feasibility studies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary and the Nuclear Regulatory Commission shall jointly establish a process under which a feasibility study conducted pursuant to the program may, in whole or in part, be utilized for purposes of a feasibility study for the siting, construction, and operation of an advanced nuclear reactor at a different site, with similar characteristics, in the applicable region.</text></section><section id="HD6F818620CD8454B8443B299EA356C84"><enum>6.</enum><header>Cost share</header><subsection id="H2699DE95AF174A18AB65AC9425200C35"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The non-Federal cost share of feasibility study conducted pursuant to this Act shall be 60 percent. </text></subsection><subsection id="H57A4F2580D2E472BB80919BDC53FA154"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reduction of non-Federal share</header><text>The Secretary may reduce the non-Federal share required under paragraph (1), if the Secretary determines the reduction to be necessary and appropriate, taking into consideration—</text><paragraph id="HBD466229494B4D058D79A5F4730C975A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>whether the proposed site of the advanced nuclear reactor and supporting facilities is at the site of a fossil fuel-fired electric generating facility that is retired or planned to be retired within the next year;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0A1D64007E045F7A0ED00DF5A56497B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whether the applicable eligible entity has participated in community engagement with the applicable communities to discuss the potential siting of an advanced nuclear reactor and supporting facilities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9688275C0D574D938C59786961765490"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the socioeconomic impacts that the siting, construction, and operation of the advanced nuclear reactor at the proposed site would have on the surrounding communities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H76D2E190AE2040FB942C044A7AFDB187"><enum>7.</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 134 of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7434">42 U.S.C. 7434</external-xref>), unobligated balances of amounts made available under such section 134 may be used to carry out this Act, to remain available until September 30, 2025.</text></section><section id="HDA3966F274C247C5828044A227902682"><enum>8.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HB3BBB420F8F2413CA39CB747905FC605" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Advanced nuclear reactor</header><text>The term <term>advanced nuclear reactor</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Nuclear Energy Innovation and Modernization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2215">42 U.S.C. 2215</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13070BCB5648453597E650A661A153E0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HE8FE0E16B6DB43729CAB72F93615A7B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Commerce, and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology, of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92D9E6D081EB4450A2CEA6CE20F7D920"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, and the Committee on Environment and Public Works, of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H68CB397BA815487EB223F63350F4E0DB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an individual or entity described in section 3(b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2996DDA4EB6F4D9E8B0971E37578B86D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8C1AB2C7D6B4A998CAC7889EA18F619"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>program</term> means the program established under section 3(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02F5854FAC1A4C11988A152E9C0C96A6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6ED37E4178D9404FB00F8352BDA0C583" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the 50 States and the District of Columbia.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

