<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD222EDC568594A14BD97B893C33D0BD1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4581 IH: Maternal and Child Health Stillbirth Prevention Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4581</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230712">July 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title V of the Social Security Act to support stillbirth prevention and research, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H29AC04AFC4F640FFB792659B85F8FD3A" style="OLC"><section id="H5350F20ACCE5407EAE96ACC8954664E0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Maternal and Child Health Stillbirth Prevention Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDC19CE95A4C74CBE9869DD52D1CBCF3A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HAA3C86FF68C043A5964AE9BCC05A42A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention—</text><subparagraph id="HE84E9E56897A45BC95A8D1E3574732C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the United States, 1 in 175 births are affected by stillbirth each year amounting to approximately 21,000 stillbirths annually;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D1AC4F1CBC94A248413E1684D42D4B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">of the 20,854 reported stillbirths in 2020, over 5,000 were experienced by Black mothers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B9A211B058F413CA9A894B64983F927"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of stillbirths each year is greater than the number of babies that die during the first year of life;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58F85A9A6A4242D3B5086216E12B40B0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>annual stillbirths are more than ten times the number of annual deaths due to Sudden Infant Death Syndrome (SIDS);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H608E090C9DC5478EBB87EEF9BB5A3CCC"><enum>(E)</enum><text>stillbirth occurs across all demographics and in otherwise healthy pregnancies. It is most common, however, among women who—</text><clause id="H86716EC4DA5A4C5FAD03DBD607BACAF8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>are Black or African American, at two times more likely than White women to have a stillbirth;</text></clause><clause id="HF6AED52CA361463E998EA9EE02F77D5E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are of lower socioeconomic status;</text></clause><clause id="HA377A86BAE444887AFEC820AB25176B8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>are diagnosed with high blood pressure, diabetes, obesity, or other medical conditions;</text></clause><clause id="H0CF67800443A49BCB40AFEE4B4EF762B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>are 35 years of age or older;</text></clause><clause id="H11D4273B93104084B8416DA5F6FAD510"><enum>(v)</enum><text>smoke cigarettes while pregnant;</text></clause><clause id="H81285994CEBC4648B4F83421C59755C9"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have previously experienced pregnancy loss; or</text></clause><clause id="HAFD2B63981E04BE48D8D7D47CFE450D7"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>have multiple pregnancies, for example triplets; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3597A23199774FD3BF100A0D059529C7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>while the rate of stillbirth has declined since the 1940s due to improvements in maternity care, in recent years, the decline has slowed or halted. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B32EAD8F90244A39788393CAA225571"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to a study by researcher Wall-Wieler et al., published in Obstetrics and Gynecology, <quote>the risk of severe maternal morbidity among stillbirth deliveries was more than fourfold higher compared with live birth deliveries</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3119A1F14EA4A528E96BF2BFE948660"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to a study by researcher McClure et al., published in the International Journal of Gynecology and Obstetrics, <quote>stillbirth was significantly associated with maternal mortality</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC14AA55D0B83447E9468A82DD141373A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to a review article by Murphy and Cacciatore, published in Seminars in Fetal &amp; Neonatal Medicine, stillbirth has psychological impacts on parents like grief, shame, and guilt and impacts to family functioning and well-being. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5971C34A66944F6985CF1EC4ED1BB15E"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Stillbirth, and the disparity in those impacted by stillbirth requires further research, support, and prevention programming.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC6C0C0E760D94B668CAB10E9D580B33C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Clarification supporting permissible use of funds for stillbirth prevention activities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 501(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/701">42 U.S.C. 701(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC6CFD20B2E554A09A7812FE942513699"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(B), by inserting <quote>to reduce the incidence of stillbirth,</quote> after <quote>among children,</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0246C2E4E9F24DD08407BEB5A2E33B23" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting after <quote>follow-up services</quote> the following: <quote>, and for evidence-based programs and activities and outcome research to reduce the incidence of stillbirth (including tracking and awareness of fetal movements, improvement of birth timing for pregnancies with risk factors, initiatives that encourage safe sleeping positions during pregnancy, screening and surveillance for fetal growth restriction, efforts to achieve smoking cessation during pregnancy, community-based programs that provide home visits or other types of support, and any other research or evidence-based programming to prevent stillbirths)</quote>. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

