<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3D900E42526E4249B0F2B5292FC2D387" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4419 IH: PHEMCE Advisory Committee Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4419</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act with respect to the Public Health Emergency Medical Countermeasures Enterprise, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H86E85FB0AD7549418100A0D5CCFE43E8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDBB458F2A5F14DBBB8C6951C415504E0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>PHEMCE Advisory Committee Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H2511F408EC82497D9D78B65EA53EFF60"><enum>2.</enum><header>Public Health Emergency Medical Countermeasures Enterprise</header> <subsection id="HC2BAF308C2D24BDC964EF9AE75244324"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Members</header><text>Section 2811–1(b) of the Public Health Service Act (42 U.S.C. 30hh–10a(b)) is amended by striking paragraph (11) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB296F224102F4AD88EAA36E313105563" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H9869063C43054BC284DB2BDD578197E1"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Biomedical Advanced Research and Development Authority.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99C59EDE3784457783009989A69779DC"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Strategic National Stockpile.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H78B1FBF8778B4ED583534494BDE83F27"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Representatives of any other Federal agency, which may include the Director of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases and the Director of the Office of Public Health Preparedness and Response, as the Secretary determines appropriate. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H29651677EE6D478A969BB84EEE416FCA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Functions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2811–1(c)(2) of the Public Health Service Act (42 U.S.C. 30hh–10a(c)(2)) is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB0AE5BFB440B44D496FE1F8169DFFF4E" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H57ADF8D69D2D4E78977D7B2CAE718567"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Input</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the PHEMCE shall solicit and consider input from—</text> <subparagraph id="H6600A3D03F3945F1A82D3BFE563A6C90"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the PHEMCE Advisory Committee maintained under subsection (d), as appropriate; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF19B238CEF544AD68689784802F9F5B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>State, local, Tribal, and territorial public health departments or officials, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H7C209F4D903A4E5E9CE65399B2D4A9B4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Advisory committee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2811–1 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/30hh-10a">42 U.S.C. 30hh–10a</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H737C052B8B914C6F984925414EA43E82" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H559E586FED2141F19B9EE4C8BB4960D4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>PHEMCE Advisory Committee</header> 
<paragraph id="H0C79C6E46F524070BB39E07280DE231C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HF321617309E94134B00E4FE0F430CDCA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish and maintain an advisory committee to be known as the PHEMCE Advisory Committee (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Advisory Committee</quote>) to seek input and ensure communication and transparency in the functions of the PHEMCE; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0951689B177741EDBF7AADECA3FEF2F3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>seek input from and consult with external partners with divergent threat portfolios, including chemical, biological, radiological, or nuclear agents and emerging infectious diseases, to ensure the right combination of threat-specific expertise on PHEMCE functions under subsection (c)(1) and to ensure appropriate capability and capacity to maintain overall readiness.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H432457CF78E74B0B8E662F65E22C6243"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8392DF3B8A1A462BBDE173AD65EC1783"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide advice to the PHEMCE in carrying out its functions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1C532797A3224D78991F536E5CCC6C89"><enum>(B)</enum><text>solicit and incorporate the input of the private sector, non-Federal partners, and stakeholders to increase communication and transparency, identify gaps of preparedness, and coordinate improvements in PHEMCE decision-making<italic></italic>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H953C90A3E7FD44B5808C7C8B2C341A1C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>aid in the PHEMCE’s strategic planning and decision-making regarding medical countermeasure research, advanced research, development, procurement, stockpiling, replenishment, deployment, and distribution;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0E65288E9B4544B0864A52B6CB9BA9E3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>aid in interactions among the PHEMCE’s members listed in subsection (b) and other government entities; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H17F6B7E057984CADBCB13AEE1A696624"><enum>(E)</enum><text>aid in the PHEMCE’s communication of decisions related to the PHEMCE’s functions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H677381ABE7FA4C5493B86096E49773C2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the members of the PHEMCE listed in subsection (b), shall appoint to the Advisory Committee at least 9, and not more than 11, individuals, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4C46D7B78574454A8CB84DB2A341F0C4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at least 3 non-Federal professionals with expertise in medical countermeasure development, including medical countermeasures for chemical, biological, radiological, or nuclear agents and emerging infectious diseases;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0F5617DC033B4026B6211EA7D61E01B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at least 2 non-Federal professionals with expertise in medical countermeasure stockpiling and replenishment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1ADACD06AE714976956D4D110FEF0169"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at least 2 non-Federal professionals with expertise in the medical countermeasure supply chain, including medical countermeasure manufacturing and distribution;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8B503FB36A824767A13DE4BA88A6C315"><enum>(D)</enum><text>at least 2 non-Federal professionals with expertise in medical disaster planning, preparedness, response, or recovery;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7A41B40EA07B41048D17C1EE02E0AA34"><enum>(E)</enum><text>1 non-Federal professional appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8DD71F9D7CE04726B5AD9A4B0A07FB1C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>1 non-Federal professional appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6806DB16D1F84E36A1C86AEEF850140E"><enum>(G)</enum><text>1 non-Federal professional appointed by the majority leader of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H47AF0A941F0F4B8AB34A719E4C0BF8DE"><enum>(H)</enum><text>1 non-Federal professional appointed by the minority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H837821ED4A62458B84E4857059B6BF02"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Term of appointment</header><text>Each member of the Advisory Committee shall be appointed for a term of 2 years and may be reappointed for two additional terms of 2 years, for a total of not more than 6 years. The first and second such terms may be consecutive. The third such term may not be consecutive.<italic></italic></text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H38A505B5EFBC4D4D83B524E131554A2A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H641EC728CF994F538C296DC067A3A368"><enum>(A)</enum><text>meet not less than 4 times in each calendar year that begins after the establishment of the Advisory Committee;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDBE2A1963D2A45A5A10F22FAB2F2D5D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>hold all meetings in-person;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6B0E9450145D42CDB717C45E06DD3C73"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for purposes of ensuring transparency, provide adequate advance notice of the date of each meeting, including by publicly posting the meeting date 30 days before the date on which the meeting is to be held;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4711C4CDBD70486CA2A999F4A7BDF9FB"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 60 days after each meeting, communicate the activities carried out and decisions made during, and minutes of, such meeting to the appropriate congressional committees; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA361459B8B63460CAA8670AF3D35DBAF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>not later than 30 days after each meeting, communicate the activities carried out and decisions made during, and minutes of, such meeting to the PHEMCE.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

