<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6FF8905741954A649B1FB92B98436FB9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4912 IH: To require the evaluation of certain criteria relating to locations for deployment of successor radar systems of the National Weather Service, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4912</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000308">Mr. Jackson of North Carolina</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the evaluation of certain criteria relating to locations for deployment of successor radar systems of the National Weather Service, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE98E8BABF4B34A209EDD473697BF25C2" style="OLC"><section id="H6E4E753A1DDB4B33B2461AAE57231B47" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Evaluation of locations for deployment of successor radar systems of the National Weather Service</header><subsection id="H398184DC3CBA47838C38B9C636891568"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan To improve radar coverage</header><paragraph id="H8AFB623F73174E6CBAA3F7FDDC831EC6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce and the Director of the National Weather Service, in consultation with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate a plan for improving radar coverage, by integrating or upgrading, to the extent practicable and as the case may be, additional observation solutions to improve hazardous weather detection and forecasting.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC546B66A69114937825E9E96597F0B9B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination</header><subparagraph id="HE2CC422BB99A4C058BFA0660FA4437D8" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing the plan to improve radar coverage under paragraph (1), the Secretary of Commerce and the Director of the National Weather Service, in consultation with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration—</text><clause id="H078C2C6BE2BE47248C1E69F5070615D3" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall prioritize locations for the deployment of the successor radar system that will replace the current Next Generation Weather Radar of the National Weather Radar Service (NEXRAD); and</text></clause><clause id="H473F9CD00E094E1482E36B7C9BB70FB1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may determine additional appropriate locations for the deployment of such successor radar system installations.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD34C818CFFCF4959B05F34AAC9A84DE5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consideration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making a determination pursuant to subparagraph (A), the Secretary of Commerce and the Director of the National Weather Service shall consider deployment in at least three locations that are not less than 75 miles from an existing NEXRAD station. In making such a determination for a deployment location, the Secretary of Commerce and the Director of the National Weather Service may also consider the criteria described in subsection (b).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE3E068C84B2D4A2480297D40A78CA00B" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Criteria described</header><text>The criteria described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H7E6ABDC1373D4E4299577527AEE30ABD" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether a population of 200,000 or more would be served by a successor radar installation at the location.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32396879D02D4C88883E1D493EE800C5" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The frequency of any of the following issuances at the location:</text><subparagraph id="H019FF31D08D4493CB06D884EE6CA0703" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Severe thunderstorm watches or warnings.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H262159CFE72B4E9CB7B9C8A85E4C2DED" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Tornado watches or warnings.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD2A095E583F4510AF34CF14788BEC48" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Flash flood watches or warnings.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB9453ED0EF7499C89A7267CFD2D9CB5" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Winter storm warnings.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

