<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1F5767B113604FD48E0750F9C41B63DA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5297 IH: Defense Small Business Past Performance Consideration Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5297</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230829">August 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Defense to amend the Department of Defense Supplement to the Federal Acquisition Regulation to include consideration of past performance of affiliates of small business concerns, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE867BC9217E44FFC812F6F9CD6863CB1" style="OLC">
<section id="HEECE2323AAB548E7994E1DB213DE7DC5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Defense Small Business Past Performance Consideration Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H44845B880DB04375B485B59B34BCF0B2" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Consideration of past performance of affiliates of small business concerns</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Not later than July 1, 2024, the Secretary of Defense shall amend section 215.305 of the Department of Defense Supplement to the Federal Acquisition Regulation (or any successor regulation) to—</text>
<paragraph id="H50D91F1B0B2A4392B3F30B6E4AC7B3A6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">require that when evaluating a bid from a small business concern (as defined under section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>)) for a Department of Defense contract, the contracting officer for such contract shall consider the past performance information of affiliates of such concern as the past performance of such concern; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3447C3AB535041458AADEA336DBA86D3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that only past performance information of such affiliates during the nine-year period preceding the date on which such concern submitted a bid described in paragraph (1) is considered as past performance of such concern.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

