<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE941D6609ACA44AAAF11B5502A75ED3D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4548 IH: Building Relationships and Increasing Democratic Governance through Engagement to DRC Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4548</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000307">Mr. James</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a national strategy to secure United States supply chains involving critical minerals sourced from the Democratic Republic of the Congo, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H93DBAA4B64C8426788504FAAA570F049" style="OLC"><section id="HABC3BAD321E647329332285897D3A98A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Building Relationships and Increasing Democratic Governance through Engagement to DRC Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>BRIDGE to DRC Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H502D3D581DCC4B58B2AEF60F2F7D18C9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H17420138899546EDB43C992E5DC7B029"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States recognized the Democratic Republic of the Congo (hereafter referred to as <quote>the DRC</quote>) on June 30, 1960.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72490C60CB3B43C0999523EFE55ABED2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The DRC has long suffered from armed conflicts and threats to its territorial integrity, including by the March 23 Movement (M23), the Allied Defense Forces, and the Forces Démocratiques de Liberation du Rwanda (FDLR).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D1941CB28FB4C248F0B78B8C523A8C1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The DRC’s instability is further exacerbated by political instability, endemic corruption, exploitation of its natural resources, armed conflict, gross human rights abuses, and humanitarian crises, which destabilize the region and cause mass human suffering.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H626DA910F235472BB2B2BEC140AF2A2C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The DRC is scheduled to conduct presidential, legislative, provincial, and local elections in December 2023.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B97C2D34291492B9219A0536C5745AF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The United Nations Stabilization Mission in the Democratic Republic of the Congo (MONUSCO) has failed to stabilize eastern DRC and failed its mandate to protect civilians.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20867FF3833B4FE891B88AEB07A8B5B7"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The East African Community’s intervention has failed to stem armed conflicts and stabilize eastern DRC.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5DFDAC6AA7D4B5D8598AD4EAA3AE1EC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The DRC has globally significant reserves of rare earth minerals and other critical minerals, including deposits of copper, cobalt, lithium, niobium, germanium, and tantalum.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD28611E0F32A44EC9B902589715A0A69"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The DRC is the world’s largest producer and exporter of cobalt and the world’s second largest producer of copper.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7CF522AF86349C79697A09FF02A14AA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The People’s Republic of China (PRC) has a near monopoly of the DRC’s cobalt mining sector, with 15 of the 19 cobalt-producing mines in the DRC being owned or financed by PRC based firms in 2021, which directly contributes to its near monopoly over global critical mineral supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DC6CD57BAFE425291B18E40AB241A38"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The PRC refines 80 percent of the world’s cobalt and 60 percent of its lithium.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1D23CBE835B465295B9421E011B8B8C"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States National Highway Traffic Safety Administration projects that the technology costs required for manufacturers to adhere to current industrial targets could increase by $90 billion over the lifetimes of vehicles through 2029, with per-vehicle costs increasing by roughly $1,110 on average per United States consumer for new vehicles.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC551AE66322844248FD4E84DDE7846F7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HD4B45DE37D38458B8B19500E0C8F54AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the stability of the Democratic Republic of the Congo is a strategic priority for the United States on the African continent, and it is in the economic and national security interest of the United States to support accountable, inclusive, and democratic governance in the Democratic Republic of Congo;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFFB26034CA744C7AB2C8CC9F442B8A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>it is in the United States interest to support additional efforts to end conflict in eastern DRC, including by seeking to stem the Rwandan Government’s support to the M23, the documented use of child soldiers, and the threat posed to the Congolese people from undisciplined elements of the Armed Forces of the DRC and other non-state armed groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84D9ADA5DF474F849670372237C6FAC6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>United States humanitarian assistance remains critical in providing millions of people in the DRC with life-saving aid and alleviating the suffering of people affected by disasters;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81143DFD9ABA41F498E5D697DD24E996"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as the largest financial contributor to the United Nations Stabilization Mission in the Democratic Republic of the Congo, with an estimated $313,000,000 in fiscal year 2023 appropriations allocated for the mission, the United States should use its voice, vote, and influence in the United Nations Security Council to support the United Nations pre-existing plan to draw down the Mission not later than December 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BFE070A80964C989A0097C4A211E8D2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the current near monopoly of the PRC over the DRC’s cobalt and critical mineral extraction and near monopsony of the PRC over the DRC’s cobalt and global critical mineral processing and refining deprives the DRC of important revenue and added value, and represents an economic and national security threat for the United States that directly impacts United States energy independence and military preparedness;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE36201FC27F242EB96CCF982FD90A3B2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the United States should ensure development of voluntary standards, support of multi stakeholder alliances and industry coalitions, and pursue actions to end human rights violations, environmental degradation, opaque businesses practices, and widespread forced labor, including child labor, in the DRC’s mining industry, a problem exacerbated by PRC linked companies’ flagrant disregard for human rights;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC066578A4BB44F49D531395F88EFB9C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>previous United States policies in regard to the DRC’s natural resources and minerals, such as section 1502 of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m</external-xref> note), have punished the DRC and incentivized illicit trade through the DRC’s neighbors; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF284F909671544A1AC2A15CB5794CD92"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The sale of the Tenke Fungurume mine in 2016, and the undeveloped Kisanfu concession in 2020, to the PRC State-tied mining company CMOC (previously known as China Molybdenum Company Limited) damaged United States economic and national security interests by contributing to the PRC’s control of global cobalt supply chains.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H1392B1DEA48C4139A4127AF150DA6270"><enum>4.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to—</text><paragraph id="HF0B393D77CF140BEB3C15114568F710C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>support the conduct of free, fair, and on time democratic elections in the DRC by advocating for enhanced civic education, an inclusive and transparent voter registration process that includes voter access in all provinces, including those where a state of siege declaration applies, and enabling all candidates to fairly compete, including through respecting all candidates’ rights to free expression and free assembly;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H233BD7E99BD848A1962F4B1CE1F2430C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>encourage the adoption of measures that ensure the elections in the DRC are free, fair and democratic, including through support for transparent tabulation processes, the publication of both preliminary and final electoral results by the Commission Électorale Nationale Indépendante (CENI) on its website and polling station premises in an appropriate timeframe to allow cross-checking against data gathered by election observers, and broad access for credible election observation by domestic and international actors including, where appropriate, civil society and faith-based entities, such as the Conférence Episcopale Nationale du Congo and the Church of Christ in Congo;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2799D4BF0F0E40E9ABFFB42BFAFBF9B0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>contribute to efforts to end the M23 conflict, including by supporting the African Union and East African Community efforts to achieve a lasting ceasefire and restricting all United States security assistance and cooperation to the Government of Rwanda until the Secretary of State certifies to the appropriate committees of Congress that Rwanda has terminated any and all military support for the M23;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD4CA8D3354D4F24B2AE9B5CCF6D7E57"><enum>(4)</enum><text>use existing sanctions authorities authorized by the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/10101">22 U.S.C. 10101 et seq.</external-xref>) against perpetrators of corruption or human rights violations in the DRC;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DE1EB699124498DABC3EFD68C6A34A9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>support efforts to accurately oversee, monitor, and prevent labor and human rights abuses in the DRC’s mining industry in order to remove child and slave labor from United States supply chains, including by encouraging the Government of the DRC to support the formalization of artisanal and small scale mining;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0CFE9EEE1754CC98B64F4098DF77905"><enum>(6)</enum><text>engage with the Government of the DRC to address factors, including opaque business and taxation practices, and unpredictable administrative requirements, that limit United States investment and constrain the ability of the United States and DRC to strengthen economic cooperation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H003859923A6F4272B703271B74D8231A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>require institutions including the Department of State, the United States Agency for International Development, the Development Finance Corporation, and the Department of Commerce to identify opportunities to increase the amount of United States investment in the DRC’s critical minerals sector; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H727F39E3CE83417A8E7D7121C7F16638"><enum>(8)</enum><text>recognize that the PRC’s influence over the DRC’s mining sector output and processing is of concern to the economic and national security of the United States.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H12E2698134454EFC938C7263F7ABDB4D"><enum>5.</enum><header>National strategy to ensure a continued role in the drc’s critical mineral sector</header><subsection id="H7016949AA8C6406487FE5CB21C5AC91E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the President, in consultation with the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Defense, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, and the heads of other appropriate Federal agencies, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a written strategy that—</text><paragraph id="H50F834FE389C4212BB1ADCEC6DB28D6B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifies the critical minerals present in the DRC that—</text><subparagraph id="HEC22CC684D314419AEC9FDF1F6CAD725"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are part of the United States Geological Survey list of 50 mineral commodities critical to the United States economy and national security; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63504B3178D148CC96F09EEB34B2A2B9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are at highest risk of supply chain disruption due to the domestic or global actions, including price-fixing, systemic acquisition and control of global mineral resources and processing, refining, smelting capacity, or undercutting the fair market value of such resources, by any covered entity; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H005F808EA58944428FE6A84113FD2195"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is focused on—</text><subparagraph id="HC288AAD3AD5F4262B7C5E2FAA075F9AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>securing United States supply chains which involve critical minerals sourced from the DRC; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AD81F6A32D74321BE576AA953F1C708"><enum>(B)</enum><text>securing and expanding United States supply chains which involve the critical minerals identified pursuant to paragraph (1)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE1D71D36D32843599A896DD9249D9CF4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The strategy required by subsection (a) shall also include the following:</text><paragraph id="H787B0FD1322B488F902EE41B1C105009"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Analysis of the national security implications and impact on national supply chain sovereignty caused by the 2016 and 2020 sales of Tenke Fungurume mine and the undeveloped Kisanfu concession to China Molybdenum Company Limited.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16D594D455B94DB29EBFAA094C2FED2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A review of the effectiveness of section 1502 of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78m">15 U.S.C. 78m</external-xref> note), including—</text><subparagraph id="HDB26B5847ADC4C1891E27416A3AADB0D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a list of all mining companies, grouped by nationality, who left eastern DRC following section 1502’s enactment in 2010;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CFBEB5D053B4DA69486FFBF2C15DD1E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>analysis showing the market share for the conflict mineral trade in eastern DRC before and after section 1502’s enactment which shall include, where possible, market share analysis for 2005, 2010, 2015 and 2020;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFEA323EC9C549C1B3A60FB04062A71E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>analysis of the unemployment factors, including disarmament, demobilization, and reintegration efforts, in eastern DRC following section 1502’s enactment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5339D780B6547689E394664A06CCEC8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>analysis of security sector reform efforts in eastern DRC since section 1502’s enactment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01FF442508024D83AF1C00D2E4C3FA9F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an assessment of the effectiveness of section 1502 in limiting financial benefits from accruing, either directly or indirectly, to armed groups in the DRC or adjoining countries; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FDB9F427EE24EF19C440E3E012C3DD1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>analysis of the level of illicit mining that has occurred in eastern DRC’s conflict mineral trade following section 1502’s enactment, which shall include—</text><clause id="H426B881417C340D2B5D6BA5BE8723060"><enum>(i)</enum><text>statistical analysis showing the degree of illegal smuggling of conflict minerals into adjoining countries; and</text></clause><clause id="HDF20C20267CD458FB04AC78296815447"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an assessment of the level of coordination and cooperation in the illegal smuggling of conflict minerals between adjoining countries and non-state armed actors present in eastern DRC.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4980676EDD984E8BBC94AF1DA85F1B89"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An analysis of the level of control exerted by the PRC over the DRC’s mining sector, including—</text><subparagraph id="H8577BE4271DE4D44B603B12FB513C98B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the market share of covered entities which shall include analysis of the market share for each of the critical minerals identified pursuant to subsection (a)(1)(B) in both the DRC as a whole and within each province where the critical minerals are located;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F81139DBCB94B0391C3449B7C6AD8D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the financial terms of covered entities investments in primary extraction; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46B9C88309E44D93B5062E7F98F44D3A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a diagram detailing the location of covered entities operations throughout the supply chain of the critical minerals identified in subsection (a)(1)(B) from extraction to refinement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAAC72BFA43E648C58BEC70A89C6FB705"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A list of each covered entity analyzed with respect to the evaluation of risk required by subsection (a)(1)(B).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79B30737AFD0428B8DB3C10FD39A7A5E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An assessment of the risks facing United States supply chains as a result of the PRC’s position in the DRC’s mining sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H930A654060E642B4BC6096A357EE5845"><enum>(6)</enum><text>An assessment of human rights and labor conditions at mines in the DRC at which covered entities operate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6238EDFAC74E441A81189819881F6202"><enum>(7)</enum><text>An assessment of the market share and capacity of trusted partner nations’ mining companies with respect to the DRC’s mining sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F7690B1CA274CAFB21ADF6DD916C62E"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A strategic plan to use bilateral and multilateral diplomatic relations, including through sustained engagement with the governments of United States allies and partners, to express to the Government of the DRC the support of the international community for the formalization of artisanal and small scale mining.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA793F31197144A589365C6196F930276"><enum>(9)</enum><text>An assessment of the factors that allowed the PRC to gain market dominance in parts of the DRC’s mining industry and which factors present the most significant barriers to increased United States investment in the DRC’s mining sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7538D0C4537C4B449F1F88D6C9B8B50B"><enum>(10)</enum><text>An assessment of the ability of the DRC’s critical mineral sector to positively contribute to United States efforts to fulfill both industrial production targets and ensure military preparedness, that includes—</text><subparagraph id="H28C1DBEC6CBC4DEF882CDB40D7F7BA7B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>analysis of the importance of the critical minerals in the DRC, as identified by subsection (a)(1)(B), in reaching current United States industrial production targets;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30043272720449A0A09D8A84FEB95C29"><enum>(B)</enum><text>analysis of the DRC’s business climate, specifically the reliability, transparency and consistency of its business practices;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E2B6B68F87A433DAA5C15A84CCD2C66"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evaluation of the impact of the factors identified in sections (b)(3), (b)(5), (b)(7), (b)(9) and (b)(10)(B) of this strategy on the ability of the United States to secure its critical mineral supply chains.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H428B8FB8F326430AAC922514E914F8D5"><enum>(11)</enum><text>An interagency approved plan to increase United States investment in the DRC, including through—</text><subparagraph id="H777DF0F92AA3499EBB068DE8B4F0C306"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increasing technical assistance and capacity building measures and conducting feasibility studies to rebuild infrastructure and reform the DRC’s business climate, including through reforms to the governance of the DRC’s State-owned enterprises (SOEs), in order to support domestic innovation and economic diversification, and increase local sub-contracting and private sector-led growth;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87871C3DE9B045B084C92C6A3EC56874"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensuring foreign assistance initiatives promote sustainable development in communities affected by mining, protect human rights, and provide professional training for local workers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16FCB0E61BFE44B4A74963F9600530D9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assessing staffing levels at the United States Embassy in Kinshasa, and increasing them if necessary, including having at least 1 Foreign Service Officer exclusively dedicated to critical minerals, to reflect the importance of the DRC to United States supply chains and enhance the competitiveness of United States development financing including through the United States International Development Finance Corporation and the Foreign Commercial Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C113215C0CA48A1868272A3E510E94C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The strategy required under subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form and may include a classified annex.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5D3AE519696B406FBD0B98C0B2C9BB6B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the submission of the initial strategy required by subsection (a), and every 3 years thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that includes—</text><paragraph id="H21C14A39E73D4E24944F8C296B5BE6FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an update of the strategy submitted pursuant to subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H118A7097444D45EB81623F1F906A5CF1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an assessment of the effectiveness of such strategy, as of the date of the submission of the update, in securing United States supply chains which rely on critical minerals sourced from the DRC.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9789DA3CFBB2401BB24029A2BB79A8AD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><paragraph id="H3C0EEF4A79C747DEB701CE6F8E120ED3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate Congressional Committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H2B6D068DBFB34557AA6E82CA3EFDF72A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Financial Services, and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F54CD9C7EDE446AA8B920784E707B3E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DCF2759AA8246E089AE1BA5CD2A2C97"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Armed group</header><text>The term <quote>armed group</quote> means an armed state or non-state actor that is identified as a perpetrator of serious human rights abuses in the Department of State’s annual Country Reports on Human Rights Practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B7EB7AF332246FDB57F3E1889DA8F35"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conflict mineral</header><text>The term <quote>conflict mineral</quote> means columbite-tantalite (coltan), cassiterite, gold, wolframite, or their derivatives, or any other mineral or its derivatives that the Secretary of State determines to be financing conflict in the DRC or an adjoining country.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H102387A661A94E33BEA72FE7B3164E72"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The terms <quote>covered entity</quote> means a foreign entity that—</text><subparagraph id="H5FB88F4C34D946BF91EFBBA87277E572"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is subject to the jurisdiction or direction of the PRC;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5C0D7964FEF4E97864DB298275DD68A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is legally registered or internationally headquartered in the PRC;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2DB6DB0DF9774C16BC34E9C395B05128"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is directly operating on behalf of the PRC;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37D6DAB4D7B84D2EACED7391D5CDBE72"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is majority owned by, or directly or indirectly controlled by, the PRC;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B13EABFDB1D4F47A135CDCDBFD00B3B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>receives funding, either directly or indirectly, from the Government of the PRC, PRC State policy banks, or any other bank that is financed primarily by the PRC;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFECE65AA77D847BFAA6654C2DFE6216E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>that is formed from a spin-off, merger or acquisition, or sale of a business unit involving an entity described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (E) or is otherwise a successor to such an entity; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE04ACFC26B6547BBA8E776DB29F8E51A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>provides financial services for an entity described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (F).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB611A55301A042399FE5D3E97B88B3AC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Drc</header><text>The term <quote>DRC</quote> means the Democratic Republic of the Congo.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88505639A3674397B2BF00069239C302"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Prc</header><text>The term <quote>PRC</quote> means the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

