<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H901494B6D6174FE2AE66ED9874FFD4ED" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3683 IH: Benton MacKaye National Scenic Trail Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3683</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000459">Mr. Fleischmann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000246">Mr. Edwards</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Trails System Act to designate the Benton MacKaye National Scenic Trail, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB10465C6E61E4DA88F3961F73723F360" style="OLC"><section id="H2A485705AD7342159909AE3AEE4C7DBA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Benton MacKaye National Scenic Trail Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCBE9E0FF50584B2ABE607FDC7EEE9BBA" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that the Benton MacKaye Trail—</text><paragraph id="HE006B39A4CD14BB791D64456C86A1AC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is a scenic, nonmotorized trail that traverses approximately 287 miles over some of the most renowned forests and mountains in the States of Georgia, Tennessee, and North Carolina;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA06D0E6906D49E189CE99D0C45622B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>showcases a wide variety of scenic views, including high elevation peaks, mature forests, and secluded waterfalls, and passes through wilderness rich with biodiversity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23854971B918446AA708537B7F0F4E4F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>passes through six designated Wilderness Areas, the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, and the Chattahoochee, Cherokee, and Nantahala National Forests;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0E4F81C5A814DB5A516B3B62A1324AE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provides a wide array of easily accessible hikes for novice and intermediate hikers, as well as more challenging trails for backpacking;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FF2F0E002ED44B99F8E131AD4D5A3AA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>supports economic opportunities for numerous rural communities that benefit from the trail’s visitors spending their money on accommodations, food, and outdoor supplies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E981B5902804EE5A9DFD19AF0B7F059"><enum>(6)</enum><text>runs from Springer Mountain in Georgia, through Tennessee, and extends through the Great Smoky Mountains National Park in North Carolina; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H728D8FD2DBBB431088D5CD1F2601F2FC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>is physically accessible and can be maintained at a minimal cost because—</text><subparagraph id="H369F5552A25845E19877B1618C60412E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Benton MacKaye Trail has been maintained at its current length since 2005;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E52DAF4841F445FB1E4C6201E0DC85A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>95 percent of the Benton MacKaye Trail is located on Federal land; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA559668811B7462980FAEE27F5EAB63F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Benton MacKaye Trail has been successfully constructed, maintained, and managed by the Benton MacKaye Trail Association since 1980.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H35BA8624EE6442D694F55A3524D813F7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Benton MacKaye National Scenic Trail</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5(a) of the National Trails System Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1244">16 U.S.C. 1244(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H17E76B0A2B114A85BEBD60C8F6354CFC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H3AF6C94C39A043D185178FE0F6679195"><enum>(32)</enum><header>Benton MacKaye National Scenic Trail</header><subparagraph id="HC2B325FC2FCC40958CBAFE908C52B009" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Benton MacKaye National Scenic Trail, a trail extending approximately 287 miles across the States of Georgia, Tennessee, and North Carolina, as generally depicted on the map entitled <quote>Benton MacKaye Trail Overview Map</quote>, dated January 6, 2022. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71D89CD0E4654565AD7F231C9B5A2E16"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Availability of map</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The map described in subparagraph (A) shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the Forest Service and the National Park Service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0786507CB6B8482EB72EBD45D3748034"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Authorized uses</header><clause id="HD6E303CF353043FEBB1FAEB7E5987081"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Existing uses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Existing non-motorized recreational activities, where authorized on the day before the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Benton MacKaye National Scenic Trail Act of 2023</short-title>, including equestrian, non-motorized bicycling, and special uses, are authorized on the trail.</text></clause><clause id="HA37519A333EA4F5B83EC8BDD81987DD1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Required comprehensive plan</header><text>The comprehensive plan required under subsection (e) shall address authorized uses and management of the recreational, scenic, and other values for which the trail is established.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H723AF291D35940998D74D86329FB9FAE"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Benton MacKaye National Scenic Trail shall be administered by the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, in consultation with—</text><clause id="H7F53C825391C4B1F854B4083419181CB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>other Federal agencies;</text></clause><clause id="H0AD7122E46EA406DA96E4C4A832E8DDC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>State, Tribal, regional, and local agencies; and</text></clause><clause id="HD4B38399D18C4B2598835C9781D061F8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>nonprofit organizations and other mutually beneficial cooperators. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

