<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H5C2BA4C789044436A306ACD606A1F1FD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3943 RH: Servicemember Employment Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 193</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3943</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–241]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on June 9, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to improve the reemployment rights of members of the Armed Forces, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HVR00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H8EEDB2CD365F4FC48F44F23959C10045"><section id="H1BBED7AFF9DD488AB9D3D0AA748C324D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Servicemember Employment Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4AB3915F90124BCE80678533DA0706EF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improvements to reemployment rights of members of the Armed Forces</header><subsection id="H909EC3B2EB774A5BB722CDC2D0CA5BAE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>USERRA purposes</header><text>Section 4301(a)(1) of title 38, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>encourage noncareer service in the uniformed services</quote> and inserting <quote>encourage service in the uniformed services</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8A09AE8FEA8E4454A102B3F7287327E0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition of retaliation</header><text>Subsection (b) of section 4311 of title 38, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>or other retaliatory action</quote> after <quote>employment action</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9444F913E09F4279BB200D86D9564EB6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expansion of injunctive relief</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (e) of section 4323 of such title is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD4BDF1FB6318400AB611A6D4433DC5D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The court shall use</quote> and inserting <quote>(1) The court shall use</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9533DC2902248ECA82C40C2E8826B41"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7703B021CF654158993B980381AC5FDC" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HVR00"><paragraph id="H626AD684076C46B9AEB342FFA1B565DD" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person bringing an action to enforce a provision of this chapter pursuant to subsection (a) shall be entitled to an injunction under paragraph (1) if such person demonstrates—</text><subparagraph id="H4EA835C4399D4D159619A953487ADC21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a violation—</text><clause id="H22CAAE77C8494A96ADD8C92E540F4610"><enum>(i)</enum><text>of the provisions of this chapter; or</text></clause><clause id="H63E891C798F449E88F7F9622D1BF42D1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>of the provisions of this chapter is threatened or is imminent;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3480EEF52A148468C4BD5B5391E32A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the harm to the person outweighs the injury to the employer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E3FE9AD323C4F8A9B0502271345152A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a likelihood of success on the merits of such action; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0864F27BE1D4033807C4C8AB58DEC47"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">awarding such relief is in the public interest.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0558304634084BD7B6483E5C7F650798" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The court may not deny a motion for injunctive relief on the basis that a party bringing an action to enforce a provision of this chapter may be awarded wages unearned due to an unlawful termination or denial of employment at the conclusion of such action.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H067F3D3D0289450F9CF5E7FDDEF0815B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Damages against a State or private employer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4323 of such title is further amended, in paragraph (1) of subsection (d), by striking subparagraph (C) and inserting the following new subparagraphs:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H01007E9E3D6C4B838A9954B2A7D09ACB" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HVR00"><subparagraph id="H399B2E90B22D44A1843EF99513CBCF81" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The court may require the employer to pay the person the amount referred to in subparagraph (B) and interest on such amount, calculated at a rate of 3 percent per year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5C4DFF96C5046F2BC5DC0FB6FE4F7BF" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The court may require the employer to pay the person the greater of $50,000 or the amount equal to the amounts referred to in subparagraphs (B) and (C) as liquidated damages, if the court determines that the employer knowingly failed to comply with the provisions of this chapter.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H8EECEA94BCA542589C56A06C617873FD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Mandatory attorney fees award in successful actions for reemployment</header><paragraph id="H15DCA207C74A4561BE3B47C8F47A5FB2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>MSPB actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (4) of subsection (c) of section 4324 of such title is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H2C1A883966594ADE895735EB5FF24604"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>may, in its discretion,</quote> and inserting <quote>shall</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97F9E10D0FC24BD1B61DF400242578A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>The Board may, in its discretion, award reasonable attorney fees in a case settled before the issuance of an order if the person can demonstrate that significant attorney fees were incurred and that justice requires such an award.</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB88228805E5C4865B99926C8C3FF5C9D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal Circuit actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (d) of such section is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H94BA24C61DAD4E049CBD4227EA3F4CF7" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HVR00"><paragraph id="H59D644F21D034FDC8D254D636BF35EFD" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In such Federal Circuit proceeding, the court shall award such person reasonable attorney fees, expert witness fees, and other litigation expenses if such person—</text><subparagraph id="HC3FEC983DAC74BDAB329CFD3126E8F0C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prevails in such Federal Circuit proceeding; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A8DAC3AC6F04277943D7331A47625F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not represented by the Special Counsel in such Federal Circuit proceeding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HD842098E8EEA470FA0F9D95F6177A825"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Actions against a State or private employer</header><text>Paragraph (2) of section 4323(h) of such title is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HC187313561714E2881E2AE71E2BA4EAB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsection (a)(2)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (a)(3)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEEAD940CAB3945F0A45FBB5B27B10FF7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the court may award any such person who prevails in such action or proceeding reasonable attorney fees</quote> and inserting <quote>the court shall award any such person who prevails in such action or proceeding reasonable attorney fees</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H387B65947C634380A134142F005EC285" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>GAO review and report on USERRA</header><paragraph id="HB5C21302315E49BD9B6681DCF183D663" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall review the methods through which the Secretary of Labor, acting through the Veterans’ Employment and Training Service, processes actions for relief under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/43">chapter 43</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1E0B00A21334B02B5CA20D32B05497B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report that includes—</text><subparagraph id="HE83B7D0773F340A89832D244935D5281"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the findings of the review required under paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C53796F4DDC482FB7B3D6680BCBFA9C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an identification of the number of actions for relief under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/43">chapter 43</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, initiated during the period covered by the report, disaggregated by employer characteristics, including size and geographic region;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEFD9417675BD4F54B8EAFF5D729D51B1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an identification of the number of such actions for relief that were dismissed, including the characteristics of such actions and reasons for dismissal;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90993B2AF1C14602855316BB0529264E"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an identification of the number of such actions for relief that were referred to the Department of Justice; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB99FCCE0661942B3AF10F6982784969F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an assessment of trends, if any, in such actions for relief initiated during such period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9C8C3385C3DC4AE4A5889ABC36B90734"><enum>(g)</enum><header>GAO review of protections for members of the uniformed services by Federal intelligence agencies</header><paragraph id="HB6E93EFF7AEA4E4591F4775836A99373"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing on the processes and procedures adopted and used by the intelligence community to provide the protections for members of the uniformed services otherwise established under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/43">chapter 43</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF470408CC6DC431188DF7F1DD10C6E5A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall provide to such committees a report on such processes and procedures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EDF4DEDF5DC4D95A7868B04E967524E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H100AB70F1B344280B4F39F057BA67639"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and Senate, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H492CF9EC2A8440E1880D91B9D11EBECD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>intelligence community</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3(4) of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003(4)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H75851F7CCE3F4CAA905339D044CD47E4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Review of investigations manual of Veterans’ Employment and Training Service</header><subsection id="H157374A132C24D9EA9F704C4DE1E483C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and once every two years thereafter for the period of five years beginning on such date, the Secretary of Labor, shall review the manual of the Department of Labor titled <quote>Veterans’ Employment and Training Service Investigations Manual: USERRA, VEOA, and VP</quote> (or a successor manual) and make such revisions to such manual as the Secretary determines appropriate. </text></subsection><subsection id="HB0237669E5984CA58F62148ABF4C4926"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after any date on which the Secretary completes a review required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate—</text><paragraph id="HBA7DC33848F249EDA2261D269ED51396"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a report that includes a description of any revision to such manual made pursuant to such review; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA37FBC9436542509FB13DC121F7070E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a copy of the entire such manual which—</text><subparagraph id="HC76E59449C044DF59BAB94BA2B431A34"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be provided to the Chairman and Ranking Member of each such committee; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B98DE0D22A647598A674A3A1A9E466C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may contain a separate addendum for portions of the manual that contain law enforcement sensitive materials.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

