<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9D6497DDAC2246F99FBF70CFB87AA73B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5395 IH: Coverage Parity for Medicare Patients Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5395</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230912">September 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to establish a demonstration program relating to medical necessity determinations under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H37AD76592CD04C179C4B32000C514EA0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4F4BE657E3734D339328D6D4A76C2650" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Coverage Parity for Medicare Patients Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H2DB0FF8A31BE4516B227FA3EE088CA00"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishing a demonstration program relating to medical necessity determinations under the Medicare program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1862 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395y">42 U.S.C. 1395y</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC1B3768790064B4A9970548CCE327078" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="HBAEE199D12824F9582BB044B1252C666"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Demonstration program relating to medical necessity determinations</header> 
<paragraph id="HE323B4D95F154674A2F5F9850ED39E48"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than January 1, 2026, the Secretary shall establish a demonstration program (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>program</quote>) under which an item or service furnished to an individual entitled to benefits under part A or enrolled under part B is deemed to be reasonable and necessary for purposes of subsection (a)(1) if such item or service meets the criteria specified in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H95F361E2392E40F3B4FD91F2F5B9A786"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of participating areas</header><text>The Secretary shall select no fewer than 5 States (or, at the option of the Secretary, no fewer than 3 Medicare administrative contractor jurisdictions relating to the administration of parts A and B (as specified by the Secretary)) in which to carry out the program.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7AFAA06A634749B69B2F175A16E0D35F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Specified criteria</header> 
<subparagraph id="H7F0DA4FA28CC4682995A1A7C92A5DFAB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the criteria specified in this paragraph are, with respect to an item or service furnished to an individual in a State or jurisdiction (as applicable) selected by the Secretary under paragraph (2), the following:</text> <clause id="HDF3E701203684777B62E14D581B8E1AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Such item or service so furnished would be covered under a significant number of group health plans and group or individual health insurance coverage offered in such State or jurisdiction if so furnished to a similarly situated individual enrolled under such plan or coverage (as applicable).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9BCCD30048794A4E85D2D61E4B6703BF" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The item or service is safe and effective.</text></clause> <clause id="H918F18E33DC1413585638399D66BE2F0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The item or service—</text> 
<subclause id="H754F24C7750743BBA332012844B071F0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is not experimental or investigational; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9BA05438B282406FB2EBEB414DD37AB4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is experimental or investigational, but is furnished as part of a clinical trial that meets the standards of coverage applicable under any national coverage determination relating to clinical trials.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H973F053548CD4AA7B57AEFE3E3C04C3A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Significant coverage</header><text>The Secretary shall through notice-and-comment rulemaking establish requirements for what constitutes coverage of an item or service under a significant number of group health plans and group or individual health insurance coverage in a State or jurisdiction. Such requirements may provide that such significant number is demonstrated through a showing that a majority of similarly situated individuals covered under such a plan or group or individual health insurance coverage in such State or jurisdiction would have benefits available under such plan or coverage for such item or service or through such other similar metrics determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H71FE2347CFD343BFB26360E851F593B4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Duration</header> <subparagraph id="HA1C5C9AE13F947039D33D988D76ED889"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The program shall be in effect for a period of not less than 4 years.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7F9C310C21F84F20B9170A2AA6083837"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Expansion</header><text>The Secretary may, during the period in which the program is in effect and as determined appropriate by the Secretary, expand the program to additional States or jurisdictions not originally selected under paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H146AD36F02B8481CA848A528AF6D50DE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Secretary may terminate the program—</text> 
<clause id="HE56FC8850C284C98968A0C5603B8294A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>only on or after the date that is 4 years after the effective date of the program; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA48465BBE3814F6B8943911004C15723"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>only once the Secretary has concluded a 60-day public comment period with respect to such termination.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

