<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C1FE5D050F242C1A7EC0B20D1D6EF03" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 672 IH: Border Security Investment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 672</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001224">Mr. Moran</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000377">Ms. Granger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000603">Mr. Luttrell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish trust funds relating to border security, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H463DBEB1E8F8483CBB672673784E16E3" style="OLC"><section id="H0ABCF6FE3423415292140E46524A4247" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Border Security Investment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC9E19162F358453BBC65C3799A33A2D2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of trust funds relating to border security</header><subsection id="H171BE5EE8DED4D9986A52FD58D7F05EE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Additional remittance transfer fees</header><text>Section 920 of the Electronic Fund Transfer Act (relating to remittance transfers) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1693o-1">15 U.S.C. 1693o–1</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H43B658E4104640C6B2ADEDBB43A2B13A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (g) as subsection (h); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8C93008ACCD4874AB1BABF9B548D83A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after subsection (f) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC0BC5DD933CC4BB48E6F4AF452AF0B70" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HAB0CB412915341DF85F8AEE4EC82868C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Additional remittance fees</header><paragraph id="HEA879286DB53413D82B80C9DC8B9C4AF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A remittance transfer provider that is a money services business shall impose a fee on each person sending a remittance transfer to a covered country in an amount equal to 37 percent of the remittance transfer amount.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1413F2D1C6394A93B0720044CE8C2BF1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transfer of fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All fees collected under this subsection shall be submitted to the Department of the Treasury for deposit in the general fund, in such form and in such manner as the Secretary of the Treasury shall establish by rule.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2AACB3AA85949FA98C10D9F53624D4F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H06ED388AA8084E32B74A2657149DFE5B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Covered country</header><text>With respect to a fiscal year, the term <quote>covered country</quote> means each country identified by the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection as one of the 5 countries that had the most citizens or nationals unlawfully enter the United States during the previous fiscal year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2EB02D355B84E99BAF45B38EA79E133"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Money services business</header><text>The term <quote>money services business</quote> has the meaning given that term under section 1010.100 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44DE91D93ED24984BF1622341F75DB7A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Border Security State Reimbursement Trust Fund</header><paragraph id="H9D0445FFBAB94CB59414962F75D9A275"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Treasury a trust fund, to be known as the <quote>Border Security State Reimbursement Trust Fund</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Reimbursement Fund</quote>), consisting of amounts transferred under paragraph (2) and any amounts credited under paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC431B76527B48248F1B97D77CBA5990" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transfer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In fiscal year 2025 and each fiscal year thereafter, the Secretary of the Treasury shall transfer to the Reimbursement Fund, from the general fund of the Treasury, an amount equal to fifty percent of the total amount of remittance fees collected under subsection (g)(2) of section 920 of the Electronic Fund Transfer Act (relating to remittance transfers; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1693o-1">15 U.S.C. 1693o–1</external-xref>) during the immediately preceding fiscal year. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95DF1FE4FF694DF9812931EAEBC5651D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Investment of amounts</header><subparagraph id="HAC0000656AC64C5B8D05A7BB401C256B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall invest such portion of the Reimbursement Fund as is not required to meet current withdrawals in interest-bearing obligations of the United States or in obligations guaranteed as to both principal and interest by the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE08B646CDA924BA7AD5744A09EE6F56C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Interest and proceeds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The interest on, and the proceeds from the sale or redemption of, any obligations held in the Reimbursement Fund shall be credited to the Reimbursement Fund. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC15B952F9DD4BDA9D32CE25BBD9B570" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Purpose; application</header><subparagraph id="HCD484C14E08949D1ABF37CF78CA8C811"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts in the Reimbursement Fund shall be available to the Secretary of Homeland Security, without further appropriation, to reimburse border States for expenditures incurred by such States relating to border security enforcement measures.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E47866070B540A58A1BF70DB67A8007" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the beginning of any fiscal year beginning in fiscal year 2025, a border State may apply to the Secretary to receive amounts from the Reimbursement Fund by submitting receipts, in such form and manner as the Secretary deems appropriate, of expenditures relating to border security enforcement measures made during the immediately preceding fiscal year. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H635162B14289409CBE608B68BBC021C5" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall promptly distribute from the Reimbursement Fund, to any border State that submits an application under subparagraph (B), an amount equal to the proportion that the amount expended by such a border State in the applicable immediately preceding fiscal year bears to the total amount expended in such fiscal year by all such border States so submitting an application.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBAC398B9C834C179B31071B69E8CCE4"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Border security enforcement measures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subparagraph, an expenditure by a border State shall be deemed to be related to border security enforcement measures if that expenditure directly or indirectly was used for the mission of deterring unlawful crossings, detecting unlawful activity and entry into the United States, or for gaining operational control of the southwest border. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E463DEABF1D4A1297DA5AE742E1DB1A" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Border Security Trust Fund</header><paragraph id="HDCB51348F5F344AE8E5F2F0122C8F582"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Treasury a trust fund, to be known as the <quote>Border Security Trust Fund</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Security Fund</quote>), consisting of amounts transferred under paragraph (2) and any amounts credited under paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1F49D8DC18440328085CB9D4BC620A3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transfers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In fiscal year 2025 and each fiscal year thereafter, the Secretary of the Treasury shall transfer to the Security Fund, from the general fund of the Treasury, an amount equal to fifty percent of the total amount of remittance fees collected under subsection (g)(2) of section 920 of the Electronic Fund Transfer Act (relating to remittance transfers; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1693o-1">15 U.S.C. 1693o–1</external-xref>) during the immediately preceding fiscal year. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H052E06E7934B43F4B2B83D8504EDCE2C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Investment of amounts</header><subparagraph id="HE6CFD39E7A7A461BBCD19DC529F62A57" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall invest such portion of the Security Fund as is not required to meet current withdrawals in interest-bearing obligations of the United States or in obligations guaranteed as to both principal and interest by the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC9873A53D3B49BEA675806D8AA71546" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Interest and proceeds</header><text>The interest on, and the proceeds from the sale or redemption of, any obligations held in the Security Fund shall be credited to the Security Fund. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBCC2BE6F77542C18ADEFD3E466E8BBB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts in the Security Fund shall be available to the Secretary of Homeland Security, without further appropriation, for the following purposes:</text><subparagraph id="H52970E81B70D49128D133556EEF0B56C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The deployment of technology intended to detect and prevent unlawful crossings along the United States-Mexico border.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H668CC2B666714CD9A3EA0566E2F744B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The installation of physical barriers at the southern border.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF203E900A9124056A6B7EACC6597F2F7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Wages and salaries for U.S. Border Patrol agents.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H75C78B09FA9D4C348C311CABFD50AAD7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rescission of excess amounts</header><text>If the sum of the total funds in each of the Reimbursement Fund and the Security Fund is greater than $50,000,000,000, an amount equal to the funds in excess of $50,000,000,000 shall be—</text><paragraph id="HEEDEDD3713D94EBBA62508B8C15A93C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>permanently rescinded from such total funds; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3C79B392BEA45D5B64FF07075AB27F9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">deposited in the general fund of the Treasury where such funds shall be—</text><subparagraph id="HA9C9F840A44149EAB92798D3A404CA39"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">dedicated for the sole purpose of deficit reduction; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H825FCAA3185C4CDCAB7E7A3976FFA2CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prohibited from use as an offset for other spending increases or revenue reductions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3F8815712DE249589E5CF8BA4FF753B3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This Act and the amendment made by this Act shall take effect and apply beginning on January 1, 2024.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

