<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H713BEC9B1239444689C1E68AF78F829B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3802 IH: Precipitation Forecasting for Agriculture Act.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3802</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230605">June 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To accelerate subseasonal to seasonal prediction skills related to precipitation forecasts for agriculture in the central United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3D0ABC48CFC4477A8C1D7B191C370968" style="OLC"><section id="H0CBE5362196C4B578A01C75C1F436774" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Precipitation Forecasting for Agriculture Act.</short-title></quote></text></section><section id="HFCD84986B7604B848FE656903980E97C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Central United States precipitation pilot project</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (h) of section 1762 of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8521">15 U.S.C. 8521</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H5EA533A06C7348D4B74B825D3411C865" style="OLC"><subsection id="H5FEC211F357C49AB83ABFF8A10897FFA"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Subseasonal to seasonal forecasting pilot projects</header><paragraph id="H39B486EEA9464F7D80A97DCFB0CEF27A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Under Secretary shall establish at least one pilot project within the U.S. Weather Research Program of the Oceanic and Atmospheric Research office of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to support improved subseasonal to seasonal precipitation forecasts for agriculture in the central United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21736131F3274CD48FD468CE0A07C8D3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Objectives</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Under Secretary shall ensure that a pilot project under paragraph (1) addresses key science challenges to improving forecasts and developing related products described in subsection (c) for agriculture in the central United States, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="H6E21548C1F0C4BAA9C4406957A245029"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Improving observations and accurate modeling of the land surface and hydrologic cycle, such as soil moisture and flash drought processes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46BD492AF09A47D8A8859D1AF71E3BD0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Improving fidelity in modeling of warm season precipitation processes.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30AD2E9843EF4A57BCE15BBEC5A6DEC2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Understanding and predicting large-scale upper-level dynamical flow anomalies that occur in spring and summer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A4907F68E3743E7B33B096A6CD6C86E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>A pilot project under this subsection shall include activities that carry out the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8C9A2E72713D4911A20BBF11033D12A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Best implement recommendations of the National Weather Service’s 2019 Report, entitled <quote>Subseasonal and Seasonal Forecasting Innovation: Plans for the Twenty-First Century</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1410C988395A4B719361562282B85115"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Achieve measurable objectives for operational forecast improvement.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2DD5D6AD0C146EC8CDC2EBAB8209859"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Engage with, and leverage the resources of, entities within the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in existence as of the date of the enactment of this subsection, including the Midwestern Regional Climate Center and the National Centers for Environmental Information.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2261C9BC28B4235A4E6DF27B09322F2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Are carried out in coordination with the Assistant Administrator for the Office of Oceanic and Atmospheric Research and the Director of the National Weather Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6E3E49904A5464A8166C58DCCEC7841"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>From amounts made available to Operations, Research, and Facilities at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, there is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67325A7A63AB43D7BE94B56D712C79F9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority under this subsection shall terminate on the date that is five years after the date of the enactment of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

