<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7B7426DFF02440BAAB992E2EF0F1DBCE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6380 IH: Wings for Veterans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6380</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231113">November 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000135">Mr. Van Orden</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Transportation to establish a pilot program to provide flight training for military veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA610D7A01A5949AE8212D4C73264CB46" style="OLC"><section id="H618061DAA22B484BA234E54BE65D1769" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Wings for Veterans Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3C63BB8655CD4E5B9BAFF832CC8735FB" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program for flight training</header><subsection id="H3B182F9530264772BEBC02A454DE4056"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall establish a pilot program (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>) to award grants to not more than 10 covered flight schools to provide flight training to eligible veterans.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB287DBD1274840568F3600EA884D9559"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each grant awarded under this section may not exceed $500,000.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC4C744CD24C14CACBC4F9C832767979C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible uses</header><text>A covered flight school may only use a grant awarded under the Program for the following:</text><paragraph id="H750FBB5A59274F67B4649696E045E84A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The provision of guidance and pilot training services, including tuition and flight training fees for veterans enrolled in such flight school and any training required for eligible veterans to earn the following certificates and ratings issued under part 141 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations:</text><subparagraph id="HFF781018AEAF4D339C4A21439A13815A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A private pilot certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADCCA74540F64143AAA4128B37369D6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A commercial pilot certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC9E500B4E4D4AE38FAB298CEF756F37"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A certified flight instructor certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2F0BB42D4914A3CBB3B4364A67FE628"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A certified flight instructor instrument certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H229FC8C6F8AF4F7FBB5B87FC29CFC6A5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An instrument rating.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB06AB34D7CC4FA190DA1B5D987EEFDA"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A multiengine rating.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BFECF081BCA43088AAC57C6A9500A5F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The provision of books, training materials, and equipment to support pilot training activities and related education for veterans enrolled in such flight school.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2EDE805F1F24D519BBD9E000176D6D0"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Administrative costs related to providing the services described in this subsection, not to exceed 10 percent of the amount awarded.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H259E138992F940CF866C1CC28C6B54CF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications To receive flight training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered flight school receiving a grant under the Program shall be responsible for—</text><paragraph id="HCCB2A385E1C14F0EA982EF4460DA2E1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>soliciting applications for flight training from eligible veterans;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA49FCA8125304769916B94323127B61F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reviewing such applications to verify that applicants meet the definition of eligible veteran; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21A55186332B44FD9AC9F3EF8596462F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">selecting from such applications eligible veterans to receive flight training and enrolling such veterans in appropriate flight training programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB2DFF34030BD48709D452C0D7BB2573C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Program shall terminate 18 months after the date on which the Program is established under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H4D6F8A5D713B490DB9B9DCEE55164950"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HA1D2141793B041B38F75CC96C8FE446A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reports to Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each covered flight school that receives a grant under the Program shall periodically submit to the Secretary a report describing the use of grant funds and include in such report documentation of training completed by veterans enrolled in such flight school under the Program. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0BCD9F543B44B3A8C8F3646C1D4E134"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the Program terminates under subsection (e), the Secretary of Transportation, in consultation with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall submit to the Committees on Education and Labor, Transportation and Infrastructure, and Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives, a report that includes a description of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HBD3193EF628646A5B189724B2D0EE1D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>How the improvement of the consistency and eligibility for assistance under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, may used to provide flight training to veterans.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3D22166BADF44E7BC359B9839020392"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The costs associated with obtaining a commercial pilot certificate and ways in which such costs could be reduced for veterans seeking a commercial pilot certificate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4833F8647E05444A9921FFF3FD34E13A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ways to increase cooperation between the Department of Transportation and veterans service organizations to recruit, screen, and train veterans as commercial pilots.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8702E9FE64054DA6B8719736568C658C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Ways to improve the availability of Federal student loans to veterans to use for attending vocational flight school.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAECD22A3A75547EFA5AF78A9F6197108"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A model program under which States and domestic commercial airlines provide assistance to veterans to obtain the flight training necessary to obtain a commercial pilot certificate with a multiengine rating.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45D40CBA608A4FEE93A42DE7CBDEFE68"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rates of successful completion of certification by veterans enrolled in a covered flight school under the Program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB573A7241172414690C65AF7BCFDCA3D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Challenges faced by such veterans while receiving flight training.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD63289573AAD4A4EA4EBA3C77DAA0DE8"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HB16072C853B545E78B6F7223D7D2F07B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered flight school</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered flight school</quote> means a flight school that holds a pilot school certificate under part 141 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BD0F5A1BD09411AA6ED6E84898E155D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible veteran</header><text>The term <quote>eligible veteran</quote> means an individual who—</text><subparagraph id="H86B06DD13CCE45A9B72B64D901BA4234"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">served in the active military, naval, air, or space service, and who was discharged or released from such service with an honorable discharge;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4990E82207984D119B1FB3EFD8461D2A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets regulatory requirements set forth by the Secretary to obtain at least a second class medical certificate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14331FD5BAD74D2CBE398266F6B0D4CB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>certifies an intent to pursue a career as a commercial pilot; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB944E6FA60A5425887353A7134221CAA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>meets any other requirements for eligibility as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

