<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1EAA9B13AA1A425BA250AFF92AEBDD78" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6669 IH: Supporting Americans Wrongfully or Unlawfully Detained Abroad Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6669</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide resources for United States nationals unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD6D5CB3BC22C4F09B18753B1F834862F" style="OLC"><section id="HC0FC520AF35E4CC98671191339ED93C0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting Americans Wrongfully or Unlawfully Detained Abroad Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H69B0FEE58BC945C1865ACC217DC70080"><enum>2.</enum><header>Resources for United States nationals unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 302(d) of the Robert Levinson Hostage Recovery and Hostage-Taking Accountability Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/1741">22 U.S.C. 1741(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H038BB87BF1F144798C1CEF956A31B412"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the subsection heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">Resource guidance</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="subsection">Resources for United States nationals unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad</header-in-text></quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7E17DAFCB0247479CC46EFDD24E5BC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking the paragraph heading and all that follows through <quote>Not later than</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAB2CB64813CE469C8B272103D0940DAA"><paragraph id="H2E7DECEA77854DDC95ACD123DE81ED81"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Resource guidance</header><subparagraph id="HC9F88D110A7C49E59FB71E35786F3657"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2D4574194A24FC396B833597D7613C5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by redesignating subparagraphs (A), (B), (C), (D), and (E) and clauses (i), (ii), (iii), (iv), and (v), respectively, and moving such clauses (as so redesignated) 2 ems to the right;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A789C9B1D72469AA3E50459B2DF65BC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (2) as subparagraph (B) and moving such subparagraph (as so redesignated) 2 ems to the right;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B7BBDEACB354F5A95B402943B74C80E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), as redesignated by paragraph (4), by striking <quote>paragraph (1)</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraph (A)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78E4CC8363A649E09B8775C326C671DA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H66D32B567E274F8F8C53A65A463C6008" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H993144698F894A10804252F2051789FE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Travel assistance</header><subparagraph id="H39C240F582B546A08C7BA6715FD3B713"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Family advocacy</header><text>For the purpose of facilitating meetings between the United States Government and the family members of United States nationals unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad, the Secretary shall provide financial assistance to cover the costs of travel to and from Washington, DC, including travel by air, train, bus, or other transit as appropriate, to any individual who—</text><clause id="HA5D39900CAE445C590DBD6E63F6822B0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is—</text><subclause id="H81A2E1E8BEAE41D69E0D759920E48039"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a family member of a United States national unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad as determined by the Secretary under subsection (a); or</text></subclause><subclause id="HE5630E046B8041FF9E5091C5025DC6D2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an appropriate individual who—</text><item id="H41EC700CC2644D3DBB8AECD7AC1C03C5"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is approved by the Special Presidential Envoy for Hostage Affairs; and</text></item><item id="H8122C5DA3A2749019DEACCDA1706EBEF"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>does not represent in any legal capacity a United States national unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad or the family of such United States national;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H0AAA4E96B65C43AEA4381D65038CC23A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has a permanent address that is more than 50 miles from Washington, DC; and</text></clause><clause id="H2B2CD9EB1B0C46CAAC4AEBF7786D2141"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>requests such assistance.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64800A56FB704BDF9BAD7C5FEA35AD1E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Travel and lodging</header><clause id="HD451E3ED1EDA49A4BA6F30B8CFEFCA86"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each such United States national unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad, the financial assistance described in subparagraph (A) shall be provided for not more than 2 trips per fiscal year, unless the Special Presidential Envoy for Hostage Affairs determines that a third trip is warranted. </text></clause><clause id="HA002EAF9DF95460D9365C4F2CE22B23D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>Any trip described in clause (i) shall—</text><subclause id="H4E7BF08F3A47461AA5682846CCB6F591"><enum>(I)</enum><text>consist of not more than 2 family members or other individuals approved in accordance with subparagraph (A)(i)(II), unless the Special Presidential Envoy for Hostage Affairs determines that circumstances warrant an additional family member or other individual approved in accordance with subparagraph (A)(i)(II) and approves assistance to such third family member or other individual; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H1CA33CEFF8A1438D8F0CC18575314D87"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not exceed more than 2 nights lodging, which shall not exceed the applicable government rate.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79AB12B63CA84D138132423599A1061A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Return travel</header><text>If other United States Government assistance is unavailable, the Secretary may provide to a United States national unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad as determined by the Secretary under subsection (a), United States assistance, as necessary, for return travel to the United States upon release of such United States national.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA80E77FD023D4412B69B48EC8EC859B5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Support</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H314ADFB2A65D4EF18ED30F411DC3713F"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>The Secretary shall seek to make available physical health services, mental health services, and other support as appropriate, including providing information on available legal or financial resources, to— </text><clause id="HEFD7FEC346DC463A92CD0C360E95BF3A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any United States national unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad; and </text></clause><clause id="H2438805089984991AD99DF3137FA0092"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any family member of such United States national.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5ED5CE4ADDED4B98B284A053F153014F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitations</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H548639F1414F49BFB2211D0B7CEC720B"><enum>(i)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>For any support described in subparagraph (A) for an individual described in clause (i) or (ii) of such subparagraph that commences following the return of a United States national who was unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad, such support shall be made available for up to 5 years from the date on which any individual identified in subparagraph (A) chooses to avail themselves of the support described in that subparagraph, unless the Special Presidential Envoy for Hostage Affairs determines that circumstances warrant extending such support.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A3A5EB238C8487387C276508A1D348B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The time limitation under clause (i) does not apply to any support provided during the pendency of the detention of a United States national unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DEF8B2311D64D748082672927180775"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Notification requirement</header><text>The Secretary shall notify the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate, the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives, and the Committees on Appropriations of the Senate and the House of Representatives of any amount spent above $250,000 for any fiscal year to carry out paragraphs (2) and (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC0381E8F86348C694965A1EEE3289BB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Funds authorized to be appropriated for the Department of State, which may include funds made available for unforeseen emergencies arising in the diplomatic and consular service, may be used to provide the support authorized by this section. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6D9F200261F4DC6849213CB360E59A5"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the end of each fiscal year, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Foreign Relations and Appropriations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs and Appropriations of the House of Representatives a report that includes—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H89E80768265F420682C31DF58F306B02"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a detailed description of expenditures made pursuant to paragraphs (2) and (3); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAFA05D627F7A471BB3919092C29F40E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a detailed description of types of support provided pursuant to paragraph (3), provided that such description does not identify any individuals receiving any physical or mental health support, in order to protect their privacy; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H4381B7CE54C84056866EF4CC32EE59CC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number and location of visits outside of Washington, DC, during the prior fiscal year made by the Special Presidential Envoy for Hostage Affairs to family members of each United States national unlawfully or wrongfully detained abroad.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H55676F0E9F4645A3A1F8D70F878FB05C"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority and requirements under paragraphs (2), (3), (4), and (5) shall terminate on December 31, 2027.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67CBE9486D4A43C1B278045534C61E86" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Family member defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>family member</term> means a spouse, father, mother, child, brother, sister, grandparent, grandchild, aunt, uncle, nephew, niece, cousin, father-in-law, mother-in-law, son-in-law, daughter-in-law, brother-in-law, sister-in-law, stepfather, stepmother, stepson, stepdaughter, stepbrother, stepsister, half brother, or half sister.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

