<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1F9D15D7124B4875B6247895D16C9856" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1487 IH: Office of Personnel Management Reform Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1487</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to reaffirm the role of the Office of Personnel Management as the leader for civilian human resource management in the Federal Government, to encourage innovation in the Office’s management of human capital, to strengthen the Office’s ability to support Federal human capital management as a strategic priority, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HA1F9233F20E44882865D44A7EDCCF174" style="OLC">
<section id="H01AF0D6CCF4E4FFD843E4F4066A1589D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Office of Personnel Management Reform Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC4FDCEE5ABCC462AB97E372FDAF795E7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Role and mission of Office of Personnel Management</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1101 of title 5, United States, Code is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H19E88B4319C1450B96381260DDA1E538"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>The Office of Personnel Management</quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC"><enum-in-header>(a) </enum-in-header>Establishment</header-in-text><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC"></header-in-text>.—The Office of Personnel Management</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3DE688E0AECD41C5B545B2D3D89F4F41"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H9B4109ED0DCF41509846012003619B4A" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="HDEA61634A407438286C5FD5AA6B7FB4B" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of Personnel Management shall lead the Federal Government in enterprise strategic human resources management, ensure the proper application of merit system principles for all Federal civilian human resource systems and employees, and carry out the policies set forth in section 3 of the Civil Service Reform Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/95/454">Public Law 95–454</external-xref>). In addition, the Office of Personnel Management shall—</text> <paragraph id="H01B8171BA94A4823949BA4BC15093E58" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>function as an independent human capital agency for Federal civilian personnel systems, employees, and annuitants;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H135FC99592D44547B6BD1A08DDD2206F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">structure as a streamlined organization capable of fulfilling all its missions in a manner that is effective, efficient, and readily navigable by those who interact with the agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E8BD01BA2A7404283A07D4890863A34" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide Government-wide leadership and facilitate appropriate and efficient access to human capital data and systems to support strategic Government-wide human capital management;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBB5576A2AD7942D58FBA42B19767D199" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>use information technology and data, data analytics, and predictive analytics to inform decision making, identify best practices and drive innovation;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41A83D61B29A493AA83E1AAC8745628D" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>develop both current and forward-looking approaches for human resource management;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA5504149B7004F5B931A0F24FB0158AE" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish and maintain an efficient, and, as appropriate, risk-based and data-driven oversight program in support of merit systems principles and other statutory requirements OPM is obligated to enforce; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H09C6AE0412E64B15B8DC316E76E37940" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote staff capacity-building to support a competent and diverse workforce, consistent with the requirements of chapter 41 of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
<section id="H55708A8EC375427BA8CAF84EA35D79AA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Qualifications of OPM Director</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/11">Chapter 11</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HA9F3AF3D568949E7B25BB37ADA53DEE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 1102—</text>
<subparagraph id="H410DC1840D354457B5B51B248C1AE055"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by adding at the end after the period the following: <quote>The individual appointed as Director shall be appointed without regard to political affiliation and have demonstrated human capital expertise and management and leadership experience.</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4C5E0895B2804E91A6B1792C5D7026C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding after subsection (d) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1EF70CE4A1E04FA98439F0D85D93A037" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="H1FB265D708D049C3B90162767280DA43"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual serving as Director or Deputy Director may be removed from office by the President only if the reasons for such removal are specifically set forth in a written statement submitted to the Committee on Oversight and Reform in the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs in the Senate. The President shall communicate in writing the reasons for any such removal to both Houses of Congress not later than 30 days before the removal. </text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21700A5B26474CCABCC3EF7544E7FF89"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 1103(a) by—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4B598070BBF34B9C833596873EBD4D0B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">redesignating paragraph (9) as paragraph (12);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBF642BF24C2D4B9F944890A3867A4D18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of paragraph (8); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4C0EE07A1CA74B18A88474FAEE006203"><enum>(C)</enum><text>inserting after paragraph (8) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H1724AFABA31D45BAAAD8C8338B448495" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H6DD0D5BF4F9C4AB291A205DA6B7117A5"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serving as the principal advisor to the President on Federal human capital policies and leading Federal civilian human capital efforts to attract and retain the optimal Federal workforce;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD46D4FAE55FB48C5A9147AD2DA232EC5"><enum>(10)</enum><text>establishing a framework for Federal agency workforce management and working with stakeholders to develop policies that foster best practices in all human capital areas;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB01B3BB02F55448EA25D94C893870C20"><enum>(11)</enum><text>setting standards of practice and working collaboratively across the Federal human capital community; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="HA682E82D91FD4901961945D71B87A26F"><enum>4.</enum><header>OPM Chief Management Officer</header>
<subsection id="HF48067AC46D04E958176CE55CCD5794C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1102 of title 5, United States Code, as amended by section 3, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H5CD1563FDE40443E94ACE311D289D48E" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H495152CAF6F44BA0AC0DB4916B11F616"><enum>(f)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA44EFAEDB39B480AA92A3098F124D982"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established within the Office of Personnel Management the position of Chief Management Officer. Such position shall be filled by a member of the Senior Executive Service in a designated career reserved position. The Director shall establish and appoint an individual to occupy such position not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Office of Personnel Management Reform Act</short-title>. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H686DF27E98E64CBB9E71649B6562F5B6" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Subject to the authority, direction, and control of the Director, the Chief Management Officer shall perform such duties and exercise such powers as the Director may prescribe, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HA8F69FCACC68411F9ED84991020913FB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assisting the Director and Deputy Director to provide continuity, strengthen internal agency organization and management, promoting the mission and strategic goals of the Office, and improving Office performance;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA0E7C3F4CD9F4752B68EEF6B021B8818"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during periods in which the Deputy Director position is vacant, serving as the principal advisor to the Director on all operations, activities, and programs in the Office;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBEC8CB54060549F684B2969FBB7CA4CA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>directing the associate Directors, program divisions, and support functions of the Office on matters for which the Chief Management Officer has responsibility;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1A7577B01B2144D89E3C4AA3F9DDF116"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during periods in which the Deputy Director position is vacant, establishing processes for supervising operations of the Office and unifying management efforts across the Office;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD19D90AB3C7E4F63885330A035002EB2"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aligning human resources policies and programs of the Office with the organization mission, goals and performance outcomes;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H40F652CB374940F5A15C0A84C583E523"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing a culture of continuous learning and positive employee engagement within the Office to attract and retain employees; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD707789483F647518AAE23B6D8C017C1"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying leading practices and benchmarks relevant to the Officer’s areas of responsibility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="HE3D28C3EAB894577A3E5C37BD1D613CF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header>
<paragraph id="H2932B0A5445B40FAB0E07165D172E888"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Section heading</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The section heading for section 1102 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding after <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="USC">Associate Directors</header-in-text></quote> the following: <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="USC">; Chief Management Officer</header-in-text></quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC9AA9810F5D0430183E4FC69BDB49BFA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Table of sections</header><text>The table of sections for chapter 11 of such title is amended by striking the item relating to section 1102 and inserting the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H2EE5693D5F3148DE8FCACB72B829D373" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">1102. Director; Deputy Director; Associate Directors; Chief Management Officer.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HC58B6AEE3F9640659B8BC818BA73F3DA"><enum>5.</enum><header>Federal Workforce Advisory Committee</header>
<subsection id="HA18ACBEFE31143969C00F3EAE447D375"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/11">Chapter 11</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H5D93487D7A8A47ABB51A1873AA47D507" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H66A2F7117F974E60957DEC3E330F345F"><enum>1106.</enum><header>Federal Workforce Advisory Committee</header> <subsection id="H5F6B53D895D2458D849E63ED318A93F8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <paragraph id="HCCD438F4EF474ABB91C1193BDF8DE452"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of the Office of Personnel Management Reform Act, the Director of the Office of Personnel Management (in this section referred to as the <quote>Director</quote>) shall establish within the Office an advisory committee to be known as the <quote>Federal Workforce Advisory Committee</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Advisory Committee</quote>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFA6914712C6D406CAFC8BE8C286CB393"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall advise and provide information and recommendations to the Director on—</text> <subparagraph id="HDA8CB0D8D143416D8060309324898DBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>strategies for making the Federal Government an employer of choice and model employer;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA0F09CA4D4C847D989010772E9CAD575"><enum>(B)</enum><text>approaches for recruiting, hiring, and retaining people with needed skills to improve Federal services; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9D788BC09FFA404ABCF74DE9C6F42595"><enum>(C)</enum><text>programs and initiatives to build and support a diverse, trusted, and effective Federal workforce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8909B89A68954F788582A86658763413"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header>
<paragraph id="H6B870BB930EB4A9EB463FE2503343B49"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header>
<subparagraph id="H817B217F59DB4C77951A4393DF6B989A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>The Director shall appoint not more than 15 members, excluding ex officio members in paragraph (2), to the Advisory Committee. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD8051DA4E1854BC7A403F7F5C8F159C0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Representation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall ensure that individuals appointed as members of the Advisory Committee shall possess knowledge and experience in human capital management and have experience in at least one of the following categories:</text>
<clause id="H134C7CC9EB744685B0C17AC69F55946F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public sector or governmental organizations, including global public sector human resource professionals.</text></clause> <clause id="H9F6E8E0D15EB4A0D95BAD661DB6B39DC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Nonprofit organizations, including labor unions.</text></clause>
<clause id="HB09BC0B59D41482B8ECCC22742582768"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Private sector organizations.</text></clause> <clause id="HF7AD9FFA8AB14271AFE2F5111276A736"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Academia.</text></clause>
<clause id="H5E77CEEA4C9C4A298B2294BC4E8D7AB9"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal employee, retiree, and labor organizations, including organizations that represent substantial numbers of Federal employees occupying General Schedule positions.</text></clause> <clause id="H800D2BDF25744BEBB7597179646AE9FA"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chief Human Capital Officers or other members from Federal agency human resource offices.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8297EFBF065A4539B76B178C9CE2F422"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ex officio members</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The following positions shall serve as ex officio members of the Advisory Committee: the Director, the Deputy Director, any Associate Director, the Chief Management Officer, the Chief Diversity, Equity, Inclusion and Accessibility Officer, the Chief Human Capital Officers Council Executive Director, and other Federal officials at the discretion of the Director.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H444527482B8C43DDAD2CEDAB97B9E928"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administrative provisions</header> <paragraph id="HBD5561F7CC9A414C9F02B19DCA2998A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Meetings</header> <subparagraph id="H64400156EF0C4530973F504AD75B24FC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Advisory Committee shall meet at least two times per year. The Chair may request additional meetings, with such additional meetings subject to the approval of the Director.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HACC274B417A747B8AED6DD85698DFD2A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Opportunity for public comment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each meeting shall include, at a minimum, opportunity for public comment during the Advisory Committee’s deliberations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB3D2F7F21AA54A5A8D0ACEC59743269C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bylaws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the first meeting of the Advisory Committee, the members shall select a chairperson and vice chairperson. The Advisory Committee’s bylaws shall be established by the chairperson and vice chairperson and shall be submitted to the members for unanimous approval by the members.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H99D7357EA6544334A7A5EF0F031C4A6D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>Seven members of the Advisory Committee shall constitute a quorum.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEBF571017D8245A2AE59A97D458CD7D2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Decisions and recommendations by consensus</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All decisions, activities, findings, and recommendations of the Advisory Committee shall be made by consensus of the members of the Advisory Committee.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HBD2108DCFE83404EABEAC4022C549D70"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the first meeting of the Advisory Committee and annually thereafter, the Advisory Committee shall submit an annual report to the Director, the Committee on Oversight and Reform of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate. The Director shall make the report available online on a publicly accessible website. The report shall contain—</text> <paragraph id="H8A7DB3F5451C49EAA5675AD92586EFD6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a detailed summary of the agenda and activities of, and the findings and recommendations made by, the Advisory Committee during the previous year;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H91FFE89EB171456497B597F6A628ADCE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if applicable, any agency actions taken to address the findings and recommendations made by the Advisory Committee; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD6F0B118D9DD44AD81491512C99417C8"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a detailed list of subjects and areas of interest that the Advisory Committee plans to examine in the next year.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H22710FF3FCF44E69A481BA81ADC7C9B7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective on December 31, 2026, the Advisory Committee and the authority of the Advisory Committee shall terminate.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H27A69038B33443B3B8EA93D7DE792794"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for such chapter 11 is amended by adding after the item relating to section 1105 the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HF4C0049D3102413193EFD2DECFD539E0" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">1106. Federal Workforce Advisory Committee.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


