<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H76ECB287930E4C528B9769DADE4EC9FC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1445 IH: Prioritizing Accountability and Accessibility for Aviation Consumers Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1445</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230308">March 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Transportation to annually report on aviation consumer complaints related to passengers with a disability.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H06FE3BAAB14E45EF893037215524677D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HAFDC7B8DD77743FDBD7741F950655E7B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Prioritizing Accountability and Accessibility for Aviation Consumers Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE96E90C343DF49AA89CCBED36BDC3074"><enum>2.</enum><header>Annual report of the Secretary of Transportation on aviation consumer complaints related to passengers with a disability</header> <subsection id="HBCEC98218E9D46C6BA67461C3D9BB94F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Transportation shall submit a report on aviation consumer complaints related to passengers with a disability filed with the Department of Transportation to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives, and shall make each report publicly available. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="H2BA30210D3774C57BBB84D461C3D32EA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Each report submitted under subsection (a) shall include, but not be limited to, the following:</text> <paragraph id="HF23EDA55B3A04B2BB1BE32509225F0E2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of aviation consumer complaints related to passengers with a disability filed with the Department of Transportation during the 5 most recent calendar years. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H3E032FC0A5D14AA7AFCF6EB3EBB0517B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The nature of such complaints, such as reported issues with—</text> <subparagraph id="H3A4F98CAE45D46EE8BCB6100DE91E45C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an air carrier, including an air carrier's staff training or lack thereof; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA4961EC75E024D049A6711E1723FBD55"><enum>(B)</enum><text>mishandling of passengers with a disability or their accessibility equipment;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H76268691928A4406A0E617D786DF3A89"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the accessibility of in-flight services for passengers with a disability;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0F5F4BA3D5324F8AB86181840D02CC81"><enum>(D)</enum><text>difficulties experienced by passengers with a disability in communicating with an air carrier or staff of an air carrier;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5DFB4593A62B46948BE62F0E0EC2E730"><enum>(E)</enum><text>difficulties experienced by passengers with a disability in being moved, handled, or having their schedule changed without consent;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8CC9BB5DDD504A6FACC6B9AAB1B9D8FC"><enum>(F)</enum><text> issues experienced by passengers with a disability traveling with a service animal; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H80E7355994CE4A5481B5B32C294DC718" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(G)</enum><text>such other issues as the Secretary of Transportation deems appropriate. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCD741CE58A204A6D9E36CDCF84679D37"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An overview of the review process for such complaints received during such period.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8F6EC9D2723F490694294089CC798305"><enum>(4)</enum><text>How quickly review for each such complaint was initiated. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H416AB3B9595A4CEEAD7C9BCA48D8DEB3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>How quickly each such complaint was resolved or otherwise addressed.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2E365C429E3F45C8AE749521E3556742"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Of the complaints that were found to violate section 41705 of title 49, United States Code, (commonly known as the <quote>Air Carrier Access Act of 1986</quote>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5D4F19BB35C54FF0927D355D94E914F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of such complaints for which a formal enforcement order was issued; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H87E8085514F6483A93B224717FDFA90E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of such complaints for which a formal enforcement order was not issued.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1F0B4FDE779A448F92B830372A5F770B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>How many aviation consumer complaints related to passengers with a disability were referred to the Department of Justice for an enforcement action under—</text> <subparagraph id="H239EFE556040499C854FA22BF9E97DDD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB66EBED0D3F04316AC4D300B9F735EBF" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC8D3707E10C34C5CADF4E7B83303C547" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other provision of law. </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H8921B172329345C390F6C494C095BA7B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>How many aviation consumer complaints related to passengers with a disability filed with the Department of Transportation that involved airport staff, or other matters under the jurisdiction of the Federal Aviation Administration, were referred to the Federal Aviation Administration. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA3E0C2CBC9F9411FADA32625A4917E19" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(9)</enum><text>How many aviation consumer complaints related to passengers with a disability filed with the Department of Transportation that involved Transportation Security Administration staff, or other matters under the jurisdiction of the Transportation Security Administration, were referred to the Transportation Security Administration or the Department of Homeland Security. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB6D3F8CCE3A74F2D9D43B2DC96227EBF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header>
<paragraph id="H7894E56D84D44894AE514A97BA4E2D06"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The definitions set forth in section 40102 of title 49, United States Code, and section 382.3 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, apply to any term defined in such sections that is used in this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B992729C0DF4C2E808E2659F5F1E282" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Passengers with a disability defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>passengers with a disability</term> has the meaning given the term <term>qualified individual with a disability</term> in section 382.3 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5D368AED8F1642EC814EA0A7F1180232"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out this section. </text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

