<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDABE32CFAF474584A742BC0458DE0651" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4107 IH: Civil Liberties Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4107</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 31, United States Code, to establish the Civil Liberties Protection Officer for the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7933C61C7F174E60AA901EDC9E7C6422" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2D039B83C2334833BF107EDD5E6B60E7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Civil Liberties Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H28FF3D5303934A5EB5D42D4E7BB9294F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Civil Liberties Protection Officer for the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 301 of title 31, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HCA3ABFFFD7954F9E9F4D810969C5554A" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="HD307BDE1A6064F1AABBA6B35D61D0189"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Civil Liberties Protection Officer for the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network</header> 
<paragraph id="H5FEDD5B4D8DA4DC89EDF84391C68BBB9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within the Office of the Secretary of the Treasury, there shall be a Civil Liberties Protection Officer for the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network who shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H71094F2745334B1A814493F3AF90227D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be designated by the Secretary of the Treasury from among members of the Senior Executive Service; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H029424BCBBDF4F48B154327A4FF526AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">report directly to and be supervised directly by the Secretary of the Treasury or, if so assigned by the Secretary, the Deputy Secretary of the Treasury.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BD32234F8394BFA98D0A7186558DD5A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Civil Liberties Protection Officer for the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H561A4720372B485281A4DDC11CDF028E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that protection of civil liberties and privacy is appropriately incorporated in the activities conducted by the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF6B443D5C5B940E0BEFF53FEF4B23DA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>oversee compliance by the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network with requirements under the Constitution and all laws, regulations, and implementing guidelines relating to civil liberties and privacy;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H683B4503639A4E55B9F29CD610EB0D3E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>review and assess complaints and other information indicating possible abuses of civil liberties and privacy in the administration of the programs and operations of the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network and, as appropriate, refer such complaints or information for investigation to the Office of Audit and Investigations for the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6186BFDFDCC143E4892EE88BA42A2F76"><enum>(D)</enum><text>ensure that the use by the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network of technologies sustains, and does not erode, privacy protections relating to the use, collection, and disclosure of personal information;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8E8D218604A54613ABCF3C135C1A64F5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>ensure that personal information contained in a system of records subject to section 552a of title 5 (commonly referred to as the <quote>Privacy Act</quote>) is handled by the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network in compliance with that section;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE8F8F04F38D347F49EAEDBDADFE34FAA"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct an annual privacy impact assessments of the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network and provide a report containing the findings to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC085B0C1EC0E43319B222047B13FA902"><enum>(G)</enum><text>perform such other duties relating directly to protection of civil liberties and privacy by the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network as may be prescribed by the Secretary of the Treasury.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFDFA329D54BB4EA98E7FD4A8C40E3770"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Civil Liberties Protection Officer for the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network shall keep the following individuals appropriately informed of the Officer’s activities:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H59F8D64AE3FB41B091CB32640E2690E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Department of the Treasury’s Chief Privacy Officer (as described under section 522 of division H of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000ee-2">42 U.S.C. 2000ee–2</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H33A8E04ADF6C41F28C530658B4CFA001"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of the Treasury’s Privacy and Civil Liberties Officer (as designated pursuant to section 1062 of the National Security Intelligence Reform Act of 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000ee-1">42 U.S.C. 2000ee–1</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H68F6A81C5CF64A90ACA5E7039280868D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Information for constitutional functions of Congress</header> 
<subsection id="H41C29E3F0F764298ADD31C6B9DC72218"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Keeping Congress informed</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall keep the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate fully and currently informed of the activities of the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network, including any significant anticipated activity of such Network.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB5EDDFF1526748BBA730F008FDBE6EAA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report of unlawful activity and corrective action</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall report promptly to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs any unlawful activity of the Financial Crimes Enforcement Network and any corrective action taken or planned to address that activity and prevent such activity in the future.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

