<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9FDBE384E05349679EE8135EBD6DABB6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4483 IH: School Food Modernization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4483</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Appropriations</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act to require the Secretary of Agriculture to make loan guarantees and grants to finance certain improvements to school lunch facilities, to train school food service personnel, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBE73F24D7D514AF8820EDADBB2BEA452" style="OLC"><section id="H6ACF08EF842D4CD5B2EBD88ABD38185F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>School Food Modernization Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD30D4A0D31314924B0F1B22831AF484F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Loan guarantees and grants to finance certain improvements to school lunch facilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act is amended by inserting after section 26 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1769g">42 U.S.C. 1769g</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block id="H1D6838C411664D81AC468CB570BF9916" style="OLC"><section id="HD1F4A8AB3DDF4DDAA640E2B3BB3A3872"><enum>27.</enum><header>Loan guarantees and grants to finance certain improvements to school lunch facilities</header><subsection id="HC2A2EDEC1135452B831D05DC2AABC53C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H23E361172E484FEA8F4DE6026FAC7BEF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Durable equipment</header><text>The term <term>durable equipment</term> means durable food preparation, handling, cooking, serving, and storage equipment greater than $500 in value.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CEF6EAEDDFD4C138DA458FC0CF44D2E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H98E325BDC8BD408DAC079049DFDE87E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a local educational agency or a school food authority administering or operating a school meal program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H253D4D5CDFBD47BD8DCBE964DB661589"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a tribal organization; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA63DF658CFFE42CCA87B5600377C091A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a consortium that includes a local educational agency or school food authority described in subparagraph (A), a tribal organization, or both.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A036B5F479344D882B0E81534068933"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Infrastructure</header><text>The term <term>infrastructure</term> means a food storage facility, kitchen, food service facility, cafeteria, dining room, or food preparation facility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAAC808C4013A462BAADEAB1A3B0396DF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>local educational agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75EAB906E99145F1925AD6DFF81D0F95"><enum>(5)</enum><header>School food authority</header><text>The term <term>school food authority</term> has the meaning given the term in section 210.2 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6D00DCE450B4925A154131910123D84"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Tribal organization</header><text>The term <term>tribal organization</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA6C4A9C731B94C72BFA101E2E123C951"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Loan guarantees for assistance to schools for infrastructure improvements and durable equipment necessary To provide healthy meals through school meal programs</header><paragraph id="HBDB4620351E54850B7BDE273AEE8234F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority to guarantee loans</header><text>The Secretary shall issue a loan guarantee to an eligible lender for purposes of financing the construction, remodeling, or expansion of infrastructure or the purchase of durable equipment that the Secretary determines will assist the eligible entity in providing healthy meals through a school meal program authorized under this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBB09E82C9B540FD870639050E64AA92"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text>In issuing a loan guarantee under this subsection, the Secretary shall give a preference to an eligible entity that, as compared with other eligible entities seeking a loan guarantee under this subsection, the Secretary determines demonstrates substantial or disproportionate—</text><subparagraph id="H4C2FE55697594B7C93A577B87DA97345"><enum>(A)</enum><text>need for infrastructure improvement; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE91415E2C645467EA424D008B133325B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>durable equipment need or impairment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEB45A1C2C604C16AC4E39F346BF1F62"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Oversight</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Under Secretary for Rural Development, shall establish procedures to oversee any project or purchase for which a loan guarantee is issued under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B2E912D66E8499F8563D6A9EC63872F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Guarantee amount</header><text>A loan guarantee issued under this subsection may not guarantee more than 80 percent of the principal amount of the loan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H986F47C3D2C94B66B3FEC9C09F07A1D0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Fees and costs</header><subparagraph id="HFE587F8E40E84AF3B93932F5C15586C7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish fees for loan guarantees under this subsection that are, to the maximum extent practicable, equal to all costs of the loan guarantees as determined under the Federal Credit Reform Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661">2 U.S.C. 661 et seq.</external-xref>), as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9013ABFBDC3143498347A4C370CE1FD9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Fee shortfall</header><text>To the extent that the Secretary determines that fees described in subparagraph (A) are not sufficient to pay for all of the costs for the loan guarantees pursuant to the Federal Credit Reform Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661">2 U.S.C. 661 et seq.</external-xref>), the Secretary may use funds described in paragraph (6) to pay for the costs of loan guarantees not paid for by the fees.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H20A951E77F6F4637B7C44024D65F1325"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Funding</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H194518B75956416596360D5FA7F7C016"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To provide loan guarantees under this subsection, the Secretary shall reserve $300,000,000 of the loan guarantee authority remaining and unobligated as of the date of enactment of the School Food Modernization Act under the program of community facility guaranteed loans under section 306(a) of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1926">7 U.S.C. 1926(a)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D1B138AE1FD4D578CB9A33EE2C7FA72"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary may use not more than 5 percent of the amount made available to carry out this subsection for each fiscal year to provide technical assistance to applicants and prospective applicants in preparing applications and creating financing packages that leverage a mix of public and private funding sources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H69089D5444EB44FBAA1A558ED7B672E5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Equipment grants</header><paragraph id="H9EBFCB5C31954057A077A592ED86759B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority to make grants</header><text>Beginning in fiscal year 2024 and subject to the availability of appropriations, provide grants to State agencies for competitive subgrants to local educational agencies and schools (tribes) to purchase the equipment needed to serve healthy meals, improve food safety, and to help support the establishment, maintenance and expansion of the school.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB017D04DDA834398AAECA87754B20A9D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Preferences</header><text>In issuing a grant under this subsection, the State agency shall give a preference to an eligible entity that, as compared with other eligible entities seeking a loan guarantee under this subsection, the State agency determines demonstrates substantial or disproportionate—</text><subparagraph id="HB808A245C53B4525A42288D978F76B98"><enum>(A)</enum><text>need for infrastructure improvement; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55FE74ECF1E54C2790AE9486A5C87908"><enum>(B)</enum><text>durable equipment need or impairment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1762393738264B81824FB822D16AF55C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subparagraph id="H363F9A578A8940338541BD1D9334031C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated $35,000,000 as may be necessary to carry out this subsection for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H989146758F37466891CE338A83DD70D9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary may use not more than 5 percent of the amount made available to carry out this subsection for each fiscal year to provide technical assistance to applicants and prospective applicants in preparing applications and creating financing packages that leverage a mix of public and private funding sources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H85D157C2EE864B28806A295462027E5D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Training and technical assistance for school food service personnel</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act is amended by inserting after section 21 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1769b-1">42 U.S.C. 1769b–1</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block id="H7E65FB8084B541469EFF6FBB0D6BD8E5" style="OLC"><section id="HFE2D839693824622990DB4E965875CA2"><enum>21A.</enum><header>Training and technical assistance for school food service personnel</header><subsection id="H5D7B84F716BA4FE8A825DD98043C4A81"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a grant program under which the Secretary shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to provide support to eligible third-party training institutions described in subsection (b) to develop and administer training and technical assistance for school food service personnel to meet or exceed nutrition standards under section 4(b)(3) and improve efficacy and efficiency of the school lunch program under this Act and the school breakfast program established by section 4 of the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1773">42 U.S.C. 1773</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H78F872361C284E688A46B0DBE8C5201F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible Third-Party Institutions Defined</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>eligible third-party institution</term> means—</text><paragraph id="HF05040BAB6644BD5B35529EE3E73644B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization with demonstrated experience in food or nutrition services training and technical assistance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02CD12396DFC46848A706EEF6448DE87"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an institution of higher education as defined in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF7836813F97404AB5A1A28930BD08B5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an area career and technical education school as defined in section 3 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2302">20 U.S.C. 2302</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D8E6811A6C9441297A09036C2CD79E3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a consortium of entities described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H941C31C800704761B2DD07C9F8482A34"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Criteria for eligible third-Party institutions</header><text>The Secretary shall establish specific criteria that eligible third-party training institutions shall meet to qualify to receive grants under this section, which shall include—</text><paragraph id="H3F2ED725C30B4E0D9D31A3CBD40DBACF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a demonstrated capacity to administer effective training and technical assistance programming to school food service personnel;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8161D0322FE4D0AACCD351052EEE8A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>prior, successful experience in providing or engaging in training and technical assistance programming or applied research activities involving eligible entities, school food service administrators, or directors;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3EE064C01184A84AD4356582FA680E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>prior, successful experience in developing relevant educational training tools or course materials or curricula on topics addressing child and school nutrition or the updated nutrition standards under section 4(b)(3); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F1B00CA01394ABC8D03FEB4590E83BA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the ability to deliver effective and cost-efficient training and technical assistance programming to school food service personnel—</text><subparagraph id="H93D25CBB1F9E41B791DECF3348CAE594"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at training sites that are located within a proximate geographic distance to schools, central kitchens, or other worksites; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA99FFF24F64A49B180215036FD054B58"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through an online training and assistance program on topics that do not require in-person attendance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5D29BFF9E9214868B5DFC93B406BBCEE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Program assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall assist the institutions receiving grants under this section in publicizing and disseminating training and other project materials and online tools to the maximum extent practicable.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0109E19E35594DD1AC212F8DB6BD9B34"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Federal share</header><paragraph id="H54A3DC25CA7F411582006B96CD29D9C9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Federal share of costs for training and technical assistance funded through a grant awarded under this section shall not exceed 80 percent of the total cost of the training and technical assistance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCDC6A2E3B52147D59708698C12B44B15"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matching</header><text>As a condition of receiving a grant under this section, the eligible third-party training institution shall provide matching support in the form of cash or in-kind contributions.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBC9AE96FD5B74F2FAEA9C82A4B066AD1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Oversight</header><text>The Secretary shall establish procedures to enable the Secretary—</text><paragraph id="HBCDA7D00D5284B819D284F8EC5F4ABCF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to oversee the administration and operation of training and technical assistance funded through grants awarded under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A9463F07A6B464AB8E87C6A4B366951"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to ensure that the training and assistance is operated consistent with the goals and requirements of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1CDB926B9D742488A9408B61950E7C5"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="H64104084E7964ADE8A8B92AA4A4B0FE1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 to carry out this section for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H792A42354B9646649C1A595182E3D3B5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary may use not more than 5 percent of the amount made available to carry out this section for each fiscal year to provide technical assistance to applicants and prospective applicants in preparing applications and creating financing packages that leverage a mix of public and private funding sources.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H287A07F1D1284C22BF34AAF089BFF9B2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after funds are made available to carry out sections 21A and 27 of the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act (as added by this Act), and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Agriculture shall submit to Congress a report on the progress of the Secretary in implementing such sections.</text></section><section id="H3BE6411565F84506B989274BD20B2AF7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Study and report to Congress on the use of State administrative expense funds</header><subsection id="HCB9ED34EAD1544DFB4FCD4C36E064E05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture shall conduct a study on—</text><paragraph id="H4A5AE6674A4D4391ABA7022B024779D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use of State administrative expense funds by State agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD548B9B0E74546BE877DFBE2D0B23544"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">innovative, effective, replicable, model policies, practices, and training methods that may be implemented using State administrative expense funds;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67859C7E5CC048E4AE1C849CA24466C4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>factors that interfere with the ability of State agencies to use State administrative expense funds effectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F3A1F5460CB4A7FBB0FCF3466B13E10"><enum>(4)</enum><text>how State administrative expense funds may be used to encourage the implementation of effective and consistent school nutrition workforce training, with particular emphasis on training and technical assistance to improve the implementation of nutrition standards for all foods sold in schools including—</text><subparagraph id="H892BF53F1789448CAC73A4D7743ABBBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nutrition standards for foods sold in schools other than foods provided under the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 and the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H288E044DBA0F4B718D016B47E9983610"><enum>(B)</enum><text>local school wellness policies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6E7C53ABF98433FBBBA06DE4875F829"><enum>(C)</enum><text>professional standards for school nutrition professionals; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C9341EB671944EB8A4EBD5A6866FB45"><enum>(D)</enum><text>other school food service practices, standards, and operational requirements as the Secretary may identify as requiring additional assistance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H376B5A5E8C3346568291CAFA86267511"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Development and use of assessment tool</header><paragraph id="H6A7FA97CA3A84B98A2AAE315576B2C67"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture shall develop an assessment tool for the purpose of carrying out the study under subsection (a). Such tool shall include a general methodology for evaluating effectiveness of State agencies in providing training and technical assistance using State administrative expense funds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B3ED367B1354071884E0C6202C4AC27"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination with other Entities</header><text>In developing the assessment tool under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consider public research, stakeholder input, and direct feedback from school nutrition personnel.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H02D3F8071AD640A7A118D39E971D18BD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate and the Committee on Education and Labor of the House of Representatives a report containing—</text><paragraph id="HF9A5C40E3C5940859B33C1E39946B3F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a summary of the study conducted under subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4ED01327BF46465B9963E8DCF7908649"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any findings and recommendations resulting from such study;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2454406823A4DC899E0BCBC69DB55D1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a plan for disseminating to State agencies best practices on the use of State administrative expense funds for training and technical assistance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF09745463C154AFB8D99BA47F505F7C5"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations, if any, for the ongoing monitoring and improvement of training and technical assistance carried out by State agencies using State administrative expense funds.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H60C3CB88C5A04C38A6B6C9A1C5E8190F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H3B242ED4F6DF4FCDB0A95151A8C8E8C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State administrative expense funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State administrative expense funds</term> means the State administrative expense funds described in part 235 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H234F8C8AAC0548B0AA2275CB456A3E38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State agency</header><text>The term <term>State agency</term> has the meaning given the term in section 235.2 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H027A84B8A4DD42FE9A486258620FFCF9" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Offset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Of the unobligated balance available for administrative expenses of the Department of Education, $45,000,000 is rescinded.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

