<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFEE2CBF5652140A981B6D60441F9DFA4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4206 IH: Bank Safety Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4206</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230620">June 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Financial Stability Act of 2010 to require covered financial institutions to include elements of accumulated other comprehensive income when calculating capital for purposes of meeting capital requirements, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H87D54E182FA647918B1C264137065BDB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE6AD68D4D060482EB704EBEF6591CDCC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Bank Safety Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H719A646AAA004E1BA39BB8462140AC69"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inclusion of elements of accumulated other comprehensive income in capital requirements for covered financial institutions</header> <subsection id="H2E71EA7E5D1F4A52A96C31B178219485"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 165 of the Financial Stability Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5365">12 U.S.C. 5365</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3900DF7E39A94EB5A6D06E182454D694" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H7605EA3B26664B7BA77590D803D5F7FF"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Inclusion of elements of accumulated other comprehensive income</header> 
<paragraph id="H29F9FB875A8540EEB11EC1AE58417362"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The computation of capital for purposes of meeting capital requirements for a covered financial institution shall include all accumulated other comprehensive income components, except for accumulated net gains and losses on cash flow hedges related to items that are not recognized at fair value.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H80827B519DC345F78922E5AC7F20AC33"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered financial institution defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <quote>covered financial institution</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H38F0C78B325C416096358E866A8B6B46"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a bank holding company (as defined in section 2(a) of the Bank Holding Company Act of 1956 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1841">12 U.S.C. 1841(a)</external-xref>)) with total consolidated assets greater than $100,000,000,000;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H183B20E0B32A4EFDBD05F9A7EF42BA8B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a insured depository institution over which a bank holding company does not have control with total consolidated assets greater than $100,000,000,000; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE639123F51CE432CBA6C973E4D12A461"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other bank holding company or insured depository institution, as determined by the appropriate Federal banking agencies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HB9A94B1C297E48C38C0C434654F8A8D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A covered financial institution (as defined in section 165(l) of the Financial Stability Act of 2010, as added by this Act) that elected to opt out of the requirement to report accumulated other comprehensive income components pursuant to the rule titled <quote>Changes to Applicability Thresholds for Regulatory Capital and Liquidity Requirements</quote> (84 Fed. Reg. 59230; November 1, 2019) shall be subject to the requirements of subsection (l) of section 165 of the Financial Stability Act of 2010, as added by this Act, on the effective date described in subsection (c).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H278F0E1693E8485E81B591326DF16243"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The appropriate Federal banking agencies (as defined in section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1813">12 U.S.C. 1813</external-xref>)) shall issue final rules to carry out this Act and the amendments made by this Act that shall take effect on a date not earlier than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and not later than December 31, 2024.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

