<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC6D465B2F43342128F6AC4CF4759EE60" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5335 IH: Special Forest Products Program Reauthorization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5335</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Agriculture to carry out a program to charge and collect not less than the fair market value for forest botanical products harvested on National Forest System lands, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HD0AD4CCA29C547BF9AAA4960C97F62FA" style="OLC"> 
<section commented="no" id="HFAA09265AAE5408AB3AD14D151487ABA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Special Forest Products Program Reauthorization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H95F275E484B34C8F9A85533B0F046988"><enum>2.</enum><header>Charges and fees for harvest of forest botanical products</header> <subsection id="HD4032937C74D4C27A7292F2B962E71A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Recovery of fair market value for products</header> <paragraph id="H9F89860DA11C4B19B5016702FD1AE0F1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and carry out a program to charge and collect fees under subsection (b) for forest botanical products harvested on National Forest System lands.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1436BD236EFF4819A621AAE1D2A70102"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appraisal methods; bidding procedures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish appraisal methods and bidding procedures to ensure that the amounts collected for forest botanical products are not less than fair market value.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H27FD573E8B464243ACEE27B685ABF7EF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Fees</header> <paragraph id="H670CA2B9B7B245C8A230FBF05E698A15"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Imposition and collection</header><text>The Secretary shall charge and collect fees from persons who harvest forest botanical products on National Forest System lands.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H91146B1B763D49E1AD5B5367772787FC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount of fee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The fees collected under paragraph (1) shall be in an amount established by the Secretary to recover at least a portion of the fair market value of the harvested forest botanical products and a portion of all the costs incurred by the Department of Agriculture associated with the granting, modifying, or monitoring the authorization for harvest of the forest botanical products, including the costs of any environmental or other analysis.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA0ACCF79403243EC966BE3DB738B9E8E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Security</header><text>The Secretary may require a person assessed a fee under this subsection to provide security to ensure that the Secretary receives the fees imposed under this subsection from the person.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H105A852B4C784A9D8B5133EA0FF3E87E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sustainable harvest levels for forest botanical products</header> 
<paragraph id="H31844A2EE0144BD5A86CF110262E281F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H8F202DB18B8443DA84290F760A11ADC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct appropriate analyses to determine whether and how the harvest of forest botanical products on National Forest System lands can be conducted on a sustainable basis; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6BA0BD1DC7B24DD89099E41D6B9A0F6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish procedures and timeframes to monitor and revise the harvest levels established for forest botanical products.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H289A932EA70B4BDE9FAE7DCB6BF25816"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on harvest in excess of sustainable levels</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not permit under the program under this section the harvest of forest botanical products at levels in excess of sustainable harvest levels, as defined under section 4 of the Multiple-Use Sustained-Yield Act of 1960 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/531">16 U.S.C. 531</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC3D5E6BB05714CFDA9B94E54AE666ECB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header> 
<paragraph id="H9A3E3F5D29934A40B8728D2B76121BF6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Personal use</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a personal use harvest level for each forest botanical product, and the harvest of a forest botanical product below that level by a person for personal use shall not be subject to charges and fees under subsections (a) and (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E9D443FA6FB446BA2956B3C8D69BBF3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other exceptions</header><text>The Secretary may also waive the application of subsection (a) or (b) pursuant to such regulations as the Secretary may prescribe.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE6BA9B3A9D9A4222AF130F4922346A91"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Deposit and use of funds</header> 
<paragraph id="H6025BAEEEA3C4097930E51D7DFF3019C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deposit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds collected under the program in accordance with subsections (a) and (b) shall be deposited into a special account in the Treasury of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8C34DD934F8F4E04BFE217EBEDA8D51C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funds available</header><text>Funds deposited into the special account in accordance with paragraph (1) shall remain available until expended without further appropriation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HDE7737C378674FC5934450C899392BE7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authorized uses</header><text>The funds made available under paragraph (2) shall be expended at units of the National Forest System in proportion to the charges and fees collected at that unit under the program under this section to pay for—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H3AEB14B3C7294AFA82B02CB4236004C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the costs of conducting inventories of forest botanical products, determining sustainable levels of harvest, monitoring and assessing the impacts of harvest levels and methods, and for restoration activities, including any necessary vegetation; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H6012AF8CFC0E45D68CD4E8C03A0A0A96"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the costs described in subsection (b)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H931DDCAE7C8C4C9ABCA852CC5E6EFF54"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Treatment of fees</header><text>Funds collected under the program in accordance with subsections (a) and (b) shall not be taken into account for the purposes of the following laws:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5963400C3F0E48FABBDE03E1AF6053B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The sixth paragraph under the heading <quote>forest service</quote> in the Act of May 23, 1908 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/500">16 U.S.C. 500</external-xref>), and section 13 of the Act of March 1, 1911 (commonly known as the Weeks Act; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/500">16 U.S.C. 500</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0631EB4DA5E64BBC88A8024BC020648E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The fourteenth paragraph under the heading <quote>forest service</quote> in the Act of March 4, 1913 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/501">16 U.S.C. 501</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H687C8523F09B4CCA8172750E58866AB4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Section 33 of the Bankhead-Jones Farm Tenant Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1012">7 U.S.C. 1012</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC2139DAFBB1403EABD7832389C8CAC2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Act of August 8, 1937, and the Act of May 24, 1939 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1181a">43 U.S.C. 1181a et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H97BDB9C46D1D41359896696036FC6729"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Section 6 of the Act of June 14, 1926 (commonly known as the Recreation and Public Purposes Act; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/869-4">43 U.S.C. 869–4</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1AB5D23DB3394B67A5EB4571427835F6"><enum>(F)</enum><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/69">Chapter 69</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5685E60DB8E0496CBC1480B8811AF8B4"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Section 401 of the Act of June 15, 1935 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/715s">16 U.S.C. 715s</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7C62DD17898E41099ACBDE4E5E94EB28"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Section 4 of the Land and Water Conservation Fund Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/460l-6a">16 U.S.C. 460l–6a</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC5DFF25BB5E0431F85935A4C452443D9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Any other provision of law relating to revenue allocation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB6674DEB08EC4D88B2EF15028E2B99B6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><text>As soon as practicable after the end of each fiscal year in which the Secretary collects charges and fees under the program in accordance with subsections (a) and (b) or expends funds from the special account under subsection (e), the Secretary shall submit to the Congress a report summarizing the activities of the Secretary under the program under this section, including the funds collected under the program in accordance with subsections (a) and (b), the expenses incurred to carry out the program under this section, and the expenditures made from the special account during that fiscal year.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H103565B892954CD6A60236317CB95C40"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section:</text> <paragraph id="H9F174F0FBE3A4385A70FFA7E29F65374"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Forest botanical product</header><text>The term <term>forest botanical product</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD544743319F646578363122E75440B74"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any naturally occurring mushroom, fungus, flower, seed, root, bark, leaf, or other vegetation (or portion thereof) that grows on National Forest System lands; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1746BDB5966D443D8FB5E4A7F41E7CA0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include trees, or portions of trees, except as provided in regulations issued under this section by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5BD40F8399DE40D1BE3C80D83C0AD6DD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>National Forest System</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>National Forest System</term> has the meaning given that term in section 11(a) of the Forest and Rangeland Renewable Resources Planning Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1609">16 U.S.C. 1609(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF9D33CAC3B474024B84D8FFC2CBDCEAE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


