<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB819F0F4AAB24E8485F32CCC36DE1F58" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6561 IH: Responsive Employees Support Productive Educated Congressional Talk Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6561</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231201">December 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for certain requirements of the Federal Aviation Administration in response to requests for information by Congress, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA3C440C6FFFC4614B8928D77AD6ACD70" style="OLC"><section id="H6C6BD1DB27234C1CB5818796CC78ADD0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Responsive Employees Support Productive Educated Congressional Talk Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>RESPECT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF4A3037FF2564AFE8A39228E46AB58C5"><enum>2.</enum><header>FAA responsiveness to Congress</header><subsection id="HBC2DB06A41C1410FADEBA6D6C7FA1382"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section is enacted pursuant to the legislative oversight responsibilities of Congress and to enable a Member of Congress to effectively represent their constituents and respond to constituent inquiries.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE1C3866BB3574E8988E42134921B1975"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a Member of Congress submits to the FAA a written request for information on proposed, previous, or current flight procedures or other data or information relating to the District of such Member, the following conditions apply:</text><paragraph id="H4650E46305A74A84918E6B3D605A4289"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Data Request</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after receipt of such request, the Administrator of the FAA shall substantively respond in writing with the requested data or information in the format requested by the Member of Congress, if—</text><subparagraph id="H491AA28C5A64425CA88DE3F8A2520D65"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the data is within the control of the FAA; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40A9EF6B2CDA412AA7E4E8FC4309690C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the data would be otherwise appropriate to provide if requested—</text><clause id="H688AAE626E714FA5AAD03400CC91CB2B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by an airline, an airport, a flight procedure proponent, an Aviation Roundtable, or anyone not employed by the FAA; or</text></clause><clause id="HF3DC30D180414942B1F04BD61F75B587"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>via a Freedom of Information request from any individual or any entity.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A90904201934D11AD126694FE707093"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator does not provide the requested information pursuant to paragraph (1), the Administrator shall notify the requesting Member of Congress, Congress, and the Chairman and Ranking Member of the Transportation and Infrastructure Committee of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB452644E8C44BC4B2D475E171DF3807"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Staffing of meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a Member of Congress submits to the FAA a written request for the FAA to provide staff at a private or public meeting with the Member, the Administrator shall provide such staff if—</text><paragraph id="H0BE0AA28F3A7456784667FCBDC29C133"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the request is made in writing at least 30 days before the meeting date; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CBFE72A5F234BC9AE5CA7D0AE14E968"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the request is made on the same terms and conditions as specified by FAA appearances at Aviation Roundtable meetings.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9F451F2804724DECA5F48C0A5F850885"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator does not comply with a request made by a Member of Congress (as described in subsection (c)), the Administrator shall provide the requesting Member of Congress, Congress, and the Chairman and Ranking Member of the Transportation and Infrastructure Committee of the House of Representatives with an explanation why the request will not be fulfilled.</text></subsection><subsection id="H57E4F56DC103425BB58C8FB4D8271612"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="H78BEB0BAA707426CB6A7E5CCCC795158"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Flight procedure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>flight procedure</quote> means a preplanned Instrument Flight Rules (IFR) procedure published for pilot use, in graphic or textual format, that provides obstruction clearance from the terminal area to the en route structure (departure) or from the en route structure to the terminal area (arrival).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H809058936008412FB1522D121076D305"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Procedure proponent</header><text>The term <quote>procedure proponent</quote> means a person or entity proposing a new or modified flight procedure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFDF9E5E51A54D0FA5EAC3BC3ECD479C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Aviation Roundtable</header><text>The term <quote>Aviation Roundtable</quote> means an organization designed to address community concerns over a sustained period of time regarding aircraft operations often associated with a nearby airport.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

