<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7F60B77A0149409C8B65943F6B0B9C54" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>111 HR 1572 IH: Hello Girls Congressional Gold Medal Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1572</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230314">March 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000546">Mr. Graves of Missouri</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To award a Congressional Gold Medal to the female telephone operators of the Army Signal Corps, known as the <quote>Hello Girls</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBCF877F1A2404FE8B394F89ED9E01DCF" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HA666D90EEB1D4CFCA61AA59ED193D244"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hello Girls Congressional Gold Medal Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD52A8DBC710348BE9A2ADF9D7E60DA29"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HC14FAEBD40C04ADD8A6BABE4DA1D60CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>On April 6, 1917, the United States declared war against Germany. As a historically neutral nation, the United States was unprepared to fight a technologically modern conflict overseas. The United States called upon American Telephone and Telegraph (referred to in this section as <quote>AT&amp;T</quote>) to provide equipment and trained personnel for the Army Signal Corps in France. AT&amp;T executives in Army uniform served at home under the provisions of the Act entitled <quote>An Act for making further and more effectual provision for the national defense, and for other purposes.</quote>, approved June 3, 1916 (referred to in this section as the <quote>National Defense Act of 1916</quote>), which allowed for the induction of individuals with specialized skills into a reserve force.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11C47FDDCFEF4D398D89C3754C64DF4B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>When General John Pershing sailed for Europe in May of 1917, as head of the American Expeditionary Forces (referred to in this section as the <quote>AEF</quote>), he took telephone operating equipment with him in recognition of the inadequacy of European circuitry and with the understanding that telephones would play a key role in battlefield communications for the first time in the history of war.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H386FBC74BF6840D4BB366E472CD4DC8B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>From May to November of 1917, the AEF struggled to develop the telephone service necessary for the Army to function under battlefield conditions. Monolingual infantrymen from the United States were unable to connect calls rapidly or communicate effectively with their French counterparts to put calls through over toll lines that linked one region of the country with another. The Army found that the average male operator required 60 seconds to make a connection. That rate was unacceptably slow, especially for operational calls between command outposts and the front lines.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H525D3A388EA047CCAAC3E96233BAE1E9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>During this time, in the United States, telephone operating was largely sex-segregated. Hired for their speed in connecting calls, women filled 85 percent of the telephone operating positions in the United States. It took the average female operator 10 seconds to make a connection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H058B25BB22214B6CA2F46B2435E63D77"><enum>(5)</enum><text>On November 8, 1917, General Pershing cabled the War Department and wrote, <quote>On account of the great difficulty of obtaining properly qualified men, request organization and dispatch to France a force of women telephone operators all speaking French and English equally well.</quote>. To begin, General Pershing requested 100 women under the command of a commissioned captain, writing that <quote>All should have allowances of Army nurses and should be uniformed.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB10CFAA036B4287AEB1014313778AAA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The War Department sent press releases to newspapers across the United States to recruit women willing to serve for the duration of the war and face the hazards of submarine warfare and aerial bombardment. These articles emphasized that patriotic women would be <quote>full-fledged soldier[s] under the articles of war</quote> and would <quote>do as much to help win the war as the men in khaki who go <quote>over the top.</quote></quote>. All women selected would take the Army oath.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DD848260B3148EBB1F0E236101AD3CA"><enum>(7)</enum><text>More than 7,600 women volunteered for the 100 positions described in paragraph (5) and the first recruits took the Army oath on January 15, 1918.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23EBBC00D1B6454982A119760EF61834"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Like nurses and doctors at the time, female Signal Corps members had relative rather than traditional ranks and were ranked as Operator, Supervisor, or Chief Operator. When promoted, the women were required to swear the Army oath again.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5F9C86EC1474D8E92FB79AEB2EB7960"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Telephone operators were the first women to serve as soldiers in non-medical classifications and the job of the operators was to help win the war, not to mitigate the harms of the war. In popular parlance, they were known as the <quote>Hello Girls</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CF74246EEA949719D13C7AAA685413B"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Signal Corps Operators wore Army uniforms and Army insignia always, as well as standard-issue identity disks in case of death, and were subject to court martial for infractions of the military code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H829AF6DFE51A47A09AD2B32410B4DB9D"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Unbeknownst to the women operators and their immediate officers, the legal counsel of the Army ruled internally on March 20, 1918, that the women were not actually soldiers but contract employees, even though the women had not seen or signed any contracts. Military code allowed only for the induction of men and the code remained unchanged despite the orders of General Pershing. Nevertheless, legal counsel also recognized that the National Defense Act of 1916, which allowed for the induction of members of the telephone industry of the United States into the Armed Forces, imposed no gender restrictions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF65A1901E73F4CD1A716BBEAF31EF978"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Four days later, on March 24, 1918, the first contingent of operators began their official duties in France. The operators arrived before most infantrymen of the Armed Forces in order to facilitate logistics and deployment and spent their first night in Paris under German bombardment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE3F866C0D1B42A09F3680B1D03D38D9"><enum>(13)</enum><text>After the arrival of the operators, telephone service in France improved immediately, as calls tripled from 13,000 to 36,000 per day.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B699D00B02E44619957EA88E0023021"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The Army quickly recruited, trained, and deployed 5 additional contingents of female Signal Corps operators. With these personnel, calls increased to 150,000 per day.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA070F36DEA04F63A7221853C4CF89E2"><enum>(15)</enum><text>In addition to standard telephone operating, bilingual Signal Corps members provided simultaneous translation between officers from France and officers from the United States, who were communicating by telephone.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1977C173EA9F421AB96B77476DEA8458"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The AEF fought their first major battles in the last 2 months of the war. By that point, the Signal Corps considered the contributions of women to be so essential that, in telephone exchanges closest to the front line, the Army exclusively used women, in rotating 12-hour shifts. In the rear, the Army established rotating 8-hour shifts and gave male soldiers the overnight shift when telephone traffic was slower.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H977CC49A6E214C33A1E2BC1B7B184EC9"><enum>(17)</enum><text>Seven bilingual operators—</text><subparagraph id="H2C7C703A8525428990C761602547BCDC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>served at the Battles of St. Mihiel and Meuse-Argonne under the immediate command of General Pershing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9740AC1DE4AA40C2A6C1D85933879666"><enum>(B)</enum><text>staffed the Operations Boards through which orders to advance, fire, and retreat were delivered to soldiers in the trenches, to artillery units on alert, and to pilots awaiting orders at French airfields; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39B426EA80E448CC99A6BE7C11B10E61"><enum>(C)</enum><text>were awarded a <quote>Defensive Sector Clasp</quote> for the Meuse-Argonne operation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB32CB9B87C5544559DE65F8DE0813534"><enum>(18)</enum><text>The Chief Operator supervising the Hello Girls, Grace Banker of Passaic, New Jersey, was awarded the Distinguished Service Medal. Out of 16,000 eligible Signal Corps officers, Banker was one of only 18 individuals so honored.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD38F01CEF5304171BE1B7884F154DEC6"><enum>(19)</enum><text>Thirty additional operators received special commendations, many signed by General Pershing himself, for <quote>exceptionally meritorious and conspicuous services</quote> in <quote>Advance Sections</quote> of the conflict.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0143045DEA8B45B2A2FF39474C24A534"><enum>(20)</enum><text>The war ended on November 11, 1918. As of that date, 223 female operators served in France and had connected 26,000,000 calls for the AEF.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84359D0C20A34325B0885D75B31225B2"><enum>(21)</enum><text>The Chief Signal Officer of the Army Signal Corps wrote in his official report 2 days after the date on which the war ended that <quote>a large part of the success of the communications of this Army is due to … a competent staff of women operators.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C6537C8992E4A60AEBC3B9CDD216F76"><enum>(22)</enum><text>After the war ended, some women were ordered to Coblenz in Germany for the occupation of that country and to Paris for the Paris Peace Treaty of 1919 to continue telephone operations, sometimes in direct support of President Woodrow Wilson.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB758E65820D14DE7B418B6F1F1D45919"><enum>(23)</enum><text>Two operators, Corah Bartlett and Inez Crittenden, died in France in the service of the United States and were buried there in military cemeteries with military ceremonies. Those operators died of the same influenza pandemic that killed more soldiers of the Armed Forces than combat operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68E30519D4214B66B1A3834F73BE67C7"><enum>(24)</enum><text>Women of the Army Signal Corps were ineligible for discharge until formal release. Because of their role in logistics, those women were among the last soldiers to come home to the United States. The last Signal Corps operators returned from France in January of 1920.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BE2A8E5E0DA48AD8B62E4310C73E928"><enum>(25)</enum><text>Upon arrival in the United States, the Army informed female veterans that they had performed as civilians, not soldiers, even though operators had served in Army uniform in a theater of war surrounded by men who were similarly engaged.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7B355EC38264F4EA6BDF05566825F3F"><enum>(26)</enum><text>Despite the objections of General George Squier, the top-ranking officer in the Signal Corps, the Army denied Signal Corps women the veterans’ benefits granted to male soldiers and female nurses, such as—</text><subparagraph id="HAF61A71CF692492489B4AB945DA6CBA7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>hospitalization for disabilities incurred in the line of duty;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CE4825A18B9432E8B438AB62C74E269"><enum>(B)</enum><text>cash bonuses;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94C0C99C16A345FE8B0D86F59C68AE89"><enum>(C)</enum><text>soldiers’ pensions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E87EAD322514183BE0B9D64B6C8C8A2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>flags on their coffins; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8C9A82F4A0E4C90A3F7197564402688"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Victory Medals promised them in France.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE54C88501C1145BBA26F22AF93200668"><enum>(27)</enum><text>For the next 60 years, female veterans, led by Merle Egan from Montana, petitioned Congress more than 50 times for their recognition. In 1977, under the sponsorship of Senator Barry Goldwater, Congress passed legislation to retroactively acknowledge the military service of the Women’s Airforce Service Pilots (referred to in this section as <quote>WASPs</quote>) of World War II and <quote>the service of any person in any other similarly situated group the members of which rendered service to the Armed Forces of the United States in a capacity considered civilian employment or contractual service at the time such service was rendered</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57CC096EC7114FC1B3A658CE9B756F60"><enum>(28)</enum><text>On November 23, 1977, President Jimmy Carter signed the legislation described in paragraph (27) into law as the GI Bill Improvement Act of 1977 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/95/202">Public Law 95–202</external-xref>; 91 Stat. 1433).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F8BA4B54145420597386EEF2885EF12"><enum>(29)</enum><text>The Signal Corps telephone operators applied for, and were granted, status as veterans in 1979.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91D2C254BB524ACBA02B6DF2131CB30B"><enum>(30)</enum><text>Only 33 of the operators who had returned home after the war were still alive to receive their Victory Medals and official discharge papers, which were finally awarded in 1979.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H243C85CE7D7543EE95FC72142FB1B6C3"><enum>(31)</enum><text>One of the women, Olive Shaw from Massachusetts, returned to the United States after the war, where she worked on the professional staff of Congresswoman Edith Nourse Rogers. Shaw lived to receive her honorable discharge and was the first burial when the Massachusetts National Cemetery opened on October 11, 1980. Shaw’s uniform is on display at the National World War I Museum and Memorial in Kansas City, Missouri.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99FCDAA86F96446FBD8E4993DB02F6D3"><enum>(32)</enum><text>Upon receipt of her honorable discharge at a ceremony in her home in Marine City, Michigan, <quote>Hello Girl</quote> Oleda Joure Christides raised the paper to her lips and kissed it. The only thing Christides ever wanted from the Federal Government was a flag on her coffin.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD85123B02464F4CB0E5D23F1087DC3E"><enum>(33)</enum><text>On July 1, 2009, President Barack Obama signed into law <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/40">Public Law 111–40</external-xref> (123 Stat. 1958), which awarded the WASPs the Congressional Gold Medal for their service to the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65171EBFFE94482A84CD5C1AC3D09423"><enum>(34)</enum><text>For their role as pioneers who paved the way for all women in uniform, and for service that was essential to victory in World War I, the <quote>Hello Girls</quote> merit similar recognition.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC33EE49DE4004B3B8DA187030959022B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header><subsection id="H616FE58E56DF4F19ABC62F8C4478A2A8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Award authorized</header><text>The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the award, on behalf of Congress, of a single gold medal of appropriate design in honor of the female telephone operators of the Army Signal Corps (commonly known as the <quote>Hello Girls</quote>), in recognition of those operators’—</text><paragraph id="HEB712B7D58E64D17BDEFAA2522155AB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>pioneering military service;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06D221C5F64E4442A598A4C31DC0BC92"><enum>(2)</enum><text>devotion to duty; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H175B0F3B7E524BE892F091A2A340DC0D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>60-year struggle for—</text><subparagraph id="H0B78E82FF359468791EA243606FABDB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recognition as soldiers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE92511DC7AE49C5B97D7C1146AD81F5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>veterans’ benefits.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF80DACFA065B490ABE2C2DF189CCE4A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text>For the purposes of the award described in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike the gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC43C655963C6418D928ED3A1AECFE8B6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Smithsonian Institution</header><paragraph id="H0826DC45477947619DAF88C775999269"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>After the award of the gold medal under subsection (a), the medal shall be given to the Smithsonian Institution, where the medal shall be available for display, as appropriate, and made available for research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C0D1642DA674B9498054BED456C501D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the Smithsonian Institution should make the gold medal received under paragraph (1) available elsewhere, particularly at—</text><subparagraph id="H4841F88DBC5247CEA917B7D7F184357B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>appropriate locations associated with—</text><clause id="HE8BE754A138647E7A312073D36C747EB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Army Signal Corps;</text></clause><clause id="HBFAB843CA5324D79B81C6741756FC99C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Women in Military Service for America Memorial;</text></clause><clause id="H1B17A029D53746EC8AFF062CE5F9EBB3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the U.S. Army Women’s Museum; and</text></clause><clause id="HEBB3B1271EF646FCB60473A537A4A8B5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the National World War I Museum and Memorial; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA63CFE9EA364A738E3CC2A75667B35A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other location determined appropriate by the Smithsonian Institution.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4D75DE6262704678B8436114AD2A003E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Under such regulations as the Secretary may prescribe, the Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck under section 3 at a price sufficient to cover the costs of the medals, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></section><section id="H019C7273A8BE412FB141323759BA158D"><enum>5.</enum><header>National medals</header><subsection id="H8459998568EF4B2A8300C38BE62DAA32"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text>Medals struck under this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H25FBADB99CB34B9E9E75AEA5E4017807"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of section 5134 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6A3B8C45EF7D4427943C9D256B720DE9" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header><subsection id="H4915EE19BC9F486E88758277EDE3F3A9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2D02E4512DB24E60BFA0BCED4A9BE006"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>Amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

