<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBA400D7BFE084D42B3013CDB20CDAA94" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1106 IH: Congressional Oversight to Secure Transparency of Relocations Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1106</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require Federal agencies to conduct a benefit-cost analysis on relocations involving the movement of employment positions to different areas, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF752A0802C9440A381A96D09098C9DF0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5B479DD8F6C444F7AB95990DF1FD2EE8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Congressional Oversight to Secure Transparency of Relocations Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COST of Relocations Act</short-title></quote> .</text></section> <section id="H83D0258BC6B246459DBCC5A71E639D57"><enum>2.</enum><header>Benefit-cost analysis on certain relocations</header> <subsection id="H8FA5E3DEF52745348970096FC9EAFC0C"><enum>(a)</enum><header> In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (d), a Federal agency may not carry out a covered relocation unless, prior to any submission to the Office of Management and Budget or other reviewing entity regarding such covered relocation—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEFA07314BE014640BBD2B8B6EA6DBFE9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such agency—</text> <subparagraph id="HBA535A1F8151487A98833283E9B16234"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducts a benefit-cost analysis on the covered relocation; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC13D221498CE415388015A55A9489630"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submits to the Office of Inspector General for such agency a report on the findings of the benefit-cost analysis and including such other information such Office of Inspector General determines necessary for compliance with subsection (c); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE9AD39B22AD141F1885098A7A9D02B5C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such Office of Inspector General reviews the report and submits to Congress the report described in subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA28B3A67E63E491B9C5C87992FE34433"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Benefit-Cost analysis</header> 
<paragraph id="H48BE6E3BDE94430CA54E4C3D0FE3B0F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The benefit-cost analysis described in subsection (a)(1) shall be conducted in a manner consistent with the economic and social science principles articulated in the guidance applicable to relocations in the Office of Management and Budget Circular A–4, as in effect on September 17, 2003.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H363ADD768A764AB2A14B519B5C221931"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Analysis report</header> <subparagraph id="H37EF43C8068747BE8373256A21AFD67C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report described in subsection (a)(1)(B) shall include, at a minimum—</text> 
<clause id="H550A3C3F0D764FC5A5A8D9E462DAB4A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the anticipated outcomes and improvements that will result from the proposed covered relocation, quantified in monetary or other appropriate measures to the extent practicable;</text></clause> <clause id="H9EAEB464D82F4621AA855E4FF6428B9E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an explanation of how the proposed covered relocation will result in the anticipated outcomes and improvements;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFC77C61BAB754BE094051CBB61DEE714"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the metrics for measuring whether the proposed covered relocation results in the anticipated outcomes and improvements;</text></clause> <clause id="HBE3F0D0D85274230BD287FCBC6F4E80B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a detailed employee engagement plan;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4E4ABD067E464E489DCAD654243D0018"><enum>(v)</enum><text>a list of stakeholders;</text></clause> <clause id="HF427DC6657A74336804AA590F59D17F9"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>a timeline of past and future engagements with stakeholders regarding the proposed covered relocation;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBE4DF097FC4E42FBA16A6F075CDA4CB2"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>an assessment of how the proposed covered relocation may affect stakeholders—</text> <subclause id="H308CEB1C6179421D94AD16DBCF6490BC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>served by the positions affected by the covered relocation; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0A9EC1184EA64843A7A62C4619D741EA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in the destination agency or region;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HF26D850325914746859D1FF985FDA2BB"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>a comprehensive strategy for accomplishing the proposed covered relocation that includes—</text> 
<subclause id="HE34BCC66DCD740CE8E8367F78CBAE2DA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>staffing, resourcing, and financial needs;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H489FE37C659D45B6B800BACDF6E12047"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an implementation timeline identifying milestones and the persons accountable for meeting such milestones;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H6D9FB9F75E7F4BECA4E6C6D6604471FF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a risk assessment;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC3EDF0EE43D14228A93F503EBC77FED3"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a risk mitigation plan; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H30CE8D188A3F4D4DB0FA174E84C82E84"><enum>(V)</enum><text>a diversity management strategy including—</text> <item id="H94A2021B7CC84307B27BE1FEB6F14FC3"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a strategy for sustaining diversity and inclusion; and</text></item> 
<item id="H6F623296F7E04818BA3C64283B5D3824"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>documentation of ongoing succession and recruiting planning processes;</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H3AE976F7283046FABFB4C61BCD239D87"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>an analysis of the effect the proposed covered relocation may have on the ability of the Federal agency to carry out its mission during the covered relocation and thereafter; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF1E568EDC23148F890A4CEBFC3D84187"><enum>(x)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of the short- and long-term effects of the covered relocation on the mission of the Federal agency.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA754219503554854A90B53762AAC4F73"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>A Federal agency shall make publicly available the report described in subsection (a)(1)(B) in a form that excludes any proprietary information or trade secrets of any person and other confidential information. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD700BEF994CA43B9B4DAA227BDAC5DB9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Inspector General report to Congress</header> 
<paragraph id="HCAD371B6D2F04EC9AE2EB976CBE5D729"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date on which a Federal agency submits a report under subsection (a)(1)(B), the Office of Inspector General for that agency shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate, the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate, the Committee on Oversight and Reform of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives a report on the findings of the review conducted under subsection (a)(2), including—</text> <subparagraph id="H1496505F7C70487496D4AA41CB22DCE5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>detailed descriptions of the data used in the benefit-cost analysis described in subsection (a)(1), including the types of data and the time periods covered by the data;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEE89859C8E9F4387BE996537D5FC9304"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the conclusions of the benefit-cost analysis and the analysis underlying such conclusions; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC75DAEA3D7F94E9CBB2C5CD363E06237"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a comprehensive assessment of—</text> 
<clause id="H5EF1A5BBD2C94FF091CCA98F2CD0E4E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the extent to which the Federal agency adhered to the guidance in the Office of Management and Budget Circular A–4, as in effect on September 17, 2003, in conducting the benefit-cost analysis, including a determination whether such adherence is sufficient to justify the use of Federal funds for the proposed covered relocation involved; and</text></clause> <clause id="HABCF7A584EA94AC3B3A4051103AB7B37"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the proposed covered relocation involves moving positions from inside the National Capital Region to outside the National Capital Region, the extent to which real estate options in the National Capital Region were compared to those in the destination as part of that analysis.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE6CF6037742C4F4EBC60673369F442DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusions</header> 
<subparagraph id="H20DF41029A2E4981B81591E6EE672A05"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of Inspector General for a Federal agency shall exclude from any report described in this subsection any proprietary information or trade secrets of any person and other confidential information.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0AAAF16C497D47359590D95ED65338F6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Explanation and description required</header><text>For each exclusion under subparagraph (A), the Office of Inspector General shall include an explanation of the reason for the exclusion and a description of the information excluded in an appropriate location in the relevant report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H69CAD0DDDF6C4A3491471056C435194E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Other requirements not abrogated</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to abrogate, reduce, or eliminate any requirements imposed by law pertaining to any covered relocation of a Federal agency or component of a Federal agency.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H577AEC28EB9C49B4BE13386582BE248B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HDADE41CB5124414A8F8588D5146A6DA8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrative redelegation of function</header><text>The term <term>administrative redelegation of function</term> means a Federal agency establishing new positions within the agency that replace existing positions within the agency and perform the functions of the positions replaced.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H51D2C3BA98CD4883A379E75D12938CFC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered relocation</header><text>The term <term>covered relocation</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7F94675059EC44F3AA30F02CDC87FDDC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an administrative redelegation of function which, by itself or in conjunction with other related redelegations, involves replacing the existing positions of more than the lesser of 5 percent or 100 of the employees of the relevant Federal agency with new positions located outside the commuting area of such employees;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCE78F0B5DCA04EFC9138A89F9DD656DC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>moving a Federal agency or any component of a Federal agency if such move, by itself or in conjunction with other related moves, involves moving the positions of more than the lesser of 5 percent or 100 of the employees of the Federal agency outside the commuting area of such employees or under the jurisdiction of another Federal agency; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9B5F314B62C244D890E233FBF4D0E858"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a combination of related redelegations and moves which together involve the positions of more than the lesser of 5 percent or 100 of the employees of the relevant Federal agency being moved to or replaced with new positions located outside the commuting area of such employees or moved under the jurisdiction of another Federal agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H546297C1546F45FF952BB27C8387ABB4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Employee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>employee</term> means an employee or officer of a Federal agency.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H774D59DE8F1140FAA117384A2A05A3D8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> has the meaning given the term <term>agency</term> in section 902 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H00239A45EC1F49AC8A9763712D2A3D21"><enum>(5)</enum><header>National Capital Region</header><text>The term <term>National Capital Region</term> has the meaning given such term in section 8702 of title 40, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

