<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF0A2497692344B9793DB57429A6715D9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3770 IH: Limiting the Intrusive Bureaucracy and Empowering Regulatory Transparency for You Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3770</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230531">May 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the definition of section 804 of title 5.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD951DF3DC7494457A0D9F0239B087FF5" style="OLC"><section id="H4ED089EEE3444D059EF3B19571EFA1F2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Limiting the Intrusive Bureaucracy and Empowering Regulatory Transparency for You Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>LIBERTY Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5836909C75F94EB181858C37EA83CAD2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Congressional review of agency rulemaking</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 804 of title 5, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HE39E29E1C3B341AEACAD927ACBE5377B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HD2FEC13F5ED847F9A9B0F3A7373DFEBF"><enum>804.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this chapter:</text><paragraph id="HEB518B74902F44A08D6167F0F29A2137"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> means any agency as that term is defined in section 551(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H914FD1B21E614B629FE6FD2531E5597B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>major rule</term>—</text><subparagraph id="HBD17ACFE426540469E0A112F51A4E263"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means any rule that the Administrator of the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs of the Office of Management and Budget finds has resulted in or is likely to result in—</text><clause id="H32FFADD4F82A42A992AECC26CF14B057"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an annual effect on the economy of $100,000,000 or more;</text></clause><clause id="H2291CCB4949B4CAAA0910D8BBB908F43"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a major increase in costs or prices for consumers, individual industries, Federal, State, or local government agencies, or geographic regions; or</text></clause><clause id="H9C4C1CEED1AE4B4EBD7564E2CF44483A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>significant adverse effects on competition, employment, investment, productivity, innovation, or on the ability of United States-based enterprises to compete with foreign-based enterprises in domestic and export markets; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1EEFD26752844E4680ED1F6647FDD92C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes significant guidance documents.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA1D13792B2747A784BE3A0258ED2A23"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>rule</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H55CA4F9B123D48AF928A2CA50B2D9C73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has the meaning given such term in section 551, except that such term does not include (except as otherwise provided in subparagraph (B))—</text><clause id="HDCC4EFDE74FE408CB5511D0AEAECF689"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any rule of particular applicability, including a rule that approves or prescribes for the future rates, wages, prices, services, or allowances therefor, corporate or financial structures, reorganizations, mergers, or acquisitions thereof, or accounting practices or disclosures bearing on any of the foregoing; </text></clause><clause id="H88B4F8E4B449409DA1CEA2786C302944"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any rule relating to agency management or personnel; or</text></clause><clause id="H430A9304E9B14FA1BCAEE2D127A7CAD4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any rule of agency organization, procedure, or practice that does not substantially affect the rights or obligations of non-agency parties; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E2909299346414495CEF8EC3D46A037"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes guidance documents.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA157F80615624F09854A08D8A9BB47E6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>guidance document</term> means a statement of general applicability and future effect, other than a regulatory action, issued by a Federal agency that sets forth—</text><subparagraph id="H81AAB2707A4044608D09BCAD557B8445"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a policy on a statutory, regulatory, or technical issue; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H175B71FDB6AE496F8D180C74D3AC591B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an interpretation of a statutory or regulatory issue.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1E6A203A5BF433F83FEF9A8692A962F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The term <term>significant guidance document</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H33C0ED19E9714C2AB68A75337EA36094"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a guidance document disseminated to regulated entities or the general public that may reasonably be anticipated to—</text><clause id="H3877C182814C4F9B8D476391F2EA7AB4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>lead to an annual effect of $100,000,000 or more, or adversely affect in a material way the economy, a sector of the economy, productivity, competition, employment, the environment, public health or safety, or State, local, or Tribal governments or communities;</text></clause><clause id="HD49F5785BB0C44E191D0C11C6B5590CE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>create a serious inconsistency, or otherwise interfere, with an action taken or planned by another Federal agency; </text></clause><clause id="H3917355D918540618411E88C6A9AD9C2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>materially alter the budgetary impact of any entitlement, grant, user fees, or loan programs, or the rights or obligations of recipients thereof; or</text></clause><clause id="H9592B0FA63F64A2E8C8EFDB0F427FF5A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>raise novel legal or policy issues arising out of legal mandates; and </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5A43DFA3A0F4768A5BB444E39F6D283"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include any guidance document—</text><clause id="HE2AFD6EC155D4ACC8D0AB388B6E8F384"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on regulations issued in accordance with section 556 or 557;</text></clause><clause id="HFA3841A0627D459494931D6E11DA56A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that pertains to a military or foreign affairs function of the United States, other than procurement regulations and regulations involving the import or export of non-defense articles and services; or </text></clause><clause id="H83643D0A26304A6D84A2A320286A8FE6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>on regulations that are limited to the organization, management, or personnel matters of a Federal agency.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HE4F50E57BD1A4AA1B40208F4E38BD0D7"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definition of <quote>rule</quote> to include significant guidance document for purposes of rulemaking</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Section 551(4) of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>, as well as significant guidance document (as such term is defined in section 804(5))</quote>. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

