<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF922536E0D97479EB06575191B0B5270" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5913 IH: Consolidating Veteran Employment Services for Improved Performance Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5913</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231010">October 10, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000135">Mr. Van Orden</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc>
</action>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to improve employment services for veterans by consolidating various programs in the Department of Veterans Affairs, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H843801EB7E784DDE9C7FAA1A78DA107B" style="OLC">
<section id="H939EECA4BF5A4346BEBBFACAC7F204FC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Consolidating Veteran Employment Services for Improved Performance Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA03C6DFEFB12470892723E6EF4D35283"><enum>2.</enum><header>Transfer of Department of Labor veterans programs to Department of Veterans Affairs</header> <subsection id="HF06CA8461F5748DCBF97450846FCD488" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Transfer of functions</header> <paragraph id="HD42C799475E94B558790A1563973AB91"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Effective October 1, 2025, there shall be transferred to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs all functions performed under the following programs of the Department of Labor, and all personnel, assets, and liabilities pertaining to such programs, immediately before such transfer occurs:</text>
<subparagraph id="HBD3767BF6B1D4EC5B7062F3A1D17F16E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Job counseling, training, and placement services for veterans under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/41">chapter 41</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDEEA233781A24431AA39FEA35EBEA63B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Federal Government employment services by the Secretary of Labor under section 4214 of such title.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8FF70161991B4FE1855A2B73E6514AEE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Administration of employment and reemployment rights of members of the uniformed services under chapter 43 of such title.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF87D8D6A43BA41DC9528C2423191002A" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Homeless veterans reintegration programs under chapter 20 of such title.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H027BF4AAD7864BB4948F32FD224080CB"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Employment and veterans benefits training under the Transition Assistance Program under section 1144 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6A833628A9AE4480950FF9740AFFC811" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Memorandums of agreement</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall enter into memorandums of agreement with the Secretary of Labor and with States (as defined in section 4101(6) of title 38, United States Code), as the Secretary of Veterans Affairs determines necessary, to implement the transition of the programs specified under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA2668110871D42449B9B3F0ED47C7DF2" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act may be construed to affect the role and responsibility of the Secretary of Labor with respect to programs not administered by the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans' Employment and Training Service as of the day before the date of the enactment of this Act that are specified under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H10108358BA234630AB48382A96307AB4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Budget request</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under section 1105 of title 31, United States Code, the President shall include in the President’s budget request for the Department of Veterans Affairs for fiscal year 2027, and for each subsequent fiscal year, funding requested for the functions referred to in subsection (a)(1).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H44101FAE8D4B45C9B5B424F93C4BE3B4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>References</header><text>Any reference in any other Federal law, Executive order, rule, regulation, or delegation of authority, or any document of or pertaining to a department or office from which a function is transferred by this Act—</text> <paragraph id="H295695B7BB414166AE18283770902F6B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the head of such department or office is deemed to refer to the head of the department or office to which such function is transferred; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H77484DF207654B488A94B86E4057E4AF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to such department or office is deemed to refer to the department or office to which such function is transferred.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF523F901E34C4092934E3A181BF3662C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exercise of authorities</header><text>Except as otherwise provided by law, a Federal official to whom a function is transferred by this Act may, for purposes of performing the function, exercise all authorities under any other provision of law that were available with respect to the performance of that function to the official responsible for the performance of the function immediately before the effective date of the transfer of the function under this Act.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H00322BBC44824FDC8E42DAD3620A9E9A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Savings provisions</header>
<paragraph id="HF4CD304848764E60A34722CC74085D26" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Legal documents</header><text>All orders, determinations, rules, regulations, permits, grants, loans, contracts, agreements, certificates, licenses, and privileges—</text> <subparagraph id="HED815028357248618B486BFA1741383E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that have been issued, made, granted, or allowed to become effective by the President, the Secretary of Labor, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, any officer or employee of any office transferred by this Act, or any other Government official, or by a court of competent jurisdiction, in the performance of any function that is transferred by this Act, and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H16F3592069194D8082FFFA110C7AE4C2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that are in effect on the effective date of such transfer (or become effective after such date pursuant to their terms as in effect on such effective date),</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph" commented="no">shall continue in effect according to their terms until modified, terminated, superseded, set aside, or revoked in accordance with law by the President, any other authorized official, a court of competent jurisdiction, or operation of law.</continuation-text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H16E3905FB93A4794B0ED54A5773D6091"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Proceedings</header><text>This Act shall not affect any proceedings or any application for any benefits, service, license, permit, certificate, or financial assistance pending on the date of the enactment of this Act before an office transferred by this Act, but such proceedings and applications shall be continued. Orders shall be issued in such proceedings, appeals shall be taken therefrom, and payments shall be made pursuant to such orders, as if this Act had not been enacted, and orders issued in any such proceeding shall continue in effect until modified, terminated, superseded, or revoked by a duly authorized official, by a court of competent jurisdiction, or by operation of law. Nothing in this subsection shall be considered to prohibit the discontinuance or modification of any such proceeding under the same terms and conditions and to the same extent that such proceeding could have been discontinued or modified if this Act had not been enacted.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4559AA346C1A40149F794617406E90E9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Suits</header><text>This Act shall not affect suits commenced before the date of the enactment of this Act, and in all such suits, proceeding shall be had, appeals taken, and judgments rendered in the same manner and with the same effect as if this Act had not been enacted.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBE0A6B97E104908AEB6321F6155A4C4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Nonabatement of actions</header><text>No suit, action, or other proceeding commenced by or against the Department of Labor or the Secretary of Labor, or by or against any individual in the official capacity of such individual as an officer or employee of an office transferred by this Act, shall abate by reason of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H149FDD53D7BE482D89677E0A2CF9C343"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Continuance of suits</header><text>If any Government officer in the official capacity of such officer is party to a suit with respect to a function of the officer, and under this Act such function is transferred to any other officer or office, then such suit shall be continued with the other officer or the head of such other office, as applicable, substituted or added as a party.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4136A9DF8F09432C94724B20421F58B9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Administrative procedure and judicial review</header><text>Except as otherwise provided by this Act, any statutory requirements relating to notice, hearings, action upon the record, or administrative or judicial review that apply to any function transferred by this Act shall apply to the exercise of such function by the head of the Federal agency, and other officers of the agency, to which such function is transferred by this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H33814370FBC84BCDA8F84DEF787334DF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Transfer of assets</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this Act, so much of the personnel, property, records, and unexpended balances of appropriations, allocations, and other funds employed, used, held, available, or to be made available in connection with a function transferred to an official or agency by this Act shall be available to the official or the head of that agency, respectively, at such time or times as the Director of the Office of Management and Budget directs for use in connection with the functions transferred.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA123AAA3AE324C3BAF21B4589DA007AE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Delegation and assignment</header><text>Except as otherwise expressly prohibited by law or otherwise provided in this Act, an official to whom functions are transferred under this Act (including the head of any office to which functions are transferred under this Act) may delegate any of the functions so transferred to such officers and employees of the office of the official as the official may designate, and may authorize successive redelegations of such functions as may be necessary or appropriate. No delegation of functions under this section or under any other provision of this Act shall relieve the official to whom a function is transferred under this Act of responsibility for the administration of the function.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H42FE4CD393DA42299B8D764833751B44"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authority of Director of the Office of Management and Budget with respect to functions transferred</header>
<paragraph id="H9871F6B58C664AAD8953FB77742F4EED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determinations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If necessary, the Director of Management and Budget shall make any determination of the functions that are transferred under this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6274806FAF17447899952D75795585CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Incidental transfers</header><text>The Director, at such time or times as the Director shall provide, may make such determinations as may be necessary with regard to the functions transferred by this Act, and to make such additional incidental dispositions of personnel, assets, liabilities, grants, contracts, property, records, and unexpended balances of appropriations, authorizations, allocations, and other funds held, used, arising from, available to, or to be made available in connection with such functions, as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this Act. The Director shall provide for the termination of the affairs of all entities terminated by this Act and for such further measures and dispositions as may be necessary to effectuate the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8EAA695FFED545568F95A3241622B797"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Certain vesting of functions considered transfers</header><text>For purposes of this Act, the vesting of a function in a department or office pursuant to reestablishment of an office shall be considered to be the transfer of the function.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H51A4B0694F7D45D88190C4664DD82547"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Availability of existing funds</header><text>Existing appropriations and funds available for the performance of functions, programs, and activities terminated pursuant to this Act shall remain available, for the duration of their period of availability, for necessary expenses in connection with the termination and resolution of such functions, programs, and activities.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H29C770F8F706448D99E3F718C7C6C4F4"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this Act—</text> <paragraph id="HD16AC898A96340BFBF29E7338B852AE6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>function</term> includes any duty, obligation, power, authority, responsibility, right, privilege, activity, or program; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H81D2D2239A2249BD9D07653EF61A7A25"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>office</term> includes any office, administration, agency, bureau, institute, council, unit, organizational entity, or component thereof.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H0EA1302FF8124844A0BC0666A5117D2C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Deputy Under Secretary of Veterans Affairs for Veterans’ Employment and Training</header> <subsection id="HE9E90F79C4B64EF18731BFFF135A56D5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subsection (a) of section 4102A of title 38, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H8F3E42EB65E04557A13B0C40BBD61CFA" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="H9533D0DEE08542DA9969D53723544B47"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established within the Department a Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training, who shall formulate and implement all departmental policies and procedures to carry out the purposes of this chapter, chapter 20, and chapter 43 of this title and the Transition Assistance Program under section 1144 of title 10, United States Code.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H725DF7C6C2A544258DDEB1355A98E079"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/41">Chapter 41</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended as follows:</text>
<paragraph id="H8C59BD9327654652A14DD1500B09383A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The section heading of section 4102A of such title is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H61FDDB3DBB7E4271B704A775FEC5B588" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H0E7B664C8F764CE39A6869EB3C8EDDE1"><enum>4102A. </enum><header>Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training; program functions; Regional Administrators</header></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF952632896B479587869B4C273B9D49"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The item relating to such section in the table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H7E1F1AD62E954B69BDB84BD640FF4F82" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">4102A. Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training; program functions; Regional Administrators.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H20DE2C312A2E457893E389FD80F07279"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on October 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HAB38238CB4ED4914982F02DEDDF401CD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Consolidation of disabled veterans outreach program and local veterans’ employment representatives</header> <subsection id="H2874452920FD49488A3F314EF9C75217"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Consolidation</header> <paragraph id="H37DD9842D0774EC1A24D91C717E25E79"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 4104 of title 38, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HD0CC067646374518881A79A8FB08EA8E" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="H83F56EB7E1C64738BEF6DDB28DE30181"><enum>4104.</enum><header>Veteran employment specialists</header>
<subsection id="H7768F47F6BE84E53985A7F73FCAF5973"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement for employment by states</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC4E90758A6DC4DDC9CFB450D0415AA2B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to approval by the Secretary, a State shall employ and assign such full- or part-time veteran employment specialists in an agency of the State as the State determines appropriate and efficient to carry out the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HB221B1C5D4FD4F25878930443C306B33" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Employment, training, and placement services under this chapter.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2A5A6E4DBBC14453823FAD4DD7931B26" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Intensive services under this chapter to meet the employment needs of eligible veterans with the following priority in the provision of services:</text> <clause id="HC7827F6400D04505917C508210B5A6DE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Special disabled veterans.</text></clause>
<clause id="H0BC5C770544E4BAD8AC47CB0DD0E5263"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Other disabled veterans.</text></clause> <clause id="H369DD801EEF3419A990EB7740325FD85"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Other eligible veterans in accordance with priorities determined by the Secretary taking into account applicable rates of unemployment and the employment emphases set forth in chapter 42 of this title.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD3F34378D41E4CEE8CADA383E53C0A91" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the provision of services in accordance with this subsection, maximum emphasis in meeting the employment and training needs of veterans shall be placed on assisting economically or educationally disadvantaged veterans.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H05E0E29F3A2240E68215C79A039A55F2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Principal duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As principal duties, veteran employment specialists shall—</text>
<paragraph id="HCB41726EE95B485EAD5406950471C467"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct outreach to employers in the area to assist veterans and disabled veterans in gaining employment, including conducting seminars for employers and, in conjunction with employers, conducting job search workshops and establishing job search groups; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9AA82E66D50E48BBB891841232A2F494"><enum>(2)</enum><text>facilitate employment, training, and placement services furnished to veterans and disabled veterans in a State under the applicable State employment service delivery systems.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HAA62BC4D30414E6C95FBE7138480B9C0" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirement for qualified veterans</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HED8E1B8176BB405BAB8D86D9D586701E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Except as provided by paragraph (2), a State shall, to the maximum extent practicable, employ qualified veterans to carry out the services referred to in subsection (a). Preference shall be given in the appointment of such specialists to qualified disabled veterans. Preference shall be accorded in the following order:</text> <subparagraph id="HEB19A6A8A6AA4B3587648011053A8A2D" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To qualified service-connected disabled veterans.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H05C59191A8AD473BA1B4DD6FC6CC6FB1" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If no veteran described in subparagraph (A) is available, to qualified eligible veterans.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H681AA1AF7D234D9385A79F963FFF658B" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>If no veteran described in subparagraph (A) or (B) is available, then to qualified eligible persons.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4FE6F05593BA4C99AF087A84679262D9" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During any period in which more than 10 percent of the individuals employed to carry out the services referred to in subsection (a) are non-veterans, the preference accorded under paragraph (1) shall be as follows:</text> <subparagraph id="H4FC990B946CB4611A724DCA2826B622B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To qualified service-connected disabled veterans.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFDADE63621F640F88BC26285797B9470" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>If no veteran described in subparagraph (A) is available, to qualified eligible veterans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD56A3D3FFA3C4411933B2B3DC095B44E" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H93B4F57648E24E15A5FAA8A12D939461"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Each State that employs a veteran employment specialist under this section shall submit to the Secretary an annual report on the qualifications used by the State in making hiring determinations for such specialists and the salary structure under which such specialists are compensated.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8847A7A3953D465B99AA09CB96B00FF0" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives an annual report summarizing the reports submitted under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H53BDCC2EA5814141B6FC1F7176447095" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The first report submitted by the Secretary under subparagraph (B) shall include an evaluation of whether the pay for veteran employment specialists should be scheduled on a standard basis for each State and include locality pay.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H39C6725AFCD141D8A581211671161863"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Part-Time employees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A part-time veteran employment specialist shall perform the functions of a veteran employment specialist under this section on a halftime basis.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBC9D05F73D61412090B6D0E68BA92BAD" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each veteran employment specialist shall be administratively responsible to the manager of the employment service delivery system and shall provide reports, not less frequently than quarterly, to the manager of such office and to the Director for Veterans’ Employment and Training for the State regarding compliance with Federal law and regulations with respect to special services and priorities for eligible veterans and eligible persons.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA3AA3A3B1289458B999963D0A21A998B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such chapter is amended by striking the item relating to section 4104 and inserting the following new item:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="HF6F68FA7E7CA4E4BA840D0580DE6FADA" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">4104. Veteran employment specialists.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0226B59403FB4D7DAC31985E1798955B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall ensure that an individual who is a veteran employment specialist under section 4104 of title 38, United States Code, as amended by paragraph (1), is properly trained to carry out the duties of such position.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H9C2C7C9E6D354644832772D71E4A42F0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Such title is further amended—</text> <paragraph id="H7B5579D3BB764E249AC53DA5B51486C7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking section 4103A and by striking the item relating to such section in the table of sections at the beginning of chapter 41 of such title;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4361FB95ECE54308B256C804445B6607"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 4102A—</text> <subparagraph id="H332D781759024879ADFF1B6F3777D4F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text>
<clause id="H8A9F8E247C8040F0B27DCF7296B2BFF1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)—</text> <subclause id="HFE71BCED1A3D4FF881299F4E1EF6BEC3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B) and redesignating subparagraph (C) as subparagraph (B);</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HCEA7C3058B704FFABF78EF3031045020"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (A) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H27CE6159D369478095C3FC4EB1460AE2"> <subparagraph id="H5D8FB57A01AC428D9052C799E174EDA7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">veteran employment specialists appointed under section 4104(a) of this title; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause>
<subclause id="HF222AC487F764F71A6731BBDD4E1F5F2"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>such specialists and representatives described in subparagraphs (A) and (B)</quote> and inserting <quote>such representatives described in subparagraph (A)</quote>;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HDF0C0D512C7E4822AED37B7AE338BC8F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialists and through local veterans’ employment representatives</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialists</quote>; </text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8DAF1EDAFD504FBBA9D2C4D46E6C13FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> <clause id="HF0F6129ED1124E6EB7268F23C413A7B9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text>
<subclause id="H1B91E73DA4AD4DEAB147B24336B25FF5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>sections 4103A(a) and</quote> and inserting <quote>section</quote>; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE56BA47DE7FB43E3984F94C26D716E83"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>section 4103A or</quote>;</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H16B669D6278043CAA7E8BD2D4F7905C1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A)—</text> <subclause id="H07A48C3CB6064218BF8B3174CA9ECDB9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i)(I)—</text>
<item id="HCAFD740C00674784844C7B3226F6BE75"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialists and local veterans’ employment representatives</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialists</quote>; and </text></item> <item id="H87F20149A9364FA0B3A5639B0BE141C8"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by striking <quote>sections 4103A and 4104</quote> and inserting <quote>section 4104</quote>;</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="HD3A7E0BD50A94AD7A8E5CAD36FB5944B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialist or a local veterans’ employment representative</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialist</quote>;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H8EA238347102436E8E5FAF4FF4F0E5A5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>4103A or</quote>;</text></clause>
<clause id="HED96382F28A2408181A64F0A1A268B9B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialist and local veterans’ employment representative</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialist</quote>; </text></clause> <clause id="H7401342339224A69BEE8CE54C6EDD125"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in paragraph (7), by striking <quote>4103A or</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HBD0C2EAB5DEA4C3AAA34531F2BBAE809"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in paragraph (8)(A)—</text> <subclause id="HA0D529E85E4D4AEB8BB6099845FCAFE3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>4103A or</quote>; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HAE7043FE18404413B6F2BE27951CC5C9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialist or a local veterans’ employment representative</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialist</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H59DB6C9B903148BF9BD19E606146CE61"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (f)(1), by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialists and local veterans’ employment representatives</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialists</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H809952D363984E21B50CA8FA84EF25B3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 4109(a), by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialists, local veterans’ employment representatives</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialists</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA0CC36C131A7469F986E85598FE4CB53"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 4112(d)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H08C404E995C941A58B0089A900927DF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialist</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialist</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFFCFCDF1814A43CF916B79CC668BDC2D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (2) and redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (2); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1BC406BF7B1443CABCA8DF5BC0BAC863"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in section 3672(d)(1), by striking <quote>disabled veterans’ outreach program specialists under section 4103A</quote> and inserting <quote>veteran employment specialists appointed under section 4104(a)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H39421446AFF14690BE20FB3BF44B7DA7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on October 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H253CCE5EC4484169B7542F343F81A113"><enum>5.</enum><header>Additional technical and conforming amendments</header>
<subsection id="H891DEC15F5A8423FB692FAA48C5FE0CD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Chapter 41</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/41">Chapter 41</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, as amended by this Act, is further amended as follows:</text> <paragraph id="H5DA814B327E54C88B7824C4434184A39"><enum>(1)</enum><text>By striking <quote>Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE245318896D14989BC707EC4C9376616"><enum>(2)</enum><text>By striking <quote>Department of Labor</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Department</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBEC709FEA6754BABA69DE0A2B37EF479"><enum>(3)</enum><text>By striking <quote>Secretary of Labor</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Secretary</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H898067AEBBDC4132BAD9B301964507A5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In section 4101, by striking paragraph (8).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H80C0E397C2634D39B1B093661DCBCC64"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In section 4102A(b)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4EE73293D1934A10B25C7EF3A8546021"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>such Assistant Secretary</quote> and inserting <quote>such Deputy Under Secretary</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2779FF76F41B4338B901D24B780F3AF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>and consulting with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H94580E1521E849489F882CBEB42CC5A5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In section 4105(b), by striking <quote>and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs</quote> both places it appears.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB976D6EC8D5E4D68912DE634E06A6B96"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In section 4106(a), by striking <quote>chapters 42 and</quote> and inserting <quote>chapter</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDD5906A536654FBAAB53FC89984802A5"><enum>(8)</enum><text>By striking section 4108.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0D0F615B0B7B4CF4A0CA00C6433BC3D5"><enum>(9)</enum><text>In the table of sections at the beginning of such chapter, by striking the item relating to section 4108.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H38CFA03E3817466C8FD7995D26489155" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In section 4110(d), by striking paragraph (1) and redesignating paragraphs (2) through (6) as paragraphs (1) through (5), respectively.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8176A09FE11149ADB6F70C8A92ACB000" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text>In section 4110A(b), by striking <quote>Congress</quote> and inserting <quote>the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives</quote>. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4F54D780E3BB4A16AA258E08A8CB9FD0"><enum>(12)</enum><text>In subsections (b) through (h) of section 4114, by striking <quote>Assistant Secretary</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Deputy Under Secretary</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC79C49FD7D084FA8943FF43AAC378A7D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Chapter 42</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/42">Chapter 42</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended as follows:</text>
<paragraph id="H04967A7C2C90413FBD571CDD39FF36E1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In section 4212(c), by striking <quote>include as part</quote> and inserting <quote>shall transmit to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs for inclusion as part</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H20EB5F6082E54D7A9C2345D8D003CC88" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In section 4215(d)(1)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H82701162A7F84FA1957EECAC26B92813" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>In the</quote> and inserting <quote>For inclusion as part of the</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8B4AAB05BA964D5084537304ECB29731" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>shall evaluate</quote> and inserting <quote>shall transmit to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs an evaluation of</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H4F5EB78890974BF197F91F7769B9C802"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Chapter 43</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/43">Chapter 43</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended as follows:</text> <paragraph id="H958C4CEA265348A5BAC9F8B9A06CD9BB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In section 4303, by striking paragraph (11).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H97B786E283CA40D5A5DA9A5657409A1F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>By striking <quote>Secretary of Veterans Affairs</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Secretary</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1683674D5B8B45D3A88BE62C9A877518"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In section 4321, by striking <quote>(through the Veterans’ Employment and Training Service)</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBB94F346349D472188D931734149FB43"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In section 4332(a)(1), by striking <quote>of Labor</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD5C3B6C5C4A34990BA31EA48F0205848"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In section 4333, by striking <quote>, the Secretary of Defense, and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs</quote> and inserting <quote>and the Secretary of Defense</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD99BDA37A5A34D8C9918FD8B9DB2E8C1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Chapter 20</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/20">Chapter 20</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended as follows:</text> <paragraph id="H9987BC6D76D7405AB7848D8A43C493F3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In section 2003(a)(4), by striking <quote>of the Department of Labor</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H657A0059E36740738BF07E2C1708673F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In section 2011(g)(2), by striking <quote>the Department of Labor,</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H25165ACC054747868C71FDE832287BE3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In section 2021—</text>
<subparagraph id="H28AA45C531CC4A4F9F49004C845ED3DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Secretary of Labor</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Secretary</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5285C7622D844C8D9F4BFFEEAB6A4623" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (e)—</text>
<clause id="H02C44C13A65748DF9BE9370568ECCDFB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking the subsection heading and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H98B27575BB124414938B84AB131A54C1" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H6EEB6042C7BD41D99C37C982F9FE3E98" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration through Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training</header></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause> <clause id="H3E760B3635E24BF5BA8EC8456E3D2683" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training</quote> and inserting <quote>Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD1E51F51C3F64872B75115CEBE377DA3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In section 2021A—</text> <subparagraph id="HBF9F76C7BB08443BA87454B3BD69CC9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Secretary of Labor</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Secretary</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3B9805F7B0814D2A8D3E895E1DE1D42D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text> <clause id="HCB22E7C5961C43BCBC95E6941EEF9583"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking the subsection heading and inserting the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HE22150D4F8944906B8E7309FFBE002E0" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<subsection id="HEE980E11473B423BB5AA6DD128953047"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration through Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training</header></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause>
<clause id="H251954BAB5714BFE9CD18FE9510EA23E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training</quote> and inserting <quote>Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC38EBE49457E43F3B931B55CF3D71DE3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In section 2023—</text>
<subparagraph id="H2816640D8BDE445892C541F6ACE99C8D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>and the Secretary of Labor (hereinafter in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretaries</quote>)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H69EFE7B2EAAD46F48BB782F8ED016CE0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Secretaries</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Secretary</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9539380C233D42CC91DED3E13234270E" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In section 2065(b)(5), by striking subparagraph (E) and redesignating subparagraphs (F) through (H) as subparagraphs (E) through (G), respectively.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF02E9D88BF774ED3A8C48C9FEB197DE9" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In section 2066(a)(3), by striking subparagraph (A) and redesignating subparagraphs (B) through (G) as subparagraphs (A) through (F), respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H884DF20016FD4CF699313FA527B93D1B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Other provisions of title 38</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title 38, United States Code, is further amended as follows:</text> <paragraph id="H32A7036D6A8F4F758EC3E53A6F275B3E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In section 542(a)(2)(B), by striking clause (i) and redesignating clauses (ii) and (iii) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H476E56AB817F4C6E93531239F361F940"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In section 544(a)(2)(B), by striking clause (i) and redesignating clauses (ii) through (vi) as clauses (i) through (v), respectively.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B72B4F6FDB145FE90439D755019F9F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In section 3118(b), by striking <quote>and the Assistant Secretary for Veterans’ Employment in the Department of Labor</quote>.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H88DD97C8A466479589E79652C1768DD2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In section 3119(c), by striking <quote>Education, the Assistant Secretary for Veterans’ Employment in the Department of Labor,</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H560D8DCF03A340108FCF2FC51EF18DA1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In section 3121(a)(3)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H67D28897747B447FBC6F0BDF119A44CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, (B)</quote> and inserting <quote>and (B)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H79D1A2155B5C4889AA29AAA2A5EDE0B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, and (C) one representative of the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training of the Department of Labor. (b) The Secretary shall, on a regular basis, consult with and seek the advice of the Committee with respect to the administration of veterans’ rehabilitation programs under this title</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA0A364D40EF84B00898F65B973FFC5FF"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In section 3692(a), by striking <quote>and the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training shall be ex officio members</quote> and inserting <quote>an ex officio member</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBBF149C8F2644383A2D53C0E838E0A1D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>In section 6306—</text>
<subparagraph id="H21DE4277AAD64AECA6ECAE380A3763E5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>shall arrange with the Secretary of Labor for the State employment service to match</quote> and inserting <quote>shall ensure that the State employment service matches</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBC8CEA1ACF0F4FA89B88D049FF409594"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor,</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB4B065A263A9436985FE3756FC6B767C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Title 10</header>
<paragraph id="H6B4C9A3DD8DF4F279B92C278CC90EA7B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>TAP Program</header><text>Section 1144 of title 10, United States Code, is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H1C8602216EEB45E3A7522E0E092242AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>Secretary of Labor</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>Secretary of Veterans Affairs</quote>;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H42F6D451695F4D9BAB0632EE80885B58"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <clause id="H8FC1E4371BEA4DBA8DFD2C81CE040E15"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>, the Secretary of Homeland Security, and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs</quote> and inserting <quote>and the Secretary of Homeland Security</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H64485401B0C542989059DC79A639118F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>, the Secretary of Homeland Security, and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall cooperate with the Secretary of Labor</quote> and inserting <quote>and the Secretary of Homeland Security shall cooperate with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HECA227BA9FBB46C9B9EEB621A4A50B47"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(1), by striking <quote>Department of Labor to</quote> and inserting <quote>Department of Veterans Affairs to</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2F4002E2EA9B4AB8877CC7C1868710C1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="USC">: Department of Labor</header-in-text></quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9D744CAF256F4212B4A0123DDE8AFC72"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/10/58">chapter 58</external-xref> of title 10, United States Code, is amended by striking the item relating to section 1144 and inserting the following new item:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H5D209746427A40AC92620F36B6888E8A" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">1144. Employment assistance, job training assistance, and other transitional services.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3D1210CDCDE64C8C80169BB40C9CD336"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on October 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H7CA0B66AA8DC4D75A9F71D96653B3C6E"><enum>6.</enum><header>Study and report on transfer of programs</header> <subsection id="H8B93B3F5CEC24658AD4358C4970635AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Labor shall jointly conduct a study on implementing—</text>
<paragraph id="H4D5DD509A96549C0941B02FBCCF5DD5C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the transfer of functions under section 2; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA0A032A2B1EC4173920D6FFFF6C80881"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the amendments made by this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEC3E7A9E59D54DFEAE9CF2BB48445552"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters included</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such study shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H53F5E09525B34BAE945CC8EEB48CF400"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A comprehensive discussion of the improvements to services for veterans made by the transfer of functions under section 2.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE78CEC5B16B245A59BF1B5D124C6B30F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An analysis of the personnel, assets, and liabilities of the Department of Labor and the Department of Veterans Affairs that would be involved in such transfer.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H18DD003127FC4140B30B8C2506F9F514"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of the Deputy Under Secretary for Veterans’ Employment and Training established under section 4102A(a) of title 38, United States Code, as amended by this Act, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H36B7EC58A9FA483899D1309E510A56C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an explanation of where such position would exist within the organization chart of the Department;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDDFDA2B91A4347A5B6871BB84ED8C099"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an identification of to whom such position would report; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H21E4E1665F344505839BDDF9AA98DED4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the functions that would be carried out by such a position.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H775DB61214B94641BE56B5EDAF888B9A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A detailed estimate of the cost to the Federal Government to implement such transfer, including any costs or savings resulting from—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA81CE417E93F4BC696E11BE5D0E8ADF5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>carrying out such implementation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H724B3F0E9B0A4D9EA405053205841002"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Veterans Affairs carrying out the functions so transferred.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFDD3DEA966B340719A4EA0C9F7A75230"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A plan to implement such transfer, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H2B3276BE7BDF487CB96812D6CA99E7C4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a detailed time line of such implementation;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H745EAD2F55ED4BEA87A901014E3AE120"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a list of the rules, regulations, and laws in effect on the date of the commencement of such study that would need to be revised for such implementation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA26128435B3F4E5689EFBC1702E6DA63"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a list of the memorandums of agreement entered into with Federal or State departments or agencies that would need to be revised for such implementation;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H78F4339FBB414D12B8B6166904679D08"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a detailed description of how to effectively enforce the administration of employment and reemployment rights of members of the uniformed services under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/43">chapter 43</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, during such implementation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2E617D4BD5634CDABB155BF4B6284EF0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>how the transfer of employees will be implemented, including—</text>
<clause id="HA29A1BBAC99742B2BD211A7F356630A1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>options available to employees who do not want to be transferred;</text></clause> <clause id="H7AB4907B3B954B058E93931A316637C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the locations of where former Department of Labor employees will be assigned in the Department of Veterans Affairs; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HED20C6B7654342CCB4364BAB518CE434"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any organizational changes required in the Department of Veterans Affairs to accommodate such former Department of Labor employees.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA2B5F9D467704E048C55089404535E35"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed plan to train employees who carry out activities under section 4104 of title 38, United States Code, to carry out the functions so transferred, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H6A16E8D98B3640F28D8D053121C45ACD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how training manuals in effect as of the date of the commencement of such study would need to be revised;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6555427ACCDE4881AD1672C0321A9B63"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whether the Secretary of Veterans Affairs or the Secretary of Labor would have responsibility for any such revision; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H307EC615A64A48C7B3BEED7E1C676AE3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>where such employees would be located.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H25783875540A4D4E90CDD47BA8D3A601"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Any other issues the Secretaries consider appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3F0F959604E845FD866C89D07DAF8BFF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretaries shall jointly submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report on such study, including—</text> <paragraph id="H78D3B01796C24553A26E2F866C21A9AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the recommendation of each Secretary as to how to best implement the transfer of functions described in such study;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEAE44794AB0243458046BE228E250DE3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the advantages and disadvantages of such transfer;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD2AC7BC5271C497890094FB46CA8B201"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a list of regulatory and statutory actions required to implement such transfer that are not included under this Act;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA6E0008CD49B446B9939A89C785E208F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the amount of time each Secretary determines necessary to carry out such transfer;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9039C60E140848BAA6454E968905227A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>whether, to carry out such transfer, any interoperability capabilities will need to be developed to electronically exchange information between the Department of Veterans Affairs and employees who were formerly under the Department of Labor before such transfer;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD47DB50B18AE42B5ADAE834E999CB74A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>whether each Secretary plans to continue collaborating with the other Secretary after such transfer is completed, including an explanation of any such planned collaboration;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE260A61613D641C3B508FD1A48B2D2C4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>an estimate of the training required to carry out the functions so transferred, including the number of employees requiring training and for which programs; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2A7C73FD308E44398FA729319C663278"><enum>(8)</enum><text>any other matters the Secretaries consider appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

