<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD875CBBC0CD147269C7D6CF82EECA43C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3966 IH: Improving Atmospheric River Forecasts Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3966</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To accelerate subseasonal to seasonal prediction skills related to precipitation forecasts for water management in the western United States, improve atmospheric river forecasts across the country, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5B32C49A109C42859736513BFD04AA1F" style="OLC"><section id="H18C57882E03E41DAAA7D4C35B24A8052" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Atmospheric River Forecasts Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5F134950ECAE477BBD463AC82887BFA6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Subseasonal to seasonal forecasting pilot projects</header><subsection id="HB6E1C9126D574D18AF98468A9C50FDE4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Improving subseasonal and seasonal forecasts</header><text>Subsection (h) of section 1762 of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8521">15 U.S.C. 8521</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="HDE779C9335CD40E9BE1CC0C8C3D50C88" style="OLC"><subsection id="HACF87FA7174949529FB033715FFCB620"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Subseasonal to seasonal forecasting pilot projects</header><paragraph id="H8D30D3DDACBC4799882047FC22BE0249" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary shall establish at least one pilot project within the U.S. Weather Research Program of the Oceanic and Atmospheric Research office of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to support improved subseasonal to seasonal precipitation forecasts for water management in the western United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H841739C90F2C4C8FA7EC78712528A66C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Objectives</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Under Secretary shall ensure that a pilot project under paragraph (1) addresses key science challenges to improving forecasts and developing related products described in subsection (c) for water management in the western United States, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="H3308BA92F6934C7C9C7CFFC0F7CD9120"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Improving model resolution, both horizontal and vertical, to resolve issues associated with mountainous terrain, such as intensity of precipitation and relative fraction of rain versus snow precipitation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3980A0985CE144A487C6D4B8C6DB7549"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Improving fidelity in modeling of—</text><clause id="H023E9C04435D447C9ED204CAB2283581"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the atmospheric boundary layer in mountainous regions; and</text></clause><clause id="H42C11DDFA9B04C528450430709AFD9BF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>atmospheric rivers.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11F16E895B2247A09D135FE0FC4C6688"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Resolving challenges in predicting winter atmospheric circulation and storm tracks, including periods of blocked versus unblocked flow over the eastern North Pacific Ocean and western United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E8CD719A2474203A97E8ED2C5B48783"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Advancing scientific understanding of the roles of atmospheric rivers in subseasonal to seasonal precipitation, and developing tools to predict periods of active or inactive atmospheric river landfalls and inland penetration over the western United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E024CD650B84F5AB88FED3B32D3D6EB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>A pilot project under this subsection shall include activities that carry out the following:</text><subparagraph id="H37E308DF793D463A83738E89A2387128"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Best implement recommendations of the National Weather Service’s 2019 Report, entitled <quote>Subseasonal and Seasonal Forecasting Innovation: Plans for the Twenty-First Century</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65265DBDBE204FC78D6340721E4E71B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Achieve measurable objectives for operational forecast improvement.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF5F836CB1B347EA985D2B566A686C57"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Engage with, and leverage the resources of, institutions of higher education (as such term is defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)) with experience in western precipitation science, as well as entities within the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in existence as of the date of the enactment of this subsection, including the Western Regional Climate Center and the National Centers for Environmental Information.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCEFE7F5439141AC853E378F4C8995B5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Are carried out in coordination with the Assistant Administrator for the Office of Oceanic and Atmospheric Research and the Director of the National Weather Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E7D01DFBE1248A38A69C66C829D8A15"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>From amounts made available to Operations, Research, and Facilities at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, there is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9881FC583A5A4BD2880818128B91043D" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority under this subsection shall terminate on the date that is five years after the date of the enactment of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block/></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HC527D838512F4AECA943FC622698ADCF"><enum>3.</enum><header>Atmospheric rivers forecast improvement program</header><subsection id="H2628FE3CBAFF47EA83D5585656C30842"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Under Secretary, in collaboration with the United States weather industry and academic partners, shall establish an atmospheric river forecast improvement program (in this section referred to as the <quote>program</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H84B391DF311F4E17B72039932188D64F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Goal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The goal of the program shall be to reduce through the development and extension of accurate, effective, and actionable forecasts and warnings the loss of life and economic losses from atmospheric rivers, including by—</text><paragraph id="H0171EC3B7C7447F09973B677FB67470C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establishing quantitative atmospheric river forecast skill metrics; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17BCC4F4D3FF428ABB5AE357906759A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>developing methods to categorize the intensity of atmospheric rivers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEF841E07E3E74308AA8864A23D5214F5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Innovative observations and modeling</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary shall ensure the program periodically examines, tests, and evaluates the value of incorporating innovative observations, such as observations from crewed or uncrewed aircraft, novel airborne and satellite-based snowpack measurements, ocean buoys data, soil moisture monitoring systems, reservoir storage data, observations from mesonets, or other emerging technologies, with respect to the improvement of atmospheric river forecasts, predictions, and warnings.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7AA90625CD7D4E39B2E09F7CBFF2FCBE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Program plan</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Administrator for Oceanic and Atmospheric Research, in coordination with the Director of the National Weather Service, shall develop a plan that details the specific research, development, data acquisition, and technology transfer activities, as well as corresponding resources and timelines, necessary to achieve the goals of the program under subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H22F6399CDB5B403B93605E09325F5566"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual budget for plan submittal</header><text>After the development of the plan pursuant to subsection (d), the Under Secretary, acting through the Assistant Administrator for Oceanic and Atmospheric Research, and in coordination with the Director of the National Weather Service, shall, not less frequently than annually, submit to Congress a proposed budget corresponding with the activities identified in such plan.</text></subsection><subsection id="H053AEF27545040C39FF14D4550E4461D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms <quote>Under Secretary</quote> and <quote>weather industry</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 2 of the Weather Research and Forecasting Innovation Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8501">15 U.S.C. 8501</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

