<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3E38B27D1A7441D3BA59F83871DE4116" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5046 IH: Preventing Election Subversion Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5046</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to provide increased protections for election workers and voters in elections for Federal office, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H27D56E14B4854B3299D2248E2814C2C3" style="OLC"><section id="H6D8971039D8045CB80F16263A303AD25" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing Election Subversion Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF72D501133214543901692F0B527D0B6" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Restrictions on removal of local election administrators in administration of elections for Federal office</header><subsection id="H80FC3241479F4CC3BD7153C810483C15"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="H4E8A3D1F4AAA42DC844D2E0D4D2038BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Congress has explicit and broad authority to regulate the time, place, and manner of Federal elections under the Elections Clause under article I, section 4, clause 1 of the Constitution of the United States, including by establishing standards for the fair, impartial, and uniform administration of Federal elections by State and local officials.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFBEE514D1FE4B46AD6A7FFF39D3496F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Elections Clause was understood from the framing of the Constitution of the United States to contain <quote>words of great latitude,</quote> granting Congress broad power over Federal elections and a plenary right to preempt State regulation in this area. As made clear at the Constitutional Convention and the State ratification debates that followed, this grant of congressional authority was meant to <quote>insure free and fair elections,</quote> promote the uniform administration of Federal elections, and <quote>preserve and restore to the people their equal and sacred rights of election.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB25FF676767342C29DB70DA78B066989"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In the founding debates on the Elections Clause, many delegates also argued that a broad grant of authority to Congress over Federal elections was necessary to check any <quote>abuses that might be made of the discretionary power</quote> to regulate the time, place, and manner of elections granted the States, including attempts at partisan entrenchment, malapportionment, and the exclusion of political minorities. As the Supreme Court has recognized, the Elections Clause empowers Congress to <quote>protect the elections on which its existence depends,</quote> Ex parte Yarbrough, 110 U.S. 651, 658 (1884), and <quote>protect the citizen in the exercise of rights conferred by the Constitution of the United States essential to the healthy organization of the government itself,</quote> id. at 666.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F27AFB2788D4D64BB2C060272686690"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The Elections Clause grants Congress <quote>plenary and paramount jurisdiction over the whole subject</quote> of Federal elections, Ex parte Siebold, 100 U.S. 371, 388 (1879), allowing Congress to implement <quote>a complete code for congressional elections.</quote> Smiley v. Holm, 285 U.S. 355, 366 (1932). The Elections Clause, unlike, for example, the Commerce Clause, has been found to grant Congress the authority to compel States to alter their regulations as to Federal elections, id. at 366–67, even if these alterations would impose additional costs on the States to execute or enforce. Association of Community Organizations for Reform Now v. Miller, 129 F.3d 833 (6th Cir. 1997).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3829ACD801784472857CB08840E520BF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The phrase <quote>manner of holding elections</quote> in the Elections Clause has been interpreted by the Supreme Court to authorize Congress to regulate all aspects of the Federal election process, including <quote>notices, registration, supervision of voting, protection of voters, prevention of fraud and corrupt practices, counting of votes, duties of inspectors and canvassers, and the making and publication of election returns.</quote> Smiley v. Holm, 285 U.S. 355, 366 (1932).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA21E8DC314D4ADCBB7BA33185FCAFFF"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Supreme Court has recognized the broad <quote>substantive scope</quote> of the Elections Clause and upheld Federal laws promulgated thereunder regulating redistricting, voter registration, campaign finance, primary elections, recounts, party affiliation rules, and balloting.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E022339D3D24550827E685EE07F6563"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The authority of Congress under the Elections Clause also entails the power to ensure enforcement of its laws regulating Federal elections. <quote>[I]f Congress has the power to make regulations, it must have the power to enforce them.</quote> Ex parte Siebold, 100 U.S. 371, 387 (1879). The Supreme Court has noted that there can be no question that Congress may impose additional penalties for offenses committed by State officers in connection with Federal elections even if they differ from the penalties prescribed by State law for the same acts. Id. at 387–88.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54248AE08B3247A58B5AA4C64775B9B3"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The fair and impartial administration of Federal elections by State and local officials is central to <quote>the successful working of this government,</quote> Ex parte Yarbrough, 110 U.S. 651, 666 (1884), and to <quote>protect the act of voting . . . and the election itself from corruption or fraud,</quote> id. at 661–62.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H772CFB4FAA2B4C2E858AB98243D45BC1"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The Elections Clause thus grants Congress the authority to ensure that the administration of Federal elections is free of political bias or discrimination and that election officials are insulated from political influence or other forms of coercion in discharging their duties in connection with Federal elections.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61FF9EDBB62B46938451A7129BC29E70"><enum>(10)</enum><text>In some States, oversight of local election administrators has been allocated to State Election Boards, or special commissions formed by those boards, that are appointed by the prevailing political party in a State, as opposed to nonpartisan or elected office holders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA628DFF646954A3E88B22E20D857B9A6"><enum>(11)</enum><text>In certain newly enacted State policies, these appointed statewide election administrators have been granted wide latitude to suspend or remove local election administrators in cases where the statewide election administrators identify whatever the State deems to be a violation. There is no requirement that there be a finding of intent by the local election administrator to commit the violation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC90BBB7E2CC4F9A9E25837DD5573701"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Local election administrators across the country can be suspended or removed according to different standards, potentially exposing them to different political pressures or biases that could result in uneven administration of Federal elections.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FB53AB0293B4784B05D142B4C9AE988"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The Elections Clause grants Congress the ultimate authority to ensure that oversight of State and local election administrators is fair and impartial in order to ensure equitable and uniform administration of Federal elections.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA37A704233A24AB6B06EEB9BAB3EC8E2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Restriction</header><paragraph id="HB243E54E1DB04C7D89AE079DB337C360"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Standard for removal of a local election administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A statewide election administrator may only suspend, remove, or relieve the duties of a local election administrator in the State with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office for inefficiency, neglect of duty, or malfeasance in office.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80C7ACE8C5304BD39248AC0FFB29B21D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Private right of action</header><subparagraph id="HDAA4672B05624DD1A9E4308AFA270BAF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any local election administrator suspended, removed, or otherwise relieved of duties in violation of paragraph (1) with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office or against whom any proceeding for suspension, removal, or relief from duty in violation of paragraph (1) with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office may be pending, may bring an action in an appropriate district court of the United States for declaratory or injunctive relief with respect to the violation. Any such action shall name as the defendant the statewide election administrator responsible for the adverse action. The district court shall, to the extent practicable, expedite any such proceeding.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53AA5CB0DCA243BB901D3F3A6E7E82F9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Statute of limitations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any action brought under this subsection must be commenced not later than 1 year after the date of the suspension, removal, relief from duties, or commencement of the proceeding to remove, suspend, or relieve the duties of a local election administrator with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBE61281D06E42788DF268EBC3A900E2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Attorney’s fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any action or proceeding under this subsection, the court may allow a prevailing plaintiff, other than the United States, reasonable attorney’s fees as part of the costs, and may include expert fees as part of the attorney’s fee. The term <term>prevailing plaintiff</term> means a plaintiff that substantially prevails pursuant to a judicial or administrative judgment or order, or an enforceable written agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6619EDCEE1E42C5B3B38EC15180634B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Removal of State proceedings to Federal court</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local election administrator who is subject to an administrative or judicial proceeding for suspension, removal, or relief from duty by a statewide election administrator with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office may remove the proceeding to an appropriate district court of the United States. Any order remanding a case to the State court or agency from which it was removed under this subsection shall be reviewable by appeal or otherwise.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29F00C08EA2348119BE004DB4A60858A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Right of United States to intervene</header><subparagraph id="H23DC1FE5BA034FD39E407814FE0234C0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Notice to Attorney General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whenever any administrative or judicial proceeding is brought to suspend, remove, or relieve the duties of any local election administrator by a statewide election administrator with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office, the statewide election administrator who initiated such proceeding shall deliver a copy of the pleadings instituting the proceeding to the Assistant Attorney General for the Civil Rights Division of the Department of Justice. The local election administrator against whom such proceeding is brought may also deliver such pleadings to the Assistant Attorney General.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14C9A9D388A84DE393FB89B4649E51FB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Right to intervene</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States may intervene in any administrative or judicial proceeding brought to suspend, remove, or relieve the duties of any local election administrator by a statewide election administrator with respect to the administration of an election for Federal office and in any action initiated pursuant to paragraph (2) or in any removal pursuant to paragraph (4).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H94C3AFAB2B544700BD9BF569F9E796C0"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In reviewing any action brought under this section, a court of the United States shall not afford any deference to any State official, administrator, or tribunal that initiated, approved, adjudicated, or reviewed any administrative or judicial proceeding to suspend, remove, or otherwise relieve the duties of a local election administrator.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H28E42B6081BE4C1280CC009F3813F2F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports to the Department of Justice</header><paragraph id="H243FC8ED19194B8D937980A7954C0025"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the suspension, removal, or relief of the duties of a local election administrator by a statewide election administrator, the Statewide election administrator shall submit to the Assistant Attorney General for the Civil Rights Divisions of the Department of Justice a report that includes the following information:</text><subparagraph id="H58386B5D3B6A4B86B2986DB590AE50B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A statement that a local election administrator was suspended, removed, or relieved of their duties.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7FF70F85BD240C993097DCCF44EE00D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Information on whether the local election administrator was determined to be inefficient or to have engaged in neglect of duty or malfeasance in office.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9528EA3168534E9CACACDCCB749E8B71"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of the effect that the suspension, removal, or relief of the duties of the local election administrator will have on—</text><clause id="HE388B402C3764319BF73C19E990227FB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the administration of elections and voters in the election jurisdictions for which the local election official provided such duties; and</text></clause><clause id="H5DB9F69B520A4E05979757F3E4FD4C68"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the administration of elections and voters in the State at large.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC83540C42154152BAACD9646A4B6A07"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Demographic information about the local election official suspended, removed, or relieved and the jurisdictions for which such election official was providing the duties suspended, removed, or relieved.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H587AEB80C6724B28BD08858FAC5C1EE8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Such other information as requested by the Assistant Attorney General for the purposes of determining—</text><clause id="H1959832C706B4A308980CE27C0ED9C76"><enum>(i)</enum><text>whether such suspension, removal, or relief of duties was based on unlawful discrimination; and</text></clause><clause id="H2BFBF52249744EF3990CFED5266AB9F2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether such suspension, removal, or relief of duties was due to inefficiency, neglect of duty, or malfeasance in office.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA575075161B54F2E8DB99E88CB5DA630"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expedited reporting for actions within 30 days of an election</header><subparagraph id="H6CF500CB526445B58F8140AD060B3B0D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a suspension, removal, or relief of duties of a local administrator described in paragraph (1) occurs during the period described in subparagraph (B), the report required under paragraph (1) shall be submitted not later than 48 hours after such suspension, removal, or relief of duties.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EF73210244B4A6CBDB9D0EE9CF437B7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Period described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The period described in this subparagraph is any period which begins 60 days before the date of an election for Federal office and which ends 60 days after such election.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB367434615A44D82B7BB35C9861E0BE0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="H00D35162D8444A97B3A2BF4D5274270D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Election</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>election</term> has the meaning given the term in section 301(1) of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30101">52 U.S.C. 30101(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98753937E6FD4E95AD0271C10E7666D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal office</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Federal office</term> has the meaning given the term in section 301(3) of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30101">52 U.S.C. 30101(3)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC556BD7B2FB4AC9B93D6764E5F5F14E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Local election administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>local election administrator</term> means, with respect to a local jurisdiction in a State, the individual or entity responsible for the administration of elections for Federal office in the local jurisdiction.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DC76A92B5F542A6AA86F45275C45B09"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Statewide election administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>statewide election administrator</term> means, with respect to a State—</text><subparagraph id="HE894E88326044BAD9B6E8489EECB3A60"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the individual or entity, including a State elections board, responsible for the administration of elections for Federal office in the State on a statewide basis; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27DD82C1227448A3A93A9AC7AFC9B022"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a statewide legislative or executive entity with the authority to suspend, remove, or relieve a local election administrator.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7546D57A97034CC4AE7D1344ABFDD554"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to grant any additional authority to remove a local elections administrator beyond any authority provided under the law of the State.</text></subsection></section><section id="H488BC0F367DF4DA9B465F5E62F0D7D85"><enum>3.</enum><header>Protections for voters on Election Day</header><subsection id="H51FC8D06EED74FDEA6E3BFD37A02F9A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle A of title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 303 the following new section: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA628B83A141641ABA4DE9744F86B7C71"><section id="H768436E8D6D14A8CAA78141EEA65A7ED"><enum>303A.</enum><header>Voter protection requirements</header><subsection id="H82496EDD65D742EAA9B4258600A14234"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements for challenges by persons other than election officials</header><paragraph id="H98062B3824BE46B3B77DCBD6629B2BE1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements for challenges</header><text>No person, other than a State or local election official, shall submit a formal challenge to an individual’s eligibility to register to vote in an election for Federal office or to vote in an election for Federal office unless that challenge is supported by personal knowledge with respect to each individual challenged regarding the grounds for ineligibility which is—</text><subparagraph id="H0CEA952A3727429E9D7E6917B7317FE3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>documented in writing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0803D2F768B4490EA79DDB724A10A7EC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subject to an oath or attestation under penalty of perjury that the challenger has a good faith factual basis to believe that the individual who is the subject of the challenge is ineligible to register to vote or vote in that election, except a challenge that is based on the race, color, ethnicity, national origin, or membership in a language minority group (as defined in section 14 of the Voting Rights Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/10310">52 U.S.C. 10310</external-xref>)) of the individual who is the subject of the challenge may not be considered to have a good faith factual basis for purposes of this paragraph. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF879951172C4BA0BE04C8E2ABCF37D6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition on challenges on or near date of election</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No person, other than a State or local election official, shall be permitted—</text><subparagraph id="H7F474453253A404FAB4B8BBC57FB9621"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to challenge an individual’s eligibility to vote in an election for Federal office on the date of the election on grounds that could have been made in advance of such date; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71951AAA53924C72BDE46EBC4D6F5F80"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to challenge an individual’s eligibility to register to vote in an election for Federal office or to vote in an election for Federal office less than 10 days before the election unless the individual registered to vote less than 20 days before the election.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC4597A84DB054D46846A4B8379A17AB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall apply with respect to elections for Federal office occurring on and after January 1, 2024.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA744C078F68D4AC89270C354BDBC3F4D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text>Section 401 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>303, and 303A</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFFABC5837FDD4F158FF93275F5D14A4D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 303 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFFF05D8333DB4089A0C08A40FE318336"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 303A. Voter protection requirements.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

