<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Placed-on-Calendar-Senate" dms-id="H77F179A44378446481A232D3C69DBC6E" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="appropriations" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5692 PCS: Ukraine Security Assistance and Oversight Supplemental Appropriations Act, 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><calendar>Calendar No. 216</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5692</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230930" legis-day="20230922">September 30 (legislative day, September 22), 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received; read the first time</action-desc></action><action><action-date date="20231003">October 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Read the second time and placed on the calendar</action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">Making supplemental appropriations for the fiscal year ending September 30, 2024, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H17F0D3EA2C6540EE8C6E421D9DADDF8F" style="appropriations"><section id="HBD0A59CDC6014DDBB0A1A7719689D25C" section-type="undesignated-section"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">That the following sums are appropriated, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, for the fiscal year ending September 30, 2024, and for other purposes, namely:</text></section><section id="LEXA-Repairid543414da545a438a919f1b60b95ce1dd" section-type="undesignated-section"><appropriations-major id="HC4E919F60417414BA0B72DABB8040811"><header>Department of Defense</header></appropriations-major><appropriations-major id="HC991BDF6D9D54E05BC79EBC69478CA20"><header>Operations and Maintenance</header></appropriations-major><appropriations-intermediate id="H83B9E083802A48A1BE015DF9F11C9583"><header>Operations and Maintenance, Defense-Wide</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HEDD931C2153E49FC8CC7B5BDAEEA859F"><header>(Including Transfer of Funds)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For an additional amount for <quote>Operations and Maintenance, Defense-Wide</quote>, for the Defense Security Cooperation Agency, $300,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025, which shall be for the Ukraine Security Assistance Initiative: <proviso><italic>Provided</italic>, </proviso>That such funds shall be available to the Secretary of Defense, with the concurrence of the Secretary of State, to provide assistance, including training; equipment; lethal assistance; logistics support, supplies and services; salaries and stipends; sustainment; and intelligence support to the military and national security forces of Ukraine, and to other forces or groups recognized by and under the authority of the Government of Ukraine, including governmental entities within Ukraine, engaged in resisting Russian aggression against Ukraine, for replacement of any weapons or articles provided to the Government of Ukraine from the inventory of the United States, and to recover or dispose of equipment procured using funds made available in this section in this or prior Acts: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That the Secretary of Defense shall, not less than 15 days prior to obligating funds made available in this section, notify the congressional defense committees in writing of the details of any such obligation: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That the Secretary of Defense shall, not more than 60 days after such notification is made, inform such committees if such funds have not been obligated and the reasons therefor: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That the Secretary of Defense shall consult with such committees in advance of the provision of support provided to other forces or groups recognized by and under the authority of the Government of Ukraine: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That the United States may accept equipment procured using funds made available in this section in this or prior Acts transferred to the security forces of Ukraine and returned by such forces to the United States: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That equipment procured using funds made available in this section in this or prior Acts, and not yet transferred to the military or national security forces of Ukraine or to other assisted entities, or returned by such forces or other assisted entities to the United States, may be treated as stocks of the Department of Defense upon written notification to the congressional defense committees: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That any notification of funds made available in this section in this or prior Acts shall specify whether such funds support ongoing or new programs, the duration and expected cost over the life of each program, a timeline for the delivery of defense articles and defense services, and any equipment that requires enhanced end-use monitoring: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That the Secretary of Defense shall provide quarterly reports to the congressional defense committees on the use and status of funds made available in this section: <proviso><italic>Provided further</italic>, </proviso>That of the amounts provided under this heading, $20,000,000 shall be transferred to the Office of Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance, as established in section 103 of this Act.</text></appropriations-small><appropriations-major id="HE89F5A8AE0734CC8AC37026CF3E63CDB"><header>General Provisions—This Act</header></appropriations-major></section><section id="HE24A582D333C49D69AE3BBAA5262DBF6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>101.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each amount appropriated or made available by this Act is in addition to amounts otherwise appropriated for the fiscal year involved. </text></section><section id="H8F91A5D2DD48451FB7AAA3EF72614525" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>102.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Unless otherwise provided for by this Act, the additional amounts appropriated by this Act to appropriations accounts shall be available under the authorities and conditions applicable to such appropriations accounts for fiscal year 2024.</text></section><section id="H15EC782EE88F42A0BE9546B676E0139B"><enum>103.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established the Office of the Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance for the following:</text><paragraph id="H84FCE8F541C14B8D80E04F88C8CD2455" indent="up1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To provide for the independent and objective conduct and supervision of audits and investigations, including within the territory of Ukraine, relating to the programs and operations funded with amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF7D2002AB7A4AF1A39B09DA9C623411" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To provide for the independent and objective leadership and coordination of, and recommendations on, policies designed to prevent and detect waste, fraud, and abuse in such programs and operations described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD99A54D60C114AEA8C8D3286BA434B33" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To provide for an independent and objective means of keeping the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Defense, and Congress fully and currently informed about problems and deficiencies relating to the administration of such programs and operations and the necessity for and progress on corrective action.</text></paragraph></section><section section-type="undesignated-section" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B6272B116194FA187540DE69D0E54A9"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ukraine Security Assistance and Oversight Supplemental Appropriations Act, 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230928" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives September 28, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Kevin F. McCumber,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation><endorsement><action-date date="20231003">October 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Read the second time and placed on the calendar</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

