<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Referred-in-Senate" dms-id="HF28A3C327A2047E3BA11576CA9048C79" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 3099 : Special Envoy for the Abraham Accords Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IIB</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3099</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc> Received; read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish in the Department of State the position of Special Envoy for the Abraham Accords, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H60A5D48BC42646A2BAF72D2AB1D31E26" style="OLC"><pagebreak></pagebreak><section id="H3FA478218203410EB71E09F3B1ECC8C9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Special Envoy for the Abraham Accords Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF1745E93D5B441FF9EAE45DF113474F1" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that the policy of the United States, as enacted in section 104 of the Israel Relations Normalization Act of 2022 (division Z of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>), with respect to the Abraham Accords remains unchanged.</text></section><section id="HC15A2568300244FD8E84EF3D80876D4E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Special Envoy for the Abraham Accords</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title I of the State Department Basic Authorities Act of 1956 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2651a">22 U.S.C. 2651a et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="H19CA7BF0230B42F791B29C9788DFB048" style="OLC"><section id="H87451729019D4AE4BA81FC1A202D9D68"><enum>64.</enum><header>Special envoy for the Abraham Accords</header><subsection id="H4C40DC66DC5F4E388771B692E358CBD8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Special envoy for the abraham accords</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established within the Department of State a Special Envoy for the Abraham Accords (in this section referred to as the <quote>Special Envoy</quote>), who shall serve as the primary advisor to, and coordinate efforts across, the United States Government relating to expanding and strengthening the Abraham Accords. The Special Envoy shall report directly to the Secretary of State and shall hold the office at the pleasure of the President.</text></subsection><subsection id="H75C387FF10074AEABB6BD9995C269396"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nomination</header><text>Pursuant to subsection (j)(1) of section 1, the Special Envoy shall be appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, and may be appointed from among the officers and employees of the Department except that such officer or employee may not retain the position (or the responsibilities associated with the position) held by such officer or employee prior to such appointment simultaneously with the position or responsibilities of the Special Envoy.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2075DEECD34B416185A4AED22F7F66D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rank and status of ambassador</header><text>The Special Envoy shall have the rank and status of ambassador.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD514C39288A1486CBD40787DBD79A49F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Special Envoy shall be responsible for—</text><paragraph id="H9FAEDF21A64A4A58AE2F7C4D8532AF4A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>encouraging countries without diplomatic relations with Israel to establish formal diplomatic, economic, security, and people-to-people ties;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE09822015FA41378E1B6373F22C4DA4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>seeking to expand and strengthen existing relationships between Israel and Muslim-majority countries, including those outside the geographic scope of the Near Eastern Affairs Bureau of the Department of State, to ensure that all parties reap tangible security and economic benefits for their citizens;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81B54EBA98F8408A93E6232E6E4314CD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>building on existing efforts, including the Negev Forum, to help foster enhanced cooperation between Israel and Muslim-majority countries on shared priorities including as relates to trade, agriculture, and water security;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B9DDFEB878749268F0A57D6157040F3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>providing diplomatic support for Israel’s integration into cooperative efforts related to regional security; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3609826895E44F27B38D809F010851E1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>coordinating lines of effort across the United States Government, including the regional and functional bureaus within the Department of State, and conducting appropriate diplomatic engagement with foreign governments, nongovernmental organizations, and other stakeholders determined appropriate by the Special Envoy in order to expand and strengthen the Abraham Accords.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10151C729B424FFE83360E2A1BC7A26C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="HC4CFE08B389149A6BE15A8C4FF435CA3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the confirmation of the first Special Envoy appointed pursuant to this section, and annually thereafter, the Special Envoy shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate a report describing all United States efforts to expand the Abraham Accords, including specific diplomatic engagements and status of efforts with respect to specific countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FFD05CF8C424648B22AE81A4B90C077"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form of Report</header><text>The report required by paragraph (1) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may contain a separate, classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230613" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives June 13, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Cheryl L. Johnson,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation></bill> 

