<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBC566E52731C49A3B92737EBA3269D22" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2464 IH: General Thaddeus Kosciuszko Memorial Exchange Program for Polish-American Defense Cooperation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2464</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230403">April 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Commander of United States Army Special Operations Command to seek to carry out a training program with special operations forces of the Polish Army.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H77EB701C8DCD4F9EA810AF9AD1FFC01B" style="OLC"><section id="HC6FF2A446BD345E0A11E65BA8A6B3F33" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>General Thaddeus Kosciuszko Memorial Exchange Program for Polish-American Defense Cooperation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5315F0CE08024537B57F4AEDCF237125"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purposes</header><subsection id="H0CA1A705DFA84922826DA8B2930F3332"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text><paragraph id="H6303F74D33764522B071DCF44AC33D21"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Thaddeus Kosciuszko served the United States and his native Poland with honor and distinction during a vital time in each country’s fight for democracy and freedom from tyranny, so it is fitting to establish in his name a fellowship to build and strengthen cooperation between officials of the United States and Poland.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8091C7BED5B486F8A1612452E17602B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Thaddeus Kosciuszko’s tactical acumen and engineering excellence were vital to the American victory at the battle of Saratoga, the establishment and defense of West Point, and the blockade of Charleston, which helped bring about the end of the Revolutionary War.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFBD76073E834486BCCAEFA3C89070E1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A fierce defender of freedom and equality, Thaddeus Kosciuszko tirelessly advocated for the end of slavery and serfdom in America, Poland, and across the globe, including leading the Polish revolution against the Russian and Prussian armies in the 18th century.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D5ADA57307F4EC9AE024CF91659FE87"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Poland is a vital ally to the United States in Europe, and the enhancement of strategic and military cooperation is of utmost importance to successful foreign policy implementation and maintaining peace and stability for the United States and its European partners.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE841861EDCC44DDA841369CDC3C46986"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Polish and American special forces possess significant expertise in the execution of all types of counterterrorism, covert operations, and unconventional warfare, from decades of training and cooperation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA71F9BBF1E104ACDB40D54CF11A3ED4F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="HC21D06FA0A3147FA9DA9A416EE0EDBC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to enhance the national security and defensive capabilities of the United States and Poland and enable both countries to effectively respond to emerging threats and future challenges in Eastern Europe and around the globe;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE319FD5DFC634DAC8033EC22806B0252"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to provide a program for the exchange of special forces soldiers that will increase capability and readiness levels for both countries through increased cooperation and training; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB17FFA3AFDF449848D872D2893FF5ADD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to encourage, through increased cooperation, more NATO allies to emphasize the ideals of peace and stability, ensured through mutual cooperation and readiness of allied defense forces.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8835D5217F0A4672B5A36E38B1F5C66D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>General Thaddeus Kosciuszko Exchange Program</header><subsection id="H488C701ACBCC4041B9FDA34A8A53859C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commander of United States Army Special Operations Command shall seek to carry out a training program pursuant to section 322 of title 10, United States Code, between special operations forces under the jurisdiction of the Commander and special forces of the Polish Army. Such program shall be known as the <quote>General Thaddeus Kosciuszko Memorial Exchange Program for Polish-American Defense Cooperation</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0E7EA5230AAC43BDBE2E776A77E568B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Officers and enlisted members of such special operations forces may participate in the program under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2504198A2BD34741A24683929F29926C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Progress report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commander shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives a report regarding progress of the Commander in carrying out the program under this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

