<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H10D2270A69184D5D9FF3B9BFFA0164C8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4512 IH: Digital Economy Cybersecurity Advisory Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4512</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230710">July 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act to establish a Digital Economy and Cybersecurity Board of Advisors, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE43646D318574608B6D96CB0FFBC3DE9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H731B962B6AB54D7E831E60F168257964" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Digital Economy Cybersecurity Advisory Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5F10704756B44AAA816C8146C9EFBA25" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Digital Economy and Cybersecurity Board of Advisors</header> <text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/901">47 U.S.C. 901 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H57C032D0F62C437B8480BFD062B8807A" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HB80CA766EB6E45F49B407EF09D576F6F"><enum>106.</enum><header>Digital Economy and Cybersecurity Board of Advisors</header> 
<subsection id="H4876DEEA90644ED9A7C84E3698172164"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established within the NTIA a Digital Economy and Cybersecurity Board of Advisors (in this section referred to as the <quote>Board</quote>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBF7017F90F8548D5B7B408E492A78120" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Board shall provide to the Assistant Secretary recommendations (for implementation by the Assistant Secretary or that the Assistant Secretary could recommend for implementation by other appropriate entities) with respect to the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HDCF98E9D36BC45BC86946E9BECDE3251" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Technical cybersecurity best practices regarding how to drive economic growth while securing information and communications networks, including how to secure the Border Gateway Protocol used by Federal and non-Federal entities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA23722A6019D49EFADED2FCFBA42831E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Cybersecurity policies to support the development and implementation of cybersecurity practices with respect to the internet and information and communications networks.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H13D1AC11429E4B1BA02BBB1C7D31A97A" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Policies that promote the security and resilience to cybersecurity incidents of information and communications networks while fostering innovation, including policies that promote secure supply chains for information and communications networks.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF1955FF880DB47DEB4DC7EE1C6ACD9D0" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Policies to remove barriers to trust, security, innovation, and commercialization with respect to information and communications networks.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE3082CD6E2DA4862B0670DF1C74D241D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Members</header> 
<paragraph id="H61F70DD86604448483D802B0B2F81319"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Composition</header> 
<subparagraph id="HC94D9688F2C948B2A5F7E3D13BCE943A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Board shall be composed of not fewer than 5, and not more than 25, members appointed by the Assistant Secretary.</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9A9C46E8D4C46B4B1A314E3C6DCB610"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Expertise</header><text>Each member of the Board shall have cybersecurity or supply chain security technical expertise, cybersecurity or supply chain security policy expertise, or expertise in running the cybersecurity or supply chain security functions of a business.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2337269F123B4554AEF8129971B7B741" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Representation</header><text>In appointing members of the Board under subparagraph (A), the Assistant Secretary shall ensure that the members appointed provide a balanced representation of the following:</text> <clause id="HF1E59D5332BE4E6E93C4078DDFEDD759"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Chief cybersecurity officers or other qualified individuals employed in cybersecurity positions, representing both the public and private sectors.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H27CAB57F86E34A6FB80B2EA754EAE1A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Persons who operate or maintain information and communications networks.</text></clause> <clause id="H8DFC0E1BDADC47599B4C3B71272C92FE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Vendors that produce or provide equipment used in information and communications networks.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDA47A011AD064D9DB3385B503BA70563"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Vendors that produce or provide software used in information and communications networks.</text></clause> <clause id="H789909A7AA294886B95916B9EB6A2417"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Persons who operate or maintain internet applications.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H97CD0F0C5CCE46AAAD0B36ABCE20517F" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An individual who is a registered lobbyist under the Lobbying Disclosure Act of 1995 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/1601">2 U.S.C. 1601 et seq.</external-xref>) may not serve as a member of the Board.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDEE20600827247198D82B67F466209E0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Terms</header> <subparagraph id="H1F5D5132A0C84D5C9574F5B41D4F33FF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraphs (C) and (D), each member of the Board shall be appointed for a term of a length not to exceed 2 years, to be determined by the Assistant Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5821E792B3D94F54938D20A0E42FAFED"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reappointment</header><text>A member of the Board, including a member appointed to fill a vacancy as provided in subparagraph (D), may be reappointed for 1 or more additional terms by the Assistant Secretary.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H72D353D94F8E4EBEB7F58619C2067AA8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Removal</header><text>The Assistant Secretary may remove a member of the Board at the discretion of the Assistant Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H80676D73FD0E4459A29059E0BD2DAC93"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Vacancy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any member of the Board appointed to fill a vacancy occurring before the expiration of the term for which the predecessor of the member was appointed shall be appointed only for the remainder of such term. A vacancy in the Board shall be filled in the manner in which the original appointment was made.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E5CBED1DB3C45C99A44544A3BA6B749"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The Chair of the Board shall be the Associate Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration for Policy Analysis and Development.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H94AB7B52F57D4B7C9EE6E2444A8F9EBB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>The members of the Board shall serve without compensation.</text></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="H3B064DBBBEE34EECB393F32A964DD991"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Subcommittees</header> <paragraph id="H6110784615FE4247849A7E49A67B3998"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the approval of the Assistant Secretary, as the Assistant Secretary determines necessary for the performance by the Board of the duties described in subsection (b), the Board may establish subcommittees, working groups, standing committees, ad hoc groups, task groups, or other subgroups of the Board.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H634A2810775046E3B85F27039604E8F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any subcommittee, working group, standing committee, ad hoc group, task group, or other subgroup of the Board established under paragraph (1) shall report to the Board and may not provide any advice, recommendation, or other work product directly to the Assistant Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H52988BB4F05040DAAB331B5D7FD3C53E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 1013 of title 5, United States Code, the Board shall terminate on the date that is 4 years after the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDB157C11A5BD4389A272F75FA83E7587"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H6EAC215E1EF3467D889384EE226D8BF4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Border Gateway Protocol</header><text>The term <quote>Border Gateway Protocol</quote> means the routing protocol used to exchange network layer reachability information among independently managed networks on the internet.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5244DF9D9500474F9CA2FEAB2299BAC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information and communications network</header><text>The term <quote>information and communications network</quote> means a network that provides advanced telecommunications capability (as defined in section 706(d) of the Telecommunications Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1302">47 U.S.C. 1302(d)</external-xref>)). </text> </paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </section> </legis-body></bill>

