<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3E7038F4E57A4BD4A146A49CBD3DCBD5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 347 IH: Reduce Exacerbated Inflation Negatively Impacting the Nation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 347</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230112">January 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001156">Mr. McHenry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001195">Mr. Smith of Missouri</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001108">Mr. Comer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Executive Office of the President to provide an inflation estimate with respect to Executive orders with a significant effect on the annual gross budget, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC8BF0BC84D8E4032AC1C12CA20E1941D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H968A43B26D804A54BE3742E2C6872771" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reduce Exacerbated Inflation Negatively Impacting the Nation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7BA9B79643254F1F91B48788CE5A502B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Executive order mandated inflation accountability and reform</header> <subsection id="HB2B4B865EE5E4188804E152D5A21C949"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mandatory inflation forecasting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For any major Executive order, the President, acting through the Director of the Office of Management and Budget and the Chair of the Council of Economic Advisers, shall prepare and consider a statement estimating the inflationary effects of the Executive order, including whether the Executive order is determined to have no significant impact on inflation, is determined to have quantifiable inflationary impact on the consumer price index, or is determined likely to have a significant impact on inflation but the amount cannot be determined at the time the estimate is prepared.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H203B6B04B0944DC7B6C6BC1890D55293"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Agency assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of each agency shall provide to the President, acting through the Director and the Chair, such information and assistance as the President, acting through the Director and the Chair, may reasonably request to assist the President, acting through the Director and the Chair, in carrying out this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H168466818FEF47478A309D0F8081C293"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every year thereafter, the President, acting through the Director and the Chair, shall submit to the Committees on the Budget of the Senate and House of Representatives a report containing each statement prepared and considered under subsection (a) during the year.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H4A880C0339B846AEB22EDD84D0286725"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HB67F7F118B524200B619F2AB87F922AC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H95F1A659051E4945BF310D8C0C04EFA5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Major Executive order</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>major Executive order</term> means any Executive order that would be projected (in a conventional cost estimate) to cause an annual gross budgetary effect of at least $1,000,000,000, but does not include any such measure that—</text> <subparagraph id="H3F8C956ADF5A4A71A3E6E68FC3CC4DAD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides for emergency assistance or relief at the request of any State or local government or any official of a State or local government; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H683CD5007DDC4ACCA1E285AF9D77FE1B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is necessary for the national security or the ratification or implementation of international treaty obligations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2E71137663624CE3B91BA72599AA1EE3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, each commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

