<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8EE7C72C43B54416BBF5BBC15F6022D6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1337 IH: Immigration Enforcement Partnership Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1337</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize States to request that the Secretary of Homeland Security enforce the Immigration and Nationality Act, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6B9BC181CE8C4509ABC7CBC09A27B352" style="OLC"><section id="H814A7CC478094BD392CBCDC50CE8B0D8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Immigration Enforcement Partnership Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H531857A6509F4F719D3D52A10FDC9302"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorizing States to request the enforcement of the immigration laws</header><subsection id="HE189D7B7FE34444C9CDBE309E92447FA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Request To fulfill duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a State attorney general finds that the Secretary of Homeland Security is not adequately fulfilling his non-discretionary duties under title II of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1151">8 U.S.C. 1151 et seq.</external-xref>), such as the arrest, detention, and removal of criminal aliens and arriving aliens, such officer may request in writing that the Secretary do so. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4CA3A466C7064399ADD0D3822AAA27F0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement To fulfill duties</header><text>Not later than 30 days after receiving a request under subsection (a), the Secretary shall either—</text><paragraph id="H810DFC3DA7524139BB7FED7699DCE294"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure that any such duties are adequately fulfilled by officers and employees of the Department of Homeland Security; or </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06D0A40D11B84201B7E4A2FE88D7932E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">exercise his authority under section 287(g) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1357">8 U.S.C. 1357</external-xref>) to authorize officials in the State to perform functions of an immigration officer related to the investigation, apprehension, or detention of aliens in that State, and fulfill such duties on behalf of the Secretary. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7F71B166B9B440B081E099F3B732C6AC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Civil action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary does not comply with subsection (b), the State attorney general may file a civil action in an appropriate district court of the United States to enforce the requirements under such subsection. The court shall advance on the docket and expedite the disposition of a civil action filed under this subsection to the greatest extent practicable. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

