<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H91B2DFABFFF14AABB28EED1225D14347" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3964 IH: Rural Broadband Modernization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3964</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To increase access to broadband telecommunications services in rural areas, to increase minimum broadband speeds in rural areas, and to provide grants, loans, and loan guarantees to finance the costs of the construction, improvement, and acquisition of facilities and equipment for broadband service in rural areas, and other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HBA8A7568F4FF415A92CE49D2EA3877F2" style="OLC">
<section id="H303F305B69E8403587D165CDCC00A584" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Broadband Modernization Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HACEE602C87B24C778C213BB8C52F6238"><enum>2.</enum><header>Rural broadband modernization</header> <subsection id="HEED0030137354709B822066F20B39422"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 601 of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB3D9115B8A75468D9076D5D0DF7E50BB" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="H11924C2E931A437A880F0268AA38045B"><enum>601.</enum><header>Access to broadband telecommunications services in rural areas</header>
<subsection id="HAB68C5D569A642A98046F58E002676D3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this section is to provide grants, provide loans, and provide loan guarantees to provide funds for the costs of the construction, improvement, and acquisition of facilities and equipment for broadband service in rural areas.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2F7634A5D9D143418BAF87DB7993E6CF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H21A50400B3F54F9C9748DCCE2999C16C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Broadband service</header><text>The term <term>broadband service</term> means any technology identified by the Secretary as having the capacity to transmit data to enable a subscriber to the service to originate and receive high-quality voice, data, graphics, and video.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9A6C03C270A14DEE9D9EB6BC840D56E1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rural area</header> <subparagraph id="H4DDAD0BC97734906ABADEE3357A4D7B7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>rural area</term> means any area other than—</text>
<clause id="H2FCAF69565784EED9F7793D358D90385"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an area described in clause (i) or (ii) of section 343(a)(13)(A) of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1991">7 U.S.C. 1991(a)(13)(A)</external-xref>); and</text></clause> <clause id="H8FC559CB373848B3BCEF5D031A36F832"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a grant or direct loan, a city, town, or incorporated area that has a population of greater than 20,000 inhabitants.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4B999E81B89B4BD58546176E7BE19FF5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Urban area growth</header><text>The Secretary may, by regulation only, consider an area described in section 343(a)(13)(F)(i)(I) of such Act to not be a rural area for purposes of this section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9F3EEE74DFC5492593A68C4274A2384A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exclusion of certain populations</header><text>The term does not include any population described in subparagraph (H) or (I) of section 343(a)(13) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1991">7 U.S.C. 1991(a)(13)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEED05FFE4B6C4D90AF102DE649E491DA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants, loans, and loan guarantees</header>
<paragraph id="HB53377AD7452479C900086D842D1D705"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall make grants, shall make loans, and shall guarantee loans to eligible entities described in subsection (d) to provide funds for the construction, improvement, or acquisition of facilities and equipment for the provision of broadband service in rural areas that, at a minimum, delivers 100 Mbps (or such greater rate as the Secretary may establish) symmetrical throughput for each rural household in the proposed service area.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H407128F870C14F64B2D04939DBABC44D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an application process for grants under this section that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4BFEFF63059D4F69878489F19D2A55CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>permits a single application for a grant and a loan under title I, II, or this title that is associated with the grant;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H75F270FE1AE448BC84D2B974FA85ACF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provides a single decision to award such a grant and loan; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF2DAC2CE6E0D48F692D1D35B1706E75F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensures timely consideration of applications by approving or denying applications within 30 days after submission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0CF3B44581E5412288AFDD23B7B6ADBD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority</header> <subparagraph id="H576197C2F13944F39BDA48B961483B83"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In making grants, making loans, and guaranteeing loans under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text>
<clause id="HB5889077D6524C96AD8171381AAAD438"><enum>(i)</enum><text>give the highest priority to applications for projects to provide broadband service to unserved rural communities that do not have any residential broadband service of at least—</text> <subclause id="H69F1913856BE4A459B2C2204D7B1B143"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a 25-Mbps downstream transmission capacity; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HED6558A08BC840D2B94D16A91DE553AF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a 3-Mbps upstream transmission capacity;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HCB5C4541425D47D3BFED7D042BF4FD4A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>give priority to applications for projects to provide the maximum level of broadband service to the greatest proportion of rural households in the proposed service area identified in the application;</text></clause>
<clause id="HBCF6C4C5C2754EA48270CC58EE4426CD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>give priority to eligible entities that have provided broadband service or utility service in rural areas for at least 5 years in the State for which an award is sought;</text></clause> <clause id="H72427F59921D4F6E917548AC82146285"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>provide equal consideration to all eligible entities, based on organizational form; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB4593BBE469C41B4AD2F3D7C601BF8A7"><enum>(v)</enum><text>with respect to 2 or more applications that are given the same priority under clause (i), give priority to an application that requests less grant funding than loan funding.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4C907F87DD4F47FBA9D4CFAAC2D4BED7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other</header><text>After giving priority to the applications described in clauses (i) through (iii) of subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall give priority to applications—</text>
<clause id="HEA94540FB35E4C80A6A750FF1D421D61"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for projects to provide broadband service to rural communities—</text> <subclause id="H59FB3EC802284ED7A774BE73EFCF563B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>with a population of less than 10,000 permanent residents;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H22AD06DD33DC46AC87C6ED3DF8733661"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that are experiencing outmigration and have adopted a strategic community investment plan under section 379H(d) of the Consoldiated Farm and Rural Development Act that includes considerations for improving and expanding broadband service;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4AFA53DACEB84EFA95A4C42F572A8ACD"><enum>(III)</enum><text>with a high percentage of low income families or persons (as defined in section 501(b) of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1471">42 U.S.C. 1471(b)</external-xref>));</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HAFC2DF96F5044C4E875326B7861FCAD8"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>that are isolated from other significant population centers; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H271D1FA628D94129B42C2011BBDFC7A6"><enum>(V)</enum><text>that provide rapid and expanded deployment of fixed and mobile broadband on cropland and ranchland within a service territory for use in various applications of precision agriculture; and</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H47D20B01365B4D049C82768E08E1C2EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that were developed with the participation of, and will receive a substantial portion of the funding for the project from, 2 or more stakeholders, including—</text> <subclause id="H0F9D03A029EC4F40A08C11E62F22DE59"><enum>(I)</enum><text>State, local, and tribal governments;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H4A60104DC3364548A92419D3B4802B2A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>nonprofit institutions; that provide community development or assistance services;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H462CEEBAD30C445993F096DCC4E5E681"><enum>(III)</enum><text>community anchor institutions, such as—</text>
<item id="HCEE030E17C2E4AECA7F7B26253B93111"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>public libraries;</text></item> <item id="H46546F7F3F1E45A9941663132B2A6E5D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>elementary schools and secondary schools (as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>));</text></item>
<item id="H5F4AE1486B8E4728BD36E93362B14CA7"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>institutions of higher education; and</text></item> <item id="H41461EFB8D614A81B13A5E26F90627D0"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>health care facilities;</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="H67A6995F2F834D4095DCE8D639B72EFF"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>private entities; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HEE564CFA476B43B0AFA4D0BE7C0CF558"><enum>(V)</enum><text>philanthropic organizations.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H447BA1B6AC6A4506A284EFAD8D2339BF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Grant amounts</header>
<subparagraph id="H828D0FB111DB4538B0A11AED5E2C0EC9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Maximum</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the amount of any grant made under this section shall not exceed 75 percent of the total project cost.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7CDE3CB6A95841B7BB0BBDD4847FEEC3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Secretarial authority to adjust</header> <clause id="H27296B74B0A64F55862A5E534D665E70"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may make grants of 100 percent of the development costs of the project for which the grant is provided to an eligible entity if the Secretary determines that the project serves an area of rural households where the population density is fewer than 7 households per square mile.</text></clause>
<clause id="HB205A3715C1F4A38A2EDBF6E9ACE4495"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Definition of development costs</header><text>In this paragraph, the term <term>development costs</term> means costs of—</text> <subclause id="HA2A6AB49D4B54E0BB0C5E4919FA9D236"><enum>(I)</enum><text>construction, including labor and materials;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H794D99568FFD45FB8F93F66D1C0D71D8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>project applications; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HD6206BA2A4104A18B4F8F334E370622A"><enum>(III)</enum><text>other development activities, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HB2BDB7B37A104DAA95A01FA419F9D593"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Density determinations</header><text>In determining population density under this section, the Secretary shall prescribe a calculation method which—</text> <subclause id="H49C8575400D94201985FC99EDDCEBFB7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>utilizes publicly available data; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H8024012DAACB4ACD9147C1324C2C7787"><enum>(II)</enum><text>includes only those areas in which the applicant is able to meet the service requirements under this section, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H019BC12256E64D1296A32042F9927A13"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Fees</header><text>In the case of loan guarantees issued or modified under this section, the Secretary shall charge and collect from the lender fees in such amounts as to reduce the costs of subsidies for guaranteed loans, except that the amount of the fees shall be determined so as to not act as a bar to participation in the programs and to not be inconsistent with current practices in the marketplace.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5B78EB53C1934EA0A9F1E94FBE02A3EE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligibility</header>
<paragraph id="HF1F2D45C97DD4DE09AD73F591B180B59"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header>
<subparagraph id="HA18D33C24398407A8E372FF4B5395672"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible to obtain a grant, loan, or loan guarantee under this section, an entity shall—</text> <clause id="H38072AD573E44DEE99167D197337CFA1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>demonstrate the ability to furnish or improve service in order to meet the broadband buildout requirements established under subsection (e)(3) in all or part of an unserved rural area;</text></clause>
<clause id="H0FAAD983B21B4010BBA684855051F63A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require; and</text></clause> <clause id="HE92AFF2FD4914DDCBA5F5658DE2C9460"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>agree to complete buildout of the broadband infrastructure described in the application by not later than 5 years after the initial date on which the application is approved and the initial funds pursuant to that award are received by the applicant.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H83649DB48B4F48A4B2729CF6390D33CD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Secretary may not provide to an eligible entity that provides telecommunications or broadband service to at least 20 percent of the households in the United States, funds under this section for a fiscal year in excess of 15 percent of the funds made available under subsection (j) for the fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF8E8560F791245FCBC2771A015C3CFA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header> <subparagraph id="H681215DCC29049E69695019973E702A8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Grant</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under this section, a project shall—</text>
<clause id="H8AB90AA4E3144CB38B0EA786166A8563"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be carried out in a proposed service territory in which not less than 90 percent of the households are unserved by terrestrial wireline or licensed wireless broadband service speeds of at least 100 Mbps downstream transmission capacity and 20 Mbps upstream transmission capacity, or such higher speed thresholds as the Secretary may determine constitute an unserved rural area pursuant to subsection (e)(2); and</text></clause> <clause id="H1EA77A71534A4E349876D4CA66383F2F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>not concurrently receive any other broadband grant administered by the Rural Utilities Service, the Department of the Treasury, the National Telecommunications and Information Administration, or a State grant program.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1B8C6CD3E97C4A4CAD30F560C72FE904"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Loan or loan guarantee</header><text>A borrower may use a loan or loan guarantee provided under this section to carry out a project in a proposed service territory only if, as of the date on which the application for the loan or loan guarantee is submitted, not less than 50 percent of the locations in the proposed service territory are unserved or have service levels below the minimum acceptable level of fixed terrestrial broadband service, whether wireline or licensed wireless, established under subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H614F8BCBEDA242ADB8C8C1AA587BE8F3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Equity and market survey requirements</header> <subparagraph id="H93EA04B64B334230B523DD245B6097DC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may require an entity to provide matching funds under this section in an amount not to exceed 10 percent of the amount of the grant, loan, or loan guarantee requested in the application of the entity, unless the Secretary determines that a higher percentage is required for financial feasibility.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE786B0B5B9214A30883E916038AB6EF8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Market survey</header>
<clause id="HC7B5E80FFFC14D00B0351B0EC0F8B8D8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may require an entity that proposes to have a subscriber projection of more than 20 percent of the broadband service market in a rural area to submit to the Secretary a market survey.</text></clause> <clause id="HACC50E4502AA4BAE9444509AB09CE6A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Less than <enum-in-header>20</enum-in-header> percent</header><text>The Secretary may not require an entity that proposes to have a subscriber projection of less than 20 percent of the broadband service market in a rural area to submit a market survey under clause (i).</text></clause>
<clause id="HC7B0CE854CBD4E7CAB251283E875C2E9"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Information</header><text>Information submitted under this subparagraph shall be—</text> <subclause id="HBDAB62B6F2DF4C60A9BB6BED0799F3C0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>certified by the affected community, city, county, or designee; or</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H670DE547D9F34FE6823C1A5DEBA9A9BF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>demonstrated on—</text> <item id="HA0356B7097B943C2A8547C9E69E5F6A7"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the broadband map of the affected State if the map contains address-level data; or</text></item>
<item id="HDD68D97F363A4551829E0322AC4855EE"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the National Broadband Map if address-level data is unavailable.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB7236239B944EB7B09F219AE7781F0C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State and local governments and indian tribes</header><text>Subject to paragraph (1), a State or local government (including any agency, subdivision, or instrumentality thereof (including consortia thereof)) and an Indian tribe shall be eligible for assistance under this section to provide broadband services to a rural area.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H456472CEE16E4296A66D5C4B7717D570"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Technical assistance and training</header>
<subparagraph id="HBD6F72AD6A444E3E875744FDB3318FA4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may provide to any eligible entity described in paragraph (1) of this subsection that is applying for assistance under this section for a project described in subsection (c)(3)(A)(i) technical assistance and training—</text> <clause id="HE9857F4DC1214E7CBF3483D996E116C8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to prepare reports and surveys necessary to request grants, loans, and loan guarantees under this section for broadband deployment;</text></clause>
<clause id="H020F369DC46644E0B25DC687DE0457C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to improve management, including financial management, relating to the proposed broadband deployment;</text></clause> <clause id="H253C2ADEC4FE4840AC35D7561957E9C9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to prepare applications for grants, loans, and loan guarantees under this section; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H5DB408C6C75A41049E82A0E648ECEF06"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>to assist with other areas of need identified by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H517DC76AEEDE4509A57BAE350FFBAC76"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Not less than 3 percent and not more than 5 percent of the amounts appropriated to carry out this section for a fiscal year shall be used for technical assistance and training under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H504EE4E6E880418AA5A836117DDA4814"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Broadband service</header>
<paragraph id="HAB63C28C602C47DA8AC9D9D556E1E2F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), for purposes of this section, the minimum acceptable level of broadband service for a rural area to be deemed served for purposes of this section shall be via terrestrial wireline or licensed wireless networks with at least—</text> <subparagraph id="HEACCCE2C51854A13871FED6B326EDEEE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a 100-Mbps downstream transmission capacity; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H43D1CAD152F44672B3B3F8509ABABC20"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a 20-Mbps upstream transmission capacity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE7D599A415E54A10B0638E20A2CCAF9B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Adjustments</header><text>At least once every 2 years and more frequently as the Secretary deems necessary and appropriate, the Secretary shall review, and may adjust through notice published in the Federal Register—</text>
<subparagraph id="H4523073E40C24ADC9C473E9DF33C1A47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the minimum acceptable level of broadband service established under paragraph (1) for an area to be deemed unserved and thus eligible for an award under this section; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC251A60B3AB943649CEBBC75BF4DBBB1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the broadband buildout requirements under paragraph (3), to ensure that high quality, cost-effective broadband service is provided to rural areas.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H44897E77FAFD41B6A6BD1F2D02625604"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Broadband buildout requirements</header>
<subparagraph id="HBA499BA327554D5C976C1D66A8E50C0A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>broadband buildout requirement</term> means the level of broadband service an applicant receiving assistance under this section must agree, at the time the application is finalized, to provide for the duration of any project-related agreement between the applicant and the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7663C87214BF47A88E664BDC89BCD50A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The broadband buildout requirement shall, at a minimum, deliver 100 Mbps symmetrical throughout for each rural household in the proposed service area. The Secretary may increase this minimum requirement for the performance broadband service in considering new applications.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H99CD62F6F1FD4D699B5196B0FC18B032"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Substitute service standards for unique service territories</header><text>If an applicant shows that it would be cost prohibitive to meet the broadband buildout requirements established under this paragraph for the entirety of a proposed service territory due to the unique characteristics of the proposed service territory, the Secretary and the applicant may agree to utilize substitute standards for any unserved portion of the project that should continue to consider the best technology available to meet the needs of the residents in the unserved area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD2A91987C67644999C7EC9034A9345A4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Technological neutrality</header><text>For purposes of determining whether to provide assistance for a project under this section, the Secretary shall use criteria that are technologically neutral and criteria that ensures the technology can meet program broadband buildout requirements and the evolving needs of rural households and businesses, including precision agriculture.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HE94E783D961148F4BA08443E721D9D96"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Terms and conditions for loans and loan guarantees</header>
<paragraph id="H8CC3986436874800B4617D999E4B11A2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a loan or loan guarantee under this section shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H5233F903E47E4930A4FDF56A05950DE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>bear interest at an annual rate of, as determined by the Secretary—</text>
<clause id="HB55CAC54C196481EA445FE35F24E1900"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a direct loan, a rate equivalent to—</text> <subclause id="H787B9184627846B7BDFD612C629AB8A6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the cost of borrowing to the Department of the Treasury for obligations of comparable maturity; or</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HA1A71672AF2B4BE2AA924836EDFDCDF9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>4 percent; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H871B0E6AC0BC4C1DB07D47125DCD0096"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a guaranteed loan, the current applicable market rate for a loan of comparable maturity; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H19693A2E36E54E488C97D2B275D7AC02"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have a term of such length, not exceeding 35 years, as the borrower may request, if the Secretary determines that the loan is adequately secured.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41B4B465CE514AAA9AA0C9B3EE6FA85F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recurring revenue</header><text>The Secretary shall consider the recurring revenues of the entity at the time of application in determining an adequate level of credit support.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H0D3538EE474849BD8F464273CCAD3113"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Adequacy of security</header>
<paragraph id="HC7DD88A5F3564C78833A78E948DE465D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that the type and amount of, and method of security used to secure, any loan or loan guarantee under this section is commensurate to the risk involved with the loan or loan guarantee, particularly in any case in which the loan or loan guarantee is issued to a financially strong and stable entity, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF78A6A9ED0434EE2901318095A2B2789"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination of amount and method of security</header><text>In determining the amount of, and method of security used to secure, a loan or loan guarantee under this section, the Secretary shall consider reducing the security in a rural area that does not have broadband service.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA2F1B70EAE104C4BAEC1FE43F164DC20"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Payment assistance for certain loan and grant recipients</header>
<paragraph id="HF345127629B443A4B5543F72F0C85C75"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header><text>The Secretary may use the funds appropriated for a grant under this title for the cost (as defined by section 502 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974) of providing assistance under paragraph (2) of this subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD500BEB97ACA463F8E2190F23A11E8DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Payment assistance</header><text>When providing a grant under this title, the Secretary, at the sole discretion of the Secretary, may make—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9C4CB6F4E0A441FC8EAE7501F8FFD6B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a subsidized loan, which shall bear a reduced interest rate at such a rate as the Secretary determines appropriate to meet the objectives of the program; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F405C2A115444C897C1B10963692E6F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a payment assistance loan, which shall—</text>
<clause id="H37459901DE154F029CE60E93CBD2B2A3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>require no interest and principal payments while the borrower is—</text> <subclause id="H4902EB939B0C48E9B63F12001084D418"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in material compliance with the loan agreement; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HB8446C9BA529475F9836720A4ADBB495"><enum>(II)</enum><text>meeting the milestones and objectives of the project agreed to under paragraph (3); and</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HC16AF079936540A1AA4AD7139BC87AA5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require such nominal periodic payments as the Secretary determines to be appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCEEB425CE8794821BF7649EC2223A170"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Agreement on milestones and objectives</header><text>With respect to payment assistance provided under paragraph (2), before entering into the agreement under which the payment assistance will be provided, the applicant and the Secretary shall agree to milestones and objectives of the project.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6113AC3F1DD3477DA65730F50E001D7C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Amendment of milestones and objectives</header><text>The Secretary and the applicant may jointly agree to amend the milestones and objectives agreed to under paragraph (3).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCE3C28D1B169433799F13839D1C460A0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In deciding to utilize the payment assistance authority under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall consider whether or not the payment assistance will—</text> <subparagraph id="H425C40558E2642B3895D57B3B55596C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improve the compliance of the grantee with any commitments made through the grant agreement;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFB9DF7E652854264997AD71CF37386C5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promote the completion of the broadband project;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF3A3A85FA6EC4122A04782EC46FCA1DC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>protect taxpayer resources; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8A955CB2A7AE4E919FA9F27A5A1DD97B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>support the integrity of the broadband programs administered by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H48046C4ABD6543C4A7171C9CBA1F3B71"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Limitations on payment assistance</header><text>The Secretary may not make a payment assistance loan under paragraph (2)(B) to an entity receiving a grant under this section that is a recipient of a loan under title I or II that is associated with the grant.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEC268952EB97483E8943F52A5AD9875C"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Funding</header>
<paragraph id="H2DA19C133D4B4AF785B47E546C086FED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Limitations on authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section not more than $500,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028, to remain available until expended.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H37207317FF6846A4BE2F4992960C9EA5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Allocation of funds</header> <subparagraph id="H7428EF36289F4C0BBEEF00B4AAA2943B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From amounts made available for each fiscal year under this subsection, the Secretary shall—</text>
<clause id="H1486CB7DAEE24103BEEF5F019B174F93"><enum>(i)</enum><text>establish a national reserve for loans and loan guarantees to eligible entities in States under this section; and</text></clause> <clause id="H6C854319E7EA4C8E9DC33517B9DE6363"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allocate amounts in the reserve to each State for each fiscal year for loans and loan guarantees to eligible entities in the State.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9FBA25D5C6844F948800F02024E5EBA9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The amount of an allocation made to a State for a fiscal year under subparagraph (A) shall bear the same ratio to the amount of allocations made for all States for the fiscal year as—</text> <clause id="H1A05FEA3105B4172A2F746A0D60F587F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of communities with a population of 2,500 or fewer inhabitants in the State; bears to</text></clause>
<clause id="H44C46E464392472E8B39950AE21681D4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of communities with a population of 2,500 or fewer inhabitants in all States.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F54C98D90344002A461FE0745348906"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Unobligated amounts</header><text>Any amounts in the reserve established for a State for a fiscal year under subparagraph (B) that are not obligated by April 1 of the fiscal year shall be available to the Secretary to make loans and loan guarantees under this section to eligible entities in any State, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H50711CB5D8E54D05A0AB2EAFB7FE7C79"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Termination of authority</header><text>No grant, or loan, or loan guarantee may be made under this section after September 30, 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H9BE46D6E11A4473C8DDE7D0F30FBC570"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect on October 1, 2023.</text></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


