<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5072F0AF9B66467BBA8F02EC2A68A0B8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 236 IH: To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to designate a week as “Battle Buddy Check Week” for the purpose of outreach and education concerning peer wellness checks for veterans, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 236</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230110">January 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to designate a week as <quote>Battle Buddy Check Week</quote> for the purpose of outreach and education concerning peer wellness checks for veterans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H241C4E8723FB48DB969E4A1445007870" style="OLC"><section id="HA7E22626891B4C27A9904CE413AEBCAC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Findings; sense of Congress</header><subsection id="HE5DF5AC3911F480F8363125AB5BA3CF9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="H2A8AEE451644421C89AA41A0752E75EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Veterans Affairs is the Federal agency charged with managing benefits and health care for the Nation’s veterans. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF574A931CBD54FB5A80E2E1686B58399"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In recent years, the Department of Veterans Affairs made the prevention of veteran suicide among the highest priorities of the Department and has developed data models to continually improve and tailor suicide prevention strategies and initiatives. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09B0C78A44464909AF08BB139BB866FE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Among the recent suicide prevention initiatives are—</text><subparagraph id="HDA0A06045A2B4F54B08C16251E7D612D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an expanded Veterans Crisis Line to three call centers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25035A49AF354EDFA4A5BC6612A9DAE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>launching the S.A.V.E. suicide prevention training video;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37A932368AB344988C768E4630BD1F6E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>implementing the Mayor’s Challenge, which engages local elected officials in veteran suicide prevention; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD40B8AD02B9B47FFBF50690CDE279F59"><enum>(D)</enum><text>partnering with the Department of Defense and the Department of Homeland Security to support veterans during their transition from military to civilian life.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8DC043D8897348BEA848BEF6F14F60AE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the Department of Veterans Affairs should—</text><paragraph id="H100B6FD2FCF941DFAD76DCD9A7C93E69"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">remain focused on screening transitioning members of the Armed Forces for factors associated with suicide and providing treatment and other services needed to reduce suicides;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H73E28D230CF34E18B7DF1AB431365BCE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>undertake suicide prevention through a multi-pronged strategy that addresses the many factors that are known to contribute to suicide;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9475E4F0DBE24F628CD4ACB659D4E0BD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>continue to regard suicide prevention as one of the highest priorities of the Department; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCB923235DBB4C70956AD86010137B7E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide guidance to other agencies and veteran service organizations on the factors that are associated with suicide.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H686FA618E277446BA90611D53EE3E60F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Designation of Battle Buddy Check Week by Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="H80C4FBCA99794B10808808F3693A7B87"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall designate one week per year to organize outreach events and educate veterans on how to conduct peer wellness checks, which shall be known as <quote>Battle Buddy Check Week</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H36D643044E7048D18E2EB7029CEF062F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Events and education</header><paragraph id="HF22EE1F36CA046BC8F520708639E02BA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>During Battle Buddy Check Week, the Secretary, in consultation with organizations that represent veterans, non-profits that serve veterans, mental health experts, members of the Armed Forces, and such other entities and individuals as the Secretary considers appropriate, shall collaborate with organizations that represent veterans to provide educational opportunities for veterans to learn how to conduct peer wellness checks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA678B350E2D9425D82FCD00AE6ED6F38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training matters</header><text>As part of the educational opportunities provided under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall provide the following:</text><subparagraph id="H2DAE29920D2D45F58C820DB4F89111DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A script for veterans to use to conduct peer wellness checks that includes information on appropriate referrals to resources veterans might need.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DB0CD533DF44AF9A8E5B127CC311FB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Online and in-person training, as appropriate, on how to conduct a peer wellness check.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H367BDE513DF94D3697F1EBA956560E44"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Opportunities for members of organizations that represent veterans to learn how to train individuals to conduct peer wellness checks.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF5F3FB1B2ED4BA6A1F42CE739A91B22"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Training for veterans participating in Battle Buddy Check Week on how to transfer a phone call directly to the Veterans Crisis Line.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7AA01FE5A244C959A0611D410A50F99"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Resiliency training for veterans participating in Battle Buddy Check Week on handling a veteran in crisis.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAF07EAF738C4E7793B3259F8A3463E4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Online materials</header><text>All training materials provided under the educational opportunities under paragraph (1) shall be made available on a website of the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H82BA4B5C2B14432A8F2999D974E29409"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>The Secretary, in collaboration with organizations that represent veterans, may conduct outreach regarding educational opportunities under subsection (b) at—</text><paragraph id="H8D9715B189DF4988BFB8851BFA0A524C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>public events where many veterans are expected to congregate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14D2540EB2DA4C47AB4BE01EFA807064"><enum>(2)</enum><text>meetings of organizations that represent veterans;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H046FD03F6CC045BF9838C86CEEE76BBB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H075BF09753674A9E859E80F6DB4F403A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>such other locations as the Secretary, in collaboration with organizations that represent veterans, considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5FA52CDC912E41EFBEDE02D987EDCB52"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Veterans crisis line plan</header><paragraph id="H5E8BC6024D644F1088ABEEF4BA50B080"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that the Veterans Crisis Line has a plan for handling the potential increase of calls that may occur during Battle Buddy Check Week.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8102FC689A5B41AA868FD658C5577C9D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Submittal of plan</header><text>The head of the Veterans Crisis Line shall submit to the Secretary a plan for how to handle excess calls during Battle Buddy Check Week, which may include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H7447732F150F46D08C638FC6ACACC551"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Additional hours for staff.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H126E0D57914048A1B725CEF78DB70394"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The use of a backup call center.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92645C2AB15A47F2BAAB9DBBBB8BDC46"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any other plan to ensure that calls from veterans in crisis are being answered in a timely manner by an individual trained at the same level as a Veterans Crisis Line responder.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE8F38EB686F045F4BE2F29933B59D4A6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Veterans crisis line defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>Veterans Crisis Line</quote> means the toll-free hotline for veterans established under section 1720F(h) of title 38, United States Code.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

