<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBB6837CD48F1484E9027680EF80A4CE7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4792 IH: Childhood Offenders Rehabilitation and Safety Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4792</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to account for the age of certain juvenile offenders and to amend title IV of the Social Security Act to allow the Secretary of Health and Human Services to award competitive grants to enhance collaboration between State child welfare and juvenile justice systems, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H9D6E755B7878493EAC03A3F9F99EEB78" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8E9A318DC4F944669C842A1248CBBA81" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Childhood Offenders Rehabilitation and Safety Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5FB2B2876CC14DB39BFBC49A5DD3E023"><enum>2.</enum><header>Amendments</header> <subsection id="H4ECD4234268E4AFCA983A4F0C6AAB25F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5031 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA526749A371D4CE58BDFDD847A69E405"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>person who</quote> and inserting <quote>person who is at least twelve years of age that has not attained their</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA9EC4288A584768A537D7DE904097F6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>not attained</quote> and inserting <quote>not attained their</quote>; and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31D24453B300427DBC59E091CC908AE1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>committed by a person prior to</quote> and inserting <quote>committed by a person who has reached their twelfth birthday but prior to their</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H845A8D0B337D4E9D92158A71D28CC77C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Delinquency proceedings in district courts; transfer for criminal prosecution</header><text>Section 5032 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4F6FD7073F6C4E69B879AB0DD29AE0C0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>fifteen</quote> and inserting <quote>sixteen</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0E35FF98E0D14629BE0B31396E6A7B06"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>fifteenth birthday</quote> and inserting <quote>their sixteenth birthday</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF106E720B72646C3B56B94EDEB97242F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>In the application of the preceding sentence, if the crime of violence is an offense under section 113(a), 113(b), 113(c), 1111, 1113, or, if the juvenile possessed a firearm during the offense, section 2111, 2113, 2241(a), or 2241(c), “thirteen” shall be substituted for “fifteen” and “thirteenth” shall be substituted for “fifteenth”.</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB9198D598E2446BC9D2B130873D58EBE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by striking <quote>However, a juvenile who is alleged to have committed an act after his sixteenth birthday which if committed by an adult would be a felony offense that has as an element thereof the use, attempted use, or threatened use of physical force against the person of another, or that, by its very nature, involves a substantial risk that physical force against the person of another may be used in committing the offense, or would be an offense described in section 32, 81, 844(d), (e), (f), (h), (i) or 2275 of this title, subsection (b)(1)(A), (B), or (C), (d), or (e) of section 401 of the Controlled Substances Act, or section 1002(a), 1003, 1009, or 1010(b)(1), (2), or (3) of the Controlled Substances Import and Export Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/952">21 U.S.C. 952(a)</external-xref>, 953, 959, 960(b)(1), (2), (3)), and who has previously been found guilty of an act which if committed by an adult would have been one of the offenses set forth in this paragraph or an offense in violation of a State felony statute that would have been such an offense if a circumstance giving rise to Federal jurisdiction had existed, shall be transferred to the appropriate district court of the United States for criminal prosecution.</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2F917B0B158449C3A1821D769A6309CF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by striking <quote>social background of the juvenile</quote> and inserting <quote>social background of the juvenile; the juvenile’s prior exposure to adverse childhood experiences, childhood trauma, and involvement in the child welfare system;</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFEE6E8D3337C4C9A886A447C6F1C5034"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by striking <quote>behavioral problems</quote> and inserting <quote>juvenile’s behavioral problems; the rehabilitative potential of the juvenile within the juvenile system; and the best interest of the child</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0D63FE4CFAA1453DBB29B76A3C4B1BEA"><enum>(7)</enum><text>by striking <quote>leadership role</quote> and inserting <quote>juvenile’s level of participation in the offense</quote>; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC04BBC64AA9F497795C4ED780AA394DB"><enum>(8)</enum><text>by striking <quote>in an organization, or otherwise influenced other persons to take part in criminal activities, involving the use or distribution of controlled substances or firearms. Such a factor, if found to exist, shall weigh in favor of a transfer to adult status, but the absence of this factor shall not preclude such a transfer</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H55939FDD8E254DB89889A2E7FD69D51A"><enum>(9)</enum><text>by striking <quote>juvenile, his parents</quote> and inserting <quote>juvenile, their parents</quote>; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H09C5822C00D84C5499E28EACCBE518C9"><enum>(10)</enum><text>by striking <quote>custodian and to his counsel</quote> and <quote>custodian and to their counsel</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3E051FE992E94A6CB638B9DB4780F577"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Commitment</header><text>Section 5039 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HDCBF5474E42A4846809112B5C1DABA3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or correctional institution in which he has regular contact with adults incarcerated because they have been convicted of a crime or are awaiting trial on criminal charges</quote> and inserting <quote>, correctional institution, or prison</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H361EAF118A414651834E459F7A445187"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>near</quote> and insert <quote>near their</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6B5EDB918C344D47814BDA3651F53F3D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Murder</header><text>Section 1111 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H71506201D5314A99A20C923CB134FC2C" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H6824459352AB4D89AB61AE9213D0A1E9"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person who was under the age of 18 at the time of the perpetration or attempted perpetration of a crime listed under subsection (a) in which the death of a human being occurs is liable for murder only if one of the following is proven:</text> <paragraph id="H80FDBDE452E147A9915B458AA81739B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the person who intentionally or knowingly causes the death of another person; or </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEF9B6D72545C4E88A818FD1171161FDC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the person was not the actual killer, but, with the intent to kill, aided, abetted, counseled, commanded, induced, solicited, requested, or assisted the actual killer in the commission of the unlawful killing of another human being. </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9841902CD8BB43288BD2D16192B84258" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <quoted-block-continuation-text quoted-block-continuation-text-level="subsection">A person who is not liable for murder under subsection (a) shall be sentenced in accordance with the crime they committed or attempted to commit.</quoted-block-continuation-text><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H2BDE5664EA4041E3B793A5423D59BA5D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Statistics, data, and research on incarcerated children and persons convicted of crimes as children</header> <subsection id="H80155B7C21934201899A637DEED2B623"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Comprehensive statistical review</header> <paragraph id="H6FFA24EBD3F64909B7F3343696CCC21D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Bureau of Justice Statistics of the Department of Justice (in this section referred to as the <quote>Bureau</quote>) shall publish, for each calendar year, a comprehensive statistical review and analysis of children under eighteen years of age who are subject to adjudication, prosecution, and incarceration by the Federal Government. The statistical review and analysis shall include the following: </text> 
<subparagraph id="H1FC12BEC0C0C4EBDBD35716241C44CBF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of children adjudicated delinquent in the calendar year and the offenses they were adjudicated for.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFA603A3CCAB04774B048DF06D51A2341"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The number of children transferred to district court for criminal prosecution in the calendar year and the offenses they were charged with.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD1817EC70B204659AAF812FF53A04470"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The number of children convicted in district court in the calendar year and the offenses they were convicted of.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2197B565F0404CF8B59270262CC04A97"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The average age of the children at the time of the commission of the offense.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2A5B05F94EF44A76915CBF6BAC86AB5F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The age of the child at the time of adjudication or conviction.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCB7E9D665EFF44E5981F0C30D503B263"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Demographic information, including race, ethnicity, nationality, disability, gender, sex, and gender identity of each child.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H90D1004BD1B44D2EBB7E5B3149C12098"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of children in Federal custody who are being detained, housed, or incarcerated more than 100 miles from the jurisdiction where they were adjudicated or convicted in.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8AAE3CFFC95A43338D5293EE9037D651"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The length of time or sentence each child in Federal custody has been ordered to serve for their corresponding offense. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD3EB6F051DF04094A0D1BF4A219BE505"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The number of people incarcerated in Federal custody for crimes they committed as children.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA510A2944990461F998F310BB5841456"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Demographic information, including race, ethnicity, nationality, disability, gender, sex, gender identity, current age, as well as age at the time of the offense for each person who is currently incarcerated in Federal custody for crimes they committed as children.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBCD15A0AB95949159FC068CCEECCC0C9"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of people in Federal custody for crimes they committed as children who are incarcerated more than 100 miles from the jurisdiction they were adjudicated or convicted in. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD027E13AFF144D3DA44BFC3ACD35FE3C"><enum>(L)</enum><text>The offense and corresponding sentence each person in Federal custody is serving for the crime they committed as a child. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H9ACC84442DFA4A4EB4B164A70DD9EC5C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authority to award competitive grants to enhance collaboration between State child welfare and juvenile justice systems</header> 
<subsection id="HB6B7C6B84C1E4D34AF7ED98900BAA81A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This section may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Childhood Outcomes Need New Efficient Community Teams</short-title> Act</quote> or the <quote><short-title>CONNECT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1A32C220B1CB4494BADF7FF22A954E44"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 436 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/629f">42 U.S.C. 629f</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> 
<quoted-block act-name="" id="H22580A7E14D34EC791BCB87AB5AF0D84" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="HEDD6D79A6F554803A97A04C8A8DBCD49"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authority To award grants to States To enhance collaboration between State child welfare and juvenile justice systems</header> 
<paragraph id="HF982D8931C274A5285C7CCF281D1949D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose of the subsection is to authorize the Secretary to make grants to State child welfare and juvenile justice agencies to collaborate in the collection of data relating to children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems) and to develop practices, policies, and protocols to confront the challenges presented and experienced by these children and their families. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC62C79293F9A47288D6B40918E899978"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority to award grants</header> <subparagraph id="H71CC72FA0A9948E6A789B05EC9165297"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may award competitive grants jointly to a State child welfare agency and a State juvenile justice agency to facilitate or enhance collaboration between the child welfare and juvenile justice systems of the State in order to carry out programs to address the needs of children including those excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA61392585FEC4521BE7220AC38848EC9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>Any grants awarded under this subsection shall be awarded from the amounts made available under subsection (a) of this section, after the application of subsection (b) of this section and before the determination of allotments under section 433.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H3AE5D6751FEA482C99FB03D7D7A4B0C4"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Length of grants</header> <clause commented="no" id="H9F78F7B1F6D745C396BA7DDBA876AF95"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A grant shall be awarded under this subsection for a period of not less than 2, and not more than 5, fiscal years, subject to clause (ii).</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HFBDB27D4733446ADBFD8FCE39B512B92"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Extension of grant</header><text>On application of the grantee, the Secretary may extend for not more than 2 fiscal years the period for which a grant is awarded under this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CD0C044F63446CEA7D9C14A70B1AC50"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header> <subparagraph id="H0634603C90044235BE2FB8D42B6CF5EE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application</header><text>In order for a State to be eligible for a grant under this subsection, it shall submit an application, to be approved by the Secretary, that includes—</text> 
<clause id="HEE72E2F21C604943B5BA3819B817CB97"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the proposed leadership collaboration group (including the membership of such group), and how such group will manage and oversee a review and analysis of current practices while working to jointly address enhanced practices to improve outcomes for children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems);</text></clause> <clause id="H761D9BC2B91042A8B7633988B1A55C91"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a description of how the State proposes to—</text> 
<subclause id="H41B8CAD6FFA24758A8D5DF38D120E402"><enum>(I)</enum><text>identify any eligible children;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H4D7C40DE57244B6A8CDBB7217F0E866B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>identify individuals who are at risk of becoming eligible children;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEEAB755148E84E83B21B975321D9FF35"><enum>(III)</enum><text>identify common characteristics shared by any eligible children in the State; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB52D6B0DBC064BE4903E1C294A159DFC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determine the prevalence of children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems) in the State;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HC60F379984D34FCB9B26FD41C68AFF65"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a description of current and proposed practices and procedures that the State intends to use to—</text> <subclause id="H1E02344B372B44FBA9BA9D07FFDC4BC7"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">screen and assess children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems) for risks and treatment needs;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H390E596FFE9041D98C53B4297E12214F"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide targeted and evidence-based services, including educational, behavioral health, and pro-social treatment interventions for children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems); and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H7994EA3F51444E40959E49B446E2A690"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide for a lawful process to enhance or ensure the abilities of the State and any relevant agencies to share information and data about children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems) while maintaining confidentiality and privacy protections under State and Federal law; and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H19FB5C737F1F470897E3F558FE6497C8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a certification that the State has involved local governments, including tribal governments, as appropriate, in the development, expansion, modification, operation, or improvement of proposed policy and practice reforms to address the needs of children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0C2E08B6A95B4A10B33336181D160BD3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No supplantation of other funds</header><text>Any amounts paid to a State under a grant under this subsection shall be used to supplement and not supplant other State expenditures on any eligible children involved with either the child welfare or juvenile justice systems.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H11464E885F694DAABD28EA7C777F4D1E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State child welfare agency and a State juvenile justice agency receiving a grant under this subsection shall jointly submit to the Secretary and to the Administrator of the Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention of the Department of Justice and the Administration for Children and Families of the Department of Health and Human Services a report on the activities carried out under the grant at the end of each fiscal year during the period of the grant. Such report shall include—</text> <clause id="H9B4A285E2C254EF793E4DAE8FCEFB926"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the scope and nature of the children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems) in the State, including the number of dual status youth; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H48F59E370B794650BA446370E065ED73"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a description of the evidence-based practices and procedures used by the agencies to carry out the activities described in subclauses (I) through (III) of subparagraph (A)(iii); and</text></clause> <clause id="H6699C589FBD64F1E852E58097FD208A8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an analysis of the effects of such practices and procedures, including information regarding—</text> 
<subclause id="HDBD7D896E12044158932B3519ED6E4A4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the collection of data related to individual children;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HBA7982B53A3343B8AB3852A5ABC77DA2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>aggregate data related to the eligible children population, including—</text> 
<item id="HD1B289D939E7426B97BE10FED6E7089A"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">characteristics of children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems) in the State;</text></item> <item id="H719E87B72C364AF189EDB8104DBF737C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>case processing timelines; and</text></item> 
<item id="H1279085C3E074BC5B1ED4C255C17A796"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>information related to case management, the provision of targeted services, and placements within the foster care or juvenile justice system; and</text></item></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="HA576CAD300114736BC2B82461D754F5E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the extent to which such practices and procedures have contributed to—</text> 
<item commented="no" id="H68E326C681F94172B2ABB11F8A89EA55"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>higher educational attainment for any eligible children; </text></item> <item commented="no" id="HB9CF39D35D314E9DBB080755712E1734"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fewer delinquency referrals for children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems);</text></item> 
<item commented="no" id="HCA360A8A0EB24115A82AEC4CA6A3775D"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shorter stays in intensive restrictive placements for children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youth (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems); or </text></item> <item commented="no" id="H393F868A0F754E099DF85EA87FE35E87"><enum>(dd)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other outcomes for children excluded from juvenile adjudication by age (under age of 12 and over the age of 15 years old), child survivors of commercial sexual exploitation, dual status youths (children in both foster care and juvenile justice systems), and cross over children (children that cross between the foster care and juvenile justice systems) as the State child welfare agency and State juvenile justice agency may identify.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA20552A697544574B6A39CA2337788C3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Training and technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary may support State child welfare agencies and State juvenile justice agencies by offering a program, developed in consultation with organizations and agencies with subject matter expertise, of training and technical assistance to assist the agencies in developing programs and protocols—</text> <subparagraph id="H94CE881EEB9B4764A068317944F34AD9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to facilitate or enhance collaboration between State child welfare agencies and State juvenile justice agencies; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4166FEA854264630909B50360373B367"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for effectively working with Federal agencies and child welfare and juvenile justice agencies from other States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCF3A15CD735C41518859CC4326E96C51"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this subsection, and every 3 years thereafter, the Secretary and the Attorney General of the Department of Justice shall jointly submit to the Committee on Finance and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate and the Committee on Ways and Means and the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives, a report on the grants provided under this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEEF2D1F5B2B445CFB07641D16C56F028"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text> <subparagraph id="H88FEF6BA2EDF4DAD9E5B0B64F9A7FEDD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Commercial sexual exploitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>commercial sexual exploitation</quote> means crimes and activities involving the sexual abuse or exploitation of a person under age 18 for the financial benefit of any person or in exchange for anything of value, including monetary and non-monetary benefits, given or received by any person.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8A13484271EE4E69B368AC685413CC91"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Dual status youth</header><text>The term <term>dual status youth</term> means a child who has come into contact with both the child welfare and juvenile justice systems and occupies various statuses in terms of the individual's relationship to such systems.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HB7184A84209D4CB8BEE41E1D8CA35131"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Leadership collaboration group</header><text>The term <term>leadership collaboration group</term> means a group composed of senior officials from the State child welfare agency, the State juvenile justice agency, and other relevant youth and family-serving public agencies and private organizations, including tribal nations, and to the extent practicable, representatives from the State judiciary branch.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H06C6216438744A2E8556C394A86263CD"><enum>(D)</enum><header>State juvenile justice agency</header><text>The term <term>State juvenile justice agency</term> means the agency of the State or Indian tribe responsible for administering grant funds awarded under the Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5601">42 U.S.C. 5601 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H94D04599BFEE4F17A12FFBB71F113BF4"><enum>(E)</enum><header>State child welfare agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State child welfare agency</term> means the State agency responsible for administering the program under subpart 1, or in the case of a tribal organization operating a direct Title IV–B (SSA) program or a Title IV–B-funded program through tribal-State agreement, or that is receiving payments under section 428, the tribal agency responsible for administering such program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5CDF12745BDC4EFAAD56801DE22D25A1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Subsections (b) and (c) of section 433 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/633">42 U.S.C. 633</external-xref>) are each amended by striking <quote>section 436(b)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsections (b) and (c) of section 436</quote>.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

