<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8853D789444A4BA794D8C7F2A326B118" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6789 IH: Rectifying Undefined Descriptions of Abusive Acts and Practices Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6789</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001213">Mr. Steil</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000471">Mr. Fitzgerald</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000612">Mr. Rose</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 to clarify standards for UDAAP enforcement actions brought by the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0940C89E6B9641618C852DDD78B23238" style="OLC"><section id="H04F03133EC7041AC8ECBFFBFC7233555" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rectifying Undefined Descriptions of Abusive Acts and Practices Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Rectifying UDAAP Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H984073977DDA4F7DB44C7CB9881C6210"><enum>2.</enum><header>Mitigating factors in assessing civil penalties</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1055(c) of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5565">12 U.S.C. 5565(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H714BCAAECADD481080CC5F09FDEDCFAD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H6A73422C273E43D4B4F9FEF87BA01F2D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, issue a rule that establishes policies and procedures relating to the imposition of civil monetary penalties sought under this subsection, including the application of the mitigating factors described in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H89DFC86EAD794A20965324BB59968334"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rulemaking relating to unfair, deceptive or abusive acts or practices</header><subsection id="HAC651822479644DA807AF168D61A31FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1031(b) of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5531">12 U.S.C. 5531</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (b) and inserting the following:</text></subsection><subsection id="idA53A29EA650341E3BB8090C2DEC18F13"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1CF50DBA274247FD8FC2D5C721591D1A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H53A2995F9887486E9BA8C347EAC37CF2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau may prescribe rules applicable to a covered person or service provider identifying as unlawful unfair, deceptive, or abusive acts or practices in connection with any transaction with a consumer for a consumer finanical product or service, or the offering of a consumer financial product or service. Rules under this section may include requirements for the purpose of preventing such acts or practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65D4A7551E154B76BACDFBADA7A3D008"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cost benefit analysis required</header><text>Any final rule issued by the Bureau relating to abusive, unfair, or deceptive acts or practices shall include a cost-benefit analysis.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F520AC1CAB4478B9F500E201F2C700C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definition of abusive act or practice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, issue a rule that defines the term <quote>abusive act or practice</quote> for the purposes of this section. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H4BDA4E617771463DA059E2A8228710E4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Opportunity for comment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, allow the public to submit comments with respect to any confusion about how the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection uses its authority with respect to unfair, deceptive, or abusive acts or practices.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF751FE6E522543188D39CE1A3F548257"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authority to declare an act unlawful based on discrimination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection may not interpret the authority of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection relating to unfair, deceptive, or abusive acts and practices, as such term is used in section 1031 of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010, to include discriminatory practices.</text></section><section id="H170327D699EA4954A098EE1A5172151C"><enum>5.</enum><header>Clarifying the abusive standard for the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1031 of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5531">12 U.S.C. 5531</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (d) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9BB693C159C5419AAC56842C9DCDD9E4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HA3C66414B6AE4C5E86CFC05EAAC9F662"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Abusive</header><paragraph id="HD07DBD32362140C2B702276DD7D0FB2E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau shall have no authority to declare an act or practice of a covered person abusive in connection with the provision of a consumer financial product or service, unless the act or practice— </text><subparagraph id="H4104624B9B5B4EE3BCA85BE816E6EA52"><enum>(A)</enum><text>intentionally and materially interferes with the ability of a consumer to understand a term or condition of a consumer financial product or service; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H120234C39F424EAE9D9F82DC4F716123"><enum>(B)</enum><text>takes unreasonable advantage of—</text><clause id="H67EBB82B5D0247F085B335D6D4EA07CC"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a lack of understanding by the consumer with respect to the possible impact, material risks, costs, or conditions of the product or service, or the likelihood of the risks, costs, or conditions of the product or service negatively affecting the consumer; and</text></clause><clause id="H0AB7C084FEC34A76985695848AD85AA9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the reasonable reliance the consumer places on an affirmative action or representation of such covered person to induce such consumer to rely on such action or representation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2605515A887D442B91D23C01D3083C49"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Abusive actions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conduct of a covered person shall be considered abusive if—</text><subparagraph id="HD7DCA9F4DE274E7DA13523D5C682258D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the act or practice causes or is likely to cause substantial injury to consumers which is not reasonably avoidable by consumers; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7872C3DEA8B41C9AD604194D3478657"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such substantial injury is not outweighed by countervailing benefits to consumers or to competition; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B9D64849CAB401C8D441A115B9D6369"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the conduct is otherwise prohibited by Federal consumer financial law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE57BA5714A59483BAF03E7A2657794AD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Good-Faith effort To comply</header><paragraph id="H908C5277DB224E318933B95C462D4547"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau may not seek monetary relief from a covered person under this section unless the covered person has not established by a preponderance of the evidence that they made a good-faith effort to comply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H76C8F6B243634B7E81DE0A7EE075DEEE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority to seek legal or equitable remedies</header><text>The limitation described in subparagraph (A) shall not restrict the authority of the Bureau to seek legal or equitable remedies, such as damages and restitution, to redress an identifiable consumer injury caused by the abusive acts or practices of such covered person.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H3DA40ECDBCAB4BF0A5EFCA417A6B33EA"><enum>6.</enum><header>Notice and opportunity to cure</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1031 of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5531">12 U.S.C. 5531</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H094FD4AC6A2F457F94E5CEAC231ED1F6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HAE25A40F17D34B4C85D76DA3E129E813"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity To cure</header><paragraph id="H7528D8D6769740B6890A7933EEF9AFD3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a covered person self-identifies a potential unfair, deceptive, or abusive act or practice carried out by such covered person, the Bureau shall, not later than 90 days after such self-identification, provide a written notice in the form of a potential action and request for response letter or a notice and opportunity to respond and advise letter of the potential unfair, deceptive, or abusive act or practice to such covered person and inform the covered person that such person has 180 days after the date the covered person receives such notice to cure such potential unfair, deceptive, or abusive act before the Bureau may pursue other legal action.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H15CC61CE7A0C4E3D8B31A77BD9EF879A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tolling of statute of limitations</header><text>Any applicable statute of limitations that applies to conduct under which the Bureau has given notice and an opportunity to cure shall not toll until—</text><subparagraph id="H77DE91A55E4446A09BC27946AB1D693A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the covered person cures the potential abusive, unfair, or deceptive act or practice and notifies the Bureau that such act or practice has been cured;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4409FDC84332483DBB39E28DB466B6BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the covered person notifies the Bureau that such covered person will not cure the act or practice; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5341C56B5551430999CE993D4EE93E24"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the 180-day period to cure ends.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H34117C1468CF4CB4AC611522C1796F34"><enum>7.</enum><header>Abusive, unfair, or deceptive acts or practices enforcement actions</header><subsection id="H207D09EE47EC4A8C9B87A6CC6F2B7B37"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle E of title X of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5561">12 U.S.C. 5561 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3E56E142D6034CC3BA8D24947217777C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H202E0A6A819840C0988CF07958E9D798"><enum>1059.</enum><header>Unfair, Deceptive, or Abusive Acts or Practices Enforcement Actions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Enforcement actions brought by the Bureau under section 1031 under this title shall be brought in—</text><paragraph id="H1122F0701407479B88F035569901E40D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the United States district court located where the covered person has its headquarters location; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EBCF8C95FAC4C1BB14CAB42ED3CA956"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States District Court for the District of Columbia.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H613E1235441242768735526F64F4A1A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Actions under section 1031</header><text>Section 1031 of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEFEB7D9F30974675BA0E7A31AA854841" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H0564C11F06964E1B8BEC7C650C189861"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Enforcement Actions</header><paragraph id="H64D4316865F24B1DBCAC626F72A6D45C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Bureau brings an enforcement action under this section, the Bureau shall state with particularity the circumstances that the Bureau alleges constitute violation of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32028F8F4EDB447FAF6CDC43490A9EC8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alternative Claims</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Bureau brings an enforcement action under this section—</text><subparagraph id="HB23F8956051040CF96C1A41FC2037FF6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>claiming that an activity is unfair or deceptive, the Bureau may not claim in the alternative that the activity is abusive; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H640BB67488524E8D84590C3DF5553F01"><enum>(B)</enum><text>claiming that an activity is abusive, the Bureau may not claim in the alternative that the activity is unfair or deceptive. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H05D401389314483387954C196A4EE46F"><enum>8.</enum><header>Look-back provisions for the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subtitle B of title X of the Consumer Financial Protection Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5511">12 U.S.C. 5511 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H250AA67F91EF499DAD30550D65683853" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HE827ABF46F524019B777F912934ED56D"><enum>1029B</enum><header>Examination period limitations</header><subsection id="H6BC9B5031A4C44368FE18DDE3BC6D66B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When enforcing Federal consumer financial laws, the Bureau may not seek a civil money penalty for any violating conduct that occurred prior to the most recent assignment of a consumer compliance rating. </text></subsection><subsection id="HD62A09AE663E4E6C8CF0BB5C0D00124A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This limitation described in subsection (a) may not be construed to restrict the ability of the Bureau to seek other forms of legal or equitable relief available under subparagraphs (A) through (G) of section 1055(a)(2) for any violating conduct that occurred prior to the most recent assignment of a consumer compliance rating.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

