<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0BEB8116343341DEB6A5AE2CFFEDC0B6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3151 IH: WIC Healthy Beginnings Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3151</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 to require the Secretary of Agriculture to make publicly available information on infant formula procurement under the special supplemental nutrition program for women, infants, and children.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF87839BB2A4842FF923D6FD580A2811E" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H8B6F244EA6C24043A6AEC5F73174EE57"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>WIC Healthy Beginnings Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HBA379878D83B470C9C3B266A2C440080"><enum>2.</enum><header>Infant formula procurement online source of information</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 17(h)(8)(A) of the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1786">42 U.S.C. 1786(h)(8)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8EB984BAB16544D1809B4E440C3E12FB"><clause id="H00B27678724541B9BB13CC5B8885CE66"><enum>(xi)</enum><header>Infant formula procurement online source of information</header><subclause id="H912BDDF3FDAB4FA6A4AA4351772621DA"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this clause, the Secretary shall make available to the public the information described in items (aa) through (dd) of subclause (II) relating to bid solicitations of State agencies for infant formula under the program.</text></subclause><subclause id="H2D95ECC8896F45BBB21D0285F89F73BC"><enum>(II)</enum><header>State agencies</header><text>In soliciting bids for infant formula under the program, a State agency, or a State agency on behalf of a State alliance, shall submit to the Secretary, not later than 5 business days after the date on which a bid solicitation is made available online to bidders by the State, a description of the bid solicitation, including—</text><item id="HA1533C2B5B594A6B993145AFB3BD6EED"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the title of the bid solicitation and the State agency administering the bid solicitation;</text></item><item id="H3D1B37D6015A40B791011223C7E5D322"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the website hyperlink and other information needed for the purpose of submitting a bid in response to the bid solicitation;</text></item><item id="HAACB3AED9C1747F8B481CD8FBC108A9D"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>the contact information and website hyperlink for the State agency administering the bid solicitation, for the purpose of gathering additional information relating to the bid solicitation; and</text></item><item id="H99AC4A0468624155AA99C35F375F7473"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>the period during which bids are accepted or the due date for bids, as applicable, under the bid solicitation.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HB166CE7657694629981814C1FCB70B8E"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Not later than 5 days after receiving a description of a bid solicitation under subclause (II), the Secretary shall make that description publicly available.</text></subclause><subclause id="H3158B8D5030C41DFA948C524A9714F49"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>The Secretary shall issue guidance to implement this clause.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

