<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD5FA8E4A706E446691E4834016AC3D26" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6074 IH: State Border Defense Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6074</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001132">Mr. Crane</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To allow States to authorize State and local law enforcement officers to enforce the provisions of Federal immigration law relating to unlawful entry into the United States and to authorize States along the southern land border to construct barriers on Federal lands to prevent unlawful entry into the United States.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7716E31813BD46D1B471C5769A977BE2" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H7F63D99A3D13431B9A53D9A3FA7FD7B3"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>State Border Defense Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2708E70E276B48C4B04CDD1C3CA67115"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authorization of State and local law enforcement officers to enforce certain Federal immigration laws</header><subsection id="HE04E5F67307D433BBF99B674C31DD784"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>States may authorize State and local law enforcement officers to enforce provisions of Federal immigration law that prohibit unlawful entry into the United States, including sections 271 through 280 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S.C. 1321 through 1330).</text></subsection><subsection id="HF48525BCC0A54C7C8F576E767B38725B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effect of authorization on Supreme Court ruling</header><text>Subsection (a) effectively abrogates the 2012 decision of the United States Supreme Court in Arizona v. United States (567 U.S. 387).</text></subsection><subsection id="H1BA789FB7E6C49AE8CCC2FC35ACB1EBD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prosecution authority</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, State prosecutors are authorized to initiate prosecutions for violations of Federal immigration law referred to in subsection (a) in a United States District Court that has jurisdiction over—</text><paragraph id="H647A289CCE5B42F08BE0CFFBEC20C618"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the place at which any such violation occurred; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2D574089CA8427EA487C70D834D4F1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the place at which the person charged for any such violation is apprehended.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCFA09AAE2B3C49B496A22DDA9C203F19"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 279 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1329">8 U.S.C. 1329</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H85270D8C5D03491AB578905A605BF966"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or by a State prosecutor pursuant to section 2(c) of the <short-title>State Border Defense Act</short-title>,</quote> before <quote>that arise</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FD04A25A1944F2AB78EBF23B046805C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>It shall be the duty of the State prosecutor of the appropriate State to prosecute every such suit when brought by a State.</quote> after <quote>United States.</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HEA28A9FE7F4F417FBA0AFB4A273F887F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization of States to place certain barriers on Federal land</header><subsection id="H529AC6A6B7F44FA0BD225133DF698B85"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, it shall not be a violation of Federal law for the States of California, Arizona, New Mexico, and Texas, or their designees, to construct barriers on Federal lands or waters for the purpose of preventing unlawful entry into the United States if—</text><paragraph id="H0C36A511966E45DA99032B879F236F52"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the barriers do not decrease the ability of U.S. Customs and Border Patrol to patrol the border between the United States and Mexico, intercept unlawful migrants, or deport unlawful migrants; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47F087FA34504B8FA5E24F63285DF7E1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the barriers do not actually and substantially impede lawful movement along any navigable water, roadway, or other avenue of interstate commerce.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2FAF7DE96C454FA393DCA2ED863E0D9C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Subsection (a) may not be construed as a defense to any claim of unlawful conduct unless the allegedly unlawful conduct consists of constructing or maintaining barriers on Federal lands or waters for the purpose of preventing unlawful entry into the United States.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

