<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Referred-in-Senate" dms-id="H07F5ED55911846119AF7824A220592C0" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 593 : To rename the Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic in Hinesville, Georgia, as the “John Gibson, Dan James, William Sapp, and Frankie Smiley VA Clinic”.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IIB</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 593</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20231114" legis-day="20231113">November 14 (legislative day, November 13), 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received; read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSVA00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To rename the Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic in Hinesville, Georgia, as the <quote>John Gibson, Dan James, William Sapp, and Frankie Smiley VA Clinic</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H55F1FDB3482645D4A6204AA530632CC2" style="OLC"><pagebreak></pagebreak><section id="HFE96CD0E680D43D39E760E8322778DE1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Name of Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic, Hinesville, Georgia</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic in Hinesville, Georgia, shall after the date of the enactment of this Act be known and designated as the <quote>John Gibson, Dan James, William Sapp, and Frankie Smiley VA Clinic</quote>. Any reference to such clinic in any law, regulation, map, document, record, or other paper of the United States shall be considered to be a reference to the John Gibson, Dan James, William Sapp, and Frankie Smiley VA Clinic.</text></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20231113" legis-day="20231113" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives November 13, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Kevin F. McCumber,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation></bill> 

