<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6B857045F46E46C1B622DF2C9BEB4A37" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2758 IH: Returning Worker Accountability Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2758</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Immigration and Nationality Act to make the exception for returning workers permanent, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9DC42FF19AD34DC6B34A9160877B8313" style="OLC"><section id="H026C715E247A40E9B5BE0366307590EA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Returning Worker Accountability Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3FA9C3E55E6A400A8CC6DE20ABCFD6DE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Returning worker exception made permanent</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 214(g)(9) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1184">8 U.S.C. 1184(g)(9)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HA8422569CC7A433B9F24204D4AC69042"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>who has already been counted toward the numerical limitation of paragraph (1)(B) during fiscal year 2019, 2020, or 2021 shall not again be counted toward such limitation during fiscal year 2022</quote> and inserting <quote>shall not be counted toward the numerical limitation of paragraph (1)(B) for a fiscal year if that alien has already been counted toward such limitation during any of the 3 fiscal years immediately preceding that fiscal year and shall satisfy the requirements under subparagraph (D)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F72E03E60974280A40F73E4187EDD93"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3ED3206E615C4F10B58BC6EED1403C05" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="HCB8D1057833C4833B431B8DF91A40DC5"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirement under this subparagraph is as follows:</text><clause id="HE327C6B312DF40749CC11C288EB4541C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An alien shall participate in the biometric entry and exit system (as such term is defined in section 7208(b) of the Intelligence Reform and Terrorism Prevention Act of 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1365b">8 U.S.C. 1365b(b)</external-xref>)). Any information collected by reason of participation in such system shall be shared with the Biometric Identification Transnational Migration Alert Program of US Immigration and Customs Enforcement and the Office of Biometric Identity Management of the Department of Homeland Security.</text></clause><clause id="H357BDAC66B364402A37D97A526FC007A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information referred to in clause (i) shall be used to investigate an alien who has been counted toward the numerical limitation of paragraph (1)(B) for a fiscal year, and to determine if that alien has ever used an alias while working or present in the United States. If an alias is identified, that alien shall be evaluated to determine if the alien poses a national security threat, if the alien has a criminal history, and if the alien is inadmissible. </text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H540B82513DBD4704B40058AD3B636345"><enum>3.</enum><header>Enhanced vetting</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall use the biometric data to vet named workers against supporting evidence (including copies of passport, current and previous visas, entry documents) and identify any aliases. If an alias is identified, the Secretary shall vet named workers and aliases for potential national security threat, criminal history, and inadmissibility. If the alien is found to violate the factors, the alien shall not be banned from participating in the H–2B program.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

