<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9FA71879F80142E4B5E1325981413B39" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4759 IH: Environmentally Sustainable Growth Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4759</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for disclosure of additional material information about public companies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDE9C45D51888463BB961DDB59C4093F5" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4C8B2BA884C445629BA5633F916D21A9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Environmentally Sustainable Growth Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H2E3C55B844A344BF80C2577721453538"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HEEBB6FB440DA488282399CD3AC1B680B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Securities and Exchange Commission has broad authority to require the disclosure of information if such information is in the interest of, or is material to investors. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD42506B0B0B64D02989063BD3864AA6C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Commission does not require companies to disclose information related to environmental, social, and governance (<quote>ESG</quote>) matters, and does not require companies to adhere to standards for disclosing such information.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC17EE3A48CCC4FF58015811496BEF759"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Investors have reported that voluntary disclosures of ESG metrics are inadequate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H248BC0BCF436471B9AFD73F6939C8267"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A rule requiring reporting and standardization of ESG disclosures is in the interest of investors. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H62E4DCCAE9FB4E8DBAA7C06D6AEB7661"><enum>(5)</enum><text>ESG matters are material to investors, and the Commission must establish standards for disclosure of such matters.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H56B3F1743C4646318E237BE9384B55AC"><enum>3.</enum><header>ESG disclosures</header> <subsection id="HD27E9990D7CC448A84B766C50C148127"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 14 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78n">15 U.S.C. 78n</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7CFD8993196046D3B95EED8EE42EF70C"> 
<subsection id="H75E38E4915524C0EB41DA6B4BFC0D62B"><enum>(l)</enum><header>ESG disclosures</header> 
<paragraph id="H72F481CAF75A4119AF27475ADF0B6E53"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each issuer the securities of which are registered under section 12 or that is required to file annual reports under section 15(d) shall disclose in any proxy or consent solicitation material for an annual meeting of the shareholders—</text> <subparagraph id="HA257CE33B22A4816B4C9C1ED76A6A17B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a clear description of the views of the issuer about the link between ESG metrics and the long-term business strategy of the issuer; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE48869D52A6B40AE812D55D59183A4E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of any process the issuer uses to determine the impact of ESG metrics on the long-term business strategy of the issuer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2728A4DC20734661B0C876B4FDB59AC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>ESG metrics defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>ESG metrics</term> has the meaning given the term in part 210 of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations as amended pursuant to section 3(b) of the ESG Disclosure Simplification Act of 2021.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0392EF08DB8041A08223D1D6B58AE975" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header> 
<paragraph id="HB36A0A9CB75244CC9B9684A482C8434A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Securities and Exchange Commission (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>) shall amend part 210 of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor thereto) to—</text> <subparagraph id="H217A1232CE1F49B69723F85DF0F89769"><enum>(A)</enum><text>require each issuer, in any filing of the issuer described in such part that requires audited financial statements, to disclose environmental, social, and governance metrics (in this Act referred to as ESG metrics); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4860263C3C8B4F4F83516FBEB8345713"><enum>(B)</enum><text>define ESG metrics.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEA655FAF39964C1794D42A337D45B4B0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sustainable Finance Advisory Committee</header><text>The Sustainable Finance Advisory Committee of the Commission shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the first meeting of such Committee, submit to the Commission recommendations about what ESG metrics the Commission should require issuers to disclose. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H801AB40402F645D6AE85DC324B5A634B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Materiality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that ESG metrics, as such term is defined by the Commission pursuant to paragraph (1), are de facto material for the purposes of disclosures under the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 and the Securities Act of 1933.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA3AEC7540D342BEB9F97EBD4112BB8C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Incorporation of international standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When amending part 210 of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor thereto) pursuant to paragraph (1), the Commission may, as the Commission determines appropriate, incorporate any internationally recognized, independent, multi-stakeholder environmental, social, and governance disclosure standards.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9F7598F339C143DA8C1ABABDEF5302E7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Location of disclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any disclosure required by paragraph (1) may be included in a notes section of the filing.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA63BF3F68F044E19235CCC819B041CE"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Delay for small issuers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may use a phased approach when applying any amendments made pursuant to paragraph (1) to small issuers and may determine the criteria by which an issuer qualifies as a small issuer for purposes of such phased approach.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HEEA672F39C6A4433846066111E81FD38"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sustainable Finance Advisory Committee</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78d">15 U.S.C. 78d</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8384D717BEA34B3F9FC4649BD13D6F66" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H71A4EEF67C6C4F038FD752557285C6A0"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Sustainable Finance Advisory Committee</header> <paragraph id="HE1ED38AFE8A744AEBAB9F3CC57548281"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Commission shall establish a permanent advisory committee to be called the <quote>Sustainable Finance Advisory Committee</quote> (in this subsection referred to as the <quote>Committee</quote>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED5C49F928624B5BBA46CE5DFC8EAA97"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties of Committee</header><text>The Committee shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H655AA5BD140D49AC96D6F408B87DB0CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit a report to the Commission not later than 18 months after the date of the first meeting of the Committee that—</text> 
<clause id="H492747C2263E4112B66FD34925181A06"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies the challenges and opportunities for investors associated with sustainable finance; and</text></clause> <clause id="H4C3B39EABC1347FDA29B77D8C3A642A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommends policy changes to facilitate the flow of capital towards sustainable investments, in particular environmentally sustainable investments;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HACC2E0AC0DE04C3A86422529B3110A43" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>when solicited, advise the Commission on sustainable finance; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDA5FBF955BC6472BA0099E8F3BD41F1E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>communicate with individuals and entities with an interest in sustainable finance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2EB75CE8789B4164B9B144B53E0568C3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<subparagraph id="H7E0177DFDF3646D48AD9DFE74448FBEA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Members</header> 
<clause id="H92B3565251EC4F5794F8C7CC0D4F6A65"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee shall consist of no more than 20 members who shall each serve for one four-year term.</text></clause> <clause id="HD732F4A6843546A48B8035221A2D639B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Representation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member shall represent individuals and entities with an interest in sustainable finance, such as—</text> 
<subclause id="H699F0525B6FC415AA521CE12E2BAACAD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>experts on sustainable finance;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H512C28BD6D6847FCB54B90EF5FB03B11"><enum>(II)</enum><text>operators of financial infrastructure;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7E1894E9C1234D03BC47750C22A26F8C"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">entities that provide analysis, data, or methodologies that facilitate sustainable finance;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H279EFCFEE0AE44A095F4E92104F01F64"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">insurance companies, pension funds, asset managers, depository institutions, or credit unions; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0CD36BEC567947EE8AB041D1376EEA6D"><enum>(V)</enum><text>other financial institutions that intermediate investments in sustainable finance or manage risks related to sustainable development.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H3DA56387DA98473489A759A613D373F0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Representation of interests</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A member may not represent a single individual or entity and shall represent types of individuals and entities with similar interests in sustainable finance.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H94882A7922664E1593099B34092AB46D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection</header> 
<clause id="HDC946398227746D3B3F068C81A55DECD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall—</text> <subclause id="H3ECC423D7A21405FB37A82920E2F2455"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">publish criteria for selection of members on the website of the Commission and in the Federal Register; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9035AAC0D19B4DDEA8E5C0D11E31B2F9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>solicit applications for membership on the website of the Commission and in the Federal Register.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H364FAF57D6A048D6B2600CEAA353D396"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Equal share</header><text>From the individuals who submit applications for membership, each Commissioner of the Commission shall select an equal number of the members of the Committee.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB20298DE4D4547029B4DD666BF277A63"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Pay</header><text>Members may not receive pay by reason of their service on the Committee but may receive travel or transportation expenses in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFFE9D9E9F5174727B4CE88EC1AE79342"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Member transparency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The name of each member and the types of individuals and entities that such member represents shall be published on the website of the Commission.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4C7220D64599473A878F94E741B6C096"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Staff</header><text>The Committee shall be supported by staff from the Office of the Investor Advocate of the Commission that are dedicated to environmental, social and governance (in this subsection referred to as <quote>ESG</quote>) issues.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1C246B89D04144E8AFFE6C8681A17605"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriation</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to finance costs associated with staff dedicated to ESG issues in the Office of the Investor Advocate of the Commission. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H28A0DFC0AE8D455FB9340043FFD92583"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Sustainable finance</header><text>For the purposes of this subsection, the term <term>sustainable finance</term> means the provision of finance with respect to investments taking into account environmental, social, and governance considerations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6C5475BF5B3647C2A690C9CD1CF1E686"><enum>(5)</enum><header>SEC Response</header><text>The Commission shall, not later than 6 months after the date on which the Committee submits a report to the Commission pursuant to paragraph (2)(A), publish a response to such report. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

