<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9C9DB121546A4D58B1246AF4C777FAA5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4909 IH: SNAP Nutrition Security Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4909</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 to improve diet quality and nutrition security, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0197BFE44B4E4E9C9D0242F6B43C0313" style="OLC"><section id="HF8D71CC33E7B4C4FB77534979FE8BCAE" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>SNAP Nutrition Security Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC1FF17209F8B49C0ABEF1D2C4ADEA52E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Food and nutrition security</header><subsection id="HA7284ED770AA4D39B0B5E2DC09933919"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Declaration of policy</header><text>Section 2 of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2011">7 U.S.C. 2011</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>Congress recognizes that the supplemental nutrition assistance program established under this Act reduces food insecurity for tens of millions of households, yet more than 10,000,000 households still suffer from food insecurity, according to the Department of Agriculture. Congress also recognizes that, according to the Department of Agriculture, approximately half of all adults in the United States (117,000,000 people) have 1 or more preventable chronic diseases, many of which are related to poor quality eating patterns. Accordingly, it is the policy of Congress that the Department of Agriculture should administer the supplemental nutrition assistance program in a manner that will further reduce food insecurity, increase nutrition security, and improve the diet quality for low-income people in the United States, especially children. Food programs administered by the Department of Agriculture should simultaneously combat food insufficiency and diet-related chronic diseases, including obesity, diabetes, hypertension, heart disease, and cancer, which cause immense suffering, significantly increase already high health care spending, increase poverty, and undermine military readiness.</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB86370DCB933401E93A640CF9B5AE13D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 3 of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2012">7 U.S.C. 2012</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H20DB60D104CC4857A0488229965D4E99" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (h) through (k), (l), (m), and (n) through (v) as subsections (i) through (l), (n), (o), and (q) through (y), respectively;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1AB0E907CE345E9A9F5492A2B7A30E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (g) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD9DC63AFBE8B4BAE8F5A6198B8357180"><subsection id="H5FB43CF9204444D79DD431700757E6B8"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Diet quality</header><text>The term <term>diet quality</term> means the extent to which a set of foods aligns with key recommendations of the most recent Dietary Guidelines for Americans published under section 301 of the National Nutrition Monitoring and Related Research Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/5341">7 U.S.C. 5341</external-xref>).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H90AE8926425D4491B759FA4D42650C0D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (l) (as so redesignated) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H85E787CB222244358CD121D729AFA668"><subsection id="HE46B87A759D04E9BBC3324656FD6C883"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Food security</header><text>The term <term>food security</term> means access by all people at all times to enough food for an active, healthy life.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H39F937013FA143269519328B1C710C67"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (o) (as so redesignated) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2535AEAADD534FEB95438D1571B22608"><subsection id="HD908F4F62F2A4FB99C946BD12D971A53"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Nutrition security</header><text>The term <term>nutrition security</term> means consistent and equitable access to healthy, safe, affordable foods essential to optimal health and well-being.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0FF46F8A03804540BA990A3F0705CBB5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Data collection and sharing</header><text>Section 9 of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2018">7 U.S.C. 2018</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6ECB9C6957B84B4EA1421E6EA2BBA5C4"><subsection id="H1C9C9C2800C241C2A3CA0C1D8312AA9D"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Store-Level data collection and sharing</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H778A144E92334D2EB656496528A03C57"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall collect the data described in paragraph (2) from a sufficient number of retail food stores approved for participation in the supplemental nutrition assistance program that utilize an integrated electronic cash register system to enable the Secretary to provide State- and nationally-representative data in the reports required under section 31. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E00E34E4AAA4C579354A443ED7484D3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Data described</header><text>The data referred to in paragraph (1) is store-level point-of-sale data that identifies the specific food items acquired at a retail food store by eligible households using benefits. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H098CC0F772D14090A3E380D8789B21D0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Paperwork Reduction Act</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/35">Chapter 35</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Paperwork Reduction Act</quote>), shall not apply to this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H20961394C7874AE2AAE21D0B6A7DA9CD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>State reports under nutrition education and obesity prevention grant program</header><text>Section 28(c)(9) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2036a">7 U.S.C. 2036a(c)(8)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC76E893B59934B54B68E6A99706E4381"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)(ii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56589EBEFB8744AE8D1DFF32BDC35352"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03AC9DB4A041492D9C55F1A8CFAD6EFF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD5845588E7D94A06B821043A503214BB"><subparagraph id="H13E178B0AA8E4DC3AAC22F1A881A0788"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a description of actions taken by the State to enhance the food security and nutrition security of participants in the supplemental nutrition assistance program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34FEF8AD1C744BF893B350DE16002A64"><enum>(F)</enum><text>recommendations, if applicable, regarding administering the supplemental nutrition assistance program in a manner that would enhance food security and nutrition security in the State.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE51CD83B36D4002A394206C894A00FE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Food and nutrition security</header><text>The Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2011">7 U.S.C. 2011 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEFD7BA56A90C4094AB5B1E7C611FE3F8"><section id="HE03F9C1488834AD99211EA687A71C567"><enum>31.</enum><header>Food and nutrition security report; food sales report</header><subsection id="H2ADC9F113D7746BDA643C4813498BF11"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Food and nutrition security report</header><paragraph id="H3E7795CC122141FA875605B4AC6DAC26"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate and the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives a report on food security and nutrition security in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51BA84F1133545839CE66BBA1A72D117"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>A report submitted under paragraph (1) shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H013C31D418354986915D6336E3873234"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an analysis of the food security, nutrition security, and diet quality of participants and nonparticipants in the supplemental nutrition assistance program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF56C79C362344B1E9AF61F03BFF60CB9"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD8E3B11164B940CE98332B4DA23B2441"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a summary of changes made to the supplemental nutrition assistance program in the year covered by the report that are intended to improve food security, nutrition security, and diet quality; and</text></clause><clause id="H2EF7275983AD4701834EAC95BAA3E580" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an analysis of the impact and effectiveness of those changes on food security, nutrition security, and diet quality; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF84094BD06C48E2A70C078C4493DCCB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recommendations for additional authority to the Secretary to improve food security, nutrition security, and diet quality for participants in the supplemental nutrition assistance program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D6CF45812AE454A9B8D0AD9CDCB4166"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Food sales report</header><paragraph id="HD20DC475AF5349F094885F778E7DE466"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than September 30, 2025, and at least once every 4 years thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate and the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives, and make publicly available on the website of the Department of Agriculture, a report on food sales in the supplemental nutrition assistance program, including an analysis of the specific food items acquired with benefits by eligible households.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8164EE8FC7E4E6E8BA970F2DEFE225C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Data</header><text>A report under paragraph (1) shall use store-level data collected pursuant to section 9(k).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3739C80CBAB4D59B90F672448A2EAA9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Privacy</header><text>For each report under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall aggregate or deidentify data in a manner sufficient to ensure that the identity of participants or retailers associated with the data cannot be ascertained.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

