<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H84E0B2B89B7E41B4A5A87CC80D7DCD5F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3224 IH: Countering Weapons of Mass Destruction Extension Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3224</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to extend the authorization of the Countering Weapons of Mass Destruction Office of the Department of Homeland Security, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1D31D035E18A4C469E9353DDFF0E042A" style="OLC"><section id="H3F392A4F344B4E68A525CE880FCA0B5A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Countering Weapons of Mass Destruction Extension Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H5C841347DBF1443795EAFE10FA68AC15"><enum>2.</enum><header>Extension of authorization of the Countering Weapons of Mass Destruction Office of the Department of Homeland Security</header><subsection id="H81C90C0C44134005993E8C57681C381B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Extension</header><paragraph id="H5D7BD304F0A949BBA5369D8A91FA93A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (e) of section 1901 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/591">6 U.S.C. 591</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>5 years after the date of the enactment of the Countering Weapons of Mass Destruction Act of 2018</quote> and inserting <quote>seven years after the date of the enactment of the Countering Weapons of Mass Destruction Extension Act of 2023</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5BFADA97402474B929A1059CEA84A31"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to sections 1931 and 1932 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (6 U.S.C. 597 and 597a; relating to the Chief Medical Officer and the medical countermeasures program of the Department of Homeland Security).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HABB30D15508D45B4824FF0B3E3B42899"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Organizational accountability</header><paragraph id="H21ABD15D80D44965801926098E62C894"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Employee morale</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary for the Countering Weapons of Mass Destruction Office of the Department of Homeland Security shall submit a report to and brief the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate regarding an employee engagement action plan and strategy to continuously improve morale within the Office.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5CE6C755BD96487F8B98C8B33D303461"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Comptroller General</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a review of and brief the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate regarding the following with respect to the Countering Weapons of Mass Destruction Office of the Department of Homeland Security:</text><subparagraph id="H1A76CCEF1B33477287CF3B02832AAEE2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The efforts of the Office to prioritize the programs and activities that carry out the mission of the Office, including research and development.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA80CF16EE980484BAE39D944F4FC305A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The consistency and effectiveness of the Office’s stakeholder coordination across the mission of the Department, including operational and support components of the Department and State and local entities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEEAACC4BE244AFFB226AA59F73043C8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The efforts of the Office to manage and coordinate the lifecycle of research and development within the Office and with other components of the Department, including the Science and Technology Directorate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

