<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF2FDDB2ECBE34D38B1ACE4CFE1C7EB6F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4417 IH: Ending Agricultural Trade Suppression Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4417</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230630">June 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000603">Mr. Rouzer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000546">Mr. Graves of Missouri</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000388">Mr. Kelly of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000474">Mr. Flood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000470">Mrs. Fischbach</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prevent States and local jurisdictions from interfering with the production and distribution of agricultural products in interstate commerce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB9936AC559C64513895D7A311C561EDE" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H129A1FD154F0460589368DFA3A94DD33"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ending Agricultural Trade Suppression Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H48AF504DF0514ACEAB2AE28BF651AAD8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition against interference by State and local governments with production of items in other States</header> <subsection id="H4D3E072EA2F043F78CA0DF25FEE2BD5E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of agricultural products</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>agricultural products</term> has the meaning given the term in section 207 of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1626">7 U.S.C. 1626</external-xref>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H58ED338A29EB490F99D0E34240687D5E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The government of a State or a unit of local government within a State shall not impose a standard or condition on the preharvest production of any agricultural products sold or offered for sale in interstate commerce if—</text> <paragraph id="H7B6D84701FF34D3687F53BBD12C41C54"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the production occurs in another State; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H950C9435B10F4E89A126204706BAB987"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the standard or condition is in addition to the standards and conditions applicable to the production pursuant to—</text> <subparagraph id="H31A3576CCEE1414785EAE17F1DFF6DCE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Federal law; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF9D44BC21E9F43D4BDAF7216AC9C5415"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the laws of the State and unit of local government in which the production occurs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8AB930BBD5A74E0D954A0E6F525FA518"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>If no standards or conditions are applicable to the production of an agricultural product pursuant to Federal law, or the laws of a State or unit of local government in which the production occurs, that lack of standards and conditions shall be deemed to be the standards and conditions applicable to the production of the agricultural product for purposes of subsection (b)(2).</text></subsection></section> 
<section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HF94E7B381C3B445AAC011EEDB4529187"><enum>3.</enum><header>Federal cause of action to challenge State regulation of interstate commerce</header> 
<subsection id="HEC04885D5ACD4CFF8D3EB7D647F03930"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of agricultural products</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>agricultural products</term> has the meaning given the term in section 207 of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1626">7 U.S.C. 1626</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H0B172D7505814D33BAD9374AAAA650BF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Private right of action</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person, including a producer, a transporter, a distributer, a consumer, a laborer, a trade association, the Federal Government, a State government, or a unit of local government, that is affected by a regulation of a State or unit of local government that regulates any aspect of 1 or more agricultural products that are sold in interstate commerce, including any aspect of the method of production, or any means or instrumentality through which 1 or more agricultural products are sold in interstate commerce may bring an action in the appropriate court to invalidate that regulation and seek damages for economic loss resulting from that regulation.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5312358F7D194D199527A97CF4D0C2E8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Preliminary injunction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On a motion of the plaintiff in an action brought under subsection (b), the court shall issue a preliminary injunction to preclude the applicable State or unit of local government from enforcing the regulation at issue until such time as the court enters a final judgment in the case, unless the State or unit of local government proves by clear and convincing evidence that—</text> <paragraph id="H99709DF4839E4F7F85D1DEDC399F9CBB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the State or unit of local government is likely to prevail on the merits at trial; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H32C65BABFF364FCBB269DD9AC907F57E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the injunction would cause irreparable harm to the State or unit of local government.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H42F9ECB770CC463296F4C2DFAAFA289C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Statute of limitations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No action shall be maintained under this section unless the action is commenced not later than 10 years after the cause of action arose.</text></subsection> 
<subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H112FE8E55DD04ED9861D5B9058089C46"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>A person described in subsection (b) may bring an action under that subsection in—</text> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H1A05BBA5A02E4296AF799E58D6719DC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the district court of the United States for the judicial district in which the person—</text> 
<subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H883E41FA098E479FBAFEF74CA5682C58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is affected by a regulation described in that subsection; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H6C80647EF546446B957A3485D2B6A502"><enum>(B)</enum><text>resides, operates, or does business; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H707EA1D591D5409482AC34F36098F3D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other appropriate court otherwise having jurisdiction.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

