<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9CAE241B008B426AA1E6BC845257E8D1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3916 IH: Screening for Communities to Receive Early and Equitable Needed Services for Cancer Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3916</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230607">June 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to reauthorize and improve the National Breast and Cervical Cancer Early Detection Program for fiscal years 2024 through 2028, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC4964F57815840B986DE92FDB19C1AED" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H86015181E8104C1FB76471EC9F4BA399"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Screening for Communities to Receive Early and Equitable Needed Services for Cancer Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SCREENS for Cancer Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H06FD64C38DAE4E8192A24A67C66D1291"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HFA9E046AFCFE4554AA94D9A564FF7B25"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In 2023, there will be more than 300,590 new cases of invasive breast cancer and nearly 44,000 breast cancer deaths in the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF5A322ACC151445D8D295030CDC0AD08"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In 2023, there will be about 13,960 new cases of invasive cervical cancer and about 4,310 deaths from cervical cancer.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD3C35C25277D4D69B1D7BB96E0CA38B3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Black women have the highest breast, cervical, and uterine cancer death rates of all racial and ethnic groups and are more likely to be diagnosed with triple-negative breast cancer, a more aggressive form of cancer.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H821EC8223711424B9018B55AD2289964"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Research shows that the COVID–19 pandemic was associated with a decline of more than 3,900,000 breast cancer screenings in 2020, as compared to 2019. Similarly, cervical cancer screening utilization dropped by 90 percent in April 2020, relative to the prior year.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB96A9C26767246F7AB0D005E5878BFC7" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Research suggests that those postponed breast screenings appeared to disproportionately affect women of color: Non-Hispanic White women had 17 percent fewer breast cancer diagnoses, while the year-over-year decline was 53 percent for Asian women, 43 percent for Hispanic women, and 27 percent for Black women.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H430E15AF27404C37ACF464D3D575C546"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The National Cancer Institute estimates that pandemic-related disruptions or delays in breast care and screening are expected to result in an excess of 2,500 breast cancer deaths by 2030.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H631D1297DC404C02987FB66082BF38A8"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Since its creation in 1991, the National Breast and Cervical Cancer Early Detection Program (referred to in this section as the <term>NBCCEDP</term>) has provided lifesaving cancer screening and diagnostic services to low-income, uninsured, or underinsured women in all 50 States, the District of Columbia, 6 territories, and 13 Tribes or Tribal organizations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE2CC39D4E2EC4F03A5856DB18802EDDC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>NBCCEDP seeks to reduce inequities in breast and cervical cancer screening and diagnosis, placing special emphasis on outreach to women who are members of racial or ethnic minority groups, and those who are geographically or culturally isolated.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBCD44B0928E3496DAFFCD6B681422BB8"><enum>(9)</enum><text>NBCCEDP has served more than 6,100,000 people and provided more than 15,700,000 breast and cervical cancer screening examinations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H137A20BC2DA442BFBB2FFDCD3CD7650E"><enum>(10)</enum><text>These screening exams have diagnosed nearly 76,000 invasive breast cancers and more than 24,000 premalignant breast lesions, as well as more than 5,100 invasive cervical cancers and 235,000 premalignant cervical lesions, of which 39 percent were high-grade.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4E5C559BE14D4A7881CEAEFC748F97FB"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The program also provides public education, outreach, patient navigation, and care coordination to increase breast and cervical cancer screening rates and reach underserved populations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA667A2C2AA934AE7AFA9EC9AACC32DC4"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Reauthorizing NBCCEDP will result in expanded services, leading to more people being screened and more cancers diagnosed at earlier stages. </text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H6981CA0A9FA34F39AAD52A1D1DEE1347"><enum>3.</enum><header>National Breast and Cervical Cancer Early Detection Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title XV of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300k">42 U.S.C. 300k et seq.</external-xref>) is amended— </text> <paragraph id="HF93BD67584CB40CF875D698933314BD9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 1501 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300k">42 U.S.C. 300k</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H38C9764F61C94B25A060443B75BC71EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <clause id="HE6A03C8FE2F3406398402C5628540F64"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>the provision of appropriate follow-up services and support services such as case management</quote> and inserting <quote>that appropriate follow-up services are provided</quote>;</text></clause>
<clause id="HF2FC1AD73E6349FD96F9B0433655AEA8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>programs for the detection and control</quote> and inserting <quote>for the prevention, detection, and control</quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H59E70DBBEBA34AAC8CCFD4E4029525B3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>the detection and control</quote> and inserting <quote>the prevention, detection, and control</quote>;</text></clause>
<clause id="H18AA2955565B4773B5C150E5A378A9C8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)—</text> <subclause id="H9866A88E945448F3BBF9ADB033F5B3FD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>monitor</quote> and inserting <quote>ensure</quote>; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H8F16D1A328684B7FB4462B17D33CB8C6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HDB06E992FB0D4794AB7A483DAD68A67B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (6) as paragraph (9); </text></clause>
<clause id="H965B55F1A6B34C7BAF82E537870B97AC"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (5), the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6D6E3B1E70C3404B9A008904790CA4FE"> <paragraph id="HA13DB30893064114A380C5E3667CAF5A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to enhance appropriate support activities to increase breast and cervical cancer screening such as patient navigation, implementation of evidence-based or evidence-informed strategies proven to increase breast and cervical cancer screening in health care settings, and facilitating access to health care settings; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H27EE0416FBC34C2C83192057C4EC33EB"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to reduce disparities in incidents of and deaths due to breast and cervical cancer in populations with higher than average rates; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67BABF1D9C544226B16FB4CDC29C6D87"><enum>(8)</enum><text>to ensure equitable access to screening and diagnostic services and improve access for individuals who encounter additional barriers to receiving services, including due to various social determinants of health; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause>
<clause id="HEBF13DE1F6724A82965A7A820A47ACBC"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>through (5)</quote> and inserting <quote>through (8)</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HA376D199992C4CFDA43A449EC979961F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subsection (d);</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6B24878081AD4FE89E550E99D6E55DCE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 1503 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300m">42 U.S.C. 300m</external-xref>)—</text> <subparagraph id="HA1C6A7D30B8E4D12B04CFC447ACF25B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text>
<clause id="H8423D250B28C4C18A59B11362F981718"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>that, initially</quote> and all that follows through the semicolon and inserting <quote>that appropriate breast and cervical cancer screening and diagnostic services are provided based on national recommendations; and</quote>;</text></clause> <clause id="H552DBD0D450B417097B2E1A56EF0D676"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking paragraphs (2) and (4);</text></clause>
<clause id="H9F5D935F3B7C4E6982C2E21C9569368F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (2); and</text></clause> <clause id="HB0187C973D2C44869F737C47FDF2C819"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a period; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6C3109AFCAAC47558F9E840D0358818E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subsection (d);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H43143A273CB943C397356A22E68DC3CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 1508(b) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300n-4">42 U.S.C. 300n–4(b)</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HEEE80FAACB62492F983086231ACBAFCC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>1 year after the date of the enactment of the National Breast and Cervical Cancer Early Detection Program Reauthorization of 2007, and annually thereafter,</quote> and inserting <quote>2 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Screening for Communities to Receive Early and Equitable Needed Services for Cancer Act of 2023</short-title>, and every 5 years thereafter,</quote>; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5FE6486B74B142F2BDD8995AC020D848"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Labor and Human Resources</quote> and inserting <quote>Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions</quote>; and </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC0A9374BCDC647C2840D4C2C07A45B97"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>preceding fiscal year</quote> and inserting <quote>preceding 2 fiscal years in the case of the first report after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Screening for Communities to Receive Early and Equitable Needed Services for Cancer Act of 2023</short-title> and preceding 5 fiscal years for each report thereafter</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE792FDEA1ED145FF8359BD493A6A5D3B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 1510(a) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300n-5">42 U.S.C. 300n–5(a)</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H92A03181BAA54A9483BFB14CCAF37593"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> after <quote>2011,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA53E67923B844D9A25315CA82169B53"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, $275,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, $330,000,000 for fiscal year 2025, $385,000,000 for fiscal year 2026, $440,000,000 for fiscal year 2027, and $500,000,000 for fiscal year 2028</quote> before the period at the end.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

