<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE21FE7D958494246A08D68C6C2681E37" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 597 IH: Stop the Cartels Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 597</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230127">January 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001118">Mr. Cline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000377">Ms. Granger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001054">Mr. Carl</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000235">Mr. Ezell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000603">Mr. Rouzer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence (Permanent Select)</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve the collection of intelligence regarding activities by drug trafficking organizations in certain foreign countries.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H583EC2E22BC4428CBAD1E9D80EA74E96" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA3F42E8497E8402E9F31D03F797C2468" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> 
<subsection id="HF38E8161034B45938B384FB9976F426B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop the Cartels Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H55E9E92FEB494BDD9D39E9B50CDAF691"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"> 
<toc-entry idref="HA3F42E8497E8402E9F31D03F797C2468" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H97C3DEF4761642A09E23D9EB35A8A56B" level="title">Title I—Prioritizing Intelligence Gathering on Drug Trafficking Organizations </toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H0EB56234D10049538C2A5B9D6535D290" level="section">Sec. 101. Assessment of activities by drug trafficking organizations in covered foreign countries.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE6DE5A6D4E9F4CBC910902CA6334FF73" level="section">Sec. 102. Assessment of human trafficking and smuggling from covered foreign countries to the United States-Mexico border.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H87CE5A94570A414C8E090F3269B54886" level="section">Sec. 103. Prioritization of intelligence resources for covered foreign countries.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H81F294A95A024E758DFE6CA19407A2F1" level="section">Sec. 104. Resolving intelligence sharing and cooperation agreements.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H1565A7A8C27544C8B758B50FFC39DC13" level="section">Sec. 105. Review of Mexico and United States bilateral cooperation.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H52DDDF01A5E5444D97DF94598462902D" level="section">Sec. 106. Designation of certain drug cartels as Special Transnational Criminal Organization.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H27E13E5930C14C3D856B06B87AC7B84B" level="section">Sec. 107. Monthly Department of Homeland Security reports on migrants.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE4E6FFA802A44719B156102CD12F0F60" level="section">Sec. 108. Definitions.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HCE4007EADAD74076B35F8C88A13867A8" level="title">Title II—Eliminating Funding for Cartel Safe Harbor Jurisdictions</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H9CD5695C4B1B4857804CF683B526857C" level="section">Sec. 201. Ineligibility for Federal grants of certain jurisdictions that violate the immigration laws.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HD4A5041868614196A88A3FF7958C87F0" level="title">Title III—Targeting Cartel Human Trafficking at the Border</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HE08C7B23496C447EA76F6E49C37CF1AB" level="section">Sec. 301. Ending family separation and protection of minors.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H04D4F1B6656049E5BDF6E842D11707E6" level="section">Sec. 302. Stopping asylum fraud.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H75A099CFFF5844A189A6EC1B93EB7310" level="section">Sec. 303. Hiring authority.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H78A57103B0974B048EFF9B2C674A4F6E" level="section">Sec. 304. Refugee application and processing centers.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H638D9E0F398A47219DF749D5AAA20B68" level="title">Title IV—Repurposing Federal Drug Programs</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="H35F47FF64B304036A729E6D556C5A794" level="section">Sec. 401. Reauthorization of block grants for prevention and treatment of substance abuse.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry idref="HF147321C7BB04D89AC4153B5E465C031" level="section">Sec. 402. Offsetting repeals.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section> 
<title id="H97C3DEF4761642A09E23D9EB35A8A56B"><enum>I</enum><header>Prioritizing Intelligence Gathering on Drug Trafficking Organizations </header> 
<section id="H0EB56234D10049538C2A5B9D6535D290"><enum>101.</enum><header>Assessment of activities by drug trafficking organizations in covered foreign countries</header> 
<subsection id="H028846DD9BA04FB5B7C46F6F888DB032"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of National Intelligence, in coordination with the Chief of Intelligence of the Drug Enforcement Administration and the Assistant Secretary of State for Intelligence and Research, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report containing an analytical assessment of the activities of drug trafficking organizations in covered foreign countries. Such assessment shall include, at a minimum—</text> <paragraph id="H25AB3B62F95146A097900C30BC1C4EF3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an assessment of the effect of drug trafficking organizations on the security and economic situation in covered foreign countries;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDE343DC8006145CD808AE8E91F4C48F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an assessment of the effect of the activities of drug trafficking organizations on the migration of persons from covered foreign countries to the United States-Mexico border;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H201A800CE32E4067A6471117316F796D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a summary of any relevant activities by elements of the intelligence community in relation to drug trafficking organizations in covered foreign countries and Mexico;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB27C5EA23DB549B48CAA12743C80D458"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a summary of key methods and routes used by drug trafficking organizations in covered foreign countries and Mexico to the United States;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA62F7922C2E84739B374FB18B719420E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an assessment of the intersection between the activities of drug trafficking organizations, human traffickers and human smugglers, and other organized criminal groups in covered foreign countries; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H46824E29724F42A3A35D9FBB535DC087"><enum>(6)</enum><text>an assessment of the illicit funds and financial transactions that support the activities of drug trafficking organizations and connected criminal enterprises in covered foreign countries.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H052B0C2B3EDC4CD3B698F7F41ED15361"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) may be submitted in classified form, but if so submitted, shall contain an unclassified summary.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAFA077A9E89840798C8B6C59C9E0DD28"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>The report under subsection (a), or the unclassified summary of the report described in subsection (b), shall be made publicly available.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HE6DE5A6D4E9F4CBC910902CA6334FF73"><enum>102.</enum><header>Assessment of human trafficking and smuggling from covered foreign countries to the United States-Mexico border</header> <subsection id="H92706DD8A95C4B89847C9D2C78C1E0D4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of National Intelligence, in coordination with the Under Secretary of Homeland Security for Intelligence and Analysis and the Assistant Secretary of State for Intelligence and Research, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report containing an analytical assessment of human trafficking and human smuggling by individuals and organizations in covered foreign countries. Such assessment shall include, at a minimum—</text> 
<paragraph id="H393C576C8A2E4392B3B2CFEC04FADA99"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an assessment of the effect of human trafficking and human smuggling on the security and economic situation in covered foreign countries;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB813F26ED3E3428B894C79B2112D424F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a summary of any relevant activities by elements of the intelligence community in relation to human trafficking and human smuggling in covered foreign countries;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE47EDB3E98B4812B5BD2CBE260D28F4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an assessment of the methods and routes used by human traffickers and human smuggler organizations to move persons from covered foreign countries to the United States-Mexico border;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB206400FBC2841B19C1BB955BC560B86"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an assessment of the intersection between the activities of human traffickers and human smugglers, drug trafficking organizations, and other organized criminal groups in covered foreign countries; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H725768293975479C914CA8E6851BF7EE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>an assessment of the illicit funds and financial transactions that support the activities of human traffickers and human smugglers and connected criminal enterprises in covered foreign countries.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8FBA5C31D23147498B24E871206024C1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) may be submitted in classified form, but if so submitted, shall contain an unclassified summary.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4392901D7E0D48A8BC94BB1A7AAC072B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>The report under subsection (a), or the unclassified summary of the report described in subsection (b), shall be made publicly available.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H87CE5A94570A414C8E090F3269B54886"><enum>103.</enum><header>Prioritization of intelligence resources for covered foreign countries</header> <subsection id="HCC59575C49E34B3BB25E3D2A94572AA6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review of Intelligence Community Efforts in covered foreign countries</header><text>The Director of National Intelligence, in coordination with the Under Secretary of Homeland Security for Intelligence and Analysis, the Assistant Secretary of State for Intelligence and Research, the Chief of Intelligence of the Drug Enforcement Administration, and other appropriate officials in the intelligence community, shall carry out a comprehensive review of the current intelligence collection priorities of the intelligence community for covered foreign countries in order to identify whether such priorities are appropriate and sufficient in light of the threat posed by the activities of drug trafficking organizations and human traffickers and human smugglers to the security of the United States and the Western Hemisphere.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7EC813ECECA147B09F5A0D34DA6D1649"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header> 
<paragraph id="HB27936DC4C0942E1829127018D95DA6A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report on initial review</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of National Intelligence shall submit to the congressional intelligence committees a comprehensive description of the results of the review required by subsection (a), including whether the priorities described in that subsection are appropriate and sufficient in light of the threat posed by the activities of drug trafficking organizations and human traffickers and human smugglers to the security of the United States and the Western Hemisphere. If the report concludes that such priorities are not so appropriate and sufficient, the report shall also include a description of the actions to be taken to modify such priorities in order to assure that such priorities are so appropriate and sufficient.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5FCE78EC8DFD44EA915C96E9FD3519C7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Quarterly reports</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date on which the report under paragraph (1) is submitted, and every 90 days thereafter for a 5-year period, the Director of National Intelligence shall submit to the congressional intelligence committees a report on the intelligence community’s collection priorities and activities in covered foreign countries with a focus on the threat posed by the activities of drug trafficking organizations and human traffickers and human smugglers to the security of the United States and the Western Hemisphere. The first report under this paragraph shall also include a description of the amount of funds expended by the intelligence community to the efforts described in subsection (a) during each of fiscal years 2021 and 2022.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5DE6E989674544CAA5E4D86815B64336"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The reports required by subsection (b) may be submitted in classified form, but if so submitted, shall contain an unclassified summary.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H81F294A95A024E758DFE6CA19407A2F1" commented="no"><enum>104.</enum><header>Resolving intelligence sharing and cooperation agreements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">None of the amounts appropriated to the Department of State to combat the threats of drug trafficking, transnational organized crime, and money laundering or appropriated to the United States Agency for International Development may be made available to the Mexican federal government or its subsidiaries until the Secretary of State certifies to Congress that Mexico has removed all barriers to bilateral cooperation created after December 2020 that have hindered law enforcement cooperation and intelligence-sharing between United States and Mexican law enforcement agencies, including the implementation of the Foreign Agents law and the limits that have been placed on issuing visas to United States law enforcement personnel.</text></section> 
<section id="H1565A7A8C27544C8B758B50FFC39DC13" commented="no"><enum>105.</enum><header>Review of Mexico and United States bilateral cooperation</header> 
<subsection id="H5053BCC619394DFA8088FAA1A6BB5BF7" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Plan To reestablish bilateral security meetings</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a plan and timeline to reestablish regular bilateral security meetings between appropriate high-level and working-level officials of the Governments of the United States and Mexico that serve as a forum to align and reconcile priorities between the United States and Mexico and to periodically assess progress for bilateral cooperation. The plan shall include possible areas of cooperation at the Federal, State, and local levels with United States goals for assistance.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3D1AC5F6FDF440ADB90DC876D47ADF10" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Comprehensive review</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State and the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, in consultation with the heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, shall submit a report to appropriate congressional committees that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2913A81A10AE410E80BBE6F7302C8C98" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provides a review of programs, projects, and activities implemented as part of either the Merida Initiative or The Bicentennial Framework; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF39C23FDCBC14CDAAD524DB91B9104A8" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H434298B5685445E7A8324B4CB9FF6924" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>evaluations, assessments, or other analyses, as appropriate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H612DD8027EED49D8B3A538F1C58E74BA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>successes, challenges, and lessons learned in achieving program outcomes and United States policy goals;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA581C2E1A44F49AF95A36EB096123968" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recommendations to change investment levels in specific projects; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H93ED8D55EF7F4A7C8A86DDDDF19097DD" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, an assessment of the effect, if any, of Mexico’s Foreign Agents law on bilateral security cooperation with the Department of State, the United States Agency for International Development, and the Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H52DDDF01A5E5444D97DF94598462902D" commented="no"><enum>106.</enum><header>Designation of certain drug cartels as Special Transnational Criminal Organization</header> 
<subsection id="H43024BE152EC4C17B6DCF385B2A8657E" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header> 
<paragraph id="H8AC966B49AD9482D9961C86E66367230" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In General</header><text>The Secretary is authorized to designate an organization as a foreign Special Transnational Criminal Organization in accordance with this subsection if the Secretary finds that—</text> <subparagraph id="H6EB5A47ED4494543B48015E2EB8E9EC7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the organization is a foreign organization;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE4BC6FC561144B31B02D81D523336228" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the organization is a self-perpetuating association of individuals who operate transnationally for the purpose of obtaining power, influence, monetary, or commercial gains, wholly or in part by illegal means, while protecting their activities through a pattern of corruption or violence or through a transnational organization structure and the exploitation of transnational commerce or communication mechanisms; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H75756AFF0A1847D1A82517FCB0526BEA" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the organization threatens the security of United States nationals or the national security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H79B3DE78F14A497D83033C1369C37A30" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Procedure</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA072727030BE449FB4752A1C8CF03205" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Notice</header> 
<clause id="HBCC56B2D1365455D9B4E0C36FC9E2F10" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>To congressional leaders</header><text>Seven days before making a designation under this subsection, the Secretary shall, by classified communication, notify the Speaker and minority leader of the House of Representatives, the President pro tempore, majority leader, and minority leader of the Senate, and the members of the relevant committees of the House of Representatives and the Senate, in writing, of the intent to designate an organization under this subsection, together with the findings made under paragraph (1) with respect to that organization, and the factual basis therefor.</text></clause> <clause id="H40A289805C274D5E86FBAA7DB11A1DBA" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Publication in federal register</header><text>The Secretary shall publish the designation in the Federal Register seven days after providing the notification under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3596F0CB49B24BD893D0FD37DBFB066E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effect of designation</header><text>For purposes of section 2339B of title 18, United States Code—</text> <clause id="H34BA130DF0ED4BE5AE20BB4205F2E9B2" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an organization designated as a foreign Special Transnational Criminal Organization shall be treated as an organization subject to such section for purposes of such section; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7034B6CCF5E94A678BEB442326AC5838" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a designation under this subsection shall take effect for such purposes upon publication under subparagraph (A)(ii).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2D149356ADA54B3095DBE2C788EF571A" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Freezing of assets</header><text>Upon notification under paragraph (2)(A)(i), the Secretary of the Treasury may require United States financial institutions possessing or controlling any assets of any foreign organization included in the notification to block all financial transactions involving those assets until further directive from either the Secretary of the Treasury, Act of Congress, or order of court.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H151EE81673884EB49FB61254A879642B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Record</header> 
<subparagraph id="H9A0B87261F7E481B964A3391CD13A275" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In making a designation under this subsection, the Secretary shall create an administrative record. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD268874002B046D1A2A36E3780F3330B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The Secretary may consider classified information in making a designation under this subsection. Classified information shall not be subject to disclosure for such time as it remains classified, except that such information may be disclosed to a court ex parte and in camera for purposes of judicial review under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD47DD394FE2D479FA7BEA7F7E205DE58" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Period of designation</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE3417ABE526E4C6A916CD76DA42D7A67" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A designation under this subsection shall be effective until revoked under paragraph (5) or (6) or set aside pursuant to subsection (c).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9C282DDCED7348D59F8EDEF71AE7FD1B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Review of designation upon petition</header> <clause id="H6812DD5AD2DD470DBFAA09E9F07B79DF" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall review the designation of a foreign Special Transnational Criminal Organization under the procedures set forth in clauses (iii) and (iv) if the designated organization files a petition for revocation within the petition period described in clause (ii).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7AAD533B0F74436E906F8986601106D6" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Petition period</header><text>For purposes of clause (i)—</text> <subclause id="H232E8FDF63F14279A7F78EFD8C25B952" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if the designated organization has not previously filed a petition for revocation under this subparagraph, the petition period begins 2 years after the date on which the designation was made; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H269C2838F39F4B7490D5B360B34FBED6" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if the designated organization has previously filed a petition for revocation under this subparagraph, the petition period begins 2 years after the date of the determination made under clause (iv) on that petition.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H96DBEAAE818145C58C0F9D525BAB938A" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>Any foreign Special Transnational Criminal Organization that submits a petition for revocation under this subparagraph must provide evidence in that petition that the relevant circumstances described in paragraph (1) are sufficiently different from the circumstances that were the basis for the designation such that a revocation with respect to the organization is warranted. </text></clause> 
<clause id="H72756B5EE86745D6820C5067A0CAD043" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Determination</header> 
<subclause id="H2D0EA60F9FE34925A221657DBAEB280F" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after receiving a petition for revocation submitted under this subparagraph, the Secretary shall make a determination as to such revocation.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H519835053A52430CA33C10DB894E4B9A" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The Secretary may consider classified information in making a determination in response to a petition for revocation. Classified information shall not be subject to disclosure for such time as it remains classified, except that such information may be disclosed to a court ex parte and in camera for purposes of judicial review under subsection (c).</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H09DE5B4AEDC048C99C4DFD39F2CD3EC3" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Publication of determination</header><text>A determination made by the Secretary under this clause shall be published in the Federal Register.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H7643E0EEE6084E32AAB6FAE9C3A97D9B" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>Any revocation by the Secretary shall be made in accordance with paragraph (6).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H14D3909B57C74E81803E0C0A2E4D0036" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Other review of designation</header> 
<clause id="H39532772C2B24781B040D0AFC1E50531" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Secretary determines that a 5-year period has elasped since the designation without a review having taken place under subparagraph (B), the Secretary shall review the designation of the foreign Special Transnational Criminal Organization in order to determine whether such designation should be revoked pursuant to paragraph (6).</text></clause> <clause id="H29CBDC5DB09948B0B1331AE03A28E4C0" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>If a review does not take place pursuant to subparagraph (B) in response to a petition for revocation that is filed in accordance with that subparagraph, then the review shall be conducted pursuant to procedures established by the Secretary. The results of such review and the applicable procedures shall not be reviewable in any court.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H62AA05D095174BB9B2F706D6F500A5D6" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Publication of results of review</header><text>The Secretary shall publish any determination made pursuant to this subparagraph in the Federal Register.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8B7EFA068383468384BDF10C5539DA00" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Revocation by act of congress</header><text>The Congress, by an Act of Congress, may block or revoke a designation made under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E540C0F2B38442DA31038FC1FB130F1" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Revocation based on change in circumstances</header> 
<subparagraph id="HCCFC4DE483294A9DBA58E731392245EC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may revoke a designation made under paragraph (1) at any time, and shall revoke a designation upon completion of a review conducted pursuant to subparagraphs (B) and (C) of paragraph (4) if the Secretary finds that—</text> <clause id="H3F6936EDC3AE499F94438FDEB0B00BBC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the circumstances that were the basis for the designation have changed in such a manner as to warrant revocation; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7CB0192C6BE743439886B21DCC35A3C4" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the national security of the United States warrants a revocation.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC43B256B65684AD889EEFBC513D291E9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>The procedural requirements of paragraphs (2) and (3) shall apply to a revocation under this paragraph. Any revocation shall take effect on the date specified in the revocation or upon publication in the Federal Register if no effective date is specified.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1C48CB287EC344AAAC013F0ECE0169CD" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Effect of revocation</header><text>The revocation of a designation under paragraph (5) or (6) shall not affect any action or proceeding based on conduct occurring prior to the effective date of such revocation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE8706DEA1744CC8B409FE8B300648B7" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Use of designation in trial or hearing</header><text>If a designation under this subsection has become effective under paragraph (2)(B) a defendant in a criminal action or an alien in a removal proceeding shall not be permitted to raise any question concerning the validity of the issuance of such designation as a defense or an objection at any trial or hearing. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA790A17CFBDB4A9C8D888A4B5F4C040B" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendments to a designation</header> 
<paragraph id="H3B9192DC19874C42A674D6D4AAAE692C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may amend a designation under this subsection if the Secretary finds that the organization has changed its name, adopted a new alias, dissolved and then reconstituted itself under a different name or names, or merged with another organization.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDC13317B962F4069B0CE6D6849A1759E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>Amendments made to a designation in accordance with paragraph (1) shall be effective upon publication in the Federal Register. Subparagraphs (B) and (C) of subsection (a)(2) shall apply to an amended designation upon such publication. Paragraphs (2)(A)(i), (4), (5), (6), (7), and (8) of subsection (a) shall also apply to an amended designation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE0372DB2B3F491C9379CE29AEE79D72" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administrative record</header><text>The administrative record shall be corrected to include the amendments as well as any additional relevant information that supports those amendments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H007348D562544545A44807E586A8416E" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The Secretary may consider classified information in amending a designation in accordance with this subsection. Classified information shall not be subject to disclosure for such time as it remains classified, except that such information may be disclosed to a court ex parte and in camera for purposes of judicial review under subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3F8595489ACF402CA25D8F8DD401D692" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Judicial review of designation</header> 
<paragraph id="HB157A0FF3B4949D28B25351F0B7D965C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after publication in the Federal Register of a designation, an amended designation, or a determination in response to a petition for revocation, the designated organization may seek judicial review in the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7A626E517E6462895EE4E79A4C756BA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Basis of review</header><text>Review under this subsection shall be based solely upon the administrative record, except that the Government may submit, for ex parte and in camera review, classified information used in making the designation, amended designation, or determination in response to a petition for revocation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8B37F3CC3B7743AEBE660AD00D7EE939" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Scope of review</header><text>The Court shall hold unlawful and set aside a designation, amended designation, or determination in response to a petition for revocation the court finds to be—</text> <subparagraph id="H1839263A86F54420A074A5B0BB0BA406" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>arbitrary, capricious, an abuse of discretion, or otherwise not in accordance with law;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H00ECF6FC907642729CF70586ED378EE9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>contrary to constitutional right, power, privilege, or immunity;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8B826EA07A8E4893807888BC6A9CA075" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in excess of statutory jurisdiction, authority, or limitation, or short of statutory right;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFC5B3A25BAC0435596D1C1F8E0B1FD08" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>lacking substantial support in the administrative record taken as a whole or in classified information submitted to the court under paragraph (2); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDF4747839303426A9DCCEA15C0952D24" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>not in accord with the procedures required by law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC9ABEC55C5F14567BB8D4293FF945621" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Judicial review invoked</header><text>The pendency of an action for judicial review of a designation, amended designation, or determination in response to a petition for revocation shall not affect the application of this section, unless the court issues a final order setting aside the designation, amended designation, or determination in response to a petition for revocation. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5F30515AFC4E4571BDF8D63FFB902E11" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>As used in this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="HE7A433FF8147499FA7A6BFB5EAB3BFAC" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>classified information</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1(a) of the Classified Information Procedures Act (18 U.S.C. App.);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8F7EEF15BD8942A2B9137E2C30BA42D8" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>national security</term> means the national defense, foreign relations, or economic interests of the United States;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE1736C39586C404994C04BD6DE1882D6" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>foreign organization</term> includes a group of persons or an organization whose leadership is primarily based in a country outside of the United States;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D5CF8D24FC34B32B2064286CDA102D8" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>relevant committees</term> means the Committees on the Judiciary, Intelligence, and Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committees on the Judiciary, Intelligence, and International Relations of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H58DF1593AC7C4A0E9F3E831663560A5C" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of the Treasury and the Attorney General.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDA72A30DE7484225B9F570CA035A625F" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall designate the following organizations as Special Transnational Criminal Organizations:</text> 
<paragraph id="HCF5D1AA9017E4DBF92A590DB3CC8E142" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Sinaloa Cartel.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF92CC08E4BE4B5EA09E0DA0F86AD883" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Jalisco New Generation Cartel.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54C7C587C9644F428A2D83F64BDBE23D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Beltran-Leyva Organization.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB7552D556EE14ECA83822600E2FEFB51" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Cartel del Noreste and Los Zetas.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCDCB3CC838F54CD582332F07E526B59D" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Guerreros Unidos.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E27CA824D204956B8CC829803B3ACB4" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Gulf Cartel.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6FCC360CFBB14804B68CA4801EDBCA98" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Juarez Cartel and La Linea.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H600582A66815453CBA7F77AFAD3BE3DA" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>La Familia Michoacana.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC368F28812F44B26B2314DECEB31039F" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Los Rojos.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H27E13E5930C14C3D856B06B87AC7B84B"><enum>107.</enum><header>Monthly Department of Homeland Security reports on migrants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than the fifteenth day of the second full month after the date of the enactment of this Act and not later than the fifteenth day of each month thereafter, the Secretary of Homeland Security, acting through the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection (CBP), shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a report relating to migrants. Each such report shall cover the period of the immediately preceding month, and include information relating to the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD9085F2F4C78414C9C040BE23D71D430"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The total number of U.S. Border Patrol apprehensions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA3AA8A95453142718A40DB11C42A5BAC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The total number of inadmissible aliens encountered by the Office of Field Operations (OFO) of CBP.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0762806C80B9437BA49D130A7AF88877"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The total number of migrants (including apprehensions and inadmissibles under paragraphs (1) and (2), respectively) voluntarily returned to Mexico.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0465ACE2347E4D5C8B668B552CBFE4AE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The total number of migrants placed into expedited removal pursuant to section 235(b)(1) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE07360FA9D347C4BECAC3831B7DAE3B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The total number of migrants placed into expedited removal who claimed credible fear pursuant to section 235(b)(1)(A)(ii) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)(A)(ii)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01465B12B00D4B33B969501944AEEAF0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The total number of migrants placed into expedited removal who claimed credible fear pursuant to such section who received a positive determination relating thereto.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H868335DA9C2544189EA782006F493B95"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The total number of migrants who were detained by CBP.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3D5F2805CCF8417F96D5E0657EFFBB90"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The total number of migrants whose detention was transferred by CBP to U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE7117F868BE84376B6F67C417966ADBF"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The total number of migrants paroled into the United States pursuant to section 212(d)(5)(A) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(d)(5)(A)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE6A9A0E54658468A9AA544A496E73179"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The total number of migrants released on bond into the United States pursuant to section 236(a)(2)(A) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226(a)(2)(A)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H77E310FFB15E4923BB71038ACF1D0B31"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The total number of migrants released on their own recognizance into the United States pursuant to section 236(a)(2)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226(a)(2)(B)</external-xref>) or any other provision of such Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDBB9458681124B51B310D2DB847CD639"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The total number of migrants released on conditional parole into the United States pursuant to section 236(a)(2)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1226">8 U.S.C. 1226(a)(2)(B)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDDCAB19F42E745E7AE15306C05FB149E"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The total number of migrants released on any other ground, including specifications of which such grounds, into the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA01F8DF0932349EEB78362949162D2D2"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The total number of migrants issued a Notice to Appear.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H471B83B8DCF643D5A55879E59CCAE278"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The total number of migrants issued a Notice to Report.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB1A6ADE4F90447BB9703514784F5DAD9"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The total number of migrants released into the United States to appear at an ICE Field Office.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5C3075E420704606AAA57255A7DD2EFB"><enum>(17)</enum><text>The total number of migrants released into the United States to appear at an ICE Field Office who failed to appear.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13B24F478A6C4ECCB6C9C5080CCC96FF"><enum>(18)</enum><text>The total number of migrants released into the United States to check-in at an ICE Field Office, whose appearance was waived.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB811EBAB090143D68BE63227E07CB76A"><enum>(19)</enum><text>The total number of migrants issued a Notice to Appear who failed to appear at an Initial Master Calendar hearing.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4B76EFBD0B164DDFAF113851E6220982"><enum>(20)</enum><text>The total number of migrants issued a Notice to Appear who failed to appear at an initial Master Calendar hearing who were ordered removed from the United States.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HE4E6FFA802A44719B156102CD12F0F60"><enum>108.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title:</text> <paragraph id="HDDAA08C01F334CBB82F3F906760C0677"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H733928E9FC6048A19C10AE14DBB00C9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Homeland Security, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5117DFE77EC5489EB39F68AE43277EB5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1EB974BE59E741BDA4A0BC1DA58E0AC0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Congressional intelligence committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>congressional intelligence committees</term> means the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H707770F69A4E41AE981FA3B22F893D52"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered foreign countries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered foreign countries</term> means Mexico, Guatemala, Honduras, Nicaragua, El Salvador, Costa Rica, Panama, Belize, Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Ecuador, Guyana, Paraguay, Peru, Suriname, Uruguay, and Venezuela.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31FFAF8CBF66432CA555D72B954C5A50"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Human trafficking</header><text>The term <term>human trafficking</term> has the meaning given the term <term>severe forms of trafficking in persons</term> by section 103 of the Victims of Trafficking and Violence Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/7102">22 U.S.C. 7102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H487FB5EF0C284551AA84861A20D32201"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Intelligence community</header><text>The term <term>intelligence community</term> has the meaning given that term in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section></title> 
<title id="HCE4007EADAD74076B35F8C88A13867A8"><enum>II</enum><header>Eliminating Funding for Cartel Safe Harbor Jurisdictions</header> 
<section id="H9CD5695C4B1B4857804CF683B526857C"><enum>201.</enum><header>Ineligibility for Federal grants of certain jurisdictions that violate the immigration laws</header> 
<subsection id="H650A53F641D248C49AFF8190F6808590"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Ineligible jurisdictions</header><text>A State or unit of local government is an ineligible jurisdiction for purposes of this section if that State or unit of local government—</text> <paragraph id="H4C41C6B0C69D43969770FBA4FC3E0981"><enum>(1)</enum><text>violates section 642 of the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1373">8 U.S.C. 1373</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5580A9E25FDF4A90BBD3B9700F0FA8D8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>otherwise restricts compliance with a detainer issued by the Secretary of Homeland Security; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA91800DF0E694F71A9CB1BD22AE23FC4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>has any law or policy in effect that violates the immigration laws.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF87E67005CF7412F9847EA525880397E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual determination of ineligible jurisdictions</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall make a determination as to whether each State or unit of local government is an ineligible jurisdiction under subsection (a) and submit such determinations to Congress.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5E5C958C0A9C42059C53CAF2DA94C2A3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal financial assistance</header><text>A State or unit of local government that is determined to be an ineligible jurisdiction may not receive any Federal financial assistance (as such term is defined in section 7501(a)(5) of title 31, United States Code) for the fiscal year following any fiscal year in which the Secretary of Homeland Security determines that the State or unit of local government is an ineligible jurisdiction under subsection (b).</text></subsection></section></title> 
<title id="HD4A5041868614196A88A3FF7958C87F0"><enum>III</enum><header>Targeting Cartel Human Trafficking at the Border</header> 
<section id="HE08C7B23496C447EA76F6E49C37CF1AB"><enum>301.</enum><header>Ending family separation and protection of minors</header> 
<subsection id="HE6064E62868148728F12AD7275630B24"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Promoting family unity</header><text>Section 235 of the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1232">8 U.S.C. 1232</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H4BB3302009D84B36B5C111AABE6A330A" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H04DA25D5B18C47ADA73A1BF7D3E294F4"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Promoting family unity</header> <paragraph id="H0B5B1F41B606446993F8537FB3AE5B7A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Detention of alien minors</header> <subparagraph id="HBC81B5726C0840C8912F5786FE472F6D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, judicial determination, consent decree, or settlement agreement, the Secretary of Homeland Security may detain any alien minor (other than an unaccompanied alien child) who is inadmissible to the United States under section 212(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)</external-xref>) or removable from the United States under section 237(a) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1227">8 U.S.C. 1227(a)</external-xref>) pending the completion of removal proceedings, regardless of whether the alien minor was previously an unaccompanied alien child.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H376BF06A617D46309E28021B9F80F8E7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Priority removal cases</header><text>The Attorney General shall—</text> <clause id="H8433571F664C4918BF5540C084297986"><enum>(i)</enum><text>prioritize the removal proceedings of an alien minor, or a family unit that includes an alien minor, detained under subparagraph (A); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H64964C39257A4ED6806F055ED2908E25"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>set a case completion goal of not more than 100 days for such proceedings.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H04364297A41F4B379906B6101950575B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Detention and release decisions</header><text>The decision to detain or release an alien minor described in subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<clause id="H9C74FC1BC947415E9A419D299B022F1A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be governed solely by sections 212(d)(5), 217, 235, 236, and 241 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(d)(5)</external-xref>, 1187, 1225, 1226, and 1231) and implementing regulations or policies; and</text></clause> <clause id="H34E5AE7B00F2489DBE86D9780144D01F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not be governed by standards, requirements, restrictions, or procedures contained in a judicial decree or settlement relating to the authority to detain or release alien minors.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFF3BE6F3BB8A468C9AC280A9FE68C48C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conditions of detention</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE874138A4E9447268120D0661A9CE131"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, judicial determination, consent decree, or settlement agreement, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall determine, in the sole discretion of the Secretary, the conditions of detention applicable to an alien minor described in paragraph (1)(A) regardless of whether the alien minor was previously an unaccompanied alien child.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4D17911FF4614FE7AA92A135A7A8D9C9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No judicial review</header><text>A determination under subparagraph (A) shall not be subject to judicial review.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1307DEBC4CF14B0B9061A6A7D486CAE9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section—</text> <subparagraph id="H37006F0F9C7E41F3A6B32D8C29F4B925"><enum>(A)</enum><text>affects the eligibility for bond or parole of an alien; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3E96C6A6CEF44194BCC224341FE22A44"><enum>(B)</enum><text>limits the authority of a court to hear a claim arising under the Constitution of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H067BA28E70FE491787C05E74A60C9BAD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Preemption of state licensing requirements</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, judicial determination, consent decree, or settlement agreement, a State may not require an immigration detention facility used to detain families consisting of one or more children who have not attained 18 years of age and the parents or legal guardians of such children, that is located in the State, to be licensed by the State or any political subdivision thereof.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H63E50970187A4A61A92D6D0E9C39DBE5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Conditions of custody</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall ensure that each—</text> <subparagraph id="H14B499DA4CBA4DC3B35902C6071FD7FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>family residential facility is secure and safe; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC2B128FAC9764525B699FB90D71ECC96"><enum>(B)</enum><text>alien child and accompanying parent at a family residential facility has—</text> <clause id="HB9E16D88AD7B4E8899257CB6F792B3F2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>suitable living accommodations;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2EE013276E6D4C9C847F8BAD6FAF2872"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>access to drinking water and food;</text></clause> <clause id="HE232D94EFB4B47948D80176EF1648A22"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>timely access to medical assistance, including mental health assistance; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4C3B641CE6084FA6A6864C2FD43D95A2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>access to any other service necessary for the adequate care of a minor child.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9432A37E987C49EA934E96E44C02739E"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6B7325A53A984F65BA85B6550EC163D2"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Applicability of consent decrees, settlements, and judicial determinations</header> 
<paragraph id="HE62D7B4EEF494CF0ABD1E035E617464F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Flores settlement agreement inapplicable</header><text>Any conduct or activity that was, before the date of the enactment of this subsection, subject to any restriction or obligation imposed by the stipulated settlement agreement filed on January 17, 1997, in the United States District Court for the Central District of California in Flores v. Reno, CV 85–4544–RJK, (commonly known as the <quote>Flores settlement agreement</quote>), or imposed by any amendment of that agreement or judicial determination based on that agreement—</text> <subparagraph id="H9F653CF4D8D64F07B0D44FE6EBBF12DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall be subject to the restrictions and obligations in subsection (j) or imposed by the William Wilberforce Trafficking Victims Protection Reauthorization Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/457">Public Law 110–457</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4A502801391F40528E9A94818EBBA68D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not be subject to the restrictions and the obligations imposed by such settlement agreement or judicial determination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C792C4DAC354A64AB71D1337F2548C7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other settlement agreements or consent decrees</header><text>In any civil action with respect to the conditions of detention of alien children, the court shall not enter or approve a settlement agreement or consent decree unless it complies with the limitations set forth in subsection (j).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H04D4F1B6656049E5BDF6E842D11707E6" commented="no"><enum>302.</enum><header>Stopping asylum fraud</header> 
<subsection id="H1BCD6D0CFF42445FBBB84C458B69A05A" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Standards To deter fraud and advance meritorious asylum claims</header><text>Section 235(b)(1)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1225">8 U.S.C. 1225(b)(1)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HF2AA4F43CCFD49DD9BB01F86643B74A4" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending clause (v) to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4A9C6C936FE8417B94B547B14F837A47" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="HC51E8B0F7D1346498C71B0E1F9F64B86" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Credible fear of persecution</header> 
<subclause id="H7FC7877B2AF24459BBA684F86F6AA136" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>credible fear of persecution</term> means that it is more likely than not that the alien would be able to establish eligibility for asylum under section 208—</text> <item id="H6275DA22F5294194884C25D114D042AE" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>taking into account such facts as are known to the officer; and</text></item> 
<item id="HB85E2644E0BF4A1CB04774DBD5D779F2" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>only if the officer has determined, under subsection (b)(1)(B)(iii) of such section, that it is more likely than not that the statements made by the alien or on behalf of the alien are true.</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H8ACEEBCAC4564160986805C91D4D4CAC" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Bars to asylum</header><text>An alien shall not be determined to have a credible fear of persecution if the alien is prohibited from applying for or receiving asylum, including an alien subject to a limitation or condition under subsection (a)(2) or (b)(2) (including a regulation promulgated under such subsection) of section 208.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5368C7F7DB4343F2904D94FD5BDFFD6E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H0ED1AA6C18904B529B27D92AED29A69E" style="OLC"> <clause id="H623F2CCB1C5048198848B47F585327D1" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Eligibility for relief</header> <subclause id="HBB8FDCBEEC2A4EE19C07A6210FF800A2" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Credible fear review by immigration judge</header><text>An alien determined to have a credible fear of persecution shall be referred to an immigration judge for review of such determination, which shall be limited to a determination whether the alien—</text> 
<item id="H984C7F5EC0E84DBDB3FF87EEFBC9D74E" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is eligible for asylum under section 208, withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3), or protection under the Convention Against Torture and Other Cruel, Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment, done at New York, December 10, 1984 (referred to in this clause as the <quote>Convention Against Torture)</quote>; and</text></item> <item id="H22419199E05F45D08371635D5E5DF7C7" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>merits a grant of asylum in the exercise of discretion.</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H794A6CD72DD544588DA64AE80E2B09E5" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Aliens with reasonable fear of persecution</header> 
<item id="H33D781F4B5724788996492923CD36A58" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in item (bb), if an alien referred under subparagraph (A)(ii) is determined to have a reasonable fear of persecution or torture, the alien shall be eligible only for consideration of an application for withholding of removal under section 241(b)(3) or protection under the Convention Against Torture.</text></item> <item id="H21BEA82CE48F4841B6B4BB4E4A0A997B" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>An alien shall not be eligible for consideration of an application for relief under item (aa) if the failure of the alien to establish a credible fear of persecution precludes the alien from eligibility for such relief.</text></item> 
<item id="H20114B3180C84D599974149C3B430E06" commented="no"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An alien whose application for relief is adjudicated under item (aa) shall not be eligible for any other form of relief or protection from removal.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H93935D8CB4E24F39BBB497C2A377208C" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Ineligibility for removal proceedings</header><text>An alien referred under subparagraph (A)(ii) shall not be eligible for a hearing under section 240.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9F196FEA53A9434E9A4A4C6BB53AB3B4" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority for certain aliens To apply for asylum</header><text>Section 208(a)(2) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1158">8 U.S.C. 1158(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HBC829DD053B64C259A5C13021730F297" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HAC94EE86DB6844FC9AD0D6A64814ABAF" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Ineligibility for asylum</header> <clause id="HC9F55FF4A4294992BBC11BA7451F451D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, including paragraph (1), except as provided in clause (ii), an alien is ineligible for asylum if the alien—</text> 
<subclause id="HB6ABFCD32E8C4E49B9C4D648FCA59B64" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has been convicted of a felony;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HBC6B40BE50E44F2D858C9ADA3D6B14B6" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is inadmissible under section 212(a) (except paragraphs (4), (5), and (7));</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H6538BF92F9A34B3FA2C72E9B2DFBFD76" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>has been previously removed from the United States; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H71F0B964A1084170AAE4A59CCF6EB476" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>is a national or habitual resident of—</text> 
<item id="H2EC7063CE8CB41C08C319E78BBC300C6" commented="no"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a country in Central America that has a refugee application and processing center; or</text></item> <item id="H315E0B72617C4EF1B502FD05D4B1F8AE" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a country contiguous to such a country (other than Mexico).</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HED81538EEA774EE4AC0E90EA3460D395" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Notwithstanding clause (i), paragraph (1) shall not apply to any alien who is present in the United States on the date of the enactment of this subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H75A099CFFF5844A189A6EC1B93EB7310"><enum>303.</enum><header>Hiring authority</header> <subsection id="H91282CB903AD45F68A77F222A53D64CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Immigration judges</header><text>The Attorney General shall increase—</text> 
<paragraph id="H088720BAE76B449F9644E5E9BF030B87"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the number of immigration judges by not fewer than an additional 500 judges, as compared to the number of immigration judges as of the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H14DC6F16BE2D48F8AD958CFD595CB7A9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the corresponding number of support staff, as necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD9335CAA549F4D6ABBFB88A55F788707"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Immigration and customs enforcement attorneys</header><text>The Director of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement shall increase the number of attorneys and staff employed by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement by the number that is consistent with the workload staffing model to support the increase in immigration judges.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD5DE3C66E63A40EB8B5876058D0B8859"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for—</text> 
<paragraph id="HBEE48EB9D1DB4D00A1E14CC1B5B9AD53"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the hiring of immigration judges, support staff, and U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement attorneys under this section; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01B5D24A8F37418DA1460F0E82F61824"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the lease, purchase, or construction of facilities or equipment (including video teleconferencing equipment and equipment for electronic filing of immigration cases), and the transfer of federally owned temporary housing units to serve as facilities, for—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9D3B52F9EA5548CF832328D985A06FEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the increased number of immigration judges, attorneys, and support staff under this section; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD1D27F2E061C46A49D6480630665D175"><enum>(B)</enum><text>conducting immigration court proceedings in close proximity to the locations at which aliens are apprehended and detained.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H78A57103B0974B048EFF9B2C674A4F6E"><enum>304.</enum><header>Refugee application and processing centers</header> 
<subsection id="HFFBEE4C38B864E30A3EF73BF1F860E4A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>Section 101(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HC9A45ADFD9514C2D9E319682A4420B48" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HE6EF8715C9A14A3D95B124E9AF143624"><enum>(53)</enum><text>The term <term>refugee application and processing center</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H21CC45C08AE94277A481CDFAD9EE8921"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a facility designated under section 207(g) by the Secretary of State to accept and process applications for refugee admissions to the United States; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5E61DD0BF37D4D589870B25203B11D46"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include a United States embassy, consulate, or other diplomatic facility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD8371D00C2E94272AA46BE2F007FDA12"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>Section 207 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1157">8 U.S.C. 1157</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H789ECACAFCAB41419FC490F298E9C32A" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H5C9BF7C8093B4635808EFC43363A9F1A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Refugee application and processing centers</header> <paragraph id="H6D1FACF12C264A8EA1047BDB7E9957B4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>Not later than 240 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall designate refugee application and processing centers outside the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H485B1F28888D486DAE8F909D5D19E22B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Locations</header><text>The Secretary of State shall establish—</text> <subparagraph id="H395D99B8BC8B45B79FB5037394FBA7C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>1 refugee application and processing center in Mexico; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF2C3C0AD76FC48D3B4EBBA15643ED2DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not fewer than 3 refugee application and processing centers in Central America at locations selected by the Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H354A5CCF2B46433BAC578F6E97375D51"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties of secretary of state</header><text>The Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall ensure that any alien who is a national or habitual resident of a country in which a refugee application and processing center is located, or a country contiguous to such a country, may apply for refugee status at a refugee application and processing center in that country.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF981E9586CE748BFB7106EAB5A8F6E65"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Adjudication by asylum officers</header><text>An application for refugee status submitted to a refugee application and processing center shall be adjudicated by a asylum officer.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H27FDA07F655B4730B9E4C8E0BEFF7FC0"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary of State shall ensure that refugee application and processing centers accord priority to applications submitted—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDCE906CB633D4461833BA74EBFAEFDC7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by aliens who have been referred by an authorized nongovernmental organization, as determined by the Secretary of State;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H363C68DD1D2E452A861C18471E780085"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date on which such referral is made; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC8E098621224475E9A6444F8A474C679"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in accordance with the requirements and procedures established by the Secretary of State under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6ACBC861ECC441D788EB1794DB746343"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Number of referrals and grants of admission for refugees</header><text>The admission to the United States of refugees under this subsection shall be subject to the limitations, including the numerical limitations, under this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6D2338FF062C4891B70456D713811823"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Application fees</header> 
<subparagraph id="HC2E7A424612F4F55995CC92E34C2163E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of State and the Secretary of Homeland Security shall charge, collect, and account for fees prescribed by each such Secretary pursuant to subsections (m) and (n) of section 286 and section 9701 of title 31, United States Code, for the purpose of receiving, docketing, processing, and adjudicating an application under this subsection.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFFEB64DEB07545059B898F85387C59E2"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Basis for fees</header><text>The fees prescribed under subparagraph (A) shall be based on a consideration of the amount necessary to deter frivolous applications and the cost for processing the application, including the implementation of program integrity and anti-fraud measures.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H866D4B1E09B049C6910D0A2A29A27D3F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall cease to be effective beginning on the date that is three years and 240 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></title> <title id="H638D9E0F398A47219DF749D5AAA20B68" commented="no"><enum>IV</enum><header>Repurposing Federal Drug Programs</header> <section id="H35F47FF64B304036A729E6D556C5A794" commented="no"><enum>401.</enum><header>Reauthorization of block grants for prevention and treatment of substance abuse</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1935(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300x-35">42 U.S.C. 300x–35(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote> $1,908,079,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027</quote> and inserting <quote>$3,961,600,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="HF147321C7BB04D89AC4153B5E465C031" commented="no"><enum>402.</enum><header>Offsetting repeals</header> 
<subsection id="HF449DF2B1F474D4E814A7D0D3EAE120C" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Substance abuse treatment programs of regional and national significance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 509 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290bb-2">42 U.S.C. 290bb–2</external-xref>) is hereby repealed.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB0668F04793A46938659EDB3A9267B0F" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Drug-Free Communities Support Program</header><text>Chapter 2 of subtitle A of title I of the National Narcotics Leadership Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1521">21 U.S.C. 1521 et seq.</external-xref>) is hereby repealed.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H38C99115256A4CA99E685A0647C8DBAA" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Community mental health services block grant</header><text>Subpart I of part B of title XIX of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300x">42 U.S.C. 300x et seq.</external-xref>) is hereby repealed.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H70BCC30083B146F48324EBF9AF2D5184" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grants for jail diversion programs</header><text>Section 520G of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290bb-38">42 U.S.C. 290bb–38</external-xref>) is hereby repealed.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDAD9214313894B449B8FB9138C70E680"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Project AWARE; certified community behavioral health clinics expansion grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall terminate by the end of fiscal year 2023, and not establish any successor programs to, the following programs carried out under section 520A of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290bb-32">42 U.S.C. 290bb–32</external-xref>):</text> <paragraph id="H0A83F62C3C0742E1A34430A4F4D08724"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Project AWARE.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H018F2054449540E9A07D436275381E7A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Certified Community Behavioral Health Clinics Expansion Grants program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H71E43FAF40784A2C9B17030080C4F736" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Priority substance use disorder prevention needs of regional and national significance</header><text>Section 516 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290bb-22">42 U.S.C. 290bb–22</external-xref>) is hereby repealed.</text></subsection></section></title> 
</legis-body></bill>

