<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF0E2BF9BBDC7422B901C156900A0AAD3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6689 IH: Student Loan Relief for Medicare and Social Security Recipients Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6689</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to forgive the Federal student loans of borrowers who are enrolled for benefits under part A of title XVIII of the Social Security Act, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB02A94E998114FEA9D3610CD2CA513AE" style="OLC"><section id="H9E42FEAF8ED0473EAEE8C946D706C2EC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Student Loan Relief for Medicare and Social Security Recipients Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5735FDF89B9F4E6E97538B02B8ACB3DE" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Federal student loan forgiveness for borrowers enrolled in Medicare</header><subsection id="H413FF0882BBE41C0A864B6A0BE8D0719"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Forgiveness required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Education shall forgive the outstanding balance of principal, interest, and fees due on the eligible Federal student loans of borrowers who meet the requirements of subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H455D92B2E1F44208817DA0A9B6D13102"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A borrower is eligible to receive forgiveness under this section if, at the time of application for forgiveness, such borrower is—</text><paragraph id="H423734D961E645C5AAE13F41EB4A6A8A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>enrolled for benefits under part A of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395c">42 U.S.C. 1395c et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0507C871EDF84B3F9C7921E3B4ABFFC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the 24-month waiting period for such benefits as described under section 226(b) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/426">42 U.S.C. 426(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC036C3F3E6514E83BE78C2C81D6F7BB5" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A borrower seeking forgiveness under this section shall submit to the Secretary of Education an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H95A53A2BAAC74C158EF33D6CB5DC25E6"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Method of loan forgiveness</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As soon as practicable after the Secretary of Education confirms that an applicant meets the requirements of subsection (b), the Secretary of Education shall—</text><paragraph id="HAE004C74F82D4BADBA23672D400CA1F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each eligible Federal student loan of the borrower that is held by the Department of Education, cancel the outstanding balance of principal, interest, and fees due on the loan; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3300A66655194CED96FC4D5F90C5CC1E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for each eligible Federal student loan of the borrower that is not held by the Department of Education—</text><subparagraph id="H5F3485E1AADF44F1A73D6F77D1BAE253"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">through the holder of a loan, assume the obligation to repay the outstanding balance of principal, interest, and fees due on the loan; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13E4ADCE087B4230A49D90EFBE0F1814"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">upon assuming such obligation, cancel the outstanding balance of such principal, interest, and fees.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE8A1A0702BA04CCC919219B454339C61" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Repayment refunds prohibited</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to authorize the refund of any payments made by a borrower on an eligible Federal student before the date on which the borrower’s loans are forgiven in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H88CBA0373C364F0CB99C915F263ACD65"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H37AA73AC08564DD2B6413967DA86E529" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible Federal student loan</header><text>The term <term>eligible Federal student loan</term> means a loan—</text><subparagraph id="H68275263AF444167B966C7D91F9290C9" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">received by a borrower at least 10 years before the date on which such borrower applies for forgiveness under subsection (c);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A4D852EFB2648A5864A7FF4DA2212AB" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>used to pay for—</text><clause id="H9BFCFC5489584DD8AD2C7389EA108077" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the undergraduate or graduate education of the borrower; or</text></clause><clause id="H71CE79AE92A148118F6B9BCCFE9893B2" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a loan made to a parent on behalf of a dependent student, the undergraduate or graduate education of such dependent student; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D118A00CB6C4E59AFF3C17ABAA9270B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">made, insured, or guaranteed under—</text><clause id="HBCECE7CBFEA247E799C85A8A0D40DD47" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">part B, part D, or part E of title IV of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1070">20 U.S.C. 1070 et seq.</external-xref>), including a consolidation loan; or</text></clause><clause id="H840235B65BE44A9EABD36ADFE7B81534" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">part E of title VIII of the Public Health Service Act.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1A9DB34598C486A9560916B3A0DCCF5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fees</term> means any amounts owed by a borrower, other than principal and interest, on an eligible Federal student loan, including the amounts of any outstanding administrative fees, late charges, and collection costs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD943CFA3FF347D58A32B3C5234BBA1B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Graduate education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>graduate education</term> means a postbaccalaureate program of study that leads to a graduate degree, including a master's or doctoral degree.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9D10A447A4A48A49EB5EBE650BCA878" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given that term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF6BD5B7374A48F9BB14DC0ADEFF27B1" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Undergraduate education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>undergraduate education</term> means a postsecondary program of study at an institution of higher education that leads to a certificate, associate degree, or baccalaureate degree.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

