<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA8650119206F46A797C3AE8B6B225C7A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2895 IH: Time Is Up Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2895</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230426">April 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the President to announce whether action will be taken with respect to a covered transaction under the Defense Production Act of 1950 that has passed the CFIUS transaction review deadline, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6FD0125055A5447EBDF7160D99E1545A" style="OLC"><section id="H341EAE885036433B800725E59B5CF941" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Time Is Up Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFFA07D30F15E4407AEBD510E36593591"><enum>2.</enum><header>Presidential announcements</header><subsection id="HC7DB3F769B334ACBA243E7804B9F9F24"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a covered transaction under section 721 of the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4565">50 U.S.C. 4565</external-xref>), the President shall make the announcement described under section 721(d)(2) of such Act with respect to such transaction before the end of the 15-day period beginning on the date of enactment of this Act, if—</text><paragraph id="H1AA344A24FC842C79154C571FBE052F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on the date of enactment of this Act—</text><subparagraph id="H42AE45CEAF6C47C28F7224530C442D30"><enum>(A)</enum><text>more than 105 days have passed since the date on which written notice was accepted under section 721(b)(1)(C) of such Act for the covered transaction or the date on which a review was initiated under section 721(b)(1)(D) of such Act for the transaction, as applicable; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H820D14F7E77543D78D7ED8DAF3F6E3F5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to a covered transaction for which an investigation has been initiated under section 721(b)(2)(B)(ii) of such Act, more than 60 days have passed since the investigation was initiated; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8096B976442D4F08B9F4D8AFACD32AA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Investment in the United States has not concluded action with respect to the transaction under section 721(b) of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H588BB18A4A3B441692FE9E0F8B3DA3C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Completion of announced suspensions and prohibitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any announcement under section 721(d)(2) of the Defense Production Act of 1950 made by the President before the date of enactment of this Act (or, with respect to a covered transaction described under paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (a), such an announcement made at any time) of a suspension or prohibition of a covered transaction, if the President has not completed such suspension or prohibition, the President shall do so—</text><paragraph id="HD462DA51B2D0410EBAFF1CB594A2E869"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to an announcement made before the date of enactment of this Act, before the end of the 30-day period beginning on the date of enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD9415EA08A54E54A73BBC0BEA056BFD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to an announcement made on or after the date of enactment of this Act, before the end of the 30-day period beginning on the date of such announcement.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

