<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H85BBC2C56A1C470FBC18E0B41317179B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6187 IH: Defense Spending Oversight Act of 2024</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6187</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231102">November 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Inspector General of the Department of Defense to submit an annual report on oversight of fraud, waste, and abuse, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5C7B4C2F719A47479129DE486D594DD5" style="OLC"><section id="H8628054DB9E0445D8868A6A721A2A5E9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Defense Spending Oversight Act of 2024</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE93F0AFDA31640AC908A146A38D2E759" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inspector General of the Department of Defense annual report on oversight of fraud, waste, and abuse</header><subsection id="H29F09904E93649D1A55E803E5DB18653"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Inspector General of the Department of Defense shall submit to Congress and the Comptroller General of the United States a detailed annual report containing—</text><paragraph id="H6B086A6AC80C41B3B97D5C204430FC1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the budget of the Department of Defense, the total amount and dollar value of oversight investigations into fraud waste and abuse conducted by the Department of Defense Office of Inspector General, and the total amount and dollar value of oversight investigations into fraud, waste, and abuse conducted by the Offices of Inspector General of each of the military departments;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD23AAED0244E426DA14CFF85E1828187"><enum>(2)</enum><text>statistical tables showing—</text><subparagraph id="H4E7EBA3342C1462DA1D80826BAA60764"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number and dollar value of oversight investigations completed and pending, set forth separately by type of oversight investigation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA4BF3C9960D4763A3FBAEA1B6D29214"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the priority given to each type of oversight investigation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EB1558A00A344D384087934BD2077B0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the length of time taken for each type of oversight investigation, both from the date of receipt of a qualified incurred cost submission and from the date the oversight investigation begins;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72C2CEAE434E4F3084E9F2867099405B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the aggregate cost of performing oversight investigations, set forth separately by type of oversight investigation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44298782FD194545A161B6BF1EBE1742"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number and dollar value of oversight investigations that are pending for a period longer than one year as of the end of the fiscal year covered by the report, and the fiscal year in which the qualified submission was received, set forth separately by type of oversight investigation;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE83A4EB6E2BE4F3696C5BE9231557ACB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a summary of any recommendations of actions or resources needed to improve the oversight investigation process; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B6BFAA8CDB64C34B571D5322096F337"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other matters the Inspector General considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4FF9DD00DA5A460890BAD73C20044A60"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report submitted under subsection (a) shall be made publicly available.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

