<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H26641E26D2C8477A8079502C5C2190C0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3795 IH: To amend the Public Health Service Act to require the development of a diagnostic testing preparedness plan to be used during public health emergencies, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3795</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230605">June 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000615">Mr. Pence</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to require the development of a diagnostic testing preparedness plan to be used during public health emergencies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8E18AF4D88BB4CA2BCCEA266F8BF4DAF" style="OLC"><section id="H6B080B08543847A684B5D8CB8DE42737" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Diagnostic testing preparedness plan</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/201">42 U.S.C. 201 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 319F–5 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d-6f">42 U.S.C. 247d–6f</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H47B3762D383A4232BA3F9115677705D3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H2035E1B71B9A4996ACA974B745081831" section-type="section-one"><enum>319F–6.</enum><header>Diagnostic testing preparedness plan</header><subsection id="H3D819DE9C4CA428ABF20AE46D8EAB47F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response, and in consultation with the heads of relevant Federal agencies, shall develop not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section and update not less than every 3 years thereafter a plan for rapid development, authorization, scaling, procurement, and distribution of diagnostics and clinical and diagnostic laboratory testing capacity during a public health emergency declared under section 319.</text></subsection><subsection id="H78AC44865E914D62877514346F9C786A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of the plan under subsection (a) shall be—</text><paragraph id="H381F7BAA73944777989D01C5ECFB1735"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to facilitate the development of diagnostics for use with respect to a novel chemical, biological, radiological, or nuclear threat or an emerging infectious disease, including any such high-throughput laboratory diagnostic, point-of-care diagnostic, or rapid at-home or point-of-use diagnostic; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H73E6DC2D236D4DCDAEA29915F49832FE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to describe the processes for rapid development, authorization, scaling, procurement, and distribution of diagnostics and clinical and diagnostic laboratory testing capacity. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4919198DD8D94CFBB671BE48BA923B2F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public-Private coordination</header><paragraph id="H324CC7D5C38E4BFE98E44FF14A91EBAA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response, shall include within the plan under subsection (a) a plan for public-private coordination on national diagnostic testing during a public health emergency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E91FA768C3A48468F804C12FBC4032B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The plan under paragraph (1) shall be designed to facilitate coordination and collaboration among—</text><subparagraph id="H87836CD7CB27470BAAEA755FFD9FB97A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>government agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7EA2DD81BEA449194C17461C255DE24"><enum>(B)</enum><text>critical private-sector diagnostic testing stakeholders, including private-sector clinical and diagnostic laboratories, diagnostic manufacturers, health care product distributors, and research laboratories.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H27D30FF9DF1B464FB86B76966253C3BE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response, shall make the plan under subsection (a) publicly available.</text></subsection><subsection id="H83C7633F09354EACBCD977421417A986"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after commencing implementation of the plan under subsection (a) for a public health emergency, the Secretary, acting through the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response, shall submit to the Congress a report evaluating the effectiveness of activities implemented under the plan.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

