<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC93031086A084F9AA36DFF4912CCED41" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1461 IH: Coastal Seaweed Farm Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1461</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230308">March 8, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Agriculture and the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to carry out a study on coastal seaweed farming, issue regulation relating to such farming, and establish an Indigenous seaweed farming fund, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H94B9894A81104A13ADB1899915505B60" style="OLC">
<section id="H06AF3DABEDCC428181DED0B258A781AB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Coastal Seaweed Farm Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7D114CF1CF084CAAB6CA855A80262305"><enum>2.</enum><header>Program on coastal seaweed farming</header> <subsection id="H3C167C32196D4972A1825BDFF82C2B0E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Preliminary study on coastal seaweed farming</header> <paragraph id="H835AFF0CCFC34B63A3B12F801CC9B9A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretaries shall jointly submit a preliminary report to Congress and publish such report on such Secretaries’ agency websites analyzing—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD2FEE297C715457A8B8BA8021A1119F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the effects of coastal seaweed farming on surrounding communities, the ecosystem, and marine and coastal wildlife;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H54B374E5ABE44C979D318AE15222D217"><enum>(B)</enum><text>best practices for cultivating and sourcing local seeds to propagate for coastal seaweed farming;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB5C127B5DE384F9F89CC210039CFC68E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>best practices to prevent the escape or spread of any organism that would alter the natural ecosystem or present a biofouling risk;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCE1A96636D454609942A0230031568E3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>best practices relating to species selection, harvesting cycles, spatial planning and siting, engineering and design, and environmental aspects of coastal seaweed farming that—</text>
<clause id="H5B93A8881A614E5BBFEC3E138275A0DC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>maximize benefits, and avoid adverse effects, on the marine ecosystem and marine and coastal wildlife;</text></clause> <clause id="H4EECD2EBBA284E9A9F05AAE8CE540843"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>lead to optimal yields;</text></clause>
<clause id="H0AFFA37EF7C2436894C6A866FD629A85"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>account for the impact climate change may have on natural habitats and coastal seaweed farming operations;</text></clause> <clause id="H72EFB9315799467CB91A58096E4625FF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>minimize entanglements and other harmful interactions between marine life and nearshore seaweed farming infrastructure and gear;</text></clause>
<clause id="H057C678220B1483E86CF58EE7AFC472E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>account for changes in migration patterns of marine mammals and highly migratory species (as defined in section 3 of the Magnuson-Stevens Fishery Conservation and Management Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1802">16 U.S.C. 1802</external-xref>)); and</text></clause> <clause id="HAB235BE66E6B421993FD505410976263"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>account for and avoid interference with competing uses, including vessel traffic and commercial and recreational fishing;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8E4DBE4FFA9948A49CB9748EE6E131FD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the potential for growing seaweed for long-term carbon sequestration and best practices for measurement, reporting, and verification approaches for growing seaweed for long-term carbon sequestration specific to the sequestration reservoir;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCE890612521443FCBD7CD8EE5C0FFF80"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the effects of co-cultivation of bivalves with seaweed on the ecosystem, ocean acidification, and hypoxia levels;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H41F9ED03819C452A8672E074F7D2EC56"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the effects of coastal seaweed farming on water quality;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H669DCE6E3F414142B581CCEF9315EA5C"><enum>(H)</enum><text>best practices for limiting the use of plastic in coastal seaweed farming gear;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H069676E254C64D2F98C5C977C7C4FC09"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the history and use of Indigenous and traditional seaweed farming practices;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4897DDB2E4DC415BB1138B49CA8F0276"><enum>(J)</enum><text>best practices for sustainable harvest and post-harvest processing of coastal seaweed farming products, including methods of reducing energy costs;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4BCABA7731594D98B1801D47326A0DC5"><enum>(K)</enum><text>scalable commercial applications for value-added seaweed or products derived from seaweed, including as feedstock for animals and other agricultural, commercial, and industrial applications;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF3D0561670B3453082381989865074B7"><enum>(L)</enum><text>processes for processing, storage, and transportation of seaweed that are cost-effective, reduce carbon emissions from transportation, and efficient;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H057FB6E1E74B4BFBBFBBE7FE76BFEBA8"><enum>(M)</enum><text>assessment of existing and potential markets and market capacity for major cultivated seaweed species;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4DE938E24AB344ED9BE3618238ACEE92"><enum>(N)</enum><text>development of baseline economic analyses and business planning models for major cultivated seaweed species;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H52DB05BE98DE42BA8AAA88F658B372B0"><enum>(O)</enum><text>the effects of water quality on the quality of cultivated seaweed for human consumption, including the absorption of toxic heavy metals and persistent organic pollutants;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE4DC763C376C48D48A99F5060765CCD6"><enum>(P)</enum><text>best practices for onshore farming issues that reduce energy requirements to pump water and include management of effluent, spatial planning and address conflicting uses of the onshore coastal zone; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H127BFC83C7654898BFB9E728267C034A"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>best practices in efficient and effective Federal and State regulatory systems for coastal seaweed farming.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H280FB1B759B448F0A7B28561F4C80BB6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In preparing the report under paragraph (1), the Secretaries shall consult with—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD36E6D741B4C49FA8BB79A0137165FD9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Interagency Working Group on Indigenous Traditional Ecological Knowledge, with respect to—</text> <clause id="H2634107E7C5A4888B0CC40DC65898BBB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>kelp, seaweed, and shellfish cultivation;</text></clause>
<clause id="H799A606D5A1B4E2C83A663AE481A19BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the use of Tribal waters for coastal seaweed farming;</text></clause> <clause id="HCCB4D5084BDC472386DFD5D9B4DA7CFE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the impact and benefits of coastal seaweed farming on Tribal waters; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HD577273631C24AFCA6E04F6F64150AF1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>best practices for engaging with Tribes on matters relating to coastal seaweed farming;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H59D9F6CA97954D79BAF24BBF44D43AEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coastal or historically coastal federally recognized Tribes, State recognized Tribes, and Inter-Tribal organizations;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6D983CD96F86474588469A9C06EB097E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Interagency Working Group on Research for Farming of Seaweeds and Seagrasses;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0CA1B4DDFF5847A49DE2B811801E3214"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Interagency Working Group on Ocean Acidification;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H66E746970D934C6DA799CD1E804D4F2F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>National Science and Technology Council’s Joint Subcommittee on Aquaculture; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H29F020FB2C91432C8828AFC0A6788D3D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>such other Federal, State, Tribal, and local government agencies as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE9E506E8B51A4F3E9F1546F7167C38C9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Update</header><text>The Secretaries shall, not later than 2 years after the date on which the report required under paragraph (1) is submitted, submit an updated report to Congress based on pertinent information derived from Federal research programs, the grant program established under subsection (c), and other sources of information.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H260A67CAF7AC4D17807C199C0C7B5967"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report on regulation of seaweed food safety</header><text>The Commissioner of Food and Drugs shall, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and in consultation with such State agencies as the Commissioner determines appropriate, submit a report to Congress making regulatory and legislative recommendations to improve Federal regulation of seaweed for human consumption, focusing on standards and testing methods to identify, address, and prevent contamination by bacteria, heavy metals, and pathogens.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H5B44FFE620534EF2B19824C4E4DC5F37"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretaries shall, not later than 1 year after the publication of the study required by subsection (a), issue such regulations as the Secretaries determine appropriate to—</text> <paragraph id="H9038DE67AFE943BE8FDCD7FC42AF33EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure that design, development, siting, species selection, operation, and production systems of coastal seaweed farming maximize potential benefits, and avoid potential adverse effects, on the marine ecosystem, wildlife, and fisheries and surrounding communities; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H24157C259E8D47FF8542D2732DF087AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish evaluation metrics to measure the impact and benefits of coastal seaweed farming on—</text> <subparagraph id="HB950C8C7BDA64A5D83C14A09F79ACD37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the marine ecosystem, including marine wildlife, biodiversity, productivity, water quality, and stored carbon; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0D87CA8A56304B638036F9EA128E5979"><enum>(B)</enum><text>surrounding communities, including relating to the equitable distribution of costs and benefits (economic and environmental) within such communities; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H94737FB68DB24400A3710855C96ADDC6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>require monitoring and reporting relating to—</text>
<subparagraph id="HFFF9D865C2F743048203A74A6880A8DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any adverse effects on the marine ecosystem and wildlife, including entanglements of marine life; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7DABE9293C094E31810E181B8E76A074"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any effects on commercial and recreational fishing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF65B4D427E0E460F8CC71F3BBD822D64"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Indigenous Seaweed Farming Fund</header>
<paragraph id="HFFB298DB8D4D4DA7862A3DAD48CC3767"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretaries shall, not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, jointly establish the Indigenous Seaweed Farming Fund to provide grants to eligible entities for the purpose of supporting coastal seaweed farming, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HD6F71194189F4A2395BC8AFF74F18DCB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>obtaining, planting, growing, and maintaining a coastal seaweed farm;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD611FE904EF14BF3803C1AA55FCDB259"><enum>(B)</enum><text>purchasing equipment for coastal seaweed farm operations;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H62D157CC3C4640CFAEC378B4EDBF3A4B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>transportation, processing, and storage of coastal seaweed farm products;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H91D1A76EBA6245CAA3936A3E9C5D341B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>funding for development and use of models and measurements to identify and mitigate adverse impacts of coastal seaweed farming, including monitoring and signal buoys; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD41BC592FEEA4F86A622DB7747F5C46A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to operate a coastal seaweed farm that performs restorative ecological functions, including providing essential habitat to native species.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0CDA62B2777D40AAAA06CEC1430437D0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>The Secretaries shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HE5E5521D68CC445AB9A06D0D23A9DE1B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct outreach and use existing programs and initiatives to make eligible entities aware of the Indigenous Seaweed Farming Fund;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCCCC15F344D146D496211DF2FAD2C3BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>solicit comments and recommendations relating to each stage of the operation of the grant program established under subsection (a);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF2EC840F87F7405BA32D5A7391F7340B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>solicit scientific input from eligible entities, including through public meetings noticed in advance and in such languages as are appropriate for the community; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H104915D8F022477DAF629463130530A2"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prepare, publish, and distribute to institutions of higher learning, including vocational schools training materials for individuals engaged in coastal seaweed farming and individuals seeking employment relating to such farming, including Indigenous youth.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA85C1F27060041CDBB54C74E6A7EC8FD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of funds</header><text>No funds provided under this subsection may be used for any purpose that the Secretary of Commerce or the head of a State or Tribal fishery management agency determines will have an adverse affect on commercial fisheries.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H139E215D39924E31B50DEA32CEC5AA66"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation on size of farms</header><text>The Secretaries shall, by regulation, determine a maximum size for coastal seaweed farming operations that may receive funding under this subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3855C6978E8B483EB1D570A4F41EEA6E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretaries shall, at the request of an applicant or grantee, provide technical assistance to such applicant or grantee to further the purposes of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC1039FA110E945BC975CF0C32D49D81C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H77F37593F1124677BE08C03BD46ED65C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2B4F339C8EC04CACAE20E3B24E6E18AB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Seaweed</header><text>The term <quote>seaweed</quote> means macroscopic multicellular marine algae species.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H69D796FDB0BF41E19CA45FFF7D90C789"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="H499E0063E87D421CBD7DA0C0FB12AB8B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a federally recognized Tribe, Native Village, or Tribal reservation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD7BF57E0DDCB478187A744E8BE9C72DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State recognized Tribe (as such term is defined in section 4 of the Native American Housing Assistance and Self-Determination Act of 1996);</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC744064B6E93400C862B37922C39BC99"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a Native person of—</text> <clause id="HFAA7447D72104C98BF9958F14434A510"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Hawaii;</text></clause>
<clause id="HABB5F46F942F4387B4B7F29B6A9B5553"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a Pacific Island;</text></clause> <clause id="H03506965409A40CDBBEF756BDCB7FF42"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Puerto Rico; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HA3C8D136B04947B6AD82154135798328"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the United States Virgin Islands;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCCC3C9CB06AD433E81A4CABDF8422E1F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a member of an entity described in subparagraphs (A) or (B); or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFA1B41E3DD4D4BFAA05A03BCE3CFB1A4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any entity owned entirely by an entity described in subparagraphs (A) through (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF96901BF265B466686FD61A87236BAAF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federally recognized tribe</header><text>The term <quote>federally recognized Tribe</quote> has the meaning given to the term <quote>Indian Tribe</quote> in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance 18 Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H731EF4F0E03047E884B64387AD42CA87"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Coastal seaweed farming</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>coastal seaweed farming</quote> means the onshore or nearshore propagation and harvesting of seaweed and seaweed products within the coastal zone (as such term is defined in section 304 of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1453">16 U.S.C. 1453</external-xref>)) that—</text> <subparagraph id="H588FAD2606534763BDA932B59721730F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>does not use—</text>
<clause id="HBF10DCDEFB9048E6A46B8E39AD4D1E43"><enum>(i)</enum><text>synthetic pesticides (as the term <quote>pesticide</quote> is defined in section 2 of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/136">7 U.S.C. 136</external-xref>)); and</text></clause> <clause id="H5FC783936CA34A66AEF0E53309BB5A71"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>plastics, unless a suitable replacement does not exist; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H499E289286464DB68C435FE64A852642"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not produce fin fish for commercial purposes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFBDDF86E340D4E2FA197090DBF72939C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretaries</header><text>The term <quote>Secretaries</quote> means the Secretary of Agriculture and the Secretary of Commerce, acting through the Under Secretary for Oceans and Atmosphere.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H74380B69CFEC4EFFBB622F6A0A879654"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated—</text> <paragraph id="H39D49D4937204768AE621D0556209935"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$3,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027 to carry out subsections (a) and (b); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA63587C4B6AB42709F7E4FD5E5E1E2E3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027 to carry out subsections (c), (d), and (e).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

