<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBCB1584AD43544FAB7AD5D84E03D145E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5458 IH: Baby Observation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5458</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Y000067">Mr. Yakym</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Patient Center Outcome Research Institute to prepare and release a report on home cardiorespiratory monitors for infants, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8B388EEDE6CB4A04B875DA09E51E84FD" style="OLC"><section id="H8D49D58A49B748E5AFC0DD1BB48D0A22" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Baby Observation Act</short-title></quote> or <quote><short-title>BO’s Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFCC60D88D3FE4161B11869BD40AE52D7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on home cardiorespiratory monitors for infants</header><subsection id="HD58886BEBA7247A8A30DB7D19BB1125F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 months after the date of the enactment of this Act and in accordance with paragraphs (8) and (9) of section 1181(d) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320e">42 U.S.C. 1320e(d)</external-xref>), the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute established pursuant to subsection (b) of such section shall make publicly available a study and report on home cardiorespiratory monitors, including—</text><paragraph id="HA7D229B86FD44E2ABCA11F7C51C4EFD9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review of the literature on, and a data analysis of, best practices to reduce or prevent sleep-related sudden infant death syndrome or sudden unexpected infant death (as such terms are defined in section 1121(e)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300c-11">42 U.S.C. 300c–11(e)</external-xref>));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H307D4565101F43D2A8E4722215D9C6BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of—</text><subparagraph id="HD972F0B044F74D47B6441FB8CD467D82"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the available evidence on the effectiveness, performance, and accuracy of home cardiorespiratory monitors that track the heart rate, blood oxygen levels, and other vital signs of an infant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DD318F7749F4DB68498418266595A96" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">new models of care to improve the home sleeping environment of an infant, including the use of cardiorespiratory monitors;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H22E199E00FDA4370A3ABABF306D721BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>health care plan criteria for medically appropriate coverage for a home cardiorespiratory monitor; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E0E0BF0166F487DADE3D171B89393FD"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations on whether home cardiorespiratory monitors have shown product efficacy supporting coverage under an employer-sponsored health care plan, a qualified health plan offered through an Exchange established pursuant to title I of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act, the Medicaid program established under title XIX of the Social Security Act, and CHIP plans under title XXI of the Social Security Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9BCEC4AFC6C8419FBAD1EE582CD645D9" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HAF1A010AD0FC477F9689B0961A6E7FA7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Home cardiorespiratory monitor</header><text>The term <quote>home cardiorespiratory monitor</quote> means a medical device used in the home to track the respiratory effort and heart rate of a sleeping infant. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA11A966B90C64BC3A41C7D34573601B2" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Infant</header><text>The term <quote>infant</quote> means a person under 2 years of age.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H89B59AAC523F41118815E71673333903"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The trustee of the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Trust Fund (as described in section 9511 of the Internal Revenue Code) shall provide from such trust fund such funds as may be required to carry out the study under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

