<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H632F3B7A20C24FDEB44A270009696FD9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5298 IH: Military Lodging Reform Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5298</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230829">August 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 10, United States Code, to transfer the authority to operate certain transient housing of the Department of Defense to the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Energy, Installations, and Environment.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8FBD723EE1E241D28E2465F082FCCD2B" style="OLC"><section id="H804B34C94FBF4CA5926E6257DD920262" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Military Lodging Reform Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H21279949211E4C3CA3D9F61B05EFCAA7" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority to operate certain transient housing of the Department of Defense transferred to Assistant Secretary of Defense for Energy, Installations, and Environment</header><subsection id="H45115701193041E3AD5C365806B22C66"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Transfer of authority</header><paragraph id="HABE77537C0CA44EB87A7EABBBDB16F80"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assignment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (7) of section 138(b) of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new sentence: <quote>The Assistant Secretary is responsible, subject to the authority, direction, and control of the Secretary of Defense, for all matters relating to lodging intended to be occupied by members of the Armed Forces that require such lodging due to a temporary duty assignment or a permanent change of station order.</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59BD8A0528284C1B9627E0FD0F26CE6F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transfer</header><subparagraph id="H4CFA3F912E694D248362D9C727AD75CA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall transfer each duty or responsibility relating to covered transient housing to the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Energy, Installations, and Environment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60420A7CBDF74EA7ACD3A380BB81AC59"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the congressional defense committees a certification that the transfer required under subparagraph (A) has been completed. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07D0374A4A3A4D4790DD511706359E6E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination on covered transient housing</header><subparagraph id="HD59C9AC599DB4649BDE764C631EDFD87"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Army transient housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On matters relating to covered transient housing of the Department of the Army, the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Energy, Installations, and Environment shall coordinate with the Assistant Secretary of the Army for Installations, Energy, and Environment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF798327E16341E7BF14122EB847CD51"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Navy transient housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On matters relating to covered transient housing of the Department of the Navy, the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Energy, Installations, and Environment shall coordinate with the Assistant Secretary of the Navy (Energy, Installations, and Environment).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1F70230841F4ECD91A1C2D4F4819632"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Air Force transient housing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On matters relating to covered transient housing of the Department of the Air Force, the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Energy, Installations, and Environment shall coordinate with the Assistant Secretary of the Air Force for Energy, Installations and Environment.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2FBAD18556AB4CDDA68287E500F8864A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>References</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any reference in law, regulation, guidance, instruction, or other document of the Federal Government to the Under Secretary of Defense for Personnel and Readiness with respect to covered transient housing shall be deemed to refer to the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Energy, Installations, and Environment.</text></subsection><subsection id="H17C78C3EDC6D49DA8FCB4C43A0104046"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered transient housing defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>covered transient housing</term> means lodging intended to be occupied by members of the Armed Forces that require such lodging due to—</text><paragraph id="HBB7EA60512E849F39DE4B2F1108F9217"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a temporary duty assignment; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7B86FD258E547A1A78056615EFDF64E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a permanent change of station order.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

