<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H06C6D25322264FECA32D9530F89E1ABD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 6018 IH: Operation Swords of Iron Supplemental Appropriations Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6018</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231020">October 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>) introduced the bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the<committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Committee on Appropriations</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">Committee on the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">Making supplemental appropriations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0EB1608D58B545C08B01594787E2B5F3" style="appropriations"><section id="H8F672D3134A34D1189A6C80A3B49F2EE" section-type="undesignated-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">That the following sums are appropriated, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, and for other purposes, namely:</text></section><section id="LEXA-Repairid4e45c61b48cf48a3b350920455abad45" section-type="undesignated-section"><appropriations-major id="H53A5FB329B4742B7963FDD9877FC5D5E"><header>DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE</header></appropriations-major><appropriations-intermediate id="H75CCE3ACEFD94A7A9D8B46770F76902B"><header>Military Programs Operation and Maintenance</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HBB2A824E028548F891EEEC0C4FFD33F8"><header>Operation and Maintenance, Defense-Wide </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For an additional amount for <quote>Operation and Maintenance, Defense-Wide</quote>, $4,400,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025, to respond to the situation in Israel and for related expenses: <italic>Provided</italic>, That amounts made available by under this heading shall be available for transfer to accounts under the headings <quote>Operation and Maintenance</quote>, <quote>Procurement</quote>, <quote>Research, Development, Test and Evaluation</quote>, and <quote>Revolving and Management Funds</quote> for replacement, through new procurement or repair of existing unserviceable equipment, of defense articles from the stocks of the Department of Defense, and for reimbursement for defense services of the Department of Defense and military education and training, provided to or identified for provision to Israel or to foreign countries that have provided support to Israel at the request of the United States: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That amounts made available under this heading may also be transferred to accounts under the heading <quote>Procurement</quote> for expansion of public and private plants, including the land necessary therefor, and procurement and installation of equipment, appliances, and machine tools in such plants, for the purpose of increasing production of critical munitions: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That of amounts made available under this heading may also be transferred to accounts under the heading <quote>Procurement</quote> and <quote>Research, Development, Test and Evaluation</quote> for the acquisition of critical defense articles: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That funds transferred pursuant to a transfer authority provided under this heading shall be merged with and available for the same purposes and for the same time period as the appropriations to which the funds are transferred: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That the Secretary of Defense shall notify the congressional defense committees of the details of such transfers not less than 15 days before any such transfer: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That upon a determination that all or part of the funds transferred from this appropriation are not necessary for the purposes provided under this heading, such amounts may be transferred back and merged with this appropriation: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That amounts may be transferred between appropriations made under this heading: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That any transfer authority provided under this heading is in addition to any other transfer authority provided by law: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amount in this paragraph is designated by the Congress as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, as amended: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amounts shall be available only if the President designates such amount as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A). </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="HEA5303A270E34FC4AA115712AACC6A87"><header>Military Programs Procurement </header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H3C12B1F4391449559B0EB81ABC096DF1"><header>Procurement of Ammunition, Army </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For an additional amount for <quote>Procurement of Ammunition, Army</quote>, $801,400,000, to remain available until September 30, 2026, to respond to the situation in Israel and for related expenses: <italic>Provided</italic>, That such amount is designated by the Congress as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, as amended: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amount shall be available only if the President designates such amount as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A). </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H0CB177BE15DC4EDE9455C1B016C3F6F6"><header>Procurement, Defense-Wide </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For an additional amount for Procurement, Defense-Wide, $4,000,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2027, for the Secretary of Defense to provide to the Government of Israel for the procurement of the Iron Dome and David’s Sling defense systems to counter shortrange rocket threats: <italic>Provided</italic>, That such funds shall be transferred pursuant to an exchange of letters and are in addition to funds provided pursuant to the U.S.-Israel Iron Dome Procurement Agreement, as amended: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That nothing under this heading shall be construed to apply to amounts made available in prior appropriations Acts for the procurement of the Iron Dome and David's Sling defense systems: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amount is designated by the Congress as being for an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, as amended: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amounts shall be available only if the President designates such amount as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A). </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H7CCA902BCED843C9B9A81ADE5CC816D0"><header>Military Programs Research, Development, Test, and Evaluation </header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="H6BD6E86AE660441FABDD5AA51CBC8C5D"><header>Research, Development, Test and Evaluation, Defense-Wide</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For an additional amount for <quote>Research, Development, Test and Evaluation, Defense-Wide</quote>, $1,200,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2026, for the Secretary of Defense to provide to the Government of Israel for the development of the Iron Beam defense system to counter short-range rocket threats: <italic>Provided</italic>, That such funds shall be transferred pursuant to an exchange of letters: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That nothing in the preceding proviso shall be construed to apply to amounts made available in prior appropriations Acts for the development of the Iron Beam defense system: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amount is designated by the Congress as being for an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, as amended: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amounts shall be available only if the President designates such amount as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A). </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-major id="H9AD5FD2B0DF74987AD516E22B8ED42E4"><header>TITLE VIII–GENERAL PROVISIONS</header></appropriations-major></section><section id="HF468EC4F956248C5B83A35C1F02EF086"><enum>8001.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 12001 of the Department of Defense Appropriations Act, 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/108/287">Public Law 108–287</external-xref>), as amended by <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/141">Public Law 115–141</external-xref>, is amended as follows:</text><paragraph id="H53381B39A63347E482285D365A3361DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In paragraph (2) of subsection (a), by striking <quote>armor</quote> and all that follows through the end of the paragraph and inserting <quote>defense articles that are in the inventory of the Department of Defense as of the date of transfer, are intended for use as reserve stocks for Israel, and are located in a stockpile for Israel as of the date of transfer</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1561D196053844328B977AFF2FA2104C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In subsection (b), by striking <quote>at least equal to the fair market value of the items transferred</quote> and inserting <quote>in an amount to be determined by the Secretary of Defense</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7D23B23B8FD407FA477F29F0EC8E719"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In subsection (c), by inserting before the comma in the first sentence the following: <quote>, or as far in advance of such transfer as is practicable as determined by the President on a case-by-case basis during extraordinary circumstances impacting the national security of the United States</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HFD07408665BA4377B7169196D24F8DFE"><enum>8002.</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For fiscal year 2024, section 514(b) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2321h">22 U.S.C. 2321h(b)</external-xref>) shall not apply to defense articles to be set aside, earmarked, reserved, or intended for use as reserve stocks in stockpiles in the State of Israel.</text></section><section id="LEXA-Repairid3309d2f8c0a44d09a96ad2596351a020" section-type="undesignated-section"><appropriations-major id="H173900977155446A89EF6DBA72D3009C"><header>DEPARTMENT OF STATE </header></appropriations-major><appropriations-intermediate id="HAA611C4FFDF5499BB07F55E093DFA075"><header>Administration of Foreign Affairs</header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HA8664BC304244CEDB4CCA0AF0E1D307B"><header>Diplomatic Programs </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For an additional amount for <quote>Diplomatic Programs</quote>, $150,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025, of which $50,000,000 shall be for responding to the situation in Israel and areas impacted by the situation in Israel, and of which $100,000,000 shall be available until expended for Worldwide Security Protection to respond to the situation in Israel and areas impacted by the situation in Israel: <italic>Provided</italic>, That such amount is designated by the Congress as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, as amended: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amount shall be available only if the President designates such amount as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A). </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-small id="H0D32B65F98864708AB6C84E7AEAF35A7"><header>Emergencies in the Diplomatic and Consular Service </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For an additional amount for <quote>Emergencies in the Diplomatic and Consular Service</quote>, $50,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025, to meet unforeseen emergencies arising in the Diplomatic and Consular Service: <italic>Provided</italic>, That such amount is designated by the Congress as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, as amended: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amount shall be available only if the President designates such amount as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A). </text></appropriations-small><appropriations-intermediate id="H8C2FA388D90A47EB9B09789023EC452E"><header>International Assistance Programs International Security Assistance </header></appropriations-intermediate><appropriations-small id="HAF868518A8A34E04B051DB66115B6F01"><header>Foreign Military Financing Program </header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For an additional amount for <quote>Foreign Military Financing Program</quote>, $3,500,000,000, to remain available until September 30, 2025, of which $3,500,000,000 shall be for responding to the situation in Israel and related expenses: <italic>Provided</italic>, That funds made available under this heading in this Act and Acts making appropriations for the Department of State, foreign operations, and related programs for fiscal year 2024 and prior fiscal years, in addition to funds otherwise available for such purposes, may be used by the Department of State for necessary expenses for the general costs of administering military assistance and sales, including management and oversight of such programs and activities: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That direct loans made using amounts described in the preceding proviso may be made notwithstanding any provision of law limiting the interest rate charged to borrowers: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That loan guarantees made using amounts described in the second proviso under this heading for loans financed by the Federal Financing Bank may be provided notwithstanding any provision of law limiting the percentage of loan principal that may be guaranteed: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That, to the extent that the Government of Israel requests that funds be used for such purposes, grants made available for Israel under this heading shall, as agreed by the United States and Israel, be available for advanced weapons systems, of which up to $3,500,000,000 may be available for the procurement in Israel of defense articles and defense services: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That any congressional notification requirement applicable to funds made available under this heading for Israel may be waived if a determination is made that extraordinary circumstances exist that impact the national security of the United States: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amount is designated by the Congress as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A) of the Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, as amended: <italic>Provided further</italic>, That such amount shall be available only if the President designates such amount as an emergency requirement pursuant to section 251(b)(2)(A).</text></appropriations-small></section><section id="HD001E69707C6435B827E050DD2B33A94" section-type="undesignated-section"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title><quote>Operation Swords of Iron</quote> Supplemental Appropriations Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

