<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H231B5D34223742A8BF21F90AAFF0E023" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1196 IH: Don Young Restoration Grants for Coastlines and Fisheries Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1196</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230224">February 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000610">Ms. Plaskett</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to establish a grant program to benefit coastal habitats, resiliency, and the economy, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4FD2C173E90E4B21810D9BBA3DBFE669" style="OLC"><section id="H76E35364F81C4569A2373D09D621E494" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Don Young Restoration Grants for Coastlines and Fisheries Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9E884147C0354DF69568EB3C81DD658A" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Don Young restoration grants for coastlines and fisheries</header><subsection id="HB08A2BE8EC564A5184DAB937DCF3C54A" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Administrator shall establish a grant program to provide funding and technical assistance to eligible entities for purposes of carrying out a project described in subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDD6A5308F9CF43E4B807ADCF67145F1D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Project proposal</header><text>To be considered for a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit a grant proposal to the Administrator in a time, place, and manner determined by the Administrator. Such proposal shall include monitoring, data collection, and measurable performance criteria with respect to the project.</text></subsection><subsection id="HABC75DFE1CA94564BC1AF126F093ACB1" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Development of criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall select eligible entities to receive grants under this section based on criteria developed by the Administrator, in consultation with relevant offices of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, such as the Office of Habitat Conservation, the Office for Coastal Management, the Office of Response and Restoration, and the Office of National Marine Sanctuaries.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1DB708D7FFC046A587479862CACAF085" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text>A proposal is eligible for a grant under this section if—</text><paragraph id="H8986EDDA66254290B0DA89E62A5BDB2F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the purpose of the project is to restore a marine, estuarine, coastal, or Great Lake habitat, including—</text><subparagraph id="HAA1D18363EAF4D5DABE162EA7DCB48AC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>restoration of habitat to protect or recover a species that is threatened, endangered, or a species of concern under the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F50D1736B074042AE0EB61D11FFFB42" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>through the removal or remediation of marine debris, including derelict vessels and abandoned, lost, and discarded fishing gear, in coastal and marine habitats; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33E1D9F47497425B96F5E86392DDAE87" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for the benefit of—</text><clause id="H7841BBE0BE8A44589E4240521310A1E7" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shellfish;</text></clause><clause id="HF1762202D6DF4FD490A26F485C8838F3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>fish, including diadromous fish;</text></clause><clause id="H54B4DB21EB014F1289637D3ECB53A8A3" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>coral reef systems;</text></clause><clause id="HBCD978719EC54C94AC1ED89203B6FFF4" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">marine wildlife; </text></clause><clause id="HD395214E28BB4697800D23EE6ED241ED" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">blue carbon ecosystems such as coastal wetlands, marshes, coastal forests, seagrasses, kelp forests, and other habitats important to carbon sequestration and storage; or</text></clause><clause id="H4918296D2E8B4311850CAEEF35820422"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>ecosystems such as beaches, dunes, oyster beds, submerged aquatic vegetation, and other ecosystems that provide protection from flooding, wave effects, and other coastal hazards; or</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H45B24FC6B76E4BB0A8B426C7E33E6F7E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides adaptation to climate change, including sequestering and storing carbon or by constructing, restoring, or protecting ecological features or nature-based infrastructure that protects coastal communities from sea level rise, coastal storms, or flooding.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5609519791540839A5F958E53F3BA1B" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In determining which projects to fund under this section, the Administrator shall give priority to a proposed project—</text><paragraph id="HAC37AF84278F4E12866B9010B066557E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that would stimulate the economy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB434C7847774DE2BB8D09E31B97CE60" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for which the applicant can demonstrate that the grant will fund work that will begin not more than 90 days after the date of award;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H10D5DB1FBD9745C38995102FDC57ADCC" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which the applicant can demonstrate that the grant will fund work that will employ fishermen who have been negatively impacted by financial hardship or pay a fisherman for the use of a fishing vessel;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD596E158CF734E978DD8E61784F0B014" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>for which the applicant can demonstrate that any preliminary study or permit required before the project can begin has been completed or can be completed shortly after an award is made;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77A622B8C3A34EE9A542789CB38AF3B7" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that includes communities that may not have adequate resources including low-income communities, communities of color, Tribal communities, Indigenous communities, and rural communities; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B2E0DC50C13423F81A019083B49AF01"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is happening within National Wildlife Refuges, National Parks, and Marine Protected Areas, such as National Marine Sanctuaries. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD341852CA6BC4110A883304F32B66469" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator $1,000,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2032 to carry out this section, to remain available until expended.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8D7CD8D59DC04053A8ECA4F71884576B" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="H148D6FECD28B4F2F91D3B3F303EAA67F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7D4AF05BC484A30AC565313383DF1BA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a nonprofit, a for-profit business, an institution of higher education, or a State, local, Tribal, or Territorial government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H011D3B5CEC4947B4BE7231A04FA20926" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Fishermen</header><text>The term <term>fishermen</term> means commercial or for-hire fishermen or oyster farmers.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

