<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4493FAB90ACD4BEBA2A1F71AF32FDA2F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3547 IH: Doxing Threat Assessment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3547</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000579">Mr. Ryan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001135">Ms. Manning</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000148">Mr. Auchincloss</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Department of Homeland Security to develop and disseminate a threat assessment regarding the use of cyber harassment, including doxing, by terrorists and foreign malicious actors, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HDA01A626291D42CEB6B01A15EB9CFBE4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE1D3DF0C244A471D999D2146E8DC7328" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Doxing Threat Assessment Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H3162377D24A84DC686B77778A21487CD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Threat assessment on cyber harassment and its use by terrorists and foreign malicious actors</header> <subsection id="H163FA2A87DB74508A7778D859691CD52"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Under Secretary for Intelligence and Analysis of the Department of Homeland Security shall develop and disseminate a threat assessment regarding the use of cyber harassment, including doxing, by terrorists and foreign malicious actors.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H62615F6BBE3949B3A8CBBF7FD2B28551"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The threat assessment developed pursuant to subsection (a)—</text> <paragraph id="H8B19B726A1934BAD8F8BBCAAF8738BD8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be developed in coordination with the Privacy Office of the Department of Homeland Security and the Office for Civil Rights and Civil Liberties of the Department of Homeland Security; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4AFC891A01EC45B7AB4F20B2E3DCD137"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may be informed by existing products, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA6C9DBFC47E24EC8BE81860AA54A5AF2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The threat assessment developed pursuant to subsection (a) shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4FD2FDAF103B4BD58149E3D23DB244D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an overview of cyber harassment tactics, techniques, and procedures used by terrorists and foreign malign actors;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H117AF704EB3A455A9C5B1B33949F7920"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a list of notable incidents of cyber harassment by terrorists and foreign malign actors;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54CC17C0DB7F42F198AF1B9DA172A536"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a review of the threat posed by cyber harassment, including tactics, techniques, and procedures not currently identified as in use by terrorists and foreign malign actors, but representing a vulnerability based on the common practices of such actors, as well as a summary of the terrorist and foreign malign actors most likely to adapt to use of such tactics, techniques, and procedures; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDAF4E17681FB407EA8BBBAA6278BF593"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an overview of cyber harassment typologies and methodologies that may inform risk indicators of relevance to State, local, Tribal, and Federal law enforcement in identifying cyber harassment that may be indicative of terrorist or foreign malign actor involvement.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB602CE5890104F2F8812374DF28C7E2B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Dissemination and publication</header><text>The Under Secretary shall—</text> <paragraph id="H684DB1EDF1B44A17A4CF4D412F5695E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, submit the threat assessment to Congressional committees of jurisdiction; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5990839D976440CE963C314201D3FFC1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consistent with the protection of classified and confidential unclassified information—</text> <subparagraph id="H1067E2348A3A42519DEEB41CB101C21E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disseminate the threat assessment developed under this section with State, local, and Tribal law enforcement officials, including officials who operate within State, local, and regional fusion centers through the Department of Homeland Security State, Local, and Regional Fusion Center Initiative established in accordance with section 210A of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/124h">6 U.S.C. 124h</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H431CB4AC228544EA8A46ED5161DD9566"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure a version of the assessment is published on the Department’s website no later than 30 days following dissemination to Congress.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H798B24D6F0DC48299C0E14CFE5DA48E5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For the purposes of this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H9F14E1E8F1B248E199C51F37B7C181F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Cyber harassment</header><text>The term <quote>cyber harassment</quote> means electronic communication that harasses, torments, threatens, or terrorizes a target.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF8EA44AAB8449BD9CDE8039D56EE19B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Doxing</header><text>The term <quote>doxing</quote> means to knowingly publish the personally identifiable information of another individual, without the individual’s consent and with the intent to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA4F410F384DF417B9DC9CBA04B0D69FB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>threaten, intimidate, harass, or stalk any person;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDEA8C756AA8645B6A2D47251767F2FBB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>facilitate another to threaten, intimidate, harass, or stalk any person;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H49EB08A9FE7C465A8BBBF89508F03596"><enum>(C)</enum><text>incite or facilitate the commission of a crime of violence against any person; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H60704EE5AC014F298C814D7A57C44629"><enum>(D)</enum><text>place any person in reasonable fear of death or serious bodily injury.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA10959F8CA484116871B430B5380A742"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Personally identifiable information</header><text>The term <quote>personally identifiable information</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H92BCFE68500F4911A8AEB8B2FAA2C686"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any information that can be used to distinguish or trace an individual’s identity, such as name, prior legal name, alias, mother’s maiden name, social security number, date or place of birth, address, phone number, or biometric data;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9334AF5EA5D54C27BC6256DE3AF61BAB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any information that is linked or linkable to an individual, such as medical, financial, education, consumer, or employment information, data, or records; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD9914C646C0B493EBFEF4A429BAFA4EC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other sensitive private information that is linked or linkable to a specific identifiable individual, such as gender identity, sexual orientation, or any sexually intimate visual depiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7C5F834A8764477C870A23B2477073BE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Terrorists</header><text>The term <quote>terrorists</quote> refers to—</text> <subparagraph id="HF46B26F26C76423DB59D3430946B3712"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any designated Foreign Terrorist Organization (FTO);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7B5AEEC5A39841468829A644627BDDAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any group or actor supporting activities that may be covered by section 2331(5) of title 18, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H936184DEC2EC4129BD1812B3133A810F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any group or actor investigated by the intelligence community pursuant to the intelligence review represented by <quote>Domestic Violent Extremism Poses Heightened Threat in 2021</quote>, 01 March 2021.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE5EB30886C34248B385245810A05930"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Foreign malign actor</header><text>The term <quote>foreign malign actor</quote> refers to any foreign adversary entities covered by section 5322(e)(2) of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3059">50 U.S.C. 3059(e)(2)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H0B979869390944168135E9F331D0D50A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of construing this Act and amendments made by this Act, the following shall apply:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB45EBD9D7DCE48398EB86D8201B2C8CD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorities</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to confer any authority, including law enforcement authority, beyond that which is authorized under existing law.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0B96A91B018F451683A10C5FFB3881D6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Constitutional protections</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to prohibit any constitutionally protected speech, expressive conduct or activities (regardless of whether compelled by, or central to, a system of religious belief), including the exercise of religion protected by the First Amendment and peaceful picketing or demonstration. The Constitution does not protect speech, conduct, or activities consisting of planning for, conspiring to commit, or committing an act of violence.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD845F21AD6BD4D1298907F253230BB55"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Privacy</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to preempt or conflict with existing Federal privacy laws, except in circumstances listed herein.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0D53910E3E0A4CA589E7384CB682B234"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Free expression</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to allow prosecution based solely upon an individual’s expression of racial, religious, political, or other beliefs or solely upon an individual’s membership in a group advocating or espousing such beliefs.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


