<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEB24B19A27674582B9E12E0858AD6A5C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3906 IH: Rural Opportunity Zone and Investment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3906</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230607">June 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to establish special rules for capital gains invested in rural opportunity zones.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7F9B6A77DBF14A49A91D864D3234835F" style="OLC"><section id="HD4B0345364DB44C980675FF3E01BAB9A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Opportunity Zone and Investment Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA4C1B186DB864E9CBA76A243C848699A" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of special rules for capital gains invested in rural opportunity zones</header><subsection id="HB48B38A6D77D4B1AAE565D3B0D24C3DE" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter Z of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2413C4806D9C43B1B34B6F05BC67D9B6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H5C13E1ADF4D54FAF8CCA9C19380A006B" commented="no"><enum>1400Z–3.</enum><header>Special rules for capital gains invested in rural opportunity zones</header><subsection id="HD214E3140944484CBBCF3B235BFF840E" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H85D841E0B6A848968A4562A0A2F37E3B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Treatment of gains</header><text>In the case of capital gain from the sale to, or exchange with, an unrelated person of any property held by the taxpayer, at the election of the taxpayer—</text><subparagraph id="H72DE90DD951B4273A95564BEFB8E7D3E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">gross income for the taxable year shall not include so much of such gain as does not exceed the aggregate amount invested by the taxpayer in a qualified rural opportunity fund during the 180-day period beginning on the date of such sale or exchange,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H007F405DC2514B68BA50772FA414F3A4" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount of gain excluded by subparagraph (A) shall be included in gross income as provided by subsection (b), and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1904CE6DCE204A4B94B624A4FC5CED97" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>subsection (c) shall apply.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H159F5B5759024A539D2DD1559F2F8987" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Election</header><text>No election may be made under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H9D23C18A4ABE412F83B6C9C6896423E6" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to a sale or exchange if an election previously made with respect to such sale or exchange is in effect, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA47B77BD34C440F085CAAED02FE02CC8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to any sale or exchange after December 31, 2032.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3C9C930305C74CD0AAB302755ED45D54" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deferral of gain invested in qualified rural opportunity zone property</header><paragraph id="H2A1774D73FB843A08A1C8A41B4AAF0D8" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Year of inclusion</header><text>Gain to which subsection (a)(1)(B) applies shall be included in income in the taxable year which includes the earlier of—</text><subparagraph id="HCA63C4740F3B44128B68431C5CB45AA0" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the date on which such investment is sold or exchanged, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA652C8EBBAC34D99B876821440F77328" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">December 31, 2032.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4E4E85C59F84652AEF6EAC6FB1B0F90" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount includible</header><subparagraph id="H54DBAD90FAD945FEB786781C76211E3C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amount of gain included in gross income under subsection (a)(1)(A) shall be the excess of—</text><clause id="H9220F6CC29394A958EFE31A7A5F5E06E" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the lesser of the amount of gain excluded under paragraph (1) or the fair market value of the investment as determined as of the date described in paragraph (1), over</text></clause><clause id="H8A550805510240A09846EF5097EEEFE1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the taxpayer’s basis in the investment.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11F6079EA8BE42839B7EC0D000FD66AE" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Determination of basis qualified rural opportunity zone property</header><clause id="HC9F31C0138F1415A955227380A67BB75" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as otherwise provided in this clause or subsection (c), the taxpayer’s basis in the investment shall be zero.</text></clause><clause id="H433C6AE3F5F44FABA6DB2BE6F311B2C8" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Increase for gain recognized under subsection (a)(1)(b)</header><text>The basis in the investment shall be increased by the amount of gain recognized by reason of subsection (a)(1)(B) with respect to such property.</text></clause><clause id="H43549CB8EAA2400DA1171FF1818750DA" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Investments held for 5 years</header><text>In the case of any investment held for at least 5 years, the basis of such investment shall be increased by an amount equal to 10 percent of the amount of gain deferred by reason of subsection (a)(1)(A).</text></clause><clause id="H7AB171ACD56F48368B09F94B92A0E76E" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Investments held for 7 years</header><text>In the case of any investment held by the taxpayer for at least 7 years, in addition to any adjustment made under clause (iii), the basis of such property shall be increased by an amount equal to 5 percent of the amount of gain deferred by reason of subsection (a)(1)(A).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B0A4A281A4A4DC69440F18A4183DEB2" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Special rule for investments held for at least 10 years</header><text>In the case of any investment held by the taxpayer for at least 10 years and with respect to which the taxpayer makes an election under this subsection, the basis of such property shall be equal to the fair market value of such investment on the date that the investment is sold or exchanged.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA94A0019E45D47709EB33DF648816306" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Qualified rural opportunity fund</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="HCC24D0731BE942BC8C0AB30B1234FB5E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified rural opportunity fund</term> means any investment vehicle which is organized as a corporation or a partnership for the purpose of investing in qualified rural opportunity zone property (other than another qualified rural opportunity fund) that holds at least 90 percent of its assets in qualified rural opportunity zone property, determined by the average of the percentage of qualified rural opportunity zone property held in the fund as measured—</text><subparagraph id="H157AD0DCCEF44D8981BB8D23556C8F2E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>on the last day of the first 6-month period of the taxable year of the fund, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96433AC11303493CBC81AA50EADFC8FE" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on the last day of the taxable year of the fund.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D850E81428A4FD481DF46EF31BAD4A8" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified rural opportunity zone property</header><subparagraph id="H7D561B6068494D9CB87BA525AB4BF654" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified rural opportunity zone property</term> means property which is—</text><clause id="H70940E2D3E5D44FEABF39171D0A99B32" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">qualified rural opportunity zone stock,</text></clause><clause id="HF126AFEC7EDE4B2EA79173C35553FEA3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">qualified rural opportunity zone partnership interest, or</text></clause><clause id="HDF43E1ABDCF7469D9A01BFE9FA96C348" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">qualified rural opportunity zone business property.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCF8A0EEFC45F48BEA83178327BF308C8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Qualified rural opportunity zone stock</header><clause id="H68B90876C630493CBC37FE07888EE73B" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), the term <term>qualified rural opportunity zone stock</term> means any stock in a domestic corporation if—</text><subclause id="H7BDED9711A784A4B8AFBE9174F01590B" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such stock is acquired by the qualified rural opportunity fund after December 31, 2023, at its original issue (directly or through an underwriter) from the corporation solely in exchange for cash,</text></subclause><subclause id="H22201B9434B049EEBAE1EAB0D6183690" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as of the time such stock was issued, such corporation was a qualified rural opportunity zone business (or, in the case of a new corporation, such corporation was being organized for purposes of being a qualified rural opportunity zone business), and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0E586DEE02F94F05BED8BBA9268C7D2A" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during substantially all of the qualified rural opportunity fund’s holding period for such stock, such corporation qualified as a qualified rural opportunity zone business.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9BEBE97B8F5D4FDDB62D4D48E77F9CAC" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Redemptions</header><text>A rule similar to the rule of section 1202(c)(3) shall apply for purposes of this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70001FEC45A34DFE8E3F98069CFE56AC" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Qualified rural opportunity zone partnership interest</header><text>The term <term>qualified rural opportunity zone partnership interest</term> means any capital or profits interest in a domestic partnership if—</text><clause id="H290DC231276F4095A863A429B2BBFD8C" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such interest is acquired by the qualified rural opportunity fund after December 31, 2023, from the partnership solely in exchange for cash,</text></clause><clause id="H3B22CA94E6704B409D9F999122D2787E" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as of the time such interest was acquired, such partnership was a qualified rural opportunity zone business (or, in the case of a new partnership, such partnership was being organized for purposes of being a qualified rural opportunity zone business), and</text></clause><clause id="H8F4FE4E799D64487963AF0BC2E7689E8" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during substantially all of the qualified rural opportunity fund’s holding period for such interest, such partnership qualified as a qualified rural opportunity zone business.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D633F4909564EF7A1524CB520893FAC" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Qualified rural opportunity zone business property</header><clause id="HD46CD21C75704D0E8E23E5028D0966CF" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified rural opportunity zone business property</term> means tangible property used in a trade or business of the qualified rural opportunity fund if—</text><subclause id="H667FD3D315D4407CBEB384BDA7623641" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such property was acquired by the qualified rural opportunity fund by purchase (as defined in section 179(d)(2)) after December 31, 2023,</text></subclause><subclause id="HDEDFC33EE8DB4D9193F750DD7E255491" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the original use of such property in the qualified rural opportunity zone commences with the qualified rural opportunity fund or the qualified rural opportunity fund substantially improves the property, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H86C9FC1E64D24AF2A62698CC366D1F24" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during substantially all of the qualified rural opportunity fund’s holding period for such property, substantially all of the use of such property was in a qualified rural opportunity zone.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HA5B56C639D2D4F5C9D1342B8266A060C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Substantial improvement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A)(ii), property shall be treated as substantially improved by the qualified rural opportunity fund only if, during any 30-month period beginning after the date of acquisition of such property, additions to basis with respect to such property in the hands of the qualified rural opportunity fund exceed an amount equal to the adjusted basis of such property at the beginning of such 30-month period in the hands of the qualified rural opportunity fund.</text></clause><clause id="H2C411A5C42C046079B1394A3CFD66BAC" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Related party</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A)(i), the related person rule of section 179(d)(2) shall be applied pursuant to subsection (e)(2) in lieu of the application of such rule in section 179(d)(2)(A).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H93868A28494D4B1F8D51F3BA9445A92D" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualified rural opportunity zone business</header><subparagraph id="H3B55BEFEAB5B4C0390FFFAB00E1D49A2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified rural opportunity zone business</term> means a trade or business—</text><clause id="H362CC41E20A049608475110630ABA6D3" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in which substantially all of the tangible property owned or leased by the taxpayer is qualified rural opportunity zone business property (determined by substituting <quote>qualified rural opportunity zone business</quote> for <quote>qualified rural opportunity fund</quote> each place it appears in paragraph (2)(D)),</text></clause><clause id="H91A11B9592B946F3ACE7EF26587A2616" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>which satisfies the requirements of paragraphs (2), (4), and (8) of section 1397C(b), and</text></clause><clause id="H485CBF4EBD3E443EB2A6628965066A23" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>which is not described in section 144(c)(6)(B).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBCAA701D8ED4E6692B7FD2A07F27697" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A), tangible property that ceases to be a qualified rural opportunity zone business property shall continue to be treated as a qualified rural opportunity zone business property for the lesser of—</text><clause id="HE27EB05D21AD480CAA3ABB53B05B734D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>5 years after the date on which such tangible property ceases to be so qualified, or</text></clause><clause id="H56DEA9299C544336B69AC110AE879058" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the date on which such tangible property is no longer held by the qualified rural opportunity zone business.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FE84A98E7C740AFB6BD33EE75C5B051"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Qualified rural opportunity zone</header><subparagraph id="H7C1955B9AD164BD4AD61ECE820F05395"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified rural opportunity zone</term> means any population census tract which—</text><clause id="HB2C61918D9BD4FFB954D6F1AD325A546"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is located in a rural county, and </text></clause><clause id="HF44C8EDD71354B8F84721A2D72E8863E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is in persistent poverty (as determined by the Bureau of the Census as of the date of the enactment of this Act).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB38C486A1B1C438C9E781766C1846129"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rural county</header><text>The term <quote>rural county</quote> means any county if more than 50 percent of the census blocks which comprise such county are rural blocks (as determined by the Bureau of the Census as of the date of the enactment of this Act). A rule similar to section 143(k)(2)(D) shall apply for purposes of the preceding sentence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1096BB50D466428DA9AF751135A9DA27" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Applicable rules</header><paragraph id="HAF0F3D171814401EBE2C5098EDDD30A1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Treatment of investments with mixed funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any investment in a qualified rural opportunity fund only a portion of which consists of investments of gain to which an election under subsection (a) is in effect—</text><subparagraph id="H658D50BEDF9D4A28A73879917F49632B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such investment shall be treated as 2 separate investments, consisting of—</text><clause id="H3859B59A24E341EA9DCE33960F9D75AC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>one investment that only includes amounts to which the election under subsection (a) applies, and</text></clause><clause id="H59434EF2F0984B6191209A5284AC1937" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a separate investment consisting of other amounts, and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6746CFD985F45178DF70EB1393F0F0D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subsections (a), (b), and (c) shall only apply to the investment described in subparagraph (A)(i).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E204974748A4619AD86761955F139BE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Related persons</header><text>For purposes of this section, persons are related to each other if such persons are described in section 267(b) or 707(b)(1), determined by substituting <quote>20 percent</quote> for <quote>50 percent</quote> each place it occurs in such sections.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC4D91B49A294A4BA066D606BEC114DE" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Decedents</header><text>In the case of a decedent, amounts recognized under this section shall, if not properly includible in the gross income of the decedent, be includible in gross income as provided by section 691.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE923E45343E04F03B4C037892A5D0E2F" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Secretary shall prescribe such regulations as may be necessary or appropriate to carry out the purposes of this section, including—</text><subparagraph id="H9F68A726E6E74117B01033D92E94B281" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">rules for the certification of qualified rural opportunity funds for the purposes of this section,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F302C09D2EA4528BD3B8A0B020F8E1A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">rules to ensure a qualified rural opportunity fund has a reasonable period of time to reinvest the return of capital from investments in qualified rural opportunity zone stock and qualified rural opportunity zone partnership interests, and to reinvest proceeds received from the sale or disposition of qualified rural opportunity zone property, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C0186568F2F4A12A84A2F3FFE3539DA" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>rules to prevent abuse.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7E0F4C5D516F4D77AA0226BFA810968C" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Failure of qualified rural opportunity fund To maintain investment standard</header><paragraph id="H837357F4024F4107917410B0F2631232" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a qualified rural opportunity fund fails to meet the 90-percent requirement of subsection (d)(1), the qualified rural opportunity fund shall pay a penalty for each month it fails to meet the requirement in an amount equal to the product of—</text><subparagraph id="H0BCF14875FB9460BAA910448F23FF6A9" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the excess of—</text><clause id="H7DE3E6A2AF6E43DAB013347FABA30F29" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the amount equal to 90 percent of its aggregate assets, over</text></clause><clause id="HC9429456ED4A474BB610575CE388E229" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the aggregate amount of qualified rural opportunity zone property held by the fund, multiplied by</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7FBB5645E8774AF4BB7EB063B425877B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the underpayment rate established under section 6621(a)(2) for such month.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA20475D951E45A4A2F2B411D4B28145" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Special rule for partnerships</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case that the qualified rural opportunity fund is a partnership, the penalty imposed by paragraph (1) shall be taken into account proportionately as part of the distributive share of each partner of the partnership.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H274FD67CEBE04E2CBF42E9D556212C59" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reasonable cause exception</header><text>No penalty shall be imposed under this subsection with respect to any failure if it is shown that such failure is due to reasonable cause.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H5DD389393A0D485CBF9956D10A65B092" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for subchapter Z of chapter 1 of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H48A17E9245804EC59BE270097B8CA59A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="yes-regeneration"><toc-entry idref="H5C13E1ADF4D54FAF8CCA9C19380A006B" level="section">Sec. 1400Z–3. Special rules for capital gains invested in rural opportunity zones.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H2C9FED6C9E9747EBB74D8B623F7BBCE8" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to amounts invested after the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

