<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4E517E507B2349BAB2FE84399A262170" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5211 IH: USPIS Surveillance Protection Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5211</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230815">August 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit funds from being used to implement the Internet Covert Operations Program under the United States Postal Inspection Service, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA482C7E90D9C4D6387BFF8D7DCDA3AC9" style="OLC"><section id="H77260835BC9C41B7B931ED604F91C69E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>USPIS Surveillance Protection Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCC8BB0F855644275AF6A4054D3F114DF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="H6FCC903C04A94AF5AF7744192C89E581"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States Postal Service has been operating a clandestine domestic surveillance program of Americans’ social media activity known as the Internet Covert Operations Program (iCOP).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB84BEC50525A47119AB62B95BAA01996"><enum>(2)</enum><text>iCOP is part of the United States Postal Inspection Service which is the law enforcement and security component of USPS.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4A9C0B96D154F04B77C17FD1A21C854"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A March 25, 2022, report by the USPS Inspector General stated: <quote>We determined that certain proactive searches iCOP conducted using an open-source intelligence tool from February to April 2021 exceeded the Postal Inspection Service’s law enforcement authority</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E630BF695FF4628A8BD7C494210EA03"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The USP Inspection Service is operating outside of its USPS jurisdiction when it monitors internet users’ sharing of information as its jurisdiction is narrowly defined within postal mail only.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F88251AD83A4F0DB53B5ACE6F6C5BEC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The iCOP program is a violation of privacy; it encroaches upon the private lives of Americans and seeks to curb constitutional rights of the First Amendment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99F79F0FE8384BA6AE0A8EAD3F0D84B5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>iCOP is not only illegal for operating outside of its stated jurisdiction, but also politically motivated in its target.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H601760CA7B0446CD90A1A879EB216AA8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on funding of program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No Federal funds (including amounts available in the Postal Service Fund established under section 2003 of title 39, United States Code) may be used to implement, conduct, or otherwise carry out the Internet Covert Operations Program operated by the United States Postal Inspection Service or any other domestic surveillance program with targets that do not have an identified connection to the mail, postal crimes, or the security of Postal Service facilities or personnel, or with politically motivated targets.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

