<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8DB132BE3C304A768E1EEEE31EBA88F1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3581 IH: Caregiver Outreach and Program Enhancement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3581</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to modify the family caregiver program of the Department of Veterans Affairs to include services related to mental health and neurological disorders, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCC30C2B3413346DAB12EF36EC0E2FD2B" style="OLC"><section id="HFF2BDC9EC58E4498B854E9A596FB26C0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Caregiver Outreach and Program Enhancement Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COPE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDE2699A7E814442FBE555E551B83C045"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority for Secretary of Veterans Affairs to award grants to entities to improve provision of mental health support to family caregivers of veterans</header><subsection id="H2F8EE5F1F4D34BA8B24A7F7C65D46A6F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/17">chapter 17</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H258195B6388C475AA356ACDDE2959287"><section id="H184944511CD04A10A2AE5B204102D29E"><enum>1720K.</enum><header>Grants to provide mental health support to family caregivers of veterans</header><subsection id="H09817AE46B0D4DFF8EE872D5F264661B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The Secretary may award grants to carry out, coordinate, improve, or otherwise enhance mental health counseling, treatment, or support to the family caregivers of veterans participating in the family caregiver program.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF413254A3B9A48928816E2A87FD61B9B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H5FCEAFFBB83240739E4745DC41EDCF72"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To be eligible for a grant under this section, an entity shall submit to the Secretary an application therefor at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49F1338ED47C417C98008871EFF0D9D1" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each application submitted under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="HEB251E3C135E4713A4F74B4AD6C0AEF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A detailed plan for the use of the grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B2B9B97B3BE427992D061677AC760C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the programs or efforts through which the entity will meet the outcome measures developed by the Secretary under subsection (g).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD7DE4EE0D2442F3AF9B4323F8BAA546"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of how the entity will distribute grant amounts equitably among areas with varying levels of urbanization.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25D1D33ADADF4285BAD3E1D5E80E172A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A plan for how the grant will be used to meet the unique needs of veterans residing in rural areas, American Indian or Alaska Native veterans, elderly veterans, women veterans, and veterans from other underserved communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB2216FD76D4470B880C9B422803C5C6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>The Secretary shall seek to ensure that grants awarded under this section are equitably distributed among entities located in States with varying levels of urbanization.</text></subsection><subsection id="H52BD830C52994D2794A5C794CDD9BEE9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>The Secretary shall prioritize awarding grants under this section that will serve the following areas:</text><paragraph id="HA54EAA26D4E9440B84ADF89696238088"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Areas with high rates of veterans enrolled in the family caregiver program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60C2A045FA7E46C6BC8F4AA8D939B608"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Areas with high rates of—</text><subparagraph id="H41163CC5F6D345A3AC289027BD72A075"><enum>(A)</enum><text>suicide among veterans; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAECB3BA3FB44413BB464070479833F1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>referrals to the Veterans Crisis Line.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD431B8B731348CC9EC42DD39302E4DA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Required activities</header><text>Any grant awarded under this section shall be used—</text><paragraph id="H1EF3DF7BC0754103810E04DC251B7283"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to expand existing programs, activities, and services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07BE668F554940CE9D01F1ABB7EC863D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to establish new or additional programs, activities, and services; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5704305E8F754178B6FB6156573AC3C0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for travel and transportation to facilitate carrying out paragraph (1) or (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1F2ADE1170049E4A76DFAD4242D6110"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Outcome measures</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE18FA01688AC44719A110CFD6D224A6A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall develop and provide to each entity that receives a grant under this section written guidance on the following:</text><subparagraph id="H7E0C50C8CF634644AA75DB444F23C5F2" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Outcome measures.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4F9BD5FB0D5412D834BF11CE7B2B543" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Policies of the Department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H839FAE32572C458488091D44B7F02A59" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In developing outcome measures under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consider the following goals:</text><subparagraph id="H5C1F045D808E4A94B716B2C72C445849"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Increasing the utilization of mental health services among family caregivers of veterans participating in the family caregiver program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCF87D7D276644DCBB1F154E69A0EFA1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Reducing barriers to mental health services among family caregivers of veterans participating in such program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H704FE1385E484180B06B81934513BBBA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Tracking requirements</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF534A499376F4D6DB31632624C6DBFFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Secretary shall establish appropriate tracking requirements with respect to the entities receiving a grant under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD240D8D5CFD3477BA0415484E80AC699" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Not less frequently than annually, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on such tracking requirements.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H34CD5DA8811641B3892493CD969E68D4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Performance review</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H55CD0A612AAC4A6ABBD5657F401FF2AD" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>review the performance of each entity that receives a grant under this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2ED9B62DEBE4E2B8B128F7071CD035C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make information regarding such performance publicly available.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H55C03BD039724E26BFEC3A60618BE6A1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Remediation plan</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H180A54A1C593423AA9887A558D346D16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In the case of an entity that receives a grant under this section and does not meet the outcome measures developed by the Secretary under subsection (g), the Secretary shall require the entity to submit to the Secretary a remediation plan under which the entity shall describe how and when it plans to meet such outcome measures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB5AC267267B4F589F17EE47EC8BB8D2" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Secretary may not award a subsequent grant under this section to an entity described in paragraph (1) unless the Secretary approves the remediation plan submitted by the entity under such paragraph.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4BDEE42A78A84DFCAE34FA44143D5DFD"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>The amount of a grant awarded under this section may not exceed 10 percent of amounts made available for grants under this section for the fiscal year in which the grant is awarded.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFBE281B0EF674377B1E73EC0BF536523"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Any grant awarded under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant funding that is otherwise available through the Department to provide mental health support among family caregivers of veterans participating in the family caregiver program.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC6F9C7D6B7CB472AB224C9B0D97B312F"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Outreach to family caregivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall include, in the outreach materials regularly mailed to a family caregiver who participates in the family caregiver program, notice of mental health support provided by recipients of grants under this section that are located in the relevant Veterans Integrated Service Network.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE00CFA924C3F4D049E4C35677BB2BCCD"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Funding</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6ACD49B00B37421896949D17B7756B69"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Amounts for the activities of the Department under this section shall be budgeted and appropriated through a separate appropriation account.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H384347051D69440BBB0ABB4931F1793E" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the budget justification materials submitted to Congress in support of the budget of the Department for any fiscal year (as submitted with the budget of the President under section 1105(a) of title 31), the Secretary shall include a separate statement of the amount requested to be appropriated for that fiscal year for the account specified in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HECA86B317D5C4F01A9DB75A62056068E"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary, for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2025, $50,000,000 to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9C964E834C994FFC82286042689CC374"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H6ECD6DC790134C12AFCA29718B2E16D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The terms <term>caregiver</term> and <term>family caregiver</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 1720G of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BE7558887A04826BAE7E14B132D8C74"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>family caregiver program</term> means the program of comprehensive assistance for family caregivers under section 1720G of this title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A3A421EB6F74C62A489E9B7E483695D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>Veterans Crisis Line</term> means the toll-free hotline for veterans established under section 1720F of this title.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HC7785F2E55B648BC921FE13E979FEA66"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections at the beginning of such subchapter is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H8FE9EFDC3558484B87E95A82CBBAB76A"><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="H184944511CD04A10A2AE5B204102D29E">1720K. Grants to provide mental health support to family caregivers of veterans.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HCAC1975E52474E3B95F91035F7622490"><enum>3.</enum><header>GAO report on mental health support for caregivers</header><subsection id="H55D8C3E23BE74769911242C5F94CB0ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the provision of mental health support to caregivers of veterans.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA42A81D033894EA7A84AD9989756C66F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report submitted under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H2908569DFD994D66822FE67713185535"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An assessment of the need for mental health support among caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H176B911BC14947D7A3B5CF962BAC0FD7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An assessment of options for mental health support in facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs and in the community for caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0C154BF8D7A4C25B3BE3570F72BABFD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An assessment of the availability and accessibility of mental health support in facilities of the Department and in the community for caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57001A9E5D6649BB9EF5A8D8FD8CAC18"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An assessment of the awareness among caregivers of the availability of mental health support in facilities of the Department and in the community for caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD775AD5306BD4300947C2AF3F868835E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An assessment of barriers to mental health support in facilities of the Department and in the community for caregivers participating in the caregiver programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H65A1F1DBE747416FA783AB3BF53076D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H00451C57B9C341D2A1EBC3724E7443DD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Caregiver</header><text>The term <term>caregiver</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1720G of title 38, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16C16E07C1B541CAAD87B54FDEFF3986"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Caregiver programs</header><text>The term <term>caregiver programs</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H236A35CA8CCB4EA195832883EC11B9BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the program of comprehensive assistance for family caregivers under subsection (a) of section 1720G of title 38, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H773A45AC1FD8477793B0C188017C7831"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the program of support services for caregivers under subsection (b) of such section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

