<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6CDFDFCAD29A487BAABE5EB7C9328C3C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3993 IH: To provide a private right of action against the maker of any component of a ghost gun, and any person who facilitated a sale of the ghost gun, for injury or death resulting from the use of the ghost gun.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3993</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide a private right of action against the maker of any component of a ghost gun, and any person who facilitated a sale of the ghost gun, for injury or death resulting from the use of the ghost gun.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCE94B569F8A94DCD94E690219D5610AA" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H94DFCCE9DE5745DB928E0BB072F76B1E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Private right of action</header>
<subsection id="HB09F130782AF4E20A5BCF2D658A4F15D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual who is injured, and any member of the family of an individual who is killed, by use of a ghost gun in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, and the State and the political subdivision of the State in which the injury or death occurs, may bring an action in the United States district court for the judicial district in which the injury or death occurs against the maker of any component of the ghost gun or any person who facilitated any sale of the ghost gun, for damages resulting from the injury or death. The court may award a plaintiff prevailing in such an action such damages, including consequential damages, as the court deems appropriate.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2F5BE13763C74FB6BD51C6F59853B902"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Affirmative defenses</header><text>In an action brought under subsection (a), it shall be an affirmative defense that the injury or death was caused by conduct of—</text>
<paragraph id="H3D10F67BD7754E6CAFCF2219A3333637"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an individual in defense against a reasonably perceived imminent threat to the safety of an individual not engaged in a violation of criminal law; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B26CB556E724595AE3C1197CBDAC2DF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a law enforcement officer in response to a reasonably perceived imminent threat to public safety.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H583C0068FE614ECABF2003596688C685"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H6505209C330948848697215E36A9B4D3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Ghost gun</header><text>The term <term>ghost gun</term> means a firearm that lacks a unique serial number engraved or cast on the frame or receiver of the firearm by a licensed manufacturer or licensed importer in accordance with section 923(i) of title 18, United States Code, and includes any combination of parts designed or intended to be assembled, or to be used in converting a device, into a firearm.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H15CAD315551747B2B1B5A7577D28BC38"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other terms</header><text>The terms <term>firearm</term>, <term>licensed manufacturer</term>, and <term>licensed importer</term> have the meanings given the terms, respectively, in section 921(a) of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

