<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0341B4F1DE5A4615B06E50BEA84FD28E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1404 IH: Facial Recognition and Biometric Technology Moratorium Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1404</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230307">March 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit biometric surveillance by the Federal Government without explicit statutory authorization and to withhold certain Federal public safety grants from State and local governments that engage in biometric surveillance.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6B9035A1C78F4202ADC90523F4345BA4" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H7605B0BE0DFE419FAED08874F7866D41"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Facial Recognition and Biometric Technology Moratorium Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HD7EBE3C90A7F4DA3A7B84565EE9F0C2C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H002E4E42A9F44CEBA705102952C8C616"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Biometric surveillance system</header><text>The term <term>biometric surveillance system</term> means any computer software that performs facial recognition or other remote biometric recognition in real time or on a recording or photograph. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD16427F936D34311B66A1222333D28D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Byrne grant program</header><text>The term <term>Byrne grant program</term> means the grant program authorized under subpart 1 of part E of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10151">34 U.S.C. 10151 et seq.</external-xref>), whether characterized as the Edward Byrne Memorial State and Local Law Enforcement Assistance Programs, the Local Government Law Enforcement Block Grants Program, the Edward Byrne Memorial Justice Assistance Grant Program, or otherwise. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26F1B8AB8B1A45D7B1FC494A22251D64"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Facial recognition</header><text>The term <term>facial recognition</term> means an automated or semi-automated process that—</text><subparagraph id="HF35560CE768B4F4A9A6C56CA36FC9C76"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assists in identifying an individual, capturing information about an individual, or otherwise generating or assisting in generating surveillance information about an individual based on the physical characteristics of the individual’s face; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42425A323B8C4B4AA58B3E94DFC5CC3C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>logs characteristics of an individual’s face, head, or body to infer emotion, associations, activities, or the location of an individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H84D03CA607084DAEB0DE6D54FA37ED4D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal official</header><text>The term <term>Federal official</term> means any officer, employee, agent, contractor, or subcontractor of the United States Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC4DEA54725E4610ADD8673CA34EE8DE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>In the united states</header><text>The term <term>in the United States</term> means all areas within the external boundary of the United States, its territories and possessions, including airports, ports of entry, and border zones. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H348C6ABEC5C44284AD22F4FF2BEE6D6F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Other remote biometric recognition</header><text>The term <term>other remote biometric recognition</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H9E91A6D993464EC08A83BE571BD9F25F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means an automated or semi-automated process that—</text><clause id="HBFB5FAB7CAB2441FAFD5DAE5674E3296"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assists in identifying an individual, capturing information about an individual, or otherwise generating or assisting in generating surveillance information about an individual based on the characteristics of the individual’s gait or other immutable characteristic ascertained from a distance; </text></clause><clause id="H5F0C80CB35FF47C395953681C208C07B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>uses voice recognition technology; or </text></clause><clause id="H0BCBB6E39F7C4BB8B881AE8726E02626"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>logs such characteristics to infer emotion, associations, activities, or the location of an individual; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF55FD7DEED1840A29B3A05F7636E6895"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include identification based on fingerprints or palm prints.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD86C76E907CC42C68E79E773220949A6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Voice recognition technology</header><text>The term <term>voice recognition technology</term> means the automated or semi-automated process that assists in identifying or verifying an individual based on the characteristics of an individual’s voice. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HA1D7CABF72E540AB97A42085E46B9755"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal Government use of biometric surveillance</header><subsection id="HD3ED5120C49F47C788189CF072DA8BD8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), it shall be unlawful for any Federal agency or Federal official, in an official capacity, to acquire, possess, access, or use in the United States—</text><paragraph id="H75849151AAEF4B788A5273A86B6D5E1E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any biometric surveillance system; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C9934468F62490A884963C9AA04CD87"><enum>(2)</enum><text>information derived from a biometric surveillance system operated by another entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H30A91ECF6471452B8620CD1A08092E9D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The prohibition set forth in subsection (a) does not apply to activities explicitly authorized by an Act of Congress that describes, with particularity—</text><paragraph id="H20F4C20EC1B24848A9E2FF4735737D3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the entities permitted to use the biometric surveillance system, the specific type of biometric authorized, the purposes for such use, and any prohibited uses;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H591A5A4D673F4F1B95AFDCB1B22EE38D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>standards for use and management of information derived from the biometric surveillance system, including data retention, sharing, access, and audit trails;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB99B9DABBD7D412AB30E918462B94625"><enum>(3)</enum><text>auditing requirements to ensure the accuracy of biometric surveillance system technologies, standards for minimum accuracy rates, and accuracy rates by gender, skin color, and age;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32460A66209945208556469006631BE6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>rigorous protections for due process, privacy, free speech and association, and racial, gender, and religious equity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD82355A2940144248F108B63DC93CE9A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>mechanisms to ensure compliance with the provisions of the Act. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF29D4BAD2D744D39A126D0841F8CBCF0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Judicial investigations and proceedings</header><paragraph id="H94C7E6A39C7146FF9C3C6F9EE29233B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Admissibility</header><text>Except in a judicial investigation or proceeding alleging a violation of this section, information obtained in violation of this section is not admissible by the Federal Government in any criminal, civil, administrative, or other investigation or proceeding.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C9CC6F00D2241F9B1110EB9E28BEBDC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cause of action</header><subparagraph id="HF48A3E34F10F4DE4B4F4234097498A89"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A violation of this section constitutes an injury to any individual aggrieved by a violation of this Act. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC90F0E9B2FDB4D73A1DB3A98581D81C8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Right to sue</header><text>An individual described in subparagraph (A) may institute proceedings against the Federal Government whose official is alleged to have violated this section for the relief described in subparagraph (D) in any court of competent jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB1C275EE8BE644CAB7CA2C375C7C8149"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Enforcement by state attorneys general</header><text>The chief law enforcement officer of a State, or any other State officer authorized by law to bring actions on behalf of the residents of a State, may bring a civil action, as parens patriae, on behalf of the residents of that State in an appropriate district court of the United States to enforce this Act, whenever the chief law enforcement officer or other State officer has reason to believe that the interests of the residents of the State have been or are being threatened or adversely affected by a violation of this Act. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAACBE49E60E14F5ABCF43D7CE70EFC42"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Relief</header><text>In a civil action brought under subparagraph (B) in which the plaintiff prevails, the court may award—</text><clause id="H2C70FB4C8549454DA74CF13E8B36A824"><enum>(i)</enum><text>actual damages;</text></clause><clause id="HF1C0BA1873E4406889B37A47AF7D626F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>punitive damages;</text></clause><clause id="HE2AD1DD69CAC47999D40C6D69AD3A195"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>reasonable attorneys’ fees and costs; and</text></clause><clause id="H2BCF9F5E4641477686E386EEF0205745"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any other relief, including injunctive relief, that the court determines to be appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H732D4F22CB9E4AF897705BC4A9D82759"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Civil penalties</header><text>Any Federal official who is found to have violated this section may be subject to retraining, suspension, termination, or any other penalty, as determined in an appropriate tribunal, subject to applicable due process requirements.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9003AD93C6E64BD98C1B59577581DDAE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Federal funding</header><paragraph id="H04841485D95143CCB23442CD8320BE75"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No Federal funds may be obligated or expended by a Federal law enforcement agency for the purchase or use of a biometric surveillance system.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1768A37C50548EDB0C5C5E15FB17BCF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Unallocated funds</header><text>No Federal agency may use any unallocated funds appropriated to the agency for the purchase or use of a biometric surveillance system. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C10DA6D7A0E4153B1FD345D6E590A3D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed—</text><paragraph id="HE3619C09DAE043E9B665E2046B820B64"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to prohibit the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) from testing or researching biometric surveillance systems or other remote biometric recognition technologies in commercial use; or </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC4B418034D04FCC8FD48FF82E57ACF5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to preempt or supersede any Federal, State, or local law that imposes a more stringent limitation than the limitations described in this section.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2A50187E9996405E9C413E050E06BBC3"><enum>4.</enum><header>Moratorium on State and local government use of biometric surveillance systems</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5669EF5407CE40DAB24F4E9F65689D7A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal financial assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the first day of the first fiscal year beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act, a State or unit of local government is ineligible to receive Federal financial assistance under the Byrne grant program unless the State or unit of local government is complying with a law or policy that is substantially similar to the prohibition set forth in section 3(a). </text></subsection><subsection id="H66409E3F9E1343D393090111E4C889F5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to preempt or supersede any Federal, State, or local law that imposes a more stringent limitation than the prohibition set forth in section 3(a).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

