<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1280CE6B69624767885DF2C912BB631C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 560 IH: Northern Marianas Population Stabilization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 560</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend section 6 of the Joint Resolution entitled <quote>A Joint Resolution to approve the Covenant To Establish a Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands in Political Union with the United States of America, and for other purposes</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H360B3C4BDCE7428BA5D8DE65DFB75529" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HC20D6E875BCA4EDAA44B310DB8B9668D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Northern Marianas Population Stabilization Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H825E82981E724243AD883C89E0125E78"><enum>2.</enum><header>Long-term legal residents of the commonwealth of the northern mariana islands</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(e)(6)(B) of the Joint Resolution entitled <quote>A Joint Resolution to approve the Covenant To Establish a Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands in Political Union with the United States of America, and for other purposes</quote>, approved March 24, 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/48/1806">48 U.S.C. 1806</external-xref>), is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7F2AFDF6A51C4DC9A1E54971B4EF87DC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by inserting <quote>except in the case of an alien who meets the requirements of subclause (VI) of clause (v),</quote> before <quote>resided continuously and lawfully</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC456B876D32A4483B1FF336922409DC6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (v)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF67EFD59329340749677EE361571A933"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subclause (IV), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBC97C5FC19F24EC9A25B0C74A966E166"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subclause (V), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>;</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE77A48D36D3E47888C64D20ACD5CE104"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H90874ABAB5AD4625837FCDA30634D950" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subclause id="H58A267972E854450BA6DC99C03685BEE"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>was admitted to the Commonwealth as a Commonwealth Only Transitional Worker during fiscal year 2015, and during every subsequent fiscal year beginning before the date of the enactment of the Northern Mariana Islands U.S. Workforce Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/218">Public Law 115–218</external-xref>); or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3EFE7DBAD7CF4E6C861EEB686289695C"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>resided in the Northern Mariana Islands as an investor under Commonwealth immigration law, and is presently a resident classified as a CNMI-only nonimmigrant under section 101(a)(15)(E)(ii) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(15)(E)(ii)</external-xref>).</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H7F4BC23B5621423B836B16FB021B5FE4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Determination of budgetary effects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The budgetary effects of this Act, for the purpose of complying with the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010, shall be determined by reference to the latest statement titled <quote>Budgetary Effects of PAYGO Legislation</quote> for this Act, submitted for printing in the Congressional Record by the Chairman of the House Budget Committee, provided that such statement has been submitted prior to the vote on passage.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

