<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAA913F6863D64D888FAF25A197DDD43D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5509 IH: Electronic Permitting Modernization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5509</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To modernize permitting systems at the Department of the Interior, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB2756F9289CA4368901C00C1BF6A382A" style="OLC"><section id="HB4DDEBE9F72B4B9698BE19BA5E5D4300" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Electronic Permitting Modernization Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H2B4E399139514346A6908EEAC5BF3671"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of the Interior permit accessibility</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In order to improve the overall economy, efficiency, and management of operations and activities of the Department of the Interior (referred to in this section as the <quote>Department</quote>), reduce paperwork, and provide high-quality services and access to the public, the Secretary of the Interior shall, to the extent practicable—</text><paragraph id="H76B8B942657B4A0880E991C78D677530"><enum>(1)</enum><text>design and deliver modernized electronic permitting systems to accept, process, and record applications (including plan submissions, payment activity, and other related correspondence) for permits, forms, and other paperwork required for activities regulated by the Department;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D52283F87574AF190392B9A76AF94B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text> provide a centralized electronic permitting system online repository, available to the public on the Department’s website, that includes—</text><subparagraph id="HAD2E3EE832974BBF93C435E7AA3F0723"><enum>(A)</enum><text>hyperlinks to facilitate navigation to all Department electronic permitting systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11935F679C3A47519DA488E62CC704DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to permits, the contact information for the appropriate Department employees providing assistance to State, Tribal, and local governments; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H89F14E3CC84246FAAECBEDB177B6F6FD"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide to the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate periodic updates on the implementation of paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

