<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1C74CF20E77F42C4B06F1F19DABC4B8A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6852 IH: Holcombe Rucker Park Landmark Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6852</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To designate Holcombe Rucker Park, in Harlem, New York, as a National Commemorative Site, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEE32ADF96C2C43CEB32C2CE2985A5E2B" style="OLC"><section id="H67161E7E5C244DD29AC286D75689CEA4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Holcombe Rucker Park Landmark Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4AD48D341EE6443E89D1CC9F7D917740" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text><paragraph id="HAF0E10043A614B5FB4CD1E854063E48D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Holcombe Rucker Park is located between West 155th Street, 8th Avenue, and Harlem River Drive in Manhattan, New York.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CD13EDF3E2B4507823E7168D7E998AB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The park has been a source of inspiration, entertainment, and education for many people who have played or witnessed basketball games at the park, also serving as a showcase of talent, creativity, and diversity that reflects the spirit of Harlem.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C3DE27480B647549D522FDC9CB14A63"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In 1974, this playground was renamed Holcombe Rucker Park after NYC Parks’ beloved Playground Director, Holcombe Rucker, at the request of Rucker’s protégés.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FD65A3861754AFA9375549A44B16C57"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Holcombe Rucker (1926–1965) is remembered for the basketball tournaments he founded at this court and the generations of players he mentored.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC573D3A58B594E13A29AABD6285B9539"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The basketball tournaments at the park’s Greg Marius Court have been the subject of three films: Above the Rim, On Hallowed Ground: Streetball Champions of Rucker Park, and The Real: Rucker Pro Legends and Fathers of the Sport.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB77C840C9BF64497850C88FAF69761D4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Born and raised in Manhattan and schooled at Benjamin Franklin High School, Rucker worked as a Playground Director for NYC Parks at various Harlem parks from 1948 to 1964.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18BC9AFE0FEA4B02BC5B031D21F6FF7A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>A pioneer of social justice and racial equality in sports, Rucker created his own basketball tournament to serve as a platform to promote integration and empower the black community.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8742600ED3CE4B31A12D6B89C3071418"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The park is considered the birthplace of streetball, a style of basketball that emphasizes creativity, flair, and individual skills over formal rules and team play.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A9FACE1810645DA81B7B06305E373CA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Many NBA legends and stars have played at Holcombe Rucker Park, either before or after their professional careers, such as Kareem Abdul-Jabbar, Wilt Chamberlain, Julius Erving, Kobe Bryant, Kevin Durant, and LeBron James.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5EA32315BE944F9DA1686D37BD5196FC" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The park has been featured in many documentaries, movies, books, and video games that celebrate the history and culture of streetball. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB308959422374BEA8B5DC95228091648"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Holcombe Rucker Park is home to the Entertainer’s Basketball Classic (EBC), founded in 1982 by Greg Marius, a rapper who wanted to showcase the talent and entertainment value of streetball, and has since become one of the most prestigious and popular streetball tournaments in the world.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B36D5306E934C25936A0DE15A5B1033"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The park has served as a platform for many basketball players who could not obtain NBA opportunities due to racial discrimination or other barriers, including Earl <quote>The Goat</quote> Manigault, Joe <quote>The Destroyer</quote> Hammond, Pee Wee Kirkland, and Herman <quote>Helicopter</quote> Knowings.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB4C1DBB49311465CBAB3E405E1110E68"><enum>3.</enum><header>National Commemorative Site</header><subsection id="H6FFC4D9597FB43B2B1550376D911C03A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Holcombe Rucker Park, in Harlem, New York, is designated as the <quote>Holcombe Rucker Park National Commemorative Site</quote> (referred to in this section as the <quote>Commemorative Site</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HCBB74FDBC2674B3F9C879D3C98BD3F64"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effect of designation</header><text>The Commemorative Site shall not be considered a unit of the National Park System.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2F7D100C8C534C1ABA79F01A209C712C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No effect on actions of property owners</header><text>The designation of the Commemorative Site under this section shall not prohibit any actions that may otherwise be taken by a property owner (including any owner of the Commemorative Site) with respect to the property of the owner.</text></subsection><subsection id="H90D48ABD92134C6D9385DCE8DCBBA54B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No effect on administration</header><text>Nothing in this section affects the administration of the Commemorative Site by New York City or the State of New York.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

