<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H37C0BADB27DF4CF6918D732736001519" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 990 IH: State Accountability, Flexibility, and Equity for Hospitals Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 990</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XIX of the Social Security Act to establish a methodology for determining State allotments for Medicaid disproportionate share hospital payments that is based on State poverty levels, to require States to prioritize disproportionate share hospital payments on the basis of Medicaid inpatient utilization and low-income utilization rates, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H35F438810E5C4E768DC7329609B23C43" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HA41BBCFB2B7B4B87A5EEE32704EF20F7"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>State Accountability, Flexibility, and Equity for Hospitals Act of 2023</short-title></quote>, or the <quote><short-title>SAFE Hospitals Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA8141E8AF7454FDDB0E45D7793880852"><enum>2.</enum><header>Determination of State DSH allotments based on State poverty levels</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1923(f) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-4">42 U.S.C. 1396r–4(f)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HEAE73D371A9244C4B96D2C4C8802E659"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><subparagraph id="HDBC2DCD486D1454AAC785807CA44AFD8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the paragraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="traditional">year 2003 and thereafter</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="traditional">years 2003 through 2025</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H36BBCB2F2C024891BCA66AA909B79386"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H12CAF2785E3A4A7BB755590A46FFCA5D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>, (7), and (8)</quote> and inserting <quote>and (7)</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HAF1FC276E04B47BD95F480C4EDE9A559"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>through fiscal year 2025</quote> after <quote>each succeeding fiscal year</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4F3D84D55E546C4BBCE9D376B6EBCF2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)(ii), by inserting <quote>through fiscal year 2025</quote> after <quote>each succeeding fiscal year</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H070AC02CE47840E0B99C76FAECA810CC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E)(i)(III), by inserting <quote>or paragraph (7), as applicable,</quote> after <quote>this paragraph</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9413EDDB1CED4EB49DAD1652CB34FDE3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)(C), by inserting <quote>or paragraph (7), as applicable,</quote> after <quote>paragraph (3)</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H030A56F45D1C4F93AE17D7B3EFCC6283"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(B)—</text><subparagraph id="H7B12FBC2170C4DAEB0243A989BF4AA12"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the subparagraph heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="traditional">and subsequent fiscal years</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="traditional">through fiscal year 2025</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED4D034F800849F4B89056ACCBAD40F7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by inserting <quote>through fiscal year 2025</quote> after <quote>any subsequent fiscal year</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF14255E36E7B4C5B96D1C1B71F58E67B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in clause (iii) of paragraph (6)(B)—</text><subparagraph id="HD24C87CA1D9047E6AAA5A33139D75A73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the clause heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="clause" style="traditional">through fiscal year 2025</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="clause" style="traditional">succeeding fiscal years</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81C42B78EFC74E74A9EE112ECBB7A4B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subclause (II)—</text><clause id="HF9E2E9BE642B4B81954057A182A01A86"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the subclause heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subclause" style="traditional">through fiscal year 2025</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="subclause" style="traditional">succeeding fiscal years</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HFC76F0E31DDD472BA762A723F41471E1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>through fiscal year 2025</quote> after <quote>each fiscal year thereafter</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BF12C084B934F67BADA45F66618B2E7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by striking paragraphs (7) and (8) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="H881B2D5D312F4CAF87CCB2F7EA508C35"><paragraph id="HD42A1E3DF3574BF89EB91ABEDCCCE1CD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State DSH allotments for fiscal years after fiscal year 2025</header><subparagraph id="HC5058DDB8F3D453AB146996F83356564"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraphs (B), (C), and (D), beginning with fiscal year 2026, the DSH allotment for a State and fiscal year shall be the amount equal to the product of—</text><clause id="H98DD639A98B64F30AC5FBEA0E01903D9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the State poverty ratio (as determined under subparagraph (E)(ii)) for the State and fiscal year; and</text></clause><clause id="HCC2510F1343E4ED5AE3B48C4A8733A9C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the DSH allotment cap (as determined under subparagraph (E)(i)) for the fiscal year.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B209D8CE7BB4AF4A38226AD37AC5F39"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Phase-in of poverty-based formula</header><clause id="HF6A38607892A46DAA2DA7731DC37D748"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>During the period of fiscal years described in clause (ii), the Secretary shall phase in the application of the determination of DSH allotments under subparagraph (A) in a manner that ensures that—</text><subclause id="HC734EE4D936143389C836F0788A54A68"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in no case is the DSH allotment for a State for a fiscal year during such period less than 90 percent of the DSH allotment for the State for the previous fiscal year (without regard to whether the State used the full amount of the DSH allotment for the previous fiscal year); and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE11BB83715B84D609D9F392AF10E3867"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total amount of DSH allotments made to all States for any fiscal year during such period does not exceed the DSH allotment cap determined for the fiscal year under subparagraph (E)(i).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HA18C1D00C97C42CE8985BB6914A63B2E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Phase-in period</header><text>The period of fiscal years described in this clause is the period that begins with fiscal year 2026 and ends with—</text><subclause id="H99B20F99F495431398AE247FD418A0BC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>fiscal year 2035; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HE53BAC3956024D66A160D5CB8C6B74BF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>at the Secretary's discretion, any of fiscal years 2036 through 2040.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H363BFA6A5522439FB612370B43973100"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Development of methodology</header><text>The Secretary shall promulgate final regulations that establish the methodology for determining State DSH allotments under clause (i) not later than January 1, 2025.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE4783EDC16B4557AC73437D1AE58DED"><enum>(C)</enum><header>State allotment flexibility option</header><clause id="HD803D21EDAC043C2B069E9BFC20EFF1B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State may elect to increase or reduce the amount of the DSH allotment for the State and a fiscal year (as otherwise determined under this paragraph) for the purpose of providing certainty or more consistent DSH funding in subsequent fiscal years in accordance with this subparagraph.</text></clause><clause id="H5202467B0DAE44A0A3209DA8836140E8"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>State option to reserve allotment amounts</header><text>For any fiscal year after fiscal year 2025, a State may request that the DSH allotment for the State and fiscal year (as otherwise determined under this paragraph) be reduced by an amount that shall not exceed 10 percent of the amount of the allotment as so determined.</text></clause><clause id="H18E60C0AA6D346C69D6AE0594CFE4A15"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>State option to increase DSH allotment from allotment reserve</header><text>For any fiscal year after fiscal year 2026, a State may request that the DSH allotment for the State and fiscal year (as otherwise determined under this paragraph) be increased by an amount that shall not exceed the DSH reserve amount for the State and fiscal year.</text></clause><clause id="H3F0ED66FBDED4A6494C117E63541D18A"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>DSH reserve amount</header><subclause id="HAEE2258F192A4485907F072D11A22AB1"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subclause (II), the DSH reserve amount for a State and fiscal year shall be equal to the sum of the amounts, if any, of any reductions to the State's DSH allotment (as otherwise determined under this paragraph) made in each of the preceding 5 fiscal years pursuant to a request under clause (ii).</text></subclause><subclause id="HB144FB3E6C8A430DABA17DBC4D571965"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Subtraction of increases from DSH reserve amount</header><text>The amount of any increase to a State's DSH allotment for a fiscal year made pursuant to a request under clause (iii) shall be subtracted from the State's DSH reserve amount for such year and shall not be available to the State in subsequent fiscal years.</text></subclause><subclause id="H528CE05CFEFC4D0B960CD73E030D7CB1"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Rule of application</header><text>In the case of an increase to a State's DSH allotment for a fiscal year that is less than the State's DSH reserve amount for such year, the Secretary shall apply subclause (II) in a manner that maximizes the DSH reserve amount that will remain available to the State in subsequent fiscal years.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H1850F90205834D9B8651A7386675AD0B"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Disregard of adjustments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any increase or reduction under this subparagraph to the DSH allotment of a State for a fiscal year shall be disregarded when otherwise determining State DSH allotments under this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF16261C2E704E58974E4CEA74EAB0D4"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Treatment of waivers</header><clause id="HB67DB0397E654CF5BD88E0EC019CD4E7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to clause (ii), with respect to a State and a fiscal year, if the State has in effect on the date of enactment of the <short-title>SAFE Hospitals Act of 2023</short-title> a statewide waiver of requirements of this title under section 1115 or other law and any part of the fiscal year occurs during the period of the waiver (as approved as of such date), the DSH allotment determined under this paragraph for such State and fiscal year shall not be less than the DSH allotment that would have been determined for such State and fiscal year under this section as in effect on the day before the date of enactment of the <short-title>SAFE Hospitals Act of 2023</short-title>, reduced, in the case of each of fiscal years 2026 through 2029, by the amount of the State's share of the reductions which would have been applicable for the fiscal year under paragraph (7) of this subsection (as so in effect), as estimated by the Secretary.</text></clause><clause id="H5A7D5B9C33494026B1D6D90E0176BAF0"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Total allotments not to exceed DSH allotment cap</header><text>The Secretary shall apply this subparagraph in such a manner that the total amount of DSH allotments determined for all States for a fiscal year under this paragraph does not exceed DSH allotment cap determined for the fiscal year under subparagraph (E)(i).</text></clause><clause id="H7D1F05D939BB43E68838861789963B93"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Nonapplication</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply—</text><subclause id="HC0C59373123C4D6583851DA369ED07E7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>with respect to a State that has in effect a waiver described in such clause if the State elects, through a revision of such waiver, that such clause will not apply; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H7B938911BD404A18A722ACFBE47019DF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with respect to any part of a fiscal year that occurs after the expiration (determined without regard to any extension approved after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>State Accountability, Flexibility, and Equity for Hospitals Act of 2023</short-title>) of such a waiver.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H887EFB0ABB0D4D5AA6EE247851A28755"><enum>(iv)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">No effect on waiver authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed as preventing the Secretary from approving a waiver under section 1115 or other law with respect to requirements under this title related to a State's use of its DSH allotment for a fiscal year.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EF38F03172F4F5784089B80A03DB8ED"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text><clause commented="no" id="H3AB110DF9C6449FFAF4C33161585EA86"><enum>(i)</enum><header>DSH allotment cap</header><text>The term <term>DSH allotment cap</term> means, with respect to a fiscal year, the amount equal to the total amount of the DSH allotments that would have been determined for all States for the fiscal year under this section as in effect on the day before the date of enactment of the <short-title>SAFE Hospitals Act of 2023</short-title>, reduced, in the case of fiscal years 2026 through 2029, by the aggregate amount of the reductions which would have been applicable for the fiscal year under paragraph (7) of this subsection (as so in effect).</text></clause><clause id="H6BA1225660F446939B097F517ED6CB54"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>State poverty ratio</header><text>The term <term>State poverty ratio</term> means, with respect to a State and fiscal year, the ratio of—</text><subclause id="H40228FD3AB594322B83584828D31DF2F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the number of individuals in the State in the most recent fiscal year for which census data are available whose income (as determined under section 1902(e)(14) (relating to modified adjusted gross income) and without regard to whether an individual's income eligibility for medical assistance is determined under such section) was less than 100 percent of the poverty line (as defined in section 2110(c)(5)) applicable to a family of the size involved; to</text></subclause><subclause id="HBFBE223527B245DE9524E7910E764B77"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the number of individuals in all States in the most recent fiscal year for which census data are available whose income (as so determined) was less than 100 percent of the poverty line (as so defined) applicable to the family of the size involved.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H970D5E1CCB0F4F2F99504543B4408462"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (9) as paragraph (8).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H77144623C54545F1A79B51C6FF3D18AC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prioritizing disproportionate share hospital payments based on Medicaid inpatient utilization and low-income utilization rates</header><subsection id="H163B3A444D764033BBBB06DEF5AC6815"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1923 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-4">42 U.S.C. 1396r–4</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H30A4689159BC4F2AA49EA3E43A462012"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(2)(D), by inserting <quote>(which, as of October 1, 2025, shall meet the requirements of subsection (k))</quote> after <quote>methodology</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61800765D88E4880B24AE7A4F91E387E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by striking <quote>and (g)</quote> and inserting <quote>, (g), and, beginning on October 1, 2025, (k)</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AED8D95245540AFAEF21526D4BE9ADC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(2)(A)—</text><subparagraph id="H3A463366B27945D596906DB155270275"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC559CA2AA494889A46DF6A0D4819669"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD813FA55E14C445A9479718D84DBAB42"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="H57C2BFB00EBD4595B0BA25F52936DFC7"><clause id="H0854A73A257240AA8C4C3590BE270B31"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that is an institution for mental diseases.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HADAE4B8FB0F34E5097822C3DA68EEF79"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" act-name="" id="HFDF3E94B40DF4972A56772C820227EBB"><subsection id="H32764F73B626473BA37FE92ACDCA3BE9"><enum>(k)</enum><header>State methodology requirements</header><paragraph id="HDF30571BEB6A45C290404CD3858EA0A0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (4), a State methodology for identifying and making payments to disproportionate share hospitals meets the requirements of this subsection if—</text><subparagraph id="H7B3253DD4D944927B6DD3F15AFC1BF46"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the methodology is uniformly applied statewide;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H04E941782DAD4C7B957CBFC74ED452C1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the methodology identifies each hospital in the State that is described in a disproportionate share hospital tier (as defined in paragraph (2)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA61FECFF06E94101885C734A21A47C96"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in making payments to disproportionate share hospitals, the methodology meets the requirements of paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H73FACF10F05E42018350258A574445CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disproportionate share hospital tiers</header><text>The term <term>disproportionate share hospital tier</term> means each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H4B840198287747FF8C10D9D69DE6A150"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Tier 1 hospitals</header><text>A category of hospitals (referred to in this section as <term>tier 1 hospitals</term>) in which each hospital satisfies—</text><clause commented="no" id="H0A893A5A01AC4E1CA5B825EC5D707644"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each of the criteria described in clause (ii) of subparagraph (B); and</text></clause><clause id="H7556B4603DFC4C708CF4572D475E82B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>one or more of the following criteria:</text><subclause id="H1EA318AC9BE148C3BF124B4B97CC3459"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The hospital has a Medicaid inpatient utilization rate (as defined in subsection (b)(2)) that is not less than 2 standard deviations above the mean Medicaid inpatient utilization rate for hospitals receiving Medicaid payments in the State.</text></subclause><subclause id="H1097506C9E3A4EF99082959AB0D94750"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The hospital has a low-income utilization rate (as defined in subsection (b)(3)) of not less than 40 percent.</text></subclause><subclause id="HA8480477580645E7BE73540A2369F077"><enum>(III)</enum><text>More than 70 percent of the inpatient days for which payments are received by the hospital are paid for under the Medicare program under title XVIII, the Medicaid program under this title, or the Children's Health Insurance Program under title XXI.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22427BFA485740AE9CE02145E214E55F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Tier 2 hospitals</header><text>A category of hospitals (referred to in this section as <term>tier 2 hospitals</term>) in which each hospital—</text><clause id="H037679C3AE8C4507BFD730D29EDDB668"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not described in the previous subparagraph; and</text></clause><clause id="H86B3F3E943974E19B76CF89AFAF6DA61"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>satisfies one or more of the following criteria:</text><subclause id="HB764A9E3B2B3495B83796A014BCCC39C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The hospital has a Medicaid inpatient utilization rate (as defined in subsection (b)(2)) that is not less than 1.5 standard deviations above the mean Medicaid inpatient utilization rate for hospitals receiving Medicaid payments in the State.</text></subclause><subclause id="H0341080284604357920845736D0AAE6E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The hospital has a low-income utilization rate (as defined in subsection (b)(3)) of not less than 35 percent.</text></subclause><subclause id="H659AEA6BD78244BDB7007387ED2250D4"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The hospital has the largest number of inpatient days attributable to individuals entitled to benefits under the State plan of any hospital in such State for the previous State fiscal year.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB2FEAD611DE444CB030CA376160A265"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Tier 3 hospitals</header><text>A category of hospitals (referred to in this section as <term>tier 3 hospitals</term>) in which each hospital—</text><clause id="HCF05427949BC4759A8AAD0F12F97C25C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not described in a previous subparagraph; and</text></clause><clause id="HEC5D0E47E879462EBD885391A2AFFD38"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>satisfies one or more of the following criteria:</text><subclause id="H62D634269ACA465AB432038E4A3B1DC8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The hospital has a Medicaid inpatient utilization rate (as defined in subsection (b)(2)) that is not less than the mean Medicaid inpatient utilization rate for hospitals receiving Medicaid payments in the State.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6F2EC6A31DDE44F6B71206108149770C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The hospital has a low-income utilization rate (as defined in subsection (b)(3)) of not less than 25 percent.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H033FDDBB920943829F5137A823D150DD"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Tier 4 hospitals</header><text>A category of hospitals (referred to in this section as <term>tier 4 hospitals</term>) in which each hospital—</text><clause id="HCF2DC759A75E42CD93F68DB1041F2CB5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is not described in a previous subparagraph; and</text></clause><clause id="H90A9C41829B2483DB169BF2CF51A8A75"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>satisfies the requirement described in subsection (d)(3).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF390507C4C5E441EBD3277B88C75ADC5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Payment methodology requirements</header><subparagraph id="H69A45558B23E40CEACD0E16A6683E3E4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Prioritization of hospitals</header><text>In making disproportionate share hospital payments, a State methodology shall prioritize hospitals in the following order:</text><clause id="H5517AF3824A74974814F0E4266456CF9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Tier 1 hospitals shall receive the highest priority.</text></clause><clause id="H84F9C3754FBE437F8E77337A266BA4D1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Tier 2 hospitals shall receive the second-highest priority.</text></clause><clause id="H43B2F463DCB4491FBAE0D715556D72B6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Tier 3 hospitals shall receive the third-highest priority.</text></clause><clause id="HDF04C08B9B0A45C09F7BFC8B53DCB15B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Tier 4 hospitals shall receive the fourth-highest priority.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DC744A9087B4B3DA0EEF3ADCE0DB3D7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Factors</header><text>The methodology specifies the factors that will be considered in determining the amount of a disproportionate share hospital payment to be made to a hospital, which may include—</text><clause id="HA7FCD10370AC49519E77A57C2E74EDF3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the hospital's net operating margins (including past net operating margins);</text></clause><clause id="HB186281603C54D4EA1B35F1AE926B836"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>past disproportionate share hospital payments to the hospital;</text></clause><clause id="HE2A0518471554E23AF0BB19CB33F1F41"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>whether the hospital was affected by a major disaster (as declared by the President under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act) in the 12 months prior to the payment; and</text></clause><clause id="HBB18D8222E0B4A658424CBF4B4088756"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other relevant factors, as determined by the State (subject to the approval of the Secretary).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H685412F8AD3C42F49F6A67F7E5CF399E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Consideration of financial circumstances of high tier hospitals</header><clause id="H8E063C9702B14BCA9233C65ED529FC4B"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The State shall certify that the State methodology adequately considers the unique financial circumstances of tier 1 hospitals and tier 2 hospitals, and takes necessary steps to mitigate net operating losses by such hospitals.</text></clause><clause id="H53D0984E4B26466EB9BA2D43CABAE558"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Guidance</header><subclause id="H153851C18B904AA4A2438EA48E980B70"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of the <short-title>SAFE Hospitals Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall issue guidance to States outlining methods that States may use to satisfy the requirement of this subparagraph.</text></subclause><subclause id="HBC1A2FFA4E92449BA9E2C5FCE320FE42"><enum>(II)</enum><header>State alternatives</header><text>Subject to the approval of the Secretary, a State may develop an alternative method for satisfying the requirement of this subparagraph.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC99A3E04684A4491BBFFA677A03D5ADA"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Treatment of IMDs and CAHs</header><text>The State shall specify how the methodology prioritizes institutions for mental diseases and critical access hospitals (as defined in section 1861(mm)(1)), but in no case shall institutions for mental diseases or critical access hospitals receive a higher priority than tier 1 hospitals.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2F4164F73D94258A181C442D9BBD7A8"><enum>(E)</enum><header>State authority to reclassify hospitals</header><text>Subject to the approval of the Secretary, for purposes of prioritizing disproportionate share payments under a State methodology under this subsection, a State may treat up to 15 percent of all disproportionate share hospitals in the State, excluding institutions for mental diseases, as belonging to a different disproportionate share hospital tier than the tier in which the hospitals are described under paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17A96139689A4ED488F9C954931B2AF6"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed as requiring a State to apply a uniform payment methodology to all hospitals within a disproportionate share hospital tier.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H06154CD8E95F416C904CF3A5C8EF175C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Methodology for States with fewer than 15 disproportionate share hospitals</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H52913D88E38047C8B556D35AC0FCEFF6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a State that has fewer than 15 disproportionate share hospitals, the State shall use the methodology for identifying and making payments to disproportionate share hospitals that is developed by the Secretary under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0A30C3D16F1C424587062CB29162B04B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Development of methodology</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of the <short-title>SAFE Hospitals Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall develop a methodology for identifying and making payments to disproportionate share hospitals for States that have fewer than 15 disproportionate share hospitals that prioritizes DSH payments to hospitals with disproportionately high volumes of Medicaid patients and low-income patients.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCF4967A3C45A4885BC0626A4F4E50B50"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No effect on waiver authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed as preventing the Secretary from approving a waiver under section 1115 or other law with respect to requirements under this subsection related to the methodology used by States to identify and make payments to disproportionate share hospitals.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HD21ECF9FE4DC41879650EA4E796887F9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Modification of cap on individual DSH payments</header><text>Section 1923(g)(1)(A)(i) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-4">42 U.S.C. 1396r–4(g)(1)(A)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(including any costs incurred by the hospital during the year that are associated with subsidizing a physician or a clinic or other health center that is owned and operated by, controlled by, or in common control with the hospital for the purpose of providing care to such individuals)</quote> after <quote>individuals described in subparagraph (B)</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDBE6FD86380D494481F3C01E45163F8A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Modification of DSH qualification requirements</header><paragraph id="HEA33DF65E211427F9671B41D0417B969"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 1923(d)(3) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-4">42 U.S.C. 1396r–4(d)(3)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>unless the hospital</quote> and all that follows through the period and inserting the following: “unless the hospital—</text><quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" act-name="" id="H6E6A7F9F3BE547BEA87F431EEE93AE01"><subparagraph id="HCE33083E29604DBD94C93D267818E65F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a Medicaid inpatient utilization rate (as defined in subsection (b)(2)) that is not more than 1 standard deviation below the mean Medicaid inpatient utilization rate for hospitals receiving Medicaid payments in the State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H382ED217691148279588F8867B59B85E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a low-income utilization rate (as defined in subsection (b)(3)) that is not less than 10 percent; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H592104CCF00342A4B659505D17778C81"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is a critical access hospital (as defined in section 1861(mm)(1)).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FA96E11424D4535B63F4891EE2222D6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall take effect on October 1, 2025.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

