<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H501BFAA745964432880A29B6B10E0FC3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4608 IH: Transportation Megaprojects Accountability and Oversight Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4608</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230713">July 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 23, United States Code, to establish additional requirements for certain transportation projects with estimated costs of $2,500,000,000 or more, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H04295D3874394D4BAF898AC8F0D9CBEF" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8E68E923707C49EFB4FB612787D3E1D1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Transportation Megaprojects Accountability and Oversight Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H687046FF22E44261959157156831E699"><enum>2.</enum><header>Additional requirements for certain transportation projects</header> <subsection id="HA6E9457084F84025892474E2B9608120"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 106 of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD50F4CC9CB5843D99A980CE3A9A306C3" style="USC"> 
<subsection id="HEFD28AD3F4F440C4854A0190DA84D4CF"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Megaprojects</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H303E3120254C47F1BB48C3B1A628690E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Megaproject defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>megaproject</term> means a project that has an estimated total cost of $2,500,000,000 or more, and such other projects as may be identified by the Secretary.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H784811EB1ACA4B5086B5D9FAFFB00850"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Comprehensive risk management plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of Federal financial assistance under this title for a megaproject shall, in order to be authorized for construction, submit to the Secretary a comprehensive risk management plan that contains—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA2542E1377A44579873B8C5627A77E67"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the process by which the recipient will identify, quantify, and monitor the risks that might result in cost overruns, project delays, reduced construction quality, or reductions in benefits with respect to the megaproject;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9574E2D96F7149D8BC6C387D68AA3673"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">examples of mechanisms the recipient will use to track risks identified pursuant to subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC91C0D928D954B09891DD4019F920ED0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a plan to control such risks; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H109EBF14D7FD4414BBE934EAF302023A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such assurances as the Secretary considers appropriate that the recipient will, with respect to the megaproject—</text> 
<clause id="H6757DD7F8EBC4B3F89B2D717CA28BBB1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>regularly submit to the Secretary updated cost estimates; and</text></clause> <clause id="H933F62DDB20C4DD6AB4F312445F3E0A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>maintain and regularly reassess financial reserves for addressing known and unknown risks.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5F2CFA7674974BE7A03FE59BA3E033AF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Peer review group</header> 
<subparagraph id="H5ED2E2BF95D74DAAB5BB797C3BC263EC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of Federal financial assistance under this title for a megaproject shall, not later than 90 days after the date when such megaproject is authorized for construction, establish a peer review group for such megaproject that consists of at least 5 individuals (including at least 1 individual with project management experience) to give expert advice on the scientific, technical, and project management aspects of the megaproject.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H015D3FAF4A2E4B7899F6FF63A3F5318B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Membership</header> <clause id="HFA5FF7E02AC74D5F9E151D88FFE72F93"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall establish guidelines describing how a recipient described in subparagraph (A) shall—</text> 
<subclause id="HFDD568161F174BEEA284A418C58F4511"><enum>(I)</enum><text>recruit and select members for a peer review group established under such subparagraph; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6D29E646E01B477A98B4833895DB7234"><enum>(II)</enum><text>make publicly available the criteria for such selection and the identity of members so selected.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H3F237E2C249C45AEAB32589AEC6A2B61"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Conflict of interest</header><text>No member of a peer review group for a megaproject may have a direct or indirect financial interest in such megaproject.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H42221F47A0804317B8B691AA041DA489"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Tasks</header><text>A peer review group established under subparagraph (A) by a recipient of Federal financial assistance for a megaproject shall—</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="HD62B3E8BB20F4B65AE58EF97B5A2E33C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>meet annually until completion of the megaproject;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HEC1FA548B15D4A4CB58236E31C2A184F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 90 days after the date of the establishment of the peer review group and not later than 90 days after the date of any significant change, as determined by the Secretary, to the scope, schedule, or budget of the megaproject, review the scope, schedule, and budget of the megaproject, including planning, engineering, financing, and any other elements determined appropriate by the Secretary; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HD926D6B6446A4A8780ABE1246D4B6BB6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit a report on the findings of each review under clause (ii) to the Secretary, Congress, and the recipient.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H44A2F6F649F4419E81DDD216F26BF1FD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Transparency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A recipient of Federal financial assistance under this title for a megaproject shall publish on the internet website of such recipient—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD01763B5D1324FA2AF49A464DBD0A22E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the name, license number, and license type of each engineer supervising an aspect of the megaproject; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC6793F163B754119B1F816909F62F54F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the report submitted under paragraph (3)(C)(iii), not later than 90 days after such submission.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE7DD07F8FC25482A9D15BD91A8DB52EA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Committee</header> 
<subparagraph id="HFCD0C4CD61964B608E16568F34BDFD00"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary of Transportation shall make appropriate arrangements with the Transportation Research Board (hereinafter referred to as the <quote>Board</quote>) of the National Academies under which the Board shall convene a transportation megaprojects committee.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDB981D403B2B43F28E91998EFB3EDB1F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The transportation megaprojects committee convened pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall—</text> 
<clause id="H69E47D684EC34390B1376F732908F580"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perform a literature search and assessment of existing megaproject studies;</text></clause> <clause id="H0BA8500ADE7C40068A95A767F9539946"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>review any relevant foreign experience and actions taken, with a particular focus on the United Kingdom and France;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1B34B858AC9B42FDBFDC5C5408037159"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identify recurring or typical problems with megaprojects;</text></clause> <clause id="HB4938549448147BA9720297818A2BDEB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>outline possible approaches to dealing with the problems in the Federal and State context; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8E561B730F5F4732BBB6560EEC401B36"><enum>(v)</enum><text>recommend any changes in the Department of Transportation’s approach to megaproject funding and oversight, such as a recommendation that each project be required to identify a peer group to work with project management and report to the Inspector General and Congress.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA9A976CF51AD47B484E6CABC62BC3F1A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this subsection, the committee convened pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall submit to the Secretary, the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report containing any results, findings, and recommendations made by the committee under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H55D1ACDCD0CC46178FDEC3EEC33B2CC0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) applies with respect to projects that are authorized for construction on or after the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

