<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9A2F6B5B4EE7453C894F486E05320317" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 751 IH: Fair Access In Residency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 751</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000546">Mr. Graves of Missouri</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000592">Mr. Golden of Maine</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to require as a condition of satisfying the definition of an approved medical residency training program for purposes of payments under Medicare for costs related to graduate medical education for hospitals operating such a program to submit information to encourage more equitable treatment of osteopathic and allopathic candidates in the residency application and review process, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFC06CA651FDA42F98EFB9B7EBC18D9E0" style="OLC"><section id="H11991873AFEA45B7AF12B8133DC97E8A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fair Access In Residency Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FAIR Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H79E194D7B1EF46BBB9E7879D7811ED73"><enum>2.</enum><header>Encouraging more equitable treatment of osteopathic and allopathic candidates in residency application and review process</header><subsection id="H7DF57418A1F64C7DB43C1DE732622B82"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1886(h)(5)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww(h)(5)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H08D3B97220BE4A9DA9FA7027F34AAF91" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text>Such term shall not include a program operated by a hospital, with respect to a year (beginning with 2024), unless such hospital submits to the Secretary for such year—</text><clause id="HBE008B461F1B43CE89A87625BCDCE146"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of applicants for residency in such program who are from osteopathic medical schools and the number who are from allopathic medical schools;</text></clause><clause id="HB28E136CAEEC4F7C8E094BB109045D59"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of such applicants who were accepted into such program from each of such types of medical school; and</text></clause><clause id="HE081BA0745AC410FBDBA72BB5385E2B8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an affirmation that—</text><subclause id="H67179643A8A341CDBC45F0B3F708BF61"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the hospital accepts applicants for such program from both osteopathic and allopathic medical schools; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HEF2F17AB4EA14877BB8D21F447E80C2E"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if an examination score is required for acceptance in such program, the Comprehensive Osteopathic Medical Licensing Examination of the United States (COMLEX–USA) and the United States Medical Licensing Examination (USMLE) are equally accepted.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H6203F0DEAE9F4BEFB2E5BDD41011D228"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall publish on a public website the information described in clauses (i) and (ii) of section 1886(h)(5)(A) of the Social Security Act, and the affirmation described in clause (iii) of such section, submitted by each approved medical residency training program for each year (beginning with 2024).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

