<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB7916A0ED1814B72B47903E08FFA33EA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1814 IH: Facilitating Investments Required for Emergency Services to All Towns in Our Nation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1814</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230327">March 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide grants for fire station construction through the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3E0AFFABCDE44BC9BC74AA833354CA0F" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HC05261D360F94864B4A3AECB85D0DDA5"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Facilitating Investments Required for Emergency Services to All Towns in Our Nation Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FIRE STATION Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HB2FF03E4334E4201B5A1D69A30664205"><enum>2.</enum><header>Assistance to firefighters fire station construction grants</header><subsection id="H1023D40AE89D43EFAFFB4161570B0951"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H7ACDE529B71D49C9881E48FB7AB00CFE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9094C7203A6A4F69BEFA552E595B370D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Career fire department</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>career fire department</term> means a fire department that has an all-paid force of firefighting personnel other than paid-on-call firefighters.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77C1ECB461C040B0B0D5D059896E61D6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Combination fire department</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>combination fire department</term> means a fire department that has—</text><subparagraph id="H253381C9E44349FD92AAB00FE14F3329"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paid firefighting personnel; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3FD72F76E9624FBAB75B9E8FD535C942"><enum>(B)</enum><text>volunteer firefighting personnel.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC17C866780AE45C9A52E858BDA7AD689"><enum>(4)</enum><header>EMS</header><text>The term <term>EMS</term> means emergency medical services. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBC94818FCDE48578C62DE70BB57ADF7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Nonaffiliated EMS organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>nonaffiliated EMS organization</term> means a public or private nonprofit EMS organization that is not affiliated with a hospital and does not serve a geographic area in which the Administrator finds that EMS are adequately provided by a fire department.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H838CA7DF0E2B474A94A81536C8FC0195" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Volunteer fire department</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>volunteer fire department</term> means a fire department that has an all-volunteer force of firefighting personnel. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H95CBD7DD700141878FEB59A30A8FA575"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall establish a grant program to provide financial assistance to entities described in subsection (c) to modify, upgrade, and construct fire and EMS department facilities. </text></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H45C64B6743834C50982AD0C9EB2F6CE0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible applicants</header><text>The Administrator may make a grant under this section to the following:</text><paragraph id="H294592C786FC4EFFAD5B7A48ED7416DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Career, volunteer, and combination fire departments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H859922DC76BD4ECCAB9450D22198EC0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Fire training facilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H088478CC05F54A85933A763EC9DC41E2" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Nonaffiliated EMS organizations, combination and volunteer emergency medical stations (except that for-profit EMS organizations are not eligible for a grant under this section). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7588407DB348407BAE38972E52209784"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An entity described in subsection (c) seeking a grant under this section shall submit to the Administrator an application in such form, at such time, and containing such information as the Administrator determines appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0680BCAEA4443A1B68FF872B71B219D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Meeting for recommendations</header><paragraph id="HC6C5ABA1859E41CCA8D7410D6E33D7F1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall convene a meeting of qualified members of national fire service organizations and, at the discretion of the Administrator, qualified members of EMS organizations to obtain recommendations regarding the criteria for the awarding of grants under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1C208DCA375423D80A5FE3096F328C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, a qualified member of an organization is a member who—</text><subparagraph id="HDA961B90210F4851A8C67F51C1F3A26F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is recognized for firefighting or EMS expertise;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27CAB8D252E44489B1C5072571F7B27F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not an employee of the Federal Government; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE51E790E97E7477AA699DA9B9EFDEDD4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the case of a member of an EMS organization, is a member of an organization that represents—</text><clause id="H89210A1F92FD4241AA4ACCB3D72EFDD6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>EMS providers that are affiliated with fire departments; or</text></clause><clause id="HB318B41A06C844B49F8D8C24D6CE98F6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>nonaffiliated EMS providers. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB66BE969E8EE4586AF9103959C5F49CF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Peer review of grant application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall, in consultation with national fire service and EMS organizations, appoint fire service personnel to conduct peer reviews of applications received under subsection (d).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0BDE236D22DA4D69B34F40D645AFC049"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Priority of grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Administrator shall consider the findings and recommendations of the peer reviews carried out under subsection (f).</text></subsection><subsection id="H2E5F187814FF4DB58F1005B55A43C32F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><paragraph id="H5ABDDAC230CA4611AE353DDA5174A907"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A recipient of a grant under this section may use funds received for the following:</text><subparagraph id="H40B5A758A53D4343A39597CE8561DEBC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Building, rebuilding, or renovating fire and EMS department facilities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08033B77C60646D79D3E6C499D9BAB80"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Upgrading existing facilities to install exhaust emission control systems, install backup power systems, upgrade or replace environmental control systems (such as HVAC systems), remove or remediate mold, and construct or modify living quarters for use by male and female personnel.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H629EE7B63A254750991D0CC09CCF9B78"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upgrading fire and EMS stations or building new stations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H704983DF01A9475DBCC1E7141AE60324"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Code compliant</header><text>In using funds under paragraph (1), a recipient of a grant under this section shall meet 1 of the 2 most recently published editions of relevant codes and standards, especially codes and standards that—</text><subparagraph id="H12356CC0385143E692DD545ED6B4BE9F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>require up-to-date hazard resistant and safety provisions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F27A0B5C76545E684A87948C0B12FBB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are relevant for protecting firefighter health and safety.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2CE6E0DFE43F4C24B81B9B3812DC7F9E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Grant funding</header><paragraph id="H9778BF1D0A7043EB8F3EC3DBBE3C839D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall allocate grant funds under this section as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H47F7A18B718342AE9B3253BA24864DCF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">25 percent for career fire and EMS departments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9663A8551A51454C91354CE742FAAC74"><enum>(B)</enum><text>25 percent for combination fire and EMS departments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H568EB93790C04D2D8867272EB0CADD8E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>25 percent for volunteer fire and EMS departments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C6B2ACC640D487C85C9281901AD5BD3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>25 percent to remain available for competition between the various department types.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5ADE6FB6A1DF44E39944DAF731592B06"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Insufficient applications</header><text>If the Administrator does not receive sufficient funding requests from a particular department type described in subparagraphs (A) through (C) of paragraph (1), the Administrator may make awards to other departments described in such subparagraphs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H267C02CD3A934EC3AF9D905657BB0168"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on awards amounts</header><text>A recipient of a grant under this section may not receive more than $7,500,000 under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A9AD8499CD944D3AC8837F70DD6C751"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Prevailing rate of wage and public contracts</header><paragraph id="H05738A6ECB4446A3B0B9D732C5C6FA4A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>All laborers and mechanics employed by contractors or subcontractors in the performance of construction work financed with the assistance of any contribution of Federal funds made by the Administrator under this section shall be paid wages at rates not less than those prevailing on similar construction in the locality as determined by the Secretary of Labor in accordance with subchapter IV of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/40/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 40, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Davis-Bacon Act</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8136E07F8328491B872FB0EB0AF30061"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Overtime</header><text>Each employee described in paragraph (1) shall receive compensation at a rate not less than one and <fraction>1⁄2</fraction> times the basic rate of pay of the employee for all hours worked in any workweek in excess of 8 hours in any workday or 40 hours in the workweek, as the case may be. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F7364C70B704A3384F147539768F98A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Assurances</header><text>The Administrator shall make no contribution of Federal funds without first obtaining adequate assurance that the labor standards described in paragraphs (1) and (2) will be maintained upon the construction work. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8FAF0870CA024638ABB2D56394A4D9D9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authority of Secretary of Labor</header><text>The Secretary of Labor shall have, with respect to the labor standards described in paragraphs (1) and (2), the authority and functions set forth in Reorganization Plan Numbered 14 of 1950 (5 U.S.C. App.) and section 3145 of title 40, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H296CE42BF3EB4321889B0562FDB3D4E4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Public contracts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Contractors and subcontractors performing construction work pursuant to this section shall procure only manufactured articles, materials, and supplies that have been manufactured in the United States substantially all from articles, materials, or supplies mined, produced, or manufactured in the United States in accordance with the requirements (and exceptions thereto) applicable to Federal agencies under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/41/83">chapter 83</external-xref> of title 41, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE762A42A9127491EB12AD8843D1E9811"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">Chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to activities carried out pursuant to this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H046CE342CA43486D8169591B3C9F54D1"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><paragraph id="H7FAA5AB5420E4D4A9E0FAC86DC9C57B5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual report to administrator of FEMA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter during the term of a grant awarded under this section, the recipient of the grant shall submit to the Administrator a report describing how the recipient used the amounts from the grant. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AC054A5B1A64148B62F34BF2D134F3F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter until the date on which the rebuilding or renovation of fire facilities and stations are completed using grant funds under this section, the Administrator shall submit to the <committee-name committee-id="SSGA00">Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate</committee-name> and the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name> and <committee-name committee-id="">Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives</committee-name> a report that provides an evaluation of the effectiveness of the grants awarded under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA56D89BB408C439783CC384E154D651C"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $750,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 to carry out this section. Funds appropriated under this Act shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

