<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H555A0EE623734EDFA0C9FD3ABF1E667F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 525 IH: Mentoring to Succeed Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 525</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230125">January 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 to give the Department of Education the authority to award competitive grants to eligible entities to establish, expand, or support school-based mentoring programs to assist at-risk students in middle school and high school in developing cognitive and social-emotional skills to prepare them for success in high school, postsecondary education, and the workforce.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HDBD8B006F98149DAA2884B2492D10BA2" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="H6B54035834B042F182FC394C1BC16807"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mentoring to Succeed Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HFCC9BDE9347E4C4DB89C345E0C1EF157"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to make assistance available for school-based mentoring programs for at-risk students in order to—</text>
<paragraph id="H2835FA62D56B475F88DB95585B58D846"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish, expand, or support school-based mentoring programs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB567F24BE7DD4549B7C44E20CB3B103A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assist at-risk students in middle school and high school in developing cognitive and social-emotional skills; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE97F1A3F321D40308498C6ED09561141"><enum>(3)</enum><text>prepare such at-risk students for success in high school, postsecondary education, and the workforce.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HA2A0F63CA8134555A687E390D8580867"><enum>3.</enum><header>School-based mentoring program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part C of title I of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/2351">20 U.S.C. 2351 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF47FF2AAF38D4A5C8A547B1732327DDA">
<section id="HF2120D6ACB8E44F8B5C74B254EA5F586"><enum>136.</enum><header>Distribution of funds for school-based mentoring programs</header>
<subsection id="HE2991C9EB861411184D1545D61DE9D81"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H6E8C15ED6AC44B4689A2F581921D90E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>At-risk student</header><text>The term <term>at-risk student</term> means a student who—</text>
<subparagraph id="H14755398D0234AB3B251F05977CCA337"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is failing academically or at risk of dropping out of school;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6D35721FEDD848C08C1073637C1654BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is pregnant or a parent;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H23A36D2F45DC412A80E833BFE759B7CE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is a gang member;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC8EA2781CF9240339AA2C657AFF7C62B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is a child or youth in foster care or a youth who has been emancipated from foster care, but is still enrolled in high school;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9566EE8309594F1AA892F2340E8B64EB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>is or has recently been a homeless child or youth;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF6BD24CE6BE84460BDAEACA32D3C96EE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>is chronically absent;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCB75E217E3AE4B3794ABE0B3C895DC95"><enum>(G)</enum><text>has changed schools 3 or more times in the past 6 months;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC933A2CBF8C04D89ADA2DC4CCBFAD67C"><enum>(H)</enum><text>has come in contact with the juvenile justice system in the past;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3E24CA8B39B44258B2322B26C491BEA6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has a history of multiple suspensions or disciplinary actions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6CDB1BF8758C4162A137ED634E341702"><enum>(J)</enum><text>is an English learner;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB222CD3C5B4D489B838DD019D7BDE153"><enum>(K)</enum><text>has one or both parents incarcerated;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFB8B768A80C9458FA5BBB638BC69E44E"><enum>(L)</enum><text>has experienced one or more adverse childhood experiences, traumatic events, or toxic stressors, as assessed through an evidence-based screening;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H47619956C6224FD9A332F7A036D50CC2"><enum>(M)</enum><text>lives in a high-poverty area with a high rate of community violence;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H55B4C75B5C3448109DEADBCB6982325B"><enum>(N)</enum><text>has a disability; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H93472DEBC4F149A4B2BF3938E58EFDE7"><enum>(O)</enum><text>shows signs of alcohol or drug misuse or abuse or has a parent or guardian who is struggling with substance abuse.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H1CCD363CD62945CABD3E48934C4F9F8E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disability</header><text>The term <term>disability</term> has the meaning given the term for purposes of section 602(3) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1401">20 U.S.C. 1401(3)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEE16778B5A914A31BEED3CD7E490AAE2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H24528C024C734190BEAE294DE125639F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a high-need local educational agency, high-need school, or local government entity; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC51DCC2028E042A58C1091AEC81F7F41"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may include a partnership between an entity described in subparagraph (A) and a nonprofit, community-based, or faith-based organization, or institution of higher education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB2939FD6B7CD4901B01BA3B11CF6B9EA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>English learner</header><text>The term <term>English learner</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFE0A61691E5946B7939CD3D78AAB67FB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Foster care</header><text>The term <term>foster care</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1355.20(a) of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H59EDABAF2CDA4C4484268B88781A8AB8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>High-need local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>high-need local educational agency</term> means a local educational agency that serves at least one high-need school.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFC5D8661539E4A58AFC8AC46077E20CD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>High-need school</header><text>The term <term>high-need school</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2211(b) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6631">20 U.S.C. 6631(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCA0A06E1F35B406A86EF40143C04BF88"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Homeless children and youths</header><text>The term <term>homeless children and youths</term> has the meaning given the term in section 725 of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11434a">42 U.S.C. 11434a</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H48AF259EFEA34ED1AD480F894BC80419"><enum>(9)</enum><header>School-based mentoring</header><text>The term <term>school-based mentoring</term> means a structured, managed, evidenced-based program conducted in partnership with teachers, administrators, school psychologists, school social workers or counselors, and other school staff, in which at-risk students are appropriately matched with screened and trained professional or volunteer mentors who provide guidance, support, and encouragement, involving meetings, group-based sessions, and educational and workforce-related activities on a regular basis to prepare at-risk students for success in high school, postsecondary education, and the workforce.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H68FC67D4E7994ECEA0C616172EB30642"><enum>(b)</enum><header>School-Based mentoring competitive grant program</header> <paragraph id="H5B86C3FA608E454B89ADCBA56D58110E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities to establish, expand, or support school-based mentoring programs that—</text>
<subparagraph id="HEB2F6B75D7594998938EEF0A33AB1EA7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are designed to assist at-risk students in high-need schools in developing cognitive skills and promoting social-emotional learning to prepare them for success in high school, postsecondary education, and the workforce by linking them with mentors who—</text> <clause id="H0C91D9D0C7254775BFD062729BBBBBE7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have received mentor training, including on trauma-informed practices, youth engagement, cultural competency, and social-emotional learning; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H724227F5D08C4842AF24708218CD58AA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>have been screened using appropriate reference checks and criminal background checks, in accordance with the requirements of paragraph (3)(B)(v)(II);</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8DFFB8346CDB4A948C01E0710C7D8CA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide coaching and technical assistance to mentors in each such mentoring program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H76F4ADF094384A7687B81F7FDFE0CA35"><enum>(C)</enum><text>seek to—</text> <clause id="HDE4E50C4108947E2B54DEDB8BFF90F55"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improve the academic achievement of at-risk students;</text></clause>
<clause id="HACE18FDF7D34457CAE22C5DCFCD86A3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reduce dropout rates and absenteeism and improve school engagement of at-risk students and their families;</text></clause> <clause id="H306D3A06433548A2BD571F8EE580C1BC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>reduce juvenile justice involvement of at-risk students;</text></clause>
<clause id="HF89F746B4A7E4E46AEEBAC94DB9FF791"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>foster positive relationships between at-risk students and their peers, teachers, other adults, and family members;</text></clause> <clause id="H084BE2AEEAAD4FF9B3B5EF9018462268"><enum>(v)</enum><text>develop the workforce readiness skills of at-risk students by exploring paths to employment, including encouraging students with disabilities to explore transition services; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H5AACB19A160840A2AC474B79C9F3438D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>increase the participation of at-risk students in community service activities; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8E8AAC20934A4C049833BAE0AF3F1D0F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>encourage at-risk students to set goals and plan for their futures, including making plans and identifying goals for postsecondary education and the workforce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1E7FFA1FB33A465B92C5234CEEFE8A2D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants under this section for a period not to exceed 5 years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6CEEBE6DC0BE41D08092E0EE2ECFBAC0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To receive a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application that includes—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA7563818E1354287B0997A5A23F02B5B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a needs assessment that includes baseline data on the measures described in paragraph (6)(A)(ii); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6B0527CF20B44C65A435EECD2E50EF84"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a plan to meet the requirements of paragraph (1), including—</text>
<clause id="HDFD0FD885F0443F88CF96EA61643F4DF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the targeted outcomes, mentee age and eligibility, mentor type, and meeting frequency for the program;</text></clause> <clause id="HE4035E13DEB1417B80E0F751A52DBF61"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of mentor-student matches proposed to be established and maintained annually under the program;</text></clause>
<clause id="HFA4661827D744708A859DFC64648F6C6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the capacity and expertise of the program to serve children and youth in a way that is responsive to children and youth of color, expectant and parenting youth, indigenous youth, youth who are lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgendered, or queer, and youth with disabilities;</text></clause> <clause id="H4D51D6A40522452CB61BD7B84AF45943"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>actions taken to ensure that the design of the program reflects input from youth;</text></clause>
<clause id="H3C574D5BFC754F7FA2A96BF86FDA4C6C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>an assurance that mentors supported under the program are appropriately screened and have demonstrated a willingness to comply with aspects of the mentoring program, including—</text> <subclause id="HDBA8F943AF2647BDBFF9918636355D41"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a written screening plan that includes all of the policies and procedures used to screen and select mentors, including eligibility requirements and preferences for such applicants;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HBBFA535D5E90435DA2A328D2D3603042"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a description of the methods to be used to conduct criminal background checks on all prospective mentors, and the methods in place to exclude mentors with convictions directly related to child safety that occur during the mentor's participation in the program or in the 10-year period preceding the mentor's participation; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HDDD77DDF947E4D1490F7E8E515878FCB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a description of the methods to be used to ensure that the mentors are willing and able to serve as a mentor on a long-term, consistent basis as defined in the application.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6C84CD02D2134607B11B1EC73AB3AABA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting grant recipients, the Secretary shall give priority to applicants that—</text> <subparagraph id="HB6BA6450AA27437482506A164BC5722D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>serve children and youth with the greatest need living in high-poverty, high-crime areas, or rural areas, or who attend schools with high rates of community violence;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7373BEAC1AD94FC7B94FDE690CC22B79"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide at-risk students with opportunities for postsecondary education preparation and career development, including—</text> <clause id="H1D5B3046E4964EBFAF9566C6CDE60C59"><enum>(i)</enum><text>job training, professional development, work shadowing, internships, networking, resume writing and review, interview preparation, transition services for students with disabilities, application assistance and visits to institutions of higher education, and leadership development through community service; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HEDE4FBC1B95A4AE29CA4ADDBE0EAC83C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>partnerships with the private sector and local businesses to provide internship and career exploration activities and resources; </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H81A95AB1EB3645BDA812D1DF7132596F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>seek to provide match lengths between at-risk students and mentors for at least 1 academic year; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1654BA33F6744B6D8DD2359028EBFBDB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>consult and engage youth in the development, design, and implementation of the program. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61D8BE8240354EB39BB1C07449285892"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may use such funds to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H18ADBE0A09C04FB49A191173D2E2A9E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop and carry out regular training for mentors, including on—</text> <clause id="HFA81884D182E41A885BE0F69B5FDDBA3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the impact of adverse childhood experiences;</text></clause>
<clause id="H085164EA8F054AEAAD770D4B1A7EBD17"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>trauma-informed practices and interventions;</text></clause> <clause id="HDF4F9156FB344B328EDFC30C6ACCB2C4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>supporting homeless children and youths;</text></clause>
<clause id="H2E8D04CCF3CE4833BD810F1C0009270D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>supporting children and youth in foster care or youth who have been emancipated from foster care, but are still enrolled in high school;</text></clause> <clause id="HAF9B24716EBA4223BAF026F61C167D3C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>cultural competency;</text></clause>
<clause id="HDB1C149A2CCA4D889D4141F5339442D5"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>meeting all appropriate privacy and confidentiality requirements for students, including students in foster care;</text></clause> <clause id="H60950D5C7D434A80A738E66ADB0D0AB9"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>working in coordination with a public school system;</text></clause>
<clause id="H6825295FA87843F7A1DE21C65E1ABC16"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>positive youth development and engagement practices; and</text></clause> <clause id="HFFDDD36C4770466D8865C8E95988EE07"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>disability inclusion practices to ensure access and participation by students with disabilities;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H28A23D4C2DBC47E08D5E21780536FE1F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recruit, screen, match, train, and compensate mentors;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8C7247D994F4CD2BF38AAFD607500CE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>hire staff to perform or support the objectives of the school-based mentoring program;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE1C6923649144BC8818CAC86EFFA2048"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide inclusive and accessible youth engagement activities, such as—</text> <clause id="H9AFF2E89E70F476E9E226CA5F3EE4883"><enum>(i)</enum><text>enrichment field trips to cultural destinations; </text></clause>
<clause id="H37426DD36BAF4471B8E08FCDFE9FC26A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>career awareness activities, including job site visits, informational interviews, resume writing, interview preparation, and networking; and</text></clause> <clause id="H1BC6DC084AA9420DB0F3BEC1B6415BBE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>academic or postsecondary education preparation activities, including trade or vocational school visits, visits to institutions of higher education, and assistance in applying to institutions of higher education; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H290CADE864EF439DB4544967F3381ED0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>conduct program evaluation, including by acquiring and analyzing the data described under paragraph (6).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0798AD6BABEA46CEB4C4056DD3041513"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header> <subparagraph id="H19F59A0F779A4429B42A731CF4BE3804"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the end of each academic year during the grant period, an eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary a report that includes—</text>
<clause id="HAAE8DC74A16345C6805CF361D98CA555"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of students and mentors, and the demographics of the students and mentors, who participated in the school-based mentoring program that was funded in whole or in part with the grant funds;</text></clause> <clause id="HADB52C1B6E5843B48FEE0743932AD3D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>data on the academic achievement, dropout rates, truancy, absenteeism, outcomes of arrests for violent crime, summer employment, and postsecondary education enrollment of students in the program;</text></clause>
<clause id="HD2E657244D3B451082AE1B2655E8FB9C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of group sessions and number of one-to-one contacts between students in the program and their mentors; </text></clause> <clause id="HEB5E76746B2341F9BAD0B60090327D97"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the average attendance of students enrolled in the program;</text></clause>
<clause id="H22E409BA427B4B1A8AE0C445628DAC2B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the number of students with disabilities connected to transition services;</text></clause> <clause id="HB6B2D778FCE44AE6925A82FA69710503"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>data on social-emotional development of students as assessed with a validated social-emotional assessment tool; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HBCAEF6AF882745738D9F740B898A293A"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary may require to evaluate the success of the school-based mentoring program.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD64DA05EE99C4B6796878B49BD8A191D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Student privacy</header><text>An eligible entity shall ensure that the report submitted under subparagraph (A) is prepared in a manner that protects the privacy rights of each student in accordance with section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1232g">20 U.S.C. 1232g</external-xref>; commonly known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFE073C2F6C064D8CBC60A878CBF4F063"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Mentoring resources and community service coordination</header>
<subparagraph id="HF731DD1FC3504DA095D6C640468FE569"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary shall work with the Office of Juvenile Justice and Delinquency Prevention to—</text> <clause id="HAFAA3FD204104146ACFE84F192422641"><enum>(i)</enum><text>refer grantees under this section to the National Mentoring Resource Center to obtain resources on best practices and research related to mentoring and to request no-cost training and technical assistance; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HB264014DE6904452BF711F4490720740"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide grantees under this section with information regarding transitional services for at-risk students returning from correctional facilities and transition services for students with disabilities.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB2D50B1CF055411EB29D14E80F194E8A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary shall, to the extent possible, coordinate with the Corporation for National and Community Service, including through entering into an interagency agreement or a memorandum of understanding, to support mentoring and community service-related activities for at-risk students.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H32AA5FD057644C61886AE96ADAA0AE69"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of funds</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H6EFA3D1B6C134E91AAB648C986D92ABC"><enum>4.</enum><header>Institute of Education Sciences study on school-based mentoring programs</header> <subsection id="H4BC05CA2487F4CF78B51380C9691A9CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Education, acting through the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences, shall conduct a study to—</text>
<paragraph id="H708BC11C75714AE1A5BC0F827CACD7D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify successful school-based mentoring programs and effective strategies for administering and monitoring such programs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BA8B95E28FA45928D267A7EAAFDA345"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the role of mentors in promoting cognitive development and social-emotional learning to enhance academic achievement and to improve workforce readiness; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2EDE42435F3C4E54B075DA188261941F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>evaluate the effectiveness of the grant program under section 136 of the Carl D. Perkins Career and Technical Education Act of 2006, as added by section 3, on student academic outcomes and youth career development.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF93D30AB697F49568CF9F37913C43C6A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Education, acting through the Director of the Institute of Education Sciences, shall submit the results of the study described in subsection (a) to the appropriate congressional committees. </text></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


