<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA0BED22B17BE4814BBBF65D876B42FFC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 888 IH: IRS Funding Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 888</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000585">Mr. LaHood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001199">Mr. Smucker</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000298">Mr. Estes</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide accountability for funding provided to the Internal Revenue Service and the Department of the Treasury under <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HE9EE28AE13BF4D3CBEAB37DE5154A8C2" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="H0A2CE28ECC1547BCB04D750450F9861A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>IRS Funding Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF5BEF1632CA0404480FE0550D395E7A3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Annual comprehensive spending plan for increased Internal Revenue Service resources</header> <subsection id="H20AF0F88D2B94F2F8B692994F988FD1B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation on funding</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H880ED78A62FE41129C9FB9BDA1CCBFD1"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Initial plan</header> <subparagraph id="H05848E4773B946009664F27B3BD57599"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>None of the funds described in paragraph (3) may be obligated during the period—</text>
<clause id="H1763160185A846A4992BAFFA702CC619"><enum>(i)</enum><text>beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></clause> <clause id="H34EEED989DE444DF908F96176E636550"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ending on the date that is 60 days after the spending plan described in subsection (b)(1)(A) has been submitted.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9FD211B0042444188912D14E177B76AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional moratorium</header><text>If Congress enacts a joint resolution of disapproval described in subsection (c) with respect to the Internal Revenue Service spending plan before the date described in subparagraph (A)(ii), then—</text> <clause id="HE6089F3ACE3C4FBC9C964E36C03932E7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall submit a new spending plan under subsection (b)(1)(A); and</text></clause>
<clause id="H996980ED8F3E401CABA5396B7D430E51"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the period described in subparagraph (A) shall not end before the date that is 60 days after such new spending plan is submitted.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0F8E6ACD4BE44580B9448FC818DD15E7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subsequent submissions</header> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H09A3417C377E4DAEA89B2269D0768F5E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds described in paragraph (3) may be obligated during any period—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7D0B2D5BE8634EA7AE00F6DEC9649E40"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">beginning on the date Congress has enacted a joint resolution of disapproval under subsection (c) with respect to any spending plan described in subsection (b)(1)(B); and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E26371A849D43F0BE99B92A9C23A6B7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ending on the date that is 60 days after the date on which the Commissioner of Internal Revenue has submitted a new spending plan under such subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1CF9ECC2F3E14EEA9A42D5A4DEB1AAC6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional moratorium</header><text>If Congress enacts a joint resolution of disapproval described in subsection (c) with respect to any new spending plan submitted under subparagraph (A)(ii) before the date that is 60 days after the date on which such new spending plan has been submitted, then—</text> <clause id="H7D4489BA61B247DCBCFAF52202978EDA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall submit an additional new spending plan under subsection (b)(1)(B); and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE0D35B088DF94F12BE6D0F9AC08BF871"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the period described in subparagraph (A) shall not end before the date that is 60 days after such additional new spending plan is submitted. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H03F977A935094297BF95EFF85D7C82B0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Funds described</header><text>The funds described in this paragraph are the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H03D34925E4C64DC3993944AEEDCB46CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Any funds made available under clause (ii), (iii), or (iv) of section 10301(1)(A) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H24DE32B9524F46D69BCACD514C7CC824"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any funds made available under section 10301(1)(A)(i) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> other than funds used for the following purposes:</text>
<clause id="H759F2F58880349BBB2DDD12BE332E7DC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Eliminating any correspondence or return processing backlog.</text></clause> <clause id="HAF9DBC2C10704FC49BDE1A72BAF49AA2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Reducing call wait times for taxpayers and tax professionals.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HDE4694FE0E4A4486BBEF249B1BE53CF3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual comprehensive spending plan</header>
<paragraph id="H9A9946CC175D44A0BA8CE1583FD10AD9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header>
<subparagraph id="HD4C449021BB84BF9B3F69909EF5397E8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial plan</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall submit to the appropriate Congressional committees a spending plan described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9B4E1E36AF1B4D54BBEA3477E236BC01"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Subsequent submissions</header> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H29E92CA327824BED862106DA0CB3D1CF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each fiscal year beginning after the plan described in subparagraph (A) is submitted and ending with fiscal year 2031, the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall submit to the appropriate Congressional committees a spending plan described in paragraph (2) on the date that the President submits the budget required under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code.</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H27356361BC05497594E960F056C8942D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Reduction in appropriation</header>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD2E8EA1D14D34CABBD6550AA17FC5819"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any failure to submit a plan required under clause (i) by the date that is 7 days after the date the plan is required to be submitted and, the amounts made available under section 10301(1)(A)(ii) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> shall be reduced by $10,000,000 for each day after such required date that report has not been submitted. </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="H9F7B7E4C6741480C90C3C92847FCE429"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Required date</header><text>For purposes of this clause, the term <term>required date</term> means, with respect to any plan required under this subparagraph, the date that is 7 days after such plan is required to be submitted. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H15164B2B203D4E2088BFD4D3B82CA0AA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Spending plan</header>
<subparagraph id="H7168A6727E8C489DAF0104A1C485D585"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A spending plan described in this subparagraph is a plan that—</text> <clause id="H19F6375A48E94C839DC536E1415FF67F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>details how the funds appropriated under section 10301(1) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> will be spent over—</text>
<subclause id="HF5645F394CC24801A66FE958D3222975"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the period consisting of the current fiscal year and the next 4 fiscal years ending before fiscal year 2032; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC7A2710E3E50496F8F38E73B64071BA3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the period consisting of the current fiscal year through the fiscal year ending with fiscal year 2031 (if such period includes any period not described in subclause (I));</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H804444A5E4E146B9B283D204C337DD6E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>contains the information described in subparagraph (B);</text></clause> <clause id="H93AA902668AE4F17AE6FB3D0E03F32E9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has been reviewed by—</text>
<subclause id="H96B8717E4CE140869D99630772C2A587"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Internal Revenue Service Advisory Council;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H661C9E10DF21424AAD8ADDCEC55EF783"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the Comptroller of the United States;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HFC40822D129146D19A953AFE433AD4DF"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the National Taxpayer Advocate; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H66AE2862429E44C6BE87CFE5E01DFD33"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the Director of the Office of Management and Budget; and</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HC553311516D04E629B61E890C5656D6E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>has been approved by the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H404AC5DBDF564C728383A97940F2A76C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Plan contents</header><text>The information described in this paragraph is the following:</text>
<clause id="H96924B432D0A44AD89BDED83FC8759FE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A detailed explanation of the plan, including—</text> <subclause id="H83CC2230D9CE4C2EBDDF86372F8CAA78"><enum>(I)</enum><text>costs and results to date, actual expenditures of the prior fiscal year, actual and expected expenditures of the current fiscal year, upcoming deliverables and expected costs, and total expenditures; </text></subclause>
<subclause id="H9C77F6FAEDA542569ACE9AEDB79DAAB0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>clearly defined objectives, timelines, and metrics for quantitatively measuring the plan’s annual progress, including with respect to measuring improvements in taxpayer services, revenue collection, information technology, cybersecurity, and taxpayer data protections; and </text></subclause> <subclause id="H9FF8DCD968E44009AA4953BB8BF11335"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a description of any differences between metrics described in subclause (II) and corresponding metrics used by the National Taxpayer Advocate, the Comptroller General of the United States, and the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H78556270824244F982AFE3CF5E18AFA1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A detailed analysis of the performance of the Internal Revenue Service with respect to the delivery of taxpayer services, including—</text> <subclause id="H0543B61392AB4A15B8545A22301D0395"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Level of Service (LOS) of phone lines (as a percent of phone calls answered by an Internal Revenue Service employee, not to include courtesy disconnects or automated call backs);</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HE3C9EC9EB49C442E8D867F787CDB6DFF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the median and average wait time to speak to a representative of the Internal Revenue Service;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HEB9687A9AB334F67AEA167C0AE1B0054"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the amount of unprocessed taxpayer correspondence, including tax returns, responses to Internal Revenue Service notices, tax payments, and other similar types of correspondence; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HBC243D5813BA464F87ACD23983D3714A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the median and average length of time for processing the items described in subclause (III) and processing refund claims.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H46DC5B866E0C44C384EBAD15E0452452"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>An analysis identifying any increase or decrease in total annual audits and annual audit rates by income group for the period beginning in 2018 and ending with the year the report is submitted. Such analysis shall include a detailed description of what constitutes an <quote>audit</quote> by the Internal Revenue Service, and if the definition of an <quote>audit</quote> used by the Internal Revenue Service differs from the definition used by the National Taxpayer Advocate, the Comptroller General of the United States, or the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration, there shall also be included an analysis using such divergent definition.</text></clause>
<clause id="H98AB47D4862A41A8A0703FB6C3B20429"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A categorizing of the number of audits for each year in the analysis described in clause (iv) which were—</text> <subclause id="H809347D3D7B04733BED31CC7258B2D0F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>correspondence audits;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H5C1DEB1D8C8F430CA2BD696907FFC785"><enum>(II)</enum><text>office audits;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H69592B6366484D35B803C1C9F7B552BA"><enum>(III)</enum><text>field audits;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H14F21A2DEF6240F7AF62F313669B7384"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>audits under the Internal Revenue Service National Research Program; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H93E76DAD27714F0BA65659E4B48804C8"><enum>(V)</enum><text>other audits.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HB897828E46304FB49165AFFFF3CA69A9"><enum>(v)</enum><text>A description of all taxpayer compliance actions or initiatives undertaken using funding appropriated under section 10301(1)(A) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> that do not rise to the level of an audit, with each action broken out by the total number of such actions undertaken for each income group and as a percentage of taxpayers in each income group.</text></clause> <clause id="H68840865381B4120B6EC70560A1FF6A9"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>An explanation of any unresolved or outstanding recommendations made by the Government Accountability Office and the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration pertaining to taxpayer-data privacy protections, Internal Revenue Service taxpayer services, and Internal Revenue Service technology modernization efforts that are addressed by the plan and a description of how they are addressed.</text></clause>
<clause id="H5DE238FCD5644D51A8DE7ACC5337C975"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>For any recommendations identified by the Government Accountability Office and the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration as <quote>high risk</quote> or <quote>priority</quote> that are not addressed in the plan, an explanation of why such recommendations are not addressed in the plan. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H15D575F42792499C86541605C54DE3E2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Testimony of relevant officials</header><text>Not later than 30 days after any spending plan described in paragraph (2) has been submitted, the Secretary of the Treasury and the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall testify in person before any of the appropriate Congressional committees that request their testimony with respect to such spending plan.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD5F786749B504487853282D50083A0DC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Requirement to notify of excess spending</header><text>The Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall immediately notify the appropriate Congressional committees if actual obligations and expenditures for any account for any period for which projections are made in a plan submitted under paragraph (2) exceed the amount of obligations and expenditures projected for such account in such plan by 5 percent or more.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB7471EAA28C046A384619CA00CE28822"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Joint resolution of disapproval of the IRS comprehensive spending plan</header> <paragraph id="H504F8DD0D2084DE3B771D5BF60E10585"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>joint resolution of disapproval of the IRS comprehensive spending plan</quote> means only a joint resolution introduced in the period beginning on the date on which a spending plan submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1)(A) is received by the appropriate Congressional committees and ending 60 days thereafter (excluding days either House of Congress is adjourned for more than 3 days during a session of Congress), the matter after the resolving clause of which is as follows: <quote>That Congress disapproves the plan submitted on ____ by the Internal Revenue Service relating to the comprehensive spending plan under section 2(b)(1) of the <short-title>IRS Funding Accountability Act</short-title> with respect to fiscal year ___.</quote>. (The blank spaces being appropriately filled in).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6A23DCDAC7424DF6B2F5A20D663D100A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application of Congressional Review Act disapproval procedures</header>
<subparagraph id="HD2779276047D474D96A515F72D06812D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The rules of section 802 of title 5, United States Code, shall apply to a joint resolution of disapproval of the IRS comprehensive spending plan in the same manner as such rules apply to a joint resolution described in subsection (a) of such section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H79B74B67319143279814515F36AAA6DE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exercise of rulemaking authority</header><text>This section is enacted by Congress—</text>
<clause id="HEED84F05D555481C957B2523BA91C627"><enum>(i)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the Senate and House of Representatives, respectively, and as such it is deemed a part of the rules of each House, respectively, but applicable only with respect to the procedure to be followed in that House in the case of a joint resolution of disapproval of the IRS comprehensive spending plan described in paragraph (1), and it supersedes other rules only to the extent that it is inconsistent with such rules; and</text></clause> <clause id="H7A7D022ADA5E47D6992ADF3BCD2CD1A9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H7D7B34E7821B4648B6FE9AC910A5134A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Quarterly reports</header>
<subsection id="H9B096BF07CE143DF984339AC0C60BC63"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Internal Revenue Service</header>
<paragraph id="HDE91E657BCDE44959D24B12B7F2A6AA1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 14 days after the last day of each calendar quarter beginning during the applicable period, the Commissioner of Internal Revenue shall submit to the appropriate Congressional committees a report on any expenditures and obligations of funds appropriated under section 10301(1) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2EF2374445524D74B5493F837D2BFAF5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Matters included</header><text>The report provided under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H2238F9E35FDB4C37AB615DD89399AE32"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A plain language description of the specific actions taken by the Commissioner of Internal Revenue utilizing any funds appropriated under section 10301(1) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H57E0EE70541743FB90B3C7891333ABCC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The obligations and expenditures during the quarter of funds appropriated under section 10301(1) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> and the expected expenditure of such funds in the subsequent quarter, including a comparison of obligations and expenditures between amounts spent for taxpayers services and amounts spent for examinations and collections by each division or office of the Internal Revenue Service, including the Large Business and International Division, the Small Business/Self Employed Division, the Tax-Exempt and Government Entities Division, the Wage and Investment Division, the Criminal Investigation Office, the Whistleblower Office, and the Office of the Taxpayer Advocate.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H74279959E7804330812EFD9E8D59D30E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of any new full-time or full-time equivalent (FTE) employees, contractors, or other staff hired by the Internal Revenue Service, including the number of new hires, the primary function or activity type of each new hire, and the specific Division or Office to which each new hire is tasked.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H20C7A3820CB74D24ACBA0E6A7E2E7431"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The number of new employees that have passed a security clearance compared to the number of new employees hired to a position requiring a security clearance, along with an indication of whether any new employee that has not passed a security clearance or suitability determination has access to taxpayer return information (as defined by <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">section 6103(b)(2)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF1AE816CD3E642B4A11D6B7D021887EB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A detailed description of any violation of the fair tax collection practices described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6304">section 6304</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 by any employees, contractors, or other staff described in subparagraph (C) (including violations tracked in Automated Labor and Employee Relations Tracking System (ALERTS) of the Human Capital Office of the Internal Revenue Service).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H244142BEDCF0461FBDF9E1FE1EBBD65C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The status of recommendations provided by the Government Accountability Office and the Treasury Inspector General for Tax Administration which have been identified as being addressed by a spending plan under section 2(b)(1), including whether the implementation of such recommendations has been completed, is in progress, or is open (including the expected date of completion for any recommendations identified as in progress or open). </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HCB7112DD50EA42A181781A018C9B5C16"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reduction in appropriation</header><text>In the case of any failure to submit a report required under paragraph (1) by the required date, the amounts made available under section 10301(1)(A)(ii) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> shall be reduced by $1,000,000 for each day after such required date that report has not been submitted.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H30E56CCA623B49D2BDFC48F4FCF1B292"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Department of the Treasury</header> <paragraph id="HE37ED380B5B440DBB48C23ECA30ECCC7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 14 days after the last day of each calendar quarter beginning during the applicable period, the Secretary of the Treasury shall submit to the appropriate Congressional committees a report containing the following information:</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H2CB8424791114D42A11B64FC05D99926"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A plain-language description of the actions taken by the Secretary of the Treasury utilizing any funds appropriated under paragraph (1), (3), or (5) of section 10301 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>. Any action which is described in a report made under subsection (a) may be described by reference to the action in such report.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD06CF2BF237C4B89A91275DA8B094C00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A detailed description of the specific purposes to which the funds appropriated under section 10301(3) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> has been (or is expected to be) obligated.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0DE95E8F889D4FE09D17E906C027E86B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A description of any new full-time or full-time equivalent (FTE) employees, contractors, or other staff hired by the Secretary utilizing funds appropriated under section 10301 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>, including the number of new hires and whether the duties of each new hire includes any functions related to the Internal Revenue Service (including implementation of tax policies, enforcement, regulations, research, press or communications, or other purposes).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEB76E122A08A46CB9E84A55F62F0F036"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A detailed description and explanation of any changes to the most recent Priority Guidance Plan of the Department of the Treasury and the Internal Revenue Service involving guidance projects that utilize any funds appropriated under section 10301 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> or which are related to the implementation of any provision of or amendment made by such Public Law.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1CCC5E416A144042BFAC0186C4FDB2B0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of any new initiatives planned to be undertaken by the Department of the Treasury within the existing or subsequent fiscal year which will (or may) utilize funds appropriated under section 10301 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H0C6E3AE0DD104F84BD67AE216B666723"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reduction in appropriation</header><text>In the case of any failure to submit a report required under paragraph (1) by the required date—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEBE90B909C2D4A4AAF65CDB243DCCA3A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amounts made available under paragraphs (3) of section 10301 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> shall be reduced by $666,667 for each day after such required date that report has not been submitted, and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H396F731C1B804D48B7A6F5E67E29CEC7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amounts made available under paragraphs (5) of section 10301 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/169">Public Law 117–169</external-xref> shall be reduced by $333,333 for each day after such required date that report has not been submitted.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" id="H734BD95C8D75488385FAD25DBCC9495E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text> <paragraph id="HF6247EC52825471E9695A362515893DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicable period</header><text>The term <term>applicable period</term> means the period beginning after the date the plan under section 2(b)(1)(A) is required to be submitted and ending on September 30, 2031.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" id="HBF8518FC94C943CA94389C65C27FBB62"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Required date</header><text>The term <term>required date</term> means, with respect to any report required to be submitted under subsection (a) or (b), the date that is 7 days after the date the report is required to be submitted.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H9ABAB44BC5554C6CA4377F289CD2829B"><enum>4.</enum><header>Appropriate Congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, the term <term>appropriate Congressional committees</term> means—</text>
<paragraph id="H24521B1E043D4F1E92BF96C786B7E91E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Finance of the Senate;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9AD508456CF749C1BE6E1B8FC32507BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H518D3ECF6F31417790F3571424A7BBB9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFC58540EE6E54787B1DBAD06053902BB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


