<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H865ADDDD3A2D4E4AB16AEE7893369273" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3640 IH: Informed Lawmaking to Combat Inflation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3640</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230524">May 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Committee on Rules</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Congressional Budget and Impoundment Control Act of 1974 to require the Congressional Budget Office to provide an inflation estimate with respect to direct spending legislation with a significant impact on the Gross Domestic Product of the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1BC262A349B3436AA3859F7EEECA62D7" style="OLC"><section id="HFEB54898BE1346648519ADB853A895DE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Informed Lawmaking to Combat Inflation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H67924B5C869E406EB2314167263029F9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Legislative mandated inflation accountability and reform</header><subsection id="H4064B2E76594461BB79675956A5D64AF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part A of title IV of the Congressional Budget and Impoundment Control Act of 1974 is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="appropriations" id="H2CE9015ECF0546A78F34C048E79953B8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H761BAD2A0AC34CA8B3E2A589233DF446"><enum>407.</enum><header>Mandatory inflation forecasting</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HD131A29D5B5044AF8844F1F48DCDA245"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text><paragraph id="HD33BD7EB439A4A7ABABB8D08E946CA26" indent="up1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>Director</quote> means the Director of the Congressional Budget Office; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1873511A5E8F483394BA019486344206" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>major legislation</quote> means any bill or joint resolution, or amendment thereto or conference report thereon, that provides for direct spending and would be projected (in a conventional cost estimate) to cause an annual gross budgetary effect of at least 0.25 percent of projected Gross Domestic Product of the United States, but does not include any such measure that—</text><subparagraph id="HB951A9ABD6624D1CBA5765135C4D3B47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides for emergency assistance or relief at the request of any State, local, or tribal government or any official of a State, local, or tribal government; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC51246A18CCE469EB18CB3DFD6BA116C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is necessary for the national security or the ratification or implementation of international treaty obligations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H091617647BD3417ABDE6B91C1A390613"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Agency assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each department, agency, establishment, or regulatory agency or commission, shall provide to the Director such information and assistance as the Director may reasonably request to assist the Director in carrying out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H833AA84F49834AFCB06992F412FF1962"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mandatory inflation forecasting</header><paragraph id="H6D6D8DFE64114E9A84638AD37AC29303"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Submission of bills to the director</header><text>On the date that a committee of authorization of the Senate or the House of Representatives orders reported major legislation, the committee shall promptly provide the legislation to the Director for the purpose of carrying out responsibilities detailed in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD5161C0EF5448A0A8ADF47107676D85"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mandatory reporting on inflationary forecasting</header><text>For any major legislation provided to the Director under paragraph (1), the Director shall prepare and submit to the applicable committee a statement estimating the inflationary effects of the legislation, including whether the legislation is determined to have no significant impact on inflation, is determined to have quantifiable inflationary impact on the consumer price index, or is determined likely to have a significant impact on inflation but the amount cannot be determined at the time the estimate is prepared.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42885BEF95884DA28C14A119FF781BF8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Amended bills and joint resolutions; conference reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a bill or joint resolution is passed in an amended form (including if passed by one House as an amendment in the nature of a substitute for the text of a bill or joint resolution from the other House) or is reported by a committee of conference in amended form, and the amended form constitutes major legislation not previously considered by either House, then the chair of the committee that reported the bill or joint resolution or any other committee chair designated by the Speaker of the House of Representatives or the President pro tempore of the Senate (as the case may be), or the committee of conference, respectively, shall ensure to the greatest extent practicable that the Director shall prepare a statement as provided in paragraph (2) or a supplemental statement for the bill or joint resolution in that amended form.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H89FFBFA98C7B439E8AB44046FE0A6F08"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Legislation subject to point of order</header><text>It shall not be in order in the Senate or the House of Representatives to consider any major legislation reported by a committee unless the committee has published a statement of the Director in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H580206A80FC3430586B7A556264CC8FF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Provisions relating to the House of Representatives</header><paragraph id="H8E12D23DE22B471AA434368E6EDA84E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>It shall not be in order in the House of Representatives to consider a rule or order that waives the application of subsection (d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB478B0E58C2F4724ABD09B2A83DE4EF9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disposition of points of order</header><subparagraph id="H5D3235C2F0BB49EEBD5404A1A3598A2A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application to the house of representatives</header><text>This paragraph shall apply only to the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07AFC6960C614DEBB5CFF46AE03D5520"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Threshold burden</header><text>In order to be cognizable by the Chair, a point of order under subsection (d) or paragraph (1) of this subsection must specify the precise language on which it is premised.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CEC530A171144FAA6F9F71B73BAD880"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Question of consideration</header><text>As disposition of points of order under subsection (d) or paragraph (1) of this section, the Chair shall put the question of consideration with respect to the proposition that is the subject of the points of order.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F95461A24EE4C868F05B22C1FECCC0F"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Debate and intervening motions</header><text>A question of consideration under this section shall be debatable for 10 minutes by each Member initiating a point of order and for 10 minutes by an opponent on each point of order, but shall otherwise be decided without intervening motion except one that the House adjourn or that the Committee of the Whole rise, as the case may be.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H239863D75F86446A85DC777433A76425"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Effect on amendment in order as original text</header><text>The disposition of the question of consideration under this subsection with respect to a bill or joint resolution shall be considered also to determine the question of consideration under this subsection with respect to an amendment made in order as original text.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H9A6551231D43432B9160EBF67E23D4E8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Congressional Budget and Impoundment Control Act of 1974 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 406 the following:</text><quoted-block id="H7C0C8AAA1C5D415895BBAE928285A040" style="OLC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 407. Mandatory inflation forecasting.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

