<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9CC44B90EE294CFA8505EC7A57A38E24" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4570 IH: Legacies of War Recognition and Unexploded Ordnance Removal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4570</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230712">July 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000560">Mr. Larsen of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize assistance to support activities relating to the clearance of landmines, unexploded ordnance, and other explosive remnants of war in Cambodia, Laos, and Vietnam, and to recognize the refugee and immigrant communities who supported and defended the Armed Forces during the conflict in Southeast Asia, including Hmong, Cham, Cambodian, Iu-Mien, Khmu, Lao, Montagnard, and Vietnamese Americans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H63953B630347434CBED0F2CF83673417" style="OLC"><section id="H5A74694AD0564D0A9BC64210C95C037F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Legacies of War Recognition and Unexploded Ordnance Removal Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H48EBFD3B3A2C45249670969D9C1EECE4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Recognition of the communities who supported and defended the Armed Forces in Southeast Asia</header><subsection id="HC5FCFE30093343DD8FDF6DD6EE54F227"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text><paragraph id="HD97A7F147CD649D696D2316B241069B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>During the conflict in Southeast Asia during the 1960s and 1970s, many Hmong, Cham, Cambodians, Iu-Mien, Khmu, Lao, Montagnard, and Vietnamese people—</text><subparagraph id="H567063EC8673490A804D118ED5AA549D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>supported the Armed Forces;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4023DEDA3B204295B369D37FF72A5A92"><enum>(B)</enum><text>rescued United States pilots shot down in enemy-controlled territory and returned the pilots to safety;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD807283E8624B1AA0A8A129B2DF591C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>gathered and provided intelligence to the Armed Forces about enemy troop positions, movement, and strength; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79B69FF72BF340FB803B74E64284260D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provided food, shelter, and support to members of the Armed Forces.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1987740B15E4F46AFB22271F592D0EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The national armed forces of Cambodia facilitated the evacuation of the United States Embassy in Phnom Penh on April 12, 1975, by fighting Khmer Rouge forces that advanced upon the capital.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H535BE7A7B55145F3BB02AB05307BE723"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A tragic legacy of the conflict in Southeast Asia is the lethal risk posed by landmines, unexploded ordnance (in this Act, referred to as <quote>UXO</quote>), and explosive remnants of war in Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia that still litter forests, rice fields, villages, school grounds, roads, and other populated areas, hindering development and efforts to reduce poverty.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8534C2274A894F23A965AF122C5ADC9C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Vietnam remains one of the world’s most contaminated countries, with an estimated 800,000 tons of UXO left over from the conflict in Southeast Asia that ended more than 40 years ago. Since 1975, UXO accidents have caused more than 105,000 casualties, including more than 38,000 deaths of Vietnamese civilians.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFB241C116C04F949442FF1B551A6FD2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>In Laos, much of the country’s land remains contaminated with tens of millions of small, unexploded cluster munitions. Since 1964, UXO and other explosive remnants of war have injured or killed more than 50,000 civilians in Laos.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H496D6CDB52CB452CA5E48AA1A952D71C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Cambodia has experienced one of the highest rates of landmine and UXO casualties in the world. Over 64,000 Cambodians have been injured or killed by landmines, UXO, or other explosive remnants of war since 1979.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E3D050971D34B6ABF54ACF07FE8C916"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The United States is the world’s leading financial supporter of demining and programs to remove UXO. Since 1993, the United States has provided more than $4,200,000,000 in assistance for locating and destroying UXO and other explosive remnants of war and related programs in more than 100 countries, including more than $185,000,000 in Vietnam, $310,000,000 in Laos, and $180,000,000 in Cambodia.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7EBF15C97004491EA6F5B3C75F370300"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H08E09C68556846DBA820D85DB8626A05"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Hmong, Cham, Cambodian, Iu-Mien, Khmu, Lao, Montagnard, and Vietnamese people deserve recognition for their support and defense of the Armed Forces during the conflict in Southeast Asia; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31C25CEBB5EA4672BA2E8996FC8058AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States should continue to support activities to clear landmines, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war and to provide related assistance in Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia, while strengthening people-to-people ties and reaffirming the long-standing commitment of the United States to Southeast Asia.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H71882BDBF6454A89AE93508F5C3ACD07"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization of Assistance for Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia</header><subsection id="HD7578E251B6E4832B338FBDD7B79703B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may provide humanitarian assistance to Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia for programs to support the following:</text><paragraph id="HD979B883D26F48E9A0B62635BC87BAD3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The development or updating of national surveys of landmines, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A9B33ED17B64435905F66EEC88FDE24"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Clearance of such landmines, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B8727D6DB1E4901B20E1D1FFE6B0052"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Stockpile management of small arms, light weapons, and ammunition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC00981126038465F8C24F3D298A78BD8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Capacity building, risk education, destruction, and physical security related to landmines, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H972C5213F6C74487A7143E10E0A03649"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Survivors of incidents involving landmines, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war, including by providing medical assistance and prosthetic devices related to landmines, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2C501CDAC5BC4DB28B0F66C13C077B8D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In carrying out this section, the President shall seek to consult, partner, and coordinate with international organizations, civil societies, donor governments, and other stakeholders, as the President determines appropriate, to leverage the expertise, financial support, and resources of such entities to minimize duplication of efforts and maximize the efficient and effective provision of assistance from the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H957EF4496537488189FEAFCE376875BB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reporting and Briefing</header><paragraph id="HA60F7C26C95C49DDAA7081A18789A8E9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the President shall provide a report to the appropriate committees of Congress on activities undertaken in accordance with this section on the progress of amounts made available from the Nonproliferation, Anti-terrorism, Demining, and related programs account for demining and clearance of landmines, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war in Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia. Such reports shall also include—</text><subparagraph id="HB56B191E8483439ABE82D742029DE760"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the status of amounts made available from the Nonproliferation, Anti-terrorism, Demining, and related programs account that are obligated pursuant to authorities provided by prior Acts and the status of unallocated amounts made available to such account as of the date of enactment of this Act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0AD612A6C1E4E59BE4609F94A6366F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how Nonproliferation, Anti-terrorism, Demining, and related programs account funds have contributed to landmine, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war clearance efforts in Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H913C3F8588F94B3AA45ADB1A981B03E3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>estimates of contaminated land that has been cleared, land that still contains landmines, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war, land that has not been assessed for contamination, and data on the origin of any antipersonnel mines cleared, to the extent possible;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF0CDF292E00427399B39DC6281767FA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of collaboration between the United States and the governments of Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia including past and current progress to date in establishing nationwide contamination databases in such countries to refine landmine, UXO, and other explosive remnants of war locations and target clearance efforts; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10B29F495B0C461F8FFF691B71EC320E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an assessment on the efforts of the Department of State to work with the Government of the Lao People’s Democratic Republic regarding the repatriation of and the efforts to reintegrate into Laotian society those of Hmonh, Lao, Khmu, and Mien or Yao descent who arrived in the United States as refugees but have since been removed.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F215D56A4E44C90BEC305C5D2C84429"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Briefings</header><text>The President shall annually brief the appropriate committees of Congress on activities undertaken in accordance with this section for each year for which amounts are authorized under subsection (d).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE392FA4A359E49158A60C954881C6C76"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the President $100,000,000 for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H73023F4177F044EEAD4B99222EBA01FB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act: </text><paragraph id="H586C3D56CA3445E2B9900F5A743D76AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H5E7FF4200EA143D8927427A17FF2B449"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Armed Services, and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H079D94E9074749128152FA3FE61DF952"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Armed Services, and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB1EFD538FD54329A244ED307B576541"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>unexploded ordnance</term> or <term>UXO</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

