<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H65EE3E9D478E4A35A121B4EEB81FB253" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3915 IH: Aviation Weather Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3915</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230607">June 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve the National Weather Service&#8217;s forecasting of turbulence and acquisition of aviation weather data, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0C6D45404DE84C75B16BAD7B57DCFF36" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6E9EB3FA90614CF4B685908F094E7195" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Aviation Weather Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H557D40EE2BB8403B9789CFDE25C38281"><enum>2.</enum><header>Aviation weather and data innovation</header> <subsection id="HA4F47C17C7054BD1A64663BBAA7E24ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The Director of the National Weather Service shall maintain an aircraft-based observation program (in this section referred to as the <quote>program</quote>) to partner with the weather industry for the deployment on aircraft of critical atmospheric sensors.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD133288F20E148D59523F3C51E651067"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>The program shall include activities that carry out the following:</text> <paragraph id="HCEBA921FDB814D5BA7461887836B18E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Procurement of weather data from commercial aircraft, including Mode S data, water vapor data, or data from Aircraft Meteorological Data Relay or Tropospheric Airborne Meteorological Data Reporting systems.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3F4FE47665454D9992DFCD68C410D122"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Acquisition of additional vertical profile observations that provide the spatial and temporal density required for numerical weather prediction systems.</text></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="H4758240E14D248A3AEFFCAB1E20BF80A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Budget</header><text>The Director of the National Weather Service shall, not less frequently than annually, submit to Congress a proposed budget corresponding with the activities described in subsection (b).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE5982CFA92D24D64B78583DA029B5BE5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to appropriated to the Operations, Research, and Facilities account of the National Weather Service up to $10,000,000 for each fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HEB7BD95850DC471CADBB823988041E59"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>weather industry</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Weather Research and Forecasting Innovation Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8501">15 U.S.C. 8501</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H196D922909F8497E8568701EC1BC9EFE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Aviation weather and turbulence forecasting coordination</header> 
<subsection id="H3A4D5CC5D6A649A4811FF0D9A1609042" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director of the National Weather Service shall include turbulence events or phenomena in the forecasting capabilities of the National Weather Service’s Aviation Weather Center, and deliver consistent, timely, and accurate weather and turbulence information for the world airspace system and the protection of lives and property.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H07D3075D90C944BAAC30B284093D8486"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Director of the National Weather Service shall coordinate with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to improve weather and turbulence forecasting capabilities, including the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB21DF0056CC045B5A49A9F0B0B78A9CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishing within the Federal Government an interagency working group to determine weather and environmental data or observation requirements, needs, and potential solutions related to aviation weather and turbulence forecasting.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD44CD0302C0E4D42ADA790F978087293"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identifying current and future potential data gaps related to turbulence events or phenomena that can—</text>
<subparagraph id="H7BBF7E67DE2E4909BEA0793B6172EBE3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify or inform route specific flight planning; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H06C8849277284A16B6861E9638774E41"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be supplemented or filled by commercial aviation tools.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6886E386EE9F47E0961AA9182DA31769"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Transitioning research initiatives and pilot programs, including a pilot program of instrumentation for observing greenhouse gases and other atmospheric factors deployed on commercial aircraft and supporting the evaluation of a sustained observing network using such platforms, into operations that improve the forecasting missions of the Aviation Weather Center.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HF53360D5704944B3B54242A74D393A3E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Next generation aviation research</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Paragraph (3) of section 102(b) of the Weather Research and Forecasting Innovation Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8512">15 U.S.C. 8512(b)</external-xref>), is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA0B8CF2A6E564B61BAFE1F9E6CFE76E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (F) and (G) as subparagraphs (G) and (H), respectively; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDAC022716D554ABD8A4762123DC8A11F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (E) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H93832118A63A496B8D25246327E49CCB" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="H05981CD9D78F482ABD28CB5385F8EB5C"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aviation weather, contrails, atmospheric composition, and turbulence events or phenomena to improve scientific understanding and forecast capabilities for the world airspace system;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

