<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0DC8E8E7611A479BB81C49163CCA914D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4911 IH: Supporting the Health and Safety of Law Enforcement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4911</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001090">Mr. Harder of California</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the establishment of a pilot program to provide grants to community mental health centers for the placement of social workers with law enforcement agencies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD80937616EE8457E9CADDC94F277438B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE22EEB2D1B874428BBBEB696D7FA661E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting the Health and Safety of Law Enforcement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCB343DFAD89A4EF39D595953C28A9869"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall establish a pilot program to provide grants to community mental health centers for the placement of social workers with law enforcement agencies to facilitate closer coordination on law enforcement issues with an underlying connection to mental health.</text></section> 
<section id="H5A341E73E22844199401EB566A6578D2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Number and amount of grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Attorney General shall award not more than 4 grants each fiscal year to community mental health centers (as such term is defined in section 1861 of the Social Security Act) in each of the 4 census regions. Each such grant shall be in an amount not to exceed $300,000. The term of such a grant shall be 3 years. Each such mental health center shall partner with a law enforcement agency that employs not more than 100 officers in order to carry out the purposes of the grant.</text></section> <section id="H7AB3177F469C42C0955B0647C0AA6496"><enum>4.</enum><header>Eligibility for placement with a law enforcement agency</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">To be eligible for placement with a law enforcement agency under this Act, a social worker shall be—</text> 
<paragraph id="HFF7AEF8A2FF74F33A223E5E6BB9746AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>licensed under the applicable State law; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFD7DD81ADDBB4782A7522B187874387B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>employed by a community mental health center.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H410CE722D5A347E9B63A2E2297F1FF75"><enum>5.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $2,500,000 for fiscal years 2024, 2025, and 2026.</text></section> <section id="HDADBCEE286FF456E81EDCDE88AD833FA"><enum>6.</enum><header>Termination of program; report to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act is repealed on the date that is 3 years after a grant is first made under this Act. The Attorney General shall report to Congress not later than six months thereafter on the outcomes of any cases where the social worker became involved and the total number of such cases, and any other information deemed relevant.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

