<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6C068025EFAE4944BB769C7F7E41A852" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3811 IH: Veterans Mental and Behavioral Health Quality of Care Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-05</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3811</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230605">June 5, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to conduct a study on the quality of care difference between behavioral and mental health care provided by health care providers of the Department of Veterans Affairs compared to non-Department providers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H66FD454C290D4F81BAA8249043C454C8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H062CDD8854374D81840DD600403B7917" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans Mental and Behavioral Health Quality of Care Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF153BBB8470E47638EB76EB490775861"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on quality of care difference between behavioral and mental health care provided by health care providers of Department of Veterans Affairs compared to non-Department providers</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H83A27D4EE5A140B493861C2EFBA79E09"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall conduct a study on the quality of care difference between behavioral and mental health care under the laws administered by the Secretary provided by health care providers of the Department of Veterans Affairs compared to non-Department providers.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H352F056ED1C74C8B96FD49203A448300"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conduct of study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct the study under subsection (a) through the use of an independent and objective organization outside the Department.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9E2B2D60600547E882A1FBB491BD7D4F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Matters To be studied</header><text>In conducting the study under subsection (a), the Secretary shall determine—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H16D09271CABB430692D2A9A864ABEEEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any differences in health outcomes for veterans between care from providers of the Department and non-Department providers, including symptom scores and suicide risk;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBBDED3F623EF431D82F5B707917F8FBA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if non-Department providers are using evidence-based practices in the treatment of behavioral and mental health issues; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB4075F91B7184219971D16543D66F627"><enum>(3)</enum><text>potential gaps in coordination between providers of the Department and non-Department providers in responding to individuals seeking behavioral or mental health care.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8944B6AB0A024F218166E72C8F8EEE14"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the study conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

