<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H692B5E9B61494D8087E29BF999AFB516" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6377 IH: Apprentice-Related Child Care Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6377</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231113">November 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a grant program for States to support apprentices in apprenticeships programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5909E02FA75E4F6C83AF6D7097E9D3EB" style="OLC"><section id="H766D616F65EA432AB8490F59D73C6D5C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Apprentice-Related Child Care Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ARCC Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF7BB19A1847641658F65549FFB3BA395"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program</header><subsection id="HD6C466B683D74E7D82C0B67CA16EF5A3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><paragraph id="HB9C5F8BE6E0B46E5AFA76E0D74ADC50E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From the amount appropriated under subsection (i)(1) that is not reserved under subsection (i)(2), the Secretary of Labor shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to 10 States for each such State to provide monthly stipends to eligible child care providers on behalf of individuals who are participating in pre-apprenticeship programs or apprenticeship programs to assist such individuals in covering the costs of childcare during such participation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B4361D0B4D940B7B5590C7389E7067B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grant amounts</header><text>In awarding grants under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall award an equal amount to each State awarded such a grant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED93D160ABDC4ACA918E42B04BC61A97"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grant periods</header><text>A grant awarded under this section shall be awarded—</text><subparagraph id="HBD9969D182554551919C1EF3DBDEEA3B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for a period of two years; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2346868E4644CB081BD7351BD901CAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in equal amounts for each year of such period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1092FCAD7914DFB8264177D8F008516"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Grant priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall ensure that States that are awarded the grants—</text><subparagraph id="H3DDF6BC04CCD46DE8819EF2D30726527"><enum>(A)</enum><text>are geographically diverse; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BACF654E1134E00B344AE80F7289C53"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have pre-apprenticeship programs and apprenticeship programs in in-demand industry sectors and occupations, including in emerging high-tech, high-growth industries.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H022E7E6B2E894A22ACA7EA574C745AC1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under this Act, a State shall submit to the Secretary an application, in such form, at such time, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, which shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HB0CBCCCDD10C47DFA29E1A6A27219A9B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information regarding how the State intends to distribute monthly stipends in accordance with subsection (c).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF378500DCC1E4073BF47B235EF1ED95D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the case of any individual who is selected to benefit from a stipend under subsection (c) and participating in a pre-apprenticeship program or an apprenticeship program that will end after the end of the grant period, any plan the State may have to provide child care support for such an individual for the period of such pre-apprenticeship or apprenticeship program during which the individual will not be benefitting from such stipends. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE91D6EB7A11F4709A41183633C057680"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header><paragraph id="HCEE6B08BF9AD4B14BD4C0E984D66A14B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State that receives a grant under this Act shall—</text><subparagraph id="HB6572FCB8CA14E86935EEBA275E226D1" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in accordance with the requirements of paragraph (3), select individuals to benefit from a monthly stipend who—</text><clause id="HCC6A992C6C3D45E196A4A5EEC00B16DE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have one or more dependent children; and</text></clause><clause id="HE8D37B93559748BAB627108C3A3D1A7E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are participating in a pre-apprenticeship program or an apprenticeship program in the State; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA86F7F291BD24CCD90DDDBFD2226A96D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>distribute such stipends to eligible child care providers directly on behalf of the individuals described under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C9F5A3661364725B025EB924477E733"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Monthly stipend amounts</header><text>A monthly stipend described in paragraph (1) shall not be less than $500 per dependent child.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC39A37C22404870B33670233A2D3E5C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In selecting individuals to benefit from a monthly stipend, a State shall prioritize individuals who are historically underrepresented in the industries of the pre-apprenticeship programs or apprenticeship programs of such individuals, based on race, ethnicity, or gender.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE24B683EB388467B9655B78128E24973"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports by States</header><paragraph id="HD49785BBCA644F279900C913FF01CD69"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the end of the grant period of the grant awarded to a State under this Act, the State shall submit to the Secretary a report that includes information on—</text><subparagraph id="HC48C281C7ADF453CB043619E51E079D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the individuals that benefitted from monthly stipends, including with respect to each such individual—</text><clause id="H3CFC014DD7DF4617951E4165B2C67B70"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total number of months such stipends were provided to a eligible child care provider on behalf of the individual;</text></clause><clause id="H87E4895586CB482287EB1804F53CE01D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total amount provided by such stipends;</text></clause><clause id="H5FE74AD74A4D4CF983129031F9875165"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an individual enrolled in an apprenticeship program, the wage rate, benefits, stipends, or other compensation provided to such individual—</text><subclause id="H40E3013D0E4B4B5CA00494375D7DBD50"><enum>(I)</enum><text>while enrolled in such program; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H2091E8C30BC94E99AFD7962D82064272"><enum>(II)</enum><text>after exiting the program and beginning work in the industry of such program;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HD2891F4366C14BCC9E0491638E844366"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an individual enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship program, a description of any compensation provided to the individual while enrolled in such program, including the wage rate, benefits, stipends, or any other compensation;</text></clause><clause id="HA92152B67DE9499694D4591696EAE9FF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the industry of the pre-apprenticeship program or apprenticeship program in which the individual was a participant; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43D852200CEE47AEAF158FBAEBB4452B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each apprenticeship program and pre-apprenticeship program for which the State provided stipends to eligible child care providers on behalf of such individuals—</text><clause id="H3EC55EF1655445C687C061BCCF47EB6F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the retention and completion rates for the individuals described in subparagraph (A); and</text></clause><clause id="H3AF0E100167848ABBB2CEF85CEE2EEB6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the retention and completion rates for the individuals not described in subparagraph (A); and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64FB8039CF0E4BFBBD7330EF21E11269"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the method the State used to distribute the stipends to eligible child care providers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A908C8CA4C94FEEA79AACA49962970C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Follow-up reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each of the 3 years after the date that a State submits the report under paragraph (1), the State shall submit to the Secretary a report on the retention and completion rates described in clauses (i) and (ii) of subparagraph (B) for the preceding year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C44BCCEB2894B8692BBC94F188E51E6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information submitted under paragraphs (1) and (2) shall be disaggregated by race, ethnicity, and gender, except that such disaggregation shall not be required in the case in which the number of apprentices in a subgroup is insufficient to yield statistically reliable information or the results would reveal personally identifiable information about an apprentice.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H511F6A8CF0B54EEF91713ED6C4EF85ED"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report by the Secretary</header><paragraph id="H45BDC767B2734A1D842E8A5AE51E0B15"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the Secretary receives the last report under subsection (d), the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that summarizes—</text><subparagraph id="HD1E8FDA78C24413B91C5B162C6DE99F2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the effect the stipends had—</text><clause id="H75A71F45918742FB86B1C66A0BF23CDB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on the pre-apprenticeship program or apprenticeship program retention and completion rates of individuals who received monthly stipends; and</text></clause><clause id="HEF0F927727F9421AAC5D6B9BC178AF5F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the wage rates and benefits received by such individuals after exiting an apprenticeship program;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H476F5DEE5D9846B4B716D2EDBB90F7A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the methods the States used to distribute stipends to eligible child care providers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6CAC16D43644B82869507E38F43B4E5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any unanticipated effect or consequence on—</text><clause id="H4243D2CB57E9470786B13C9C3C65072A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>individuals receiving the stipend;</text></clause><clause id="H6067DBBA6F894654932577F9665937DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the sponsors of the pre-apprenticeship programs or the apprenticeship programs; and</text></clause><clause id="HD9DCE4FA6A4445AD95DEC54914606081"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the local areas in which the individuals who received a stipend participated in such programs.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H565F5B71A1E240A3B232AFD4F57F65FB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Follow-up reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each of the 3 years after the date that the Secretary submits the report under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that summarizes the information in the reports received from the States under subsection (d)(2) for the preceding year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59D5C1D4665A48CEB8EB0CF96365DBF2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information submitted under paragraph (1)(A) shall be disaggregated in accordance with the disaggregation requirements of subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H024AFA7EF0944DB68F04599F2396040E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Stipend amounts excluded from Federal taxation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Stipend amounts awarded under this Act may not be included in the gross income of the individual who benefitted from such stipend for purposes of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAE36F2373FA742C2B03039CF39A83A7B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Disregard stipend amounts in other Federal programs</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, a stipend distributed to an eligible child care provider under this Act shall not be taken into account in determining the need or eligibility of the individual who benefitted from such stipend for benefits or assistance, or the amount of such benefits or assistance, under any Federal, State, or local program financed in whole or in part with Federal funds. </text></subsection><subsection id="H533D92C7182C4F269BC03C45A18EB01F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Supplement and not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any monthly stipend distributed to an eligible child care provider on behalf of an individual under this Act shall supplement and not supplant the wages such individual earns while participating in a pre-apprenticeship program or apprenticeship program.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD047B4820FD24DEDB8A6C798A2D20682"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="HE7FD1B16CA0D4586B1C454C0AB5E443A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024–2025.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FDE30321C064E18AD9ADE58A259DD86"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text>The Secretary shall reserve 1.5 percent of the funds appropriated under paragraph (1) for each fiscal year to carry out the study and report required by subsection (e).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E610FF38EDD4543A39EC0C150FB0AA7"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HA334E73259324FCFAFC3EDC709E783FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Apprenticeship program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>apprenticeship program</term> means an apprenticeship program registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; 50 Stat. 664, chapter 663; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>), including any requirement, standard, or rule promulgated under such Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H886C986FB73B4BE5A8101536075049D0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible child care provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible child care provider</term> has the meaning given the term in section 658P of the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9858n">42 U.S.C. 9858n</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H53B0BFF4EAC940619557D33A967B612C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pre-apprenticeship program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>pre-apprenticeship program</term> means a program, initiative, or set of strategies that—</text><subparagraph id="H036E9C3FCE1D45808D4C88FE5368812F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is designed to prepare individuals to participate in an apprenticeship program, including preparing individuals with the skills and competencies necessary to succeed in such program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00C091A98F5045968BBCA819BAD6F142"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is carried out by an entity that has entered into a formal agreement with one or more sponsors of an apprenticeship program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF02E4B1160D140D39BFC1C6F9E1695D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>includes—</text><clause id="HDA691632B58046B1940848835C9EA8D2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>theoretical education (including the use of curricula); and</text></clause><clause id="H479D34262F4140FF8E2D2DE19FDDCD53"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>training (including hands-on training)—</text><subclause id="H3D7B2BE924704170A9121B3EDE6B6AEA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>aligned with industry standards of an apprenticeship program; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H31306F4F679646B2B2A7EC5A0A7E7745"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that does not displace an employee where such training takes place.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2430DE07868E47EF8ED3E1DAA119E8B6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State board</term> means a State workforce development board established under section 101 of the Worker Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3101">29 U.S.C. 3101</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H004C5B073F6749D69E4E58961D481C0D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>WIOA terms</header><text>The terms <term>area career and technical education school</term>, <term>community-based organization</term>, <term>in-demand industry sector or occupation</term>, <term>local area</term>, <term>local board</term>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State</term>, have the meaning given such terms in section 3 of the Worker Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3103">29 U.S.C. 3103</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

