<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="H68E685E9CEA64BD0810D967D7D4938D3"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 813 RH: Global Investment in American Jobs Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 108</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 813</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–137]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230202">February 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000615">Mr. Pence</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on February 2, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Commerce, in coordination with the heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, to conduct an interagency review of and report to Congress on ways to increase the global competitiveness of the United States in attracting foreign direct investment.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HIF00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H7F8F15F1FDCD4996BD9404ED25F9C473"><section id="H9D00194AE18B4A44998AFFC6C3527504" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Global Investment in American Jobs Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H935A2D0BA3B84493A0CC923141843CDC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H41A3C9FAAF0F4EB4BD99E93B29132607"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the ability of the United States to attract foreign direct investment from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries is directly linked to the long-term economic prosperity, global competitiveness, and security of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D2C70BAF70F41B08D240D6F5572CF88"><enum>(2)</enum><text>it is a top national priority to enhance the global competitiveness, economic prosperity, and security of the United States by—</text><subparagraph id="HC3B7C227AF2F49709CA12DB2B0FA1F90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>removing unnecessary barriers to foreign direct investment from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries and the jobs that such investment creates throughout the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AA28BAE0512477E8E5FE95A81F4982E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promoting policies to ensure the United States remains the premier global destination to invest, hire, innovate, provide services, and manufacture products;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF5F1CC4F26F49CBADF34E27AB7EF90C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>promoting policies to ensure the United States remains the global leader in developing and deploying cutting-edge technologies, such as self-driving vehicle technology, artificial intelligence, Internet of Things, quantum computing, blockchain; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF315B58C68E24A64B80B7A69C9F724C1"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promoting policies that maintain and expand resilient supply chains and reduce the dependence of the United States on supply chains from China and other foreign adversaries;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8597DAD3621A4428BEC28AE841B6F923"><enum>(3)</enum><text>maintaining the United States commitment to an open investment policy with private-sector entities based in trusted countries encourages other countries to reciprocate and enable the United States to open new markets abroad for United States companies and their products;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9669DAF7554E478BB724A36361AA3660"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">while foreign direct investment by responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries can enhance the United States economic strength, policies regarding foreign direct investment should reflect security interests and should not disadvantage domestic investors, companies, or the workforce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6177D1C6B56D473194C1171C80EFF88E"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">United States efforts to attract foreign direct investment from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries should be consistent with efforts to maintain and improve the domestic standard-of-living, including for the workforce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7398884509FF4BAF993851CA8BEA4E07"><enum>(6)</enum><text>as digital information becomes increasingly important to the United States economy and the development of new technologies and services that will be crucial to the country’s competitiveness in the 21st century global economy, barriers including data localization and infringement of intellectual property rights must be further addressed; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78DE2FE79731433AA761DADB0CE2B546"><enum>(7)</enum><text>foreign direct investment by companies or other entities owned, directed, supported, or influenced by the Chinese Communist Party is a threat to United States security and merits an aggressive policy framework to protect United States interests, jobs, intellectual property, and security;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AEE78F095A2444489E2E9142CB1FB4D"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">foreign direct investment from any source should not result in the net loss of United States economic activity, productive capabilities, and supply chain resilience; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H531CD58140A441ED922E91BD39EBFEF7"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">foreign direct investment from any source should strengthen United States security and support United States workforce, health and safety, consumer, and financial standards. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HEDDA5C82DE3948D386E6F8017799746B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Foreign direct investment review</header><subsection id="H3E2E452D60BD4A07939F6848C3BD628B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The Secretary and the Comptroller General of the United States, in consultation with the Federal Interagency Investment Working Group established pursuant to Executive Order 13577 (76 Fed Reg. 35715; relating to establishment of the SelectUSA Initiative) and in consultation with the heads of other relevant agencies, shall conduct an interagency review of the global competitiveness of the United States in attracting foreign direct investment from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries and addressing key foreign trade barriers that firms in advanced technology sectors face in the global digital economy.</text></subsection><subsection id="H99AFCB2F76AE4667B660133DD2DFBD54"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Specific Matters To Be Included</header><text>The review conducted pursuant to subsection (a) shall include a review of the following:</text><paragraph id="HF31D22240B2B4B658D25CF42A3D8683C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The economic impact of foreign direct investment in the United States, with particular focus on manufacturing, services, trade (with an emphasis on digital trade), and United States jobs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB5864F7DFF04108AF650A397262F01A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Trends in global cross-border investment and data flows and the underlying factors for such trends.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA677B152C6DE4D1285EE96DE8BBEA187"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Federal Government policies, that facilitate foreign direct investment attraction and retention from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7783B4B74584387BAF110FB27D31992"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Foreign direct investment as compared to direct investment by domestic entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE34E75E985548B9A05AFD8D62298092"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Foreign direct investment that takes the form of greenfield investment as compared to foreign direct investment relating to merger and acquisition activity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AF43B2175FB4C8AA5E6E5C5B95385F2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The unique challenges posed by foreign direct investment, particularly acquisitions, in the United States by State-owned or State-backed enterprises, especially from State-directed economies, including companies or other entities owned, directed, supported, or influenced by the Chinese Communist Party.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52DF714A9DF946609FC973E9795818BB"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Specific information on the prevalence of investments made by State-owned or State-backed enterprises, especially from State-directed economies, including companies or other entities owned, directed, supported, or influenced by the Chinese Communist Party, with a particular focus on investments relating to manufacturing, services, trade (with an emphasis on digital trade), and jobs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0846C421301147FFA6BC3F59338BA71B"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How other trusted countries are dealing with the challenge, including screening for and preventing market distorting investments, of State-directed and State-supported investment and whether there are opportunities to work with like-minded nations to address such challenge.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C29C16B25E74CB7881714012269F5A2"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Ongoing Federal Government efforts to improve the investment climate and facilitate greater levels of foreign direct investment in the United States from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F5F8B3054B84BAAA5E0F34FABC59255"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Innovative and noteworthy initiatives by State and local government to attract foreign investment from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE68DAFB6B0845F989538C5102A03B8E"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Initiatives by other countries to identify best practices for increasing global competitiveness in attracting foreign direct investment from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E9D5BF5EC35491C81592B1EC6E37515"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The impact that protectionist policies by other countries, including forced data localization rules, forced localization of production, industrial subsidies, and the infringement of intellectual property rights, have on the advanced technology economy of the United States and the ability for United States located firms to develop innovative technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5841116906049E39F3F9C42E6417DA1"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other barriers to the ability of the United States to compete globally in an increasingly connected and digital global economy, including the use of technical barriers to trade (such as country-specific standards for technology products and digital services).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEBAFFC28CCB439DAA3D18FC1E095068"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The adequacy of efforts by the Federal Government to encourage and facilitate foreign direct investment in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98EC503F64664528990A166B0D8B3E53"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Efforts by the Chinese Communist Party to circumvent existing laws to gain access to United States markets, foreign direct investment responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries, or intellectual property.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD29622BF32241F8A9C25D0EB1B868E3"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The extent to which foreign direct investment from any source, including the Chinese Communist Party, results in displacement, offshoring, or outsourcing, including the impact of such investment on supply chains. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H99796D3EC9544D93961359FFE83D10A8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The review conducted pursuant to subsection (a) may not address laws or policies relating to the Committee on Foreign Investment in the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9913703AF30F4F03A3CFDAEEAEA4CB3D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public Comment</header><paragraph id="H0F53DBF1B02047D794834D216BC2C627"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review</header><text>Not sooner than 60 days before the date on which the review is commenced pursuant to subsection (a), the Secretary shall publish notice of the review in the Federal Register and shall provide an opportunity for public comment on the matters to be covered by the review.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BDFCDC82C064C4BBA2D852D178B8768"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not sooner than 60 days before the date on which the report is submitted pursuant to subsection (e), the Secretary shall publish the proposed findings and recommendations in the Federal Register and shall provide an opportunity for public comment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5162D6980F3E4016B4DC04BF8A1FDE85"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary, in coordination with the Federal Interagency Investment Working Group and the heads of other relevant agencies, shall submit to Congress a report on the findings of the review required pursuant to subsection (a) and include recommendations for increasing the global competitiveness of the United States in attracting foreign direct investment from responsible private-sector entities based in trusted countries in a manner that strengthens or maintains the security, workforce, consumer, or financial protections of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD854AF5C59C649658CA516E3CAA2A4D1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H22307656D12841069A1EE712DFE95847"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H161C97B035EE46CF99795BF30D6CDB41"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign adversary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>foreign adversary</term> has the meaning given that term in part 7.4 of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4871FEBA4B94741A06B5522A1F849F3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Responsible private-sector entity</header><text>The term <term>responsible private-sector entity</term> means an entity that the Secretary determines is—</text><subparagraph id="HC4FA5E8E303F422EA72410AF762865A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not organized under the laws of a foreign adversary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE3130F3C75D74C7B96D572BB2E814EBB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not owned, controlled, or otherwise subject to the influence of, a foreign adversary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A45F5A9616643F3AE1DE643884F21EC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0AA7C12583D94E799FBEA02B7B79F231" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, each commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H848B0C903ADB4C42B53AD1FFA86715DE"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Trusted country</header><text>The term <term>trusted country</term> means a country or economy that is not determined by the Secretary to be a foreign adversary of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

