<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE4E2162861304D19B25213C78CCBA140" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6841 IH: To amend the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 to allow the Secretary of Commerce to establish a Coastal and Estuarine Resilience and Restoration Program, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6841</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231215">December 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 to allow the Secretary of Commerce to establish a Coastal and Estuarine Resilience and Restoration Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H06E0D47D166A4754B807DACD2AB6AD73" style="OLC"><section id="HFB20C73AE651451D8B93E8FD66D26041" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Coastal and Estuarine Resilience and Restoration Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 307A of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1456-1">16 U.S.C. 1456–1</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7E911ADCAF2A4E9F9AA3BCBDF193646A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the heading and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="traditional">Coastal and Estuarine Resilience and Restoration Program</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31DA4C684A4F4870AD92B502025C91E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending subsection (a) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="HC626992595754730A43E851B03788824" style="OLC"><subsection id="H760BDCD9D88D484B9A824CF36E733141"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may conduct a Coastal and Estuarine Resilience and Restoration Program, in cooperation with State, regional, and other units of government, the National Estuarine Research Reserves, and non-governmental organizations for the purposes of—</text><paragraph id="HB840B230C97B4BE0B785ED49674863E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>protecting important coastal and estuarine areas that—</text><subparagraph id="H267D5D441206449FB35C240B379E4A66"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have significant conservation, recreational, coastal access, ecological, historical, community protection, or aesthetic value;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9530116CAAFD4411A98DD2828D643CE1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>are threatened by conversion from their natural, undeveloped, or recreational state to other uses; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC65A56F52E6E406FA59C5603C4AC960D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>could be managed or restored to effectively conserve, enhance, or restore ecological function or mitigate climate change; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC21BC33710F24032A029FF401AF3AE4C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">restoring developed property in vulnerable coastal and estuarine areas to a natural state to restore ecological function, allow for shoreline migration, and protect coastal communities.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H768B3CFFAD34491ABF410BED4DB331F1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (b), by striking <quote>or National Estuarine Research Reserve units</quote> and inserting <quote>, National Estuarine Research Reserves, or non-governmental organizations that meet the requirements of subsection (k)</quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H508C0EDA6A76416DB579752B9AAFE98A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="H644DC69C3B05410FAC3E5151131C3173" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>or National Estuarine Research Reserves</quote> and inserting <quote>, National Estuarine Research Reserves, or non-governmental organizations</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BC6AE2512FB48F981E84EAE02B63A59" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>shall identify</quote> and inserting <quote>may identify</quote>; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5CE441BF2194115AF3C9B0C3CB554B9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (7) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H495F6215D1404A8D96085DEC09061C89" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H7BEC3C36049A4E3590DE1682DF6EE276"><enum>(7)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4231F611F7704BC28A2946D803C79C1E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Priority shall be given to lands that—</text><clause id="H57CD640EAF264A6894CED012BFAD4754" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">can be effectively managed and protected and are described in subsection (a)(1)(A);</text></clause><clause id="H68F9B00FD0FF4C218C7E5EE46135C36B" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, benefit communities that may not have adequate resources to prepare for or respond to coastal hazards or to access coastline, including low-income communities; or</text></clause><clause id="H2283835182C7494EB3BBAF8D05EB112B" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H8E0E431F500546EA8F95F369E382B943"><enum>(I)</enum><text>are under an imminent threat of conversion to a use that will degrade or otherwise diminish their natural, undeveloped, or recreational state;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA719FC3436D6406E92A4164AD2A947FB" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>serve to mitigate the adverse impacts caused by coastal population growth on the coastal environment;</text></subclause><subclause id="H1C7B6F4F7A59424F94EAB8E44D675AF8" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>are within or adjacent to a National Estuarine Research Reserve designated under section 315, a national wildlife refuge, or a national estuary program, or are proposed for designation as such a reserve or other such protected area; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H55D64C7B2FCF4BB4BE01D2E420F02341" indent="up1"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>are under threat due to climate change or may serve to mitigate the adverse effects of climate change, including through long-term carbon storage, and to facilitate inland migration of coastal ecosystems in response to sea level rise.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB667AC8587E24940A22E619BC30A97CD" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the projects that are given priority under subparagraph (A), priority shall be given to lands that reflect conservation priorities identified pursuant to paragraphs (1) through (4).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H778A137D13F04B86B23F803D0F592A34"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (10), by striking <quote>triennially</quote> and inserting <quote>every 5 years</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E1E090AC1E0433499A324980E0F0ADA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (f)—</text><subparagraph id="H4C37EE303F4B44E28A068C2E1B749809"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(B), by inserting <quote>for any territory of the United States that is unable to provide such match,</quote> after <quote>community,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B4A464DECBC4975B8AF42C0D0BBB246" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text><clause id="HBF3A0B5B04A249CA84C79C60ECCAC5D4" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)(i), by striking <quote>the land meets the criteria set forth in section 2(b) and</quote> and inserting <quote>such use will further the goals set forth in subsection (b) and such land interest</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H3430124D49E046E7AD02F71BFAA0CA42" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking subparagraph (B) and redesignating subparagraph (C) as subparagraph (B);</text></clause><clause id="HA6DA3305E36542EBBE695DD30D7DAFCA" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B) (as so redesignated), by striking <quote>described in (A)</quote> and inserting <quote>described in subparagraph (A)</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H0747432594814122B6E42B4F0FD05DDA" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by inserting at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5D1B90B600084658ACF7AB6A490A8648" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H4510CBB8DEEB41CBBD6E8077861A3412" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The value of ecosystem services that such interest in land provides, including as a buffer for storm surge, as a habitat for economically valuable species, and as a long-term carbon store.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB39026F6852A4EA48FB545DAAE59BF1B"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (g), by striking <quote>15</quote> and inserting <quote>20</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F6128A8DF124B3694D6F97EA3E7589A" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (k) and (l) as subsections (l) and (m), respectively;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD412D08763824889B57E5E98918E5869" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (j) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3A72FBDA94564E23A11A8E2563CD83E0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HFE93EA2B16294330A0C852BA770F622D" commented="no"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Non-Governmental organizations</header><paragraph id="H43A723A6F295455B8335C3949911F8F7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A non-governmental organization that applies for a grant under this section may only be awarded a grant under subsection (b) to acquire property or an interest in property if such organization, with respect to the property or interest in property—</text><subparagraph id="HEC02A07243DE4717BC04B068EBC4E89E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides such documentation as the Secretary determines appropriate to demonstrate that the agency that is primarily responsible for managing coastal and estuarine land of the State in which the property or interest in property is located has provided public notice of the support of such agency for the grant application of such organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB27569F925D44308F09099EC36D57F9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>either—</text><clause id="HE085B06E43374E128FF8008AD1E396B4" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>ensures that the property or interest in property is, or will be made, accessible to the public; or</text></clause><clause id="H30DE565D17DE4D14A29979A4C44AF0A4" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides documentation showing that public access to the property or interest in property is required to be restricted to maintain the biological integrity, biological diversity, or environmental health of the property or interest in property; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE721EF7D936C40E6BEE391F243320B7F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>includes in the deed for the property or interest in property a clear statement regarding how the property or interest in property will be disposed of if such organization becomes nonviable after the date such organization acquires such property or interest in property.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F03FE0ACFAA4633B9643DD80060734E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance</header><text>The Secretary shall develop objective measures that each non-governmental organization that applies for a grant under this section shall use to demonstrate the compliance of such organization with the requirements of paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9E85D0B0EAA4CDD8E5400F093F49B54"><enum>(9)</enum><text>in subsection (m), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>fiscal years 2009 through 2013</quote> and inserting <quote>fiscal years 2024 through 2028</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H92BF3C348E284694B7981DAFC2F4273F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Amendments to National Estuarine Research Reserve System program</header><subsection id="H2A6DD3FE89164BCAAE4F3BAAADA17D36"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation of additional reserves</header><paragraph id="H5CE748400C0145A2BC0590F47FE0268D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall designate not less than 5 new national estuarine reserves in the System.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9631BB8B1B64145B46A9262ECC7FA8D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text>In making each designation under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall prioritize nominated sites that will promote the following with respect to the System:</text><subparagraph id="HF0594F1183AF41A3A4AEB7A3C85C3074"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The presence of a National Estuarine Research Reserve in each coastal State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21F4FF91798E476293F3041E2CABE54C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Full representation of biogeographic regions to ensure research in areas with distinct biodiversity or estuarine geography.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2B2A5BEB016B4133B61C1E5314265CA0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Financial assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 315(e)(1)(A)(ii) of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1461">16 U.S.C. 1461(f)(1)(A)(ii)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>and maintaining</quote> after <quote>constructing</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4420EE97F6194F9FAFDC918082ADB920"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Guidelines for tracking and modeling the impacts of climate change</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 315(c) of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1461">16 U.S.C. 1461(c)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HA9EA06B33BE2497791B60CB30F49F50F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraphs (3) through (5) as paragraphs (4) through (6), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4F21024DF5B41ECAFC3094C1C006225"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H282902879DA24587A3B09BB23C9CE3A1"><paragraph id="H58983373F56F49DCB0E90845DDE4962B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the establishment of coordinated long-term data monitoring and methods throughout the System for tracking and modeling the impacts of climate change on estuarine systems, including impacts on lake levels and sea levels;</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0BAB44BAE155458F95ACA4630929CA1B" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Program elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 315 of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1461">16 U.S.C. 1461</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCA73A1D233B44863919CA7424BA3403E"><subsection id="H08C29924FC5948AE9A9AF8345BEE11DC" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Systemwide Elements of the National Estuarine Research Reserve System</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall coordinate systemwide programs and activities in the System including—</text><paragraph id="H2B2CC238CC294B33AE0AE7285D99D433" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the centralized management and dissemination of data from System observation and monitoring networks;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5C33665B4B34A1FAC43C971BCE97B95" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a grant program employing the collaborative research model on coastal research and management priorities to be conducted at research reserve sites focused on the priorities determined by the Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB94585830C7C4B7CAA82109D65C060BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>using National Estuarine Research Reserves as living laboratories and as preferred placements for fellowship and research positions for the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC9AC336C1464C8C98195650AE6028D0" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establishing the Margaret A. Davidson Graduate Research Fellowship Program to address key coastal management questions and the coastal research and management priorities of the System and its place-based sites to help scientists and communities understand the coastal challenges that may influence future policy and management strategies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB73ADA90E8034D48A3523E75AEAD7537" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Place-Based Program Elements of the National Estuarine Research Reserve System</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each National Estuarine Research Reserve shall establish and maintain place-based program elements that include—</text><paragraph id="H1DB4F32CEF704FF89232ADDAE1563676" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a research, monitoring, and observation network that detects environmental change and informs suitable adaptation and mitigation strategies to coastal hazards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B6F7849410946FC83F611B6BCD5C78B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifying and monitoring sentinel sites that provide an opportunity to develop and test techniques for adapting to and mitigating the harmful effects of climate change;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB9E460C80054DC8864973DC0AD9C9E9" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>education, outreach, training, and interpretive programs that communicate the value and changing dynamics of coastal systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F2C0025001E44B3B5E10EAF9F8AC969" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>stewardship programs that provide science-based tools, habitat management, and restoration and that provide resources and information to inform coastal management;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC16328DB298F49B99E02EF5A48889981" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>coastal training programs that provide technical assistance to coastal communities, resource managers, and coastal decisionmakers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFF429FBDBDE4433876760E9ABF9ACA3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>identifying priority land for acquisition to enhance ecosystem and community resilience to the negative effects of climate change; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDD25DA6623B46E0872FCBC85E4FC319" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the lands and facilities that support such accessible research, monitoring, stewardship, education, and coastal training activities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5631A4EDBC984DE79B4F9098D6F979D6" commented="no"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Existing Uses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise explicitly provided in a management plan of a National Estuarine Research Reserve, each Reserve shall permit existing uses of System lands and waters, including (as applicable)—</text><paragraph id="H31EE28473BD84F77BCA5E11DA3BDE834" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>commercial and recreational fishing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28A28DACFD294A38A8B6134C14025623" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>hunting; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4123AA908D74482CAD6298B5CE80304C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>cultural uses.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H84D639C9902244388A36D33CC55D2F48" commented="no"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $47,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to provide financial assistance under this section.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H0C9978BDFFB84E238B923021AC878A17"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H8A2FA4C405E741E89807E0037E4F2C42"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coastal State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>coastal State</term> has the meaning given the term <term>coastal state</term> in section 304 of title III of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1453">16 U.S.C. 1453</external-xref>), as applicable to such title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4B4710B92534DBA8BC302AAB2B74723"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary</term> has the meaning given the term in section 304 of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1453">16 U.S.C. 1453</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9DD51B15AD84B8C9E95382E67983A2F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>System</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>System</term> means the National Estuarine Research Reserve System established under section 315 of the Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1461">16 U.S.C. 1461</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

