<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBE60C69D22C9454A960EC4578EEDE327" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2628 IH: Employee Profit-Sharing Encouragement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2628</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to deny the deduction for executive compensation unless the employer maintains profit-sharing distributions for employees.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF5EA6D46FD694085A21756B672B5BD96" style="OLC"><section id="HE665440AC64E42C08B44873B316D9021" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Employee Profit-Sharing Encouragement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H393D34BFC1994ABD9D4EE339CDA2BD33" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Denial of deduction for executive compensation unless employer maintains profit-sharing distributions</header><subsection id="H1DC73A97C4794609AC90C5D599B1A4A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/162">Section 162</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by redesignating subsection (s) as subsection (t) and by inserting after subsection (r) the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDDA5766E63246CBB0EF3E0FE637F616" style="OLC"><subsection id="H51D7DAB8C8174068B65DF2629C68B444"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Executive compensation paid by employers who do not maintain profit-Sharing distributions</header><paragraph id="H5FD512E7CF7347369B90A01EA330EB47"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a specified employer, no deduction shall be allowed under this chapter for applicable employee remuneration with respect to any highly compensated individual (within the meaning of section 105(h)) for any taxable year unless qualified profit-sharing distributions are made during such taxable year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F1D6DBE90FD49B58A8AF8D76F44262D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified profit-sharing distributions</header><text>For purposes of this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="H2EB6683F67AF4186A2FC98AD0B370CF5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>qualified profit-sharing distributions</quote> means a cash distribution made pursuant to a written plan of the employer under which—</text><clause id="H4FF8F629FCAF4612A5846B0B431FAA62"><enum>(i)</enum><text>employees (including part-time employees) who have been employed for at least 1 year as of the date of the distribution have a right to such distribution, and</text></clause><clause id="HCFA07DC9B41442C8BDA81B60C0494550"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount of such distributions are defined under such plan on the basis of a measure of the receipts, profit, revenues, or earnings of such employer.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC40D84C899994EAB8F5734AA3209CB14"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum distribution requirements</header><text>Such term shall not include any distributions made pursuant to such plan during the taxable year if the aggregate distributions made pursuant to such plan during such taxable year are less than 5 percent of the employer’s net income for the taxable year as determined pursuant to the employer’s books and records prepared in accordance with the employer’s accounting procedures.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB47C7B80601C48998AA55E6DC64DEA25"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Nondiscrimination</header><text>Such term shall not include any distributions made pursuant to such plan during the taxable year unless such plan satisfies requirements similar to the requirements of section 401(k)(3)(A)(ii) applied by treating the distributions made pursuant to the plan as though such distributions were contributions paid over to the trust referred to in such section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H527A704231824F789E2A630770D958B2"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Exception if distributions would jeopardize the business</header><text>An employer shall not fail to be treated as making qualified profit-sharing distributions during the taxable year to the extent that such employer establishes to the satisfaction of the Secretary by clear and convincing evidence that making such distributions would jeopardize the ability of the employer to continue as a going concern.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5328A2BB37EA443CB79F443B050921DC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Specified employer</header><text>For purposes of this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="H0E2498BB846149E59AFDB08B28F5C80B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>specified employer</quote> means, with respect to any taxable year, any employer which meets the gross receipts test of section 448(c) (determined without regard to paragraph (4) thereof) for such taxable year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1D55614BEA6481F825D92CE99EE08AB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Application of gross receipts test to individuals, etc</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subparagraph (A), in the case of any employer which is not a corporation or a partnership, the gross receipts test referred to in such subparagraph shall be applied in the same manner as if each trade or business of such employer were a corporation or partnership.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59058D606E8D4FEEAB57F9DF2B6FA42F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applicable employee remuneration</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <quote>applicable employee remuneration</quote> has the meaning given such term by subsection (m)(4), determined without regard to subparagraph (B) thereof.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H93CD2DDB178F4AF1993441A803284FE7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Controlled groups</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, all persons treated as a single employer under subsection (b), (c), (m), or (o) of section 414 shall be treated as one employer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DB6463B3BFF421796CFD38FDC05D1F6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rules similar to the rules of subparagraphs (D) and (E) of subsection (m)(4) shall apply for purposes of this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD079734CA6064E468E2A40FCB31FF5E0"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Authority to address abuse</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall have the authority to address any abuses by employers under this subsection, including, but not limited to, a reduction in employee compensation or benefits in conjunction with the payment of qualified profit-sharing distributions.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H06ABAABFA54245C4835E7F9AEF685032"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

