<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEF158CBBF116474486799CC79DCEE937" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 514 IH: National Development Strategy and Coordination Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 514</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230125">January 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish a National Development Strategy, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H754AC012E8064AD683BE3F2108E958CB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD8B4377EE02C4E4E9FA074C205316BF3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Development Strategy and Coordination Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H988E5EAE03BF43418A393777E11F5FA6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB1505A628EEF419681A70C5CDC29F4F7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committee</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committee</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HAAAC092DDDB74A2084BC9451327FF94B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Finance, the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8AA778C3035A41EE96AE198D3E6C2C19"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Energy and Commerce, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4C0EB07A8FC14B318C3313CA7303CF0E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Country of concern</header><text>The term <term>country of concern</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7DAC668FC0E24101BEAC2EF0C7577758"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the People’s Republic of China and any other foreign government or foreign non-government person determined to be a foreign adversary under section 7.4 of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFFD45A8F9F324CA2921434FC991FF929"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any country determined by the Secretary of Commerce, in consultation with the United States Trade Representative, the Secretary of Defense, and the Director of National Intelligence, to have inadequate safeguards in place to protect United States funds (or intellectual property developed using such funds) from theft or transfer to a foreign government or foreign non-government person described in subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF4FE6DDBC46843D897F4B9082996E613"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Entity of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>entity of concern</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HDC7B2C78E1BC462CAE0D2765D1DA9469"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an entity headquartered in a country of concern;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H778C7BF8EE3242C5AE454D1102614960"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity that is more than 25-percent owned by individuals or entities in countries of concern;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2AF49BE5C8F3490D9EE5365E375F9BCD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an entity on the list of specially designated nationals and blocked persons maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury (commonly referred to as the <quote>SDN list</quote>);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3381C554AFE04868A2F7CD3E895B42C3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an entity on the Non-SDN Chinese Military-Industrial Complex Companies List—</text> <clause id="H8191FB18E8854375BD5683A26BA7DB54"><enum>(i)</enum><text>established pursuant to Executive Order 13959 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to addressing the threat from securities investments that finance Communist Chinese military companies), as amended before, on, or after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF30478AA4A6A4E3FBD133020EC7FBE3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3658F2DA7566464F97DC88CAF415F5EF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a Chinese military company on the list required by section 1260H of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/113">10 U.S.C. 113</external-xref> note);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCE79D0F0B7F74DAE933A751A5A570673"><enum>(F)</enum><text>an entity on the Entity List maintained by the Bureau of Industry and Security of the Department of Commerce and set forth in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H651D10FE23BF44A1A89650F7A86B772A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>an entity that produces equipment or services on the list of communications equipment and services that pose an unacceptable risk to the national security of the United States or the security and safety of United States persons maintained by the Federal Communications Commission under section 2 of the Secure and Trusted Communications Networks Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1601">47 U.S.C. 1601</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H19A70CB78CE540D59943E75B124B8499" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(H)</enum><text>any entity that is majority owned or controlled by, or under common ownership or control with, an entity described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (G). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="H0A61AC825C5748EEAD4BC9F0BC3EAE8C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of the Interagency Committee for the coordination of National Development Financing Programs</header> <subsection id="HF6D7097E6BE144E39AEA25F40259B88C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established in the Executive Office of the President a Committee to be known as the Interagency Committee for the Coordination of National Development Financing Programs (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Committee</quote>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H88A0B2DE9F3D4ABEA6371E04581B0B8B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<paragraph id="H3A584CEE9D474E0A89F3A42EC74FD37D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The Committee shall consist of the following members:</text> <subparagraph id="H2FFBEBAFF1E14A6189E1F774A2E27FA1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary of Transportation or a designee of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC33CD3744E594E73A74135DCE72D688D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Secretary of Energy or a designee of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD3DB0846645F4942974A5774C7160098"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Secretary of Commerce or a designee of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCB138EC3E645450F8370B04353B970A3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Secretary of Labor or a designee of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF1102386F4284BA3ACED8A5DFC30B32A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Secretary of the Treasury or a designee of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2EAE85828CE94216B4F6D3AA978C49A0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Small Business Administration or a designee of the Administrator.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H59D1B037048D439BA1F899EA187D06AF"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense or a designee of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4CA6D9E776834B2DA3390BAC74CF2CF5"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The Director of National Intelligence or a designee of the Director.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H83E3FF3B39FF4BA8AC0AB44F5E2E4C5F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Secretary of Agriculture or a designee of the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H66555114E0A142B7A6975202F4C24337"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The United States Trade Representative or their designee.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC2302E31E414CA08593780661D1ED22"><enum>(K)</enum><text>The Chair of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve or a designee of the Chair, who shall serve as a nonvoting member.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H193B504EB05347CB9FFC3847B69AEE68"><enum>(L)</enum><text>The Secretary of the Treasury or a designee of the Secretary, who shall serve as the chair of the Committee.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H6C9ADCB2F1A1405EA5AA4271D9F0BD41"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Tie vote</header><text>In the event of a tie vote, the vote of the chair of the Committee shall serve as the tie-breaker.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2C39B52429F24DCA939E4B37E96D54F7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Committee—</text> <paragraph id="H14195E41955643E4828BC23163AD8CBF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall submit to Congress the National Development Strategy described in subsection (d);</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCE3CBC8241714A7F94984E9112D113D9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H15AE99891ACB4940872FC6C7663ECF1A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 1 year after January 20, 2024, and every 4 years thereafter, and in each such year not earlier than the latest date on which the budget of the President may be submitted to Congress under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code, submit to Congress the National Development Strategy described in subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0AEDB66EBE59444CA71434F3BD87EF7F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall identify economic sectors of the United States, regions of the United States, and, as necessary and supported by substantial evidence, projects or partnerships that advance the goals of the National Development Strategy described in subsection (d), to which financing assistance should be prioritized by member agencies of the Committee and should be provided or supported by the Federal Financing Bank.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD4EE7AB685BD4DB8A8A79D7E9F5C477D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>National Development Strategy</header><text>The Committee shall develop a publicly available (except for an allowable classified annex) National Development Strategy, which shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1875DEE939BD4AC6B31D98DBF919F491"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify and address vulnerabilities in United States supply chains in industries critical to national security;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCCADAAC91D16422790806F04667EEF85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify and address vulnerabilities and shortfalls in domestic manufacturing capabilities that threaten the ability of the United States to maintain a global advantage in innovation and manufacturing;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H83AE8CF662324280AD264BB278CB9100"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify weaknesses and discuss opportunities to strengthen the broad industrial base of the United States, which may include—</text> <subparagraph id="HBA96F23685EE454EAF8FB870C67F1D44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>strengthening supply chain resiliency;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD2E513C686B945ACAE07C93161D35381"><enum>(B)</enum><text>supporting industries critical for the national security;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE23353EDE0044BEDA880D8D0F8D1213B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>developing technologies that provide scientific or commercial value to the United States;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H209469CB8E34487386BE9B6A6F84DEAF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>supporting job growth and development of critical manufacturing capabilities within the United States workforce;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC24606BC387F4517AE8B9407D5FF53B8"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting the development and adoption of innovative resource extraction technologies, including technologies for renewable energy; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD818112A9E1C4BC18E738BEA5358BF82"><enum>(F)</enum><text>supporting job growth and economic development in critical industries in qualified opportunity zones (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1400Z">section 1400Z–1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA7A27A7D6054CFC8D38E2B4AE77491A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify industries and regions in the United States that require assistance in order to address vulnerabilities and advance the goals described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC577EDFD459E481F86C09188018E34A2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>outline a strategic plan to promote investment in the industries described in paragraph (4), which shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="HEC9FF09D2E6941F19CCCA3C699F560D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an estimate of the amount and nature of public financing needed to achieve the goals and address vulnerabilities described in paragraphs (1), (2), and (3);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H912AC956121041778E2DF6E394545C11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an inventory of all Federal programs in existence as of the date of the National Development Strategy that are capable of providing the financing described in subparagraph (A), the level of investment from each such Federal program in the preceding 5-year period, and a detailed description of how each such program is advancing development goals in the United States;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H238E3F62F6704255B4D5DF59F91168FE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recommendations as to how Federal agencies may, under existing Federal authorities, leverage and attract private investment to accomplish the goals described in this subsection;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4984739656B44C0399E2715ACEB5A798"><enum>(D)</enum><text>recommendations, if applicable, on any changes to Federal financing programs, including changes to how financing decisions are prioritized or creation of new financing programs, that may be needed to advance the goals of the National Development Strategy;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0EADC7587F20411AB969C7FC7466EDC9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>directives to the Federal Financing Bank to accomplish the goals of the National Development Strategy; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H32E40CD327A945EC82711BE9F39F2119"><enum>(F)</enum><text>performance metrics to evaluate and monitor projects supported by the Federal Financing Bank in alignment with the National Development Strategy. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB798ED55A69545D4947FF5284C2990F9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Advice and input</header><text>The Committee shall seek the advice and input of industry partners, manufacturing policy experts, State and local development officials, and manufacturing worker interests when preparing the National Development Strategy described in subsection (d), including by—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0CD44D20BDBC4A27A8A351057A38514F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>holding not less than 4 public hearings per year, either virtually or in person, during which industry representatives, worker groups, and regional representatives can provide insight into strategic development prioritization; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H33D290545C7D41A6B503E6EE62941947"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establishing an Industry Advisory Board of not more than 10 members appointed by the President, which shall include—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDC100C17A2BE403895EBB3E2864CB176"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an expert in industry competitiveness and national security;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H756CFE77391B4F109510FB1794CB88D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a manufacturing trade association representative;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H52F423E3661F4B399755F3F456A001F4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a representative of small business government contractors;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5570C725CA8D4A389BC7B386BA74A7FE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a manufacturing worker representative;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7004D09AEB4D49938FB34AF737B8F35A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a representative from a private investment firm investing in critical industries and frontier technology; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC8C0568B90064FDD8B60B6E5FB53AF1A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>such other representatives as the President may appoint.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB0FC1CEA39414EFC91DA405623664895"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Assessment of National Development Strategy</header><text>In January of each year in which the Committee does not submit a new National Development Strategy as required under subsection (d), the Committee shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees an assessment of the most recently published National Development Strategy, which shall include—</text> <paragraph id="H92B0691617C8475687D0B86B4EAA00D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an accounting of any new investments made by the Federal Financing Bank or member agencies of the Committee in the preceding year, including ZIP Code, North American Industry Classification System code, and financing stage;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H57EC15493B3C4802956BBF58616B3486"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the performance of such investments, in accordance with performance metrics established by the Committee;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA931ABC7F7DD4F9F80BC59D94A507D74"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an assessment of the implementation of the National Development Strategy, including an assessment by each agency represented on the Committee, supported by sufficient evidence, of steps taken to align such agencies’ financing, research, and development activities with the goals of the National Development Strategy; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H224724518F004F45B13F963A3F3FA8F5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a determination on whether or not an update is needed to the National Development Strategy as a result of a change in assumptions, geopolitical dynamics, or other factors.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H401CC752B01449D0B5D3B05BFD90BDCE"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Memorandum of coordination with Federal agencies engaged in investment and financing activities</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Committee shall negotiate a memorandum of understanding among the Federal agencies represented on the Committee, which shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3300E8F0A1D944569323584EAB5D4C6C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish procedures for—</text> <subparagraph id="H2751BD7C15784616AC0E41C192DD54CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>aligning their respective investment and financing authorities to ensure maximum efficiency and comply with the goals of the National Development Strategy;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1B629531A50645ABA6FF02FE871190ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>resolving conflicts in cases of overlapping jurisdiction between their respective agencies; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3AB3034CDFD749A5984D12ADD08E3607"><enum>(C)</enum><text>avoiding conflicting or duplicative operation of services; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H584E8FE1540B418BBAC8402E19F554A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be reviewed and updated annually in coordination with the submission of the assessment outlined in subsection (f).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H217B534E1C584C38AA11795C16F92E66"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee shall meet regularly and as required by the President, but not less frequently than annually.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1CDFFA4D81AD4A48A1B4E266808C28DC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Strategic alignment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each Federal agency represented on the Committee shall—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H24133736603C4285BC41927EDB58AC72"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult on a regular basis the most recently published National Development Strategy described in subsection (d); and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H4EF5B9EA9F12431C8444C880B535EC2A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent practicable, give priority consideration to projects that align with the goals of the National Development Strategy when engaged in financing, research, and development activities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H6D5015F618D54707AF1B4461D73A09FD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Requirements of the Federal Financing Bank relating to the National Development Strategy</header> <subsection id="HED39EDA7355443A980B35E439BCB994B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Financing Bank Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/2281">12 U.S.C. 2281 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBBF56DE4258D48178B34E3E44D370EFF"> 
<section id="H9E3E7244798C4E318D12631D6864FA10"><enum>21.</enum><header>Functions with respect to the Committee</header> 
<subsection id="HE94784D3EF1049199FAC6DA0CB68C814"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Bank shall carry out any directives made to the Bank by the Interagency Committee for the Coordination of National Development Financing Programs pursuant to subsections (c)(2) and (d)(5)(E) of section 3 of the <short-title>National Development Strategy and Coordination Act of 2023</short-title>. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H699F8A146A31454780AE14E065BD6BBF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>Pursuant to subsection (a), the Bank is authorized, upon direction by the Interagency Committee for the Coordination of National Development Financing Programs, to—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6A7CD7161CE94CDDB7D3941643AF05B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>issue securities that are backed by financing assistance through any member agency of the Committee;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0BEBE57B043A4EE381C2B1B46FDD019B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>purchase from the private market loans or other debt or equity instruments guaranteed in whole or in part by any member agency of the Committee; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE94853176E314AD5AEF6214ADAB5D568"><enum>(3)</enum><text>participate in agency loans or loan guarantees in an amount less than 100 percent of the principal amount of financing.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD4F86878135943FBA1830CF62DDFD461"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Purchase not for resale</header><text>As directed by the Interagency Committee for the Coordination of National Development Financing Programs in accordance with the National Development Strategy established under section 3(d) of the <short-title>National Development Strategy and Coordination Act of 2023</short-title>, the Bank may, as necessary, purchase not for resale to the private market any loans or other debt or equity instruments described in subsection (b)(2).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H1B22BBF99DE24EAA8F7CBE762C23EBD8"><enum>22.</enum><header>Secondary market operations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided in the <short-title>National Development Strategy and Coordination Act of 2023</short-title>, obligations purchased by the Bank may be resold in the secondary market in a similar manner to secondary market sales of Treasury notes. </text></section> <section id="HCE18452C8FE542FDB943E30FBF12D236"><enum>23.</enum><header>Ombudsman</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Board of Directors of the Bank shall designate an official as the Ombudsman who shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4E43BC51771446B5B911EACAC95CC20F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review investments made by the Bank on projects or partnerships identified by the Interagency Committee for the Coordination of National Development Financing Programs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA11D602E081641068333A13119E01A83"><enum>(2)</enum><text>review the risk profiles and performance of any such projects or partnerships;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H299FFD8989C54E97A657033923613251"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide oversight relating to any such projects or partnerships; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCCDC5A37FDA84E10A41EF59C073961C7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide annually to the appropriate congressional committees a report detailing investments made by the Bank in projects or partnerships identified by the Interagency Committee for the Coordination of National Development Financing Programs, the performance of such investments, and any new or existing investments that may present cause for concern regarding the potential of repayment or lack of alignment with strategic directives.</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H866B9776F4104D1DAFBD8DDA97CBB07D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal Credit Reform Act</header><text>If the Committee determines that a project or partnership receiving financial assistance through any member agency is investing in frontier technologies for which no reasonable market comparison exists, obligations purchased in connection with such project or partnership by the Federal Financing Bank under section 21 of the Federal Financing Bank Act of 1973, as added by subsection (a) of this section, shall not be subject to the Federal Credit Reform Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661">2 U.S.C. 661 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></subsection></section> <section id="H5827C054E5CC44B2A604F86ED0AADAEE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations for the Federal Financing Bank</header> <subsection id="H05A47E657EF44C70B6E7D00D71362C4C" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Federal Financing Bank, to remain available for 10 years after the date of distribution, to carry out projects and partnerships selected by the Interagency Committee for the Coordination of National Development Financing Programs established under section 3 of this Act— </text> 
<paragraph id="H2AC0860818BD4909A2211BE45B4D970D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2024, $5,000,000,000;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2172321583F94A78BD3B8F31E41B7004" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2025, $5,000,000,000;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D4B9A2579BB4016979C0DCC6ADC1008" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2026, $5,000,000,000; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99A8D05317F242E4AB9032E32F1ADD25" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2027, $5,000,000,000;</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H926C4FFAE7BD46FDB0A322EF23E990BF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Set aside</header><text>Not more than 2 percent of funds appropriated under this section shall be utilized for administrative costs, including the hiring of new staff to oversee and accomplish the functions of the Federal Financing Bank.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE3E2B4E87AA94D8BAF89E727DE9A2071"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that the Federal Financing Bank should use amounts appropriated under this section as soon as possible. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H338F7D6B99F041259A2D174B6B5C6290"><enum>6.</enum><header>Prohibitions and policy</header> 
<subsection id="HE5C1D62DAAF244D595BD220C3CF79630"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>No funding or authorities provided under this Act may be used to support projects or partnerships with any entity of concern.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE187A4210DF241F8916478F6C1633604"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Policies</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Committee shall establish policies to ensure that any support to projects or partnerships provided by the Federal Financing Bank in accordance with this Act—</text> 
<paragraph id="H558FAF360E4443F0987D5F26C045491D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>includes assurances that no support provided in such project or partnership shall be used to expand operations in a country of concern;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8974AC2FFB02453B87E516D9FC7C5636"><enum>(2)</enum><text>includes protections to ensure against transfer of intellectual property to countries of concern; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC252DD7F626941F0973B7755958DF345"><enum>(3)</enum><text>includes requirements that any firm participating in a project or partnership funded by this Act disclose any affiliate, parent company, or subsidiary located in a country of concern.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

