<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1471BFEAD48D47618452C66B06182E4C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 261 IH: Article I Regulatory Budget Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 261</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230110">January 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">Committee on the Budget</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Small Business</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Congressional Budget Act of 1974 to establish a Federal regulatory budget and to impose cost controls on that budget, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H844E63CEA20C4F3BBADDE967D3235A5E" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6F36FCBDA02F42B8B52BBB5D31E0B542" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Article I Regulatory Budget Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HBE8C1025AEC143DAB073A14763570F5A"><enum>2.</enum><header>President’s annual budget submissions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H395141CDD5EC4CE7A84C4B21E9908394" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="H49847A92D4C849DDA459B842C76A1077"><enum>(40)</enum>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H0D86B20AF8ED4BAC8023D56C9DC6FD87"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for the first fiscal year that begins at least 120 days after the date of enactment of this paragraph, and every fiscal year thereafter until the fifth fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this paragraph, a projection of the Federal regulatory cost of any proposed Federal regulation, rule, or statement (as such terms are defined in section 321 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974) for the fiscal year and at least each of the 4 ensuing fiscal years, which shall include—</text> <clause id="HF7A42CBF79D0493AB6D73EE818415E92" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the projection of the Federal regulatory cost by agency and program; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H56A5546FBF1345AAB9A3EF3920E45FFA" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any changes in a Federal regulation, rule, or statement in the Unified Agenda of Federal Regulatory and Deregulatory Actions, compiled by the Regulatory Information Service Center of the General Services Administration; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA9CDF9D8001423CAF9A25F4B2BFE070" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for the fifth fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this paragraph, and every fiscal year thereafter, a regulatory authority budget analysis of the Federal regulatory cost of complying with all current and proposed Federal regulations, rules, and statements and proposals (as such terms are defined in section 321 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974) for complying with section 322 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974 for the fiscal year for which the budget is submitted and the 4 fiscal years after that year, which shall include a regulatory authority budget analysis of the Federal regulatory cost by agency and program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section id="H27F4C8DFE8DB42E893845D4F778B6021"><enum>3.</enum><header>Estimation and disclosure of costs of Federal regulation</header>
<subsection id="H82E2CC6C08EE403CA0F93B303F2DB2AE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Costs to private sector of new federal regulations</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/6">Chapter 6</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, popularly known as the <quote>Regulatory Flexibility Act</quote>, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HCA29741A68BF42FDB0D3AC0C7720485E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 603—</text>
<subparagraph id="H80F392614109408886768F004262FFEC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), in the second sentence, by inserting before the period the following: <quote>and shall discuss in detail whether the cost to businesses of complying with the proposed rule will vary depending on the size of the business and, if so, to what extent the cost will vary and what factors contribute to the variation</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9E7082AE5AD74CDD8DB05EE94826AFB2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text>
<clause id="HCA55202666B64D789B45B93C32C28B53"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (1), (2), (3), and (4) as subparagraphs (A), (B), (C), and (D), respectively, and adjusting the margin accordingly;</text></clause> <clause id="HCA1F289628574D608D5738B772191ED5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> after <quote>(c)</quote>; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HEA0CC651534F4962AB7416C9A75B20B4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Consistent with the</quote> and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2D89309408E14D36B993AA170236673E" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="HF77741EE476D4F0DA5AD5F6CBDFD48FA" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The analysis of significant alternatives to the proposed rule shall include a detailed analysis of the costs and benefits of the proposed rule and each alternative, which shall separately address the costs and benefits for each industry.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB1285ACF55F6482BB27D07A465B81B4E" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Consistent with the</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H11F326B7D83D415C8C9A1D4BD32592BA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H566C7F0D40DC46FDB1B85D1E5639725E" style="OLC">
<subsection id="HBE9CC35F2F9B4B56B8CB5BCE61F4C6FC"><enum>(e)</enum><text>Each initial regulatory flexibility analysis shall also contain a description of the nature and amount of monetary costs that will be incurred by small entities, other businesses, and individuals in complying with the proposed rule.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF1DF1EB77BB547258F9F20952DE28FF6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 604(a)—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1299C3933C7B4972849BDD08B4A52E4A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the first paragraph designated as paragraph (6) (relating to minimization of significant economic impacts), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7FA578A1B84E4C7D87B4AE1A5E08149A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating the second paragraph (6) (relating to covered agencies), as paragraph (8); and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H820B98F2CD4446989419F8ADE9FB4AF6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (6) the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H48844AC2EA7F46D1B131907B1A923934" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H9D3B04A7C1B742FC84210C9923708AF4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>a statement of the nature and amount of monetary costs that will be incurred by small entities, other businesses, and individuals in complying with the rule; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4012EE74300C4CFAA0BECB316D679CB5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 607, by inserting before the period the following: <quote>, except that estimates of monetary costs under sections 603(d) and 604(a)(7) shall only be in the form of a numerical description</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H113FBB30A796469CB1B37C3775CC32B8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Agency reports</header><text>Each agency that prepares an initial regulatory flexibility analysis under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/6">chapter 6</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall, at the same time submit to each House of Congress, the Congressional Budget Office, and the Office of Management and Budget a cost estimate and cost benefit analysis of any new proposed regulations, rules, or statements that would have a Federal regulatory cost (as defined in section 321 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974, as added by this Act) of at least $100,000,000 for any fiscal year.</text></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H30332549C18946979B01F496D1738F3E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Guidance documents</header>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3741565147D84826AC7CF798BBBD2A85"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05D605B993714A79834F4F3390556BC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the terms <term>agency</term> and <term>rule</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 551 of title 5, United States Code;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE24320A0CD9041898728DB838499E6D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>guidance document</term> means an agency statement of general applicability and future effect, other than a rule, that sets forth a policy on a statutory, regulatory, or technical issue or an interpretation of a statutory or regulatory issue; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8496D2B3D4E4766801E449DF623FF9D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>significant guidance document</term>—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB132089E232F4ED2B0C5DEC59E68F123"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a guidance document that the Office of Management and Budget determines will be disseminated to regulated entities or the general public and may reasonably be anticipated to—</text> <clause id="H9A9B951161BF4BFD870A226C954BA044"><enum>(i)</enum><text>lead to an annual effect of not less than $100,000,000 on, or adversely affect in a material way, the economy, a sector of the economy, productivity, competition, jobs, the environment, public health or safety, or State, local, or tribal governments or communities;</text></clause>
<clause id="H0A9FAA3BCA3F4B83BBF887C77C26D108"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>create a serious inconsistency or otherwise interfere with an action taken or planned by an agency other than the agency issuing the guidance document;</text></clause> <clause id="HFB42A26754604DAD8B2840625D9A210C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>materially alter the budgetary impact of entitlements, grants, user fees, or loan programs or the rights or obligations of recipients thereof; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HF360FDFB09434D41911E1100D3FD648C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>raise novel legal or policy issues arising out of legal mandates, the priorities of the President, or the principles set forth in Executive Order 12866 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/601">5 U.S.C. 601</external-xref> note; relating to regulatory planning and review); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H74314C2F540D47C5B9072EC89BD81B4F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include a guidance document that the Office of Management and Budget determines—</text>
<clause id="H46A647D74DE6449291B676CCB59341C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>relates to regulations issued in accordance with the formal rulemaking provisions of sections 556 and 557 of title 5, United States Code;</text></clause> <clause id="H56DFE107AE724C7BBF71AFB9FC9009E7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>pertains to a military or foreign affairs function of the United States, other than procurement regulations and regulations involving the import or export of nondefense articles and services;</text></clause>
<clause id="H4133486E604B4EB9850B4B41B3284018"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>relates to regulations that are limited to agency organization, management, or personnel matters; or</text></clause> <clause id="HD87B6F43E56C4CEEA2A7412487A91E7B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>is within a category of guidance documents exempted by the Administrator of the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H09B53FA0F2B54CB197FB8978A3C24E2A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation on guidance documents</header><text>An agency may not issue a significant guidance document unless the agency issues the significant guidance document after notice and an opportunity for comment in accordance with the requirements for the promulgation of a rule under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCA4AA0CF95CE46EA89468ACDFBFAD375"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Private right of action</header><text>Any person aggrieved of an action taken or failed to be taken under a guidance document that was not issued in accordance with subsection (b) may bring a civil action in an appropriate district court of the United States alleging that the guidance document should have been treated as a significant guidance document.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H2AF7918DC4E142389AA56435373DC37A"><enum>5.</enum><header>Amendments to the Congressional Budget Act of 1974</header>
<subsection id="HEBC20581E49B48548DC93CBC20D9D4E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Federal regulatory budget cost control system</header><text>Title III of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974 is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HC99FBE7966764AAC93934CEA499F327E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting before section 300 the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8970E121EC6469F9C84B62DAD332D2D" style="traditional">
<part id="H6463204C4E9145748B8B6DC073E4C94C" style="OLC"><enum>A</enum><header>General provisions</header></part><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">and </continuation-text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H424877BF51AC44499EAB340648BCDEC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2414735FE7C14D999391E3F992DF49D8" style="OLC"> <part id="H21F7FC11B78243A58929071B74DB477D"><enum>B</enum><header>Federal regulatory budget cost control</header> <section id="HCB476E9262D346F0B2C68E9BD726BBA2"><enum>321.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part—</text>
<paragraph id="H336032C0FF6A47C39660D4D8A4ED2853"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>CBO</term> means the Congressional Budget Office;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3B07212080E54037B9459DA73A2B3353"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>direct cost of Federal regulation</term> means all costs incurred by, and expenditures required of, the Federal Government in issuing and enforcing Federal regulations, rules, and statements and Federal statutes;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE3A2DC85D7814AB980342F9E64761A05"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>Federal regulation, rule, or statement</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H7267153E44524ADBB84D5AD85207AA28"><enum>(A)</enum><text>includes any guidance document issued after notice and an opportunity for comment in accordance with the requirements for the promulgation of a rule under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H684358126F1544F48B569196E1C9BED7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include—</text> <clause id="HF43885BAF2A746168577B15517F3458C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a Federal regulation, rule, or statement applying to—</text>
<subclause id="HF1F6204A8926428CAEF79AFB0C02E001"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the military; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H37BAF23A1F5B4493B38E477255345BB0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>agency organization, management, or personnel; or</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HB56368AD1FF94F1FADCDDE7B11B0628D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a Federal regulation, rule, or statement designated by the President as being—</text> <subclause id="H1BAF70F29B7E43078384BC092664B9D1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>necessary because of an imminent threat to health or safety or other emergency;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HE18F3EBAFC454F508B08B1DCDD6CC96D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>necessary for the enforcement of criminal laws; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H23E84DF680F844008A3DFE34DD338ED7"><enum>(III)</enum><text>necessary for national security;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9C4391AB93FB4B109EA84FB179323A19"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>Federal regulatory cost</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H281BFCE7C76B4EA8BFFCF0B53D1CA7DF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means all costs incurred by, and expenditures required of, the private sector, States, or local governments in complying with any Federal regulation, rule, or statement or any Federal statute; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFF07979F931A437E8BCF14A6B9C992A6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include the value of any benefit under the Federal regulation, rule, or statement or the Federal statute;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H515D1B112980481D82229DCEBB074D19"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>gross domestic product</term> means the gross domestic product of the United States during a fiscal year, consistent with Department of Commerce definitions;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H314564F018F544DA832F780F5E37B91C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <term>OMB</term> means the Office of Management and Budget; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2187F51B68924BE5B8696A07BC10E693"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the term <term>regulatory baseline</term> means the projection described in section 326(a) of the Federal regulatory cost for the fiscal year after the date of the projection and the outyears.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HB0A0AE4DF9FD417BA34244EA51A5BF04"><enum>322.</enum><header>Establishment of level and allocations</header>
<subsection id="H1ADC617766DF4D2E867A87ED6E063F2A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of level</header>
<paragraph id="H4FED0AA7F8384C5BA2E1CFA58AC0D7C9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to the requirements under section 301, a concurrent resolution on the budget for a fiscal year shall set forth the appropriate level for the Federal regulatory cost for the fiscal year and for at least each of the 4 ensuing fiscal years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF238169BF0554D95A0649E9E7FF01AEF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transition period</header> <subparagraph id="H650E684F526F4B4487D8B86BE7368DC9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the first fiscal year that begins at least 120 days after the date of enactment of this section, and each fiscal year thereafter until the fiscal year described in section 326(a), the Committee on the Budget of the Senate and the Committee on the Budget of the House of Representatives shall include in the concurrent resolution on the budget for the fiscal year as the appropriate level for the Federal regulatory cost for the fiscal year and any other fiscal year covered by the resolution the proposed levels submitted by the President under section 1105(a)(40) of title 31, United States Code.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H06A83B9071C44DA3B5B49B4391B5A5E3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amendments</header>
<clause id="H1E07944A5887463CA98FC99F102245B1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the Senate and the House of Representatives, it shall not be in order to consider an amendment to a concurrent resolution on the budget that, if agreed to, would result in a net increase in a level included pursuant to subparagraph (A).</text></clause> <clause id="H563D0DBA04DD4F95A0204AF3AED10454"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Waiver and appeal</header><text>A point of order under clause (i) may only be waived by the affirmative vote of three-fifths of the Members, duly chosen and sworn. An affirmative vote of three-fifths of Members, duly chosen and sworn, shall be required to sustain an appeal of the ruling of the Chair on a point of order raised under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEF6A999A44C24D4DA37700351A6F8520"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Default total</header><text>If there is not a level for the Federal regulatory cost that is in effect for a fiscal year under a concurrent resolution on the budget—</text> <subparagraph id="HD5441004853E4A3C9820E7B7E77856CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for the first fiscal year that begins at least 120 days after the date of enactment of this section, and every fiscal year thereafter until the fiscal year described in subparagraph (B), the appropriate level for the Federal regulatory cost for the fiscal year shall be the proposed level submitted by the President under section 1105(a)(40) of title 31, United States Code;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H658AAA1EBA484D78AE7D3742CECA4EC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for the fifth fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this section, the appropriate level for the Federal regulatory cost for the fiscal year shall be the amount of the first regulatory baseline submitted under section 326; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC34712B28E7F4F0292099529387543AF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for each fiscal year after the fiscal year described in subparagraph (B), the appropriate level for the Federal regulatory cost for the fiscal year shall be the level for the most recent fiscal year for which such a level was in effect (under subparagraph (B), this subparagraph, or a concurrent resolution on the budget).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HB8DB64F5F81246B18BAFC98D5915538A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Allocation of totals</header>
<paragraph id="HC1E86BB0ECF8436A8AA0B1E1E66BF474"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the first fiscal year that begins at least 120 days after the date of enactment of this section, and each fiscal year thereafter, the joint explanatory statement accompanying the conference report on a concurrent resolution on the budget for such fiscal year shall include allocations of the Federal regulatory cost in effect under subsection (a) for such fiscal year and at least each of the 4 ensuing fiscal years—</text> <subparagraph id="H021B1C7AA1B642B88B19B1C7BC751602"><enum>(A)</enum><text>among each committee of the Senate and each committee of the House of Representatives;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB5B193719C1D4EB1838C64FE170ABF78"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by major functional category; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC014B53E28464BA1ACC91435111B4135"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H17A07D6436BC4A56BA08AC21FBB73788"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Suballocations</header><text>As soon as practicable after receiving an allocation under paragraph (1), each committee shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HA6138361E8254490862AAEF636D771E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>suballocate its allocation—</text>
<clause id="HB686C03CE9DE4E4187A8683EB68AD3CF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>among its subcommittees;</text></clause> <clause id="HA7ECAEDF5CEB43A089A6634E3C9C5EC3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>among programs over which the committee has jurisdiction; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H8AC83DC7E81D429FB946A1416FB4BF00"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by agency; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H217B071D0D184143980F94F23F761D7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit for printing in the Congressional Record a statement detailing each suballocation made by the committee under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HCBCD74E2250344ED8E4EB9FE32E27506"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Point of order</header>
<paragraph id="H57D3FAE449F649A68907A2DFB7C01794"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a concurrent resolution on the budget setting forth the appropriate level for the Federal regulatory cost for a fiscal year has been agreed to, it shall not be in order in the Senate or the House of Representatives to consider any bill or resolution, or amendment thereto, which would cause an allocation or suballocation of the Federal regulatory cost made under subsection (b) for that fiscal year to be exceeded.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBD67A2FFF46846D1B3BD561035069DDB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver and appeal</header><text>A point of order under paragraph (1) may only be waived by the affirmative vote of three-fifths of the Members, duly chosen and sworn. An affirmative vote of three-fifths of Members, duly chosen and sworn, shall be required to sustain an appeal of the ruling of the Chair on a point of order raised under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H6E3A94F7EF4E437C966E104BA89657CB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Determinations by budget committees</header><text>For purposes of this section, the amount of the Federal regulatory cost for a fiscal year and the amount of the Federal regulatory cost of a bill or resolution, or amendment thereto, shall be determined by the Committee on the Budget of the Senate or the Committee on the Budget of the House of Representatives, as the case may be.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HE5AD8AD676E0459CB9E30701FD40F9C9"><enum>323.</enum><header>Analysis of Federal regulatory cost by Congressional Budget Office</header> <subsection id="HFECC84B4B0734AD1991D42AE6C108BE1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">CBO shall prepare for each bill or resolution of a public character reported by any committee of the Senate or the House of Representatives (except the Committee on Appropriations of each House), and submit to such committee—</text>
<paragraph id="H3FE3D0C58E624CBB8317E967B6DC4746"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an estimate of the costs which would be incurred by the private sector in carrying out or complying with such bill or resolution in the fiscal year in which it is to become effective and in each of the 4 fiscal years following such fiscal year, which shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H420F57E850D24045AFCF48DC1353525B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a net present value estimate of the cost of compliance by the private sector with such bill or resolution; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H71C93EBE900F449F8E3D2B7DCCD9B9DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a discussion of the methodology used to prepare, and the basis for, each such estimate; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB9DF7E72EB3430DAA4226DA05BB7E91"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a comparison of the estimate of costs described in paragraph (1) with any available estimates of costs made by such committee or by any agency.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H23CE9D3201A94165B265CCD7942A4E42"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Look-Back reviews</header><text>CBO shall periodically submit to Congress a report, prepared in consultation with the Chairman of the Administrative Conference of the United States, that—</text> <paragraph id="H0DDBBAB0AD2A42AD81A823E58F0F1D11"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reviews a sample of laws of a public character for which an estimate was prepared under subsection (a)(1); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBA86D6EC80B34DA1912AB12E07FD1F00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>compares the estimates of the costs described in paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (a) and the actual costs incurred by the private sector in carrying out or complying with the law in the fiscal year in which it took effect and in each of the 4 fiscal years following such fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H16E2429B233E49649B8E049F6417F80F"><enum>324.</enum><header>Enforcement</header> <subsection id="H9205CE336BA34EA6AF3F4BB6EED61177"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Enforcement language required in appropriation acts</header><text>If a concurrent resolution on the budget that includes levels and allocations of the Federal regulatory cost for a fiscal year has been agreed to, it shall not be in order in the Senate or the House of Representatives to consider a bill, joint resolution, amendment between the Houses, or conference report making appropriations for the fiscal year that does not include a provision prohibiting amounts made available under the measure from being obligated or expended to enforce a Federal regulation, rule, or statement that would cause a breach of any level or allocation of the Federal regulatory cost in effect for a fiscal year.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H4736112E3D8640ADA6AED885CCFF7200"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver and appeal</header><text>Subsection (a) may be waived or suspended in the Senate only by an affirmative vote of two-thirds of the Members, duly chosen and sworn. An affirmative vote of two-thirds of the Members of the Senate, duly chosen and sworn, shall be required to sustain an appeal of the ruling of the Chair on a point of order raised under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDBBFF9B9E2C3405DAC5FE57F9DCE3F52"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Review of cost</header> <paragraph id="HD252B11DB7F74511938AFDC738704EDE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determinations of cost</header> <subparagraph id="HE88486AA668E44E9A0F0F05F5F8E86AD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>BEA determination</header><text>The Bureau of Economic Analysis of the Department of Commerce shall determine the change in the Federal regulatory cost attributable to each newly promulgated, or amendment to a, Federal regulation, rule, or statement.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBBAF7806778042479B1474FC8694859C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Guidance for agencies</header><text>The Bureau of Economic Analysis of the Department of Commerce shall issue guidance to agencies regarding the methodology to be used to determine the amount of, and any change in, the Federal regulatory cost attributable to each newly promulgated, or amendment to a, Federal regulation, rule, or statement.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H71307B7BE40841DFB117A62FBA8068DE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Mandatory use by agencies</header><text>For purposes of any analysis conducted by an agency (without regard to whether the analysis is conducted for purposes of this Act), each agency shall determine the amount of, and any change in, the Federal regulatory cost attributable to each newly promulgated, or amendment to a, Federal regulation, rule, or statement in accordance with the guidance issued under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF082B1C897C41DCBD34F1AF07E31014"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">OMB determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The OMB shall determine whether the change in the Federal regulatory cost determined under paragraph (1) would cause a breach of any level or allocation of the Federal regulatory cost in effect for a fiscal year, which shall incorporate any reduction to the level or allocation of the Federal regulatory cost attributable to a revision of a Federal regulation, rule, or statement during the fiscal year.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFF7A950A69CB48EEB91EA58634213FB1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>CBO review</header><text>The CBO shall—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA9A2C0C1FB5F41628F76E7B24941996E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>review the methodology used by the Bureau of Economic Analysis and the OMB for each determination under paragraphs (1) and (2); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2A26A821E5FA4EECB3117951564ADE1E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>issue an opinion on whether the change in the Federal regulatory cost attributable to the applicable newly promulgated, or amendment to a, Federal regulation, rule, or statement would cause a breach of any level or allocation of the Federal regulatory cost in effect for a fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7E8DFC545B70431896E3DE56E629B3F7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The OMB shall issue a directive prohibiting funds from being obligated or expended to enforce a newly promulgated, or amendment to a, Federal regulation, rule, or statement during a fiscal year if—</text> <paragraph id="H31F51D190E98408B937AC7D507CAA51E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the OMB determines that change in the Federal regulatory cost attributable to the newly promulgated, or amendment to a, Federal regulation, rule, or statement, as determined by the Bureau of Economic Analysis under subsection (c)(1), would cause a breach of any level or allocation of the Federal regulatory cost in effect for the fiscal year; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBCE042205E984B95BEDA6B6C774AB6C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the appropriation Act making the applicable appropriations for the fiscal year contains a provision described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H943C3CCE67EF42F190756F3DE4230A0C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Offsetting savings</header><text>In making determinations under this section with respect to a newly promulgated, or amendment to a, Federal regulation, rule, or statement, the Bureau of Economic Analysis, the CBO, and the OMB shall subtract from the amount of the Federal regulatory cost, and any applicable allocation thereof, any reduction to the Federal regulatory cost that is attributable to a revision of another Federal regulation, rule, or statement made as part of the same rulemaking.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H16C2B568495540019B16B00DA27C865F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Private right of action</header><text>Any person aggrieved of an action taken or failed to be taken under a Federal regulation, rule, or statement for which the OMB has issued a directive prohibiting enforcement under subsection (d) may bring a civil action in an appropriate district court of the United States alleging that the Federal regulation, rule, or statement should not have been enforced.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HD654351A72CA4AC4AADC5CA95CCD748A"><enum>325.</enum><header>OMB–CBO reports</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this section, and not later than September 15th of each odd-numbered year thereafter, OMB and CBO shall jointly submit to the President, the Senate, and the House of Representatives a report that includes—</text>
<paragraph id="HA8344CDA71624072960D8D8A91A1F656"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a projection of the direct cost of Federal regulation and the Federal regulatory cost for the first fiscal year beginning after the date of the report and at least each of the 4 ensuing fiscal years;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF056E97DDBE341378FCA8B16B91791ED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a calculation of the estimated direct cost of Federal regulation and Federal regulatory cost as a percentage of the gross domestic product;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H84603960A64E4BA4B916829C1D887983"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the reduction in estimated gross domestic product attributable to private sector compliance with all Federal regulations, rules, or statements and all Federal statutes;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFB90F850419F4865BBFFC6A11571EB3E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a detailed description of the effect on the economy of the United States of Federal regulations, rules, and statements and Federal statutes, which shall be categorized as relating to—</text>
<subparagraph id="HFC1FBECEE906499EB6DFD41EB0C025DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>regulation of the economy;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H417BF4AE12134B1EB479E8705BD96309"><enum>(B)</enum><text>security, including homeland security;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFEA22C70389249B3AF7F0CB5959ECBB5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the environment;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC6B10A6C1054411D9D18A08A2E22C978"><enum>(D)</enum><text>health and safety; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA7A0CB7110F74AC4900E682D1BE270C2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Federal budget;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC7ACAD9BE1DF4BD3A7DEFFFB25C17C3B"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a discussion of the expected reduction in personnel, administrative overhead, and programmatic costs that would be achieved by Federal agencies that issue regulations, rules, or statements with a Federal regulatory cost if the Federal agencies reduced the Federal regulatory cost by 5 percent;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8894C13FA934476DB7D480EF9743157B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>recommendations for budgeting, technical, and estimating changes to improve the Federal regulatory budgeting process;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02598A0DD9D1466F971529666296F397"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Federal regulatory cost imposed by each Executive branch agency on regulated entities;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC35B8C1F10CB4210B11FEFA8F0E06407"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the direct cost of Federal regulation attributable to each Executive branch agency;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA55FE7AAD28846769E6056FFFBA5E95C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the Federal regulatory costs imposed by each Executive branch agency on small businesses, small organizations, and small governmental jurisdictions (as those terms are defined in section 601 of title 5, United States Code); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H685B4F3EAA1E47049E812BA3EE595B11"><enum>(10)</enum><text>the sum of the costs described in paragraph (9).</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HED5E36181BE844729A157F464B35CE50"><enum>326.</enum><header>Regulatory baseline</header> <subsection id="HDA1D7A8E5B584FF2BE45800660D46B61"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the fifth fiscal year that begins after the date of enactment of this section and for every second fiscal year thereafter, CBO, in consultation with OMB, shall submit to the President, the Senate, and the House of Representatives a regulatory baseline, consisting of a projection of the Federal regulatory cost for the fiscal year and at least each of the 4 ensuing fiscal years. In preparing the projection of the regulatory baseline under this subsection, for the second fiscal year covered under the projection and each fiscal year thereafter, CBO shall adjust the baseline for the estimated growth during that fiscal year in the gross domestic product.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H9255C5B601FD47A784612E43D975D63B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text>The CBO shall submit a regulatory baseline required under subsection (a) for a fiscal year not later than the date on which the CBO submits the report required under section 202(e)(1) with respect to that fiscal year.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5C27B5F01C8A4B2494CD48C2DE4CF18B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regular updates on development of regulatory baseline</header><text>Not later than the date on which the CBO submits the report required under section 202(e)(1) with respect to each fiscal year during the period beginning on the date of enactment of this section and ending on the date on which the CBO submits the first projection of the Federal regulatory cost under subsection (a), the CBO shall submit to the Committee on the Budget of the Senate and the Committee on the Budget of the House of Representatives an annual update on the progress of the CBO in developing the regulatory baseline.</text></subsection></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE53CACE5BF274BF8A9FDB8EAEE836FD8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>The table of contents set forth in section 1(b) of the Congressional Budget and Impoundment Control Act of 1974 is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HA4A04EB94FD84A9DB982A6B1184DB3F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting before the item relating to section 300 the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HE5B7CAD534ED41968DA4F860F0D5BD98" style="traditional">
<toc>
<toc-entry idref="H6463204C4E9145748B8B6DC073E4C94C" level="part">Part A. General provisions</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">and </continuation-text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7DC3DEDFF8A24AD68C9FA6F26E991F91"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 315 the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H4756C354491A45588EB585EACD975145" style="OLC"> <toc> <toc-entry idref="H21F7FC11B78243A58929071B74DB477D" level="part">Part B. Federal regulatory budget cost control </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="HCB476E9262D346F0B2C68E9BD726BBA2" level="section">Sec. 321. Definitions. </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="HB0A0AE4DF9FD417BA34244EA51A5BF04" level="section">Sec. 322. Establishment of level and allocations. </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="HE5AD8AD676E0459CB9E30701FD40F9C9" level="section">Sec. 323. Analysis of Federal regulatory cost by Congressional Budget Office. </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="H16E2429B233E49649B8E049F6417F80F" level="section">Sec. 324. Enforcement. </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="HD654351A72CA4AC4AADC5CA95CCD748A" level="section">Sec. 325. OMB–CBO reports. </toc-entry> <toc-entry idref="HED5E36181BE844729A157F464B35CE50" level="section">Sec. 326. Regulatory baseline.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A13F524429C4783BBF3B3BDEFAB3B91"><enum>6.</enum><header>Study of nonmajor rules</header> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H47FE6B70E88045288DED41C1DEC2A318"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4A1E7868092E45DA9EA5FCEB1F813541"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB2EA6CD374974ED4B80FE3F8E8D018D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>covered guidance document</term> means any guidance document that has resulted or is likely to result in an annual effect on the economy of not less than $10,000,000;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H91C8660D3F3748BB8D11C93024F89112"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>covered nonmajor rule</term> means any rule that has resulted in or is likely to result in an annual effect on the economy of not less than $10,000,000 and not more than $100,000,000;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HECBEE1E42AB54FF2B4A2472ADEB66454"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>guidance document</term> means an agency statement of general applicability and future effect, other than a rule, that sets forth a policy on a statutory, regulatory, or technical issue or an interpretation of a statutory or regulatory issue;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE314D5882DC24B07B9491AB01B1C91E1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>Federal regulatory cost</term> has the meaning given that term under section 321 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974, as added by this Act; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB92F212361814EA2A0561ED77F28F670"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>rule</term> has the meaning given that term in section 804 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1085CD5CC5346D8AA284E9BB17CB14E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act and every 2 years thereafter, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report regarding covered nonmajor rules and covered guidance documents, which shall include, for the 4-year period immediately preceding the report—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC03D1877EE847EC841D8F6554638F86"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of covered nonmajor rules promulgated;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE9EFC7AD6786439388DD4D5E426CF11E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of covered nonmajor rules implemented;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB4DD927A5E964113818606E2495AF47D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the number of covered guidance documents developed;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H92F4F696825447D7A064AC0AEA549172"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the number of covered guidance documents issued;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA74FAE60041F4F1E8E15DFA3409B5313"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Federal regulatory cost of each covered nonmajor rule implemented;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF60CD6E211904A3FAC1ABAE4DD9CB583"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Federal regulatory cost of each covered guidance document issued;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBC2C48E325134B75934A920ABA4C5017"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the aggregate Federal regulatory cost of all covered nonmajor rules implemented;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H129EE3F652034AE6A72EBE6DA327B1B6"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the aggregate Federal regulatory cost of all covered guidance documents issued; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99D5D59C406843A1AB364AA42A03FEAA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>a discussion of any covered nonmajor rule for which an initial regulatory flexibility analysis was prepared under section 603 of title 5, United States Code, a final regulatory flexibility analysis was prepared under section 604 of title 5, United States Code, or a cost benefit analysis was prepared that underestimated the actual Federal regulatory cost of implementing the covered nonmajor rule.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

