<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6963C25A66834CB8AC0CBA97F1F4D4E2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2931 IH: Smart Sentencing Adjustments Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2931</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 to provide incentives for States to implement policy changes to reduce prison populations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6A0728E61F024DF288CDAD31A3562CB4" style="OLC"><section id="H7686E2543B0142DFB7B702EFFF0D31C7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Smart Sentencing Adjustments Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF3B037F0744A4E679FAB7F8AAE4BAF9F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program</header><subsection id="H57BCC3248EB04FF29ABCE9CA5B4C7328"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Street Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10101">34 U.S.C. 10101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC152C83F6EB9403DBF3DCF9FFA5CBC54"><part id="HED36846444F8494195009D42072A6D09" style="OLC"><enum>PP</enum><header>State prison population reduction grant program.</header><section id="H55BBCD696E724A1D8A6796387D4ADDA6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3061.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part:</text><paragraph id="H222506E204A647F1BA6B493FFAC04F71"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation grant</header><text>The term <term>implementation grant</term> means a grant awarded to a State for the purpose of reducing the prison population of the State by not less than 20 percent, based on the average total prison population of the State for the 3-year period preceding the date on which the State applies for the implementation grant under section 3062(d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBE4790EB9D14C7CABF9D78BB597C474"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Planning grant</header><text>The term <term>planning grant</term> means a grant awarded to a State for the purpose of—</text><subparagraph id="H8053C342357945178136E907ED291E77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>analyzing criminal justice trends and factors to better understand excessive and unnecessary prison incarceration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54F5ED55ED254DC7AE2BC2991DABD75E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>exploring the feasibility of developing, adopting, and implementing policy changes to ameliorate criminal justice trends and factors causing excessive and unnecessary prison incarceration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9653FEDA908D40519CAE19F1D5CAC580" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prison</header><text>The term <term>prison</term> means a publicly or privately operated institution of a State for the confinement of an individual convicted of a criminal offense with a sentence of not less than 1 year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H632CBD093F6E4ACC99FBDFC408D95117"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> has the meaning given the term in section 901. </text></paragraph></section><section id="H029E609EEFE24774AAED9D733300FABE"><enum>3062.</enum><header>Grant program</header><subsection id="H32E83EB019474E5A9897CD7970E23747"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Smart Sentencing Adjustments Act</short-title>, the Attorney General shall award planning grants and implementation grants to States, on a competitive basis, in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDCE72C10A46B46B787A35B846928C0F2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Planning grants</header><paragraph id="HCED305C70BB64F1C8FC6FD0A1344FABC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>A State seeking a planning grant under this section shall submit to the Attorney General an application at such time and in such manner as the Attorney General may require, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HA75328F59FA04D748C80C8E767DD1F99"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the State’s need for a planning grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H67AC877F6869435C869300482EA7C896"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the activities the State will carry out with the planning grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0E6776980CC46EAA302D61518BD70E3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A State that receives a planning grant under this section shall use the grant solely for the purpose of developing plans for the policy changes that would be required to carry out subsection (c)(3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H750F0D9CEF664C169898C17B8CFB91D2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Planning grant report</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the end of the period of the planning grant of a State, the State shall submit to the Attorney General a report that describes—</text><subparagraph id="H5A0DE458FE734811B5EABFC397A08F57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the projects to be undertaken by the State using amounts made available under the planning grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C16C6CE97E443D8AD6858BB75CD6B76"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any additional information determined appropriate by the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4052EB47006C43A8884116DDCC4635DB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation grants</header><paragraph id="HEFFAA7FBE4C14230BBEFC1CAEA1FFF11"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>In order to be eligible to apply for an implementation grant under paragraph (2), a State shall apply for, receive, and fully execute a planning grant under subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48312837C8C54CFC80E6143B846FE6DC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>A State seeking an implementation grant under this section shall submit to the Attorney General an application at such time and in such manner as the Attorney General may require, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H029E21A758F246CFA61272582F960444"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the total prison population of the State, including racial, ethnic, gender, and socioeconomic information of the population and information relating to the income, education, and housing status of the population;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06DF7C46315F48BD9F5F8F8287D7ED81"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the rate of prison population growth of the State in relative and absolute estimates during the 25 year-period preceding the date of the application; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF49A452A9B9344BD8885D5431B2CFE97"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a comprehensive and coherent plan detailing the proposals of the State to use amounts from the implementation grant that—</text><clause id="H1E6EAC3CBB554ACEBA5C70C9D22B4BDF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is based upon the activities the State performed with a planning grant received under this section; and</text></clause><clause id="H4F02B5C0166D41D98B574B060E18C727"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>describes the policy changes planned to carry out paragraph (3) to achieve the purpose of the implementation grant.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H05BE4FCEBE534C5AB1BF0BD8FD9D3BA6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A State that receives an implementation grant under this section shall use amounts from the grant to—</text><subparagraph id="H9937D7F3B23A46408770F7506CB464C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>reduce the prison population of the State by—</text><clause id="H6FB1EDBF73544460BF949D2928BF7853"><enum>(i)</enum><text>establishing or supporting programs that divert individuals from incarceration;</text></clause><clause id="HC813CF326D3343FEAFF835179C09307F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>eliminating policies, with a retroactive effect, that drive excessive and unnecessarily lengthy terms of imprisonment, including by—</text><subclause id="H09919B91C38A474B82048399908A2FEF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>repealing mandatory minimum penalties for certain offenses;</text></subclause><subclause id="HA5297D4152AB4D5D91E8CAD3E75F72AC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>repealing sentencing enhancements for certain offenses; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HAEFAB65EBF2940FD91980C4AA5863EAB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>downgrading certain criminal offenses, such as reducing felony offenses to misdemeanor offenses;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H273487B6DEC44E87A546EEA72D1DDE37"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>implementing policies, with a retroactive effect, that help promote proportionality and fairness in sentencing, including by—</text><subclause id="H72C9E492B1FC4360B98AD7D260BFBEEC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>capping sentences; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H1E47DDBCDBA147348A5BFF32A8C29A66"><enum>(II)</enum><text>reviewing and modifying sentences automatically after 15 years;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HDD00F247E0744F818CE9298E2285E737"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>implementing policies, with a retroactive effect, that increase opportunities for early release, including by—</text><subclause id="H1B433DAF5DD74EBC9FD04005C84F8303"><enum>(I)</enum><text>expanding opportunities and incentives for incarcerated individuals to earn time off of their custodial sentence;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6D9C5CD7647C450F91AC4C9EA0C9CDE6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>repealing policies that restrict or reduce parole eligibility, such as truth in sentencing laws; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HDC13A3D1C3084604B51038C5BE232D49"><enum>(III)</enum><text>eliminating policies that delay initial parole eligibility beyond 10 years;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HDDAA995D7E9D456BA96E7BB0B54D3E8B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>reducing or eliminating the use of incarceration as a sanction for non-criminal rule violations of community supervision, such as technical parole and probation violations, including missing drug treatment classes;</text></clause><clause id="H95CB7FF90FF74C6E8EDCED2B0060FBD1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>improving the executive functions of the State that can promote early release by—</text><subclause id="H5F5EBFC154AE419F89C85F19C63677FA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>establishing or expanding the use of mechanisms providing for the early release of incarcerated individuals based on specific criteria, such as advanced age and terminal illness, by—</text><item id="H586F50CDA8A84744A7339380D9003E24"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>convening or staffing boards of experts to advise officials of the State with the authority to promulgate sentencing policy on the exercise of the State’s compassionate, medical, and geriatric release power;</text></item><item id="HE4E1F1082A0E4E9B974E5B4D5F0B14D1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>broadening eligibility criteria for release;</text></item><item id="HC8D68C0045744845B957E56B17226204"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>streamlining and clarifying application for release review protocols; and</text></item><item id="H9E3F5CB8D2A24C509B9CC47DC34E3C0E"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>increasing the number of compassionate, medical, and geriatric releases; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H78815D0D83FF4FD798DF067C12C5BD15"><enum>(II)</enum><text>improving clemency processes, including by—</text><item id="HEA83A822ED35484496238AA291BF2DC6"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>convening or staffing boards of experts to advise officials of the State with the authority to promulgate sentencing policy on the exercise of the State’s clemency power;</text></item><item id="H6901F34F80FD4465975D3AFBEA8FAF24"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>broadening eligibility for clemency;</text></item><item id="HC4EDAB3C63BB452DB875778D2AF45F2F"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>streamlining and clarifying clemency application review protocols; and</text></item><item id="H1A640851A0DB457986E06DB979840315"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>increasing the number of clemency grants;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H663E407A494746FF85F9E4ABBAA8773E"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>improving prosecutorial functions to correct extreme, disproportionate, unjust, or wrongful criminal convictions and custodial sentences by—</text><subclause id="HA1BDF78B1C2D4654BF148E7C5EE77FEC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>establishing or expanding conviction integrity units or conviction review units within prosecutorial offices that work to prevent, identify, and remedy false convictions; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HAB19B1CA665048E0A24BC152D734BCDD"><enum>(II)</enum><text>establishing or expanding sentencing review units within prosecutorial offices to address overcrowding, racial inequities, and lengthy prison sentences that are considered extreme or disproportionate; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HA302F2E8A4AA4F82855E553B11EA26A5"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>improving the quality of indigent defense; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1004E46D0D9469FB86DD509CA2F1E9C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>reduce the recurrence of recidivism after a term of incarceration and reduce the collateral consequences experienced by individuals with criminal records by—</text><clause id="HC76E99BEBD05484DAD163FD33666AECC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>expanding programming for incarcerated populations within prisons that enables those populations to successfully transition back into society;</text></clause><clause id="H0C351466B1A14FB19DEA0A15EB424C5D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>improving access for expungement and record sealing processes;</text></clause><clause id="H15D7ECAC1E664054B08B4C7DF4469F46"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>adopting laws prohibiting employers from asking applicants about their criminal history on applications for employment or prior to tendering an employment offer;</text></clause><clause id="HCF024CE4996B47AE929C9EC3D454DFEC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>eliminating fees imposed on a defendant by—</text><subclause id="HDF39875A85474B798B6AB9475305FAB9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>discharging any fine or fee debt for individuals who are incarcerated or exiting prison; or </text></subclause><subclause id="HDC84FCE1EC6545E297B0A0C6629A16C2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>developing policies and programs to assess fines and fees based on an individual’s ability to pay;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFE51945F95FE4282B5280D999FE6FA71"><enum>(v)</enum><text>establishing or supporting wrap-around or community-based services for individuals reentering their communities after incarceration, including services relating to housing, disability, employment, education, healthcare, behavior and mental health, substance abuse, and childcare; or</text></clause><clause id="HA703D44BBF35432BA45C1145223957E1"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>supporting community-based crime prevention programs that work directly with formerly incarcerated individuals or in communities that have a higher prevalence of individuals with criminal records, such as—</text><subclause id="HFE555708C5984818A8AB6EB0E3AFA9C4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>programs involving violence prevention;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6C5A4A6EF91342E48D52FE8DA6B1C5DC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>housing and supportive housing;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF15BB0ADBE814096ABB3E9F07F431829"><enum>(III)</enum><text>jobs and job placement;</text></subclause><subclause id="H981C9347FD2847E0818DC1BB2D388AD5"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>substance abuse or mental health treatment; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H6EFC670BA45F49A492B78AD41AE02C83"><enum>(V)</enum><text>other wrap-around support services aiming to build pathways to life stabilizing opportunities.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEBED19CE711483B810A75938C10BF04"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Implementation grant report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which a State receives an implementation grant under this section, and annually thereafter, the State shall submit to the Attorney General a report, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Attorney General may require, that—</text><subparagraph id="H83CCD1849CD147B69AB389DA77D11A50"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifies the programs and policies funded with the grant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C508204FD124986B54E20EDAB9A4659"><enum>(B)</enum><text>assesses racial, ethnic, gender, age, and socioeconomic impacts of the programs and policies funded with the grant with independent researchers or a consortium of independent researchers, such as research or academic institutions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5F28DF8AF3E474880C09B483AD7B0C3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>includes an evaluation of increases or decreases in a State's prison population by assessing changes in—</text><clause id="H7389656B10BA4A36BBFB144F406785CB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>pretrial detention;</text></clause><clause id="H791CF121EFEC4A0A801AAF11DFE6216B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>sentencing;</text></clause><clause id="H8E0A800DE233496F923BDA878EADC3DA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>incarceration;</text></clause><clause id="HE9A2C5F0C26A43518C6BB2A4B44C10F1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>probation; </text></clause><clause id="HB757F426B2A84755BBF5EDD2CF0A05C2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>parole;</text></clause><clause id="HF8F69F72FB134021982615CD16808496"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>clemency; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB9E664925D9F45E383850281AB979A9D"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>compassionate, medical, or geriatric release.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2329A6848E5B4873ADF2F139E0AEDF25"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Subgrants</header><subparagraph id="HC48B47EFD8C9409CAF2CCFE5FA35A497"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State receiving an implementation grant under this section shall use not less than 20 percent of the amount of the grant to award subgrants to nonprofit organizations that meet the criteria described in subparagraph (B), which shall assist in the implementation of the policy changes described in subsection (c)(2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B8EDE2A30B24388A7D8CF5046BF1764"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Criteria</header><text>In selecting nonprofit organizations to receive subgrants under paragraph (1), a State shall give priority to nonprofit organizations that—</text><clause id="HB6853981059C404B91209DD3F2CF4BCB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have a demonstrated track record of providing services to reintegrate individuals released from prison into society with a goal of reducing the recurrence of recidivism;</text></clause><clause id="HC84CF8FB280C43BCAC999C125459CA71"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are based in geographic areas with a higher prevalence of individuals with criminal records;</text></clause><clause id="HD1483D50EC65457B9171F5DA2822DC43"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>are led by or employ individuals who have been incarcerated or have family members who are or have been incarcerated; or</text></clause><clause id="H2AB05AF6944B4D45A6AC39B4059FCC25"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>primarily serve individuals who—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBE5266ECEA7D4ECBB0CF3394EF5D01D5"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have been arrested or convicted of a criminal offense; or</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD0E304365DFF4B6FBEA019E33330E683"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have spent time in jail, prison, or on probation or parole. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H69CC4971D3DE4825997369AEB953E0FF"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Renewal</header><text>A State that receives an implementation grant under this section may apply for an additional implementation grant at the end of the term of the implementation grant if the State has reduced the prison population of the State by not less than 20 percent, based on the average total prison population of the State during the 3-year period preceding the date of the application for the implementation grant under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B2C5487B1844E1E960F7566B47EA51E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Terms and conditions</header><paragraph id="H614C19AC69834D86A036659E924E625F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Duration</header><subparagraph id="H0568D569A4AB4045A11D0265EA920655"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Planning grant</header><text>A planning grant under this section shall be awarded for a period of 2 fiscal years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA4F77C00B04433F8BC1E034922E9E84"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation grant</header><text>An implementation grant under this section shall be awarded for a period of 3 fiscal years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H60D030512F084E508A646DD36BF420C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount</header><subparagraph id="H3C7DB76FB9EF462DB8DB52E7F8632EE3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Planning grant</header><text>The amount of each planning grant awarded under this section shall not exceed $700,000 for the duration of the grant.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31D2EF85CC3B46EA8403EF51E8713A83"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation grant</header><text>The amount of each implementation grant awarded under this section shall not exceed $70,000,000 for the duration of the grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD311139C0144F708A6C5D9D1E97EA49"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Number of grant awards</header><subparagraph id="H45817A2D1AEE4123A0FF07B361054CD2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Planning grants</header><text>The Attorney General may award planning grants under this section to not more than 25 States during each fiscal year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42577F9AFD5C46E78DB366B21F17A8BD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation grants</header><text>The Attorney General may award implementation grants under this section to no more than 25 States during each fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C41EB06C28E4F669A77438748D6B815"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><subparagraph id="H94CBEDCCBEED46E4B4FD771350F69704"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Inmate transfers</header><text>During any grant term under this Act, a State may not transfer an individual convicted of a criminal offense with a sentence of not less than 1 year from a prison of the State to any penitentiary, jail, or other institution or facility for the confinement of individuals convicted of criminal offenses with sentences of less than 1 year for the purpose of carrying out subsection (c)(3).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B74756FCAA8450F81FD693F5EAFEB5B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Policies</header><text>During the term of any grant awarded under this section, a State that receives the grant may not establish or amend any—</text><clause id="H33727C2A63354391BDE99C645B0A58E0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>sentence enhancement or law that would increase the punishment of an individual previously convicted of a criminal offense;</text></clause><clause id="H860DDD0312E744989F4FE2FDAF36B9A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>habitual offender law or law that imposes longer sentences on individuals who have been convicted of a certain number of criminal offenses;</text></clause><clause id="H87998839F411479182A3837D5F422B34"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>truth in sentencing law or law that aims to reduce the difference between sentences imposed and the actual time that individuals serve in prison; </text></clause><clause id="HAD1B388CF2344FD3BE93F9B58DBE3FFA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>mandatory minimum sentencing law or law that requires judges to sentence offenders to a specified minimum prison term for specific offenses to increase the minimum prison sentence; or</text></clause><clause id="HD611B796A89B47A8B5E3B2EF701D7992"><enum>(v)</enum><text>policies that would result in increased incarceration. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27F59E972994487EA441185BE37BEFF2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><text>A State receiving any grant under this part may not use amounts from the grant to—</text><clause id="HF91E38B744424E8697FE9D81D5DC5C7D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>build or maintain any prison, jail, or other facility designed for the confinement of individuals convicted of criminal offenses;</text></clause><clause id="HC3860C628FF74ED9B07A5E798AC656A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>enter into a contract with a for-profit company to build or manage prisons, jails, or other correctional facilities;</text></clause><clause id="HE3BEE1BEC1D048EA94D9A42E906E8DB5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>hire, train, or maintain sworn law enforcement officers; </text></clause><clause id="H7EF741BB797641B59ECCEF9ECE89473A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>purchase law enforcement equipment; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H568E214B46DD4A9289B5DAA917195126"><enum>(v)</enum><text>create or fund programs that would increase incarceration.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE55D62CADCCB44E99508F449A52EABEA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>If the Attorney General determines that a State receiving a grant under this section violates a provision of this part, the Attorney General shall—</text><subparagraph id="HAFEE9A10B83F4EF5B2DAE25313698A5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>require the State to repay 10 percent of the amount of the grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80E75F068CED4F268110B513296742BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prohibit the State from receiving any other grant under this part for not less than 3 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0762036881F04C46B2C35151AF66278C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Maximums</header><text>The Attorney General may award a State under this section—</text><subparagraph id="H8A1EEBB80CA94938ACD6083D0CD710E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not more than 1 planning grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB6BEC2A27514DEA9DF47FAA55BC8A7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not more than 2 consecutive implementation grants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA3CDFB80EB5C48E98BAC376D46974470"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text>The Attorney General shall reserve not more than 5 percent of the amount appropriated to carry out this part for administration, oversight, and technical assistance activities through the Office of Justice Programs.</text></subsection></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCFDB0FF0BFC3476EA97B615A4B8CEA24"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>Section 1001(a) of title I of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10261">34 U.S.C. 10261(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1AF185F7EBA74350BF3802DFA7322DC0"><paragraph id="H2D60CF708C9440F78F4C9A0E99BE62AC" indent="up1"><enum>(29)</enum><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out part PP $2,000,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2034.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

