<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H417432F350354E7EBFCC9D14F041009F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1049 IH: Protecting Airport Communities from Particle Emissions Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1049</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to conduct a study relating to ultrafine particles, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEAC3F4DE0DDA4F019C6BC62ECBA6A046" style="OLC"><section id="HD41744FA32634ECEAEE8A080E2C04813" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Airport Communities from Particle Emissions Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3070F4E2AFF149D282861C57DA040115"><enum>2.</enum><header>Airborne ultrafine particle study</header><subsection id="HC1B9C05F626D41D4899B07A96400BA41"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, jointly with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, shall enter into an agreement with an eligible institution of higher education to conduct a study examining airborne ultrafine particles and their effect on human health.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA652F97C35D4B4F86D9A4B0C779D179"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scope of study</header><text>The study conducted under subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="H3702BBB14A3C461A973FFF21D9FC7C9E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>summarize the relevant literature and studies done on airborne ultrafine particles worldwide;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72C0EA6411584E389E25CBFF592280FF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>focus on large hub commercial airports in—</text><subparagraph id="HE100A6ECF29E4645A032C97350A9C4B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Seattle;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE45B9189D47B4448940C5E3AEAB15C5B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Boston;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD947C96421764636BAA1440AB49B5338"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Chicago;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H852255ED5B3E4E24869E39DE96C54C59"><enum>(D)</enum><text>New York;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C63D00530724AA9A69E6A8ED15D1090"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Northern California Metroplex;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C2B4B5DB9C84DDF8F9886EDB1CBE259"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Phoenix;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58F5F621A05F4B9185FC66A4BAF71868"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Southern California Metroplex;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B1BBF040BDE4A7FA24F6DE8A750866D"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the District of Columbia; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H640299ECA01A4E8FA9CF3CB49C15D562"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Atlanta;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6B29696088C4130A275C14C7F65FBEC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>examine airborne ultrafine particles and their effect on human health, including—</text><subparagraph id="H1FD4012EE5364AC6BBB11A31D94E0A96"><enum>(A)</enum><text>characteristics of UFPs present in the air;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CD8E0004B874037B16CB4C9F1B088F4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>spatial and temporal distributions of UFP concentrations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H265BC50233C34DF29E172C40533F8291"><enum>(C)</enum><text>primary sources of UFPs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAFF921628FB849FEB6FDDC083C6F96D8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the contribution of aircraft and airport operations to the distribution of UFP concentrations when compared to other sources;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2854FF258152430B9D7CE578783DF84E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>potential health effects associated with elevated UFP exposures, including outcomes related to cardiovascular disease, respiratory infection and disease, degradation of neurocognitive functions, and other health effects, that have been considered in previous studies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85106F0BBBE641B6A9F9FDA2D36359EB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>potential UFP exposures, especially to susceptible and vulnerable groups;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E48FB105DF645DFA31DDED5B6C96E5D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identify measures, including the use of sustainable aviation fuels, intended to reduce emissions from aircraft and airport operations and assess potential effects on emissions related to UFPs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFA3B6815E28481DB4B0D643A267A5DC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identify information gaps related to understanding relationships between UFP exposures and health effects, contributions of aviation-related emissions to UFP exposures, and the effectiveness of mitigation measures.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H769DE1930F074F06B6F26C4AC1335D42"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>An institution of higher education is eligible to conduct the study if the institution—</text><paragraph id="HBE1097B7144B401DA3F806FF5AAB4CA5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is located in one of the areas identified in subsection (b);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A0AF49695CA4EDAB77E4B8820B740BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>applies to the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration in a timely fashion;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D1FA4630023463EB4167FD86C7ECF60"><enum>(3)</enum><text>demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Administrator that the institution is qualified to conduct the study;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H339F57AF616A4B46B1853A316A01CF5F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>agrees to submit to the Administrator, not later than 2 years after entering into an agreement under subsection (a), the results of the study, including any source materials used; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2B8170E3886454388F83569D6D32D6A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>meets such other requirements as the Administrator determines necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3896C9CFD80435CBA214A8DAFD257B4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Administrator may coordinate with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, and any other agency head whom the Administrator deems appropriate to provide data and other assistance necessary for the study.</text></subsection><subsection id="H597A73171AA64E6E84CFF0F3112C7FD2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after submission of the results of the study by the institution of higher education, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the study including the results of the study submitted under subsection (c)(4) by the institution of higher education.</text></subsection><subsection id="H78FA211C8D3F412A8B0850B930114E08"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this Act, the terms <quote>ultrafine particle</quote> and <quote>UFP</quote> mean particles with diameters less than or equal to 100 nanometers.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

