<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H19B737C18AB6472FAE799B36F4CB8CB0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>101 HR 6278 IH: MOVE Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6278</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231107">November 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000605">Mr. Perry</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of General Services to identify two Federal agencies to consolidate into the GSA Headquarters Building, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB30B7718C63047929E7D392973DF0A77" style="OLC"><section id="H1FDD2114D49E48CA8BAE973B6D1407A0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Maximizing Office Value and Efficiency Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote>MOVE Act of 2023</quote>. </text></section><section id="HF96CCB56071F4952B5EB2ADAAF5A18CE" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Public building consolidation and sale</header><subsection id="H6F53C06D047045F29BDE45600F3337A1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Consolidation plan</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (c), not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator, in coordination with the director, shall—</text><paragraph id="H012AD671D9AD4CFFB2705CC58F14E30D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (3), identify not less than 2 Federal agencies to consolidate into the GSA Headquarters Building that will produce a building utilization of not less than 60 percent; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4886BEC6C9141FCA5766D5FDE4943AE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a plan to consolidate under paragraph (1); and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1152236199704356B0B5F4DC0BCF70CB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in identifying Federal agencies under paragraph (1), consider Federal agencies that use on average 9 percent or less of the capacity of the headquarters buildings of such agencies as identified by the Government Accountability Office pursuant to the statement of the Government Accountability Office titled <quote>Federal Real Property: Preliminary Results Show Federal Buildings Remain Underutilized Due to Longstanding Challenges and Increased Telework</quote> and issued on July 13, 2023 (GAO–23–106200). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA1120B7A3E1F4A8395B0668836E5284D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Commencement of consolidation</header><text>Not later than 1 year after submission of the plan pursuant to subsection (a)(2), the Administrator shall commence implementation of such plan.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8A4449BE3CB4472FAF8EF4EE3E5D60F6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Alternative plan</header><text>If the Administrator, in coordination with the Director, fails to identify Federal agencies pursuant to subsection (a)(1) and complete a consolidation under subsection (a)(2) not later than 3 years after the submission date of the plan described in subsection (a)(2), the Administrator shall consolidate the General Services Administration personnel based in the GSA Headquarters Building into another federally-owned public building occupied by another Federal agency and prepare the GSA Headquarters Building for sale.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA67D10C2324F43C48BF5417C0700ADD1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sales</header><paragraph id="H0D6E3ACA89D54FD88BF0B27FC58DEBB8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after implementation of the plan pursuant to subsection (a)(2), the Administrator shall sell any public buildings vacated as a result of such plan for fair market value at highest and best use.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56BB73CD01074CDAADE81AF5300B3758"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alternative sale</header><text>In the event, the alternative plan is carried out pursuant to subsection (c), the Administrator shall sell the GSA Headquarters Building for fair market value at highest and best use.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36F4F419D3704F6F9720C2A7DCD21016"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Net proceeds</header><text>Any net proceeds from a sale under this subsection shall be paid into an account in the Federal Buildings Fund established under section 592 of title 40, United States Code, and upon deposit, such proceeds may be expended only subject to a specific future appropriation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H01F2829166A74D0395AF6CF1B1E754A1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HC464091A3FEA4F2BB5654A4B5B52A389"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Actual utilization rate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>actual utilization rate</quote> means the total useable square footage of a public building or federally-leased space divided by the occupancy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H066B033F4AAA4AD8A364B4E65DF4C089"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of General Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79BFC860FBF9425EB2FEED7288725AA8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Building utilization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>building utilization</quote> means the percentage of utilization generated by comparing the actual utilization rate with the capacity based on a utilization benchmark of 150 useable square feet per person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2D845BF4BD94BA38AD88282D5755B0E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Capacity</header><text>The term <quote>capacity</quote> means the total usable square footage of a public building or federally-leased space divided by a utilization benchmark.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A15EA27DD6D4E5BAB4BEDA990BD237E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <quote>Director</quote> means the Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E72BD0D14C946F9929168A71E31D8F7"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <quote>Federal agency</quote> means an executive department covered by the CFO Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/101/576">Public Law 101–576</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E043562905540819E0DA6CC44591AE0"><enum>(7)</enum><header>GSA Headquarters Building</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>GSA Headquarters Building</quote> means the property located at 1800 F Street NW in Washington, District of Columbia.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC545482529194A558ED05D367C247469"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Occupancy</header><text>The term <quote>occupancy</quote> means the total number of employees performing duties in-person in a public building or federally-leased space at least 5 days per week on a regular basis.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

