<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE137DD01EEF94A669D05D9F2D6233610" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6342 IH: Military and Veterans in Parks Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6342</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To promote and enhance outdoor recreation opportunities for members of the Armed Forces and veterans on Federal recreational lands and waters.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1B40D55BBCDE4124902B01FF4BAF918D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6D4299525A6844D49960D23D8BABD2D6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Military and Veterans in Parks Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MVP Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H98E5644B6C094AF6B02D7741CC7BFEF7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Accessible trails and recreation opportunities for military servicemembers and veterans</header> <subsection id="H005A5EECC159411F89DD8EC220E8CAFE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Accessible recreation inventory</header> <paragraph id="H45F9A0D76E7A44ACA7042A08E4EAC008"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HEBA3C4AE084243648144DF85A3A85618"><enum>(A)</enum><text>carry out a comprehensive assessment of outdoor recreation facilities on Federal recreational lands and waters under the jurisdiction of the respective Secretary concerned to determine the accessibility of such outdoor recreation facilities, consistent with the Architectural Barriers Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4151">42 U.S.C. 4151 et seq.</external-xref>), including—</text> <clause id="H74932702A2BB4B4CA8ADBFB1615B219A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>camp shelters, camping facilities, and camping units;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7890598975994FF7A19C983816F88144"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>boat launch ramps;</text></clause> <clause id="H54CDB19BBD7A4F7FBC81170876D8CC71"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>hunting, fishing, shooting, or archery ranges or locations;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD188AF5F73414464B80E0E16EDC5BB0A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>outdoor constructed features;</text></clause> <clause id="HD5E6543802974C648999B8EBA6B5BE92"><enum>(v)</enum><text>picnic facilities and picnic units; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HE95B728A00D04299BC98A097E9376DFD"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>any other outdoor recreation facilities, as determined by the Secretary concerned; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF1EB13DCAD6F4474ACE228CAA0713B99"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make information about such opportunities available (including through the use of prominently displayed links) on public websites of—</text> 
<clause id="H00FFDE11E613440A9C21F071E42F8D6E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each of the Federal land management agencies; and</text></clause> <clause id="HE2B57412A2E44DF896E56C9BE8411867"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each relevant unit and subunit of the Federal land management agencies.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7652584883D64EEAB7DB17093148E88C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion of current assessments</header><text>As part of the comprehensive assessment required under paragraph (1)(A), to the extent practicable, the Secretary concerned may rely on assessments completed or data gathered prior to the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE374DC140A164C73A887E67881422C9B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public information</header><text>Not later than 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall identify opportunities to create, update, or replace signage and other publicly available information, including web page information, related to accessibility and consistent with the Architectural Barriers Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4151">42 U.S.C. 4151 et seq.</external-xref>) at outdoor recreation facilities covered by the assessment required under paragraph (1)(A).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H443669AB2810466FB05B9184FDAC1F14"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Trail inventory</header> 
<paragraph id="H064BA9BFF0D443E599E02C8F87F13D2D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>Not later than 7 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H3763EBCAA51A47D89795C3905DD11345"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct a comprehensive assessment of trails on Federal recreational lands and waters under the jurisdiction of the respective Secretary concerned, including measuring each trail’s—</text> 
<clause id="HC79196A6BBD64A68A638A340DEA4A22B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>surface;</text></clause> <clause id="H4654838C5A2D4A51A7C9FD4B6BA63623"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>clear tread width;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9389A1633E0440919250B5BE53BB3589"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>passing spaces;</text></clause> <clause id="H4E08386CF2D14C3EAB1626B18CCB4840"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>size;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H02B5B9E363FA44DBB7620275B9DAD580"><enum>(v)</enum><text>tread obstacles;</text></clause> <clause id="H67C13779203640C1AEF0CB5AD9DBBF99"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>openings;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3944D41E80A74696A41F8CFF3F2829DB"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>slopes, including cross slope;</text></clause> <clause id="HD5CAEAC130274EA5A798D0B65306644F"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>maximum running slope and segment length;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1E671369D8F64F64B12D65EC63AEBF13"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>resting intervals;</text></clause> <clause id="H9426E82EDBB24FFE8E76D87BCEDD1473"><enum>(x)</enum><text>length;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD163EE7AA17146489B651AC94D84348D"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>width;</text></clause> <clause id="H9E7FE0FDD5764B41ACDE2A8072DB7A90"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>turning space;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H67B003558E084047B12C054B409B9E6D"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>protruding objects; and</text></clause> <clause id="HE8FBDED705DB442FAB58C95B642176DA"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>trailhead signs; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6442E1D76894437BB4168D70C5EFE14C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>make information about such trails available (including through the use of prominently displayed links) on public websites of—</text> <clause id="HB35CDB99F94845B9A4E4C41216F68B38"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each of the Federal land management agencies; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0D5DA638AB3E46AC8B7AA59A98AC45D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each relevant unit and subunit of the Federal land management agencies.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H940D319427F541C793561265DFABEBBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion of current assessments</header><text>As part of the comprehensive assessment required under paragraph (1)(A), the Secretary concerned may, to the extent practicable, rely on assessments completed or data gathered prior to the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H91B4F49607B842FAADF6CF15F92E1DD9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public information</header><text>Not later than 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall identify opportunities to replace signage and other publicly available information, including webpage information, related to such trails and consistent with the Architectural Barriers Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4151">42 U.S.C. 4151 et seq.</external-xref>) at trails covered by the assessment required under paragraph (1)(A).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3DFFB1AF82AB4C2E812FF574CF21E2EE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text>The Secretary concerned shall consult with stakeholders, including veterans organizations and organizations with expertise or experience providing outdoor recreation opportunities to individuals with disabilities, in selecting priority trails to measure under paragraph (1)(A).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA2FD434F4D5841A0BC9DC9F74689A342"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Assistive equipment specification</header><text>In publishing information about each trail under this subsection, the Secretary concerned shall make public information about trails that do not meet the Architectural Barriers Act accessibility guidelines but could otherwise provide outdoor recreation opportunities to individuals with disabilities through the use of certain assistive equipment.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5A62A7644E504D4F94BA54A85B2D1B76"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Trail pilot program</header> <paragraph id="H76BCEEC3C931480B8C85A8277AB5FD8E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall carry out a pilot program to enter into partnerships with eligible entities to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4C6DC2F3B7B1489C90F0BD87CF207040"><enum>(A)</enum><text>measure trails as part of the assessment required under subsection (b);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H075F63310D2A42B59C59E4844BBDB778"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop accessible trails under subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9A17E8182B1F4DA19B518380F4BBE605"><enum>(C)</enum><text>make minor modifications to existing trails to enhance recreational experiences for individuals with disabilities using assistive technology—</text> <clause id="H7C0F97028B90434E9BA5DC29757D1268"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in compliance with all applicable land use and management plans of the Federal recreational lands and waters on which the accessible trail is located; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H036584DAEC0B4E25A043E11AE7A67F9A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in consultation with stakeholders, including veterans organizations and organizations with expertise or experience providing outdoor recreation opportunities to individuals with disabilities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H098E579DCDB741288C749FE85ED33E02"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Locations</header> <subparagraph id="H17319CB118D649879795A59A2DEC93AB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary concerned shall select no fewer than 5 units or subunits under the jurisdiction of the respective Secretary concerned to carry out the pilot program established under subparagraph (1).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBB02449C4F20478BBD8124B26DC42A1D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Special rule of construction for the department of the interior</header><text>In selecting the locations of the pilot programs, the Secretary of the Interior shall ensure that at least one pilot program is carried out in a unit managed by the—</text> <clause id="H93621F2C797A418C813BD2BEAAA911EA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>National Park Service;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0E06807D14704015BF7195DABA95157C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Bureau of Land Management; and</text></clause> <clause id="H7A28EBD21BFA459BA44453EAB46018D3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H98C7E03B5B074D528656ADF3B5D18CF9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The pilot program established under this subsection shall terminate on the date that is 7 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2F0DA324255A4B31A6485F4BDC740451"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Accessible trails</header> <paragraph id="HED1CCCCA3BA940D088EF5B6264B9326D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall select a location or locations to develop at least 3 new accessible trails—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H12E79603B7494E6FA497FB7330B61A08"><enum>(A)</enum><text>on National Forest System lands in each region of the Forest Service;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HED46171C4F5047C8B0BE0235F137FC52"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on land managed by the National Park Service in each region of the National Park Service;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB7EC0194113542459335FBC08A83B0EE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>on land managed by the Bureau of Land Management in each region of the Bureau of Land Management; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H33ABEE3EA3D74D26A832328F990BDCB2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>on land managed by the United States Fish and Wildlife Service in each region of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC9B9BF1189194D03B0E3E8DE3560CB8D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Development</header><text>In developing an accessible trail under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned—</text> <subparagraph id="HD793B1CF027740DCA4DBCF6C896C75B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may—</text> 
<clause id="H651F4E6A7E3442E498618DE3641E6B96"><enum>(i)</enum><text>create a new accessible trail;</text></clause> <clause id="H9E013D1B6D0A4DB0B1D5E330BF0B85FE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>modify an existing trail into an accessible trail; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF43D905C87984236B65DD5217A9F16D4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>create an accessible trail from a combination of new and existing trails; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFA3A96768242409FA96B14771D70935D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall—</text> 
<clause id="H194B06A0DB5D424C9C4224DADE65144A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consult with stakeholders with respect to the feasibility and resources necessary for completing the accessible trail;</text></clause> <clause id="H56FB5D3E69B24451A4028334D53972F8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure the accessible trail complies with the Architectural Barriers Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4151">42 U.S.C. 4151 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB44FD568E9184E78ADFB8A2C9F0E8CCC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, ensure that outdoor constructed features supporting the accessible trail, including parking spaces and restroom facilities, meet the requirements of the Architectural Barriers Act of 1968.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0857FCED4AE34BF4AF7EEF98A7923663"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Completion</header><text>Not later than 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned, in coordination with stakeholders consulted with under paragraph (2)(B), shall complete each accessible trail developed under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H14F3FFDAA17B45F493AB3A8CEA451FEE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Maps, signage, and promotional materials</header><text>For each accessible trail developed under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HEFB8E27604604F40B2CB8175DE45B01B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>publish and distribute maps and install signage, consistent with Architectural Barriers Act accessibility guidelines; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H71981BE839BF4C27B83D284EE12AA8E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate with stakeholders to leverage any non-Federal resources necessary for the development, stewardship, completion, or promotion of the accessible trail.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF550C3F4BE494A3CB5B785CAF8CB3E31"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Conflict avoidance with other uses</header><text>In developing each accessible trail under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned shall ensure that the accessible trail—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD7ED63B4507144ED97D1059A48679231"><enum>(A)</enum><text>minimizes conflict with—</text> <clause id="HDB3C825887634D1D99CE6C1B3FCBE3C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the uses in effect before the date of the enactment of this Act with respect to any trail or road that is part of that accessible trail;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H45AFD70CA74948B589C74EDCA217860E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>multiple-use areas where biking, hiking, horseback riding, off-highway vehicle recreation, or use by pack and saddle stock are existing uses on the date of the enactment of this Act; or</text></clause> <clause id="H2E64CB214AF74838858F18533F73CD26"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the purposes for which any trail is established under the National Trails System Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1241">16 U.S.C. 1241 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8CA830A78D5F43F6AE3D5370B46D9AE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>complies with all applicable land use and management plans of the Federal recreational lands and waters on which the accessible trail is located.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E31622C3A8745B2A8D04261C7745B24"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Reports</header> <subparagraph id="H7BEC69E96EBE49459560E64A7E6D1741"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Interim report</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned, in partnership with stakeholders and other interested organizations, shall prepare and publish an interim report that lists the accessible trails developed under this subsection during the previous 3 years.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBF1F55FB99094079AFA039F8CC7C1AFE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned, in partnership with stakeholders and other interested organizations, shall prepare and publish a final report that lists the accessible trails developed under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBD085A78145843218AC9FF6CB7CF4109"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Accessible recreation opportunities</header> <paragraph id="HF47BD727060646DAA6B09FF52FEBFE7B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned shall select a location to develop at least 2 new accessible recreation opportunities—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5CE1C4ADD1634FA7A72505CA29F64DB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>on National Forest System lands in each region of the Forest Service;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC8EFAB1BF17640B785FCF3C43D2C109A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on land managed by the National Park Service in each region of the National Park Service;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0D39F603666545BD8E664EBF80F00341"><enum>(C)</enum><text>on land managed by the Bureau of Land Management in each region of the Bureau of Land Management; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H53416CB4110D494A81D2DE2EC488A1D5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>on land managed by the United States Fish and Wildlife Service in each region of the United States Fish and Wildlife Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA55A462030A450FA6CCA257936E9401"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Development</header><text>In developing an accessible recreation opportunity under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned—</text> <subparagraph id="H5A295D4DEA9545F1AE9C5964F79240C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may—</text> 
<clause id="HACE98E9CC73B4AEF953500E24E7BAF52"><enum>(i)</enum><text>create a new accessible recreation opportunity; or</text></clause> <clause id="H537ADD24D8CF4C2AAAA75F58372E772F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>modify an existing recreation opportunity into an accessible recreation opportunity; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAA31B95B04E44C20B88609ABF7657C9F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall—</text> <clause id="H58EF8D405AAF40F2A2FE9E7DE6FC3BCF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consult with stakeholders with respect to the feasibility and resources necessary for completing the accessible recreation opportunity;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H8045E61416B14C9AA4B72E3D081E8F26"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure the accessible recreation opportunity complies with the Architectural Barriers Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4151">42 U.S.C. 4151 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></clause> <clause id="H10A5465778A3492E886F4A6535F50826"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, ensure that outdoor constructed features supporting the accessible recreation opportunity, including parking spaces and restroom facilities, meet the requirements of the Architectural Barriers Act of 1968.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC994E86D2F204F769271EF14F186E509"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Accessible recreation opportunities</header><text>The accessible recreation opportunities developed under paragraph (1) may include improving accessibility or access to—</text> <subparagraph id="H734183C7BB7949639EDA3D4978B7EBF1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>camp shelters, camping facilities, and camping units;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H61EACB18F1044CAF8D54A5A5956F86A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>hunting, fishing, shooting, or archery ranges or locations;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5FF4EC58AC164E999E3598AA5D1ED154"><enum>(C)</enum><text>snow activities, including skiing and snowboarding;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1B786CCE579740C48ECE8B075A88AEE6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>water activities, including kayaking, paddling, canoeing, and boat launch ramps;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1297554A5F884FCBADEE912A18D4A5DE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>rock climbing;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7079D1DA21E541BD9B6E7DD41D40306C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>biking;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA6DFE0D8418F495B86149FB19FB7776B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>off-highway vehicle recreation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBA07BEECE23E4E0E83B84E544FDB7F03"><enum>(H)</enum><text>picnic facilities and picnic units;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95205278922348F7A45CAD0C6AB128F0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>outdoor constructed features; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCCF762B806444E11876CE1F060B7E4EE"><enum>(J)</enum><text>any other new or existing recreation opportunities identified in consultation with stakeholders under paragraph (2)(B) and consistent with the applicable land management plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H23E624C168C64E1695E51B1F891AEE1A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Completion</header><text>Not later than 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned, in coordination with stakeholders consulted with under paragraph (2), shall complete each accessible recreation opportunity developed under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9CFCB75813E544C8A7E5DF80800BCEB6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Maps, signage, and promotional materials</header><text>For each accessible recreation opportunity developed under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H5A572B9AC8714A6BAB6C641885045B21"><enum>(A)</enum><text>publish and distribute maps and install signage, consistent with Architectural Barriers Act accessibility guidelines; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1CBEC994438749BBA71161636A219256"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate with stakeholders to leverage any non-Federal resources necessary for the development, stewardship, completion, or promotion of the accessible trail.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4EADCD3012CE4785B24A6F958C3DAEFC"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Conflict avoidance with other uses</header><text>In developing each accessible recreation opportunity under paragraph (1), the Secretary concerned shall ensure that the accessible recreation opportunity—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9B8FD8F98A834DFE9CBB743281B5E3F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>minimizes conflict with—</text> <clause id="H98031818CABA4EDC8B46675FB2039D88"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the uses in effect before the date of the enactment of this Act with respect to any Federal recreational lands and waters on which the accessible recreation opportunity is located; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H59287D534FCB4D1DAA2EA8D3F6AF9F99"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>multiple-use areas in existence on the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HECD63524CAF44F8A9727670EDA4592FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>complies with all applicable land use and management plans of the Federal recreational lands and waters on which the accessible recreational opportunity is located.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HABA3C93F42864960A0D3A5DD1FA4CDD7"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Reports</header> 
<subparagraph id="H9759364833F9455391E3CE5FC3997112"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Interim report</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned, in partnership with stakeholders and other interested organizations, shall prepare and publish an interim report that lists the accessible trails developed under this subsection during the previous 3 years.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC1E9215E216F427FAA934A5A0F5D989A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary concerned, in partnership with stakeholders and other interested organizations, shall prepare and publish a final report that lists the accessible trails developed under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H09F1B102FC434C9187496907DC04BC69"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Assistive technology</header><text>In carrying out this section, the Secretary concerned may enter into partnerships, contracts, or agreements with other Federal, State, Tribal, local, or private entities, including existing outfitting and guiding services, to make assistive technology available on Federal recreational lands and waters.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H892EF4DFC04148CFAE52879386C479CB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text>Nothing in the Act shall be construed to create any conflicting standards with the Architectural Barriers Act of 1968 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4151">42 U.S.C. 4151 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H7022F98D279445088693CD76958A63A6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Promotion of outdoor recreation for military service members and veterans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary concerned, in coordination with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense, shall develop educational and public awareness materials to disseminate to members of the Armed Forces and veterans, including through Transition Assistance Program classes, on—</text> <paragraph id="H15714EEBEC074A5988D86B70DDAA7E40"><enum>(1)</enum><text>opportunities for members of the Armed Forces and veterans to access Federal recreational lands and waters free of charge under section 805 of the Federal Lands Recreation Enhancement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6804">16 U.S.C. 6804</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3F9DE95159FE4823AC5AAA918D5A60C7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the availability and location of accessible trails, including new accessible trails developed and completed under section 2(a);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H68E3B6672BAF480995F2DC5450F1325A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the availability and location of accessible recreation opportunities, including new accessible recreation opportunities developed and completed under section 2(b);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1C0C22F998DD4E9AB46619EDA09796F9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>assistive technology assistance pursuant to section 1151(c) of title 38, United States Code;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1E1B7C9FD88846F68592735C818CF7C1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>outdoor-related volunteer and wellness programs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5AB8CD73FAE44C67B3012387EA063F8A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the benefits of outdoor recreation for physical and mental health;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA48FB3800EBB429592054B9D6301B8E7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>resources to access guided outdoor trips and other outdoor programs connected to the Department of Defense, the Department of Veterans Affairs, the Department of the Interior, or the Department of Agriculture; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H82C0E6AAA058432689EC0686FEF6BF1C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>programs and jobs focused on continuing national service such as Public Land Corps, AmeriCorps, and conservation corps programs.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H7FF0284EED324138AF32A93AC7456C48"><enum>4.</enum><header>Military Veterans Outdoor Recreation Liaisons</header> <subsection id="H777A4C16C30D4A498480EBC148586B39"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretaries and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall each establish within their Departments the position of Military Veterans Outdoor Recreation Liaison.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H245BCA08925B4DFD9E651386F3146D2A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Military Veterans Outdoor Recreation Liaison shall—</text> <paragraph id="HADF375768BF843C8861120A454BA20F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coordinate the implementation of this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5D951CCEF3B8485BBD9A36675485018F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">implement recommendations identified by the Task Force on Outdoor Recreation for Veterans established under section 203 of the Veterans Comprehensive Prevention, Access to Care, and Treatment Act of 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/214">Public Law 116–214</external-xref>), including recommendations related to—</text> <subparagraph id="H966D943D436843C5B31B4C183278F311"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying new opportunities to formalize coordination between the Department of Veterans Affairs, Department of Agriculture, Department of the Interior, and partner organizations regarding the use of Federal recreational lands and waters for facilitating health and wellness for veterans;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H920E615ACA2846919AF34B3F0EACF8F3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>addressing identified barriers that exist to providing veterans with opportunities to augment the delivery of services for health and wellness through the use of outdoor recreation on Federal recreational lands and waters; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H62B4DEE6E75D4769969BA37CBFAD226D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>facilitating the use of Federal recreational lands and waters for promoting wellness and facilitating the delivery of health care and therapeutic interventions for veterans;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA1F2F869E32E4D758CDB1C43603A6524"><enum>(3)</enum><text>coordinate with Military Veterans Outdoor Recreation Liaisons at other Federal agencies and veterans organizations; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCCFFEFC926844D9B990846360D5963E3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>promote outdoor recreation experiences for veterans on Federal recreational lands and waters through new and innovative approaches.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2962051EC1394F19BD86C3459745F901"><enum>5.</enum><header>Partnerships to promote military and veteran recreation</header> 
<subsection id="HD6DAB2E7467748C5B0E4EC7EF346C7D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary concerned shall seek to enter into partnerships or agreements with State, Tribal, local, or private entities with expertise in outdoor recreation, volunteer, accessibility, and health and wellness programs for members of the Armed Forces or veterans.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2495E29AAE044CAE9903D0B5A61601C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text>As part of a partnership or agreement entered into under subsection (a), the Secretary concerned may host events on Federal recreational lands and waters designed to promote outdoor recreation among members of the Armed Forces and veterans.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFBB758A1301745468A5F19DD949C2274"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Financial and technical assistance</header><text>Under a partnership or agreement entered into pursuant to subsection (a), the Secretary concerned may provide financial or technical assistance to the entity with which the respective Secretary concerned has entered into the partnership or agreement to assist with—</text> <paragraph id="H7490978078944B9B9D06355EF1C55EBD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the planning, development, and execution of events, activities, or programs designed to promote outdoor recreation for members of the Armed Forces or veterans; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC6D1161A42D64A348F6BADFBC4824224"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the acquisition of assistive technology to facilitate improved outdoor recreation opportunities for members of the Armed Forces or veterans.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HAB9F12BD6741427094365CF8B47358EB"><enum>6.</enum><header>National strategy for military and veteran recreation</header> <subsection id="H8853AFE8384641D7AECAAB21B6C5C178"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Strategy</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretaries, acting jointly, shall develop and make public a strategy to increase visits to Federal recreational lands and waters by members of the Armed Forces, veterans, and Gold Star Family members.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H04DA10CD3CC749038EBF0A56061E8086"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A strategy developed under subsection (a)—</text> <paragraph id="H7597012D62BD488B920BE3457E1905C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0FC357EFE4E449E689F4785A6C94BCEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish objectives and quantifiable targets for increasing visits to Federal recreational lands and waters by members of the Armed Forces, veterans, and Gold Star Family members;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAFEBD659205D44349C08F810A041DF95"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include an opportunity for public notice and comment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H113D1F249519469CBE8B64E249A0C59D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>emphasize increased recreation opportunities on Federal recreational lands and waters for members of the Armed Forces, veterans, and Gold Star Family members; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEFDDEE260CE34A5684C6059B4BF8D380"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide the anticipated costs to achieve the objectives and meet the targets established under subparagraph (B); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72A8142486D74574BD98C9676906A3FB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall not establish any preference between similar recreation facilitated by noncommercial or commercial entities.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4AFE7B80405448508590F544B7BF0B4D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Update to strategy</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of the publication of the strategy required under subsection (a), and every 5 years thereafter, the Secretaries shall update the strategy and make public the update.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HC50609429A5041E6A0B2B0576D6E468F"><enum>7.</enum><header>Recreation resource advisory committees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 804(d)(5) of the Federal Lands Recreation Enhancement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6803">16 U.S.C. 6803(d)(5)</external-xref>), is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H0950992903E745AB9BB54C27263AE379"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>11</quote> and inserting <quote>12</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H35108563E1084B72A07A8F971629C704"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D)(ii)—</text> <subparagraph id="H37546C7C3A3A4B088F38B1D4CDB3A340"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Three</quote> and inserting <quote>Four</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H462F8FF28A1C4A669771D57AEB7F3295"><enum>(B)</enum><text>after subclause (III), by inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HB042D040DDDF45D1871E7B0A85FFAC31" style="OLC"> <subclause id="HD79ED43AFBD747A0B4835EFB838668CD"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Veterans organizations, as such term is defined in section 9 of the <short-title>Military and Veterans in Parks Act</short-title>.</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H0E186E13CD834FDB9D0B3DEFC49A9E51"><enum>8.</enum><header>Career and volunteer opportunities for veterans</header> 
<subsection id="HD21D31B0541746DA96EB8566712D511E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Veteran hiring</header><text>The Secretary concerned is strongly encouraged to hire veterans in all positions related to the management of Federal recreational lands and waters.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H62FBDE8740D047579D4E58F53DEFB5FA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Pilot program</header> <paragraph id="H149F120D18F84AA4A1EF7A8506D6EDBA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall establish a pilot program under which veterans are employed by the Federal Government in positions that relate to the conservation and resource management activities of the Department of the Interior.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF1E02C1AB0BF42838209C797F0819FA4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Positions</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H871B552A6D02489894E3A582CCE3E5C5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify vacant positions in the Department of the Interior that are appropriate to fill using the pilot program; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H411D1EFC22524EDD829E9D6E17810E81"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, fill such positions using the pilot program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF2602A5262B74413A201135F2AE60540"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application of civil service laws</header><text>A veteran employed under the pilot program shall be treated as an employee as defined by section 2105 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H20E9A64BF6AF44DC838A95ED3EDB8A5F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Briefings and report</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE7D7193A771E4670AC5736DEB1484ED7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial briefing</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of the Interior and the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training shall jointly provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing on the pilot program under this subsection, which shall include—</text> <clause id="H9EFE4F310C424D96820FD51AA13BBAF7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a description of how the pilot program will be carried out in a manner to reduce the unemployment of veterans; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6425B64B827A496CB4BE2F2B088A1AE9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any recommendations for legislative actions to improve the pilot program.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1BBECF3D160E49A5B9788433535432D5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation briefing</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which the pilot program under subsection (a) commences, the Secretary of the Interior and the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training shall jointly provide to the appropriate congressional committees a briefing on the implementation of the pilot program.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H69E48B3F3D6C4533987C2D329F2FFC2A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which the pilot program under subsection (a) is completed, the Secretary of the Interior and the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Veterans’ Employment and Training shall jointly submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the pilot program that includes the following:</text> <clause id="H4CB10B69E4FC4C869FFD82CA39D00192"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of veterans who applied to participate in the pilot program.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H63E92EE79FD048E9A6E3A1F939393019"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The number of such veterans employed under the pilot program.</text></clause> <clause id="HA1F3556BE0014C898230D2CD404FC85F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The number of veterans identified in clause (ii) who transitioned to full-time positions with the Federal Government after participating in the pilot program.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF6B82E8B334C4EC08D57A91F30C6F923"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Any other information the Secretary and the Assistant Secretary determine appropriate with respect to measuring the effectiveness of the pilot program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0D7705A1BDA4C58AA1C2034BD3D6FC4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The authority to carry out the pilot program under this subsection shall terminate on the date that is 2 years after the date on which the pilot program commences.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA69AE13A58ED4BE69A8BA5315B18C734"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <paragraph id="HC743222291E44925B34A366FA2605CBA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1623FF184B744AE68E4747919047E0B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Veterans’ Affairs and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H188FFFD2902F48B096C19A8957378DC1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Outdoor recreation program attendance</header><text>Each Secretary of a military department is encouraged to allow members of the Armed Forces on active duty status to participate in programs related to environmental stewardship or guided outdoor recreation.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H6D38517118CA45A198925F1B5BF8636E"><enum>9.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H8CCFDE2186AD4D2DB8B39D59AEE01D9B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Accessible trail</header><text>The term <term>accessible trail</term> means a trail that meets the requirements for a trail under the Architectural Barriers Act accessibility guidelines.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE6541FCAC84E42CC9B8E275E0B1EA9FC" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Architectural Barriers Act accessibility guidelines</header><text>The term <term>Architectural Barriers Act accessibility guidelines</term> means the accessibility guidelines set forth in appendices C and D to part 1191 of title 36, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations). </text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HDC6B721347564ABCA4D5CCF87F4D31FF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Assistive technology</header><text>The term <term>assistive technology</term> means any item, piece of equipment, or product system, whether acquired commercially, modified, or customized, that is used to increase, maintain, or improve functional capabilities of individuals with disabilities, particularly with participating in outdoor recreation activities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HED3C737C33B9470F819283A099D63B53"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Federal land management agencies</header><text>The term <term>Federal land management agencies</term> means the National Park Service, the Bureau of Land Management, the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, and the Forest Service. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF50E7CB6B26B4428BC2BDD0523AFA58C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Federal recreational lands and waters</header><text>The term <term>Federal recreational lands and waters</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Federal recreational lands and waters</term> in section 802(5) of the Federal Lands Recreation Enhancement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6801">16 U.S.C. 6801(5)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1F06987EFE2947FE91E304847A3734DB" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Gold Star Family member</header><text>The term <term>Gold Star Family member</term> means an individual described in section 3.3 of Department of Defense Instruction 1348.36.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HFAD617AC34B24084A62B1AA8B6967993" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Outdoor constructed feature</header><text>The term <term>outdoor constructed feature</term> has the meaning given such term in Appendix C to part 1191 of title 36, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H138777BD559049DCB38C1921BDAD5DAE"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretaries</header><text>The term <term>Secretaries</term> means the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Agriculture. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB62C2ED015BE465FA1D9620090C0D69B"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Secretary concerned</header><text>The term <term>Secretary concerned</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5BBF23785ECB4AC58D18912CC9EA4C7E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of the Interior, with respect to lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB8DB7E584F4A487EAF81A27CF5702B6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of Agriculture, with respect to National Forest System lands.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA22944A4D314461588DF86AD70593634"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Veterans organization</header><text>The term <term>veterans organization</term> means a service provider with outdoor recreation experience that serves members of the Armed Forces, veterans, or Gold Star Family members. </text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill> 

