<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H189A265130CF47F4ACE8667E8398B8B0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4333 IH: Safeguarding the Homeland from the Threats Posed by Unmanned Aircraft Systems Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4333</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance the authority granted to the Department of Homeland Security and Department of Justice with respect to unmanned aircraft systems and unmanned aircraft, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9DD26197902E4431A2F5149A42152414" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H7C2396FFE57A40F6BA0CB91C00744F92" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safeguarding the Homeland from the Threats Posed by Unmanned Aircraft Systems Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA329C7832523405C9E50E52F3C15AE89" changed="not-changed"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Homeland Security and Department of Justice Unmanned Aircraft System Detection and Mitigation Enforcement Authority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subtitle A of title II of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/121">6 U.S.C. 121 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by striking section 210G (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/124n">6 U.S.C. 124n</external-xref>) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H9E7E09A2A5C8420FBE95ECF042FE3AE6" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC" changed="not-changed"> 
<section id="H511587E2CD6D4742A1424ACD7EE02920" changed="not-changed"><enum>210G.</enum><header>Protection of certain facilities and assets from unmanned aircraft</header> 
<subsection id="HFD4A83C62C474465AF3097D35DCBD995" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H0654194A8079477BAAA2923A04BF6AA0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>air navigation facility</term> has the meaning given the term in section 40102(a) of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H313A777283A04E179029E2D39C0B7C14" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>airport</term> has the meaning given the term in section 47102 of title 49, United Sates Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H977D9B902EDC4B72AB57FBC8B79C9BDB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>appropriate committees of Congress</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE465B8EAA29C46918A46FCE58B3277C3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8377A29B76284B9DAA1F93DBDDF244E6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security, the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure, the Committee on Oversight and Accountability, the Committee on Energy and Commerce, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8B1DEC8B5B3E4509A4EB42E6C77B31ED" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>budget</term>, with respect to a fiscal year, means the budget for that fiscal year that is submitted to Congress by the President under section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H389EF9EBCF6B47C9AC6BBFDC9BC59394" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The term <term>covered facility or asset</term> means any facility or asset that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H12585A4A06224C16947B0A6907502A36" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is identified as high-risk and a potential target for unlawful unmanned aircraft or unmanned aircraft system activity by the Secretary or the Attorney General, or by the chief executive of the jurisdiction in which a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated pursuant to subsection (d)(2) operates after review and approval of the Secretary or the Attorney General, in coordination with the Secretary of Transportation with respect to potentially impacted airspace, through a risk-based assessment for purposes of this section (except that in the case of the missions described in clauses (i)(II) and (iii)(I) of subparagraph (C), such missions shall be presumed to be for the protection of a facility or asset that is assessed to be high-risk and a potential target for unlawful unmanned aircraft or unmanned aircraft system activity);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF29A7D0C55B74867B2B4F9307320AAE8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is located in the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2585283564084FE3A5856124191A592C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>directly relates to 1 or more—</text> <clause id="H328C526D25E540BDA0D83C090800FAE2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>missions authorized to be performed by the Department, consistent with governing statutes, regulations, and orders issued by the Secretary, pertaining to—</text> 
<subclause id="H29BE2BB3A7B045C98DE06DBC0FF4B47A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>security or protection functions of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, including securing or protecting facilities, aircraft, and vessels, whether moored or underway;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE0B714A21DA34962910200BAC25C4ECC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>United States Secret Service protection operations pursuant to sections 3056(a) and 3056A(a) of title 18, United States Code, and the Presidential Protection Assistance Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/18/3056">18 U.S.C. 3056</external-xref> note);</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3199922C129142F39B7397F99BB9DC5E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>protection of facilities pursuant to section 1315(a) of title 40, United States Code;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H953A5380464A45A59CC9C19F3074584A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>transportation security functions of the Transportation Security Administration; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H42AE3F6CF4D94CB58B97F10964FDEE70" changed="not-changed"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the security or protection functions for facilities, assets, and operations of Homeland Security Investigations;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HCBB6A7FFB2A5497286417B52106924F8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>missions authorized to be performed by the Department of Justice, consistent with governing statutes, regulations, and orders issued by the Attorney General, pertaining to—</text> 
<subclause id="H0E4180111E4C4266BB99E93A35104F8B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>personal protection operations by—</text> <item id="HDC6AEF63C60A4498AA66414DEA5739A1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the Federal Bureau of Investigation as specified in section 533 of title 28, United States Code; or</text></item> 
<item id="H4CA7F5DA4609416EAE187DE097A9D49C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the United States Marshals Service as specified in section 566 of title 28, United States Code;</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="H164B12951AAD4DAC80CF54E384E524D4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>protection of penal, detention, and correctional facilities and operations conducted by the Federal Bureau of Prisons and prisoner operations and transport conducted by the United States Marshals Service;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEF7F8E3B4567459E9C93005969901383" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>protection of the buildings and grounds leased, owned, or operated by or for the Department of Justice, and the provision of security for Federal courts, as specified in section 566 of title 28, United States Code; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6C65F82B669C41CBAE7F13C467681403" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>protection of an airport or air navigation facility;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H16BE2D54BC89410CA48F33DFDAE52007" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>missions authorized to be performed by the Department or the Department of Justice, acting together or separately, consistent with governing statutes, regulations, and orders issued by the Secretary or the Attorney General, respectively, pertaining to—</text> <subclause id="H1C8C5033AF4F4B85BD8C6E935EFB515F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>protection of National Special Security Events and Special Event Assessment Rating events;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HB9468DC610CE4CA3BDCF509B68F2C222" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the provision of support to a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency, upon request of the chief executive officer of the State or territory, to ensure protection of people and property at mass gatherings, that is limited to a specified duration and location, within available resources, and without delegating any authority under this section to State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2593A8600975472EA4E196D51F0FFE1D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>protection of an active Federal law enforcement investigation, emergency response, or security function, that is limited to a specified duration and location; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2B3EF795FF7B423E80A02EA94AFE1EFC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the provision of security or protection support to critical infrastructure owners or operators, for static critical infrastructure facilities and assets upon the request of the owner or operator;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H9EE69D397A3046F7AA3BABDB1CB054B1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>missions authorized to be performed by the United States Coast Guard, including those described in clause (iii) as directed by the Secretary, and as further set forth in section 528 of title 14, United States Code, and consistent with governing statutes, regulations, and orders issued by the Secretary of the Department in which the Coast Guard is operating; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H46C5E00A1A084CA4A9FA464ED8B6D9E0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>responsibilities of State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement agencies designated pursuant to subsection (d)(2) pertaining to—</text> <subclause id="H8C3346843C3742BBB18F1CB90E00EB5F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>protection of National Special Security Events and Special Event Assessment Rating events or other mass gatherings in the jurisdiction of the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HF1FBF2A3157840E79C03AB0CEDD95427" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>protection of critical infrastructure assessed by the Secretary as high-risk for unmanned aircraft systems or unmanned aircraft attack or disruption, including airports in the jurisdiction of the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H93F88EC861B146908E787A788095E0A5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>protection of government buildings, assets, or facilities in the jurisdiction of the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H92E0ACCC048441FD951FC2E966746BF8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>protection of disaster response in the jurisdiction of the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1657527472A54E158E3F5DE94A36C2AC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The term <term>critical infrastructure</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1016(e) of the Critical Infrastructure Protection Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBACA8A63B1804B27A83ECAA417C7C7D2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The terms <quote>electronic communication</quote>, <quote>intercept</quote>, <quote>oral communication</quote>, and <quote>wire communication</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 2510 of title 18, United States Code. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H51E0B8EE4BD44210A34A4C1F518B38D0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The term <term>homeland security or justice budget materials</term>, with respect to a fiscal year, means the materials submitted to Congress by the Secretary and the Attorney General in support of the budget for that fiscal year.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6A9B6D4F72D8467097C58C13EE469E2A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(9)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9594C0028BA14A7B83407A3B1814BB58" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>personnel</term> means—</text> <clause id="HF01EA83F939B4316A8CADD3D82403167" indent="up1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an officer, employee, or contractor of the Department or the Department of Justice, who is authorized to perform duties that include safety, security, or protection of people, facilities, or assets; or </text></clause> 
<clause indent="up1" id="H1AC5F72671B04A409BDB29C6D130E623" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an employee who—</text> <subclause id="H294D35235A6E402996D698D7819A828A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is authorized to perform law enforcement and security functions on behalf of a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated under subsection (d)(2); and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H67A7E0F2D2374BABAEB3903727F54B92" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is trained and certified to perform those duties, including training specific to countering unmanned aircraft threats and mitigating risks in the national airspace, including with respect to protecting privacy and civil liberties. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" id="H79A3341489844E7BB1F5302DF10B8247" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To qualify for use of the authorities described in subsection (b) or (c), respectively, a contractor conducting operations described in those subsections shall—</text> 
<clause id="H6699B354D28A42289BB83F73811F856D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>be directly contracted by the Department or the Department of Justice;</text></clause> <clause id="H766A4270E52F4D868738699BFE314FFE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>operate at a government-owned or government-leased facility or asset;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H74861C9455FC41D1B0F5122510A812B8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>not conduct inherently governmental functions; </text></clause> <clause id="H210954A48A464A0AB802B6D96BF96E16" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>be trained to safeguard privacy and civil liberties; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF7BDCE79A1FF415797765D3AD4110CCF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>be trained and certified by the Department or the Department of Justice to meet the established guidance and regulations of the Department or the Department of Justice, respectively.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" id="HA555416DC96547BBB54AE1B84117AEE7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>For purposes of subsection (c)(1), the term <quote>personnel</quote> includes any officer, employee, or contractor who is authorized to perform duties that include the safety, security, or protection of people, facilities, or assets, of—</text> 
<clause id="H0D611A8C0ED3443CB1A7CC00C77180DC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency; and</text></clause> <clause id="HE25557FB1A4F40EDA3DB77EDFD22B3AF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an owner or operator of an airport or critical infrastructure.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCF88563864194980AF4444A2B2AFE475" changed="not-changed"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The term <term>risk-based assessment</term> means an evaluation of threat information specific to a covered facility or asset and, with respect to potential impacts on the safety and efficiency of the national airspace system and the needs of law enforcement and national security at each covered facility or asset identified by the Secretary or the Attorney General, respectively, of each of the following factors:</text> <subparagraph id="H130455718E5A4F9AAEA3305AA5A5665E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Potential impacts to safety, efficiency, and use of the national airspace system, including potential effects on manned aircraft and unmanned aircraft systems or unmanned aircraft, aviation safety, airport operations, infrastructure, and air navigation services relating to the use of any system or technology for carrying out the actions described in subsection (e)(2).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H07F8E68225704AD48DD85BD6CDDB1406" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Options for mitigating any identified impacts to the national airspace system relating to the use of any system or technology, including minimizing, when possible, the use of any technology that disrupts the transmission of radio or electronic signals, for carrying out the actions described in subsection (e)(2).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H452AEB3F26034E28B47083E325300D6E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Potential consequences of the impacts of any actions taken under subsection (e)(2) to the national airspace system and infrastructure if not mitigated.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD4C80341964F4C928548615DA9920470" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The ability to provide reasonable advance notice to aircraft operators consistent with the safety of the national airspace system and the needs of law enforcement and national security.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H50101570B0394113A5C4439ABBFC9DF2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The setting and character of any covered facility or asset, including—</text> 
<clause id="HFDD5B0550518449695A2EBFF08A909EA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>whether the covered facility or asset is located in a populated area or near other structures;</text></clause> <clause id="H95DE715E9CE8471E88F2947116F5C662" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether the covered facility or asset is open to the public; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HD873EBE51A434F3EA2ACD917666E24E4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>whether the covered facility or asset is used for nongovernmental functions; and </text></clause> <clause id="HAC386B76D92C4703A5FE9FDEF2EB6EFA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>any potential for interference with wireless communications or for injury or damage to persons or property.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF0CD3DF1A85F4B3D8A3EAFAB912E7681" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The setting, character, duration, and national airspace system impacts of National Special Security Events and Special Event Assessment Rating events, to the extent not already discussed in the National Special Security Event and Special Event Assessment Rating nomination process.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCDD97E79D12C44118DA2EC3D4ED0CA8C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Potential consequences to national security, public safety, or law enforcement if threats posed by unmanned aircraft systems or unmanned aircraft are not mitigated or defeated.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA15F81D75EE14047B3C1BF1A21B6B0E1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Civil rights and civil liberties guaranteed by the First and Fourth Amendments to the Constitution of the United States. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H412263BE55964BFE82756EE7B29E6632" changed="not-changed"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The terms <quote>unmanned aircraft</quote> and <quote>unmanned aircraft system</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 44801 of title 49, United States Code. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC9A5F953D9BD4AEAA744BBB8F6F57D48" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority of the Department of Homeland Security and Department of Justice</header><text>Notwithstanding section 46502 of title 49, United States Code, or sections 32, 1030, 1367, and chapters 119 and 206 of title 18, United States Code, the Secretary and the Attorney General may, for their respective Departments, take, and may authorize personnel with assigned duties that include the safety, security, or protection of people, facilities, or assets to take, actions described in subsection (e)(2) that are necessary to detect, identify, monitor, track, and mitigate a credible threat (as defined by the Secretary and the Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation, acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration) that an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft poses to the safety or security of a covered facility or asset.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H643A4128D6E84248BCB98E8333F1C48D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Additional limited authority for detection, identification, monitoring, and tracking</header> <paragraph id="H363A33EB54544E27AF653783E07C6402" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraphs (2) and (3), and notwithstanding sections 1030 and 1367 and chapters 119 and 206 of title 18, United States Code, any State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency, the Department of Justice, the Department, and any owner or operator of an airport or critical infrastructure may authorize personnel, with assigned duties that include the safety, security, or protection of people, facilities, or assets, to use equipment authorized under this subsection to take actions described in subsection (e)(1) that are necessary to detect, identify, monitor, or track an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft within the respective areas of responsibility or jurisdiction of the authorized personnel.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H07C33520B67D4DA79B65ADBD291B0068" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorized equipment</header><text>Equipment authorized for unmanned aircraft system detection, identification, monitoring, or tracking under this subsection shall be limited to systems or technologies—</text> <subparagraph id="H9731BDE1181E45A28D06192A1F0A9491" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>tested and evaluated by the Department or the Department of Justice, including evaluation of any potential counterintelligence or cybersecurity risks;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H662B9C5AC8FE4AC5BD6AAB0AC30CAEB9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that are annually reevaluated for any changes in risks, including counterintelligence and cybersecurity risks;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA28112D0008B4DA0BF02801403941E43" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>determined by the Federal Communications Commission and the National Telecommunications and Information Administration not to adversely impact the use of the communications spectrum; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF76EC7C90FC84B8AB57EF1D54798AEAC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>determined by the Federal Aviation Administration not to adversely impact the use of the aviation spectrum or otherwise adversely impact the national airspace system; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB8FFF2B366AD432095AAB15DA1457404" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>that are included on a list of authorized equipment maintained by the Department, in coordination with the Department of Justice, the Federal Aviation Administration, the Federal Communications Commission, and the National Telecommunications and Information Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFE6CAF36433446AFA072A1E7BBEF47A2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State, local, Tribal, and territorial compliance</header><text>Each State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency or owner or operator of an airport or critical infrastructure acting pursuant to this subsection shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H6460F5D1330A47E087A34E1E0B8B8C0B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prior to any such action, issue a written policy certifying compliance with the privacy protections of subparagraphs (A) through (D) of subsection (j)(2); </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2363BAC603F54F708FE44BFAFC15C9A6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>certify compliance with such policy to the Secretary and the Attorney General annually, and immediately notify the Secretary and Attorney General of any noncompliance with such policy or the privacy protections of subparagraphs (A) through (D) of subsection (j)(2); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3592AECE56184E00B77FDE0D720AD710" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>comply with any additional guidance issued by the Secretary or the Attorney General relating to implementation of this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H47D3D10F5C664E17850C03480AD92043" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to authorize the taking of any action described in subsection (e) other than the actions described in paragraph (1) of that subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7E2CE4EFB80F4AC387EF865FBC0974DB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Pilot program for State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement</header> <paragraph id="HACD8777768CC4FF9B58E4BCD1E79765D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary and the Attorney General may carry out a pilot program to evaluate the potential benefits of State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement agencies taking actions that are necessary to mitigate a credible threat (as defined by the Secretary and the Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation, acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration) that an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft poses to the safety or security of a covered facility or asset.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9C77C6FF89044944B1819C374640EFCD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Designation</header> 
<subparagraph id="HCDBF53927EBF4DADA4DCECE03106E862" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary or the Attorney General, with the concurrence of the Secretary of Transportation (acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration), may, under the pilot program established under paragraph (1), designate 1 or more State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agencies approved by the respective chief executive officer of the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency to engage in the activities authorized in paragraph (4) under the direct oversight of the Department or the Department of Justice, in carrying out the responsibilities authorized under subsection (a)(5)(C)(v). </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAB8CFE721622481280D2F541FC7D6F10" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Designation process</header> <clause id="H5888ADE697EC40F185FB01C7AA1137FB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Number of agencies and duration</header><text>On and after the date that is 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Safeguarding the Homeland from the Threats Posed by Unmanned Aircraft Systems Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary and the Attorney General, pursuant to subparagraph (A), may designate a combined total of not more than 12 State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement agencies for participation in the pilot program, and may designate 12 additional State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement agencies each year thereafter, provided that not more than 60 State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement agencies in total may be designated during the 5-year period of the pilot program.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H50DDE0379E1E464F85C2D583A117999D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Revocation</header><text>The Secretary and the Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation (acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration)— </text> <subclause id="H27668C5157814C709CD6FF3E5549E4CF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>may revoke a designation under subparagraph (A) if the Secretary, Attorney General, and Secretary of Transportation (acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration) concur in the revocation; and </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HBE62E51028D94B79BBE34512E25C0721" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shall revoke a designation under subparagraph (A) if the Secretary, the Attorney General, or the Secretary of Transportation (acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration) withdraws concurrence.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4B4455950F5F4C25ABF00AB959C91E92" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Termination of pilot program</header> <subparagraph id="HA3439EA6D7494B53B28247B0948AAE47" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The authority to designate an agency for inclusion in the pilot program established under this subsection shall terminate 5 years after the date that is 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Safeguarding the Homeland from the Threats Posed by Unmanned Aircraft Systems Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF1D357BEC58845EBA96E2CBD9AF13324" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Authority of pilot program agencies</header><text>The authority of an agency designated under the pilot program established under this subsection to exercise any of the authorities granted under the pilot program shall terminate not later than 6 years after the date that is 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Safeguarding the Homeland from the Threats Posed by Unmanned Aircraft Systems Act of 2023</short-title>, or upon revocation pursuant to paragraph (2)(B)(ii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H188079394A2342A692F41E69518C093A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>Notwithstanding section 46502 of title 49, United States Code, or sections 32, 1030, 1367 and chapters 119 and 206 of title 18, United States Code, any State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated pursuant to paragraph (2) may authorize personnel with assigned duties that include the safety, security, or protection of people, facilities, or assets to take such actions as are described in subsection (e)(2) that are necessary to detect, identify, monitor, track, or mitigate a credible threat (as defined by the Secretary and the Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation, acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration) that an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft poses to the safety or security of a covered facility or asset in carrying out the responsibilities authorized under subsection (a)(5)(C)(v). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAAAF88F99D4F4B7AA76E7711A0EA691B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Exemption</header> 
<subparagraph id="H8A3B3D9591274192AB470C1909BC69F5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the Chair of the Federal Communications Commission, in consultation with the Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration, shall implement a process for considering the exemption of 1 or more law enforcement agencies designated under paragraph (2), or any station operated by the agency, from any provision of title III of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/151">47 U.S.C. 151 et seq.</external-xref>) to the extent that the designated law enforcement agency takes such actions as are described in subsection (e)(2) and may establish conditions or requirements for such exemption. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE723F7B551814ABBA85DC686826FCB0D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The Chair of the Federal Communications Commission, in consultation with the Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration, may grant an exemption under subparagraph (A) only if the Chair of the Federal Communications Commission in consultation with the Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration finds that the grant of an exemption—</text> 
<clause id="HFFE450995C8F470F80E4065F8DEA4F79" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is necessary to achieve the purposes of this subsection; and </text></clause> <clause id="H135E50779B344D2D866B36888EAEA5B9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will serve the public interest. </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H97F172845B964FF096E0041B1E4C320F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Revocation</header><text>Any exemption granted under subparagraph (A) shall terminate automatically if the designation granted to the law enforcement agency under paragraph (2)(A) is revoked by the Secretary or the Attorney General under paragraph (2)(B)(ii) or is terminated under paragraph (3)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD852EC6296414728BCCA82CA192FC6BB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date on which the first law enforcement agency is designated under paragraph (2), and annually thereafter for the duration of the pilot program, the Secretary and the Attorney General shall inform the appropriate committees of Congress in writing of the use by any State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency of any authority granted pursuant to paragraph (4), including a description of any privacy or civil liberties complaints known to the Secretary or Attorney General in connection with the use of that authority by the designated agencies.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H729DE8348AF546E98FBE15F0C9E29F37" changed="not-changed"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Restrictions</header><text>Any entity acting pursuant to the authorities granted under this subsection—</text> <subparagraph id="H9C1A924652CE4382A4977B5B8B00E147" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may do so only using equipment authorized by the Department, in coordination with the Department of Justice, the Federal Communications Commission, the National Telecommunications and Information Administration, and the Department of Transportation (acting through the Federal Aviation Administration) according to the criteria described in subsection (c)(2);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE227A7CC6BC844D39EA0161C7308320C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall, prior to any such action, issue a written policy certifying compliance with the privacy protections of subparagraphs (A) through (D) of subsection (j)(2); </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0A911A0098C24BFA98DF84C9BBB4F44C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall ensure that all personnel undertaking any actions listed under this subsection are properly trained in accordance with the criteria that the Secretary and Attorney General shall collectively establish, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, the Chair of the Federal Communications Commission, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information, and the Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H701CE3AD89DB497C8C4B4CDFEC3D3753" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall comply with any additional guidance relating to compliance with this subsection issued by the Secretary or Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H185F366099D34EF384726FF48EC76648" changed="not-changed"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Actions described</header> <paragraph id="H053171242F5D4F0EA681021FCF4FC400" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The actions authorized under subsection (c) that may be taken by a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency, the Department, the Department of Justice, and any owner or operator of an airport or critical infrastructure, are limited to actions during the operation of an unmanned aircraft system, to detect, identify, monitor, and track the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft, without prior consent, including by means of intercept or other access of a wire communication, an oral communication, or an electronic communication used to control the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA71FAD6992043C99C441C7A221FBCD5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>The actions authorized in subsections (b) and (d)(4) are the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H0937A0D4747C41F9BE228585E6A05CA3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>During the operation of the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft, detect, identify, monitor, and track the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft, without prior consent, including by means of intercept or other access of a wire communication, an oral communication, or an electronic communication used to control the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC1C40DB182B541A6BE4ACC0CAC8ED1B5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Warn the operator of the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft, including by passive or active, and direct or indirect, physical, electronic, radio, and electromagnetic means.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2BF98AED36E84849892BEBD7141255AA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Disrupt control of the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft, without prior consent of the operator of the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft, including by disabling the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft by intercepting, interfering, or causing interference with wire, oral, electronic, or radio communications used to control the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD2A02A81DB3F401BA09FAB7B3BB0314B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Seize or exercise control of the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H91D1B65A5B0D494C831D3AB25978FBE1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Seize or otherwise confiscate the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCB3A56DDD825483CB3C8CD8179D98858" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Use reasonable force, if necessary, to disable, damage, or destroy the unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3BEA3E6984D54D5CB7B47324DE926218" changed="not-changed"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Research, testing, training, and evaluation</header> <paragraph id="HA5CDC2FD3635466181998E611DE7B542" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header> <subparagraph id="HB3E6B50565234B0B8339380026564C8B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 46502 of title 49, United States Code, or any provision of title 18, United States Code, the Secretary, the Attorney General, and the heads of the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agencies designated pursuant to subsection (d)(2) shall conduct research, testing, and training on, and evaluation of, any equipment, including any electronic equipment, to determine the capability and utility of the equipment prior to the use of the equipment in carrying out any action described in subsection (e). </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H893207C25EF74154AD30A2FD0C19EA18" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>Personnel and contractors who do not have duties that include the safety, security, or protection of people, facilities, or assets may engage in research, testing, training, and evaluation activities pursuant to subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7AA4E9C634D49A2B715291BA4E45FE1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training of Federal, State, local, territorial, and tribal law enforcement personnel</header><text>The Attorney General, acting through the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, may— </text> 
<subparagraph id="H451429482EA14A70B7D89B6B7761D2A8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide training relating to measures to mitigate a credible threat that an unmanned aircraft or unmanned aircraft system poses to the safety or security of a covered facility or asset to any personnel who are authorized to take such measures, including personnel authorized to take the actions described in subsection (e); and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBF9A8A07BD57401F987B40C558B704B7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish or designate 1 or more facilities or training centers for the purpose described in subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8D7050C1267D40B4BEAADD8038A3999D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination for research, testing, training, and evaluation</header> 
<subparagraph id="H724806753F8D496BA5AC18581CBD8157" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, the Attorney General, and the heads of the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agencies designated pursuant to subsection (d)(2) shall coordinate procedures governing research, testing, training, and evaluation to carry out any provision under this subsection with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration before initiating such activity in order that the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration may ensure the activity does not adversely impact or interfere with safe airport operations, navigation, air traffic services, or the safe and efficient operation of the national airspace system. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H870B3EE7892C477092071EC679D43DF4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional requirement</header><text>Each head of a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated pursuant to subsection (d)(2) shall coordinate the procedures governing research, testing, training, and evaluation of the law enforcement agency through the Secretary and the Attorney General, in coordination with the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H40477E702F244A17AE18AC0BE5D97CD5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Forfeiture</header><text>Any unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft that is lawfully seized by the Secretary or the Attorney General pursuant to subsection (b) is subject to forfeiture to the United States pursuant to the provisions of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/46">chapter 46</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HD5C4F416AE52418398497D461633918A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>The Secretary, the Attorney General, and the Secretary of Transportation— </text> 
<paragraph id="H79278FF174AA4B3CB4B271BAD7BF3084" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may prescribe regulations and shall issue guidance in the respective areas of each Secretary or the Attorney General to carry out this section; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1029853E82AC4518B4FF18204800D4BA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in developing regulations and guidance described in paragraph (1), shall consult the Chair of the Federal Communications Commission, the Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration, and the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9EBE6B0EB21E4058A5049590786825C2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Coordination</header> 
<paragraph id="H63234D425BB74B31922EC2ED47B3A71F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary and the Attorney General shall coordinate with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration before carrying out any action authorized under this section in order that the Administrator may ensure the action does not adversely impact or interfere with— </text> <subparagraph id="H63ACC00DFD2242258D7B2FFEDEC1C4EE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>safe airport operations;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9BEA10E57F7F475BB7F81D2C3A46FE2F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>navigation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H90345596F251449EAC85AFF75BCC732A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>air traffic services; or </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC6D14F7DC79D4406B163DD129DB3E1C3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the safe and efficient operation of the national airspace system.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5F002EE62B5A4EC78FB753E7060DA45A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>Before issuing any guidance, or otherwise implementing this section, the Secretary or the Attorney General shall each coordinate with—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD83CB982549A47008AA0A2D5236F4DEA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of Transportation in order that the Secretary of Transportation may ensure the guidance or implementation does not adversely impact or interfere with any critical infrastructure relating to transportation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBA57001CDBBC453D9E0AFE864FC592D3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration in order that the Administrator may ensure the guidance or implementation does not adversely impact or interfere with—</text> 
<clause id="H2921086971584838A3B4E6F965196AA3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>safe airport operations; </text></clause> <clause id="HD650537B8C4048A6BCCD8434C24E4FD8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>navigation; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H7219B2EA59DA446486C838860900BD5D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>air traffic services; or </text></clause> <clause id="H9E0F0178F20A409D9AD2B4E5D4561B5B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the safe and efficient operation of the national airspace system.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB27178B55DE94F7184A5627D40535CCD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination with the FAA</header><text>The Secretary and the Attorney General shall coordinate the development of their respective guidance under subsection (h) with the Secretary of Transportation (acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9456B1806EFC4FA79F78ECE85B138C46" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Coordination with the Department of Transportation and National Telecommunications and Information Administration</header><text>The Secretary and the Attorney General, and the heads of any State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agencies designated pursuant to subsection (d)(2), through the Secretary and the Attorney General, shall coordinate the development for their respective departments or agencies of the actions described in subsection (e) with the Secretary of Transportation (acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration), the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information, and the Administrator of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB2956578E5584C2B9B14E145E28D94C1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State, local, Tribal, and territorial implementation</header><text>Prior to taking any action authorized under subsection (d)(4), each head of a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated under subsection (d)(2) shall coordinate, through the Secretary and the Attorney General—</text> <subparagraph id="HC6577AAA002149A5A9DA79E1EF8F744D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with the Secretary of Transportation in order that the Administrators of non-aviation modes of the Department of Transportation may evaluate whether the action may have adverse impacts on critical infrastructure relating to non-aviation transportation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H04AEB10D8C1E44FA83DDF33A4D92A847" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration in order that the Administrator may ensure the action will not adversely impact or interfere with— </text> <clause id="H3EDE70C785BF438CB8287F18A7ADE272" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>safe airport operations; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HCB2C7C1434F1499EB5C6D6642996049F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>navigation; </text></clause> <clause id="HE11B0CF5420747BBA090DC967E5F2959" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>air traffic services; or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H6900A3EEFE4C49C79A1B3C56B7A0C1C7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the safe and efficient operation of the national airspace system; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H037B5E24F5D64F0EAC861D3314638414" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to allow the Department and the Department of Justice to ensure that any action authorized by this section is consistent with Federal law enforcement or in the interest of national security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC1075E72EAB441DEA3A3A181BEFA3DE7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Privacy protection</header> 
<paragraph id="HDD81DA3985C84FB5B89EDA2952EA6E20" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any regulation or guidance issued to carry out an action under subsection (e) by the Secretary or the Attorney General shall ensure for the Department or the Department of Justice, respectively, that—</text> <subparagraph id="H2523D637B2994346BF694BCE33D6F6AE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the interception of, acquisition of, access to, maintenance of, or use of any communication to or from an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft under this section is conducted in a manner consistent with the First and Fourth Amendments to the Constitution of the United States and any applicable provision of Federal law;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H83F48744B69848AFAB06BB8CFF045346" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any communication to or from an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft are intercepted or acquired only to the extent necessary to support an action described in subsection (e);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB46DCA43680D45A7B3DDDED6EC1FCD53" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any record of a communication described in subparagraph (B) is maintained only for as long as necessary, and in no event for more than 180 days, unless the Secretary or the Attorney General, as applicable, determines that maintenance of the record is— </text> 
<clause id="HE2489B7880F84CDBA10D30D304DAEECE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>required under Federal law; </text></clause> <clause id="H4150A9C8232F42A78AE4DD691603BD53" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>necessary for the purpose of litigation; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HED81A103E3224C549C7EE1DBAB1F432B" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>necessary to investigate or prosecute a violation of law, including by—</text> <subclause id="H4B73B4A3A77345AA88A0907D8EEC4B49" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>directly supporting an ongoing security operation; or </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9F1D21A6A2E64886964EA816C8755CB9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>protecting against dangerous or unauthorized activity by unmanned aircraft systems or unmanned aircraft; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2DBB29145F0E48DFABD7FA5F219EE242" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a communication described in subparagraph (B) is not disclosed to any person not employed or contracted by the Department or the Department of Justice unless the disclosure—</text> 
<clause id="H03A9C435101A45F7979947661C485430" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is necessary to investigate or prosecute a violation of law;</text></clause> <clause id="H120FFC94DB304044A2E760315B45A7CD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will support—</text> 
<subclause id="H9E9CB3FB17484746A2C5EB235555E647" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Department of Defense; </text></subclause> <subclause id="H69CA5FEC47AB45849560E7E915859B0E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a Federal law enforcement, intelligence, or security agency; </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H4A5F8A0F72A3464B8F1D94DB7AE86C70" changed="not-changed"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency; or </text></subclause> <subclause id="HA4117B2DD10F411EBFE5FC950FDB8CDF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>another relevant entity or person if the entity or person is engaged in a security or protection operation;</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H9621932F307B4D3CB1AE27E1CD4BF5F6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is necessary to support a department or agency listed in clause (ii) in investigating or prosecuting a violation of law;</text></clause> <clause id="HEBEBD5B385E440A3A93996C8077A612E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>will support the enforcement activities of a Federal regulatory agency relating to a criminal or civil investigation of, or any regulatory, statutory, or other enforcement action relating to, an action described in subsection (e);</text></clause> 
<clause id="HED29913479EB452EB832F1134750D56D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>is between the Department and the Department of Justice in the course of a security or protection operation of either department or a joint operation of those departments; or</text></clause> <clause id="HEF48FA00A693495E8EF9465D49566845" changed="not-changed"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>is otherwise required by law.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3C9E4310BE1246848886F9C1F343FBB3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Local privacy protection</header><text>In exercising any authority described in subsection (c) or (d), a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated under subsection (d)(2) or owner or operator of an airport or critical infrastructure shall ensure that—</text> <subparagraph id="HE4B0EA150AB24E0DBD058306692FBBDA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the interception of, acquisition of, access to, maintenance of, or use of communications to or from an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft under this section is conducted in a manner consistent with— </text> 
<clause id="H0FC5AC36DFF648CC818F772498D611EA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the First and Fourth Amendments to the Constitution of the United States; and </text></clause> <clause id="HA89BADA1EB144ABF8245BF63F98233DC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>applicable provisions of Federal law, and where required, State, local, Tribal, and territorial law;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1374DFFA2B75441E9B40CB86E6CC9A2F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any communication to or from an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft is intercepted or acquired only to the extent necessary to support an action described in subsection (e);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H20EFF513F7194BD491224E1F262685EE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any record of a communication described in subparagraph (B) is maintained only for as long as necessary, and in no event for more than 180 days, unless the Secretary, the Attorney General, or the head of a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated under subsection (d)(2) determines that maintenance of the record is— </text> 
<clause id="H6FE408E267E3426C88FEA847AE3A5074" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>required to be maintained under Federal, State, local, Tribal, or territorial law; </text></clause> <clause id="H0F0C1F0ED9FE4BE58134D53ADF015F73" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>necessary for the purpose of any litigation; or </text></clause> 
<clause id="H637C3DB22A944CE080E4FA8C746F76A5" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>necessary to investigate or prosecute a violation of law, including by—</text> <subclause id="H018B08D4F94E4168A601684B88246521" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>directly supporting an ongoing security or protection operation; or </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H1A846382E8274A70A0DF92C5FFCE908C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>protecting against dangerous or unauthorized activity by an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE09B1BE3D38A4E268D7865863CD0158D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the communication is not disclosed outside the agency or entity unless the disclosure—</text> 
<clause id="H0BBF1AA908F94E8DA50971EA172C87A7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is necessary to investigate or prosecute a violation of law;</text></clause> <clause id="HB658283AD9F040469C6F2A218E7C6FD8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>would support the Department of Defense, a Federal law enforcement, intelligence, or security agency, or a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC5B932927F2A4696BD4A5A206E05778D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>would support the enforcement activities of a Federal regulatory agency in connection with a criminal or civil investigation of, or any regulatory, statutory, or other enforcement action relating to, an action described in subsection (e);</text></clause> <clause id="H67653B4E310C4E119AD58D0F560CE1BE" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>is to the Department or the Department of Justice in the course of a security or protection operation of either the Department or the Department of Justice, or a joint operation of the Department and Department of Justice; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H4637FF775D6A4B1983FC95C8E47DD72E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>is otherwise required by law.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H555C4D287F4940CCA536268D97FEACE6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Budget</header> <paragraph id="HFF9E832E145740CDA92B60A288C4ACB7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary and the Attorney General shall submit to Congress, as a part of the homeland security or justice budget materials for each fiscal year after fiscal year 2024, a consolidated funding display that identifies the funding source for the actions described in subsection (e) within the Department and the Department of Justice. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H543C34B39F44483A8A0A179510F64B3C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Classification</header><text>Each funding display submitted under paragraph (1) shall be in unclassified form but may contain a classified annex.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HABDC8ADEE94A4E84B509B6AA68E06891" changed="not-changed"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Public disclosures</header> <paragraph id="H04DE075ACFAE4389B22588C2B05CFF13" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any provision of State, local, Tribal, or territorial law, information shall be governed by the disclosure obligations set forth in section 552 of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>), if the information relates to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8162BD0CBB7047AE9635AD75BE6BE6D2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any capability, limitation, or sensitive detail of the operation of any technology used to carry out an action described in subsection (e)(1) of this section; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF5B2CE92504744ACB08DD04A2BEDEA15" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an operational procedure or protocol used to carry out this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H431169E01EA84F1BBB01DC297924A91C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State, local, Tribal, or territorial agency use</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD5F2F8C2494F4048B16FF0BB034816EF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Control</header><text>Information described in paragraph (1) that is obtained by a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency from a Federal agency under this section—</text> <clause id="H082913AD7F2142F999B2CE68618ACCD9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall remain subject to the control of the Federal agency, notwithstanding that the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency has the information described in paragraph (1) in the possession of the State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="HF728D10AE2C34C8A8E9ED0D34812B968" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not be subject to any State, local, Tribal, or territorial law authorizing or requiring disclosure of the information described in paragraph (1). </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H375656A718AC4477BB7539E19D085CC2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Access</header><text>Any request for public access to information described in paragraph (1) shall be submitted to the originating Federal agency, which shall process the request as required under section 552(a)(3) of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3C6F0696D9724450BE960999566583BD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Assistance and support</header> 
<paragraph id="HA50B102E9C1140A2A78C90532C542CF8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Facilities and services of other agencies and non-Federal entities</header> 
<subparagraph id="H4A4586084E8741B99C766D0616701A35" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary and the Attorney General are authorized to use or accept from any other Federal agency, or any other public or private entity, any supply or service to facilitate or carry out any action described in subsection (e). </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H03983F14352F4A0A8232CD4FC9A29F96" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reimbursement</header><text>In accordance with subparagraph (A), the Secretary and the Attorney General may accept any supply or service with or without reimbursement to the entity providing the supply or service and notwithstanding any provision of law that would prevent the use or acceptance of the supply or service. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA96E9148B65B4E6B9662F499A6DF9D7C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Agreements</header><text>To implement the requirements of subsection (a)(5)(C), the Secretary or the Attorney General may enter into 1 or more agreements with the head of another executive agency or with an appropriate official of a non-Federal public or private agency or entity, as may be necessary and proper to carry out the responsibilities of the Secretary and Attorney General under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H504928AF89F64EF0BB70795172322570" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Mutual support</header> <subparagraph id="H4338F3A797D240A68B2E7249204F5427" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the Secretary and the Attorney General are authorized to provide support or assistance, upon the request of a Federal agency or department conducting— </text> 
<clause id="H575897D3C16D496D95544B264D9B1DAD" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a mission described in subsection (a)(5)(C); </text></clause> <clause id="H42637155B5DF419580299C4078AEE8B3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a mission described in section 130i of title 10, United States Code; or </text></clause> 
<clause id="HE5A9F62EBBF2419EBE5622C999FDA6E1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a mission described in section 4510 of the Atomic Energy Defense Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/2661">50 U.S.C. 2661</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8D0A1655ABEA46F095389FBC944E4513" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Any support or assistance provided by the Secretary or the Attorney General shall only be granted—</text> 
<clause id="H8DA4FB9CCE7F47D9B6FD9D913611BC73" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for the purpose of fulfilling the roles and responsibilities of the Federal agency or department that made the request for the mission for which the request was made;</text></clause> <clause id="HC18ADE617CDB444489EBEC7B12C0CC56" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>when exigent circumstances exist; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H0342176ADB28445BA49A9E8A50A8EC36" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for a specified duration and location;</text></clause> <clause id="HE5272FDA25764BB6989F68F84A381750" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>within available resources;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H29A2F808F3C84DF1828C46CFA458F4B7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(v)</enum><text>on a non-reimbursable basis; and</text></clause> <clause id="H6DF4449A024E4033A9FA5E20AD600F3E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in coordination with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H17104205186B47749CE22E03893224AC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Semiannual briefings and notifications</header> 
<paragraph id="H15E9D9B573B242BB9DBD7493783142BF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On a semiannual basis beginning 180 days after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Safeguarding the Homeland from the Threats Posed by Unmanned Aircraft Systems Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary and the Attorney General shall each provide a briefing to the appropriate committees of Congress on the activities carried out pursuant to this section. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1C775AD7AA174E288E12A8C493AF20D0" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The Secretary and the Attorney General each shall conduct the briefing required under paragraph (1) jointly with the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4E70E9C2C7BF48DCBF62B536C58D93D9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Content</header><text>Each briefing required under paragraph (1) shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="HF8F16AD43BBA4794A43A276B74ECD432" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>policies, programs, and procedures to mitigate or eliminate impacts of activities carried out pursuant to this section to the national airspace system and other critical infrastructure relating to national transportation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H33C5C8897A9F4795B261B11F310D6681" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of—</text> <clause id="HE0C10D7CF4AF4D4BBA0367E7503B1A35" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each instance in which any action described in subsection (e) has been taken, including any instances that may have resulted in harm, damage, or loss to a person or to private property;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H08A2ECB27494411B8782E7D4EF2A3AB6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the guidance, policies, or procedures established by the Secretary or the Attorney General to address privacy, civil rights, and civil liberties issues implicated by the actions permitted under this section, as well as any changes or subsequent efforts by the Secretary or the Attorney General that would significantly affect privacy, civil rights, or civil liberties; </text></clause> <clause id="H6F9CDBE7BAAC42EF9CA46A895B10984A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>options considered and steps taken by the Secretary or the Attorney General to mitigate any identified impacts to the national airspace system relating to the use of any system or technology, including the minimization of the use of any technology that disrupts the transmission of radio or electronic signals, for carrying out the actions described in subsection (e)(2); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA4987EE5A55D425082C30D1C5A1E1746" changed="not-changed"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>each instance in which a communication intercepted or acquired during the course of operations of an unmanned aircraft system or unmanned aircraft was—</text> <subclause id="H77B7A30CA39D4A408A2C85228236876F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(I)</enum><text>held in the possession of the Department or the Department of Justice for more than 180 days; or </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8533EEE91E4843A3BC9CA0CCE80B44CB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(II)</enum><text>shared with any entity other than the Department or the Department of Justice;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H00B247898FE7462A8609F0BA648D97C7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an explanation of how the Secretary, the Attorney General, and the Secretary of Transportation have—</text> 
<clause id="H88CC4B16ACB1451A98D069930A0283B7" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>informed the public as to the possible use of authorities granted under this section; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC1BEDEA6B1B644A1A2586E9A4576FEB8" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>engaged with Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement agencies to implement and use authorities granted under this section;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC9564AFD27114B8BBB857F2B36D59E9C" changed="not-changed"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an assessment of whether any gaps or insufficiencies remain in laws, regulations, and policies that impede the ability of the Federal Government or State, local, Tribal, and territorial governments and owners or operators of critical infrastructure to counter the threat posed by the malicious use of unmanned aircraft systems and unmanned aircraft;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H57BDF2C03206403B919D366A3C2E2AE1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an assessment of efforts to integrate unmanned aircraft system threat assessments within National Special Security Event and Special Event Assessment Rating event planning and protection efforts; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H74710659F8B94B4483DCDCAC9985C753" changed="not-changed"><enum>(F)</enum><text>recommendations to remedy any gaps or insufficiencies described in subparagraph (D), including recommendations relating to necessary changes in law, regulations, or policies;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB44671FAB0934959A2028919EF7F3ECF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a description of the impact of the authorities granted under this section on— </text> 
<clause id="HE99BDA6E27394DC9B794ACB1703837E4" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>lawful operator access to national airspace; and </text></clause> <clause id="HE1AC0CFE370044E081A9BB09C0BBFBB2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>unmanned aircraft systems and unmanned aircraft integration into the national airspace system; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1026B931FE1A4517BF27C7C64E650357" changed="not-changed"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a summary from the Secretary of any data and results obtained pursuant to subsection (r), including an assessment of—</text> <clause id="HD365088FADDE4541B26B4D1AB3D45164" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>how the details of the incident were obtained; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H1B350C615AA64F43ACB3CF182EA15DE2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether the operation involved a violation of Federal Aviation Administration aviation regulations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD78BB4C5F77C4C33BB9B7ECCBB9D54E9" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Unclassified form</header><text>Each briefing required under paragraph (1) shall be in unclassified form but may be accompanied by an additional classified briefing.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H18336458147741E2A8CD6C2FC24706E1" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Notification</header> 
<subparagraph id="H95146E5F634441D2A46028389319EC75" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after an authorized department, agency, or owner or operator of an airport or critical infrastructure deploys any new technology to carry out the actions described in subsection (e), the Secretary and the Attorney General shall, individually or jointly, as appropriate, submit a notification of the deployment to the appropriate committees of Congress. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H22E81F5A6A884403B7D12AB467A843DA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>Each notification submitted pursuant to subparagraph (A) shall include a description of options considered to mitigate any identified impacts to the national airspace system relating to the use of any system or technology, including the minimization of the use of any technology that disrupts the transmission of radio or electronic signals in carrying out the actions described in subsection (e).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H28AA003186C745998C8B1C9DC2A2744A" changed="not-changed"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to—</text> <paragraph id="H25CC6038B9414D76B73BA0CA7E0B4C84" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><text>vest in the Secretary, the Attorney General, or any State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency that is authorized under subsection (c) or designated under subsection (d)(2) any authority of the Secretary of Transportation or the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBE0BAB60BE9E46E5AA44845F3A70E72D" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><text>vest in the Secretary of Transportation, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, or any State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated under subsection (d)(2) any authority of the Secretary or the Attorney General;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD2ECF42B799478498E60044DE3AB684" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><text>vest in the Secretary any authority of the Attorney General;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA091CEF2EC2145CFB755986F7D775033" changed="not-changed"><enum>(4)</enum><text>vest in the Attorney General any authority of the Secretary; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC99C03FFADC747CABD597C14DDE7687E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide a new basis of liability with respect to an officer of a State, local, Tribal, or territorial law enforcement agency designated under subsection (d)(2) or who participates in the protection of a mass gathering identified by the Secretary or Attorney General under subsection (a)(5)(C)(iii)(II), who—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5827A9A5E9A94008BA4C07D50CD143AF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is acting in the official capacity of the individual as an officer; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAA78BC25CA0C4C5FAC0FB06C00DEEF0E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not exercise the authority granted to the Secretary and the Attorney General by this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H91B03849E1E54FC09265EC78728B12C2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(p)</enum><header>Termination</header> 
<paragraph id="H0F26C3E3B6984B9B9D81FD661EDEBBF3" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Termination of additional limited authority for detection, identification, monitoring, and tracking</header><text>The authority to carry out any action authorized under subsection (c), if performed by a non-Federal entity, shall terminate on the date that is 5 years and 6 months after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Safeguarding the Homeland from the Threats Posed by Unmanned Aircraft Systems Act of 2023</short-title> and the authority under the pilot program established under subsection (d) shall terminate as provided for in paragraph (3) of that subsection.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H25324E04F6B34CD28612C97CC7A2AACA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Termination of authorities with respect to covered facilities and assets</header><text>The authority to carry out this section with respect to a covered facility or asset shall terminate on the date that is 7 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Safeguarding the Homeland from the Threats Posed by Unmanned Aircraft Systems Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAF4A76EDA43742F29D563C427B6EA166" changed="not-changed"><enum>(q)</enum><header>Scope of authority</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to provide the Secretary or the Attorney General with any additional authority other than the authorities described in subsections (a)(5)(C)(iii), (b), (c), (d), (f), (m), and (r).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD65139030F6244EA9B5574DB0D284506" changed="not-changed"><enum>(r)</enum><header>United States Government database</header> <paragraph id="H5B36A80E69F3418BA69E0D86B6F7C1B6" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>The Department is authorized to develop a Federal database to enable the transmission of data concerning security-related incidents in the United States involving unmanned aircraft and unmanned aircraft systems between Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement agencies for purposes of conducting analyses of such threats in the United States. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H95C67FAA26AE45E19C63BE433150ABBB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Policies, plans, and procedures</header> 
<subparagraph id="H1658A4577FCE4366A2E301A236001B2F" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Coordination and consultation</header><text>Before implementation of the database developed under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall develop policies, plans, and procedures for the implementation of the database—</text> <clause id="HD25D50531EBB473F8B9EE9EDA3E17D66" changed="not-changed"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in coordination with the Attorney General, the Secretary of Defense, and the Secretary of Transportation (acting through the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H65794B71431A47D99B7E37E6D8043748" changed="not-changed"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in consultation with State, local, Tribal, and territorial law enforcement agency representatives, including representatives of fusion centers.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB2A06FF2F08145008496A39998B93EC2" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>The policies, plans, and procedures developed under subparagraph (A) shall include criteria for Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial reporting of unmanned aircraft systems or unmanned aircraft incidents.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5CFA7B1135E643009533F4DC49954E33" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Data retention</header><text>The policies, plans, and procedures developed under subparagraph (A) shall ensure that data on security-related incidents in the United States involving unmanned aircraft and unmanned aircraft systems that is retained as criminal intelligence information is retained based on the reasonable suspicion standard, as permitted under part 23 of title 28, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

