<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC3F9A26FD78C4927A82C739A36B76FEB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2815 IH: Hong Kong Business Integrity and Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2815</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Commerce to submit to Congress a report on the protection of consumer information in the possession of United States companies operating in Hong Kong and requests issued by the Government of Hong Kong to such companies for consumer information, content takedowns, or law enforcement assistance.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBFFAD587A58F46B6BC8A2464BF63DE52" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H17CB81A95FF649BDAA9322A39FB25E5E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hong Kong Business Integrity and Transparency Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HD5574B632EA048979BAB6D150AE1997B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on requests from Government of Hong Kong to United States companies for consumer information, content takedowns, or law enforcement assistance</header> <subsection id="HD5CD4AC0803E45CDA5798718EFCCAD8C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter, the Secretary of Commerce, in consultation with the heads of other appropriate Federal departments and agencies, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees and make available to the public a report on—</text>
<paragraph id="H69261D64EB7D44C28B3532E2A864B715"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the protection of consumer information in the possession of United States companies operating in Hong Kong; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDBAF70F75C0245A9990A1CF7A5559DAF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>requests issued by the Government of Hong Kong to United States companies operating in Hong Kong for content takedowns or law enforcement assistance.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H27283ED920EF49DF88F309A431CDE576"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall, with respect to the 180-day period preceding the date of submission of the report, include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H57D8807B36EE4C019610EB9CCC102260"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of requests, issued by the Government of Hong Kong to United States companies operating in Hong Kong for consumer information in the possession of such companies, content takedowns, or law enforcement assistance, that were fulfilled and by which companies.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1751138689CC4AE3ADFAE79E0153F928"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An identification of the Hong Kong laws under which such requests were issued.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBD3CF27EB5CF4A938B66446C6B662335"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An identification of any United States consumer protection laws that may have been violated in the case of the fulfillment of such requests by such companies.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HBEE22EF69FD747C8B9666E175BA67DF9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form of report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified index.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB4328A0C6C6B4D26931E27FCD8B57990"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="HCE5A12194B2844B4BACC54E419A1E480"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H68FF58C650104C4580BEE59BF000D996"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation, the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Finance, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H58C058C8069B4005A699B17D6B74A65F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Energy and Commerce, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Financial Services, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H490C84A2EC7C4A9AA8AE99BE37156FDB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Content takedown</header><text>The term <quote>content takedown</quote> means the removal of, disabling of access to, or restriction of access to any material, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9761912F3CCA4D29AFA270B28D195C3B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>material on a website or online service;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H87D6DCB08BB94640B172C16CC85B46B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a software application; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4EDCC88ADA3B434FA52E38F1D8DDB862"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any feature of a software application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

