<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC94796C20C494C5D896EE7129309E000" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3466 IH: To enhance Financial Stability Oversight Council transparency.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3466</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance Financial Stability Oversight Council transparency.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4884427BC4A6496B8E2C006368E55B45" style="OLC"><section id="HF17AC363507B47AABF59E87840DE37B0" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>FSOC transparency</header><subsection id="H507FA02AE6BF4126A1F64FAC7A116688"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Financial Stability Act of 2010</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Financial Stability Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5311">12 U.S.C. 5311 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3813F2B403374E2CB8D5ED7A9923A2EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 111—</text><subparagraph id="H0FA1BBB7D8B74C3490646CB88590D57E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1)—</text><clause id="HA2753F64A22843DDBAE0E68937B91C72"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="HAB3E91BAA93346C98BB171E206D5B070"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and </text></clause><clause id="H849DF213339341159B773DC8EC2CDAEF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H44DF230A896C4EC2B1229BA1EF8C0129" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H9F220C883AF1405ABC64766EA800907F"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an independent member appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, and not of the same political party as the President.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87D0BB70AB064B5B81E418A6912A635D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><clause id="H9C95C4E4F6684487AD967D1AB1AB112D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>independent member</quote> and inserting <quote>independent members</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H4244FF64D3B64CA189AD4CE3904E25A8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text><subclause id="HE7A90302BAF6473588DC8508D09D74F0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in the heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">independent member</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">independent members</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HF0BE449E6BCD4A3B9911E8E39304FB57"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsection (b)(1)(J)</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraph (J) or (K) of subsection (b)(1)</quote>;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60794034013944999ACBACF7CC8C406F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking subsection (d);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4A50BA281814BFCA03C3BEF50074887"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (e) through (j) as subsections (d) through (i), respectively;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4792ED387EE74FBAB8DED42062240E67"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in subsection (d), as so redesignated, by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB64D6A37BCFA4A7EAAD7F285CB18BB6A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H74ED7B2B9A72458590DCD5E5720DDD8E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notice to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chairperson shall notify the chair and ranking members of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking members of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of a meeting at the same time as the meeting participants are notified.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE54127F2B13A4E4F9082BDBD4F23AFD0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in subsection (f), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>, or to any special advisory, technical, or professional committee appointed by the Council, except that, if an advisory, technical, or professional committee has one or more members who are not employees of or affiliated with the United States Government, the Council shall publish a list of the names of the members of such committee</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD111BC12FD99440E9D78925686879662"><enum>(G)</enum><text>in subsection (g), as so redesignated, by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, but if such services, funds, facilities, staff, or other support services are provided with respect to any Council program or activity that has, or is planned to have, duration of greater than 90 days, the Council shall notify Congress of such provision</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC15B9FC8FE904F46A26B0EF9788CC74F"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (i), as so redesignated, by adding at the end the following: <quote>The Council shall report on such detailed employees on a monthly basis to Congress.</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H69076F66500F4A58973C8236E0D3B48C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 112—</text><subparagraph id="HB8514C75FE9341C4B185B59AC0FA80DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(2)—</text><clause id="HEF3732F9DDDA4321A40AE9E9BE2734EB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting after <quote>system</quote> the following: <quote>and only after notifying Congress</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H0865525F9CC7443289D13CFD3C68FB67"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking subparagraphs (D) and (I);</text></clause><clause id="H6E8A9CA3492E419A961FC8FADE6D716F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (E), (F), (G), (H), (J), (K), (L), (M), and (N) as subparagraphs (D) through (L), respectively;</text></clause><clause id="H347274928FA544BABFB5EC9EF214F4CA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>agencies and</quote> and inserting <quote>agencies, Congress, and</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H2B1E59CBE962430988D14A51F694119D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), as so redesignated, by inserting after <quote>to the member agencies</quote> the following: <quote>, the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H912A7176F50540BAA5FE7501E40C9B5C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>may</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HC2F227A87DF54A66A02079F22CF1F2E2"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (H), as so redesignated, by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>, and notify the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of such identifications</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H8EB9D1514A6F41CFB2E567CB6E573E8A"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (I), as so redesignated, by inserting after <quote>primary financial regulatory agencies to apply</quote> the following: <quote>primary financial regulatory agencies, the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate on the costs and benefits of applying</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H131DD03F6A9F48B89F6B1AA416C27AB4"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (J), as so redesignated, by inserting <quote>the Congress and</quote> before <quote>the Commission</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5271A0A364B24F579CD5EA597FB2D6DB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c), by inserting <quote>no later than 60 days</quote> after <quote>hearing,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC784CAEBEB29464C8578A856BDFECECB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><clause id="H48592CB4D7C04EFE8C0342B4395FA44D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subclause id="HAE71AE1A90BF4A49A3AD6C313672321B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>as necessary</quote> and all that follows through <quote>to monitor</quote> and inserting <quote>as necessary to monitor</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H4BB8741D9477496C87F80C469E460491"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a period; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H9910EAFA839A41AD9024B599DC2BE3DB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B);</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HD0D5CDB050D54B2A82677FB89DC97D92"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>and to Congress</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HBD989412478343658123C2CCC15FC3E7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5E51C97BEF8440F98BF481AAC3C1C50F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H8BDBCE75EB714BFB9AA509E424546E25"><enum>(D</enum><header>Congressional notification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Council may not require the submission of periodic and other reports under this paragraph until 30 days after the Council has notified the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of the Council’s intention to require such submission.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H39487DEC7D8046AEAC3EDEEA96640368"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by inserting after <quote>Council may</quote> the following: <quote>, after notifying the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate,</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H2C9999C07C3743F4B183D5C1D39F95DF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(A), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, except that Congress may request any such confidential data, information, or reports</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DEF0261696647048644ED61B9377EA2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in section 113—</text><subparagraph id="H0C0EE1A157CF41FA995C6AB0BC1F661B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(2)—</text><clause id="H26B1221FD8184B12AD1BE4286765E5B4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="HB2366A9FBDA54917B960CB1AFC1C51C8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a period; and</text></clause><clause id="H9B8F7CBD137F4FC7BF6B34D6EBF4EAE4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (K);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5793113A0B3C46AD80EC6BF2C63CA339"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(2)—</text><clause id="H287B79CF94C348A0A923005C97B3D351"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), by adding <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="H3F1CD726910E4C4395B197F4A5B6BD93"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a period; and</text></clause><clause id="H3D62ECF12B954F77994EE4EC7E7151C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (K);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC15BD602C2B2420898196EFFF8C03BD4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking subsection (f);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21C7BA69A3304FA69D82C6C9241A4C4F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (g), (h), and (i) as subsections (f), (g), and (h), respectively;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4196A6C1B8C4C4A85A4451F36F4B99F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in subsection (g), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>subsection (d)(2), (e)(3), or (f)(5)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (d)(2) or (e)(3)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4EB776AC2D74C578F20F1DAADCC8821"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H34E54BCD03C7429D95C10EEA7F01ED45" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H4494D237572C4E0D9D6A1793C67E5AD4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Congressional review</header><paragraph id="H493391372F78494ABE089EBF76B6B1B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>If the Council makes a determination under this section, the Council shall immediately notify Congress of such determination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A322606E6A24F32AC7C0BEBED3A3446"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effectiveness of determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A determination made by the Council under this section—</text><subparagraph id="H60D88AF4909C4556B9C233B59DAF176B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may not take effect until the end of the 60-day period beginning on the date that the Council notifies the Congress of such determination; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F944BCE0BE14DB79C0C7772C55CAE30"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall have no force or effect if disapproved, as provided under this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA660778ED9A4899825B59CEBD2C32E7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Congressional disapproval procedure</header><subparagraph id="H0F8B68F23DBD4A7387E736030D39F24F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Joint resolution defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this paragraph, the term <quote>joint resolution</quote> means only a joint resolution introduced during the 60-day period described under paragraph (2)(A), the matter after the resolving clause of which is as follows: <quote>That Congress disapproves the determination of the Financial Stability Oversight Council submitted in a notification to Congress on ___, and such determination shall have no force or effect.</quote> (The blank space being filled in with the appropriate date.).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H73C4C96A2931438EAF781ABA26B894E7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Treatment in Senate</header><clause id="HB0B93489B03B49DF952A0D2A589F5534"><enum>(i)</enum><text>In the Senate, if the committee to which is referred a joint resolution has not reported such joint resolution (or an identical joint resolution) at the end of the 20-day period beginning on the date Congress is notified of a determination, such committee may be discharged from further consideration of such joint resolution upon a petition supported in writing by 30 Members of the Senate, and such joint resolution shall be placed on the calendar.</text></clause><clause id="H3FAF8618A548422CBEC676069CFD4F41"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the Senate, when the committee to which a joint resolution is referred has reported, or when a committee is discharged (under clause (i)) from further consideration of a joint resolution, it is at any time thereafter in order (even though a previous motion to the same effect has been disagreed to) for a motion to proceed to the consideration of the joint resolution, and all points of order against the joint resolution (and against consideration of the joint resolution) are waived. The motion is not subject to amendment, or to a motion to postpone, or to a motion to proceed to the consideration of other business. A motion to reconsider the vote by which the motion is agreed to or disagreed to shall not be in order. If a motion to proceed to the consideration of the joint resolution is agreed to, the joint resolution shall remain the unfinished business of the Senate until disposed of.</text></clause><clause id="HB2DC337A90E540E29FD1BDD2837FF936"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the Senate, debate on the joint resolution, and on all debatable motions and appeals in connection therewith, shall be limited to not more than 10 hours, which shall be divided equally between those favoring and those opposing the joint resolution. A motion further to limit debate is in order and not debatable. An amendment to, or a motion to postpone, or a motion to proceed to the consideration of other business, or a motion to recommit the joint resolution is not in order.</text></clause><clause id="HB53AD091E75245F18F82EB97D7BDF301"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the Senate, immediately following the conclusion of the debate on a joint resolution, and a single quorum call at the conclusion of the debate if requested in accordance with the rules of the Senate, the vote on final passage of the joint resolution shall occur.</text></clause><clause id="HCEF481C216474ED9B3112DE2AA5D0906"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the Senate, appeals from the decisions of the Chair relating to the application of the rules of the Senate to the procedure relating to a joint resolution shall be decided without debate.</text></clause><clause id="HA4148BE1E32048E6949F1384B5FE9EE9"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the Senate, the procedure specified in this subparagraph shall not apply to the consideration of a joint resolution after the end of the 60-day period described under paragraph (2)(A).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2776D00820AC495A9D19D58CF4B264F8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Treatment of joint resolution received from the other House</header><text>If, before the passage by one House of a joint resolution of that House, that House receives from the other House a joint resolution, then the following procedures shall apply:</text><subparagraph id="H51EBE79655B943FABFB95CC2F3544AEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The joint resolution of the other House shall not be referred to a committee.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2578EFE78D764AB6B4474B940F51847F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>With respect to a joint resolution of the House receiving the joint resolution—</text><clause id="H67F1ABF905F34CD7A1B156D335DAFE77"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the procedure in that House shall be the same as if no joint resolution had been received from the other House; but</text></clause><clause id="HD4841EC2025749439FAC3A9FC36D6B47"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the vote on final passage shall be on the joint resolution of the other House.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H27FBFD8FDDB94890BFB24BFAD96A8CFA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Treatment of this paragraph</header><text>This paragraph is enacted by Congress—</text><subparagraph id="H1BC5F8892ECE4386AFD9E8679FDD7F16"><enum>(A)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the Senate and House of Representatives, respectively, and as such it is deemed a part of the rules of each House, respectively, but applicable only with respect to the procedure to be followed in that House in the case of a joint resolution, and it supersedes other rules only to the extent that it is inconsistent with such rules; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F251DB819654DDA8FB8230434637FBD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change the rules (so far as relating to the procedure of that House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of that House.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HED4887C0DD3D495980FE02F34DB97529"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 115—</text><subparagraph id="H7A7239FDAEDA47C0BF965E24F4DE18C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1), by inserting after <quote>recommendations to</quote> the following: <quote>the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31097D1F512C4D07A19688EA146E1A89"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c)(3), by inserting after <quote>recommendations to</quote> the following: <quote>the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00CB2BC899F24B29B160C1C6961DFE5C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><clause id="H92F2A00F884F422BB6F4051F04F4ABC6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting after <quote>make recommendations to the Board of Governors</quote> the following: <quote>, if the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate are notified of such recommendations,</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H8AE65A3291D247A4922206F00F406F8F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), by inserting after <quote>make recommendations to the Board of Governors</quote> the following: <quote>, if the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate are notified of such recommendations,</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE616FACCFE5F4C75BF3512A1FAB8FF6D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (e), by inserting after <quote>make recommendations to the Board of Governors</quote> the following: <quote>, if the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate are notified of such recommendations,</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBE71E73D0C441238CA9F777D17DF102"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (f), by inserting after <quote>make recommendations to the Board of Governors</quote> the following: <quote>, if the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate are notified of such recommendations,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D4D5BD93E6D4583A00F87748C2CCB46"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (g), by inserting after <quote>make recommendations to the Board of Governors</quote> the following: <quote>, if the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate are notified of such recommendations,</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H32DA0CD6392644879FD52B00D4CE8B6D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in section 116(a), by inserting after <quote>may</quote> the following: <quote>, after notifying the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate,</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95E42C6F4D7149519046EC26A004AC76"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in section 120—</text><subparagraph id="H877F3F5E2F7D45458A85C1843F17EE9C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by inserting after <quote>regulatory agencies</quote> the following: <quote>, if the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate are notified of such recommendations,</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8643ADAEC3984118A0302F2EC808E80C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><clause id="H817405EF905B493EBE458DF4742B583A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting after <quote>to the public</quote> the following: <quote>and Congress</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HA06CB514670F411EBAF870ADD9C2DB09"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A), by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>, and the notice required under paragraph (1) shall contain data, methodology, and analysis detailing such costs</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83F13C36767441F1BEDD6E05571E30F7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(2), by inserting after <quote>recommended by the Council</quote> the following: <quote>, after notifying the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of such imposition,</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE67A901501AC48C58281E43527654289"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(2)(A), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, and notify the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of such determination and the factors, data, and analysis leading to such determination</quote>; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2900BF439EE14C1B9B463D2420280F79"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H316D6FAE734040E7841C183E7682CEC7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H1B83A8107F73454384799F4CEF74AC6C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Delay in implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A primary financial regulatory agency may not implement a recommendation made by the Council under subsection (a) until the end of the 90-day period beginning on the date such recommendation is issued.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H756D3D289B6D467CB08442B53F7BF5BC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in section 121—</text><subparagraph id="H072D37F9B45F42C6B2BF450FFB118686"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (d), by inserting after <quote>Governors may</quote> the following: <quote>, after notifying the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAFC9D4CB93F4CE69915F5823CF07A1D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEC2F178C7A6B4583B1AD234A4516D293" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H009C5ED7BF5447688BB445DF6250C549"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Notice to Congress; delay in implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board of Governors—</text><paragraph id="H9EAEBB0A85184B9B9CD35981812B9C62"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall notify the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of an intention to take an action described under paragraph (1) through (5) of subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC9B033AC64E4637A33ED3FEA36DE8BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may not take such an action until the end of the 60-day period beginning on the date of such notification.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H84627B5F30CE40F8A5A4E0121A1DDF99"><enum>(8)</enum><text>in section 122—</text><subparagraph id="H3B4D2CE5C4E94B5DA535E07793273903"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a), by striking <quote>may audit</quote> and inserting <quote>shall annually audit</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H531D44FE322C46ADBDE79D202E297376"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(2)—</text><clause id="H550A015D759342E79CD2E97C696EFB64"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Comptroller</quote> and inserting <quote>The chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate, and the Comptroller</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H4A776054FF9745A38C57930366C8FFAD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>as the Comptroller General</quote> and inserting <quote>as the chair, ranking member, or Comptroller General, as applicable</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE39D66342ACD421A87675C4F7905ECA6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(9)</enum><text>in section 152(e), by adding at the end the following: <quote>The Office shall report on such detailed employees on a monthly basis to Congress.</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9636F6092D3D4F93BD983DCB8D6FFA7C"><enum>(10)</enum><text>in section 153—</text><subparagraph id="H6E2C159CF37545AC9DFE5BD4E769DF0E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><clause id="H6C165B93E52D4457BF32233134866B1C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>essential</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HE8C8835ADAB34FFFA34FDF290BA2572A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (5);</text></clause><clause id="HC8C2CBC5BDAE4F84B5FC061A05C01527"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (6) and (7) as paragraphs (5) and (6), respectively; and</text></clause><clause id="H5606356C74174CE1B26E9024254794DF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), as so redesignated, by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>, the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H427DDDCBF9C540E2830909F1199F87EC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><clause id="H97C38CA339124B369DBDDC256857DECA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subclause id="H4EA15C20BE1E438DABBCC37F49B66020"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting after <quote>with the Council,</quote> the following: <quote>the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives, the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate,</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H281AD70F77024D6B8D9B8D5ADD64F738"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>and without prior notice of such sharing being provided to the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H38E37FC4A6AA4BE0BC9333A4CC8E0D8D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>, after providing notice to the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of such research projects</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H945128D972414092B13B589AAB9091AB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (3), by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, after providing notice to the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of such assistance</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H342FBF569D3946E49282B035903DA54F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (f)(1), by striking <quote>but only</quote> and inserting <quote>but not earlier than 60 days after the Director notifies the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate of the requirement to produce such data and only</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB88DCEA7F372454599A6F62C6DF2C5CF"><enum>(11)</enum><text>in section 154—</text><subparagraph id="HC6A220A2E19D488B9B3D4CE3AC992C99"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><clause id="H98E8F7E797DF4EA09566693168750D57"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(B)(i), by inserting after <quote>by the Council,</quote> the following: <quote>after notifying the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the chair and ranking member of the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate,</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HE7DFBD3517E149DF96FD73F1CEF5ED5F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF79BFD6A0C1A4AFA987F53363C579A4D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H5214D4122C6E42EDA8C6BD55B6658C89"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Review and report on the cost of the databases</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Data Center shall review and report to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate annually on the cost to the Government and the cost to private sector entities of maintaining the financial company reference database and the financial instrument reference database, relative to a detailed quantification of benefits.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04D55DDD015D495DA8C4B326DD021431"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(1)(E), by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>or Congress</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD65C8F7C73C649669E63D4F4837BCC9D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(2)—</text><clause id="HEF14AD360D8B4F2B833B5EB6AB9AA095"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="H9103B17A46DB4E0DB8B8245A92FB6F44"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H22B9ABADEC0E488D9B14938B058EFF1E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3B6C72E8624B4706824172B2376D48DA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="HBF41BBDBD38E42389A53DAF5B5033CE4"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evidence of inefficient, ineffective, or burdensome regulations.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H22EB6582E5F9465BA2591C415A4B3902"><enum>(12)</enum><text>in section 155(d)—</text><subparagraph id="H4F11EE5948384B5480A99BC9E75F187A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Beginning</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD29263572DFB40EAB74FFB414E22B998" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HEB77858936E64B3483862B47B26DBEF1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47BDA15C00CD43A09B9BB60E0FB9AC7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF0A625C2A8B24D80B286A2EFE0FDFBC9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H38DF0E855CD44BF2B310DA548E425A86"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maximum assessment amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The aggregate amount of assessments collected pursuant to paragraph (1) may not exceed the aggregate amount of assessments collected in the most recently completed fiscal year ending before the date of enactment of this paragraph, as such aggregate amount is adjusted annually by the Director of the Office to reflect the change in the Consumer Price Index for All Urban Consumers published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics of the Department of Labor.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H39C432DEB38943C8B429A98A3EAD2DED"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="HCBC4056C130A41828AF13EAF7678116A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Title 5</header><text>Section 5314 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>Independent Member of the Financial Stability Oversight Council (1)</quote> and inserting <quote>Independent Members of the Financial Stability Oversight Council (2)</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29C0B7D239334FC292E6E1AC6710C41D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 176 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9F49A7025E3C43F896E914DAFDFF31BC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 177. Congressional notice.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

