<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFF0FA0CFC61D4A4F9BB3682C67820B21" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5222 IH: Energy Workers Health Improvement and Compensation Fund Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5222</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230815">August 15, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000136">Mr. Vasquez</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To establish the Energy Workers Compensation Fund to compensate energy workers for certain medical expenses.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H44E6A3725FAD4A749F6A443248C17574" style="OLC">
<section id="H8F12299DF2E44E408BE0AE596B142677" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Energy Workers Health Improvement and Compensation Fund Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H38A4555B3E514E7981F62BA556154172"><enum>2.</enum><header>Energy Workers Compensation Fund</header> <subsection id="H4318AFFB5B814D66A2723CA06EAB8355"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Creation of trust fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Treasury of the United States a trust fund to be known as the <quote>Energy Workers Health Compensation Fund</quote>.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H9F0F89EE95E042ACB778AC2F2BBD444E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deposits</header>
<paragraph id="H9E66508A841F44259451A714EB1A3002"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each oil company shall pay with respect to each calendar year (not later than March 31 of the calendar year immediately following such calendar year) an amount equal to the aggregate amounts paid as compensation (including the fair market value of any deferred compensation) to the 10 most highly paid (taking into account all compensation taken into account under this subsection) employees of such company during such calendar year. Such amounts shall be deposited into the Energy Workers Health Compensation Fund.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFFDD07EEF6BC4F90B056305E702A9ADC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties for underpayments</header><text>If the Secretary of Labor determines that the amount paid by any oil company with respect to any calendar year is less than 98 percent of the amount properly determined under paragraph (1), such oil company shall pay an additional amount equal to 10 percent of such difference. Such amount shall be deposited into the Energy Workers Health Compensation Fund.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H32212784550D40F2ACA05235CAC3D008"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Elective contributions</header><text>An oil company may contribute, in addition to any amount required to be paid under paragraph (1) or (2), an additional amount to the Energy Workers Health Compensation Fund not in excess of the amount required to be paid under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0CB58D1EC26D49FBA43A406153DD87A3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Tax treatment of contributions</header><text>No deduction shall be allowed under section 162 (or any other provision) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 for any amount required to be paid under paragraph (1) or (2) or any amount contributed to the Energy Workers Health Compensation Fund which is in excess of the amount permitted under paragraph (3).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H90FD3FF0378149989888D2950A739557"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Expenditures</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts in the compensation fund shall be available to the Secretary of Labor, without need of further appropriation, for the purposes of section 3.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H86993478740046F6B482C5FD861B4AB0"><enum>3.</enum><header>Compensation for medical expenses</header> <subsection id="H7F5AB5F52D374A2E97C404000BFE5767"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible worker, or family member thereof, shall be entitled to compensation in order to reimburse such eligible worker (or family member thereof) for medical expenses, including copayments and costs not covered by private insurance, Medicare, or Medicaid, associated with—</text>
<paragraph id="HCF6DBC10DA4C4A1DA4ED46007242F681"><enum>(1)</enum><text>asthma;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF6A5A76DAD054D62BBE330A30DE4B34C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>heat-related illness; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3B2DFF052BA14A6984DAA3D6C397B555"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other respiratory or cardiovascular diseases determined by the Secretary, in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Occupational Safety and Health, to be associated with methane emissions, high levels of smog, and exposure to particulate matter and volatile organic compounds.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFFD3A924463E420BBCEAB8C1DE7C86AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Payment from trust fund</header><text>The compensation under this section shall be paid from the compensation fund established under section 2.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HFD09987464DA4312BA2C451C9F7A35E8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Processing of claims</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide the compensation to which an individual is entitled under subparagraph (a) in the order in which claims for compensation are received.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H5C45521D8BE8435DA536783D1CA5A336"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="H10B4166DF50645A1BB2AA3D356BD9ACE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible worker</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>eligible worker</quote> means any individual who—</text> <subparagraph id="H7AB3850F2BA543EEB9691C2351229E2C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>either—</text>
<clause id="H575A4125082942D5A02C64640E4B67D3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>works or has worked within or around a oil and gas extraction or exploration site for not less than 1 year; or</text></clause> <clause id="H7BBFD687098B4EDB99DE452FF4CDB259"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>lives or has lived within 20 miles of such a site for not less than 1 year; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H52503D098E2E4FD1A51E05DA6E1972CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>works or has worked for an oil company engaged in oil and gas extraction or exploration or for a company contracted to perform those duties.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H53298BCFC5E44D4EA173B0162180C5B3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Family member</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>family member</quote> means the spouse, son, daughter, or parent of an eligible worker, if such spouse, son, daughter, or parent lives or has lived within 20 miles of an oil and gas extraction or exploration site for not less than 1 year.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD8DF6948F7D74F79BA2A020B922CDF55" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Oil company</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>oil company</quote> means a company engaged in oil or natural gas exploration or extraction with annual revenue greater than $50,000,000.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H08BE7F65D9C340F6B25EA82D6DC64C4F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H22476857D43B46C792D396C3D979A1C2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Compensation fund</header><text>The term <quote>compensation fund</quote> means the Energy Workers Health Compensation Fund established under section 2.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

