<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE60525C928BD4F54997E1C188E091A4C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 562 IH: Improving Veterans Access to Congressional Services Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 562</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000474">Mr. Flood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to permit Members of Congress to use facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs for the purposes of meeting with constituents, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD5F850A3C4924E568930E001808C3137" style="OLC"><section id="H8DB47A30017D40808432D45B75D123F4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Veterans Access to Congressional Services Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2454E15FEA5148C8AF6F1F2EBC0C823E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Use of facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs by Members of Congress</header><subsection id="HABA6A9D13E0C4CB99DCEA4947F3254F2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon request of a Member of Congress and subject to regulations prescribed under subsection (b), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall permit the Member to use a facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs for the purposes of meeting with constituents of the Member. The Secretary and the Administrator of General Services shall jointly identify available spaces in facilities of the Department for such purposes.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDFC27379E9C34A318ADD2C877B8EE817"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall prescribe regulations regarding such use of a facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs by Members of Congress. Regulations prescribed under this subsection—</text><paragraph id="H321B9212BEEE4280B9DECDB7DABF3EC1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall require that a space within a facility of the Department provided to a Member under subsection (a) is—</text><subparagraph id="HB273357010604E80BD7D05137E40CF5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>available during normal business hours;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA4E20A3731E43A3ADDD1C87FEA5A095"><enum>(B)</enum><text>located in an area that is visible and accessible to constituents of the Member; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C2D0C2E3ED9486AAEE334E3D62448E5"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">subject to a rate of rent (payable from the Member’s Representational Allowance or the Senator’s Official Personnel and Office Expense Account, as the case may be) that is similar to the rate charged by the Administrator of General Services for office space in the area of the facility;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE38B658EA28A4AF99978E8B9D1032965"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not prohibit a Member from advertising the use by the Member of a space within a facility of the Department under subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA799FE89C7B94D5183AF93F60F9A666A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall comply with sections 7321 through 7326 of title 5, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Hatch Act</quote>) and section 1.218(a)(14) of title 38, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulation), by prohibiting activities including—</text><subparagraph id="HEBDED1892DF54F1ABD59EFCD865829D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>campaigning in support of or opposition to any political office;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4EE858E299746B59B1CB9D5BC85B532"><enum>(B)</enum><text>statements or actions that solicit, support, or oppose any change to Federal law or policy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47156F7ADDF2443F87189DA321F375B5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any activity that interferes with security or normal operation of the facility;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1429BA68861447389CC17A0533FA5CE9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>photographing or recording a veteran patient at such facility;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B7B119AC1EE42E1A479D01CE544B5E9"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">photographing or recording a patient, visitor to the facility, or employee of the Department without the consent of such individual; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD915BCEC88854C60A61EF5BE53A4976F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>photography or recording for the purpose of political campaign materials;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AFA61A21CFE48DBA9C0C8CC9CFE874D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>may not permit a Member of Congress to use such a facility during the 60-day period preceding an election for Federal office in the jurisdiction in which such facility is located; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE88807BCB954ADB95D3B9D274618EBD"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not unreasonably restrict use of a facility of the Department by a Member under subsection (a) if—</text><subparagraph id="H0F427B6E21CE4DB5ACFBD76F9C9D7B5A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>there is space in such facility not in regular use by personnel of the Department; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1432C059AA1140D2A3184FFA8CC06536"><enum>(B)</enum><text>use of such space shall not impede operations of the Department in such facility.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

