<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H402E0A722FEA47E3A59E595433CD0EB5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5706 IH: U.S. Capitol Power Plant Retrofit Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5706</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Architect of the Capitol, using existing funding, to study the feasibility of retrofitting the Capitol Power Plant to incorporate an advanced nuclear reactor.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H99F1206B4FA44BAD88753C9245A935D3" style="OLC"><section id="HCE86E7E4F4344989AC79AD8F46EA8D9B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>U.S. Capitol Power Plant Retrofit Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H007B8F650CA34999A5EEFBCF0D17EDA9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; sense of Congress</header><subsection id="H1994121D88AD41C894F47AA63D767B9F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H799B3FF6B3C445C3B906083BCD2EA039"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Capitol Power Plant was originally built in 1910 to provide electricity for the United States Capitol Complex, and continued to provide electricity for the Complex until 1951.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE976793E6B7840F39A6101645F8466F7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 1951, the Plant diverted its electricity responsibilities to a local utility, but instead utilized the Plant to provide steam and chilled water for building heating and cooling systems throughout the Complex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45B3339E674E4E65BE26F13015D81610"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2018, the Architect of the Capitol competed installation of a new combined heat and power natural gas-fired co-generation system, which has a natural gas-fired turbine that has the potential to generate 7.5 MWe and be paired with a heat recovery steam generator to produce steam.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD608AF63D83345A1BF071D1AB3060796"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The electricity that the Plant generates today is used to power certain internal operations in the Complex and to supply some of the demands of the chilled water system.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE6B7D6A6DBF487BBE881DA13FD67F76"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On average, two-thirds of electricity for the chilled water needs of the Complex is supplied by the Plant, with the rest of the required electricity purchased from a local utility. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H535D96FE6EF6452D94CC8A569C2D6587"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H367D3690B4084E6FB9F438047883EA09"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Architect of the Capitol should be encouraged to collaborate with the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and the Department of Energy to determine the feasibility of retrofitting the Capitol Power Plant to incorporate an advanced nuclear reactor;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70C19725BBCC43048B4E55B81E61B3C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Architect of the Capitol should recognize the inherent benefits that an advanced nuclear power plant can provide, including zero-emissions steam and chilled water production, grid resiliency, and energy independence; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3FA410B792D45F8A134FCDB5EA0EC60"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress understands that evaluating the feasibility of retrofitting the Capitol Power Plant to incorporate an advanced nuclear reactor will ultimately assist with improving public support for advanced nuclear energy. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H07E3351E7B9146E1A8360116AF8E5993"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study of feasibility of retrofitting Capitol Power Plant to incorporate advanced nuclear reactor</header><subsection id="H6B03FAF9EA8C4AFA8203531E69200590"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Architect of the Capitol shall begin consultation with the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and the Department of Energy about developing and conducting a study of the feasibility of retrofitting the Capitol Power Plant to incorporate an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9D18E93ACE4A480988BC87EAB5F1A65F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Specifics of study</header><paragraph id="H145EA6B6BF6C4F669EF821A95878F22E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The feasibility study conducted under this section shall include, at a minimum, a general description of the background and objective of the feasibility study, and may also include any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HF62F748AD79C48A1B694B09060A50DF8" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Organizational responsibilities for the preparation of the study preparation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54812C46651D481492C97F915D3DC99E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Potential project stakeholders.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2C3334FD9F3847F1B8C9AFC35380FD00" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of the following:</text><clause id="H16AA650E70D44568A6E7A635F6B62511" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The demand for electricity in the region of the Capitol Power Plant.</text></clause><clause id="HB6AF02C2DD064E34A9DE775B5A51F76A" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The transmission capacity and transmission facilities and systems in such region.</text></clause><clause id="H6F2D8B1E73604DE588CDD351807E1D3C" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The structure of the market for electricity.</text></clause><clause id="H19245C936EDC43939998213C19C3F341" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>How the construction and operation of the advanced nuclear reactor at the Plant would affect the issues described in clauses (i), (ii), and (iii).</text></clause><clause id="HEA1C6BB6F55144CD9217E82AB9C2B936"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The potential for the advanced nuclear reactor to produce electricity to not only provide power for the Capitol Complex but to produce chilled water and steam.</text></clause><clause id="HA72D3C403AC1499C9D163D18BEC416FA"><enum>(vi)</enum><text> Whether the piping capacity of the Plant is sufficient to produce and distribute heat through the Capitol Complex. </text></clause><clause id="H5E1B05AD0BDA444BAEED5B83F1A387E3" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Site analysis, including preliminary site layout and site preparation and potential effects of the advanced nuclear reactor and supporting facilities on the applicable region, including population distribution and current uses of land and water.</text></clause><clause id="HBC180FE7D55745968C206743715364CC" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Environmental analysis of constructing and operating the advanced nuclear reactor, including—</text><subclause id="H807615E00EF44D0C964B730DBC572C3E" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a comparison of similar characteristics in the applicable region; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H71DB5F921E7B4299B1454248391FC02F" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an overview of environmental protection requirements in the region.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H8F2C989D93254C6F804F766F1F74FD75" commented="no"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>How to approach the licensing process and authorization for the siting, construction, and operation of the advanced nuclear reactor.</text></clause><clause id="H92DB558CD8FC41B89B51991FC42BE1B4" commented="no"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Potential contractual approaches, procurement plans, project schedules, project management, and risk management plans.</text></clause><clause id="HFE636E7DAAE743B9AC1046113544A3E0" commented="no"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Organizational requirements and responsibilities for each phase of retrofitting the Plant with an advanced nuclear reactor, including requirements and responsibilities relating to human resources and training, workforce logistics and staffing requirements, and maintenance of the advanced nuclear reactor.</text></clause><clause id="H2A8B9BE12282471D9117679B9E725C76" commented="no"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>Economic feasibility of retrofitting the Plant with an advanced nuclear reactor, including a cost-benefit analysis.</text></clause><clause id="H53959897A34D479898191C2C43CE3177" commented="no"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>Plans for emergency preparedness and coordination, including on-site emergency planning and coordination with off-site emergency response organizations.</text></clause><clause id="H1632A8C55249492AAA97CCE0818BD735" commented="no"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text>Co-generation opportunities which may arise after the Plant is retrofitted with an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></clause><clause id="H13F5A30548F34462B2F4ED6A9149FDA0" commented="no"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>Safety and performance analysis, including—</text><subclause id="H62ED14FAF8364863B9ABEE75626F2E38" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>fuel cycle evaluation and impact assessment;</text></subclause><subclause id="H1199693602EC4D4C82932768B3C9F08D" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>radioactive and conventional waste management assessment; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H74A2A8FF313B44DB9CF893493C95EAD9" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>interim waste storage and related issues.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB1C4D694AEBD4824A95B80B9306D06AF" commented="no"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>Decommissioning analysis for the advanced nuclear reactor, including the cost of decommissioning the advanced nuclear reactor, and the environmental impact of decommissioning the advanced nuclear reactor.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3D9EDD0FE1048F58AAFDB0B4AD0B2B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Architect of the Capitol may incorporate in the study the following additional considerations:</text><subparagraph id="H1D37A05881E44C0D8EC06696628BC72F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>How retrofitting the Capitol Power Plant would affect other Federal and District of Columbia laws, including the Clean Air Act, and what would be needed in terms of regulatory clarity and licensing to retrofit the Plant with an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF54D315E74D94F349D39D695CCC2144A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Economic considerations relating to how the retrofitted power plant compares with the current combined heat and power natural gas-fired co-generation system, as well as how the retrofitted Plant compares with Plant when it was powered by coal and an analysis of how much retrofitting the plant with an advanced nuclear reactor would save the Federal Government and the American taxpayer annually.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B7208E8914044A198D98EDB9FF619F9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How such feasibility would impact the utility energy service contract between the Architect of the Capitol and the local utility, including potential Federal funding opportunities to pay off the utility energy service contract before the May 2037 anticipated timeline.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99909F0F7D724EDA9F6C2534C8BCB8CC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>How local power outages currently affect the Plant, and how the power outage impacts could be alleviated from retrofitting the Plant with an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F1C8F40AEF645F9AF3BDCF0C82AC52B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The potential for the retrofitted Plant to once again provide electricity, along with steam and chilled water, to the Capitol Complex, and how this would benefit the Complex in terms of grid security and protection against cyberattacks and digital data infiltration efforts.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83D407C7A82D4509A4C2E0182270FA6E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>How retrofitting the Plant to incorporate an advanced nuclear reactor would fit within the <quote>Greening the Capitol Initiative</quote>, which was created in March 2007 to <quote>provide an environmentally responsible and healthy working environment for employees</quote>.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4D5852B28F2485699C6AC759A697CC6"><enum>(G)</enum><text>How the retrofitted Plant can take advantage of the high-energy waste heat and other biproducts of operating an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA6C3985492942CA9563982B033D6AF5"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The extent to which there is an opportunity to keep the existing combined heat and power natural gas-fired co-generation system infrastructure, and the extent to which there is a possibility for the advanced nuclear reactor to provide electricity, chilled water, and steam (or any combination thereof).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57B5BD0C7EDB4C8180DAC22287B9F069"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The role of thermal combustion resources and infrastructure in the Plant’s existing operational capacity, and what the role of such resources and infrastructure would be if the Plant was retrofitted with an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07C2A97A322841E3AC22ACAC2C4A00C6"><enum>(J)</enum><text>How to incorporate a consent-based, community-focused approach for conducting this feasibility study, including sharing the facts with surrounding businesses, residents, and the general public, including tourists and other individuals that visit the Capitol Complex for business purposes, and how to alleviate concerns relating to the feasibility of retrofitting the Plant with an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28B0234467454528ACFE5A9B6B495A37"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether energy savings performance contracts available to the Architect of the Capitol, and which are currently used mostly for building improvements, can be utilized to retrofit the Plant with an advanced nuclear reactor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB18850BF09524FB099F02136DC1B8573"><enum>(L)</enum><text>Whether the Plant can continue operations during the process of retrofitting the plant with an advanced nuclear reactor, and related concerns.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA37B7AE5DC3C4A21AD70D4079F40CDCA"><enum>(M)</enum><text> How to secure the Plant from sabotage and other forms of attack, including physical and cyber attack.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H126EEC7425F744D28695342BE02616E5"><enum>(N)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> How to ensure that the emergency planning zone surrounding the advanced nuclear reactor, as required under regulations of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, is small enough to ensure the safety of the Plant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB407DE8AC7AD4B6C8019633C19B019E5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public sessions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the course of conducting the feasibility study under this section, the Architect of the Capitol, in conjunction with the Department of Energy and the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, shall hold at least two in-person public sessions to give members of the public the opportunity to learn about the study, and shall provide the public with notice of such sessions to the greatest extent possible.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCB5B065F44BB46E5815D7AFE8C8B2411"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deadline for completion</header><text>The Architect of the Capitol shall complete the feasibility study under this section not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA1587DF72D6545F39AB7DA19CDE8388D" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Advanced nuclear reactor defined</header><text>The term <term>advanced nuclear reactor</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H0E912AA3152A427B8F79C8ED85B8852D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nuclear fission reactor, including a prototype plant (as defined in sections 50.2 and 52.1 of title 10, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations)), with significant improvements compared to reactors operating on October 19, 2016, including improvements such as—</text><subparagraph id="H0AD31033E8E5498FA0ED3ECF1A7A842C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>additional inherent safety features, including features designed to prevent the release of radioactive material;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6D41417DD634C4E93861E5DA9041EF9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>lower waste yields;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H742B71A5F3B34C0ABA0A4EB774166AEF" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>improved fuel and material performance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96D971A45ACC4CE08CE9271C4F7432C1" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>increased tolerance to loss of fuel cooling;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA89F6EA92787488F9B93E1BFC641266C" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>enhanced reliability or improved resilience;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C82329459024AAE91A9A4F8C2FC04D3" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>increased proliferation resistance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D04F55B070E40B9A609E4663C93FA7A" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>increased thermal efficiency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4346AFD9BC5C4D66A014974C9AE8BC15" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><text>reduced consumption of cooling water and other environmental impacts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFEB5DA75E2A54F25A341A33E6D92FC5B" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the ability to integrate into electric applications and nonelectric applications;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FED657AE11C41AC87379C3A127DD3E1" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text>modular sizes to allow for deployment that corresponds with the demand for electricity or process heat; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8344427E092476091AAA9DB49059F62" commented="no"><enum>(K)</enum><text>operational flexibility to respond to changes in demand for electricity or process heat and to complement integration with intermittent renewable energy or energy storage;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB01ED62C7164CDD8D66FCA3B14B0C0C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a fusion reactor; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H920139E2E31041F8AE999B69DE3E6E27" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a radioisotope power system that utilizes heat from radioactive decay to generate energy. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA0277A86A91946C58C758B094F5C127C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report</header><subsection id="H4F59EAC4BBB94FBFA4FC758C0ECF9C80"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after completing the feasibility study under section 3, the Architect of the Capitol shall submit a report to the appropriate congressional committees that outlines the findings of the feasibility study, along with the Architect’s final determination as to the whether it is feasible to retrofit the current Capitol Power Plant to encompass an advanced nuclear reactor. </text></subsection><subsection id="H8BDD6432F40D471BB340113E2DDBE707"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H683AAB027691423E92ED78CD0CFD7C74"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Energy and Commerce and the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H234BBC07977B4993A010E8FB1DAD3C17"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, the Committee on Environment and Public Works, and the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H96F8281E3FA04C70A9131BFFDBD3C319"><enum>5.</enum><header>Use of existing funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The Architect of the Capitol shall carry out this Act using funds appropriated for the Office of the Architect of the Capitol prior to the date of the enactment of this Act which remain unobligated as of such date.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

