<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4B34A3DA3EF449509BD207C9888AA923" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5613 IH: Sanctions Lists Harmonization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5613</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230920">September 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a review of whether individuals or entities subject to the imposition of certain sanctions through inclusion on certain sanctions lists should also be subject to the imposition of other sanctions and included on other sanctions lists.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA7FBCB17F927423696430A5809408A6F" style="OLC"><section id="HA00E105C3EA048A78790BEDA803E3EAE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sanctions Lists Harmonization Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H22BB7BC5F85243589128961427865F49" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirements to include individuals and entities subject to United States sanctions on certain other sanctions lists</header><subsection id="H9B8B1644EB9E40D195F9B8BE8CDD9E72"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification to other Federal officials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date on which an individual or entity is included on one of the lists described in subsection (d), the Federal official responsible for administering such list shall notify the Federal officials responsible for administering the other lists described in subsection (d) of the inclusion of the individual or entity on such list.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5AD5449244974C968BB87E1D7764A8F6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determination and other requirements of other Federal official</header><paragraph id="HA136DF5CB7EC4CD0943BC459AB32A479"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date on which a Federal official receives a notification under subsection (a) of the inclusion of an individual or entity on one of the lists described in subsection (d), such Federal official shall—</text><subparagraph id="H296A93726CAE4AE4B99E634EC6B3FEF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conduct a review and make a determination of whether to include such individual or entity on such other lists; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8F752160F1A047FEA4D7BBCF8EF11209"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make available to the public, including by publishing in the Federal Register, the determination made under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H59244AD38B7E4B059BB4757C077D6BA6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Advance congressional notification</header><subparagraph id="H0AA58A4961DF47E381AB9DF6FD5793A6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a determination under paragraph (1)(A) not to include an individual or entity on such other lists, the Federal official shall, not later than 7 days after making the determination, submit the determination to the appropriate congressional committees, including a justification for why the individual or entity did not meet the eligibility criteria for inclusion on such other list.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE12462FE0D3F47E9AD0C5BF405085145"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Form</header><text>A notification required under this paragraph shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2E5AA6285F94DD787AA45195912AFB4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a determination under paragraph (1)(A) not to include an individual or entity on such other lists, the Federal official shall, not later than 1 year after making the determination, conduct an additional review to determine if the individual or entity should be included on such other lists, particularly if there is a material change in the activities of the individual or entity. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H034E56D6F02346119A8EBD4056F2CC09"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Congressional notifications for determinations not To list new individuals and entities</header><paragraph id="HAB4BCA3AA22D4D04ABFB122CECE36C1D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notification to congress</header><subparagraph id="HBAE6B70C456E4BB691C573A3D0344A49"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the date on which a Federal agency, department, or office first conducts deliberations regarding the designation of a new individual or entity on any list described in subsection (d) and determines not to designate that individual or entity, the Federal official responsible for administering such list shall notify the appropriate congressional committees of such negative determination and include with such notification—</text><clause id="HFECF7CF328E541E994BA4D0ECD82BBB1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an identification of the nondesignated individual or entity by name;</text></clause><clause id="HB7BF7EFF48DB4B3B9DE6081001672666"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an articulation of the reasons that the individual or entity was initially considered for designation; and</text></clause><clause id="HD294A832B0F24AFB8820BA853E0D52B4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a full explanation and justification for the subsequent determination that the individual or entity did not meet the eligibility criteria for designation on the applicable list.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB2CE62F817542159CCE209D1D8E6C26"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Form</header><text>A notification required under this paragraph shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB72CDAA4A8BA4DC7BD727BC378B5FC47"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deliberation defined</header><text>For purposes of the notifications under this subsection, the term <quote>deliberation</quote> includes any meeting where a Federal Government official with the power to place an individual or an entity on one of the lists described in section 2(c) reviews the potential designation with one or more executive branch counterparts for a conclusive decision.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2945F0B3B9E4AB7823DBE13656F30E8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Lists described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The lists described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="HFBE0BE670629482BBB30C8E45F1DE1D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The list of specially designated nationals and blocked persons maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H707437B1395E4D33ACC2C61B43556C2A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The list maintained and set forth in Supplement No. 4 to part 744 of the Export Administration Regulations (commonly known as the <quote>Entity List</quote>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45D2D9847014469A901E2119F922B7CC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Department of Defense’s list maintained and published under section 1237 of the Strom Thurmond National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5796479D1A574F4F8A4C95F67BBCDAEC"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Department of Defense’s list maintained and published under 1260H of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/113">10 U.S.C. 113</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89E6FC88386541F28DE75D45F58AE3AD"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Non-SDN Chinese Military-Industrial Complex Companies (NS–CMIC) List of the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H847EDDD7C379415EB08F19CB10E9E9C9"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Sectoral Sanctions List of the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BC584EA2C654037B661F39189E58028"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Unverified List of the Bureau of Industry and Security of the Department of Commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF89BBE8EE7EE483B93C616C058700C3C"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Military End User List of the Bureau of Industry and Security of the Department of Commerce.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6992B8B7F0D5403F914E4DD867FD7F43"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H084D4FDA868B4F7BA20D329CBCFC318E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HB50ED7A1731A4EA8B864D843076A218F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18636B128B7A424BA2DE3966DA5F3388"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Foreign Relations, and the Committee on Finance of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H155F839D2F154B5BBF6A49A55661186A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Export Administration Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Export Administration Regulations</quote> means the regulations set forth in subchapter C of chapter VII of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations, or successor regulations. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

