<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1658F5075C5348129468A9E5F603D392" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2730 IH: Health Equity and Middle Eastern and North African Community Inclusion Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2730</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230419">April 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to include Middle Easterners and North Africans in the statutory definition of a <quote>racial and ethnic minority group</quote>, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAFA677C7875D4CC09231C62847E0A330" style="OLC"><section id="H79A01ECAEA9946F5B6C700F3576EF6AC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Health Equity and Middle Eastern and North African Community Inclusion Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Health Equity and MENA Community Inclusion Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD17A504D25034881AC9C9625A49B3D61"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the terms <term>Middle Eastern and North African</term> or <term>MENA</term>, with respect to individuals or populations, includes individuals and populations who identify with one or more nationalities or ethnic groups originating in a country (or portion thereof) in the Middle Eastern and North African region (such as Lebanese, Iranians, Egyptians, Moroccans, Yemenis, Chaldeans, Imazighen, Kurds, Palestinians, and Yazidis).</text></section><section id="H4216747DD9B54817B5B73C887631111A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H096E2E690A0E4930BAF6A3049CAA6490"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Through the establishment of the Office of Minority Health (OMH) in 1986, the Department of Health and Human Services has developed health policies and programs that eliminate health disparities and improve the health of racial and ethnic minority populations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F4CB293443A484C99EC71ABE5D30B88"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Congress has funded the OMH to develop and implement health care service programs that address physical activity and nutrition, clinical conditions, individual social needs, and the social determinants of health for <quote>racial and ethnic minority groups</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H193B6789A98B4E62B4D5E0C5C4380AC2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before the amendments made by this Act, section 1707(g)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300u-6">42 U.S.C. 300u–6(g)(1)</external-xref>)—</text><subparagraph id="H4431F3C304EF4D9D988BD7743AFF4D15"><enum>(A)</enum><text>defined the term <term>racial and ethnic minority group</term> (for whom the OMH works to improve health outcomes and eliminate health disparities) to exclude Middle Easterners and North Africans; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADA9DED1C3BE4664A58534D551834B84"><enum>(B)</enum><text>thereby prevented MENA populations from accessing critical resources intended to assist historically marginalized communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA01EC31CD5340DDABB27B36F9EE21B7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Independent researchers and private sector research initiatives have found significant health disparities between MENA individuals and the non-Hispanic White population, as well as significant overlap between the health outcomes and health conditions of MENA individuals and those of other racial and ethnic minority groups.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4796C53BF364DA79D72170E38DF9038"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Poor health outcomes are often connected to impoverishment in other aspects of life and are exacerbated by additional barriers to access high-quality health coverage, whether in terms of language, eligibility, health literacy, or discrimination at the point-of-service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H840039D4A2BA40C69A912F8CAAC2CF9B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A recent study published in Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences suggested that MENA individuals are not perceived as White and do not perceive themselves as White.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4BA32705CA543CFB1D42C169B399467"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Research on the health outcomes and health conditions of MENA individuals is troubling and suggests that efforts must be made on the Federal level to disaggregate the demographic data of MENA individuals from the demographic data of individuals in the non-Hispanic White category and fully understand the social determinants of health for health disparities and outcomes experienced by MENA individuals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AB3E03BB7CC40F6BA3E41A0EBC81DFD"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Under the current Federal standards for data on race and ethnicity, demographic data on MENA individuals is aggregated into the same category as demographic data on individuals of European ancestry, which limits the ability of the Federal Government to understand the factors that contribute to health outcomes for MENA individuals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0782D9EA3C8C43AEA8B97BC9657EBE7B"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The Federal standards for data on race and ethnicity effectively obscure the reality of minority health and health disparities by aggregating demographic health data on MENA individuals with that Europeans.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5024C5F02B1C4F33A6AE6435C5F6C5B8"><enum>(10)</enum><text>MENA individuals are not included among the groups for whom the OMH works to improve health outcomes and eliminate health disparities, which further limits the opportunity of MENA individuals to access programs designed to address their experiences and health conditions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H998CA824900E4837818C85B5157E4A39"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The OMH could better assess and eliminate health disparities by conducting a comprehensive study of the health of MENA individuals and recognizing MENA individuals as a racial and ethnic minority group.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H6D54017C317945A58729CD999F00E997"><enum>4.</enum><header>Inclusion of Middle Easterners and North Africans in definition of racial and ethnic minority groups</header><subsection id="HAF3F110686314FBB8BCFE662862F2370"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1707(g)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300u-6">42 U.S.C. 300u–6(g)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and Hispanics</quote> and inserting <quote>Hispanics, and Middle Easterners and North Africans</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8F07B023CC0C4DCC9B4ED892367D1BA2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that subsection (a) should be implemented so as to ensure that—</text><paragraph id="HFCB3B2B97C2E4A849F1CFC473B6D75A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the definition of a <quote>racial and ethnic minority group</quote> in section 1707(g)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300u-6">42 U.S.C. 300u–6(g)(1)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a), is applied in the implementation and execution of Federal programs and activities that reference such definition; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DE18C30495F49ABA70EA380E732DA65"><enum>(2)</enum><text>no racial and ethnic minority group served by such programs and activities is negatively impacted by subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFAAC3A511759487EB6D0B31286C03260"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Undefined references</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text><paragraph id="HF5C8ED98FB8040ADB26BAABEE9CA6045"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify all regulations, guidance, orders, and documents of the Department of Health and Human Services for establishment or implementation of a health care or public health program, activity, or survey that—</text><subparagraph id="HE34DF0DDCA7A475EB24BE1BD084FBC7C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>use the term <term>racial and ethnic minority group</term> or similar terminology; but</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0229882E32564AF48248CA463073CB6B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>do not define such term or terminology; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H001D2AF6E6D2475DAE6426C0CA0B6B19"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">take such actions as may be necessary to clarify whether the definition of <quote>racial and ethnic minority group</quote> in section 1707(g)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300u-6">42 U.S.C. 300u–6(g)(1)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a), applies to such term or terminology.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF931D73C3D504F2290536817286703AB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit a report to the Congress on the implementation of this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H943F982185554143A4795885874CFF34"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report on the health of the Middle Eastern and North African population</header><subsection id="H485409B54C7A4405A2935E0A0680F98C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study required</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall conduct or support a comprehensive study regarding the unique health patterns and outcomes of MENA populations.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB43B42EA4ECF481EA1AFAFDF9D1DDB23"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements for study</header><text>The comprehensive study under subsection (a) shall include an enumeration of MENA populations across the United States, disaggregated by subpopulation, and with respect to each such population and subpopulation—</text><paragraph id="H1CE37DEB9070467E8055B12FDA1A8540"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the rates of—</text><subparagraph id="H74DE5F88B3A24664B5BB54F378AB21B7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>obesity, diabetes, sickle cell anemia, stroke, asthma, pneumonia, lung cancer, HIV/AIDS, HPV, high cholesterol, high blood pressure, chronic heart, lung, and kidney disease;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H149BFEC1E3004DEEBA24347DC91C02D2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>morbidity and mortality, including the rates of morbidity and mortality associated with the health conditions listed in subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32242A4E5D9E43809688F5B5E6C34BCD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>mental health and substance use disorders; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A5D13AD3AB144FAA7655A7B1D5845CE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, sexual harassment, and stalking;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H03705CEC8047495D89D7E7DA5E091E4D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>analysis of—</text><subparagraph id="HD94D0C93769D4344A4A6E0BEA5266055"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the rates described in paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7ECE86C5FB25418AB1CB754FFCC9E7C6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the leading causes of pregnancy-associated morbidity and mortality; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0FCF4C8428F44DAB59DC4F034F95740"><enum>(C)</enum><text>access to health care facilities and the associated outcomes of care;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC30D3284613843929242DD722150DC20"><enum>(3)</enum><text>analysis, enumeration, or quantification of any other health or health-related parameters the Secretary may deem necessary; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H13EB06103CE34B3CB0A47AB073184E4C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>analysis of the relationship between the health factors, outcomes, and conditions described in paragraphs (1) through (3) and the implementation of Federal health programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA1658D0A2A6A4B74A05F9398DB69248A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H22E2C89801F94EDFB8207DA6A24460AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out this section in consultation, as appropriate, with the Director of the Census Bureau, the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Director of the National Institutes of Health, the Assistant Secretary for Mental Health and Substance Use, and other stakeholders (including community-based organizations); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7420570E7164D35BD3F4F43BBDAEEB9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>determine through such consultation the subpopulations to be used for purposes of disaggregation of data pursuant to subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0E80BDDEF2934849A13EE5F5B80006B8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text>The Secretary shall conclude the comprehensive study under this section not later than two years after the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1487EA63090447608088F6E9AEBAA047"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Online portal</header><text>Upon conclusion of the comprehensive study under this section, the Secretary shall establish a public online portal to catalogue the results of the study, its underlying data, and information in the report submitted pursuant to subsection (f).</text></subsection><subsection id="H29DECAF9B0804CFBB5FC49E324099E4E"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the conclusion of the comprehensive study under this section, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report describing—</text><paragraph id="HD2D3BE9B87F746B1B383FC3D10962483"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the study; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07605338D21D4B14B8001AD60A155938"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the rulemakings and other actions the agencies described in subsection (c)(1) can undertake to more equitably include MENA individuals in their programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B47B79B76044AFAA3E0BC6B2929DDEF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Privacy</header><text>The Secretary shall not include any personally identifiable information on the online portal under subsection (e) or in the report under subsection (f).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

