<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H92AD7881641F447B8C7623ADFC772A96" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1607 RH: To clarify jurisdiction with respect to certain Bureau of Reclamation pumped storage development, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 213</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1607</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–264]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230314">March 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231103">November 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231103">November 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on March 14, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To clarify jurisdiction with respect to certain Bureau of Reclamation pumped storage development, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HII00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H5978807F2415439CA1F8745CC3771C8B"><section id="H6D4B53E3E5794EE6BBCCF0AA5AE94EE5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Land withdrawal and reservation</header><subsection id="H199569FFDDB14521A352FD206C014D00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HE65981F52AB144DF9D931C8D1CE65790"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agreement</header><text>The term <quote>Agreement</quote> means the agreement between the United States and the Association dated September 6, 1917, as amended.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3256186DB9884FDAB60914E1065E8BA6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Association</header><text>The term <quote>Association</quote> means the Salt River Valley Water Users’ Association.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69BA4F3969B04EE9B5362B93D688B1B2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered land</header><text>The term <quote>covered land</quote> means the portion of the National Forest System land located on the south side of the Salt River from the March 9, 1903, 1-mile withdrawal area for the Bureau of Reclamation purposes extending an additional 2 miles from the Salt River at Roosevelt Dam to 18.25 river miles downstream, in the State of Arizona, not including the Superstition Mountain Wilderness Area and the Tonto National Monument, as depicted on the Map.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD46ED74B9B1A4A029E5FAE8087B74256"><enum>(4)</enum><header>District</header><text>The term <quote>District</quote> means the Salt River Project Agricultural Improvement and Power District.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD83D4185517647EBB64ABBFE6C25DE20"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Map</header><text>The term <quote>Map</quote> means the map prepared under subsection (e)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC045D0263FE144B9AA486A1CEB5A0225"><enum>(6)</enum><header>SRP</header><text>The term <quote>SRP</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HA3E5539FB3E641D7B37BB06D52F6B9DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the District; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25790D9CD78A4D21A119781E433CEB18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Association.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE7B9877F655B43E3A64BBD9817D59F45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reservation of covered land</header><text>Subject to valid existing rights, the covered land is reserved to the United States, through the Secretary of the Interior, for the exclusive right to use the covered land and interests in the covered land for the development, generation, and transmission of electrical power and energy for the use and benefit of the Salt River Federal Reclamation Project pursuant to the Agreement.</text></subsection><subsection id="H730E23F2D5E94DDAA39E417ACDA661A4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Withdrawal of covered land</header><text>The covered land is permanently withdrawn from—</text><paragraph id="HAD2B53B3542743788185EC4C558349F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>all forms of entry, appropriation, and disposal under the public land laws;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14FD7C9A1466414B91A44F63C377B840"><enum>(2)</enum><text>location, entry, and patent under the mining laws; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3FD2B85EE5649C7AD3F9E4EBAABBD46"><enum>(3)</enum><text>operation of the mineral leasing, mineral materials, and geothermal leasing laws.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H713DC08DAF164C55BB92DCAF6575F58C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Facilities</header><text>With respect to facilities constructed by SRP on the covered land for the development, generation, and transmission of electrical power and energy—</text><paragraph id="H004288186B534E09BA21A3E870CC6AE2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the design and specifications shall conform to Bureau of Reclamation standards, and final designs shall be subject to review and approval by the Secretary of the Interior;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8035E52C3A784B268974772FD755BB3A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>all construction work shall be subject to inspection and approval by the Secretary of the Interior;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8F9FD981319440DB9452C33A0EBDCC1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>upon a determination of substantial completion of such facilities, the Secretary of the Interior shall accept title on behalf of the United States as part of the Salt River Federal Reclamation Project pursuant to—</text><subparagraph id="HD8B8F144F6274C6A9751A49DABD1AFD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>section 6 of the Act of June 17, 1902 (32 Stat. 389, chapter 1093; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/498">43 U.S.C. 498</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H581E79116DDC4AD3A8BA10479488E194"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Agreement; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H834A7265C033408795FC1898471EC081"><enum>(4)</enum><text>SRP shall be responsible for the care, operation, and maintenance pursuant to the Agreement.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA9E441933EF741B9B6A698C8961C6EAE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Map</header><paragraph id="H5BBAB20F46DC4B458EA4AFB28E62ECE0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As soon as practicable after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture shall prepare a map depicting the boundary of the covered land.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9137F3BF103E4B859E02B19ADAF4C7B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>The Map shall be on file and available for public inspection in the appropriate offices of the Forest Service and the Bureau of Reclamation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C3515FF2F6348ADBB2E0C3DBF1C7BE1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Management of covered land</header><text>Management of the covered lands shall be in accordance with the Management Memorandum among the District, United States Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, and the Bureau of Reclamation, dated April 27, 1979, as amended.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4F8B606984844AB8BEE927339BF1740F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Relation to other law</header><paragraph id="HFB27C0239AF14CF8A7142B4D4627948C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Compliance with environmental laws</header><text>The Secretary of the Interior is directed to carry out all necessary environmental compliance under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref>, et seq.), the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531</external-xref>, et seq.), and all other applicable environmental laws and regulations, prior to construction of facilities on the covered land for the development, generation, and transmission of electrical power and energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1CFFB93C90D438391FF17A5540227E3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Lead agency</header><text>The Bureau of Reclamation shall be the lead agency with respect to environmental compliance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E8F22C1556C49ABB707148D3C7E6241"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Withdrawal not major Federal action</header><text>The withdrawal of the covered land shall not constitute a major Federal action under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321</external-xref>, et seq.).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB08294F04ED049169A0AF5EC00B6A99B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Antideficiency</header><text>The United States shall not be liable for failure to carry out any obligation or activity authorized to be carried out under this title (including any such obligation or activity under the Agreement) if adequate appropriations are not provided by Congress expressly to carry out the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231103">November 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

