<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB8FC0CFB38BC4ADF9ED85807B4500BE2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 605 IH: Special Drawing Rights Oversight Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 605</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230127">January 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001058">Mr. Huizenga</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Special Drawing Rights Act in order to strengthen congressional oversight with respect to allocations of Special Drawing Rights by the International Monetary Fund, and to prohibit such allocations for perpetrators of genocide and state sponsors of terrorism without congressional authorization, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H445ECA55D38E402EA3A5C877B58DFCD5" style="OLC"><section id="H853BAF679B8743FC9A1A719D080ED471" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Special Drawing Rights Oversight Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="HF8B63856A9BD40AFA747EAFB35F95054"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="H0E314FF610634A9DBE5CEFF9420197E4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The allocation of Special Drawing Rights (SDRs) through the International Monetary Fund (IMF) creates unconditional liquidity for IMF member countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D038E07BFC740D1B593D0397CDD772F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to article XVIII of the Articles of Agreement of the IMF, allocations of SDRs <quote>shall seek to meet the long-term global need</quote> in reserve assets.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86DCCFD19CDC4150A7D067FACE4E6CC2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>SDRs are allocated in proportion to the quotas of IMF members, such that the G20 alone is entitled to approximately two-thirds of a general allocation. At the same time, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System has swap line arrangements with the central banks of eight G20 members, including the European Central Bank, the Bank of Japan, and the Bank of England, for the purpose of providing sufficient liquidity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCDF610A807244E7A2AF2DA6295146FD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The size of SDR allocations has expanded dramatically, rising from 9,300,000,000 SDRs in 1970–1972, to 12,100,000,000 SDRs in 1979–1981, to 204,000,000,000 SDRs in 2009, with proposals for a new, unilateral allocation that bypasses congressional authorization in an amount of approximately 450,000,000,000 SDRs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE35C33C320A4F0988EE2856384701EF"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Under current law, the Secretary of the Treasury is able to bypass Congress and approve an allocation of SDRs in a manner that provides unconditional liquidity in the following approximate amounts: $41,700,000,000 to the People’s Republic of China; $17,600,000,000 to the Russian Federation; $4,900,000,000 to the Islamic Republic of Iran, and $5,000,000,000 to Venezuela. In addition, current law permits allocations in these amounts to be made in successive years that span two basic periods.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB88F7B9CECB3477A93BE6EEB2E354074"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In the 98th Congress, the House of Representatives passed the bipartisan International Recovery and Financial Stability Act, which would have prohibited new allocations of SDRs without congressional authorization.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4FFB03D9B7704DD78AC4A759B02C3F03"><enum>3.</enum><header>Strengthening congressional oversight</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Special Drawing Rights Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/286q">22 U.S.C. 286q</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1D870F1078CF4FCAB804BB079CD015C8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="HA2AFF070C3A4416AA368322BF03C5EE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>each basic period</quote> and inserting <quote>any 10-year period</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H163241D4432B4672BE850A3CE54FAD66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>25 percent of</quote> before <quote>the United States quota</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H05025B9F2C924A0F896F99453F1C3F0C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="HB31F1B64F825490DA6F3CCD40C598270"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or consent to or acquiesce in such an allocation,</quote> before <quote>without consultations</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H871F6B46E8B44EBDAD8E76CE7543F005"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>90</quote> and inserting <quote>180</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF037965E7C841B2B40F8393E85C1A94"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>Chairman and ranking minority members of</quote> before <quote>the appropriate subcommittees</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H754E03D767A245EDB0A0FAB6B07EAE4E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on allocations for perpetrators of genocide and state sponsors of terrorism without congressional authorization</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(b) of the Special Drawing Rights Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/286q">22 U.S.C. 286q(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA807CCDE6CA7469EADAE750B0DAACED1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H6C289045B5694A228ED811F850ED9D3D" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Unless Congress by law authorizes such action, neither the President nor any person or agency shall on behalf of the United States vote to allocate Special Drawing Rights under article XVIII, sections 2 and 3, of the Articles of Agreement of the Fund to a member country of the Fund, if the President of the United States has found that the government of the member country—</text><subparagraph id="HB0A7DC19B4724C9DAD001CBB8355DD3C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has committed genocide at any time during the 10-year period ending with the date of the vote; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0B458DDF4EE4C93868CBAA830786696"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has repeatedly provided support for acts of international terrorism.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

