<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8A1DC28E111041BB816A1F8A8D3BC9C2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4207 IH: Stopping Bonuses for Unsafe and Unsound Banking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4207</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230620">June 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit a large banking institution from paying discretionary bonus payments when the institution is subject to a Matter Requiring Immediate Attention and does not provide the appropriate Federal banking agency with a remediation plan to correct the matter, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB2990DF6D1104A45B8EDC55142CFC964" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HEE31F4D2A0D449CCB7F2D9EECD97A276" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stopping Bonuses for Unsafe and Unsound Banking Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HDFC1279062AF43DD98E171BBDBDCE60A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Freeze on discretionary bonus payments by large banking institutions in certain circumstances</header> <subsection id="HCB248A1C91F9442989D6556FC27C7FED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the appropriate Federal banking agency issues a <quote>matter requiring immediate attention</quote> (or similar supervisory notice) to a covered banking institution, the institution may not make any discretionary bonus payment to a senior executive officer until the matter is resolved to the satisfaction of the appropriate Federal banking agency.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H83F6E2BCF7764BD89BF635399915DBC9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Remediation plan exception</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to a covered banking institution receiving a <quote>matter requiring immediate attention</quote> (or similar supervisory notice)—</text> <paragraph id="H56AB78050D4F45F1B4EC5D543102CEF1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during the period beginning on the date the covered banking institution receives the <quote>matter requiring immediate attention</quote> (or similar supervisory notice) and ending on the date of the deadline described under paragraph (2) to submit a remediation plan; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB07993A59F1D46DBA3660031BC7D445A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the covered banking institution provides the appropriate Federal banking agency with a remediation plan (which shall include an implementation period) to correct the matter that is accepted by the appropriate Federal banking agency by such deadline as determined by the appropriate Federal banking agency, during the period beginning on the date the remediation plan is accepted and the end of the implementation period.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0C4E0DA767BC425BA8D84A6B04DEEAAA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H3A394EE803CF42A49F4EAF7D74B10714"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered banking institution</header><text>The term <quote>covered banking institution</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HCFA8D6044030442F8B6A42D708EF307F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a bank holding company with more than $50,000,000,000 in consolidated assets;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4E97DCB2B5A148EFBC8C98D150C05994"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a bank subsidiary of a bank holding company described under subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD65B3E442287455F9AAA6DA869B08827"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a bank that does not have a bank holding company and that has more than $50,000,000,000 in consolidated assets.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H38949609C9574A659F1461FD28D68203"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>appropriate Federal banking agency</quote>, <quote>bank</quote>, <quote>bank holding company</quote>, and <quote>Federal banking agency</quote> have the meanings given those terms, respectively, under section 3 of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

