<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBF55A0FFB28B45E18D8311A99E2DA3A9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5245 IH: Science and Technology Agreement Enhanced Congressional Notification Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5245</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230822">August 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the State Department Basic Authorities Act of 1956 to require certain congressional notification prior to entering into, renewing, or extending a science and technology agreement with the People’s Republic of China, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF247D05AA3E94FF7A62027BD3AFDD0F3" style="OLC"><section id="H3B97C720A4F14C538FEA5B777FAF5952" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Science and Technology Agreement Enhanced Congressional Notification Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4169A8055B24478890CFBFFFDBF0E3AE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Enhanced congressional notification regarding science and technology agreements with the People’s Republic of China</header><subsection id="HCFFC9AC646224FCEBBA6A7A10C66F71B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title I of the State Department Basic Authorities Act of 1956 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2651a">22 U.S.C. 2651a et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8C01A70371BB479C9AFDA459516737C7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HB9E458DB17704CC8A4BE43D841E5B178"><enum>64.</enum><header>Congressional notification regarding science and technology agreements with the People’s Republic of China</header><subsection id="HF451E25BE4184545BC649A00E8AC9ECB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State may not enter into, renew, or extend any science and technology agreement with the People’s Republic of China until—</text><paragraph id="HD55E4E437FE5427BB766C1D9E96723DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary submits to the appropriate congressional committees a notification containing each of the matters described in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H851B37F0A48F403497CF5C82534B4F42"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a period of not less than 30 days has elapsed following such submission.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDC344BE312744572B5C1BC30A361574B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters described</header><text>The matters described in this subsection are, with respect to the science and technology agreement for which the notification is submitted, the following:</text><paragraph id="H38299965DE15466AB83DFD393C24BD07"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A written notice of such agreement, including the full text of such agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51D0ECE2DF844AA19F3363D86A223DD6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed justification for such agreement, including an explanation as to why such agreement is in the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09547130BFFB48279375D4F8BAE22723"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the risks and potential effects of such agreement, including any potential for the transfer under such agreement of technology or intellectual property capable of harming the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED725ED58E304E12A5A64D778473CBD9"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed justification for how the Secretary intends to address human rights concerns in any scientific and technology collaboration proposed to be conducted under such agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H89272B66BAA240C48F03A60755A399DB"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the extent to which the Secretary will be able to continuously monitor the commitments made by the People’s Republic of China under such agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H219FA35D15044EC2AF12A7D4C32C09E8"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other information relating to such agreement as may be determined appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA3FB8C53443C4623A45288BF692658B5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H96752D5CC8AA4E22BCBF0678F92FBC71"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H672106225B6440D6A9D8EE0EDEFCF591"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D76B095BDD44ABD80DCBD69DEB3C8AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF023A991112E4664B0D77C2895F27ED8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Science and technology agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>science and technology agreement</quote> means any treaty, memorandum of understanding, or other contract or agreement between the United States and one or more foreign countries for the purpose of collaborating on or otherwise engaging in joint activities relating to scientific research, technological development, or the sharing of scientific or technical knowledge or resources between such countries.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HDFC06F11C2974ACBBCCDF4D6D18A650D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><paragraph id="H8CD562C078B04FA8A39E1B46D66BBEE4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements under section 64 of the State Department Basic Authorities Act of 1956, as added by subsection (a), shall apply with respect to science and technology agreements entered into, renewed, or extended on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1485A8C8E10747E4A42D74E6D382AD9C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Existing agreements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any science and technology agreement between the Secretary of State and the People’s Republic of China in effect as of the date of the enactment of this Act shall be revoked unless, not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State submits to the appropriate congressional committees a notification of such agreement containing each of the matters described in subsection (b) of such section 64.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H517D009942654C6A95FC5BDD5BE34806"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> and <quote>science and technology agreement</quote> have the meanings given such terms in subsection (c) of such section 64.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

