<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HDDC1A61A7DF6421F90F6E13104C99F04" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2577 RH: DHS Suicide Prevention and Resiliency for Law Enforcement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code> 
<calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 189</calendar> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2577</legis-num> 
<associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–237]</associated-doc> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000136">Mr. Vasquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor></action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc> 
<action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction>
<action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on April 13, 2023</action-instruction>
</action> 
<action> 
<action-desc><pagebreak/></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to establish the Law Enforcement Mental Health and Wellness Program, and for other purposes.<pagebreak/></official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HHM00" reported-display-style="italic" id="HC230B63264CC4C8896E7B1B4EEC4AAFE"> 
<section id="H31687B0EABAC4F20A0DB0469617EC315" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DHS Suicide Prevention and Resiliency for Law Enforcement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H94366DF971124E5E9AB56B073C4446DF"><enum>2.</enum><header>DHS Suicide Prevention and Resiliency for Law Enforcement</header> <subsection id="HA985EC0EB1FF40EEB104805A4890536C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Homeland Security Act of 2002 is amended by inserting after section 710 the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HE28CABCFA0784DA8B5B626CDF318C589"> 
<section id="H7862E8329E5647969D46B5F5D08132C5" commented="no"><enum>710A.</enum><header>Suicide prevention and resiliency for law enforcement</header> 
<subsection id="H3E3AC8017D024D238699D6C46F81F03A" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Department components defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>Department components</term> means the following:</text> <paragraph id="H11CCE96A5767425EABCA621CA3D81790" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF55691DB454541E8B8EA490C8070355E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF08282A309244792AC33C54FA8F47D81" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of the Inspector General of the Department of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEE93B4FB02C046E9843B0351A8F69AB4" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Secret Service.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD87F138919E4705B29F3DCC82D8FE2C" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Transportation Security Administration.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H52D9ACDFF7404B75A954F7DA25622E60" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other Department component with law enforcement officers or agents.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFC4DF326899D466697C53CBB8EB8887F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Law Enforcement Mental Health and Wellness Program</header> <paragraph id="HD1E037DBBEB6400DB1E2A21396D394C9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header> <subparagraph id="HF30743DA111A4BEB8536C6F78180909E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish, within the office overseen by the Chief Medical Officer of the Department, the Law Enforcement Mental Health and Wellness Program (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAA6F0246037F47F1AE19F437197EF79D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the Program shall be to provide a comprehensive approach to address the mental health and wellness of Department law enforcement officers and agents.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8FB3E315CD494AA09274E2F2FFB802A2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The Secretary, working through the Program, shall—</text> 
<clause id="H9F1997A525F345569566A3008B2CF4E6"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish and maintain policies and standard operating procedures, consistent with best evidence-based practices, that detail the authority, roles, and responsibilities of the Program;</text></clause> <clause id="HF0FAFE2D1FB54ED49E4EAB2245E654B9" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct data collection and research on mental health, suicides, and, to the extent possible, attempted suicides, of Department law enforcement officers and agents, in accordance with section 552a of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the Privacy Act of 1974), section 501 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/791">29 U.S.C. 791</external-xref>), the Department’s directives and policies, and section 2(a) of the Law Enforcement Suicide Data Collection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/143">Public Law 116–143</external-xref>);</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9694CC7908FA4A018CBC94D9B7A1973A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>track current trends and leading practices from other governmental and nongovernmental organizations for law enforcement mental health and wellness;</text></clause> <clause id="H10563F6D3B9C40CDB18F9175ECD6D039"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>evaluate current mental health and resiliency programs within the Department components;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCFB09EE0C0F84D11B5842F67370E72C3"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote education and training related to mental health, resilience, suicide prevention, stigma, and mental health resources to raise mental health awareness, and provide support to others, inclusive of the needs of supervisors, clinicians, care-givers, peer support members, chaplains, and those who have been exposed to trauma; </text></clause> <clause id="HB064BF8257604148B645D0BD87593E45"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>establish a Peer-to-Peer Support Program Advisory Council, which shall—</text> 
<subclause id="H9D028B6383244609B4B1A34A3FB4B2B1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>include at least one licensed clinician and at least one official with requisite and relevant training and experience in peer support from each Department component;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H3BA3CF8BCC284EC9AD33F132D937E29E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>evaluate component peer support programs;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HA348D010938046DC9976EEFDF947A86D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>identify and address any potential deficiencies, limitations, and gaps;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HAA1E168A81E7456E811A9C0F0ED0A1B2"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>provide for sharing of leading practices or best practices, including internationally recognized peer support standards of care protocols;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8EC8A67EB8804D7197D7F0B65B424628"><enum>(V)</enum><text>create a peer support network that enables the sharing of trained peer support personnel, chaplains, and other peer-to-peer personnel across Department components; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H55823EC48ADF466CB650E6527EFD9409"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>sustain peer support programs through ongoing funding of annual and refresher training and resources for peer support programing in the workplace to—</text> 
<item id="HEFD4416E4A6F4C58BE45B722A7D8D731"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>ensure minimum standards for peer support services; and </text></item> <item id="HADD82C65F426480E926FFFFC93D387C6"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>provide appropriate care for peer support personnel across Department components; </text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H2589076B67004C498123098DBA0FD676"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>assist Department components in developing a program to provide suicide prevention and resiliency support and training for—</text> <subclause id="HEA010CFF3E3C4CD185DF2D9FA7639E90"><enum>(I)</enum><text>families of Department law enforcement officers and agents; and </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HC69C19C53E4D447D997053BDE4B7D20E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>surviving families of officers and agents who have been lost to suicide;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H9CC9A4192A2F4BEE8571950A34CCABE6"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>work with law enforcement mental health and wellness program officials of Department components (including peer support-trained personnel, agency mental health professionals, chaplains, and, for components with employees having an exclusive representative, the exclusive representative with respect to such program) to implement new policies, procedures, and programs that may be necessary based on findings from data collection, research, and evaluation efforts; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H68A0AF1FB9E64D3B85EA36653E6EF0E9"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>conduct regular outreach and messaging, across Department components, of available training opportunities and resources.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H95165E8545684C61A7D87E96FA6F8EE1"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Confidentiality; limitation</header> <clause id="HEF5B0E597AC240168EF805D24D4D5686"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Activities described in subparagraph (C) may not include the publication of any personally identifiable information.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2F8A04FD782D4A93AD58AABA99A12801" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Personally identifiable information collected pursuant to subparagraph (C) may not be maintained or used for any purpose other than implementation of this section, unless otherwise permitted under applicable law. Any such personally identifiable information that is so collected, maintained, or used pursuant to this section is subject to applicable public nondisclosure requirements, including sections 552 and 552a of title 5, United States Code.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F7870AD1BDB45ABB63C28A2166FA177"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Personnel</header> <clause id="H5FFA06ACEF87428C92357AE627555073" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Management</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Workplace Health and Wellness Coordinator of the Department, under the direction of the Chief Medical Officer of the Department, shall be responsible for the ongoing management of the Program.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0D126EBEB3B146359A15559EB3812923"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Minimum core personnel requirements</header><text>Subject to appropriations, the Secretary shall ensure the Program is staffed with the number of employees the Chief Medical Officer of the Department determines necessary to carry out the duties described in subparagraph (C), including representatives from each Department component and the Office of the Chief Privacy Officer.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB178B4AD9AFB4634902A5C3D9586FDF3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Directive</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Chief Medical Officer of the Department shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDF086088952A41DF87BE6C23A6968AB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>issue a directive or policy that outlines the roles and responsibilities of the Program; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAB0105F5418F44928B16E6E8298192AC" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>distribute such directive or policy among all Department personnel.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1C561D266B54498E867FE702215FD74A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Chief Medical Officer of the Department shall require the Program to regularly coordinate with the Department components by assigning at least one official from each such component to the Program for the purpose of coordinating with field points of contact who are responsible for carrying out duties within Department mental health and wellness programs.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBCC635BBC2E2448A93233D09FAB07809" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Department components</header><text>The Secretary shall require the head of each Department component to prioritize and improve mental health and wellness programs that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7749A52F4B724BE9B2DEECE3D423C250" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide adequate resources for law enforcement mental health, well-being, resilience, and suicide prevention programs and research;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8A3E50A14F7D4FCBA4824BC411E610B8" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote a culture that reduces the stigma of seeking mental health assistance through regular messaging, training, and raising mental health awareness;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H71D378EC4B6C4D27A822FC72BE855D19" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer several avenues of seeking mental health or counseling assistance, both within the component and through private sources that provide for anonymity and include access to external mental health clinicians, service animals, and any other appropriate, data-driven resources that improve mental health;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H34642E4AE9EE45FC903C11A449F2C023" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review and revise relevant policies of Department components that inadvertently deter personnel from seeking mental health or counseling assistance;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0D3A2301E0FD42F28AA3C11C0CDAD4C9" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that such programs include safeguards against adverse or disciplinary action, including retaliation or automatic referrals for a fitness for duty examination, by such component with respect to any employee solely because such employee self-identifies a need for psychological health counseling or assistance or receives such counseling or assistance; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA54620FC0B364CCEA52C8908B8DF75A6" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">implement policies that require in-person or live and interactive virtual suicide awareness and law enforcement resiliency trainings to be provided to law enforcement officers and agents;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC0E1BFA48E73474997F78BE0E55B22C4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>makes such trainings available, as appropriate, to other component personnel—</text> <subparagraph id="H3BBFCCD7F08B4E88843EE7C00932AE6B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">upon the commencement of such officers’, agents’, and other component’s personnel’s employment;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB9E897DFACAD4942B960877A21D772D5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on an annual basis during such employment; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H06FB4DF191AC4E70A53CD300CDB90A40" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during such officers’, agents’, or other component’s personnel’s transition into supervisory roles; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1A68AF949C4C416E8A32CA07024FC4AE" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if feasible, shortly before such officer, agent, or other component’s personnel terminates his or her employment with the Department, if such officer, agent, or other component’s personnel elects to participate; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF3BC601547864565959FB02B3EA1C365" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include prevention and awareness training opportunities and support services for families of agents, officers, and other component personnel.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H472E9466705C43A98B742139F87CA2EF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Data collection and evaluation</header> 
<paragraph id="H8AF4E1A112B4481FBDFE3E6231A66194"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assessment of effectiveness of law enforcement health and wellness programs</header><text>The Workplace Health and Wellness Coordinator, under the direction of the Chief Medical Officer of the Department—</text> <subparagraph id="HE3660FBB16EF4BABA8B31360ED4E2915"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall—</text> 
<clause id="HF40B44721BE54E9C9B2A634D36884D57"><enum>(i)</enum><text>develop criteria to assess the effectiveness of law enforcement health and wellness programs carried out by the Department;</text></clause> <clause id="H6363E26BA26E4F929EFFFB66155D5281" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>conduct annual confidential surveys of law enforcement officers and agents within Department components to assist in evaluating the effectiveness of law enforcement health and wellness programs in accordance with the criteria developed pursuant to clause (i); and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1E65F4376B11476BA80305AA1E583AC0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>ensure that the surveys conducted pursuant to clause (ii)—</text> <subclause id="HEFBE8B4027B340489BDF696324E48579"><enum>(I)</enum><text>incorporate leading practices in questionnaire and survey design and development; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HD4C8D32CC55C4AC5A3682607A6E76F53"><enum>(II)</enum><text>establish a baseline and subsequently measure change over time; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H436A5EF354624546B196DC063B379A6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may utilize contractor support in carrying out the duties described in subparagraph (A). </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H47A4AB2DFD6044D7B284D158B0C33E8A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The Chief Medical Officer of the Department shall provide recommendations to Department components based on the evaluation of programs and the results of the surveys conducted pursuant to paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0228AF998AF4559AA94ECF069E4BA89" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Incident reports</header><text>Each Department component shall report to the Workplace Health and Wellness Coordinator incidents of suicide involving law enforcement officers and agents, together with any data relating thereto consistent with data collected under section 2(a) of the Law Enforcement Suicide Data Collection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/143">Public Law 116–143</external-xref>). The Coordinator shall forward such information to the Law Enforcement Officers Suicide Data Collection Program established pursuant to such section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF5679F43908245D897B0A1BA6929B375" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Confidentiality; limitation</header> 
<subparagraph id="H630EC540FE6A4B12B3DE799EA9A1C4AC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Activities described in paragraph (1) or reporting described under paragraph (3) may not include the publication of any personally identifiable information.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBDAC6CE8E5684A37B284106DF4A5CE05" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Personally identifiable information collected pursuant to paragraph (1) may not be maintained or used for any purpose other than implementation of this section, unless otherwise permitted under applicable law. Any such personally identifiable information that is so collected, maintained, or used pursuant to this section is subject to applicable public nondisclosure requirements, including sections 552 and 552a of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7C5C76F2338C4EB3835489C5A58065A4" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section and annually thereafter through fiscal year 2027, the Chief Medical Officer of the Department shall provide to the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="SSGA00">Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate </committee-name>a briefing regarding the implementation of this section. </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H39585A3B4C634A6A9AD11E648C94F497"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 710 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H16780F5192174FAF870120BDD8AC9753" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">Sec. 710A. Suicide prevention and resiliency for law enforcement.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
<endorsement display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231002">October 2, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement> 
</bill> 


