<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5D1646D36C144898B263CF5719FF583A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1710 IH: Office of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1710</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230322">March 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Office of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy and strategic national manufacturing policy for the United States, to provide manufacturing and industrial perspective and advice to the President, to provide for a comprehensive survey and cross administration management of efforts to ensure global leadership in manufacturing critical to the long-term economic health and national security of the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H80520147F9224AE7A768957AFB1A9344" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H89F72E4134524B94B2F9D14D97EE8928"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H7568DBFB8CE34EA19253C47DF0AAE1D3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Office of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC0A0C3B63F0D4F569DAC28F1E5536416"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents is as follows: </text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H89F72E4134524B94B2F9D14D97EE8928" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB992511A3719453397DA4638ED64A592" level="title">Title I—National Manufacturing Policy and Priorities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H167ABBC306CD46DF8C55971A40392776" level="section">Sec. 101. Findings.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5B56765EEF854C10BBD38FA8112C3AE5" level="section">Sec. 102. Sense of Congress.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H59F0450333DB4E9B9B4DB35FAA7F7F8E" level="title">Title II—Office of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5A8513768D3F4BD2A541350DC626BB34" level="section">Sec. 201. Establishment.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDCE84DB9F1F8403BB171A4F57624E291" level="section">Sec. 202. Chief Manufacturing Officer; Associate Manufacturing Officers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H67C13A886A7D4FC58B27CB820813979B" level="section">Sec. 203. Policy planning, analysis, and advice.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5AE372264A62430A97A8FCAAC4714451" level="section">Sec. 204. National strategic plan for manufacturing and industrial innovation.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCB151D0943284EDBA4F4E67CB74EE8F1" level="section">Sec. 205. Additional Functions of the Chief Manufacturing Officer; Administrative Provisions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H00120C8A6F544575924C3C6AF11C78E8" level="section">Sec. 206. Manufacturing and industrial innovation report.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H79590C358CEC4EB4B6A67D1B3D1498D4" level="section">Sec. 207. Comptroller General Report.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBD12468CF98F4383AD83291CD0FDCC05" level="title">Title III—President’s Advisory Committee on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1E141F480F6240DE9E071EEEA0F56A96" level="section">Sec. 301. Establishment.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA8B9BDF0B69D454D8A8DEA28423AE170" level="section">Sec. 302. Membership.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC658A117F2C6421082B0938470F401A9" level="section">Sec. 303. Federal Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Survey.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5DCCB016B45140BE9007F5D2CE20F569" level="section">Sec. 304. Continuation of Committee.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3C3A95DD51834497A04E08D9A25E042E" level="section">Sec. 305. Staff and consultant support.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H393F2259252B4D62BA9688F47624BEBB" level="title">Title IV—Federal Strategy and Coordinating Council on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE711108F55E7452482A7600303A4737B" level="section">Sec. 401. Establishment.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA9B2A072503541ED9A4D0F861993C62D" level="section">Sec. 402. Membership.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H27DDE28F0D374C608C138EADA632A365" level="section">Sec. 403. Council on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Efforts.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB0A7297493654EB28F1A63719CB6A918" level="section">Sec. 404. Coordination.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBD2DAEED06CB4862820251E688818FBD" level="section">Sec. 405. Administration.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H430B7D16B2A6421C923599D12864CBC0" level="title">Title V—Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy Institute</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HCA738448B1B04A02B73363AEA3AA758F" level="section">Sec. 501. Establishment.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1A067F40571C4325AEF2959C5AA26710" level="section">Sec. 502. Incorporation.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0264CF94732C40C890A37675EF1F9A73" level="section">Sec. 503. Duties.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD37CCA45C0574A8784134132499B8253" level="section">Sec. 504. Consultation of Institute activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6ACB2FE364624824A0DBA1D8FD6637E0" level="section">Sec. 505. Annual Reports.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3230AB4B44634D5EA59DDB07E66325DA" level="section">Sec. 506. Sponsorship.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H678FE91D247644B894F9F63D93F191D0" level="title">Title VI—National Medal of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBAD42184B0B345B7A830BDFB5BF09FE1" level="section">Sec. 601. Award.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H6381FF599BB24EBF886ED1B2754B6439" level="title">Title VII—General Provisions</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7983C7B732C44330A360317783039D7F" level="section">Sec. 701. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><title id="HB992511A3719453397DA4638ED64A592"><enum>I</enum><header>National Manufacturing Policy and Priorities</header><section id="H167ABBC306CD46DF8C55971A40392776" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>101.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress, recognizing the profound historical role that all aspects of manufacturing, including research and development, engineering, skilled trades, and production, has played in the economy and society of the United States, and in the economic and innovative standing of the United States in the global community, and the interrelations of robust manufacturing on economic, environmental, national security, social, political, and institutional factors, finds that—</text><paragraph id="H6FF9329BC64D4428B56149DFAAFA4712"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the general welfare, security, and economic health and stability of the United States require a long-term, substantial, coordinated, and multidisciplinary strategy and implementation of cohesive objectives to remain at the forefront of industrial innovation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61C8B9C1781540CD9008DBFBE989B694"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the large and complex innovative and technological capabilities of global supply chains and manufacturing economies, which influence the course of national and international manufacturing and innovative relevance, require appropriate attention, including long-range inclusive planning and more immediate program development, to encourage and support private manufacturing growth in the United States and participation in the public decision-making process;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB569A82D39604D95A53098738ACB8F5D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the innovative and manufacturing capabilities of business in the United States, when properly fostered, applied, and supported, can effectively assist in improving the quality of life of people in the United States, in anticipating and addressing emerging international, national, and local problems, and strengthening the international economic engagement and pioneering leadership of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD39ADF5D667403BB0C2B5AE05E7C95E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>just as Federal funding for science and technology represents an investment in the future, strategically addressing gaps in the innovation pipeline of the United States would—</text><subparagraph id="H69061838575948C5859E38896D7E7F58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>contribute to converting research and development investments into high-value, quality job-creating product production and capture domestic and global markets; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F18D48B21AF47F1AA553A4686114434"><enum>(B)</enum><text>strengthen the economic posture of the United States; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3DEDF69E76334612BE38B3CD807760D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the capabilities of the United States at both the Federal and State levels need enhanced strategic planning and influence over policy formulation for industrial innovation and technology development, as well as a means to ensure an adequate workforce.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H5B56765EEF854C10BBD38FA8112C3AE5"><enum>102.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><subsection id="HE1AB1522BB20452EADCD6FC5F8E2E4C8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Priority goals</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that manufacturing and industrial innovation should include contributing to the following priority goals:</text><paragraph id="H57A2402097A0406FABC15B5081EFD4EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Taking concrete national action to rebuild, restore, and expand domestic manufacturing capabilities, skills, and production capacity, including world-class infrastructure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02DC538B7C4E4D7A9233D34AD6FEE0E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Rebuilding the industrial innovation commons, to include common resources, technical knowledge, and entrepreneurial opportunities associated with technical ideas.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECF0BF476E674CCFB0C6070519C4E39A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Supporting domestic supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H40C94E265F474ED5AD70FF95495EA4BF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Expanding production capabilities, cooperation, and knowledge.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H993247DA6E874FA1A33B8847C41224B8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Revitalizing communities harmed by historical and poorly conceived, implemented, and enforced regulatory and trade policies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E4FB15E83A8464AA5896F2B35B6FA78"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing a strategy for innovation and establishment of manufacturing industries of the future, including adoption and production of Industry 4.0 technology to support domestic economic expansion, particularly manufacturers with fewer than 800 employees, and in traditionally underserved communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86B9342BA49845F3870F1663FF20CBCB"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Contributing to national health and security and emergency readiness and resilience, including addressing environmental concerns.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9442DD5794644BBEA2A719211E147C10"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Strengthening the economy of the United States and promoting full employment in high-quality, high-wage jobs through useful industrial and technological innovation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F47E35F8E0547559E000A7FA44077EC"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cultivating, utilizing, and enhancing academic and industrial thought-leadership with practical workforce development and training to the fullest extent possible.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6ACDC9EA9784A298FFAAF4BEE2F44C5"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Implementing a national strategy that identifies and prioritizes high growth, high value-added industries, products, and components of national importance to the long-term economic, environmental, national security, and public health of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H13057D262AE342DE89BBC43CA3768E74"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National policy</header><text>In view of the findings under section 101, it is the sense of Congress that the Federal Government and public and private institutions in the United States should pursue a national policy of manufacturing and industrial innovation that includes the following principles:</text><paragraph id="H05B0F782254F46EE939F1D4F08F754BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Ensuring global leadership in advanced manufacturing technologies critical to the long-term economic, environmental, national security, and public health of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85C1E436C87F4F249B20073AE4E0D749"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Restoring and strengthening the industrial commons of the United States, which include—</text><subparagraph id="H7AF9939E59284C32B540228384C1F0D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>essential engineering and production skills;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H130FE2E5A7D04FEAA22901D682492DD9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>infrastructure for research and development, standardization, and metrology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF24C9F7CD52C4CABAA07E89568F7C8E5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>process innovations and manufacturing know-how;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H857F3E40F4B746E6953347186EAD8570"><enum>(D)</enum><text>equipment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00048C9EE7D644DA8341DA7538631C50"><enum>(E)</enum><text>suppliers that provide the foundation for the innovativeness and competitiveness of all manufacturers in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0404634876814E37B1AB4FEEAD6D51CC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Strengthening the technical, financial, and educational commons and assets necessary to ensure that the United States is the best positioned nation for the creation and production of advanced technologies and products emerging from national research and development investments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D748F561AD043F5B2674FCD958C6273"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Capitalizing on the scientific and technological advances produced by researchers and innovators in the United States by developing capable and responsive institutions focused on advancing the technology and manufacturing readiness levels of those advances.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4EC0D110FEB4995AE3814A65B287DB6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Supporting the discovery, invention, start-up, ramp-up, scale-up, and transition of new products and manufacturing technologies to full-scale production in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H873D7455728D4EA99111265B960D90E6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Addressing the evolving needs of manufacturers for a diverse set of workers with the necessary skills, training, and expertise as manufacturers in the United States increase high-quality, high-wage employment opportunities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1B7F3B1678545849C8BCC96518F402E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Improving and expanding manufacturing engineering and technology offerings within institutions of higher education, including 4-year engineering technology programs at polytechnic institutes and secondary schools, to be more closely aligned with the needs of manufacturers in the United States and the goal of strengthening the long-term competitiveness of such manufacturing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD8A573870844B9FB34772D022ECCF21"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Working collaboratively with Federal agencies, State and local governments, Tribal governments, regional authorities, institutions of higher education, economic development organizations, and labor organizations that primarily represent workers in manufacturing to leverage their knowledge, resources, applied research, experimental development, and programs to foster manufacturing in the United States so as to anticipate and prepare for emergencies and global, national, and regional supply chain disruptions, including disruptions brought on and exacerbated by changing environmental and other circumstances.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA88BD63620DA4803BF02DA4D145AFC67"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Recognizing that, as changing circumstances require the periodic revision and adaptation of this title, the Congress is responsible for— </text><subparagraph id="H1A8F4967CA734A9F81F4354D230CEA07"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifying and interpreting the changes in those circumstances as they occur; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B97F12E7FDE451BAFEBDDBFE21B6F40"><enum>(B)</enum><text>affecting subsequent changes to this title as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6EBC23C86864472B8C8AFB664265126B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that, in order to expedite and facilitate the implementation of the national policy described in subsection (b)—</text><paragraph id="HD37DB7FDC79E4EF98D52AE7780DC6999"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Federal procurement policy should—</text><subparagraph id="H1C0C80F5E022431691B418D9AD80E489"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prioritize and encourage domestic manufacturing and robust domestic supply chains;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8FF96781ECD4866A2E87FA88FB12617"><enum>(B)</enum><text>support means of expanding domestic manufacturing job creation; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A7DF86A568145D89326BEAD452F5A44"><enum>(C)</enum><text>enhance manufacturing workforce preparedness;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HAA58E33EC485495C9073DA01BCE10BD8"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prioritize the development of means to support diversity and inclusion throughout the manufacturing and industrial sector;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HFC3906C1DDB34E2CADC0D05446A3FF62"><enum>(E)</enum><text>promote the consideration of, and support to, minority-owned and women-owned manufacturing contractors of the Federal Government; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H00BAC6452A994297B631EA1C42DCB0DA"><enum>(F)</enum><text>support the ingenuity and entrepreneurship of the United States by providing enhanced attention to manufacturing startups and small businesses in the United States;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F46AD9404BA49A996FC23516638E8CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Federal trade and monetary policies should—</text><subparagraph id="HF1AA6FEC0F7D45F5B67D65B40042ECC7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensure that global competition in manufacturing is free, open, and fair;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66CF9370FBFA4F4B9A44D23969B62774"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prioritize policies and investments that support domestic manufacturing growth and innovation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H256A66CEFAD342C28ADA5CD4FA535F02"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not be utilized to offshore poor manufacturing working conditions or destructive manufacturing environmental practices;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F8918EA9B36492FBD6FC36A72EE4F36"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Federal policies and practices should reasonably prioritize competitiveness for manufacturing and industrial innovation efforts in the United States, but should not sacrifice the quality of employment opportunities, including the health and safety of workers, pay, and benefits;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C0BE40BF48D46DC80C80959039E83FF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Federal manufacturing and industrial innovation policies, practices, and priorities should reasonably improve environmental sustainability within the manufacturing industry, while minimizing economic impact;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79829DC56AFD4AB98EE7BA383CAB5EAA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Federal patent policies should be developed, based on uniform principles, which have as their objective to preserve incentives for industrial technological innovation and the application of procedures that will continue to assure the full use of beneficial technology to serve the public;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF6F8DFE1C0A4A2C8F9521655A6E1B21"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal efforts should promote and support a strong system of intellectual property rights to include trade secrets, through both protection of intellectual property rights and enforcement against intellectual property theft, and broad engagement to limit foreign efforts to illegally or inappropriately utilize compromised intellectual property;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83F1067BE9C0425881883DD7A33E5F8D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>closer relationships should be encouraged among practitioners of scientific and technological research and development and those who apply those foundations to domestic commercial manufacturing;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5398B2F79934AA5BEFCD891CE56F059"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the full use of the contributions of manufacturing and industrial innovation to support State and local government goals should be encouraged;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F4D6C63CB9149E7B29C858B97043FDA"><enum>(9)</enum><text>formal recognition should be accorded to those persons, the manufacturing and industrial innovation achievements of which contributed significantly to the national welfare; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81D8974DC26243949FC13A1A9741AD23"><enum>(10)</enum><text>departments, agencies, and instrumentalities of the Federal Government should establish procedures to ensure among them the systematic interchange of data, efforts, and findings developed under their programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10C9A9D7463A427D950475344A3AE598"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>To implement the national policy described in subsection (b), it is the sense of Congress—</text><paragraph id="H81AB8341344F424FA11338694F7E6D18"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that—</text><subparagraph id="H2C4893B130BB4EAABEBCBD9ACEC9C799"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Federal Government should maintain integrated policy planning elements in the executive branch that assist agencies in such branch in—</text><clause id="H4C171977F1884FDC87563A29EB4C21E6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identifying problems and objectives that could be addressed or enhanced by public policy;</text></clause><clause id="H7D3F3FCB902F42EB93D85E06BB11D303"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>mobilizing industrial and innovative manufacturing resources for national security and emergency response purposes;</text></clause><clause id="H6589FCC37F7A48DF8767AB14D75E68FF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>securing appropriate funding for programs so identified by the President or the Chief Manufacturing Officer;</text></clause><clause id="H815A22E9B1E24834B270424AC88BAC2D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>anticipating future concerns to which industrial and innovative manufacturing can contribute and devise industrial strategies for such purposes; and</text></clause><clause id="HB4FD002171304CBBB454FAE615C074F3"><enum>(v)</enum><text>reviewing systematically the manufacturing and industrial innovation policy and programs of the Federal Government and recommending legislative amendments to those policies and programs when needed; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B901349772F4B9A80FC56E4EC7E76DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the elements described in subparagraph (A) should include a data collection, analysis, and advisory mechanism within the Executive Office of the President to provide the President with independent, expert judgment and assessments of the complex manufacturing and industrial features involved; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C60839291134D5BB0755F6545C4E41C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that it is the responsibility of the Federal Government to—</text><subparagraph id="HBF3E937C61D04549A86A892CA191F0BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote prompt, effective, reliable, and systematic dissemination of manufacturing and industrial information— </text><clause id="H281B132226D24A75B1DDD8033F494762"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by such methods as may be appropriate; and </text></clause><clause id="H0317C8D0A3324E92B2A01F24576812F6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>through efforts conducted by nongovernmental organizations, including industrial groups, technical societies, and educational entities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37F9EC7D9114424EA753F939423CBB6C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate and develop a manufacturing industrial strategy and facilitate the close coupling of this manufacturing strategy with commercial manufacturing application; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF492C8075FF14D60ABDF580D173ABB6B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enhance domestic development and utilization of such industrial information by prioritization of efforts with manufacturers, the production of which takes place in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H59F0450333DB4E9B9B4DB35FAA7F7F8E"><enum>II</enum><header>Office of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy</header><section id="H5A8513768D3F4BD2A541350DC626BB34"><enum>201.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is established in the Executive Office of the President an Office of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy (referred to in this title as the <quote>Office</quote>) to serve as a source of manufacturing and industrial innovation analysis and judgment for the President with respect to the major policies, plans, and programs of the Federal Government relating to manufacturing and industrial innovation. </text></section><section id="HDCE84DB9F1F8403BB171A4F57624E291"><enum>202.</enum><header>Chief Manufacturing Officer; Associate Manufacturing Officers</header><subsection commented="no" id="HA2C9B47866DB429B9BD429EE09970B87"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Chief Manufacturing Officer</header><paragraph id="HE618CA478ADF40B8ABE37F2F3153DD26"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Office shall be headed by a Director, to be known as the Chief Manufacturing Officer, who shall be— </text><subparagraph id="H781DC1F7485F42038734CD280BFDD7E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FA722E0C5454D4DA0BFEC8AC039FFF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>compensated at the rate provided for level II of the Executive Schedule under section 5313 of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E3392AE3D9E4F3A919F846F506A525C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Functions</header><subparagraph id="HCECF7DC6571648AEB2BC184102A57908"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Primary function</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The primary function of the Chief Manufacturing Officer shall be to advise the President, and such agencies within the Executive Office of the President as may be appropriate, on issues regarding and impacting manufacturing and industrial innovation efforts of the Federal Government, or of the private sector, that require attention at the highest levels of the Federal Government.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC467E824BF34466802FF8CF1767DEFE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Other functions</header><text>The Chief Manufacturing Officer shall—</text><clause id="HE5BC50C647CE48DC8DDF1EE4847E22B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>advise the President on manufacturing and industrial innovation considerations relating to areas of national concern, including— </text><subclause id="H793993AE63AE40F5ABAB7C1C12F01C11"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the economy of the United States; </text></subclause><subclause id="HB5ED2BEB92FF479C882EB53332E42A04"><enum>(II)</enum><text>national security; </text></subclause><subclause id="H226C9C87616E49BAB1243FB47BDD72DB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>public health; </text></subclause><subclause id="HDCED1B42E36C435B9CFA05C5AEE0E071"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the workforce of the United States; </text></subclause><subclause id="H15B7DAE5631740B3B0714C72B77C96F1"><enum>(V)</enum><text>education; </text></subclause><subclause id="HCB58BAAA07114FEE9CEB0F96B6077D9C"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>foreign relations (including trade and supply chain issues); </text></subclause><subclause id="H0EA0334D3DAC4DB49AABFCFB50B7FA38"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>the environment; and </text></subclause><subclause id="HA4474C7F8A244C6C8848E95C62DF3C2E"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>technological innovation in the United States;</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H9BFC22859701442BB9D401518ECE0BD2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">convene stakeholders, including key industry stakeholders, academic stakeholders, defense stakeholders, government stakeholders, and stakeholders from nonprofit organizations and labor organizations that primarily represent workers in manufacturing, to develop the national strategic plan required under section 204; </text></clause><clause id="HB0F04B69F94E4D90A410BD0C1A25CD54"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>evaluate the scale, quality, and effectiveness of the effort of the Federal Government to support manufacturing and industrial innovation by the Federal Government or by the private sector, and advise on appropriate actions;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H9544D30EED12436AAA7E2126BADB9D5A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>advise the President on the budgets of agencies of the executive branch of the Federal Government with respect to issues concerning manufacturing and industrial innovation;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HC16EA51A1B6C4BEC8CA84727B1A30EFA"><enum>(v)</enum><text>assist the Director of the Office of Management and Budget with an annual review and analysis of the budget proposed by the President, with respect to manufacturing and industrial development by agencies in the executive branch;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HEB1B2515E7794CC3AF48E38C1CD02F2C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>aid the Director of the Office of Management and Budget and the heads of agencies of the executive branch of the Federal Government throughout the budget development process, particularly with respect to developing budgets to support manufacturing and industrial development;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H8BE83FD171434258AC4CFBAEA16C6DD8"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>assist the President in providing general leadership and coordination of activities and policies of the Federal Government relating to and impacting manufacturing and industrial innovation; and</text></clause><clause id="H1ADAF6939B1B4622B560004DD93C344D"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perform such other functions, duties, and activities as the President may assign.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0AF022DA851D49F68E51B10657141828"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Authorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the duties and functions under this Act, the Chief Manufacturing Officer may—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF22B36381B2B421EB68C5811AACDC4E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>except for the positions described in subsection (b), appoint such officers and employees as may be deemed necessary to perform the functions vested in the position and to prescribe the duties of such officers and employees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HCFFD0ED028E34963B1C2C22820E6A342"><enum>(B)</enum><text>obtain services as authorized under section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, at rates not to exceed the rate prescribed for grade GS–15 of the General Schedule under section 5332 of title 5, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1097E0CA0D594994945A0D632A7405CB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>enter into contracts and other arrangements for studies, analysis, and other services with public agencies and with private persons, organizations, or institutions, and make such payments as determined necessary to carry out the provisions of this title without legal consideration, without performance bonds, and without regard to section 6101 of title 41, United States Code. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H7BCEB12EAD0E4FB7A8FD8BAC1E544803"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Associate Directors</header><paragraph id="H4FDB506E08A54A8585A75A0482F27A96"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may appoint not more than 5 Associate Directors, to be known as Associate Manufacturing Officers, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate, to carry out such functions as may be prescribed by the Chief Manufacturing Officer. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B2EA03AB11B4AFCA7FAB387527466BD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>Each Associate Manufacturing Officer shall be compensated at a rate not to exceed that provided for level III of the Executive Schedule under section 5314 title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H67C13A886A7D4FC58B27CB820813979B"><enum>203.</enum><header>Policy planning, analysis, and advice</header><subsection id="HCF8E8A1899034B69B5F4E8352C1C557A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the provisions of this Act, the Chief Manufacturing Officer shall—</text><paragraph id="H2D2A06A6DC0B45ECA75DD0BC37127F93"><enum>(1)</enum><text>monitor the status of technological developments, critical production capacity, skill availability, investment patterns, emerging defense needs, and other key indicators of manufacturing competitiveness to— </text><subparagraph id="H9FA48284DE084E6EB2582AE666091933"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide foresight for periodic updates to the national strategic plan required under section 204; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45C0F3250E6C4ECF86BAE18A7003ABEA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>guide investment decisions;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1B9F98A0B56241C08588FE277FFAE7DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>convene interagency and public-private working groups to align Federal policies that drive implementation of the national strategic plan required under section 204; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0E7AD03D3AA467E9BC556AA4FBA3A30"><enum>(3)</enum><text>initiate and support translational research in engineering and manufacturing by entering into contracts or making other arrangements (including grants, awards, cooperative agreements, loans, and other forms of assistance) to study that research and to assess the impact of that research on the economic well-being, climate and environmental impact, public health, and national security of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBC342B8B5AB4FD8B929BCE7D7DA16DE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>advise the President on the extent to which the various programs, policies, and activities of the Federal Government are likely to affect the achievement of priority goals of the United States described in section 102(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DB3F4D04ABB4ACBAE689C229D4E607A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide the President with—</text><subparagraph id="H8E87500FC6924D2EA24FCFCAAA80E178"><enum>(A)</enum><text>periodic reviews of Federal statutes and regulations that affect manufacturing and industrial innovation activities conducted by the Federal Government or the private sector, or which may interfere with desirable technological innovation; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A6316C1BD9E4F6E81F3AAF13FEB2F3F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations for the elimination, reform, or updating of such Federal statutes and regulations, as appropriate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FC3019D093D49A09C92EDA867955EE8"><enum>(6)</enum><text>periodically survey the nature and needs of the policies relating to national manufacturing and industrial innovation and make recommendations to the President, for review and submission to Congress, for the timely and appropriate revision of the manufacturing and industrial innovation policies of the Federal Government;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11859C9AE9BE4DB5B5F06EE8E59A1397"><enum>(7)</enum><text>perform such other duties and functions and make and furnish such studies and reports thereon, and recommendations with respect to matters of policy and legislation as the President may request; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57B537BA0F4B4BE7BCB59153F066EC3A"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate, as appropriate, Federal permitting with respect to manufacturing and industrial innovation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB37672C161FC40859CA910A95C1E3D41"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Intergovernmental Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Panel</header><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCD3EC2CD1A3433CAB0E807C8A01C56E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Chief Manufacturing Officer shall establish an Intergovernmental Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Panel (referred to in this title as the <quote>Panel</quote>) within the Office, the purpose of which shall be to—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC850853F3E124B548FD135D779FA52E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify instances in which the policies of the Federal Government with respect to manufacturing and industrial innovation can help address problems at the State and local levels;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0ACE3CAB8D9641C1A177126DEB07E256"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify instances in which the policies of the Federal Government unnecessarily impede manufacturing and industry;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB48F404D6A48488EB8A1DE966595CD3D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>make recommendations for addressing the problems described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70685C60F39A4107BF79750E5F79363C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>advise and assist the Chief Manufacturing Officer<italic></italic> in identifying and fostering policies to facilitate the application to and incorporation of federally funded research and development into manufacturing and industrial innovation in the United States, so as to maximize the application of such research.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD9AF8CA1F4E4DB587A1725909934174"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The Panel shall be composed of—</text><subparagraph id="H54C4E304DB884E98A24014495865DDA0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Chief Manufacturing Officer, or a representative of the Chief Manufacturing Officer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HACBECD99DD6D41B38517C6AD858F4C79"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not fewer than 10 members representing the interests of the States, appointed by the Chief Manufacturing Officer after consultation with State officials; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1EAE5BE5E5DC4D40B36807C40F81E8EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Standards and Technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E69DD04E5414467A962E4F896E37210"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H636B8D1542394DFD9A95F2A1FDA71DA2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Manufacturing and Industrial Base Policy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBA73C95F4CD4366BDC24DEBD7D9AC93"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the Assistant Secretary of Labor for Employment and Training;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEA55FACAF494F88B456FE4697356639"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Small Business Administration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49D08F69E18C4789A8E7729B0C0696AE"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Assistant Secretary of Energy for Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H510382278C27488EA9251BBBF9C754B9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The Chief Manufacturing Officer, or the representative of the Chief Manufacturing Officer, shall serve as Chair of the Panel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8156B9E94C14E35ADD551F49B1F540A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Panel shall meet at the call of the Chair.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB07319A5B5EE492AA33E21D6825245E4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Compensation</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="HAC7A15B4AD5448B8AA73160542040CDF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each member of the Panel shall be entitled to receive compensation at a rate not to exceed the daily rate prescribed for GS–15 of the General Schedule under section 5332 of title 5, United States Code, for each day (including travel time) during which the member is engaged in the performance of the duties of the Panel.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCC2EE367760348B98412ACE0191B91DF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>Each member of the Panel who is serving away from the home or regular place of business of the member in the performance of the duties of the Panel shall be allowed travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in the same manner as the expenses authorized by section 5703 of title 5, United States Code, for persons in government service employed intermittently.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5AE372264A62430A97A8FCAAC4714451"><enum>204.</enum><header>National strategic plan for manufacturing and industrial innovation</header><subsection commented="no" id="HD88770EDD78D464ABD4352BDEF03B22B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><paragraph id="H4A3A3572E2974674BE07B9A3BBA85A3F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Chief Manufacturing Officer shall, to the extent practicable, in accordance with section 202(a)(2)(B) and in consultation with other agencies and private individuals as the Chief Manufacturing Officer determines necessary, establish a national strategic plan for manufacturing and industrial innovation that identifies—</text><subparagraph id="H623E1B24DDC94AB68522141693A68527"><enum>(A)</enum><text>short-term, medium-term, and long-term needs critical to the economy, national security, public health, workforce readiness, environmental concerns, and priorities of the United States manufacturing sector, including emergency readiness and resilience; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD517DAB4AF64393B9E5A49449799C1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>situations and conditions that warrant special attention by the Federal Government relating to—</text><clause commented="no" id="HC424FD31BE754A0CA6B85F90D8A60B62"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any problems, constraints, or opportunities of manufacturing and industrial innovation that—</text><subclause commented="no" id="H36C720E6729446E79EE9C0A4D3FB2926"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are of national significance; </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HDE2B660F088F41FCAE02E034B1B1A823"><enum>(II)</enum><text>will occur or may emerge in the 4-year period following the establishment of the national strategic plan; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H0C54229A151641378189956E238A2798"><enum>(III)</enum><text>are identified through basic research; </text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H595509DE471E435AB354C480D079D513"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an evaluation of activities and accomplishments of all agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government that are related to carrying out such plan; </text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H017D7035B29C44F4A025740E64EE5900"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>opportunities for, and constraints on, manufacturing and industrial innovation that can make a significant contribution to— </text><subclause commented="no" id="H89A05BAFD42242B994B76CB1CB5C2B10"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the resolution of problems identified under this paragraph; or </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HECEB0D7CE3AF4F7AB4039D62521CF812"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the achievement of Federal program objectives or priority goals, including those described in section 102(a); and</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HFD7C4D703EA940D28590EDF5FE6813AA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>recommendations for legislation, regulation, and budget proposals to carry out such plan.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCDFA668BAD59487CB617AC702BC3FE45"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Revisions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 4 years after the establishment of the national strategic plan under paragraph (1), and every 4 years thereafter, the Chief Manufacturing Officer shall revise that plan so that the plan takes account of near- and long-term problems, constraints, and opportunities and changing national goals and circumstances. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFBD0C59C1249446899F52B386EF49A54"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation with other agencies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chief Manufacturing Officer shall consult, as necessary, with officials of agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government that administer programs or have responsibilities relating to the problems, constraints, and opportunities identified in the national strategic plan under subsection (a) in order to—</text><paragraph id="HF31D59466D11404EB8EC065D67EAA784"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify and evaluate actions that might be taken by the Federal Government, State, and local governments, or the private sector to deal with such problems, constraints, or opportunities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A6AF337DB3E4799ACDC55D727064721"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure to the extent possible that actions identified under paragraph (1) are considered by each agency of the executive branch of the Federal Government in formulating the budget, programs, and legislative proposals of each such agency. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HF534A68EAEEB472E971BD19BCD7034EC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation with manufacturing stakeholders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chief Manufacturing Officer shall consult broadly with representatives from stakeholder constituencies, including from technology fields, engineering fields, manufacturing fields, academic fields, worker training or credentialing programs, industrial sectors, business sectors, consumer sectors, defense sector, public interest sectors, and labor organizations which primarily represent workers in manufacturing to ensure information and perspectives from such consultations are incorporated within the problems, constraints, opportunities, and actions identified in the national strategic plan under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HD0172A47B4C84766B243CCA7A911E45D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Consultation with OMB</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chief Manufacturing Officer shall consult as necessary with officials of the Office of Management and Budget and other appropriate elements of the Executive Office of the President to ensure that the problems, constraints, opportunities, and actions identified under subsection (a) are fully considered in the development of legislative proposals and the President’s budget.</text></subsection></section><section id="HCB151D0943284EDBA4F4E67CB74EE8F1"><enum>205.</enum><header>Additional Functions of the Chief Manufacturing Officer; Administrative Provisions</header><subsection id="HFD2D96F814CB4024AFAB56D9D14544A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chief Manufacturing Officer, in addition to the other duties and functions under this title, shall serve—</text><paragraph id="H8B05F57709B94C55844D451A535CF976"><enum>(1)</enum><text>on the Federal Strategy and Coordinating Council on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation established under title IV; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HBFD3C82F7AD84D56A20E71406E55ED60"><enum>(2)</enum><text>as a member of the Domestic Policy Council, the National Economic Council, and the Office of Science and Technology Policy Council.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE9F88B01F49E4B2984A1CB748772F7E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Advice to National Security Council</header><text>For the purpose of ensuring the optimal contribution of manufacturing and industrial innovation to the national security of the United States, the Chief Manufacturing Officer, at the request of the President, shall advise the National Security Council in such matters concerning manufacturing and industrial innovation as may be related to national security.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAB08DA3E050748B9A03BEE87E277A08B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination with other organizations</header><paragraph id="HBD527DA4205E484DAE9FDAC4460DACD9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In exercising the functions under this Act, the Chief Manufacturing Officer—</text><subparagraph id="HFB04B0B9AC7F40D091AF710F0BB9AA20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall—</text><clause commented="no" id="HCCF0E83CA7FD4274A7A8D47D52CB22F6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>work in close consultation and cooperation with the Director of the Domestic Policy Council, the National Security Advisor, the Assistant to the President for Economic Policy and Director of the National Economic Council, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, and the heads of other agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government; </text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H9117EE2187294DAA9A1F24AAF4A626AA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilize the services of consultants, establish such advisory panels, and, to the extent practicable, consult with— </text><subclause commented="no" id="HA0749C3355214EAB827D569C25D6DB39"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">State and local government agencies; </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H77E23F770EDE4B5AA2B075539852829F"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">appropriate professional groups; </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HAD2058824CC24A06A8A8BEBD6648EB7C"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">representatives of industry, universities, consumers, labor organizations that primarily represent workers in manufacturing; and </text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HF4C8E0F436F24F0882E493793E517F6A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other public interest groups, organizations, and individuals as may be necessary;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9D526190B0E24BFC99EEB757BC2C6663"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>hold such hearings in various parts of the United States as necessary to determine the views of the agencies, groups, and organizations described in paragraph (2), and of the general public, concerning national needs and trends in manufacturing and industrial innovation; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H053721BF6E7C44708565C12D9F76B7A6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>utilize, with the heads of public and private agencies and organizes, to the fullest extent possible the services, personnel, equipment, facilities, and information (including statistical information) of public and private agencies and organizations, and individuals, in order to avoid the duplication of efforts and expenses; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC5AC22AB94A4EF0811A076A2F3ACDE0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may transfer funds made available pursuant to this Act to other agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government as reimbursement for the utilization of such personnel, services, facilities, equipment, and information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A6FE99CEE624315AC365A3403B189DE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Furnishment of information</header><text>Each department, agency, and instrumentality of the executive branch of the Federal Government, including any independent agency, shall furnish the Chief Manufacturing Officer such information as necessary to carry out this title.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H00120C8A6F544575924C3C6AF11C78E8"><enum>206.</enum><header>Manufacturing and industrial innovation report</header><subsection commented="no" id="HF8DD76F9EF5940D6BB2F16404ED62FD8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 4 years thereafter, the President shall submit to Congress a Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Report (referred to in this Act as the <quote>report</quote>), which shall be prepared by the Chief Manufacturing Officer, with appropriate assistance from agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government and such consultants and contractors as the Chief Manufacturing Officer determines necessary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9E7739D24642456D96219A3028B4CAFC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text>Each report required under subsection (a) shall draw upon the most recent national strategic plan established under section 204 and shall include, to the extent practicable and within the limitations of available knowledge and resources—</text><paragraph id="H546C4116C25D40F9BA506960644C1E71"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a review of developments of national significance in manufacturing and industrial innovation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3BDCEBC5A1EB47C0B193B987A21635E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the significant effects of trends at the time of the submission of the report and projected trends in manufacturing and industrial innovation on the economy, workforce, and environmental, health and national security, and other requirements of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE552C5B485B14CE8B0FB833624EB3BC0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a review and appraisal of selected manufacturing and industrial innovation related programs, policies, and activities of the Federal Government, including procurement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58BAD7DF958B420686A7FD4F308BE304"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an inventory and forecast of critical and emerging national problems, the resolution of which might be substantially assisted by manufacturing and industrial innovation in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC163D67AF1543CC8E922A391C1D539A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the identification and assessment of manufacturing and industrial innovation measures that can contribute to the resolution of the problems described in paragraph (4) in light of the related economic, workforce, environmental, public health, and national security considerations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB953498551D453382B152D3584BC817"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at the time of the submission of the report, and as projected, the manufacturing and industrial resources, including specialized manpower, that could contribute to the resolution of the problems described in paragraph (4); and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE36C778E3C5F4DFEA9D97BA7CB89B475"><enum>(7)</enum><text>recommendations for legislation and regulatory changes on manufacturing and industrial innovation-related programs and policies that will contribute to the resolution of the problems described in paragraph (4).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H6DDA1A089946429AAC9C5209CE894875"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Preparation of report</header><text>In preparing each report required under subsection (a), the Chief Manufacturing Officer shall make maximum use of relevant data available from agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4808EA102972427099143AB5128687B5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public availability of report</header><text>The Chief Manufacturing Officer shall ensure that the report is made available to the public.</text></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H79590C358CEC4EB4B6A67D1B3D1498D4"><enum>207.</enum><header>Comptroller General Report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives, and make available to the public, a report—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HCB1663B4D2D74E6F914F74FBBBD1A0CE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>containing an assessment of the efforts of the Office to implement or advance the priority goals described in section 102(a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66E0D993F877444BB5CE14132EC48959" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing recommendations on how to improve the efforts described in paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></section></title><title commented="no" id="HBD12468CF98F4383AD83291CD0FDCC05"><enum>III</enum><header>President’s Advisory Committee on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation</header><section commented="no" id="H1E141F480F6240DE9E071EEEA0F56A96"><enum>301.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The President shall establish within the Executive Office of the President the President’s Advisory Committee on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation (referred to in this title as the <quote>Committee</quote>), which shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HED04077874FE40C79F89F49D11DD7F07"><enum>(1)</enum><text>promote regular communication between the Federal Government and the manufacturing sector in the United States, including significant communication with representatives of manufacturers with fewer than 800 employees;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6794B35004AC46B082B178B2376EABAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>advise the Chief Manufacturing Officer on policies and programs of the Federal, State, and local governments that affect manufacturing in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD324A0C38CB446038922C6C7E8AA99EC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide a forum for discussing and proposing solutions to industry-related problems; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H52B502E8006C4F548A25AD03E30920DB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>promote efforts to ensure that the United States remains the preeminent destination for investment in manufacturing throughout the world.</text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="HA8B9BDF0B69D454D8A8DEA28423AE170"><enum>302.</enum><header>Membership</header><subsection commented="no" id="HADFC03B77F0D49108B97B7DDCC4039FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Composition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee shall consist of—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H5E0EBE5F74AC41F18206071157825201"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Chief Manufacturing Officer; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCCAE6C58982347EF84C1F9AADF551B7B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>not fewer than 8 and not more than 14 other members, who shall be appointed by the President not more than 60 days after the date on which the Chief Manufacturing Officer assumes office. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HFAB50145AD1444A58A7A7D3B6F3E5E57"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of the Committee appointed by the President under subsection (a)(2) shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HF4A1E0BE7E1647BB8D94B59A320E3938"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be capable of critically assessing the policies, priorities, programs, and activities of the United States, with respect to the findings and policies described in title I; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H2D7C5AE99FE4407F8F5620BB0D82B719"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collectively constitute a balanced composition with respect to—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H59ACFB895DCF4AD0802C952195631A8D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">technology, engineering, manufacturing fields;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F152DD583504BDD856960D5E41EC229"><enum>(B)</enum><text>academic, industrial, and governmental experience,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74A9BFBF714E4B768F612534231E8B50"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the business sector, the consumer sector, the defense sector, the public interest sector, and labor organizations that primarily represent workers in manufacturing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HBC850E840CD94C62B622F16085B33FA0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>regional diversity; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HFCD525F18AFF4C0D85B3A59779360510"><enum>(3)</enum><text>each be qualified and distinguished in not less than 1 of—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H95BA0922C57448DC817AC46AB72E2DFC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>engineering;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H33B9DC3CCD8C427C9E2ABFBEB232727E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>technology;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE9DBF1CC2335431BA2B3E381834659F8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>entrepreneurship;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB309262C316A4BBCBD99CA50775C005F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>manufacturing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0448B36672C74F3BA6B5AA8054ADB50E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>trade;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HBA6CF62964014DBDB42C5B5E3F7C9AC2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>information dissemination;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB3A3EF34E36849AEBBD9DC573F3C7D57"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H304B2D7545804C49BEB3C2DF5D87F4D3"><enum>(H)</enum><text>worker training or credentialing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H958635F45327473E9DB595621E3C7685"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">labor organizations that primarily represent workers in manufacturing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD95692AE74B941DDB1C3A203BEA8CBA1"><enum>(J)</enum><text>public affairs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55E70B7F7E854D299DEA3F86B46EA9E4"><enum>(K)</enum><text>public policy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HF4E0A2C8326D445292A37BF19AAEDC92"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Chair</header><text>The President shall appoint 1 member of the Committee to serve as Chair and another member to serve as Vice Chair, for such periods as the President may determine appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H33DAE9772C1647619B83644619D68EB0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Compensation</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H4285E3370BC544F1A3F5AC060B03546D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each member of the Committee who is not an employee of the Federal Government shall be entitled to receive compensation at a rate not to exceed the daily rate prescribed for GS–15 of the General Schedule under section 5332 of title 5, United States Code, for each day (including travel time) during which the member is engaged in the performance of the duties of the Committee.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF98732A4B49B4EDBAEBB330C86C59BC8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>Each member of the Committee who is serving away from the home or regular place of business of the member in the performance of the duties of the Committee may be allowed travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in the same manner as the expenses authorized by section 5703 of title 5, United States Code, for persons in government service employed intermittently.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="HC658A117F2C6421082B0938470F401A9"><enum>303.</enum><header>Federal manufacturing and industrial innovation survey</header><subsection commented="no" id="H0D1DD882069F46949B9BFA6C27FBF438"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duties of the Committee</header><paragraph commented="no" id="HC995AB4B26F64E708D706AD674586931"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee shall—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB0D595CDA4C44E6CA679922F773C1BCB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">survey, examine, and analyze the overall context of the manufacturing and industrial innovation efforts of the Federal Government, including the mission, goals, personnel, funding, organization, facilities, and activities of those efforts; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5331067905894C1CBC5C0AF503E0B0D8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in carrying out subparagraph (A), take adequate account of the interests of individuals and groups that may be affected by Federal manufacturing and industrial innovation programs, including, as appropriate, by consulting with those individuals and groups.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF53B4B2B9799425EBE0D29E17C147DA3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the functions of the Committee under this section, the Committee shall consider the need for—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HBF616EEBA59D48619E9C6E88AB0B8B15"><enum>(A)</enum><text>organizational reform, including institutional realignment or establishment designed to place within a single cabinet-level department (either within an existing agency or a new cabinet-level department) with missions that are primarily or solely devoted to manufacturing and industrial innovation; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC24B85C1060441BC83B5339633E02ADF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improvements in existing programs and policies of manufacturing and industrial innovation of the Federal Government, including consideration of the appropriate role to be played by the private sector;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB526082FCF1146AC9988284E4BE4233C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>improved manufacturing and industrial innovation assessment in the executive branch of the Federal Government;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H049BEA6ACB1D4326A5B518D4156A4B71"><enum>(D)</enum><text>improved methods for effecting development of manufacturing capabilities, especially capabilities arising from federally funded research;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4FCF721F1ACE4A4DA2943A10599340D1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>stimulating more effective Federal-State and Federal-industry liaison and cooperation in manufacturing and industrial innovation policy, including the formation of Federal-State mechanisms for the mutual pursuit of the shared goal of growing and improving manufacturing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H50BD8FD9DBA44E809E04E33F519C9749"><enum>(F)</enum><text>reforming any Federal regulation or administrative practice or procedure that may have the effect of slowing technological innovation or opportunities for the use of technological innovation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF87C53E5DC734F0CBE3B36C32A433D68"><enum>(G)</enum><text>improvements to Federal research and development activities to make those activities more responsive to industrial needs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4D2572F54EB24692B90C1621ACC85672"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ways of strengthening the competency of academic institutions in the United States for education and workforce training to better foster manufacturing and industrial innovation, capacity, and diversity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7393E143611D4983AA8DECD714791058"><enum>(I)</enum><text>ways of effectively integrating manufacturing and industrial innovation into the national and international policies of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD8E8B1457B22456BA508B7FD4B6FD658"><enum>(J)</enum><text>manufacturing and industrial innovation designed to meet community and individual needs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5D8BF0C3B39E4D48994766789D7967D9"><enum>(K)</enum><text>maintaining the quality and quantity of adequate manufacturing and industrial innovation manpower;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H641F0F7ED1A7453DBE7F731E6E1AA4CE"><enum>(L)</enum><text>improved systems for planning and analyzing Federal manufacturing and industrial innovation programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9D7942905E064C299BBF240DF1DABDED"><enum>(M)</enum><text>long-range study, analysis, and planning with respect to the application of manufacturing and industrial innovation to major national problems or concerns; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62EBDCB22EA444E09854877C782D3263"><enum>(N)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying unnecessary or duplicative regulations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H0CC35BA18A9D414BA1DC622D8837B3C3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA009CBB96054881B7E4C468BC5A43F8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>To the President</header><subparagraph id="H1765430C46AC40929025C6D5DEE71CA2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Interim report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date on which every member of the Committee has been appointed under section 302(a), the Committee shall submit to the President an interim report on the activities and operations of the Committee, as of the date on which the interim report is submitted. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H423872E155624165ACBF60A2BED7ABAF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date on which every member of the Committee has been appointed under section 302(a), the Committee shall submit to the President a final report on the activities, findings, conclusions, and recommendations of the Committee, including any necessary supporting data and material.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HC333A008A4CB4C64AB8FCF4C32BF2E12"><enum>(2)</enum><header>To Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date on which the President receives the final report required under paragraph (1)(B), the President shall submit to Congress—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H138285AAA59744DEB7D065121CDDDC98"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the interim report submitted under paragraph (1)(A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2A266658F3D2424FB0DFFB3A15533C2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the final report submitted under paragraph (1)(B); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H348E373BD74F4536B9C225F24E5248E5"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any comments on, observations of, and recommendations with respect to the reports described in this paragraph that the President determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H5DCCB016B45140BE9007F5D2CE20F569"><enum>304.</enum><header>Continuation of Committee</header><subsection commented="no" id="H62C62C5D487B42A1BD80FE7E49373B9D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding <external-xref legal-doc="usc-act" parsable-cite="usc-act/Federal Advisory Committee Act /1013">section 1013</external-xref> of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/1013">5 U.S.C. 1013</external-xref>), the Committee shall terminate not later than 90 days after the date on which the President submits the reports under section 303(b)(2), unless the President, before the expiration of the 90-day period, makes a determination that it is advantageous for the Committee to continue in being.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H2316824E4E0843B2A61215149BF24812"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Continuation of Committee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the President determines that it is advantageous for the Committee to continue in being under subsection (a)—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H8BEA24C2A1014BC29D45B1A880470AFF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee shall exercise functions prescribed by the President; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H81E511650C874BD8AE0DECB5B8AB7521"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the members of the Committee shall serve at the pleasure of the President.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H3C3A95DD51834497A04E08D9A25E042E"><enum>305.</enum><header>Staff and consultant support</header><subsection commented="no" id="H82A3D3B5DC8F4B4EB5EE5965BCF43A1F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Functions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the performance of the duties described in section 303(a), the Committee may—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HD9BC8E9EF9DE460E87CD24777FBF3145"><enum>(1)</enum><text>select, appoint, employ, and fix the compensation of specialists and other experts necessary to carry out those duties;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCBC102A669004164AFFAC3D215031598"><enum>(2)</enum><text>select, appoint, and employ, subject to the civil service laws, officers and employees necessary to carry out those duties; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF05948C6E3884790973FA436E5A06A52"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide for the participation of civilian and military personnel detailed to the Committee pursuant to subsection (b) of this section to carry out the duties of the Committee.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H3A55AC3927B945B89EB85D5CE9A75B7D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Support</header><text>Upon request of the Committee, the head of any agency, department, or instrumentality in the executive branch of the Federal Government may—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HE3649C0BF0814F1FA686C6FB7C9D55BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>furnish to the Committee necessary information to carry out the functions of the Committee that is available to, or procurable by, such department, agency, or instrumentality; and </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H480D2A3C57A44095B43CAD759A9A694D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>detail to temporary duty with the Committee on a reimbursable basis personnel within the administrative jurisdiction of the head of the agency, department, or instrumentality that the Committee needs or believes to be useful to carry out the duties of the Committee.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H790A522575ED4884941632D4FD1B2246"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Committee detail</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual who is detailed to temporary duty to the Committee under subsection (b)(2) may not experience as a result of being assigned to the detail—</text><paragraph id="HBE962B48698E47AA8C50A3FF9427B922"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to an individual who is a civilian employee, a loss of seniority, pay, or other employee status; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37D53A9DA75E4A278D2FBE7348B656DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to an individual who is a member of the military, a loss of—</text><subparagraph id="H6BF5C5E593E048B0B45A5E2370FD6D94"><enum>(A)</enum><text>status, rank, officer, or grade; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H083A8811C9734A069656AF561E86CDA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any emolument, perquisite, right, privilege, or benefit incident to military personnel that is detailed and made pursuant to an agreement between the Chair and the head of the relevant department, agency, or instrumentality, in accordance with the provisions of subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/33">chapter 33</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title commented="no" id="H393F2259252B4D62BA9688F47624BEBB"><enum>IV</enum><header>Federal Strategy and Coordinating Council on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation</header><section commented="no" id="HE711108F55E7452482A7600303A4737B"><enum>401.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is established in the executive branch of the Federal Government the Federal Strategy and Coordinating Council on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation (referred to in this title as the <quote>Council</quote>).</text></section><section commented="no" id="HA9B2A072503541ED9A4D0F861993C62D"><enum>402.</enum><header>Membership</header><subsection commented="no" id="HEF586CC09FCB4F7DAB65165BBFFA3BF4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Composition</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H095E3B122D2A4C038338662B664485AD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Council shall be composed of the following:</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC8E7DA921F654C359C534E62D70AF069"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The President, who shall serve as Chair of the Council.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9E9F867751CC449EAA0915882779B282"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Vice President.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA04C068945224DF482F4CCB396CE27C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Secretary of Commerce.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF26FE44CE53F4304B58F2F3D9B40E996"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HAF4E420D61974EC9977846BCB2B6E6E4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Secretary of Education.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0A58836465914498B355BAA116F53F4C"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Secretary of Energy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9D62CBC9E93B43A6852D60628FA053CA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H73A53D97CCB44F5A8DC2240AC1985187"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7190954145C746EC90CD5A54906D28D3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Secretary of Labor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HCB22D44432C44F3BBD1F8E15839CA73E"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The Secretary of State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC0D5274E71464D5F9C877BA544DBF539"><enum>(K)</enum><text>The Secretary of Transportation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE707F2BB11A548589D97A3D3CE32D53E"><enum>(L)</enum><text>The Secretary of the Treasury.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H37ED8298906A44C0B196EFB8A1619D0F"><enum>(M)</enum><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1618D864707240CDB0A50062B1B67C25"><enum>(N)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF9407AA23D514132BB668435380C2C96"><enum>(O)</enum><text>The Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HDF7B39D86D1040808F81518DFD657D6F"><enum>(P)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Small Business Administration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H745A084AA82843A5A7E9A726E8072E64"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>The Director of the National Science Foundation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF9877D2B6B514B068CFA102C624B49E3"><enum>(R)</enum><text>The Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF2D341F36DD74E1E8874B8DF6BD9849B"><enum>(S)</enum><text>The Assistant to the President for Science and Technology.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6037AD9B42346B4A5069CB22008002D"><enum>(T)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Trade Representative.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H57EFA8B5F51C4DD392C4C5F9D298C00F"><enum>(U)</enum><text>The National Security Advisor.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5023539B2FBC409882E5160170DA230E"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The Assistant to the President for Economic Policy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H88D67F869A5D40959DBB4BA0F3A0C768"><enum>(W)</enum><text>The Director of the Domestic Policy Council.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB4BA9C461E4041A6B97E2B544FA88230"><enum>(X)</enum><text>The Chair of the Council of Economic Advisers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H52DDECA05AEF4C3B953ACCBAD2A85249"><enum>(Y)</enum><text>The Chief Manufacturing Officer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H692E39030FD24A6D9D31E2F942D94E48"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Additional participants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may, from time to time and as necessary, appoint officials in the executive branch of the Federal Government to serve as members of the Council.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H88CFB0DD034E44CDA6823C66E7DAF7A6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Meetings of the Council</header><paragraph commented="no" id="HF4883CF149A44D819B60596EA68D601B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President or the Chief Manufacturing Officer may convene meetings of the Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H31F9F0CAC74340F09E91B1D276CB5CB9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Presiding officer</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H202F01556C5A4F5486274A7A6ADEC396"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (B), the President shall preside over the meetings of the Council.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H95025DD22A804982A74444623ACDB2E0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the President is not present at a meeting of the Council, the Vice President (and if the Vice President is not present at a meeting of the Council, the Chief Manufacturing Officer) shall preside and be considered the Chair of the Council.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H27DDE28F0D374C608C138EADA632A365"><enum>403.</enum><header>Council on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Efforts</header><subsection commented="no" id="H8BA843AC0405498DB206CCF577A322F7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duties of the Council</header><paragraph commented="no" id="HFBB15E05C0A049258301724B70952543"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>The Council shall—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HEF9A9EF0573B4FBBA97511968342D58C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider problems and developments, including concerns regarding the workforce concerns, in manufacturing and industrial innovation and related activities of more than 1 agency in the executive branch of the Federal Government;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HDEB3B6DF286B4DE287241F848FEFE820"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate the manufacturing and industrial innovation policy-making process;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BE78B32D3144EF2A3588C8A537E769E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>harmonize the Federal permitting process related to manufacturing and industrial innovation, as appropriate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA1405091B6264E78B324C2B7A40D79C8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>ensure manufacturing and industrial innovation policy decisions and programs are consistent with the priority goals of the United States described in section 102(a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE3301CDE42094C0C9E66EF76C8445D8D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>help implement the priority goals described in section 102(a) across the Federal Government;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA000AB6718D345D19F0635B4DBD66942"><enum>(F)</enum><text>ensure manufacturing and industrial innovation are considered in the development and implementation of Federal policies and programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H16232F7AF8344D2BA1F6493C137222E7"><enum>(G)</enum><text>achieve more effective use of foundational aspects of manufacturing and industrial innovation, particularly scientific, engineering, and technological resources and facilities of agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government, including the elimination of efforts that have been unwarrantedly duplicated;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HDDDB6DBC96BE4E5195EDC8ECCD74B03F"><enum>(H)</enum><text>identify—</text><clause commented="no" id="HACE9140CBA4D41F19905FDCA57B64EDB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>threats to and vulnerabilities of supply chains;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HF4021D8A490C4C64BE07BF09DA0EB31B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>workforce skills; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H81F2DF6E5849432E8918466DB56DF9DA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>aspects of supply chains and workforce skills requiring additional emphasis; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC581895F3AA64B9E99D4E7BAEFC7DF0F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>further international cooperation on manufacturing and industrial innovation policies that enhance the policies of the United States and internationally agreed upon policies.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H5CE1F379A8BD4C078AC955E24D4FF30E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other duties</header><text>The Chief Manufacturing Officer may take such actions as may be necessary or appropriate to implement the functions described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="HB0A7297493654EB28F1A63719CB6A918"><enum>404.</enum><header>Coordination</header><subsection commented="no" id="HA75F1793F03D49F086A9A5D7E2549E1C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement To coordinate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of each agency in the executive branch of the Federal Government, without regard to whether the head of the agency is a member of the Council, shall—</text><paragraph id="H6267FE83C24743A49FB2700CE5D30F2A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>coordinate manufacturing and industrial innovation policy with the Council; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0931BB28A9E4ADB92625E2AAC539EEC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>share information on manufacturing and industrial innovation policy-related budget requests with the Council.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H2A67B61679574F0A92C67F61F6B510A3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Budget recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Council shall develop for submission to the Director of the Office of Management and Budget recommendations for the budgets of agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government relating to manufacturing and industrial innovation policy that reflect the priority goals described in section 102(a).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HCAC591C29BC5443DA25E08289A679836"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Council shall provide advice to the Director of the Office of Management and Budget concerning the budget proposals of agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government concerning manufacturing and industrial innovation policy. </text></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="HBD2DAEED06CB4862820251E688818FBD"><enum>405.</enum><header>Administration</header><subsection commented="no" id="H913205A033DD40AE8000568DB0896402"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Coordination with National Science and Technology Council</header><text>In carrying out the duties of the Council, the Council shall consult with the National Science and Technology Council, as necessary.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H8CA3D05F92854C45B5CBB229B2068221"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ad committees; tasks forces, interagency groups</header><text>The Council may function through established or ad hoc committees, task forces, or interagency groups. </text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H38343E2DEBFC4ECD96B5CBED99A873FD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirement To cooperate</header><text>Each agency in the executive branch of the Federal Government shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HD8D5C86A7D014647B04205F1B55CC54E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>cooperate with the Council; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H603A5F7B4AEE44EE9CA987DFE8229CB2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide assistance, information, and advice to the Council, as the Council may request, to the extent permitted by law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HCE5950844E884D879D7F3143CDFA9840"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Assistance to Council</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this section, the head of each agency that is a member of the Council shall furnish necessary assistance and resources to the Council, which may include—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H93013EF081004235ABA68586D4B344FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>detailing employees of the agency to the Council to perform such functions, consistent with the purposes of this section, as the Chair may assign to those detailees;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H305C1299A0EC4CEA9B8FD4F95940480B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>providing office support and printing, as requested by the Chair; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3C0B2F96BD444D259F2794FEA88B854B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>upon the request of the Chair, undertake special studies for the Council that come within the functions herein assigned as necessary to fulfill the duties of the Council described in section 403.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H430B7D16B2A6421C923599D12864CBC0"><enum>V</enum><header>Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy Institute</header><section id="HCA738448B1B04A02B73363AEA3AA758F"><enum>501.</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There shall be established a federally funded research and development center to be known as the <quote>Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation Policy Institute</quote> (referred to in this section as the <quote>Institute</quote>).</text></section><section id="H1A067F40571C4325AEF2959C5AA26710"><enum>502.</enum><header>Incorporation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Institute shall be—</text><paragraph id="H03FF4505A6854454B425B7A3B03CADAC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>administered as a separate entity by an organization managing a federally funded research and development center on the date of enactment of this Act; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H63F0EF07AFFE4D378CEABB6DA9D603A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>incorporated as a nonprofit membership corporation.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0264CF94732C40C890A37675EF1F9A73"><enum>503.</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The duties of the Institute shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H83B8D406F16047DE893CA164ECB6106E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The assembly of timely and authoritative information relating to significant manufacturing and industrial innovation development and trends in research, development, and their applications in the United States and abroad, including information relating to—</text><subparagraph id="H6F0E2742CEC64B67B4586E1C9C76D4B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the developments identified in the most recent report submitted to Congress by the President under section 206; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25DDD98943B9493192F7CCE8B9B185D4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>projections and strategies identified in the most recent national strategic plan established under section 204(a).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD718BB53CE7042569A6B33358F817080"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The development and maintenance of relevant informational and analytical tools.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACAD91D97B114ECBBBBBC2C514DC5EA9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The analysis and interpretation of the information described in paragraph (1), with particular attention to the scope and content of the Federal manufacturing and industrial innovation policy portfolio that affects interagency and national issues.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB020604E3E22467298DEF9C4B8A669EA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The initiation of studies and analysis of available manufacturing and industrial innovation alternatives to ensure the long-term strength of the United States in the development and application of manufacturing and industrial innovation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4E3D0A84CBE43BE86AF2B4B1B91C8CC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The determination of appropriate roles of the Federal Government, State governments, private industry, and institutes of higher education in the development and application of manufacturing and industrial innovation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FFEF148602E4B15B0B042D67DE1AD4E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The provision, upon the request of the Chief Manufacturing Officer, of technical support and assistance—</text><subparagraph id="H589E4D077F4942079241BAA91AA7A5B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the committees and panels of the Federal Strategy and Coordinating Council on Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation established under section 401 that provide advice to agencies in the executive branch of the Federal Government on manufacturing and industrial innovation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A5D966FC71A4D8DB0C1828A52DF2882"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to the interagency committees and panels of the Federal Government concerned with manufacturing and industrial innovation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HD37CCA45C0574A8784134132499B8253"><enum>504.</enum><header>Consultation of Institute activities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In carrying out the duties described in section 503, personnel of the Institute shall—</text><paragraph id="H772F428611E34133A9D326332A23AC18"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult widely with representatives from—</text><subparagraph id="H7B904886413141D0A6110637D4EC3537"><enum>(A)</enum><text>private industry; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED077E3259224CA39E74611AA179BB73"><enum>(B)</enum><text>labor organizations that primarily represent workers in manufacturing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF267741BFA22459E9269B2FDFC46DA30"><enum>(C)</enum><text>institutions of higher education, including worker training and credentialing programs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5593C72D47E2402DAE575D9935017196"><enum>(D)</enum><text>nonprofit institutions that reflect racial, ethnic, gender, and regional diversity; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H40FC86BB52A646E0ABC8C60DD814AD38"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, incorporate information and perspectives derived from consultations under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H6ACB2FE364624824A0DBA1D8FD6637E0"><enum>505.</enum><header>Annual reports</header><subsection id="HA37655FF69084041BD0871121185E732"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Institute shall submit to the President a report on the activities of the Institute.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2880AACC2382476E996AABCF43B6897E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall prescribe requirements for the report submitted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H3230AB4B44634D5EA59DDB07E66325DA"><enum>506.</enum><header>Sponsorship</header><subsection id="H367C831BB2694B0A8FEE410F6D581C16"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sponsor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall be the sponsor of the Institute.</text></subsection><subsection id="H84F839E9796D4564AD796DC00AD80E53"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Agreement</header><paragraph id="H83C0760D32BB42D0A579484DDCD11A72"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, in consultation with the Chief Manufacturing Officer, shall enter into a sponsoring agreement with respect to the Institute that requires the Institute carry out functions determined by the Chief Manufacturing Officer that are consistent with the duties described in section 503.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88CA3462129D45858F036CC9A7B41F44"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consistency with requirements prescribed by Administrator for Federal Procurement Policy</header><text>The Administrator for Federal Procurement Policy shall prescribe general requirements for the sponsoring agreement entered into under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title commented="no" id="H678FE91D247644B894F9F63D93F191D0"><enum>VI</enum><header>National Medal of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation</header><section commented="no" id="HBAD42184B0B345B7A830BDFB5BF09FE1"><enum>601.</enum><header>Award</header><subsection commented="no" id="H2AFA22D81B774EEBA4720FA6CAB60624"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The President shall from time to time award a medal, to be known as the <quote>National Medal of Manufacturing and Industrial Innovation</quote>, on the basis of recommendations received from the National Academies of Sciences, the Chief Manufacturing Officer, or on the basis of such other information and evidence as the President determines appropriate, to individuals who in the judgment of the President are deserving of special recognition by reason of outstanding contributions to knowledge in manufacturing and industrial innovation.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HC1B717452D6B46AF818C9EA87C38D693"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Number</header><text>Not more than 20 individuals may be awarded a medal under this section in any one calendar year.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1D770EA7F6DE4BAB9CB258D7BD8070C5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Citizenship</header><text>An individual may not be awarded a medal under this section unless at the time such award is made the individual—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H0CA65206933E4134A292C569AA89D965"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is a citizen or other national of the United States; or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCBC5CD06FD25473F85C51B5C65FCE496"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is an individual lawfully admitted to the United States for permanent residence who—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0D8C1592D0AA45E5A86BEDC0DB66D4E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has filed an application for petition for naturalization in the manner prescribed by section 334(b) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1445">8 U.S.C. 1445(b)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H90E6A21A40F5402D9BC8E43D14C3FA17"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not permanently ineligible to become a citizen of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HE5E2FA88C6204F009D53FBA0623AFF48"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Ceremonies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The presentation of the award shall be made by the President with such ceremonies as determined proper, including attendance by appropriate Members of Congress.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="H6381FF599BB24EBF886ED1B2754B6439"><enum>VII</enum><header>General Provisions</header><section id="H7983C7B732C44330A360317783039D7F"><enum>701.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated—</text><paragraph id="H1773BCB3179F4B818A3108F85FD87A62"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for fiscal year 2024—</text><subparagraph id="HB51BA7650A1444F09C70AF5FAC6776FC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$5,000,000, for the purpose of carrying out title II;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27D7FB685EE44A02836ACBDDEA108B96"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$5,000,000, for the purpose of carrying out title III; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HACA257525E2C4976A8BDCF3B7DDD2D2D"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$5,000,000, for the purpose of carrying out title IV; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05AAE9B45EF846A0814050FDD795FA1C"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$5,000,000, for the purpose of carrying out title V; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H944E5CAD43604C00884617C8F5EA2CE6" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for each fiscal year thereafter, for the purpose of carrying out titles II through V, such sums as may be necessary.</text></paragraph></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

