<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAB7834C227844369BA706E37C665D03B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1123 IH: Understanding Cybersecurity of Mobile Networks Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1123</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001039">Mrs. Cammack</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information to submit to Congress a report examining the cybersecurity of mobile service networks, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HABF82BAB127242BAA3730DFAD0E46F1B" style="OLC"><section id="HF6EA9CB26EF8472280281D0DB76CF53E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Understanding Cybersecurity of Mobile Networks Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC2D9CCA7837E486799EF2052C284774A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on cybersecurity of mobile service networks</header><subsection id="H63EB843D251F4061A9D6FDEED17DE8A1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary, in consultation with the Department of Homeland Security, shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report examining the cybersecurity of mobile service networks and the vulnerability of such networks and mobile devices to cyberattacks and surveillance conducted by adversaries.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9E521A410C274168B3199C626FC9ED76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HCEC814CDCF8541ADBC1F74E21771A6BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An assessment of the degree to which providers of mobile service have addressed, are addressing, or have not addressed cybersecurity vulnerabilities (including vulnerabilities the exploitation of which could lead to surveillance conducted by adversaries) identified by academic and independent researchers, multistakeholder standards and technical organizations, industry experts, and Federal agencies, including in relevant reports of—</text><subparagraph id="H0CAC096CBE5543BAB3BBAF29EBB48B73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the National Telecommunications and Information Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFC60A7FB2EE492CB5CFB38482BDA6BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the National Institute of Standards and Technology; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBA37FB3897284ED7BE65F25451B55390"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Department of Homeland Security, including—</text><clause id="HA7CE10FD9DCE4789BF0EC1955D028EC6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency; and</text></clause><clause id="H54213C2F54B343258ECE1AE1F85F5D3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Science and Technology Directorate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DA237084C4A4B6181E2188E978876CE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A discussion of—</text><subparagraph id="H80F5A10B5A944C1ABB28D809C61ECD08"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the degree to which customers (including consumers, companies, and government agencies) consider cybersecurity as a factor when considering the purchase of mobile service and mobile devices; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B529C093B254718AAFFD06A7EB4DF3C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the commercial availability of tools, frameworks, best practices, and other resources for enabling such customers to evaluate cybersecurity risk and price tradeoffs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H17194820BAA44434B3E52089F68F2951"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A discussion of the degree to which providers of mobile service have implemented cybersecurity best practices and risk assessment frameworks.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF707B87EF234AECB8A44D338C7A4BB6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An estimate and discussion of the prevalence and efficacy of encryption and authentication algorithms and techniques used in each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H300123E00AEA432FAC6E84E8AB3CE44F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Mobile service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFAEDBEE3D8A34B26AAF053162F021800"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Mobile communications equipment or services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC2602F4E4CC04B42A359DAD320F0115D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Commonly used mobile phones and other mobile devices.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13E643AA1EA4482C98B16735E48A3FFB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Commonly used mobile operating systems and communications software and applications.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3EDEC019C3242739A03B81920F0BBA2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A discussion of the barriers for providers of mobile service to adopt more efficacious encryption and authentication algorithms and techniques and to prohibit the use of older encryption and authentication algorithms and techniques with established vulnerabilities in mobile service, mobile communications equipment or services, and mobile phones and other mobile devices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F7B7E21008549629DF9DD3B6191D00A"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An estimate and discussion of the prevalence, usage, and availability of technologies that authenticate legitimate mobile service and mobile communications equipment or services to which mobile phones and other mobile devices are connected.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08457F69104D4F0DB4B8C606B7B3687D"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An estimate and discussion of the prevalence, costs, commercial availability, and usage by adversaries in the United States of cell site simulators (often known as international mobile subscriber identity catchers) and other mobile service surveillance and interception technologies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4FA96E8C8E404C6494165061B34A7ADD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In preparing the report required by subsection (a), the Assistant Secretary shall, to the degree practicable, consult with—</text><paragraph id="H0E3C90A5E4A445A39B5C4911C157DA45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Federal Communications Commission;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AB9619205C840D7AC649332E522FA90"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the National Institute of Standards and Technology;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE76F623B8E2B45F3867E355D883C07C6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the intelligence community;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A8F3F3171134838A5772E998F8BFCCF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency of the Department of Homeland Security;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC511789A2C4A4E2EBD7F68C04B7315A6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Science and Technology Directorate of the Department of Homeland Security;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB6870AB04AB4723B5AF7C2661FE65C2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>academic and independent researchers with expertise in privacy, encryption, cybersecurity, and network threats;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7B8E3B8CD3A4ED68502FC05C0206E80"><enum>(7)</enum><text>participants in multistakeholder standards and technical organizations (including the 3rd Generation Partnership Project and the Internet Engineering Task Force);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H819FCD11AAA34AFDB6C2A6BAFFF99AF1"><enum>(8)</enum><text>international stakeholders, in coordination with the Department of State as appropriate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB273D94782F46B7B38C1920F9FFFBA0"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providers of mobile service, including small providers (or the representatives of such providers) and rural providers (or the representatives of such providers);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D84E91BA68C405391A7D2437E4C9E0C"><enum>(10)</enum><text>manufacturers, operators, and providers of mobile communications equipment or services and mobile phones and other mobile devices;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF9A95BE97D54FFCA4AF9D5F793EA4AA"><enum>(11)</enum><text>developers of mobile operating systems and communications software and applications; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6B41469043D4242ACD8319F712AF3FD"><enum>(12)</enum><text>other experts that the Assistant Secretary considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H77FBCAE61CD645139845444A794EC770"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Scope of report</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H0FB7EA9599EB42E1B2C6F5AE957542A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>limit the report required by subsection (a) to mobile service networks;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3EEB5982642C49848E35BE917B0014C6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>exclude consideration of 5G protocols and networks in the report required by subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE062DD74C4DE45DB9EFA7BFDA82A0BFE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>limit the assessment required by subsection (b)(1) to vulnerabilities that have been shown to be—</text><subparagraph id="H2FD91DED61CC440EA6F8B097987FD62C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>exploited in non-laboratory settings; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09CFFACC9583430083C1252A21ABDD2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>feasibly and practicably exploitable in real-world conditions; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H107DFBB18539447E8BD9B52A066A9D14"><enum>(4)</enum><text>consider in the report required by subsection (a) vulnerabilities that have been effectively mitigated by manufacturers of mobile phones and other mobile devices.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD69C12F7DCF41A19B8540FAFE142570"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Form of report</header><paragraph id="H26F0707E342A426B8821771601935BDB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall be produced in unclassified form but may contain a classified annex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD4E391A647D4F0C86D1E525F566E46A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Potentially exploitable unclassified information</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall redact potentially exploitable unclassified information from the report required by subsection (a) but shall provide an unredacted form of the report to the committees described in such subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF962A442F1B84149BF6A4D3DCB20A00A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $500,000 for fiscal year 2024. Such amount is authorized to remain available through fiscal year 2025.</text></subsection><subsection id="H721EF78C551844C5BA356B238B10E224"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H4CCD1E061C3E415AA50640C6153988DB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adversary</header><text>The term <quote>adversary</quote> includes—</text><subparagraph id="H60566C3807544D7AB1420C37DCD2AB7B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any unauthorized hacker or other intruder into a mobile service network; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1E721B891F24A01A21796223645E7A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any foreign government or foreign nongovernment person engaged in a long-term pattern or serious instances of conduct significantly adverse to the national security of the United States or security and safety of United States persons.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H91121FAA8FA740C89537C7AE0FB36D1A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assistant secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Assistant Secretary</quote> means the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Communications and Information.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7D97BF9DAD8470F9A776805716D8488"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Entity</header><text>The term <quote>entity</quote> means a partnership, association, trust, joint venture, corporation, group, subgroup, or other organization.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDFDFB221AE44F319D4FC53BB65B0E82"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Intelligence community</header><text>The term <quote>intelligence community</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99E8567AF1E742499057D1C0716D8034"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Mobile communications equipment or service</header><text>The term <quote>mobile communications equipment or service</quote> means any equipment or service that is essential to the provision of mobile service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2A533F602A44F1C8EF3D786D20FF703"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Mobile service</header><text>The term <quote>mobile service</quote> means, to the extent provided to United States customers, either or both of the following services:</text><subparagraph id="HABA3E94CD89A48AD9072627F26F02601"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Commercial mobile service (as defined in section 332(d) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/332">47 U.S.C. 332(d)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3980A887EBC477BAC1B7911E6470A36"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Commercial mobile data service (as defined in section 6001 of the Middle Class Tax Relief and Job Creation Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1401">47 U.S.C. 1401</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4629AE03A6C4EC9A11278ABD41FC3E2"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Person</header><text>The term <quote>person</quote> means an individual or entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70368F36A43A4934A493F1E1235B943C"><enum>(8)</enum><header>United states person</header><text>The term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HF6BA068FD4F445E19ED41B6361D436B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an individual who is a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70E65D8C6A734D0C968559612D6D995A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EB2AC41D0FD4E28899FBD8A5D5861A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any person in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

