<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Placed-on-Calendar-Senate" dms-id="H621B46DEE4FF4F95A9E5E51AAE16A724" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 300 PCS: Settlement Agreement Information Database Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><calendar>Calendar No. 7</calendar><congress>118th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>H. R. 300</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230125">January 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received; read the first time</action-desc></action><action><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Read the second time and placed on the calendar</action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/3">chapter 3</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, to require the publication of settlement agreements, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H29ED6A02901B4C6AB46F696785F3F955" style="OLC"><section id="H14CE476DEF824D0C897FB6BD0DE54ED2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Settlement Agreement Information Database Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF8C2C76F6F9B455281FCE64CF0B2E72B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Information regarding settlement agreements entered into by Federal agencies</header><subsection id="H7C8F1D42C0D94774A4C985B5D1BA64FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements for settlement agreements</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/3">Chapter 3</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block id="H50EAC33024074729AA9019EF6FF6811C" style="USC"><section id="H9F71230BE6D4431CA7570BFD008EC2D0"><enum>307.</enum><header>Information regarding settlement agreements</header><subsection id="H43C9193A75A44FDA992C78CD86497A55"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H300D856994034C1183E5941773637EA7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Local government</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>local government</term> has the meaning given that term in section 6501 of title 31.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H47C31F68ECF44DF9A9295AC44824C254"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Order type</header><text>The term <term>order type</term> means the type of action or instrument used to settle a civil or criminal judicial action.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB861DF468DFB40208E6A84DFB001CA00"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Settlement agreement</header><text>The term <term>settlement agreement</term> means a settlement agreement (including a consent decree) that—</text><subparagraph id="H8C9957DD750B442EB217250E74ADD9C8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is entered into by an Executive agency; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C15E0B5A2A4413695B8353BA7050AC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>relates to an alleged violation of Federal civil or criminal law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F179ECEFFA1431FAEA277B0B2B9FF36"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, each territory or possession of the United States, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5797371692AA4E8D8220FE34D6A1C991"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Settlement Agreement Information Database</header><paragraph id="H5B0710D76F844557A938F4B394751F00"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Executive agency requirement</header><subparagraph id="HF2B50D725A45477D9CBCF32A6D85FAD6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (B), the head of each Executive agency shall, in accordance with guidance issued pursuant to paragraph (2), submit the following information to the database established under paragraph (3):</text><clause id="HC34B9D888DA54050B8E64F47663D68CB"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A list of each settlement agreement, in a categorized and searchable format, entered into by the Executive agency, as a party to a lawsuit, which shall include, for each settlement agreement—</text><subclause id="HE67964E5A4D34F57940FA05AFDD0049B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the order type of the settlement agreement;</text></subclause><subclause id="H4EBF4AFE51644E898C5753E4BB20E402"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the date on which the parties entered into the settlement agreement;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD3A1C2004DF74BA796676B1E6D226ACC"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a list of specific violations that specify the basis for the action taken, with a description of the claims each party settled under the settlement agreement;</text></subclause><subclause id="HAA6CA5B0F4334FFDA84455642A9891C4"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the amount of attorneys’ fees and other litigation costs awarded, if any, including a description of the statutory basis for such an award;</text></subclause><subclause id="H9A1CF1A84E264BA6AE8A3A17A587ABB9"><enum>(V)</enum><text>the amount each party settling a claim under the settlement agreement is obligated to pay under the settlement agreement;</text></subclause><subclause id="H4F3C50E59EDC4382A8C9B3B0AA628992"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>the total amount the settling parties are obligated to pay under the settlement agreement;</text></subclause><subclause id="HAEE2156A47784C4C842D4655869CA401"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>the amount, if any, the settling party is obligated to pay that is expressly specified under the settlement agreement as a civil or criminal penalty or fine;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HA38E4E0AB6D74687807B5C98E38D346F"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any payment made under the settlement agreement, including a description of any payment made to the Federal Government;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB750E975B3914DB4B5BC2CFA5B6FDAE4"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>the projected duration of the settlement agreement, if available;</text></subclause><subclause id="HE65E87F95822452FAA67A593506DF872"><enum>(X)</enum><text>a list of State or local governments that may be directly affected by the terms of the settlement agreement;</text></subclause><subclause id="HCA8C1785E74A4C73BC4748325E1244A2"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>a brief description of any economic data and methodology used to justify the terms of the settlement agreement;</text></subclause><subclause id="H4E52C8A8C0A04A34BA6FF90456C4407C"><enum>(XII)</enum><text>any modifications to the settlement agreement, when applicable;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD807F804D8E64C049F13D3CAC2511D09"><enum>(XIII)</enum><text>notice and comments, when applicable; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HE63148A602B74725A53DE5FA4E20DDCD"><enum>(XIV)</enum><text>whether the settlement agreement is still under judicial enforcement and any period of time by which the parties agreed to have certain conditions met.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H5E327F8347714776980241A63969B9C8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A copy of each—</text><subclause id="HE6A49F3CF3CF47E29F61107FFBEDB261"><enum>(I)</enum><text>settlement agreement entered into by the Executive agency; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3B50A264915A4F569E0A61858B77C002"><enum>(II)</enum><text>statement issued under paragraph (4).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5AFE2BDE74E4CFBAE361177C5BB0F7C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Nondisclosure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirement to submit information or a copy of a settlement agreement under subparagraph (A) shall not apply to the extent the information or copy (or portion thereof)—</text><clause id="HD6EDF49A14D84983A80AB302663BC09D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is subject to a confidentiality provision that prohibits disclosure of the information or copy (or portion thereof); and</text></clause><clause id="HA5298BAF2A2842FCA59C23B8BCBE305F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">would not be disclosed under section 552, if the Executive agency provides a citation to the applicable exemption.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3483FF38B52248709F673A10054DD349"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Clarification of responsible agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a case in which an Executive agency is acting at the request or on behalf of another Executive agency (referred to as the originating agency), the originating agency is responsible for submitting information under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4576993A945142159333C73098E42447"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall issue guidance for Executive agencies to implement paragraph (1). Such guidance shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H60848C0CB00D47D4AB51089BA9CC02C4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Specific dates by which submissions must be made, not less than twice a year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD001C7CF35F34C2BADDCB011CD5137C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Data standards, including common data elements and a common, nonproprietary, searchable, machine-readable, platform independent format.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E84D42811644E3893F952796D6B03C8"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A requirement that the information and documents required under paragraph (1) are publicly available for a period starting on the date of the settlement through not less than 5 years after the termination of the settlement agreement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE7EDE0A65AB475AA3E7A5BD7F43F010"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Establishment of database</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Management and Budget, or the head of an Executive agency designated by the Director, shall establish and maintain a public, searchable, downloadable database for Executive agencies to directly upload and submit the information and documents required under paragraph (1) for immediate publication online.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFE15210BDA3432AA41627A911A75023"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Statement of confidentiality</header><text>If the head of an Executive agency determines that a confidentiality provision in a settlement agreement, or the sealing of a settlement agreement, is required to protect the public interest of the United States, the head of the Executive agency may except the settlement agreement from the requirement in paragraph (1) and shall issue a written public statement stating why such action is required to protect the public interest of the United States, which shall explain—</text><subparagraph id="H8702DB99500D4442BBF86984BF504C52"><enum>(A)</enum><text>what interests confidentiality protects; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1DBC12287544FB18513E52618A26823"><enum>(B)</enum><text>why the interests protected by confidentiality outweigh the public’s interest in knowing about the conduct of the Federal Government and the expenditure of Federal resources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HFE81368C4C5C4701ADFE20C2951544FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/3">chapter 3</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block id="H7D25150435A0482A84BF3A4C6DFFFFFA" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">307. Information regarding settlement agreements.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H4774D2DE96854BE393960D6E12480678"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deadline To establish database</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall issue guidance required by section 307(b)(2) of title 5, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), and establish the settlement agreement information database required by section 307(b)(3) of title 5, United States Code, as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H28F6C4B74E41441EBEF39440942A3E3A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deadline for first submission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the Director issues guidance under section 307(b)(2) of title 5, United States Code, as added by subsection (a), the head of each Executive agency (as defined in section 105 of title 5, United States Code) shall begin submitting information to the database established under such section 307.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD22A6B1C247840FC8B482154274DCAED"><enum>3.</enum><header>Amendments to the Freedom of Information Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 552(a)(2) of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8A209334BE9841C6B3E1A40E296C41CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) through (E) as subparagraphs (C) through (F), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17ED198E624F4E9B939B4B539DF98D27"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block id="HC1C1EA4678DA4B85BBCCD203842B21A8" style="USC"><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7F527AC7B452459681D4A9ECDBA5813D" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each settlement agreement (as defined in section 307) entered into by an Executive agency, with redactions for information that the agency may withhold under paragraph (8) and subsections (b) and (c) of this section;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="H79C52ADC85B44E16A05E3E5C47D23374"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, shall be construed to require the disclosure of information or records that any agency may properly withhold from public disclosure under section 552 of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>).</text></section><section commented="no" id="H8C97C6A8C3A94B87895632DDCB004782"><enum>5.</enum><header>Effective date; applicability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall be effective 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and shall apply—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H446E935B606C402E9650F9A08A29224A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to any settlement agreement (as such term is defined in section 307 of title 5, United States Code, as added by section 2), entered into on or after the date of the enactment of this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H807E87D3455D482EB827ACB39538DEC0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to the extent practicable, any such settlement agreement (as such term is defined in section 307 of title 5, United States Code, as added by section 2) that remains in effect on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230125" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives January 24, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Cheryl L. Johnson,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Read the second time and placed on the calendar</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

