<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H03C488EA3B514A3AB2C2F77D37276931" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6222 IH: Justice for Victims of COVID Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6222</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231103">November 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a COVID&#8211;19 Victims Compensation Program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H596F70716DF34AA6B1B7CBDBAB373AA3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3F964AA375414CA1979CE5F8A37DE377" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Justice for Victims of COVID Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HBEBA4008B6FA4A8795DDAAD13D720411"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="HBEE6A397112744029ACD177E623982EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the COVID–19 pandemic has killed more than 1 million Americans.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H906B3420B9D04278959BE4AEDC675CD2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The People’s Republic of China showed willful disregard and indifference toward the life, welfare, safety, and rights of Americans by—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7CD9A59B8F26488BBBAD3C73926F3D99"><enum>(A)</enum><text>concealing vital medical and scientific data from the World Health Organization;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H128C5BC8C6474F3B937DDF2F4066192B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>suppressing crucial information that should have been shared with international health authorities;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9F7F46E71BF0490481EB059FAC8586C5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>arresting and silencing whistleblowers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3F140EE1D7CB438CB279D5179039B36A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>denying human-to-human transmission in the face of mounting evidence;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H55628C4BB41B49529632482670467B88"><enum>(E)</enum><text>destroying evidence; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA186C7726BD1498D92415379236E89D9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>continuing international air traffic out of Wuhan, the virus’s epicenter, despite a domestic travel lockdown.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HCC9DB2CF7EFE447B9930C87A569A9B5B"><enum>3.</enum><header>COVID–19 Victims Compensation Fund</header> 
<subsection id="HF9EBCA93E94C4267BB9609092899C479"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of Fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is hereby established in the Treasury of the United States a fund to be known as the COVID–19 Victims Compensation Fund (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Fund</quote>), consisting of such amounts as may be appropriated to the Fund as provided in subsection (b).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H848AEF6D040F42B7ABFE9C70BE00AE95"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transfer to Fund of amounts equivalent to special tariff</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is hereby appropriated to the Fund for fiscal year 2024 and each subsequent fiscal year an amount equal to the total amount of duties collected for each fiscal year under section 5.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H943541E40F1544DF981ABD324FC46B2B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Availability of funding</header><text>Amounts in the Fund shall be available, without further appropriation and until expended, for carrying out section 4.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HF18A753D5DCA4637B9C43AC950144D0F"><enum>4.</enum><header>COVID–19 Victims Compensation Program</header> <subsection id="H9DBEEFAC7DDE4BA39B74C1A25993CB86"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall establish a program to be known as the COVID–19 Victims Compensation Program (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>) for the purpose of providing compensation to eligible survivors of eligible deceased individuals whose primary cause of death was COVID–19.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H93B7E2D68DE34B8C9B5303EF0E77EC7C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Petitions</header> 
<paragraph id="H301C7C6005534572994568B8A70A4534"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To receive compensation under the Program, an eligible survivor may submit to the Secretary a petition at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, which shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="HFBD9A9FB8D01447EAABA9BD72E4E72BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>evidence (of a type determined admissible by the Secretary) that COVID–19 was the primary cause of death of the eligible deceased individual in relation to whom the eligible survivor seeks compensation; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H866F5EF560CC456793D563B7ABE0F163"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the name and contact information of each eligible survivor of such eligible deceased individual.</text> </subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B406AB44CCE49B8961D0F1E33919816"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Not more than 1 petition per eligible deceased individual</header><text>Not more than 1 petition may be submitted in relation to any given eligible deceased individual.</text> </paragraph> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H25213C20F9A2445BA3E6925F5DAD5EB5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Payment of compensation</header> 
<paragraph id="H3A848F78185742529C015EF460D07229"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), for any petition for which the Secretary determines by a preponderance of the evidence that COVID–19 was the primary cause of death of the eligible deceased individual, the Secretary shall, from amounts in the Fund, pay the eligible survivors of the eligible deceased individual—</text> <subparagraph id="H18A88EB6C53A4FFABECA6C43222F6535"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of 1 eligible survivor, the amount described in paragraph (2) to such eligible survivor; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF6CCF70D120C42E4B11710F3C7AD4C7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of multiple eligible survivors, the amount described in paragraph (2) divided equally among such eligible survivors.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0B9F665D9914E2EAE7ACDDD75E4EC93"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The amount described in this paragraph is the total of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H75D783A996D24185A2EB3675FCACAED6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount of out-of-pocket health care costs incurred by the eligible deceased individual for the treatment of such eligible deceased individual’s case of COVID–19 and any associated symptoms and complications; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDDFA1DA10665490C8A1638C3F5BB2B64"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount, not to exceed $50,000, of wages lost by the eligible deceased individual as the result of the death of such eligible deceased individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4C2060BC1B0A4193B55FDE4524EDD738"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Insufficient funds</header><text>In the case of insufficient amounts in the Fund to pay the full amount described in paragraph (2) to all eligible survivors in relation to whom the Secretary has made the determination described in paragraph (1), the Secretary may prioritize payments, on a rolling basis, in the order in which such determinations are made.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3663AFCB8FA04F77B35C35419802307C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Judicial review</header> <paragraph id="H3FB8D9CFF8B145598AC31FEE0B3F5E0A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appeal of denial</header><text>An individual, if aggrieved by a denial of a petition submitted under the Program for an eligible deceased individual in relation to whom such individual is an eligible survivor, may appeal such denial in the United States Court of Federal Claims.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1A53A2CFAB694ACC877A0CDE5E244F5C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cause of action for improper exclusion</header> 
<subparagraph id="H3C48251E9F8B4513A6900DDABF6C2E48"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For any petition for which compensation is awarded to 1 or more eligible survivors under subsection (c), an eligible survivor who was not awarded such compensation may, not later than 3 years after the date on which such compensation is awarded, bring an action in a Federal court of competent jurisdiction against the eligible survivors to whom such compensation was awarded, for the amount described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF353ACD25FAF4668BFBFA4A45D22A9F0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount</header><text>The amount described in this subparagraph is—</text> 
<clause id="HCAB895B7C8504F2A9FF11C3052C1AD52"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a defendant whom the court determines, by a preponderance of the evidence, intentionally excluded the name and contact information of the plaintiff from the petition submitted under subsection (b)(1), the total of—</text> <subclause id="H59E79827E17B4AE1B03D609378CEC5E3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the equal share of compensation that the plaintiff would have received under subsection (c)(1), if included on the petition; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8FAD1C4385D94F278C22F7685800409E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any applicable attorney’s fees and reasonable court costs; or</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H8A8EA2F83C124E4693FD1C4BFCF1217E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in any other case, such equal share of compensation.</text> </clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5CAA0648F691484E8B8D9A2A878D8345"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H93EDC540197640D692727D452E80293B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible deceased individual</header><text>The term <term>eligible deceased individual</term> means an individual who—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD19338CE7F48472AB0EA3E9AA7543D98"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is deceased; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H065D56DA2B9544B8A4A46CF48E94BCCA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at the time of death, was a citizen of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCD01F27CCC1746A4A7E4DD5402C21C1A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible survivor</header><text>The term <term>eligible survivor</term> means, as of the time of submitting a petition under subsection (b)—</text> <subparagraph id="H7B5AF445B83C4B7ABFD88091CFF858E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the surviving spouse of the eligible deceased individual;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4285443A8A884F639E97883467ADDD97"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if there is no surviving spouse, the surviving children of the eligible deceased individual; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD8759BE01925438A84049C9444868A34"><enum>(C)</enum><text>if there is no surviving spouse or children, the surviving parents or legal guardians of the eligible deceased individual.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> </section> 
<section id="H5C4521B720A841CDAED6C3A633CDA543"><enum>5.</enum><header>Special tariff</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, there is hereby imposed, in addition to any other duty in effect as of the date of the enactment of this Act, a duty of 10 percent ad valorem on all products of the People’s Republic of China imported into the United States.</text></section> <section id="H6F8F4FB369684B93B87F5C37867AB361"><enum>6.</enum><header>Exception to foreign sovereign immunity</header> <subsection id="HA2DABF56552B425C99C0AED1E8DFDBC0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law (including <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/28/85">chapter 85</external-xref> of title 28, United States Code, commonly referred to as the <quote>Foreign Sovereign Immunities Act</quote>) a person may bring an action for damages (including economic damages, and damages for pain and suffering) before an appropriate district court of the United States against the Government of the People’s Republic of China for personal injury, death, or harm resulting from any misrepresentation pertaining to COVID–19 made by the Government of the People’s Republic of China.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE898B6C53F3640C7B0BAE946F7B4B4C2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Presumption of liability</header><text>For purposes of a civil action under this section, there shall be a rebuttable presumption that a misrepresentation described in subsection (a) was a proximate cause of any harm suffered as a result of COVID–19.</text> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

