<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD789B252048F42B3BC54266FF8D2C5B1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>114 HR 3559 IH: FAA Research and Development Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3559</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000491">Mr. Lucas</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for Federal Aviation Administration research and development, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA9CCB1B30A9A40C8BD60EC0643A35B36" style="OLC"><section id="H9EC8CDFBB5CF423CA216F6B49B67B803" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H592F6ED597B64ED383BD2B774BDAF6C9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>FAA Research and Development Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HE788F88C00D54D338AD41DFC95FABFC9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="H9EC8CDFBB5CF423CA216F6B49B67B803" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE0358A8BBB3A4E99849401018F0B34BD" level="section">Sec. 2. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7346EB70E5B949F2A773AE0242AAE13B" level="section">Sec. 3. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2F4C272EB1654D5E93DE35DCF746BB61" level="title">Title I —FAA Research and Development Organization</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HED36C200B02D4448BF3AD1045BF16659" level="section">Sec. 101. Assistant Administrator for Research and Development.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3B54CE3F814F44ED94CBD0BCE1685070" level="section">Sec. 102. Report on implementation; funding for safety research and development.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB276F5EAC1E042B5B8C53FD8707EBE8F" level="title">Title II —FAA Research and Development Activities</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9D96AA6914364BAA8EC4111B35D3D506" level="section">Sec. 201. Aviation fuel research, development, and usage.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3E643F44BCDF4AE094F0A63D6E8C4A2C" level="section">Sec. 202. Continuous lower energy, emission, and noise (CLEEN).</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBB8361FEAD7E4421BB098F2C6156D302" level="section">Sec. 203. Hydrogen aviation research and development.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9A0CD3E6D67248E8BCF26FBBFD3961E4" level="section">Sec. 204. Air traffic surveillance over oceans and other remote locations.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7DE29AF6B90A4A3DA465A6D1E6F6CFA3" level="section">Sec. 205. Utilization of space-based assets to improve air traffic control and aviation safety.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3D4938F83331483FB140FF6A0A8C42D7" level="section">Sec. 206. Aviation weather technology review.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HEEA15A551CFF4656A4E938883FD44B0E" level="section">Sec. 207. Air traffic surface operations safety.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD9008D3A0E31403FB3C388C416D2BA91" level="section">Sec. 208. Airport and airfield pavement technology research program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HFD1BA800279D40E78D27B1B3FE1096EE" level="section">Sec. 209. Technology review of artificial intelligence and machine learning technologies.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1C6114637D6D4E41AB94D8D45137C5B2" level="section">Sec. 210. Research plan for commercial supersonic research.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H149266FB5B1A47C9972EBD1D14B3658C" level="section">Sec. 211. Electromagnetic spectrum research and development.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9E0BFE74C90B488A847C1B5B998891EE" level="section">Sec. 212. Aviation structures, materials, and advanced manufacturing research and development.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDE125CC5373D4FCB93B5CA93BEDAFDD1" level="section">Sec. 213. Research plan on the remote tower program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1D475E0B540D4713A1BCB782255DB675" level="section">Sec. 214. Air traffic control training.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF2B522BC06324118A917A9E3CA38E95C" level="section">Sec. 215. Report on aviation cybersecurity directives.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HE0358A8BBB3A4E99849401018F0B34BD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H42CC05C4BC6F4308A10BA031AB813F8F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC22B02267BF34D4B8F3221997C575D80"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text>The terms <quote>appropriate committees of Congress</quote> means the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CAD25F0DEA44C22BD0C5C203E7AF5FD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>FAA</header><text>The term <quote>FAA</quote> means the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23538E5E5E1F4CD8A8F97A8961C81085"><enum>(4)</enum><header>NASA</header><text>The term <quote>NASA</quote> means the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6FDBED2A55349D491C9E17374189203"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7346EB70E5B949F2A773AE0242AAE13B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (a) of section 48102 of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC419CE96F472447894BE9ACF9B0D55F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (14), by striking <quote>and</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H765BEA05C23C4B2D89C7B746C09A4FBD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (15) by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF90A27CC1764A63878F579FD0308899"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block id="H2038302F486A4D8BB4DDC33DFF473976" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H0E2EAD5C511F4279B5793946F313F37A"><enum>(16)</enum><text>$255,130,000; for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H432907F01B504D44B932B9AD7EE55C3D"><enum>(17)</enum><text>$261,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5D66878F3093467A8CC599341CA44EB0"><enum>(18)</enum><text>$267,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFC67B9D22324913A5E0FC92BF04D0A3"><enum>(19)</enum><text>$273,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF5F7EB4CB664D138A6AD7F4A405345D"><enum>(20)</enum><text>$279,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><title id="H2F4C272EB1654D5E93DE35DCF746BB61"><enum>I </enum><header>FAA Research and Development Organization</header><section id="HED36C200B02D4448BF3AD1045BF16659"><enum>101.</enum><header>Assistant Administrator for Research and Development</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No funds are authorized to be appropriated for the Office of the Administrator for a fiscal year unless the Administrator has implemented section 711 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/254">Public Law 115–254</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/106">49 U.S.C. 106</external-xref> note).</text></section><section id="H3B54CE3F814F44ED94CBD0BCE1685070"><enum>102.</enum><header>Report on implementation; funding for safety research and development</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the allocation of funding pursuant to section 48102 of title 49, United States Code, to the Secretary of Transportation to conduct civil aviation research and development under sections 44504, 44505, 44507, 44509, and 44511 through 44513 of such title, and to assess the implementation of section 48102(b)(2) of such title.</text></section></title><title id="HB276F5EAC1E042B5B8C53FD8707EBE8F"><enum>II </enum><header>FAA Research and Development Activities</header><section id="H9D96AA6914364BAA8EC4111B35D3D506"><enum>201.</enum><header>Aviation fuel research, development, and usage</header><subsection id="H8F4D0B087CD24B3FA8C50863584EA34D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Roadmap</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation shall coordinate with the Administrator of NASA, the Secretary of Energy, and the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and consult relevant stakeholders, including those in industry and academia, to prepare and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a coordinated research and development roadmap to safely eliminate the use of leaded aviation fuel without adversely affecting the existing piston engine fleet. Such roadmap shall consider activities to promote the development, testing, and certification of safe and lead-free fuel for use in general aviation aircraft, including requisite airport refueling infrastructure.</text></subsection><subsection id="H66BDB178F2C84001A580E2E6ACDC6ED0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Partnership with private industry</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall coordinate with industry regarding research programs for mass production and distribution of unleaded aviation gasoline for market viability, and define criteria to explore incentive programs to reduce lead emissions for communities in need.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3E643F44BCDF4AE094F0A63D6E8C4A2C"><enum>202.</enum><header>Continuous lower energy, emission, and noise (CLEEN)</header><subsection id="H347E479E01CC42108B94ADDBBE68AF7C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall broaden the CLEEN program to include hydrogen and other alternative aviation fuel for development, maturation, and testing of certifiable continuous, lower energy, emission, and noise (CLEEN) aircraft, engine technologies, and fuels for civil airplanes.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9AF8C87FB9384A9E926BD43B61616124"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scope</header><text>Subsection (a) of section 47511 of title 49, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H75C4FDC297454D1588937C110444FE0C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>jet</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB602B13C0D2A4835A12392B8A8CFE557"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsonic</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HBB8361FEAD7E4421BB098F2C6156D302"><enum>203.</enum><header>Hydrogen aviation research and development</header><subsection id="HF0B97F00FCF041BCBD27BD694551066C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in consultation with the Administrator of NASA and the heads of other relevant Federal agencies, shall lead the development of a research and development strategy on the safe use of hydrogen as part of a sustainable future for aviation. Such strategy shall consider the following:</text><paragraph id="H5D6D989AC4294F4B8D784260B8A422CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The feasibility, opportunities, challenges, and pathways toward the potential uses of hydrogen in aviation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF474CD5E263D4D61BB944D322A375547"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The use of hydrogen in combination with other research and development efforts for alternatives to traditional aviation fuel.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8BC73EFBF5D14C308165A58EDB5CD6C9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transmittal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of the Act, the Administrator shall transmit to the appropriate committees of Congress the research and development strategy required under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6D591AC9E2D64780BDF81687CFD7610D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Research and development</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Based on the results of the research and development strategy under subsection (a), the Administrator, in coordination with the Administrator of NASA, may, using amounts made available under section 48102(a) of title 49, United States Code, conduct research and development activities into the following:</text><paragraph id="H566BF1E33FCF4378BA277A4012FCC7DA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The qualification of hydrogen aviation fuel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3165E1CFA114919AEDA90D3497BCECA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The safe transition to such fuel for aircraft.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6D9D531C3EC401B9F45C933565DB248"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The advancement of certification efforts for such fuel.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9A0CD3E6D67248E8BCF26FBBFD3961E4"><enum>204.</enum><header>Air traffic surveillance over oceans and other remote locations</header><subsection id="H3AC2EA99258D426E903CAF0A2E4DC4E2" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Air traffic surveillance over oceans</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in consultation with the Administrator of NASA and the heads of other relevant Federal agencies, shall carry out research, development, demonstration, and testing on civilian air traffic surveillance over oceans and other remote locations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3E125702D21149CDAC015CAE771BB21A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the research, development, demonstration, and testing under subsection (a), the Administrator shall—</text><paragraph id="H322616E89A0B4C15A643AE31461801B3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consider the need for international interoperability of technologies, data, operations, and air traffic control systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B52FCD828CC442A8CE7F9B43A9CE908"><enum>(2)</enum><text>examine the status of using air traffic surveillance technologies, including space-based Automatic Dependent Surveillance-Broadcast, to facilitate the implementation of minimal separation standards over United States-controlled oceanic airspace;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE75F34EE519A468BB8B61DB6444F912B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify mitigating approaches to reducing any operational challenges, associated costs, or workload impacts; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D7A9D0A267946F88BD9D2A7F0DA5DEB" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use testing, data collection, evaluation, and analysis on the use of air traffic surveillance technologies, including space-based Automatic Dependent Surveillance-Broadcast, to support the activities described in paragraphs (1) through (3).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H176A990887CA4C449B9DD153225EC473"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may carry out a pilot program to test and evaluate air traffic surveillance equipment over United States-controlled oceanic airspace and other remote locations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1059EC7545F04F3C95A6857159C7188A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the activities carried out under this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H7DE29AF6B90A4A3DA465A6D1E6F6CFA3"><enum>205.</enum><header>Utilization of space-based assets to improve air traffic control and aviation safety</header><subsection id="HBB7A9CA187D54A068B19C17E8C370677"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Using amounts available under section 48102(a) of title 49, United States Code, the Administrator, in coordination with the Administrator of the NASA, and in consultation with industry stakeholders, shall carry out research, development, demonstration, and testing of air traffic Space-Based Automatic Dependent Surveillance-Broadcast (ADS-B) data. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6275B14681BC4BA394B2095DBCD6B84A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Research activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the research, development, demonstration, and testing under subsection (a) the Administrator shall focus on the following:</text><paragraph id="H7E1E41CFF21842348C2900C05F61B7A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Monitoring and automatically reporting air turbulence events.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BA8B74E56374DB9BFC4A6DB3581CFD3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Providing space-based multilateration surveillance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8B05633C7954CCFA1FBD025D576DC2C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identifying global positioning system (GPS) and global navigation satellite system (GNSS) disruptions affecting air traffic services and assessing the impact of such events on the safety of air traffic and the National Airspace System.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20C0960B4EC24632830AC21138D08B32"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Evaluating the feasibility of implementing and using aviation safety technologies and systems using space-based Automatic Dependent Surveillance-Broadcast data.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD8FF611A0A145EB9D9F949B70ED1671"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall provide to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the research and development program under subsection (a) and the information obtained pursuant to the activities researched pursuant to subsection (b).</text></subsection></section><section id="H3D4938F83331483FB140FF6A0A8C42D7"><enum>206.</enum><header>Aviation weather technology review</header><subsection id="HF8FDA63F112941CFA6F69322270B9210" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in consultation with the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, shall conduct a review of current and planned research, modeling, and technology capabilities that have the potential to more accurately detect and predict weather impacts to aviation, inform how advanced predictive models can enhance aviation operations, and increase national airspace system safety and efficiency.</text></subsection><subsection id="H792DBF48FC0F41ECA257E4B8D36973D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report containing the results of the review conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="HEEA15A551CFF4656A4E938883FD44B0E"><enum>207.</enum><header>Air traffic surface operations safety</header><subsection id="H928561D27AB34E9FB228B3EB1A3DF064" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Research</header><text>The Administrator, in consultation with the Administrator of NASA and the heads of other appropriate Federal agencies, shall continue to carry out research on technologies and operations to enhance air traffic surface operations safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6B763A71457E494F9FAC8A92FF7F2971"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The research program under subsection (a) shall examine the following:</text><paragraph id="H636B566E1961428C8DC4394163E0335C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The safety of current air traffic control operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A235AA1E61141899CEAD3220422FD83"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Emerging in-cockpit technologies to enhance ground situational awareness.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30FA9BA421C04A4688A797D0BD09171E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Emerging technologies to enhance air traffic control situational awareness.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAEB2725C46449A0BD8D342655DC7B50"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Air traffic surface operations safety for diverse advanced air mobility operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE625905E825A43648FCCF3D0689CFF76"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Safety and operational data needed to inform current and future safety programs on advanced air mobility vehicles.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H345AC1529CEA424482E3C61DD450F63E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the research carried out under this section, including regarding the transition into operational use of such research.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD9008D3A0E31403FB3C388C416D2BA91"><enum>208.</enum><header>Airport and airfield pavement technology research program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 744 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/254">Public Law 115–254</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/44505">49 U.S.C. 44505</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HBD676EEE1D494971A82EF477E4862532"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>and</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D1166CA23874E5A9B19FC1017565778"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>durable airfield pavements.</quote> and inserting <quote>resilient and sustainable airfield pavements; and</quote>; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80A245EEBD6D42E4B4C6F062622E62B8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA47AC94DCA984C029DB76083234EF4A5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H9420588776F64AFAAD833F66B60A1C65"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop sustainability and resiliency guidelines to improve long-term pavement performance and reduce carbon emissions.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HFD1BA800279D40E78D27B1B3FE1096EE"><enum>209.</enum><header>Technology review of artificial intelligence and machine learning technologies</header><subsection id="HC04ED2E373A14493A0A58019DF4A5CE6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text>The Administrator shall conduct a review of current and planned artificial intelligence and machine learning technologies to improve airport efficiency and safety.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFC8202FB784C4345B9C4B5C06EA1B59F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Summaries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The review conducted under subsection (a) shall include examination of the application of artificial intelligence and machine learning technologies to the following:</text><paragraph id="H9C699904765F4FFD8FD714D3334DA10A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Jet bridges.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC99761D478D4DA4B7927D70901088B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Airport service vehicles on airport movement areas.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EE752B5A5CB4964A26599F17A86E5DA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Aircraft taxi.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2F2D895DE7644A7A288D2C08DF864EA" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">FAA air traffic control operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H883EB21983544B838ECB5FA6F6E856D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Airport security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6235D312A1A54589B3A71C370F737B37"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Any other areas the Administrator determines necessary to help improve airport efficiency and safety.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1A19E64BC2A4C5F9519C879F5168B66"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report containing the results of the review conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H1C6114637D6D4E41AB94D8D45137C5B2"><enum>210.</enum><header>Research plan for commercial supersonic research</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator, in consultation with the Administrator of NASA and industry, shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a comprehensive research plan to build on research and development and identify any further research and development needed to support establishment of Federal and international policies, regulations, standards, and recommended practices relating to the certification and safe and efficient operation of civil supersonic aircraft and supersonic overland flight.</text></section><section id="H149266FB5B1A47C9972EBD1D14B3658C"><enum>211.</enum><header>Electromagnetic spectrum research and development</header><subsection id="HFD421050D53B4885A9929FCE3BEE52B2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall conduct research, engineering, and development related to the effective and efficient use and management of radio frequency spectrum in the civil aviation domain, including for aircraft, unmanned aircraft systems, and advanced air mobility. Such research, engineering, and development shall, at a minimum, address the following:</text><paragraph id="HAC365D915A4C4BDF8845D56965DD3D55"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">How reallocation or repurposing of radio frequency spectrum adjacent to spectrum allocated for communication, navigation, and surveillance may impact the safety of civil aviation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17B60A86F85545AEAE0DA253AE94C9BE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The effectiveness of measures to identify risks, protect, and mitigate against spectrum interference in frequency bands used in civil and commercial aviation operations to ensure public safety.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41BDC607EC6F49B989C76BEE9EF43108"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The implications, including risks, of new or emerging technologies or other factors on the environment for radio frequency spectrum interference.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C6C8670E9E145B3918D6966888DC344"><enum>(4)</enum><text>How various new or emerging technologies may enable improvements in the prevention of, mitigation of, or resilience to interference.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H247D3FF0E5264C7FA039DE3E2764D299"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report containing the results of the research, engineering, and development conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H9E0BFE74C90B488A847C1B5B998891EE"><enum>212.</enum><header>Aviation structures, materials, and advanced manufacturing research and development</header><subsection id="H9DCD35FF9DA44B15801A3AE2ABFDE498"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Using the amounts available under section 48102(a) of title 49, United States Code, the Administrator, in coordination with the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, shall carry out a research and development program for advancing aviation structures, materials, and manufacturing for the safe use in and on aircraft.</text></subsection><subsection id="H599F0C31AAA440A28EC0FEEC906AA927"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The program under subsection (a) shall, to the extent practicable, include research and development relating to the following:</text><paragraph id="H1D08E4699B454FAE880F5DF42A853BE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Metallic and non-metallic based additive materials and processes, composites, and other advanced materials.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1AE7677336E4629957797C3B9DA6E0C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Process development for the development of design and manufacturing standards for aviation structures, materials, and additive manufacturing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6C28479E4BA4BB3BF93F9108F68B596"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Improving certification efficiency of aviation structures, materials, and additively manufactured aviation products and components.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83D6BF507DA2417887CE13CFDBC4F884"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Evaluating long-term material and structural behavior and associated maintenance, including support for fatigue life determination, structural changes related to fatigue, thermal, corrosive environments, and expected maintenance of such materials, including recommended repair techniques.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22D675E774B347849659931E5C1D8CD5"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Partnering with commercial entities to mature and certify, as appropriate, metal additive manufacturing, including large-scale additive manufacturing, aviation structures, and advanced materials capabilities, including the development and qualification of new material chemistries, to be used in the manufacture of aircraft.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H45DEE4892EEE499F998FEB98969C09B1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall provide to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the findings of the research under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="HDE125CC5373D4FCB93B5CA93BEDAFDD1"><enum>213.</enum><header>Research plan on the remote tower program</header><subsection id="H3CBEC9EEDAE74709A95A9DDD34BED30D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a comprehensive plan for research, development, testing, and evaluation needed to mature remote tower technology and provide a strategic roadmap to support standards development, validation, and operational certification of such technology.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1D1710962F5C4D75BEB9BFB0A6EF8C1E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>As part of the plan required under subsection (a), the Administrator should consider the use of remote tower technologies for advanced air mobility operations.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1D475E0B540D4713A1BCB782255DB675"><enum>214.</enum><header>Air traffic control training</header><subsection id="H9301BF877EAC4FD78DC0FDC8C855AAD9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Using amounts made available under section 48102(a) of title 49, United States Code, the Administrator shall carry out a research program to evaluate opportunities to modernize, enhance, and streamline training time to become a Certified Professional Controller.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCD55487F3F9245A5869EA2E05EF842D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The research under subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="H71FBC9C8F2E34DF7AAC5E160F152FB3A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assess the use of advanced technologies, such as artificial intelligence, machine learning, adaptive computer-based simulation, virtual reality, or augmented reality, to enhance controller knowledge retention, improve performance, and improve the effectiveness of training time; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F3CF5722E374B358C4FD89BB448DCB9"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop a timeline to deploy proven advanced technologies and associated processes for accreditation in training programs and training facilities within the national airspace system.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7AE6058A4904486AAE961FA6AB541B15"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the findings of the research under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="HF2B522BC06324118A917A9E3CA38E95C"><enum>215.</enum><header>Report on aviation cybersecurity directives</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the status of the FAA’s implementation of section 2111 of the FAA Extension, Safety, and Security Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/114/190">Public Law 114–190</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/44903">49 U.S.C. 44903</external-xref> note; relating to the development of a comprehensive and strategic aviation cybersecurity framework and establishment of a research and development plan to mitigate cybersecurity risks in the National Airspace System). The report, at minimum, shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HFD06AD26B3BC4FA8828D44308473CE12"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the FAA’s progress in developing, implementing, and updating such framework.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD1F531695944079B2E3FDF786AB46BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of prioritized research and development activities for the most needed improvements with target dates to safeguard the National Airspace System.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C80A7D6A44A41B5B99AC6ABECA6FAAA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An explanation for any delays or challenges in so implementing such section.</text></paragraph></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

