<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC867185A1F7B458E850BB654E86D5545" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2733 IH: Department of Veterans Affairs Office of Inspector General Training Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2733</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="W000809">Mr. Womack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to require the employees of the Department of Veterans Affairs to receive training developed by the Inspector General of the Department on reporting wrongdoing to, responding to requests from, and cooperating with the Office of Inspector General of the Department, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4DE00DFCF74041A29E82D5AC9914620A" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H0F2FBFCB74744B0A93404C5CC00494B7"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Veterans Affairs Office of Inspector General Training Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H4F48844835664AE6BECF40E9B5D1DFC0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs employee training regarding Office of Inspector General</header><subsection id="HEF753B5A10D14EC6B65FD9ED218BD5AF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Training</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall require each employee of the Department of Veterans Affairs who begins employment with the Department on or after the date of the enactment of this Act to receive training that the Inspector General of the Department shall develop on the reporting of wrongdoing to, responding to requests from, and cooperating with the Office of Inspector General of the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAF0B424C4E0A464C88258ACD471DA8B4" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timing of training</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary shall require each employee of the Department covered under such subsection to undergo the training required by such subsection not later than one year after the date on which the employee begins employment with the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2698010F026C4E08A69097A5F1781BD8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>Training developed and required under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HC2ECCF58D38448B2965B634E4E4ADED0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Definition of the role, responsibilities, and legal authority of the Inspector General of the Department and the duties of employees of the Department for engaging with the Office of Inspector General.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CC9FB511395409685184281A19055DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Identification of the circumstances and mechanisms for reporting fraud, waste, abuse, and other wrongdoing to the Inspector General, including making confidential complaints to the Inspector General.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CFCE9D880F34E7796DD2B1C2C2B44BE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Identification of the prohibitions and remedies that help to protect employees of the Department from retaliation when reporting wrongdoing to the Inspector General.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA1A1D6FFDE841DAB2201CB45B9A523A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Recognition of opportunities to engage with staff of the Office of Inspector General to improve programs, operations, and services of the Department. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFA99EB303BFE4C67B2A4AB8337BD836D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Design and update</header><text>The Inspector General of the Department shall design, and update as the Inspector General considers appropriate, the training developed and required by subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H07B578EB567645E9908822721262ECF8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>System</header><text>The Secretary shall provide, via the talent management system of the Department, or successor system, the training developed and required under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H59D238673EFF4345A32C83FCC5B05668"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Relation to certain training</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that training developed and required under subsection (a) is separate and distinct from training provided under section 733 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H625FB89E3E7E48D5A2C7452CC5855A89"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Notice to employees</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that the Inspector General is afforded the opportunity, not less frequently than twice each year and more frequently if the Inspector General considers appropriate under extraordinary circumstances, to use the electronic mail system of the Department to notify all authorized users of such system of the following:</text><paragraph id="HD763FED94B4B437D9F841DB82C06BC95"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The roles and responsibilities of the employees of the Department when engaging with the Office of Inspector General.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFD36F4B68F94360AA56E0DE03DB4ADA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The availability of training provided under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADEDA3A31A5445289B7D40C698A18385"><enum>(3)</enum><text>How to access training provided under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBADDA6D3B58844AAB79F9BA182B475A4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Information about how to contact the Office of Inspector General, including a link to any website-based reporting form of the Office.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

