<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H42AE6E4CBE0342D0B35FCE9F55376E30" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 527 IH: Ensure Vaccine Mandates Eliminate Non-Competes Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 527</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230125">January 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To void existing non-compete agreements for any employee who is fired for not complying with an employer&#8217;s COVID&#8211;19 vaccine mandate, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCABDF2ADC24E4C75AD253B1B3032614A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD626C045FC504044B7D9B408C987F729" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ensure Vaccine Mandates Eliminate Non-Competes Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>EVEN Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H8FFA2A5E128140D78EE879EAD7C1B92A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Certain non-compete agreements unenforceable</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Any non-compete agreement between an employer and an employee or former employee who has been fired for not receiving a COVID–19 vaccine shall be unenforceable. </text></section>
<section id="H2440F4562C71498A864A809274F9282F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on certain non-compete agreements</header>
<subsection id="HD214A4BA94664982A824633AD1CB1FFA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Regulations required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commission shall issue regulations under section 553 of title 5, United States Code, to prohibit an employer from enforcing a non-compete agreement with an employee or former employee who has been fired for not receiving a COVID–19 vaccine. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H36BBF455053F4052A47B22B4766FDD4E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement</header> <paragraph id="HA30B5E34B5D3488EAA7A9EBB79EA501A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be treated as a violation of a regulation under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>) regarding unfair or deceptive acts or practices.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2F6F94647B7341EFA2509DD353B922BB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of the commission</header><text>The Commission shall enforce this section and the regulations promulgated under this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section, and any person who violates this section or a regulation promulgated under this section shall be subject to the penalties entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB6FBBDA9AC484BCE95F5DBF575B15370" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Enforcement by state attorneys general</header><text>If the chief law enforcement officer of a State, or an official or agency designated by a State, has reason to believe that any person has violated or is violating this section or a regulation promulgated under this section, the attorney general, official, or agency of the State, in addition to any authority it may have to bring an action in State court under its consumer protection law, may bring a civil action in any appropriate United States district court or in any other court of competent jurisdiction, including a State court, to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H132ACD9592D0473092D44E86E8880DDF" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enjoin further such violation by such person;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC965A6DA6BFC4C47800A83CA6D605C09" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>enforce compliance with such subsection;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC6BCA6FA6263457F878F528A7F3ED9BD" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>obtain civil penalties; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB4D308C33EFF4731B6023B0C4719320C" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>obtain damages, restitution, or other compensation on behalf of residents of the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HF0EA2B6E598644279AF54292AC4AB143"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H17AD7EE13A5F458B80B45A31E5D0525E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Trade Commission.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCE8855E6C4B94908841924501641D1D5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Employer</header><text>The term <quote>employer</quote> has the meaning given in section 3 of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/203">29 U.S.C. 203</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7CC4D37E96BA4A19A4D4B18ACC35A00B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Non-compete agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>non-compete agreement</quote> means an agreement, entered into between an employer and an employee, that restricts such employee from performing, after the employment relationship between the employer and the employee terminates, any of the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H15D928C3C20A438087D51B581D7F5A41"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Any work for another employer for a specified period of time. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC34B1FCAA04B4FF2B5F376E4D1995ED2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any work in a specified geographical area. </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB9AC0281588B48B891CB99C7D487F50E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any work for another employer that is similar to such employee’s work for the employer that is a party to such agreement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

