<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4FF01CD7D3A847D6ABDCF1B646D50920" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6872 IH: Hydrogen for Ports Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6872</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Energy to establish a grant program to support hydrogen-fueled equipment at ports and to conduct a study with the Secretary of Transportation and the Secretary of Homeland Security on the feasibility and safety of using hydrogen-derived fuels, including ammonia, as a shipping fuel.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF40DC40C95194C458D8260CF2ED470F3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H386527B9641343E08B7F5392E3C3860F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hydrogen for Ports Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H08E396DF58DC48A2BA564B150AC559EA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Maritime modernization grant program</header> <subsection id="H58E1D59D78664B129579D54BD43A7121"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HF9C7DD6A7C13401FBA434548539F2854"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <term>eligible entity</term> means an entity described in subsection (d).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF9179FAB58074730A6D72624C78DED00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the <act-name parsable-cite="ISDA">Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFBB6DE96E4F343068F0A26CAE4F93209"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Low-income or disadvantaged community</header><text>The term <term>low-income or disadvantaged community</term> means a community (including a city, a town, a county, and any reasonably isolated and divisible segment of a larger municipality) with an annual median household income that is less than 100 percent of the statewide annual median household income for the State in which the community is located, according to the most recent decennial census. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC90943D3F2FA4833BDD330C4FBB850F8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>program</term> means the program established under subsection (b).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCAFB420C7D2646C28CCA33C436ABEDC5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA0FB1A7E7BAE4AF587E5E22941CAC669"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a program under which the Secretary shall provide grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities for—</text> 
<paragraph id="H0E90D59960C644C980098B8E01991901"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the purchase, installation, construction, facilitation, maintenance, or operation of, as appropriate—</text> <subparagraph id="H824B87446DC745BA999D91DC8440B0CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>hydrogen- or ammonia-fueled cargo-handling equipment, including, at a minimum, equipment used for drayage applications;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H46F91D8255024BB0ABA1B0F072F3542B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>hydrogen fuel cell or ammonia-fueled trucks for use at ports;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H146B6FE6A8A840B8B9C20920EF0F5CCE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>hydrogen fuel cell or ammonia-fueled ferries, tugboats, dredging vessels, container ships, bulk carriers, fuel tankers, and other marine vessels;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H16D6805B740C4778A84A81D165F7A0C9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>hydrogen fuel cell-based shore power for ships while docked at the port;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAED69EFFFF6945AA8D656CA683FBA93F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>hydrogen fuel cell or ammonia onsite power plants; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF8065D0BAF124B1DA721FB9297A5E7BC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>port infrastructure for hydrogen or ammonia import, export, storage, and fueling; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2684C5424FBD4661BB0E62EF5B65AB9B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the training of ship crew and shore personnel to handle hydrogen or ammonia. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2444B8EC2B374E39A3A67646DF1DEEC3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Goals</header><text>The goals of the program shall be—</text> <paragraph id="HF1093EB9F5B24E8288B500B1380165BA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to demonstrate fuel cell, hydrogen, or ammonia technologies in maritime and associated logistics applications;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9FF97391D97546B2B5F05001719EEB1F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to assist in the development and validation of technical targets for hydrogen, ammonia, and fuel cell systems for maritime and associated logistics applications;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H381D14EF5FB3419394356513B991365B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to benchmark the conditions required for broad commercialization of hydrogen, ammonia, and fuel cell technologies in maritime and associated logistics applications;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44418FF3E18D4B2AB8F0546C8BD9E3F9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to assess the operational and technical considerations for installing, constructing, and using hydrogen- or ammonia-fueled equipment and supporting infrastructure at ports; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HED132C7946FD4046A9D8C27513371200"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to reduce emissions and improve air quality in areas in and around ports. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1A9A134B9A934BE0B9A33B67D0F0C937"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header> 
<paragraph id="H884D541BBB8248B380E7132811145229"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity eligible to receive a grant under the program is—</text> <subparagraph id="H5057E04251A94A0893BD7E61A43784F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF4C7D25CD9E344A480DB01B31CA746DE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a political subdivision of a State;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCAAF24CDA2B745C0B5BD258742750808"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a local government;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0EA004EB28744FF29D7739FC5E37731E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a public agency or publicly chartered authority established by 1 or more States;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFD8472EAD7BA44299A91867C522FE808"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a special purpose district with a transportation function;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5893AF5A8F4B43368A7D6648AE43B284"><enum>(F)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe or a consortium of Indian Tribes;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H72BB59FC55B64A4D940039A747780A00"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a multistate or multijurisdictional group of entities described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (F); or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3B2AB9A08E3C4BB595DF2E0292ADF7A7"><enum>(H)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (2), a private entity or group of private entities, including the owners or operators of 1 or more facilities at a port.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0C1540E8316B42F09ADFFF40615692FD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Joint eligibility with private entities</header><text>A private entity or group of private entities is eligible for a grant under the program if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3AD091F82EF5404A8CE5E40D9D714BB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the private entity or group of private entities partners with an entity described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (G) of paragraph (1) for purposes of applying for, and carrying out activities under, the grant; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8B3B4CE50C724D3D86F8A7DE170B0424"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the entity described in the applicable subparagraph of that paragraph is the lead entity with respect to the application and those activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H71C6E15EE2704716BDF1FDC3840AA8B2" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Applications</header> 
<paragraph id="H474C28654D2C46E0BA3C3DEFB8243623" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under the program shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8B4CE1F654694D2A8F18FF4B75803584" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The application of an eligible entity described in subparagraph (H) of subsection (d)(1) shall be submitted jointly with an entity described in subparagraphs (A) through (G) of that subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9CEAA06300BE4565B24EA60E673145EF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In providing grants under the program, the Secretary, to the maximum extent practicable, shall—</text> <paragraph id="HEA425521A0834CFAA2D0464044448B18"><enum>(1)</enum><text>select projects that will generate the greatest benefit to low-income or disadvantaged communities; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H684250EF9AD94D95AF1E47F22AEF68EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>select projects that will—</text> <subparagraph id="H811C9540C43C4F3AAB59EB806BB74A98"><enum>(A)</enum><text>maximize the creation or retention of jobs in the United States; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBB1B3AC1872F48A78F81B2BE039DD002"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide the highest job quality.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0850986C4D144755A0158289B39725C2"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In selecting eligible entities to receive a grant under the program, the Secretary shall give priority to projects that will provide greater net impact in avoiding or reducing emissions of greenhouse gases.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8F9063D074904124A46408620DB35B98"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Leak detection</header><text>Each eligible entity that receives a grant under the program shall conduct—</text> <paragraph id="H677DC7D15E2D43FD99FABD1BA96475F2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a hydrogen leakage monitoring, reporting, and verification (also known as <quote>MRV</quote>) program; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCB9A6203E4F64384A645D6BBFC4D0ADA" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a hydrogen leak detection and repair (also known as <quote>LDAR</quote>) program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCFEFFA8D5909429FA752C50150E7A95A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section $100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7B348EBF4B5046DE88E363996A4F6199"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Prohibition on use of funds</header><text>None of the funds made available under this section may be used to provide a grant to purchase fully automated cargo handling equipment that is remotely operated or remotely monitored with or without the exercise of human intervention or control, if the Secretary of Transportation determines such equipment would result in a net loss of jobs within a port or port terminal. </text></subsection></section> <section id="HE56A8395C9BD4737BEA5D76BD8130BA2"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study</header> <subsection id="HC04DFBDF81A548BFAEB54A3875FAB4C1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy, in consultation with the Secretary of Transportation and the Secretary of Homeland Security, shall conduct, and submit to Congress a report describing the results of, a study—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7F3B95985EED45E78D600387A397B87F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to fully address the challenges to ensure the safe use and handling of hydrogen, ammonia, and other hydrogen-based fuels on vessels and in ports;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD5560DB785164440926868FD23ECC176"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to identify, compare, and evaluate the feasibility of, the safety, environmental, and health impacts of, and best practices with respect to, the use of hydrogen-derived fuels, including ammonia, as a shipping fuel; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF0180810F4904072A37D3CC1A8501472"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to identify and evaluate considerations for hydrogen and ammonia storage, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H9E32FA64400244479E6D4486F830662B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at ports; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7133CF6E5BCD47F892CCF6B2648C9E2B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>on board vessels; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6592B4C6A8CF44B88C2471A72F004190"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for subsea hydrogen storage; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF1AB88DF48B34F8BA28D8582C530A861"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to assess the cost and value of a hydrogen or ammonia strategic reserve, either as a new facility or as a modification to the Strategic Petroleum Reserve established under part B of title I of the Energy Policy and Conservation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6231">42 U.S.C. 6231 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H51014D6AD56545BB85B34DC9E6222CCD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary of Energy, the Secretary of Transportation, and the Secretary of Homeland Security shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H558BC71915F146BDB0FA0726AA6F2BB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>take into account lessons learned from demonstration projects in other industries, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HC478AA736E3044C3A9510023B38375E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>projects carried out in the United States;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF3C219053A654C01A9C2CD376E7BBB11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>projects carried out in other countries; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H662CA5FD01AD48AC9E29F2D3C4FC9048"><enum>(C)</enum><text>projects relating to the automotive industry, buses, petroleum refining, chemical production, fertilizer production, and stationary power; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7496116834B447569BE93E6D5D0C601F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>evaluate the applicability of the lessons described in paragraph (1) to the use of hydrogen in maritime and associated logistics applications.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

