<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF5E3172EEE52403497B46523D058AB88" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6780 IH: Medically Tailored Home-Delivered Meals Demonstration Pilot Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6780</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M000317">Ms. Malliotakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to establish a Medically Tailored Home-Delivered Meals Demonstration Program to test a payment and service delivery model under part A of Medicare to improve clinical health outcomes and reduce the rate of readmissions of certain individuals.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H19D06353C3AA4A1AB77FD2E8CD5AA852" style="OLC"><section id="H2FF946E4C1014129BEA12B42B0BF7010" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medically Tailored Home-Delivered Meals Demonstration Pilot Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H40D6630393D94131AFBD9575DF5B29D2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Medically Tailored Home-Delivered Meals Demonstration Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part E of title XVIII of the Social Security Act is amended by inserting after section 1866G (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc-7">42 U.S.C. 1395cc–7</external-xref>) the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9404A84CFD3E4901ACF936DC12DFDD05"><section id="H22526DC9401547079BACC3B605BC603B"><enum>1866H.</enum><header>Medically Tailored Home-Delivered Meals Demonstration Program</header><subsection id="HF918654E75794DDBACFAAA4279F7FFAC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the 4-year period beginning not later than 30 months after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall conduct, in accordance with the provisions of this section, a Medically Tailored Home-Delivered Meals Demonstration Program (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>) to test a payment and service delivery model under which selected hospitals provide medically tailored home-delivered meals under part A of this title to qualified individuals, with respect to such hospitals, to improve clinical health outcomes and reduce the rate of readmissions of such individuals.</text></subsection><subsection id="H449A44CE62E34352B232DB857B819284"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Selection of hospitals To participate in Program</header><paragraph id="H4CB2BA6C067A445BB623FC0056776586"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Selected hospitals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the Program, the Secretary shall, not later than January 1, 2024, select to participate in the Program at least 20 eligible hospitals across all geographic regions, with consideration given to eligible hospitals located in rural areas and other underserved communities, that the Secretary determines have the capacity to satisfy the requirements described in subsection (c). In this section, each such eligible hospital so selected shall be referred to as a <quote>selected hospital</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D0E6D57F532481AACDD887DD391DFE3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible hospitals</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <quote>eligible hospital</quote> means a subsection (d) hospital (as defined in section 1886(d)(1)(B)) that—</text><subparagraph id="H621267BDD14B42E1AAE3EEDB5B06995D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submits to the Secretary an application, at such time and in such form and manner as specified by the Secretary, that contains—</text><clause id="H6A590B67801B4591B0FF502D6DFDD3A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an attestation (in such form and manner as specified by the Secretary) that such hospital has the ability, or has in effect an arrangement with a provider of services, supplier, or other entity with at least 1 year of experience in furnishing medically tailored home-delivered meals that has the ability, to comply with the requirements described in subsection (c); and</text></clause><clause id="HD55D640A44EB4A17B6D6FE4931044122"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary may require;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H825C63EFB5204EC4A2DA6EC8F45CF141"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has, for the 2 most recent fiscal years ending prior to the date of selection by the Secretary under paragraph (1), averaged at least 3 stars for the overall hospital quality star rating on the Internet website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (including Care Compare or a successor website); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H467F75786A2F4A7CBEFA00C5AEB0374B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is not, as of the date of selection by the Secretary under paragraph (1), subject to—</text><clause id="H853A038ABAB84FFD85992D11A1031F5E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the requirement to return any overpayment pursuant to section 1128J(d); or</text></clause><clause id="H2DC7DBAB59994051B4CDE8E00AE418A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any activity described in section 1893(b) (relating to Medicare integrity program actions).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA9E9AA97625A4BBD96A332F64A34CFDB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Minimum Program requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the Program, a selected hospital shall comply with each of the following requirements:</text><paragraph id="HF729F817EBA549609FDB00A3C3D92811"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Staffing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The selected hospital shall provide (including through an arrangement described in subsection (b)(2)(A)(i)), for the duration of the participation of the hospital under the Program, a physician, registered dietitian or nutrition professional, or clinical social worker to carry out the screening and re-screening pursuant to paragraph (2), and medical nutrition therapy pursuant to paragraph (3)(B).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30299DEDCB194AB5972FDCD46A3D88EA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Screening and re-screening</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The selected hospital (including through an arrangement described in subsection (b)(2)(A)(i)) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H7F960B0A97264392A91EB3D28A5F0AF8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as part of the discharge planning process described in section 1861(ee), screen individuals that are inpatients of such selected hospital with validated screening tools (as developed by the Secretary) to determine whether such individuals are qualified individuals; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9862BD08BC844D1E913C9E3EF01C869C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an individual determined pursuant to subparagraph (A) or this subparagraph to be a qualified individual, re-screen such individual with validated screening tools (as determined by the Secretary) every 12 weeks after such determination occurring during the participation of the hospital under the Program to determine whether such individual continues to be a qualified individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8ED56F0DC7254199B54328B0C985B131"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Providing medically tailored home-delivered meals and medical nutrition therapy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an individual that is determined by the selected hospital pursuant to paragraph (2) to be a qualified individual, the selected hospital (including through an arrangement described in subsection (b)(2)(A)(i)) shall with respect to the period during which such hospital is participating in the Program—</text><subparagraph id="H05820E0A4BB24021AE2F3DA5277FA94B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide, for each day during a period of at least 12 weeks, for the preparation and delivery to such individual of at least 2 medically tailored home-delivered meals (or a portioned equivalent) that meet at least two-thirds of the daily nutritional needs of the qualified individual; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD893098EE9714AD98DBEBFAD636E5FFE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide to such qualified individual, in connection with delivering such meals and for a period of at least 12 weeks and not more than 1 year, medical nutrition therapy. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5B8AAF432914178A954B286E473C199"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Data submission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The selected hospital shall submit to the Secretary data, in such form, manner, and frequency as designated by the Secretary, so that the Secretary may determine the affect of the Program with respect to the factors described in subsection (e)(2)(B).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAF04CC6CD0B41288DC0E503BCE42BC9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header><text>The selected hospital shall satisfy such additional requirements as may be specified by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HA12214B9283D408FB485513FD6CC9F5A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Payment; cost-Sharing</header><paragraph id="HBE72DF6D61FF48808E811BF5FA92D861"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Payment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall determine the form, manner, and amount of payment to be provided to a selected hospital under the Program. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A8A39C0BA6B4419B7019AAEFF0AE85F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cost-sharing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Items and services for which payment may be made under the Program shall be provided without application of any deductible, copayment, coinsurance, or other cost-sharing under this title.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HE96EFDD7635E4162839791718D1389E7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Evaluations</header><paragraph id="HF85BC21B9B9B4B0E8C51ABB80759E3F4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assessing clinical health outcomes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall assess the clinical health outcomes of each individual who is determined by a selected hospital pursuant to subsection (c)(2) to be a qualified individual for a period of at least 12 weeks and not more than 1 year after the date on which such individual is so determined under subparagraph (A) of such subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FC009DD52E94322B271F8E43B43197E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Intermediate and final evaluations</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct an intermediate and final evaluation of the Program. Each such evaluation shall—</text><subparagraph id="H4D6451B58A8345E195AE8676FDB027DB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>based on the assessments conducted under paragraph (1), with respect to individuals determined to be qualified individuals and the periods for which such assessments are so conducted, determine—</text><clause id="HBAFFE8114218436397E8054D6E2EBCA8"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of inpatient admissions of such individuals;</text></clause><clause id="HFBBA0BF14DE84ADD9583530E4A9B04AE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of admissions to skilled nursing facilities of such individuals; and</text></clause><clause id="HC6925327C64740248197209D13D98F41"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total expenditures under part A with respect to such individuals; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1EA92277A21F4476BED0C7C168CFA23A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>determine the extent to which the Program has—</text><clause commented="no" id="H3EE0F94D73D84966828BEC2B5CBA0EE7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improved clinical health outcomes, as defined by the Secretary;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HC1B89FFCA7264C089A58F0F5D08A2692"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reduced the cost of care under part A (including costs associated with readmission as defined in section 1886(q)(5)(E)); and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H7D36735875D64A91ADCD0FFCB662B19B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>increased patient satisfaction, as defined by the Secretary; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C492D04FEF94AC0A26DE772F1804033"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specify the form, manner, and amounts of payments made under the Program pursuant to subsection (d)(1) and the effectiveness of such payment form, manner, and amounts. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H553720C4B8594582925F79F2ED8CF270"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to Congress—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H0AE9FD7593064F06AD520A81588BC690"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 3 years after the date of implementation of the Program, a report with respect to the intermediate evaluation under paragraph (2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9430F4E4599548C5AF1DCA11ACF5AFFF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 6 years after such date of implementation, a report with respect to the final evaluation under such paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HE7B3A428FC0049AB9C25B82B80F38A44"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H364050824C374486AD1B3406D755DE73"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H6DA406508846435F95100C3F029970D3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Medical nutrition therapy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>medical nutrition therapy</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1861(vv)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5C339A60BD6477DAC96F220EA55662D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Medically tailored home-delivered meal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>medically tailored home-delivered meal</term> means, with respect to a qualified individual, a meal that is designed by a registered dietitian or nutritional professional for the treatment plan of the qualified individual.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H377280A437B847159701E4B8AE1C4F9F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualified individual</header><text>The term <term>qualified individual</term> means an individual, with respect to a selected hospital, who—</text><subparagraph id="HEF9C20288DEF434D928D21838F00EC54"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is entitled to benefits under part A;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7AA1C2D12758407DB72BAAF84952CA6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a diet-impacted disease (such as kidney disease, congestive heart failure, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, or any other disease the Secretary determines appropriate); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CBE5D132AD2455EB64C66EF07DA1758"><enum>(C)</enum><text>at the time of discharge from such hospital—</text><clause id="H5ED86918028D4BFA91B884C8DE073A96"><enum>(i)</enum><text>lives at home;</text></clause><clause id="HBD0DB5EC860A464B97828FDFFFA8F9C2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is not eligible for—</text><subclause id="H862F567A92F0498F880DD04F32578931"><enum>(I)</enum><text>extended care services (as defined in section 1861(h));</text></subclause><subclause id="HCAA39D5BE993488499486C0AAE7B1657"><enum>(II)</enum><text>post-hospital extended care services (as defined in section 1861(i)); or</text></subclause><subclause id="H39039006EBFE4F9FA4EED1C314632283"><enum>(III)</enum><text>post-institutional home health services (as defined in section 1861(tt));</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HEDB6A8ED32F34DECAFE9C3C28A6633A2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>has not made an election under section 1812(d)(1) to receive hospice care;</text></clause><clause id="HD539E910F575441B8CEF6D788346A2B5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is certified by a physician at the time of discharge to be limited with respect to at least 2 of the activities of daily living (as described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7702B">section 7702B(c)(2)(B)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986); and</text></clause><clause id="H25F5137459BE45B2A29F2A24E98F1FD2"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets any other criteria for high-risk of readmission (as determined by the Secretary).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD2BB15F21B14F37BC345DDEABB68CBF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Registered dietitian or nutrition professional</header><text>The term <term>registered dietitian or nutrition professional</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1861(vv)(2). </text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

