<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5092E3FFCDA742228EB8B55B86B6610F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4362 IH: Saving Organs One Flight at a Time Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4362</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001129">Mr. Collins</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration and the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to jointly issue regulations relating to air carrier transport of human organs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD36B5E171B3547C0BE9AE0E64529C790" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H06777D22BAF54E2C8B1C05B5B62D6037" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Saving Organs One Flight at a Time Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H487542EE2C6B497E86E49595300CB62D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Regulations relating to air carrier transport of human organs</header> <subsection id="H8CF690ED65524684AFAFD3F1319BEF09"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration and the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall jointly take such actions as may be necessary to issue regulations to enable air carriers to efficiently and safely carry organs for transplant above wing. Such regulations shall include the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HB5FF0FB51FCA43D0879A3F39784B19D0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A definition of covered materials that includes organs and containers associated with the transfer of such organs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F78E09929964A1EBADF06F5778C88F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Consideration of protocols for air control outages that impact timeliness of flights transporting organs for transplant.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1A3B333D791442259C0BCAEA703E6A4F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A requirement that air carriers implement a protocol for human person accompaniment of organs to and from the aircraft and between connecting flights.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B3552D429044B959DC6682179FBA03F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A standardized process for commercial air carrier acceptance, handling, and management of organs in transit.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC6FEBDD562FC451A95343C0AC2296DEB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Consistent use of flight notes to indicate organs on board to permit air traffic control to ensure priority takeoff and landing of flights transporting organs for transplant.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAAE812BD92BA4E058B51F9A2E20254EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In promulgating the regulations required under subsection (a), the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administrator and the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall jointly consult with the Organ Procurement and Transplantation Network (OPTN) to identify metrics regarding air carrier handling of organs and organ-related tissue in order to increase transparency and aid the development of best practices and improvement initiatives.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9DE160921BA14C9ABC1F7B8AAF476292"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this Act, the term <quote>organ</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 121.2 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations.</text> </subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

