<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAE6142C4F53748DBA25FB2568C6A8F1A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5667 IH: Pay Our Military Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5667</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Committee on Appropriations</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To ensure continuity of pay and allowances for members of the Armed Forces in the event of a lapse in appropriations.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA55A1560A9E14DECB79C20D3BBBBDF36" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HFAAFA5BE0C3040BEB2A96C78FB23A365" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pay Our Military Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HD92F6839A2964B4F80775FFEAC56E384"><enum>2.</enum><header>Continuing appropriations for pay and allowances for members of the Armed Forces</header> <subsection id="HC3F17344ACE64D5EA8F71C4D3D398481"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are hereby appropriated for fiscal year 2024, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, for any period during which interim or full-year appropriations for fiscal year 2024 are not in effect, such sums as are necessary to provide pay and allowances to—</text> 
<paragraph id="HAD64920CE1BC4B488564A14896C2810B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">members of the Armed Forces, including the reserve components thereof, who perform active service or inactive-duty training during such period;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBCDCF14C4BFF4AC5A48BF71B33BD4FD1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">civilian employees of the Department of Defense (and the Department of Homeland Security in the case of the Coast Guard when the Coast Guard is not operating as a service in the Department of the Navy) whom the Secretary concerned determines are providing support to members of the Armed Forces described in paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFFA45BDA1F9745858E0D5DE8A31F3E71"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">contractors of the Department of Defense (and the Department of Homeland Security in the case of the Coast Guard when the Coast Guard is not operating as a service in the Department of the Navy) whom the Secretary concerned determines are providing support to members of the Armed Forces described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFD36E0466A0B497B811977935AC29515"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>Appropriations and funds made available and authority granted pursuant to this Act shall be available until the first of the following occurs:</text> 
<paragraph id="HEDFA9C12DC804A8E8E926C75F868E426"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The enactment into law of an appropriation (including a continuing appropriation) for any purpose for which amounts are made available in subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE31B225413A4D289E5D98B15EE68C96"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The enactment into law of the applicable regular or continuing appropriations resolution or other Act without any appropriation for such purpose.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H84D9C2469D694E1693CEA70C8C84A454"><enum>(3)</enum><text>January 1, 2025.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H34971F591FC84402BD482AF8A3041C38"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="HEB74D135593C4F808FA31EDE8B412FB5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The terms <quote>active service</quote>, <quote>Armed Forces</quote>, and <quote>inactive-duty training</quote> have the meanings given such terms in section 101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H452171734345430AB34D348F34A44C0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>reserve components</quote> means the components named in section 10101 of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC4C47517A15640C49EBDF1B743F411BF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>Secretary concerned</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="HE019D7664E634E54A9AB30C1C14665F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary of Defense with respect to the Department of Defense; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA88C297DFE744B4DB1C4735785789F69"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Homeland Security with respect to matters concerning the Coast Guard when the Coast Guard is not operating as a service in the Department of the Navy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

