<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HC61CEAA7FE4641FC8FCBD03BE49FD59D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4755 RH: Privacy Enhancing Technology Research Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 170</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4755</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–210]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on July 19, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To support research on privacy enhancing technologies and promote responsible data use, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HSY00" reported-display-style="italic" id="HD8C6450F772F41A7BD2F5B5337418C44"><section section-type="section-one" id="H590F4E51744F4F12A36ECB1B4B270DFA"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Privacy Enhancing Technology Research Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H72AF591B20ED4DF6906136E6A4740DE0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Privacy enhancing technology</header><subsection id="H8F72F33566744F6B8CBE45F5D189F1D2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National Science Foundation support of research on privacy enhancing technology</header><text>The Director of the National Science Foundation, in consultation with the heads of other relevant Federal agencies (as determined by the Director), shall support merit-reviewed and competitively awarded research on privacy enhancing technologies, which may include the following:</text><paragraph id="H381F7A9784944DACBF2F16665DCE62A2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fundamental research on technologies for de-identification, pseudonymization, anonymization, or obfuscation to mitigate individuals’ privacy risks in data sets while maintaining fairness, accuracy, and efficiency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CBCC7DC2E6E43E4B95348FF3C1E4AD0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fundamental research on algorithms and other similar mathematical tools used to protect individual privacy when collecting, storing, sharing, analyzing, or aggregating data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62CF653B9AA44D9F9B314148D5D5CB74"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fundamental research on technologies that promote data minimization in data collection, sharing, and analytics that takes into account the trade-offs between the data minimization goals and the informational goals of data collection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H36C16EDC50634310BB4334EDC5DBCB1E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Research awards on privacy enhancing technologies coordinated with other relevant Federal agencies and programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H374E0216AB3147728365FE30245FBAE5"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Supporting education and workforce training research and development activities, including re-training and upskilling of the existing workforce, to increase the number of privacy enhancing technology researchers and practitioners.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE107DF1829294B0DA10FD9E153B19D13"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Multidisciplinary socio-technical research that fosters broader understanding of privacy preferences, requirements, and human behavior to inform the design and adoption of effective privacy solutions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AB02A0C68944814BF661C2FDE4848AD"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Development of freely available privacy enhancing technology software libraries, platforms, and applications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43EC095D596644A1BF75B34D1A4C1B65"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Fundamental research on techniques that may undermine the protections provided by privacy enhancing technologies, the limitations of such protections, and the trade-offs between privacy and utility required for the deployment of such technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB69602793D5446C8B3C57C3349EEFFC"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Fundamental research on technologies and techniques to preserve the privacy and confidentiality of individuals from unconsented, unwanted, or unauthorized location tracking, including through GPS.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2D4620195D7F445AA14123AFC8D83B3C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Integration into the computer and network security program</header><text>Subparagraph (D) of section 4(a)(1) of the Cyber Security Research and Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/7403">15 U.S.C. 7403(a)(1)(D)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, including privacy enhancing technologies</quote> before the semicolon.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5D3E570BF2EF40ACB4796BF2B1D387C9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination with the National Institute of Standards and Technology and other stakeholders</header><paragraph id="H8DFCA8D7E68841B680B2C3F668608F08"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, acting through the Networking and Information Technology Research and Development Program, shall coordinate with the Director of the National Science Foundation, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Federal Trade Commission, and the heads of other Federal agencies, as appropriate, to accelerate the development, deployment, and adoption of privacy enhancing technologies. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCEF058A7751A40C3B9EC0F21C497F3AE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>The Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology shall conduct outreach to—</text><subparagraph id="HD8D2729C44774ADB831C21BA0EBE3780"><enum>(A)</enum><text>receive input from private, public, and academic stakeholders on the development of privacy enhancing technologies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H93CF26CD00FF497FA3D317F86453390D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> facilitate and support ongoing public and private sector engagement to inform the development and dissemination of voluntary, consensus-based technical standards, guidelines, methodologies, procedures, and processes to cost-effectively increase the integration of privacy enhancing technologies in data collection, sharing, and analytics performed by the public and private sectors.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBD21E8E0C3FD4B13BE59A2943953CC0C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report on privacy enhancing technology research</header><text>Not later than three years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy, acting through the Networking and Information Technology Research and Development Program, shall, in coordination with the Director of the National Science Foundation, the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, and the heads of other Federal agencies, as appropriate, submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, Science, and Related Agencies of the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate, the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, and the Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, Science, and Related Agencies of the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives, a report containing information relating to the following:</text><paragraph id="HB9B369D7D5684D958EC7215823B4B73F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The progress of research on privacy enhancing technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H619C802903AD4C52A212A524C7EFA84D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The progress of the development of voluntary resources described under subsection (c)(2)(B).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11454CFB6F2D4BFAA61839DF7C26D401"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any policy recommendations that could facilitate and improve communication and coordination between the private sector and relevant Federal agencies for the implementation and adoption of privacy enhancing technologies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5C4A293B658E417782EB0944BB4FB75D" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Protecting personal identifying information</header><text>Any personal identifying information collected or stored through the activities authorized under this section shall be done in accordance with part 690 of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations (relating to the protection of human subjects), or any successor regulation.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC9BA6450C63D40C5A43998E9017D5EAC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>privacy enhancing technology</quote>— </text><paragraph id="H8560C8D12E35401DBA7EFD113EA1C074"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means any software or hardware solution, technical process, or other technological means of mitigating individuals’ privacy risks arising from data processing by enhancing predictability, manageability, disassociability, and confidentiality; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AA664F98B9E47828C6B8F73FFC3C90F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may include—</text><subparagraph id="H3590A11710AE416ABA2E5389E75C1E48"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cryptographic techniques for facilitating computation or analysis on data while mitigating privacy risks;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD804E7A4A8684673866BF067198DBBF2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">techniques for—</text><clause id="H2567890CDC85454F982752D8F4669DE7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>publicly sharing data without enabling inferences to be made about specific individuals;</text></clause><clause id="H64E59A25C45E4E66A623DD5EA36AF9C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">giving individuals’ control over the dissemination, sharing, and use of their data; and</text></clause><clause id="H942044D9F2524714A55B401F78234EBE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>generating synthetic data; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4EC707E14F24C6A9C77637936B74099"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other technology or approach that reduces the risk of re-identification, including when combined with other information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

