<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4731A53D0C43423C8897B97A237FFF88" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5666 IH: To establish an Office of Public Engagement within the Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5666</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an Office of Public Engagement within the Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB85AE0A1B0F94C66BFB703F38CCBE4B6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H87E140F84EF74683AD39222CD3AED2DF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Office of Public Engagement</header> 
<subsection id="H1146E39D0CB04CE59800CADECE920342"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration shall establish an office within the Administration known as the Office of Public Engagement (in this section referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>).</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HD40719A43139481B93B1C01D23D0A3C1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of the Office is to proactively engage with pipeline stakeholders, including the public, to promote the adoption and increased use of safety programs and activities, provide technical expertise, raise awareness to continuously improve pipeline safety, and to assist the public with inquiries regarding pipeline safety.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H2D584C1A3A9E444DA41B87DAC7FA1918"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Location</header><text>The Office shall be located in an appropriate location within the Administration as determined by the Administrator.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H88835363134F4F178E63D01F59932561"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The Office shall be administered by a Director. The Director—</text>
<paragraph id="H9DCB4223762048DF90EEAA10A0A5E4AB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall be appointed by the Administrator, or the Administrator’s designee;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H19CF0EABC35149C18156D8E9E76056B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall be responsible for the discharge of the functions and duties of the Office;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCF99CA084117403DA4D879AB5DD69E10"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may assign the duties of employees of the Office;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9DBEE4371DC44753A88A69956292FC8F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall coordinate active and ongoing assistance and engagement with the public with respect to the authorities exercised by the Administration; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD9355E2FDB6B44C3B8689D3CFE757D85"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall ensure such Office initiates programs accessible to the public, including language access and auxiliary aids and services.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6578C836016D4CBBAEAC8F325E2770E2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $12,000,000, for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2027 to establish the Office. </text></subsection> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

