<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H04CAA7C481CC4A92BE8486B44D541343" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5703 IH: Strategic Homeland Investment in Economic and Logistical Defense Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5703</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an Office of Economic and Security Preparedness and Resilience, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H35796B6BC5E84C75AD7A72FDF3C5B995" style="OLC"><section id="HB1237D308C01472A886616554944E235" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strategic Homeland Investment in Economic and Logistical Defense Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SHIELD Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2C52E76B1F4E41F49E0E27C3DB192E4E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Office of Economic and Security Preparedness and Resilience and Supply Chain Mapping Unit</header><subsection id="H7E6927D91EB54B33BE640C9EEB29EC9B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Office of Economic and Security Preparedness and Resilience</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall establish in the executive branch an office, to be known as the <quote>Office of Economic and Security Preparedness and Resilience</quote>, to oversee, coordinate, and set priorities for cross-agency efforts to ensure resilient United States supply chains and robust domestic production in sectors that are vital to the national security of the United States, particularly in the context of growing great-power competition with the People’s Republic of China.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA2A7B2CD1B334CBBADF957779633F4C1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Supply Chain Mapping Unit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office shall establish a dedicated unit, to be known as the <quote>Supply Chain Mapping Unit</quote>, to—</text><paragraph id="HB9689B2B326545859F67FB441244864A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine requirements, set priorities, and coordinate efforts among Federal agencies and industry to continuously map, monitor, and analyze supply chains that are critical to the national security of the United States, including—</text><subparagraph id="H9C63FA08B4AA45E99EA095AE99E82993"><enum>(A)</enum><text>semiconductors;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B46CC879927405FAB10B8E216244CA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>rare-earth elements and critical minerals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAE5877634F340B9B726EFE32F7DE98C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>pharmaceuticals and active pharmaceutical ingredients; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0215EA842351463280AFDF4485A55FE0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>castings and forgings; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5344C35682046638EF0D6D094437DA8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop interoperable performance measures to monitor and assess current United States supply chain resiliency and risk mitigation efforts, including data collection on United States supply chain dependencies on direct and indirect suppliers owned or controlled by or otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the People’s Republic of China or the Chinese Communist Party, with a particular focus on defense-critical and critical infrastructure supply chains.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2537F9AD009441EBA5547C2351F83902"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure defined</header><text>In subsection (b)(2), the term <quote>critical infrastructure</quote> has the meaning given that term in the Critical Infrastructures Protection Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="H73071B014A6D4045B7ECD79629489BDD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Defense Mobilization Unit</header><subsection id="HFAA5BC56A43C4301BC6B5B985A8CD6AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Executive Office of the President a unit, to be known as the <quote>Defense Mobilization Unit</quote>, to be responsible for coordinating and setting priorities for—</text><paragraph id="H13B73F0D522A4E39B9E6BBEEFD935A64"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assessing the requirements for weapons, munitions, supplies, and other equipment necessary to equip, support, and defend United States forces and to assist United States allies and partners in a context of growing great-power competition with the People’s Republic of China;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA0E8392B38A4FD6B02B30116DB184B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>determining the adequacy of existing United States stocks and available productive capacity and existing United States allies’ and partners’ stocks and available productive capacities to meet the needs described in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC482FBFED4034807859AB5344F115999"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying potential shortfalls or bottlenecks that might impede production and resupply to meet the needs described in paragraph (1), to include the impact of partial or complete disruptions in United States-China trade on defense mobilization and domestic availability of critical materials, products, and supplies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1359FF818F2840808D2AB22EDEEB74C1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommending corrective measures to address the corrective measures determined and identified in paragraphs (2) and (3), to include adjustments to funding and support mechanisms as necessary to ensure the achievement of such corrective measures. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H97533BBAE43349858B4A74C25AD2FB0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The President shall consult with the heads of other Federal departments and agencies on a regular basis to—</text><paragraph id="HD21DA8AF6D04446EBA2F96D2FADF5C2E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify shortfalls and bottlenecks in the current defense industrial base; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87E3430612264F5A987833EEB87FDCB2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support industrial capabilities and additional measures needed to address the shortfalls and bottlenecks identified under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB30F101694204355BF311F6D881881F3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><paragraph id="H59AD0BFB703B4DD78E943EA562188380"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that describes the shortfalls and bottlenecks identified under subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD10E7E024BD84718BA7CF1CE62836299"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H2C6CB94D616142FD847844AE5160549A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H39D3E20E483A4FACA837F477A69309A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

