<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H97E551339322497B9F2EA1180A95D818" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2775 IH: Nuclear Weapons Abolition and Conversion Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2775</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the United States to sign the Treaty on the Prohibition of Nuclear Weapons and convert nuclear weapons industry resources and personnel to purposes relating to addressing the climate crisis, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5EF55A211D154F42A2C25327FA8CE04E" style="OLC"><section id="HF623F804FDCB430AA74DE89530315419" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Nuclear Weapons Abolition and Conversion Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HFA9A7ECDBB024AD99C12C0F90E6D5B54"><enum>2.</enum><header>United States abolition of nuclear weapons and conversion of resources to energy and economic purposes</header><subsection id="H3C34B1FDD8C14CC59D5A93D4169B3C29"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States should provide leadership by—</text><paragraph id="H7E541506A6504E0ABB649A291CF0C3F0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>signing the Treaty on the Prohibition of Nuclear Weapons; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H217640DF979C4EC3B83F25E4A6AD515C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ratifying such treaty when it is clear that ratification will result in—</text><subparagraph id="H14CFB82B8E414D86926EA6D585E488B1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the dismantlement and elimination of all nuclear weapons in every country; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H252CA7B480E14B9B9E2D04B0CA89DAB5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>strict and effective international control of such dismantlement and elimination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C34066D8F5E4F48A30676CD68C18C9E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Redirection of resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date on which the President certifies to Congress that all countries possessing nuclear weapons have begun the verifiable and irreversible elimination of such weapons under the Treaty on the Prohibition of Nuclear Weapons, the United States shall redirect resources that are being used for nuclear weapons programs to be used for—</text><paragraph id="HABA613F058DE418FB13F50E29C6FB22E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>purposes related to addressing the climate crisis, including through the development and deployment of clean, renewable energy sources, by converting all nuclear weapons industry processes, plants, and programs for such purposes and by retraining nuclear industry employees;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6154DA1657545E0A51911CACB98A1A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>addressing human and infrastructure needs, such as health care, housing, education, agriculture, and environmental restoration, including long-term radioactive waste monitoring; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09198B3524234825B8843F956E8C82D9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>actively promote policies to induce all other countries to join in the commitments referred to in paragraphs (1) and (2) to create a more peaceful and secure world.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

