<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBB9FB691AB9F4C1E878E8797B65D694C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4533 IH: Cost of Wokeism in the Military Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4533</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230711">July 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Defense to assess, and submit a report to Congress on, civilian staffing at the Department of Defense Office for Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD227EA52056146378127D880205253B4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HDBC7EBC987124E779120D990CA36B05C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Cost of Wokeism in the Military Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H80567A35B8F248DCBB7468ED95BCD013"><enum>2.</enum><header>Assessments of staffing in DOD Office for Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion</header> <subsection id="HCD153D0600D040299B42FBEE212D9BAA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="HCF19135DC5834E1CBC01901A03C9164E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Secretary assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall conduct an assessment validating each civil service position in the Office for Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion against existing personnel of the Office. For purposes of carrying out such assessment, the head of the Office shall submit to the Secretary the alignment of total force manpower resources of the Office against core missions, tasks, and functions, including a mapping of missions to the originating statute or Department policy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EB0F7A32BCA487C911291294C2A10AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Office assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of the Office shall conduct an assessment on the tasks, functions, and associated civilian personnel the Office believes are necessary to perform the duties of the Office.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF984300C813941C5AEDAB07DBBC6CF11"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary analysis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall determine whether there is any conflict between the assessment conducted under paragraph (1) and the assessment under paragraph (2), and what personnel actions (if any) the Secretary will take to eliminate such conflict.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDE4083EF99C54D01BFFF7AE3BF6FB5AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Interim briefing and report</header> 
<paragraph id="H6CCE79C624D6498E96287D2ECD63CC4C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Interim briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than April 1, 2024, the Secretary shall provide to the congressional defense committees an interim briefing on the assessments under subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H51EF4ED478B54566BCA2D7289609C324" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report on the assessments under subsection (a). Such report shall include the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HC8E0D3A16F4F41C1924F1B4CE4C51E89" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A validation of every civil service position in the Office against existing civilian personnel requirements.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA16116CC874F407E997881DF2779AEB6" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The methodology and process through which such validation was performed.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7D1F9F27727E4D9B9806C4F3A0509FE7" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Relevant statistical analysis on civil service position fill rates against validated requirements.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB55DAA4603F3467B8A37C8828EB15CBA" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Analysis of each civil service position and grade and whether the position description and grade match the function and task requirements of the position.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3891697F0D084C6E929F7CC851EEAB4E" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Plan to update grades and position descriptions to meet current and future requirements, tasks, and functions.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8DF7D7FA53A44AA99126FE12F20EEF5E" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Lessons learned through the civilian position validation process and statistical analysis under subparagraphs (B) through (F).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC42BF548A9D440299199A20A838E310C" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Any legislative, policy or budgetary recommendations of the Secretary related to the subject matter of the report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H527E30CCA54C4AFBB5642C543FEBC3D6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>If the final report is not submitted to Congress under paragraph (2) within one year after the date of enactment of this Act, until the date that such report is so submitted—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H12CAFE0E79194EF19D378108AB4B5FDC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no new civil service position may be established at the Office;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE783233B95EB4006AAEAA53EBAA61FEB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">members of the uniformed services may not be detailed or otherwise used to carry out any function or duty of the Office; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF59610D3A6D6406E8B06DE16BB69D674" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no additional personal services contractors may be appointed to a position at the Office.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H95CA8A80C4C34649B1389F1547D94F8A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Budget requirement</header><text>The Secretary shall, in the Secretary’s annual budget submission to the Office of Management and Budget for fiscal year 2025 and each fiscal year thereafter, identify mission changes, opportunities for automation, and business process improvements that could better optimize the size, structure, composition of the Department of Defense’s workforce and its allocation against validated requirements.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2ACF791BAD1943E182CB09F0D6434564"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="H475395DF50AB476F9C0C7A6076080CAC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>civil service</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2101 of title 5, United States Code;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE7FE7B5CB86344E7A384CB42929BE332"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> the term <term>congressional defense committees</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101(a)(16) of title 10, United States Code; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9148B9E8DB7D46FBAD25AB46C2C13F90"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>Office</term> means the Office for Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in the Department of Defense; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7EFEFA00A26B4DB9BA5D087697C9D715"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Defense. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

