<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDA95D54030614D319B6CC180128D0494" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 471 IH: Safer Highways and Increased Performance for Interstate Trucking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 471</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 23, United States Code, with respect to commercial motor vehicle parking, safety, and licensing, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H49C779AA9BAB47BCB49E86CACA05B5C1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4D3DD23DDC0046FC9A65CB98608A210F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safer Highways and Increased Performance for Interstate Trucking Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SHIP IT Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H845B00109D9A45A0AEB8E0922C76521E" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modernizing authority for certain vehicle waivers during emergencies</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 127(i) of title 23, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HF51FAA80DC5D4BD0ACB08FB77246A5C1" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H3CBF857A8B994427ADD45225F5B77CD2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Special Permits During Periods of National Emergency</header> 
<paragraph id="HC6396432969E47D0BB94A5F51F78D55E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of this section, a State may issue special permits during an emergency to overweight vehicles and loads that can easily be dismantled or divided if the conditions of either paragraph (2) or paragraph (3) are met.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H699E2B1C6A6D4AFD898C6AD894A1F9A5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Presidential declaration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The conditions of paragraph (2) as referenced in paragraph (1) of this subsection are—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBAA3410D879B47C685C1DF54812A6C01"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the President has declared the emergency to be a major disaster under the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5121">42 U.S.C. 5121 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBD6C4062BEDD447EB71FE612298CFEE5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the permits described in paragraph (1) are issued in accordance with State law;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2E157F61F00441F8BFF3278F02519F86"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the permits are issued exclusively to vehicles and loads that are delivering relief supplies; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2B8C3E41501A490298C23C61A0087283"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a permit shall expire not later than 120 days after the date of the declaration of emergency under subparagraph (A) of this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0E628D2925A44EF0B53A4477B0B969A7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretarial declaration</header><text>The conditions of paragraph (3) are the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HAA56C9C1610C497583781E7412D98F24"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary has declared that—</text> 
<clause id="HF5CB031E31024041BDBA35C4B2C65505"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">emergency or other unusual conditions, including weather, fire, earthquake, disease, or natural emergencies and including financial or other non-natural emergencies, are having a negative impact on commerce in a State or regionally or nationally; or</text></clause> <clause id="H0821AD5D414E4C50AA7C24D6D15493EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supply chains in United States commerce are functioning in a suboptimal manner in a State or regionally or nationally, either in terms of slow overall movement, freight traffic congestion, or otherwise. </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H796A5E3DBF99495280B495F6B16C80B1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The permits described in paragraph (1) are issued in accordance with State law.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1DAFACD73D2A47A59FF441DBAEDC6B26"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The permit shall expire—</text> 
<clause id="H1C3650407C4F4E3EA5AD53B38D4704E6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>365 days after the Secretary makes a declaration pursuant to subparagraph (A), unless the expiration date is extended by the Secretary; or</text></clause> <clause id="H5F61D5E4647140CEB55FCFEB107BFFD1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">180 days after the Secretary declares that the emergency or other condition declared by the Secretary pursuant to subparagraph (A) has expired, whichever is later.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H85C4D937B0304AA4A6107509D12F749E"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In administering this paragraph, the Secretary shall give weight to requests by a State to make or extend subparagraph (A) declarations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H7725E3BD591A4EEF807AD211E38A0D6F" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Eligibility for workforce grants</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 134 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9F73548A573547D3A8752E98613F1220" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H3867BC797D384539AFEF5F1AAD07E2BA" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Truck drivers</header> 
<paragraph id="H8C0BA2E1B76C48FEB5039E0536F8F799" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to the commercial motor vehicle operator profession, the Secretary shall provide grants to individuals for the tuition and fees and other costs of entry level driver training provided by an entity listed as a training provider on the registry maintained by the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration and for such other education and training costs as the Secretary may approve, including the cost of course materials, supplies, technology, and fees for graduation, licensure, or certification.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBD5A40144B7849A28A3D3307ED2F3672"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Simplified process</header><text>As soon as practicable after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall develop a simplified process through which grants may be provided under this subsection that would be readily accessible to individuals with non-Federal share requirements set at the lowest level allowed under other provisions of this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H580D132662F9457C94FF5EC7D8FFB39F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Expenses authorized under paragraph (1) shall be provided both through the structure of existing programs pursuant to subsections (a) through (d) of this section and through the process developed by the Secretary under subsection (e). </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H26C39C4264A247D7AB85C10C4F4940DF"><enum>4.</enum><header>Strengthening supply chains through truck driver incentives Act</header> <subsection id="H32ECEF50BED1436CB37AE327886FDB05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after section 36B the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF113DB5DEB7849548E2E56F74135E79D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H1D84156D06524B299AAA26AC78B22161"><enum>36C.</enum><header>Credit for commercial truck drivers</header> 
<subsection id="H83E410B4633B41AFAF6900FCD4B73149"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Allowance of credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an eligible individual, there shall be allowed as a credit against the tax imposed by this subtitle an amount equal to $7,500 for the taxable year.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2B22E29B49204F998D00A4B720CD5FAB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of this section, the term <quote>eligible taxpayer</quote> means, with respect to a taxable year, an individual—</text> 
<paragraph id="H150BEA64507848DBA5158166EC880298"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who holds a valid Class A commercial driver’s license (except as provided in subsection (c)) who operates a tractor-trailer combination that qualifies as a Group A vehicle under section 383.91(a)(1) of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations,</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H542818FFA326458590367C9E1FAB408D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whose adjusted gross income for the taxable year does not exceed—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3299BE7ABC094CC0BA70FFAC29A1BC89"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a joint return or surviving spouse, $135,000,</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC144592D2B7645719169C4AEBAE1B5AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an individual who is a head of household, $112,500, or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H59E775D1B3F741BE87B10BB064310071"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any other individual, $90,000, and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H08B6B684A5F74052ABC7C5C678531A78"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who drove such a vehicle in the course of a trade or business—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H9CE00C6979874248A6D9A2AF369DEF9F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">and served not less than 1900 hours of on-duty time, including driving time, during such taxable year, or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H54568098AC544E3297415481746721DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an individual who did not drive a commercial truck in the preceding taxable year, not less than an average of 40 hours per week of on-duty time, including driving time, with respect to weeks during the taxable year in which such individual drove such a vehicle in the course of a trade or business.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H40FDD6FD5FB54ED0B1F7C1851AADBABD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Special rule for apprentices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to an individual enrolled in an apprenticeship program registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the ‘National Apprenticeship Act’), who, upon completion or in the course of such apprenticeship program will receive a Class A commercial driver’s license—</text> <paragraph id="H10F49E25E5B14888A877BEB3F6A697F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the requirements of subsection (b)(1) shall not apply, and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H377163C22BCB42EEBADE58473E88982B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such individual may count training hours in such program as hours driving a vehicle described in subsection (b)(1) for the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H75EC2AB5C7984BDAA011B237065BC655" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Special rule for new truck drivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (e), in the case of an eligible taxpayer who did not drive a commercial truck in the course of a trade or business during the preceding taxable year, subsection (a) shall be applied by substituting <quote>$10,000</quote> for <quote>$7,500</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC7ABC6423FDA4172BD889764FBD392A8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Special rule for drivers with less than 1420 hours</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of an eligible taxpayer who did not drive a commercial truck in the preceding taxable year who drives a commercial truck and served for less than 1420 hours of on-duty time, including driving time, in the course of a trade or business during the taxable year, the amount of the credit allowed by subsection (a) shall be the amount that bears the same proportion to the dollar amount (determined without regard to this subsection) with respect to the individual under subsection (a) as the number of hours of on-duty time, including driving time, such individual drove a commercial truck in the course of a trade or business during such taxable year bears to 1420 hours.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC0421C3839F445C29890487900EBFD7D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any taxable year beginning after 2022, the dollar amounts in this section shall be increased by an amount equal to—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA052BEC98EC0435EAADFADAFD4234B35"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such dollar amount, multiplied by </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCF394E52E46849F5821480F05DAE20BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year in which the taxable year begins, determined by substituting ‘calendar year 2021’ for ‘calendar year 2016’ in subparagraph (A)(ii).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEA32BD0999A84721BE34A274BC1C2545" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An eligible individual shall be allowed the credit under this section only 2 times. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H860DAFCCA6BB425F97A211A5441DA913" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the terms “on-duty time” and “driving time” shall have the meaning given such terms in section 395.2 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFE20DDECBC3844CEA07EFDDFF7FAE1DC" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="H0DA8E60F70954EACA00BDA18CB875B97" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6211">Section 6211(b)(4)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting <quote>, 36C</quote> after <quote>36B</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A2E4FED955E414C8373CB3671D1C72C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Refund of internal revenue collections</header><text>Section 1324(b)(2) of title 31, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, 36C</quote> after <quote>, 36B</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA0C934EBBFFC4E4D90B2BA026F03C960" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for subpart C of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 36B the following new item: <quote>Sec. 36C. Credit for commercial truck drivers.</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8A6244502DF44620AE1532CA6027421D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to taxable years ending on or after December 31, 2022.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD7AF8E2724C94EE6AC9055C6D9A5D16B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Parking for commercial motor vehicles</header> 
<subsection id="HAB56311B9BB1434694CAA20EF608330C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that it should be a national priority to address the shortage of parking for commercial motor vehicles on the Federal-aid highway system to improve highway safety.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF0BB7434756248E7A1FD3AF83A22797E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/23/1">Chapter 1</external-xref> of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HE2BEB55C627648B4A40B453468340CAB" style="USC"> 
<section id="H9E962D3E3E4F45A987A537A286F53795"><enum>180.</enum><header>Parking for commercial motor vehicles</header> 
<subsection id="H1B34C5366A964DFA973CD120C69B2AA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant authority</header><text>Subject to the availability of funds, the Secretary shall make grants under this section, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities for projects to provide parking for commercial motor vehicles and improve the safety of commercial motor vehicle operators.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H795F15C76A374B45A14B1DB239303851"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall submit to the Secretary an application at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0B6B3A00829F42BD895AC72D17FED3F2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application contents</header><text>An application submitted under subsection (b) shall contain—</text> <paragraph id="H3B84E1E81463480395452875A02ABA8A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of the proposed project; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H74CE151382D24B778317712DC4A07EB2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any other information that the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFF039A962D794754B4D73A94B8DE5055"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>The following entities shall be eligible to receive amounts under this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD43D6B17C2D74EC6A17EEC735728EB0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A State.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H094FAB8E50F444C185D3BAD72A3D6546"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A metropolitan planning organization.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H74EC8A49563C440C8A050F7594293303"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A unit of local government.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H30BDB32F6E3449C19B148ED8D8F59507"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A political subdivision of a State or local government carrying out responsibilities relating to commercial motor vehicle parking.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEA0954FF754F4C49AE2F4552D669E6A0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A Tribal government or a consortium of Tribal governments.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9917B99B72F14241BA5F66FDC71AF1F0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A multistate or multijurisdictional group of entities described in paragraphs (1) through (5).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H36F9DE428AE84BE3B8241F2D276DD51F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Private sector participation</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section may partner with a private entity to carry out an eligible project under this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H95B5F2EB24C54671BA794579F1252676"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header> <paragraph id="H81D35C17FC614913BD075E025DBE8803"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity may use a grant awarded under this section for a project described in paragraph (2) that is on—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H3087940D026A416FA4D796C61F032D44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a Federal-aid highway; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H431EFDC6AA354127BEE20666B80F434E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a facility with reasonable access to—</text> 
<clause id="H8E18F6D6C59544409C9D5DF34B0D57F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a Federal-aid highway; or</text></clause> <clause id="H118D413F209E49B8A3AE758BA5FFB83E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a freight facility.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA8B3A33B132442529EC4F3ACBC9891F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Projects described</header><text>A project described in this paragraph is a project to—</text> <subparagraph id="HFE93036D8610408496D7855DD9CB56E4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>construct safety rest areas (as such term is defined in section 120(c)) that include parking for commercial motor vehicles;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H30ABF4D460BA4C9997EE0733AD859DC4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>construct additional commercial motor vehicle parking capacity—</text> <clause id="HB11EA4AF79AD4D538B0D9E483E6041D5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>adjacent to private commercial truck stops and travel plazas;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9878338F8F8F4DE7B02C7F56CBC8FBEA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>within the boundaries of, or adjacent to, a publicly owned freight facility, including a port terminal operated by a public authority; and</text></clause> <clause id="H9DB908D379804E39B608CDC7BFB64701"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>at existing facilities, including inspection and weigh stations and park-and-ride locations;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2FF823EA80A24EC3A29CEAEC89844D20"><enum>(C)</enum><text>open existing weigh stations, safety rest areas, and park-and-ride facilities to commercial motor vehicle parking;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H37AD2B7E87014EBC8F3E3C4F9E09B2C7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>construct or make capital improvements to existing public commercial motor vehicle parking facilities to expand parking utilization and availability, including at seasonal facilities;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAD4B8F797F5D4D17A194FB1D43402C33"><enum>(E)</enum><text>identify, promote, and manage the availability of publicly and privately provided commercial motor vehicle parking, such as through the use of intelligent transportation systems;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H312100E7E8224C7B83189C37A1CD758E"><enum>(F)</enum><text>improve the safety of commercial motor vehicle operators at parking facilities as part of a project described in subparagraphs (A) through (D); or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC05967FBE7944F10BED5C9A0BD9416A4"><enum>(G)</enum><text>improve a parking facility, including through advanced truck stop electrification systems and other improvements determined appropriate by the Secretary, as part of a project described in subparagraphs (A) through (D).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE39B5909428342E2A674755CA35E0592"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publicly accessible parking</header><text>Commercial motor vehicle parking constructed or opened with a grant under this section shall be open and accessible to all commercial motor vehicle operators.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H62B504F39C1A4F12BDC54C5FB02DC5AA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Use of funds</header> 
<paragraph id="HD3076E9CEFA240FAB8A848980B77B848"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity may use a grant under this section for—</text> <subparagraph id="HA70CCFCBF20A41B79D102C2F0FFF858A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>development phase activities, including planning, feasibility analysis, benefit-cost analysis, environmental review, preliminary engineering and design work, and other preconstruction activities necessary to advance a project under this section; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8F32C0D178C74EFD8506DA587240050C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>construction and operational improvements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2E4364C4CF9A4122842890B6F76C590A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header> <subparagraph id="HA6D99688E0454F238EE951CF1463AE5F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible entity may use not more than 25 percent of the amount of a grant under this section for activities described in paragraph (1)(A).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H783E9C1AFC7E4F599360453513BF300C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Existing facilities</header><text>Not more than 10 percent of the amounts available for each fiscal year for grants under the program may be used for projects described under subsection (f)(2)(E) that solely identify, promote, and manage the availability of existing commercial motor vehicle parking.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H86E705B3A2284D3B82954089937C0FE5"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text>In making grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall give priority to applications that demonstrate—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5E18D6012C184B8798B8C5319AB2978F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a shortage of commercial motor vehicle parking capacity in the corridor in which the project is located;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H749973768DC34B26ACC7E109B9BF689A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consultation with motor carriers, commercial motor vehicle operators, public safety officials, and private providers of commercial motor vehicle parking;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC8F8E3911BF45C7A3DD3D0DFBA6B0F0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that the project will likely—</text> <subparagraph id="H9562B1A48A774F33B1FD5DF0B18FC048"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increase the availability or utilization of commercial motor vehicle parking;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD8FCE008EE31446FB651963B36053FF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>facilitate the efficient movement of freight; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5CBE15B24CC64DE0956BC34004440DAD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>improve highway safety, traffic congestion, and air quality; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H79AC671C23834E07B0D940828B76F568"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the ability to provide for the maintenance and operation of the facility.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF69071016D5D4556A2638F735C8D231E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>Notwithstanding section 120, the Federal share for a project carried out under this subsection shall be up to 100 percent.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H81D4157030D044DD979E967743138876"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Treatment of projects</header> 
<paragraph id="HDB609C4889AC442B98A550038480E743"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, projects funded under this section shall be treated as projects on a Federal-aid highway under this chapter.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF908255E1FE341F48AA1398B7A3C0384"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Period of availability</header><text>Funds appropriated for projects under this section shall remain available for a period of 3 years after the last day of the fiscal year in which the funds are made available.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H59BE0E7C81FA4A5582A69439C93710FA"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Prohibition on charging fees</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under this section, an eligible entity shall agree that no fees will be charged to a commercial motor vehicle to access parking constructed, opened, or improved with a grant under this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H56F9B358CB6A47B593877ADBB56B75DF"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Notification of congress</header><text>Not less than 3 business days before making a grant for a project under this section, the Secretary shall notify, in writing, the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on the Environment and Public Works of the Senate of the intention to award such a grant.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H20C6C573A72C498280DBA8C1BE0EF88D"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Survey and comparative assessment</header> 
<paragraph id="HE391C1B41B7844A3816611BD104317CE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this subsection, and every 2 years thereafter, the Secretary, in consultation with appropriate State motor carrier safety personnel, motor carriers, State departments of transportation, and private providers of commercial motor vehicle parking shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on the Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report that—</text> <subparagraph id="H7283191D8B92454690074E8A7823D206"><enum>(A)</enum><text>evaluates the availability of adequate parking and rest facilities, taking into account both private and public facilities, for commercial motor vehicles engaged in interstate transportation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5F69FCB1EF19479296A6DC1F92D7A054"><enum>(B)</enum><text>evaluates the effectiveness of the projects funded under this section in improving access to commercial motor vehicle parking;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCB8E8F39E1AB4F8B8942690E9AD5818F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evaluates the ability of entities receiving a grant under this section to sustain the operation of parking facilities constructed with funds provided under this section; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3A61B375AA664D3BAF7E2471EB161E9E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>reports on the progress being made to provide adequate commercial motor vehicle parking facilities in the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAB78B0434C3F4EC0B7EF1CB25919CEB8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Results</header><text>The Secretary shall make the report and subsequent updated reports under paragraph (1) available to the public on the website of the Department of Transportation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6CD4B57ACBF14D6DB83C07FFDA3C28DC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Alignment of reports</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Secretary shall consider the results of the commercial motor vehicle parking facilities assessments of the States under section 70202 of title 49 and seek to align the contents of the report and reporting deadlines under paragraph (1) with the requirements of such section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF3B51A8D704B4592B0290114870B9927"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Commercial motor vehicle defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>commercial motor vehicle</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 31132 of title 49.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H39F1EF67C040459A9037F49669DAA6B3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/23/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding after the item relating to section 177 the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H9BF4C281E45E459C89DA0D47DD1C9D3C" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">180. Parking for commercial motor vehicles. </toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H91D35832238444B2AF83A8357F7D0831"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of Appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated out of the general fund of the Treasury for projects for commercial vehicle parking under section 177 of title 23, United States Code (as added by this Act)—</text> 
<paragraph id="HEBBDDF8ABDFE42CD81B93EF0CBD3887B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$175,000,000 for fiscal year 2023;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H44B255E3258340DE98C77CDE8944A64B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$185,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H35DF359FDD1A476DA1948ED861D2EB1E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$195,000,000 for fiscal year 2025; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC00FBC795E334843B93D8F47BF6BE3ED"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$200,000,000 for fiscal year 2026.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HAE3EA3A6372D4660A21E637272AF42B8" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Licensing Individual Commercial Exam-takers Now Safely and Efficiently Act</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation, acting through the Administrator of the Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration, shall—</text> <paragraph id="HB222913DA3014749951FCF6B71F70497" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">revise section 384.228 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation), to allow a State or third-party examiner to administer a commercial driver’s license knowledge test so long as the examiner—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCAD766AF193043E4A389A834207DA3EA" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>maintains a valid commercial driver’s license test examiner certification; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAEED7BDA774B4255AE8BC53FCC579DD8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>completes a commercial driver’s license skills test examiner training course that meets the requirements of subsection (d) of such section; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3B1029321FC943FD9398B5556C37B2F2" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>completes 1 unit of instruction described in subsection (c)(3) of such section; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3293FBAA2682452ABC9A17D24721F143" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>revise section 383.25(a)(1) of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation), to allow a commercial driver’s license holder accompanying a commercial learner’s permit holder to be present anywhere in the cab of the vehicle being operated by the commercial learner’s permit holder; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4AE5F65D5CAD405AA8357653DE1C1738" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>revise section 383.79 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation), to allow a State to administer a driving skills test to any commercial driver’s license applicant, regardless of the State of domicile of the applicant or where the applicant received driver training.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H4E5CB87096EC45898224BACD80AE7C62" commented="no"><enum>7.</enum><header>Exemption for zero emission class 7 vehicles</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 31301(4) of title 49, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, except that, for vehicles powered primarily by means of electric battery power, the weight of the electric battery or batteries shall not count towards the gross vehicle weight rating and gross vehicle weight stated in this subparagraph, or towards any lesser gross vehicle weight rating or gross vehicle weight that may be prescribed by the Secretary by regulation</quote> after <quote>10,001 pounds</quote>. </text></section> 
<section id="H20CC6FA2142A4F62BC8515F3112D380A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>8.</enum><header>Safety data collection program for certain 6-axle vehicles</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 127 of title 23, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="HBE192699C14D4FD89FCF21CF8B32D16F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subsection id="H49A80430FE4B467B80B6E4C6E24ECB84"><enum>(x)</enum><header>Pilot program for safety data collection on certain 6-Axle vehicles</header> <paragraph id="H8B8487266CF54E0FAE4FF107EC4E6516"><enum>(1)</enum><header>General authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall establish a pilot program (referred to in this subsection as the ‘pilot program’) under which States selected by the Secretary under paragraph (2) may allow covered 6-axle vehicles to be operated on the Interstate System in the State.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9503DFA189994831AA7B81522F321EB7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of States for the program</header> 
<subparagraph id="H13B453EE35DD49148E5DFFDB3868AB31"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 30 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, a State seeking to participate in the pilot program shall submit an application to the Secretary in electronic form, containing such administrative information as the Secretary may require, including a certification that the State will have the authority pursuant to State law to implement the pilot program.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF4296340C1B74DEF94680BA1048750AB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall select for the pilot program, on a rolling basis, States that submit a completed application under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBCBEA0E903974E0193976A666B1954B5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Election to no longer participate</header><text>If a State elects to no longer participate in the pilot program, the State shall notify the Secretary of such election.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7DE7B96FF8F40F789FD0FB6EF4EDB2E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Means of implementation</header> <subparagraph id="H5B103DF7575147DAA4FE8762D7B491D9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to participate in the pilot program, a State shall agree to implement the pilot program through the issuance of permits per vehicle or group of vehicles with respect to covered 6-axle vehicles.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAC155ED7B8594121B695A4371FC8B2A8"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Permit</header><text>A permit described in subparagraph (A) shall—</text> <clause id="H7FEEBDF05D524E05B0FF4DEEAD819DDD"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describe the Interstate System routes that may be used while operating at greater than 80,000 pounds gross vehicle weight in a covered 6-axle vehicle; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDC21A82D9DE3400085E9E9B09A09C3E1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require the permit holder to report to the State, with respect to such permit holder—</text> <subclause id="H97AE03FEE45D417691B2C2718FB890B7"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each accident (as such term is defined in section 390.5 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection) that occurred in the State involving a covered 6-axle vehicle on the Interstate System in the State;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HEE0101F3D5AE4A17B90A06B11E3B094C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the estimated gross vehicle weight of each covered 6-axle vehicle at the time of an accident described in subclause (I); and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H87B28C4700814FEFABBEBDFCCDFDA251"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the estimated miles traveled by covered 6-axle vehicles on the Interstate System annually.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD9C66B9DB0C047BE9E491049690C1FBE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Safety equipment incentive</header> 
<clause id="H0A7D31CF2CED4AC7BEE5E5E76ED4A87C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Fee reduction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any fee associated with a permit under this paragraph, the State shall reduce the fee otherwise applicable to a vehicle by 67 percent if the vehicle is equipped with an automatic emergency braking system, including such systems in use on the date of enactment of this subsection. </text></clause> <clause id="HC31D219E9FD04C8FA446013EB65E11D1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Group of vehicles</header><text>As applied to a permit for a group of vehicles, the reduction under clause (i) shall only apply with respect to individual vehicles in the group that are equipped with an automatic emergency breaking system, including such systems in use on the date of enactment of this subsection. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H11187CFD67704326B771FCF53DFE4E61"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Other authorizations not affected</header><text>This subsection shall not restrict—</text> <subparagraph id="H547D985974724FFDA008174694411354"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a vehicle that may operate under any other provision of this section or another Federal law; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H26F3843253394560BF3EFD4709C25DEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a State’s authority with respect to a vehicle that may operate under any other provision of this section or another Federal law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3570AFAC3EC6449EBECCF402C72257B3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No highway funding reduction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding subsection (a), funds apportioned to a State under section 104 for any period may not be reduced because the State authorizes the operation of covered 6-axle vehicles within such State in accordance with this subsection.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5FEA3A70341646DB9E8D91671E662933"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the first March 1 after the date of enactment of this subsection, and annually thereafter, a State participating in the pilot program shall submit to the Secretary with respect to the previous calendar year, a report on—</text> <subparagraph id="H06E8323E04414A27964D5D3544C052F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of accidents (as such term is defined in section 390.5 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this subsection)) that occurred in the State involving covered 6-axle vehicles on the Interstate System in the State;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4A5A62F5D8934E24A145D0929CEAA7F5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the estimated gross vehicle weight of each such vehicle at the time of the accident in the State described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0C0495DC91EE4E1ABE8A6C22934B3297"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the estimated miles traveled by such vehicle on the Interstate System in the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCEFAEBD2EEB14D6F8787C4D994C315C7"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Termination of pilot program</header> 
<subparagraph id="H89FE0CD5CD0043C7813C33EAD1D09302"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the pilot program shall terminate on the date that is 10 years after the date of enactment of this subsection.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H72E6669D6789468999DB16A33CA45D01"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional application; continuation of authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For a period of 10 years beginning on the date described in subparagraph (A), the Secretary may continue the pilot program with respect to each State in the program, upon the application of a State and after consideration of—</text> 
<clause id="H0450B750C1EC4FFCB8A14FD6B0878F93"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the actual experience of the State under the pilot program; and</text></clause> <clause id="HBCA12BEB5F58404DA71A14AA3B30A3A6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any documents or other material submitted by the State in support of such an application.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB62C37574D7C4A3E85CF57D755A05D0D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Covered 6-axle vehicle defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <quote>covered 6-axle vehicle</quote> means a vehicle—</text> <subparagraph id="H4EE68FBC1B7F4D1988957057C08CEEA2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>equipped with 6 or more axles;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1F0E0EC4889D4D9EBEEAE1BC8D38686C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which the weight—</text> <clause id="HB286473F9C4B440283BA4208C4C6396E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on any single axle of the vehicle does not exceed 20,000 pounds, including enforcement tolerances;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HAD5384CEE52241E2897C43AD8C6E417E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on any tandem axle of the vehicle does not exceed 34,000 pounds, including enforcement tolerances; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA04A1EB7A84F4C1B940A6ED2413F30CB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on any group of three or more axles of the vehicle does not exceed 45,000 pounds, including enforcement tolerances;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H975F9F2CF24243268E7979139975433F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for which the gross weight does not exceed the lesser of—</text> <clause id="H289A5974E675410C9DA668A432523E08"><enum>(i)</enum><text>91,000 pounds, including enforcement tolerances; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H29156031E2E14B21B8BD8DDC59CEF43A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the maximum permitted by the bridge formula under subsection (a); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA08A8264E74B46079D9A0B3B4649927B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>that is not a longer combination vehicle, as such term is defined in subsection (d)(4). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="H0B056781D5BA40CA9C8339507F16DF83"><enum>9.</enum><header>Haulers of Agriculture and Livestock Safety Act</header> 
<subsection id="H5E58D909BFB74A05A26EE16CD52734D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Transportation of agricultural commodities and farm supplies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 229 of the Motor Carrier Safety Improvement Act of 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/31136">49 U.S.C. 31136</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/159">Public Law 106–159</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H1DA5D37843E94C44BDC173143B38A83B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB3AE7F5532EE405381C3887C21261F52"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) by striking <quote>during planting and harvest periods, as determined by each State,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE0BBF61DB0204D7C93A5D8237C1DC573"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (A) and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H6856771E0CFE491E9C582434111AE2B5" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="HB97E5D685BC144FD88F04E5F40E7EDEB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>drivers transporting agricultural commodities within a 150 air-mile radius from—</text> <clause id="H2C9824CB19E84CA781DE16D5F59271D5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the source of the agricultural commodities; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB940B4275B6D4A3689B36808FABB791D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the destination of the agricultural commodities;</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3653DEB614AB4DD7B7C45BB46D28A72A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(8) by striking <quote>during the planting and harvesting seasons within each State, as determined by the State, and livestock feed at any time of the year</quote> and inserting <quote>and livestock feed</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA682B80ABCCB4F678F9C835A157F3639"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition of agricultural commodity</header> 
<paragraph id="H938004EA9CD04F0E9F91E554FEF58EED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 229(e) of the Motor Carrier Safety Improvement Act of 1999 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/31136">49 U.S.C. 31136</external-xref> note; <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/106/159">Public Law 106–159</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (7) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H33AE98A544854372A6352065418CE316" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H74F6B192F84443BA9C7C9591D7EFD864"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Agricultural commodity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>agricultural commodity</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 395.2 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H195BC5A6CFB4480889A8F305C515C8C1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Transportation shall revise the definition of the term <quote>agricultural commodity</quote> in section 395.2 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations, to include—</text> <subparagraph id="H693CD1D40DE14A2F817E74EF15CBABF7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any nonprocessed product planted or harvested for food, feed, fuel, or fiber;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEA5911C0639F4B26907099D397500C34"><enum>(B)</enum> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HA494EB38E835418C9A871A75456CFA63"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any nonhuman living animal, including—</text> <subclause id="H60A6ED6F9C8F4C908B59FAA9DFB62E68" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>fish;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HD2992D7F2B8440CC97E883818B93ABA2" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>insects; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HA422420596D740198EF47FC152FB3A92" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>livestock (as such term is defined in section 602 of the Emergency Livestock Feed Assistance Act of 1988 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1471">7 U.S.C. 1471</external-xref>); and</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H8F7D7C663D534B0AA5292888429EE6F7" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the nonprocessed products of any nonhuman living animal, including—</text> <subclause id="H9774CA7F92E94E74B3E6AA7EC59F0C9E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>milk;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8FF4800DF64A4B54B1A4D66B5B1C9384"><enum>(II)</enum><text>eggs; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H433108F5C4B44FC1A1D4D661BF2A6CFB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>honey; </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9164ADBEDEF741A7B7847A976ED22037"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">nonprocessed forestry, aquacultural, horticultural, and floricultural commodities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H15A5DFC4CD84495F8C02EBA3655982B3"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fresh or minimally processed fruits and vegetables, including fruits and vegetables that are rinsed, cooled, cut, ripened, or otherwise minimally processed, as determined by the Secretary; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA03D95C556444A7983FF7ABDFE1AEA79"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">animal feed, including the ingredients of animal feed; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEE24BF791C0048079A540B6629BAF25E"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any additional agricultural or forest product, whether unprocessed or processed, including paper and packaging products and food and beverage products. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


