<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H59CF3BBA8ECD4EA0BAB67279535BC1E3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>103 HR 2604 IH: Family Violence Prevention and Services Improvement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2604</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Family Violence Prevention and Services Act to make improvements.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H72614B0F864B4AE290046E2BB1F73F13" style="OLC"><section id="HCFBC36481C33461794D78B386EAFFA3B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; references; severability</header><subsection id="HD93D75260AF14116A2CBBB4EC807AAAA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Family Violence Prevention and Services Improvement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF4DC271032894A5AA9799A85B3BB35E0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>References</header><text>Except as otherwise specified, amendments made by this Act to a section or other provision of law are amendments to such section or other provision of the Family Violence Prevention and Services Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10401">42 U.S.C. 10401 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H3ECF61196DC9422FBBA9B1317AAFF8FA" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, an amendment made by this Act, or the application of such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, the amendments made by this Act, and the application of such provision or amendment to any person or circumstance shall not be affected thereby.</text></subsection></section><section id="HBF8C021921E24911866D6E9C0F0AC5D8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (b) of section 301 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10401">42 U.S.C. 10401</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDA53A2562C8A4828834FBA7998CF32AF" style="OLC"><subsection id="HA29B802B4DF74C1D87BF24A0127E69D1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the purpose of this title to improve services and interventions for victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, and to advance primary and secondary prevention of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence by—</text><paragraph id="H2B3F12CD8C67426BA21BD72E472B9850"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assisting States and territories in supporting local domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence programs to provide accessible, trauma-informed, culturally relevant residential and non-residential services to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence victims and their children and dependents;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6B8524A383F44F2C9200902EDF4C0A19"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strengthening the capacity of Indian Tribes to exercise their sovereign authority to respond to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence committed against Indians;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04C243DB9FD5416B92E1064959FF90BF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>providing for a network of technical assistance and training centers to support effective policy, practice, research, and cross-system collaboration to improve intervention and prevention efforts throughout the country;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31C5CAF35DD843AFBCE774A132A81487"><enum>(4)</enum><text>supporting the efforts of State, territorial, and Tribal coalitions to document and address the needs of victims and their children and dependents, including victims and their children and dependents who are underserved, implement effective coordinated community and systems responses, and promote ongoing public education and community engagement;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B461EE4FB1B4B0AB9943E5B08B3ABC4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>maintaining national domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence hotlines, including a national Indian domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence hotline; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E43B9B53AA64D6C872FB5B0E0AEDCCA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>supporting the development and implementation of evidence-informed, coalition-led, and community-based primary prevention approaches and programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H97AD3C7ED3D6488DA4AE6D464CB0D251"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 302 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10402">42 U.S.C. 10402</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H2AD2F470327C4F7498CECC0BBFA4936B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H46950D2BDDFE4096AE2FE8F10F727770"><enum>302.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title:</text><paragraph id="H41BF59071E5D4F15B8C167C83F1A24D6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Alaska native</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Alaska Native</quote> has the meaning given the term Native in section 3 of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1602">43 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC974B8B7FD349DB838236342A72244A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Child</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>child</term> means an individual who is younger than age 18.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FD7D0447F19414D8E0916388F6D7012" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Dating partner</header><subparagraph id="HBEC26A437EF64E75A21EF2A1A2B76356"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>dating partner</term> means any person who is or has been in a social relationship of a romantic or intimate nature with an abuser, and where the existence of such a relationship shall be determined based on a consideration of one or more of the following factors:</text><clause id="HBD9C984BACC546C48387714B7B88AF08"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The length of the relationship.</text></clause><clause id="HFD677B82B92F45D79739184AC435BF3C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The type of the relationship.</text></clause><clause id="H8C9D7958E5234D45A91DA5D1A800A3ED"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The frequency of interaction between the persons involved in the relationship.</text></clause><clause id="H4DCDD6424D444BA0A6402C3D98D63DAB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The cultural context of the relationship.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H850983792D994DA6A79AFFD93BAE54B3"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sexual contact is not a necessary component of a relationship described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H15E576FD4F034E07A85771011CA8FA83" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Digital services</header><text>The term <term>digital services</term> means services, resources, information, support, or referrals provided through electronic communications platforms and media, which may include mobile phone technology, video technology, computer technology (including use of the internet), and any other emerging communications technologies that are appropriate for the purposes of providing services, resources, information, support, or referrals for the benefit of victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1024F65A5BA74BFAADB567FD77DE891F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Domestic violence, dating violence, family violence</header><text>The terms <term>domestic violence</term>, <term>dating violence</term>, and <term>family violence</term> mean any act, threatened act, or pattern of acts of physical or sexual violence, stalking, harassment, psychological abuse, economic abuse, technological abuse, or any other form of abuse, including threatening to commit harm against children or dependents or other members of the household of the recipient of the threat for the purpose of coercion, threatening, or causing harm, directed against—</text><subparagraph id="HF613C7050E6342FCB089F2A7E2BF441E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a dating partner or other person similarly situated to a dating partner under the laws of the jurisdiction;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H641462279F70446D9F2098B8AF6A130F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a person who is cohabitating with or has cohabitated with the person committing such an act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1EFAACC868BA4806A923FC06C596ECA1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a current or former spouse or other person similarly situated to a spouse under the laws of the jurisdiction;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFDA075F80041413BBE12BF8623E92DEF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a person who shares a child or dependent in common with the person committing such an act;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF1B0B13E63C43D7AF740F3B545297EE"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a person who is related by marriage, blood, or is otherwise legally related; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6ED364ED8ACD4DF0B789F09C174F4072"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other person who is protected from any such act under the domestic or family violence laws, policies, or regulations of the jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H64B9E1D5F28149428E666878EA1001A3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Economic abuse</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term ‘economic abuse’, when used in the context of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, means behavior that is coercive or deceptive related to a person’s ability to acquire, use, or maintain economic resources to which they are entitled, or that unreasonably controls or restrains a person’s ability to acquire, use, or maintain economic resources to which they are entitled. This includes using coercion, fraud, or manipulation to—</text><subparagraph id="H69C5809816AF44C18FD97BC4E96C1622"><enum>(A)</enum><text>restrict a person’s access to money, assets, credit, or financial information;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5F4753BF919462C969DFBDBBE0E4497"><enum>(B)</enum><text>unfairly use a person’s personal economic resources, including money, assets, and credit, for one’s own advantage; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H751AD37BC76B44BA91B5ADA37FB51184"><enum>(C)</enum><text>exert undue influence over a person’s financial and economic behavior or decisions, including forcing default on joint or other financial obligations, exploiting powers of attorney, guardianship, or conservatorship, or failing or neglecting to act in the best interests of a person to whom one has a fiduciary duty.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEA620B4ECD94E4B8867AE25FED75646" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Indian; Indian Tribe; Tribal organization</header><text>The terms <term>Indian</term>, <term>Indian Tribe</term>, and <term>Tribal organization</term> have the meanings given the terms <term>Indian</term>, <term>Indian tribe</term>, and <term>tribal organization</term>, respectively, in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA15F9BB8DC184A2081E362E831411F2E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H99BBB61BAA5F48FA99857ED22E9DE45D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Native Hawaiian; Native Hawaiian organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms ‘Native Hawaiian’ and ‘Native Hawaiian organization’ have the meanings given such terms in section 6207 of the Native Hawaiian Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7517">20 U.S.C. 7517</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67E1BB81BF524B5AB0D524628AB658E9"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Personally identifying information</header><text>The term <quote>personally identifying information</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 40002(a) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(a)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H421D4F6F0CC84DCABBEF3251CD73BC87" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Population specific services</header><text>The term <term>population specific services</term> has the meaning given such term in section 40002(a) of the Violence Against Women Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F978AFEAFED46369007DEE327A990CF"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Racial and ethnic minority group; racial and ethnic minority population</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>racial and ethnic minority group</quote> and <quote>racial and ethnic minority population</quote> include each group listed in the definition of such term in section 1707(g) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300u-6">42 U.S.C. 300u–6(g)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87F607C380DB42E493A4EF26A9E3F311"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A3764F92D784AACAA87D7207DE63814" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Shelter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>shelter</term> means the provision of temporary refuge and basic necessities, in conjunction with supportive services, provided on a regular basis, in compliance with applicable State, Tribal, territorial, or local law to victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence and their children and dependents. Such law includes regulations governing the provision of safe homes and other forms of secure temporary lodging, meals, other basic necessities, or supportive services to victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence and their children and dependents.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC39A05E4BE2C4D359CB410B71180CA87"><enum>(15)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and, except as otherwise provided, Guam, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E115B726C4F4F889C3F9D83006EB672"><enum>(16)</enum><header>State domestic violence coalition</header><text>The term <quote>State Domestic Violence Coalition</quote> means a statewide nongovernmental nonprofit private domestic violence, dating violence, and family organization designated by the Secretary that—</text><subparagraph id="H85F13AD93CD84040A80B152A3EC47F48"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has a membership that includes a majority of the primary-purpose domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence service providers in the State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54DD7CEB052C49718E884E62CBD3A486"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has board membership that is representative of primary-purpose domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence service providers, and which may include representatives of the communities in which the services are being provided in the State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90B9D53D2DE447A7A9431B5F6A48C3C1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has as its purpose to provide education, support, and technical assistance to such service providers to enable the providers to establish and maintain shelter and supportive services for victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and their children and dependents; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H395663EAD9354F5EA176BA46B54733F3"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serves as an information clearinghouse, primary point of contact, and resource center on domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence for the State and supports the development of polices, protocols, and procedures to enhance domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence intervention and prevention in the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA84E569823A4E98910987627069053F"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Supportive services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>supportive services</quote> means services for adult and youth victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, and children and dependents exposed to domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, that are designed to—</text><subparagraph id="HDBF682AAA84F418ABEF88E7634228653"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meet the needs of such victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, and their children and dependents, for short-term, transitional, or long-term safety; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EAA42B5E4DD4968BF0C78BA87EF2737"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide counseling, advocacy, or assistance for victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, and their children and dependents.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0191B4B6D884ED58584E43FE4497BA0"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Technological abuse</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>technological abuse</quote> means an act or pattern of behavior that—</text><subparagraph id="H986799B4C6BB4CBE807D55CECFF4721E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>occurs within domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C9305BF47834E848B56AB530D5A3412"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is intended to harm, threaten, intimidate, control, stalk, harass, impersonate, exploit, extort, or monitor, except as otherwise permitted by law, another person; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA5FAA592077D4DE5A90CA58BBBA65C24"><enum>(C)</enum><text>uses any form of information technology, including any of the following:</text><clause id="HEE5394666D6A49D799323BA56EA192DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Internet-enabled devices.</text></clause><clause id="H60C38732341E4DB3B4867574E0E3B52D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Online spaces or platforms.</text></clause><clause id="H6A8E1D70260B4D188EF761F03B3584EC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Computers, mobile devices, or software applications.</text></clause><clause id="H347D6382C1D24B7E86DAC704041C2CB3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Location tracking devices.</text></clause><clause id="HD0032173616D4F4E90CC478A9C15B8DE"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Communication technologies.</text></clause><clause id="HD5EDD184CC314F49BB1F622D84F21E04"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Cameras or imaging platforms.</text></clause><clause id="H235E5C5DB9434D52B5EF038BF2A1C665"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other emerging technology.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FF1F3A4E6134B10851B04D6F6AD4448" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Tribal domestic violence coalition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Tribal domestic violence coalition</term> means an established nonprofit, nongovernmental Indian organization recognized by the Office of Violence Against Women at the Department of Justice that—</text><subparagraph id="H05706BF92013412FB1E380E36660E5B5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides education, support, and technical assistance to member Indian service providers in a manner that enables the member providers to establish and maintain culturally appropriate services, including shelter (including supportive services) designed to assist Indian victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence and the children and dependents of such victims; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H742C56A9F56549B6B9AA31FA2B1F7900"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is comprised of members that are representative of—</text><clause id="H8D029823A02743688D6BE10F2D9F39FE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the member service providers described in subparagraph (A); and</text></clause><clause id="H422053E1E4F34DBBBB703F17FD27893D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Tribal communities in which the services are being provided.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDE72A1E82E24CFE81958B291FE3C747"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Tribally designated official</header><text>The term <quote>Tribally designated official</quote> means an individual designated by an Indian Tribe, Tribal organization, or nonprofit private organization authorized by an Indian Tribe, to administer a grant under section 309.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88DD570E75C24E2A9AD3C70D51DF7CB7"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Underserved populations; underserved individuals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>underserved populations</quote> and <quote>underserved individuals</quote> mean victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, and their children and dependents who face obstacles in accessing and using State, Tribal, territorial, or local domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence services, or who may be overrepresented in experiencing domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence due to historical barriers. Populations may be underserved on the basis of, marginalized racial and ethnic minority populations, Indigenous status, cultural and language barriers, immigration status, disabilities, mental health needs, sexual orientation or gender identity, age (including both elders and children), geographical location, faith or religious practice or lack thereof, or other bases, as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC74BE0C833142F184B7060E7B26A44D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Victim</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>victim</quote> means an individual against whom an act of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence is carried out.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68672957BA08406CBFE2D4BEF966C2A9"><enum>(23)</enum><header>Youth</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term ‘youth’ has the meaning given the term in section 4002(a) of the Violence Against Women Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(a)(45)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HCD3FBA6D0AD84749899521D04134C787"><enum>4.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 303 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10403">42 U.S.C. 10403</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE23FD95BA9E54BA18FDC87C3BC8D1B4E" style="OLC"><section id="HF8D77B73B4FE40D6BDDB93BEFDDCCF16"><enum>303.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subsection id="H664DD4692D104A90AC975D4A071FF870"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><paragraph id="HA0AB962835E84E889827716A5951CE69"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out sections 301 through 312 and 316, $270,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB350A1186FA2494FB69F2FFF3CC2332F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reservations for grants to tribes</header><text>Of the amounts appropriated under paragraph (1) for a fiscal year, 12.5 percent shall be reserved and used to carry out section 309.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2371957BE3B34664A3AF8883DF2F201B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Formula grants to states</header><text>Of the amounts appropriated under paragraph (1) for a fiscal year and not reserved under paragraph (2) (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>remainder</quote>), not less than 70 percent shall be used for making grants under section 306(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74DC066345C244F1AC6B8B2A78F79B07"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Technical assistance and training centers</header><text>Of the remainder, not less than 6 percent shall be used to carry out section 310.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H490921FCB8C54FEBAF46BD0DE98E0846"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Grants for state and tribal domestic violence coalitions</header><text>Of the remainder—</text><subparagraph id="HC23EA288780E4C12A785CDC2CA1C596F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not less than 10 percent shall be used to carry out section 311; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB02DE802652E47E89CB8D615A7FB5514"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not less than 3 percent shall be used to carry out section 311A.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8BB7D3F1795E4BDBA73C27861DD44FB1"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Specialized services</header><text>Of the remainder, not less than 5 percent shall be used to carry out section 312.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50BE7BBC28A34A56915E85F1E5868EDF"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Culturally specific services</header><text>Of the remainder, not less 2.5 percent shall be used to carry out section 316.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B7781C4C10E477F9822EA84459449E5"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Administration, evaluation, and monitoring</header><text>Of the remainder, not more than 3.5 percent shall be used by the Secretary for evaluation, monitoring, and other administrative costs under this title.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1CA203EDE2334A3EA36FB37274FC55B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National domestic violence hotline</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out section 313 $14,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection><subsection id="H77181A05D2FF49EA94366E55955D0681"><enum>(c)</enum><header>National Indian Domestic Violence Hotline</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out section 313A $4,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA2AFEB2C03CF4E0D9DDDC09B973EA46B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Domestic violence prevention enhancement and leadership through alliances</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out section 314 $26,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection><subsection id="H83A5F256D2DF438AA8FA76B9D010E071"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grants for underserved populations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out section 315 $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7EC056244EAC485EB9376655F4CD3FC6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Research and evaluation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for research and evaluation of activities under this title $3,500,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HD7038AAF534A410BA5FE334050159953"><enum>5.</enum><header>Authority of Secretary</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 304 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10404">42 U.S.C. 10404</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HA72502A8174D422CB59B39CA0897998C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H2D427F73DA614364A1BBEB56D8A98103"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>or institutions of higher education, including to support and evaluate demonstration or discretionary projects in response to current and emerging issues,</quote> after <quote>nongovernmental entities</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CC39D15188245E7B40157346C96EF6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>CAPTA Reauthorization Act of 2010</quote> and inserting <quote><short-title>Family Violence Prevention and Services Improvement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D6D86770ED943EDB8B7222899C85F19"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H61ACE7C705C64C7085CD17294888C7CB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>have expertise in the field of family violence and domestic violence prevention and services and, to the extent practicable, have expertise in the field of dating violence;</quote> and inserting <quote>have expertise in the field of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence prevention and services;</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE243AC0B8784CE9918FBAFA8F3CE4F6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>prevention and treatment of</quote> and inserting <quote>prevention of, intervention in, and treatment of,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD366C725F1EB48089FDDCF0EBA80B726"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><clause commented="no" id="H6D5405056BBA43A7A8527C3F15C73551"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HCA9C0C0C51DA4AE59C81D860E67D7E78"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding after subparagraph (C) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H720F7DC8ECD240ABB38E3D67A2A7B607" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H3A86C71BB26F42FC9FDD9A44AF5DC1BC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>making grants to eligible entities or entering into contracts with for-profit or nonprofit nongovernmental entities or institutions of higher education to conduct domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence research or evaluation; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8035882352A4CDCB0F7297C88556774"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HDC654F445DE44BE88A0EE99ACE8B685A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H7B54E97FB619438EB76EEF240870FF05"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Emergency authority</header><paragraph id="H343C29DA0C9F4AD6946F016A4EF36997"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In response to any emergency or disaster described in paragraph (3) that substantially disrupts the provision of services under this title, for the duration of the emergency or disaster, the Secretary may—</text><subparagraph id="HEBEDD1EDD41F4D49879A8FEE9F17A688"><enum>(A)</enum><text>modify or broaden the allowable uses of funds by grantees and subgrantees solely to ensure the continuity of services authorized under this title, including for remote and mobile service delivery; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H872172D1E6654DE98C539BAAD5A0497C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>modify or waive any administrative conditions, processes, or deadlines, including with respect to—</text><clause id="H904B0400936D43B68106C3C13FB542A9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>application requirements;</text></clause><clause id="H2EFE5102FD5343328C621457A12CCAC7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>reporting requirements; and</text></clause><clause id="HEF0978E057E24F20B15EB9DCDA989B68"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>grant award extensions.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3BD663FFB8446068B38EEBE8A39DCA5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to allow altering or waiving the requirements in section 306(c)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70DDA46E14E74AFF8EB3C94BD84A4D99"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Emergencies described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The emergencies and disasters described in this paragraph are the following:</text><subparagraph id="HCCC4422C12214D3792C13EBA73AAE17E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A major disaster declared by the President under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6844D1EF83644E08B43436893795378"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An emergency declared by the President under section 501 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5191">42 U.S.C. 5191</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AFB996092B6472081063D5A74A8FE06"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A public health emergency determined by the Secretary of Health and Human Services pursuant to section 319 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d">42 U.S.C. 247d</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="HFB4ED8AC77B343E29FCF712334E42FE8"><enum>6.</enum><header>Allotment of funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 305 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10405">42 U.S.C. 10405</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H1E76D1874C5A434D98EC668E297C9589"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by amending subsection (a) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H172669B4B8634EE4BB9B8E1150934CC6" style="OLC"><subsection id="HDAB1AC5C37AF4AB09E66A20083A2BD1D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From the sums appropriated under section 303 and available for grants to States under section 306(a) for any fiscal year, each State shall be allotted for a grant under section 306(a), $600,000, with the remaining funds to be allotted to each State (other than Guam, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands) in an amount that bears the same ratio to such remaining funds as the population of such State bears to the population of all such States (excluding Guam, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0222965E359747AA90FBE6754C568D88"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (e), by striking <quote>under section 314</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>under this title</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4E3D317071544740BD75E850F2413AA1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking subsection (f).</text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="H7CF68AFE6DC74FD4A905889C31F78AA4"><enum>7.</enum><header>Formula grants to States</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 306 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10406">42 U.S.C. 10406</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HE1EA422FF4764126B69170571BA9A191"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="HC8F307A3E6064DCA96A490B1AF239DF4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>dependents</quote> and inserting <quote>children and dependents</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D116EB9D3364404AD8186AD0013ABDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>Indians, members of Indian Tribes, or</quote> after <quote>who are</quote>; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H57E1ACED295E4AD88C1382C435B9C345"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3F23C4A75DA24260A74AEFA79BDD07F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause commented="no" id="H2BD7554B2D7446FDB80E6ABC956F473D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (A) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB84F8360608740E8AA8FC70BEE8A0A18" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H492A48A195684FA4AE5BDF6D76488243"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Application of civil rights provisions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Programs and activities funded in whole or in part with funds made available under this title are considered to be programs and activities receiving Federal financial assistance for the purpose of applying the prohibitions against discrimination under the Age Discrimination Act of 1975 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/6101">42 U.S.C. 6101 et seq.</external-xref>), section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>), title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1681">20 U.S.C. 1681 et seq.</external-xref>), section 40002(b)(13)(A) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(b)(13)(A)</external-xref>), and title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000d">42 U.S.C. 2000d et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause commented="no" id="H6CAB723574A94201BA75A055D2879008"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)(i)—</text><subclause id="H49C5E99BF5B541C59C58F3E094E814AF"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, including sexual orientation or gender identity,</quote> after <quote>on the ground of sex</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7C20D335445E4E85AD8A315EEB658120"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking the second sentence and inserting the following: <quote>If sex-segregated or sex-specific programming is necessary to the essential operation of a program, nothing in this paragraph shall prevent any such program or activity from being provided in a sex-specific manner. In such circumstances, grantees may meet the requirements of this paragraph by providing comparable services to individuals who cannot be provided with the sex-segregated or sex-specific programming.</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HC8D1D3768BED4A7C904611F8725ACD1D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text><subclause commented="no" id="H249206A57F84497E9948DE6D38281A80"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Indian tribe</quote> and inserting <quote>Indian Tribe</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H22232BD30CFE4C8FA3779267839ED976"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribally</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribally</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HCEBC3FBA831645E6AE3DC14E68A104FB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>Indian tribe</quote> and inserting <quote>Indian Tribe</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE37A37D9047D4307BF8F9695938826A1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (4);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD45ABD41DE4E45D6A66222F0CF14DD4A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (5) and (6) as paragraphs (4) and (5), respectively;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2F7BDE5DE6334BFDBE255CD9F23DB0E9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), as so redesignated—</text><clause commented="no" id="H909F2AE2FEE24C84ACD8FF9B81039B4B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by adding at the end the following: <quote>The nondisclosure of confidential or private information requirements under section 40002(b)(2) of the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/12291">34 U.S.C. 12291(b)(2)</external-xref>) shall apply to grantees and subgrantees under this title in the same manner such requirements apply to grantees and subgrantees under such Act.</quote>;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H0E141EBBAC904D5DAAECC02DEE0DC511"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G)(i), by striking <quote>tribal</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribal</quote>;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HFBCCB113A071419C9B6E65E3FDB52611"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking subparagraphs (B), (C), (D), and (F); and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HE5CF9D6EE58F4473806C4AF2856AFE84"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (E), (G), and (H) as subparagraphs (B), (C), and (D), respectively; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H068E1B1D60784B2C9E3948238E787FE2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), as so redesignated—</text><clause commented="no" id="H2B11D2D92FEF4E3EAEF261816197988F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Indian tribe</quote> and inserting <quote>Indian Tribe</quote>; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H167DDC475FAB4791A46BDBF2D3FE39F7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribal</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribal</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CEF2869FB7D45878D1157D441640AF4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d) by inserting <quote>and information on the development and implementation of barrier removal plans to ensure compliance with the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 and section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>)</quote> after <quote>activities,</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4C895347A58E4DC9AB483518E571A3A7"><enum>8.</enum><header>State application</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 307 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10407">42 U.S.C. 10407</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD6BE8F723CC847598B4C6658B300CC2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H3AD6347CFAB44471B0D36288E0FEE373"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="HD64F9E8C60034255AA69F74CF383E931"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribally</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribally</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H95437E8B40F9471DAE25FD322015C160"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding <quote>For purposes of section 2007(c)(3) of the Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act of 1968, a State’s application under this paragraph shall be deemed to be a <quote>State plan</quote>.</quote> at the end; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B4396C773FC47C2982BDE6BD59BF876"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H61CA77E6E9D940579FB57B8CED4EF718"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subclause id="H694738466D1E49EB83C3B24D17F5FA04"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>assurances</quote> and inserting <quote>certifications</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3F5D53FB6A164B1BA5F0A4F743AF2E12"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (iii)—</text><item id="H1B41DEC4265040BA9702AC2BF62F0B78"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in subclause (I)—</text><subitem id="HBA31329082A541E7A069643947520D26"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>by striking <quote>operation of shelters</quote> and inserting <quote>provision of shelter</quote>; and</text></subitem><subitem id="H786D15FA607240F39F8C3BB3E9BD448F"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>by striking <quote>dependents</quote> and inserting <quote>children and dependents</quote>; and</text></subitem></item><item id="HD214BB9B74544940A5E1D1A2DA1574CE"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by striking <quote>dependents</quote> and inserting <quote>children and dependents</quote>;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="HB5112142204140AD9E8C4416A8F96248"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>an assurance</quote> and inserting <quote>a certification</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H8C3EA75FF4E24B1ABFB161B3B26F5864"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D)—</text><subclause id="H05A896ED449D4BE3815C44113A897428"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>an assurance</quote> and inserting <quote>a certification</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H0EFE430606ED4D5E83244F2BF4C369D5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>planning and monitoring</quote> and inserting <quote>planning, coordination, and monitoring</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H37EBE4CDDA6F495D95258670C9D076F7"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and the administration of the grant programs and projects</quote> and inserting <quote>, the administration of the grant programs and projects, and the establishment of service standards and best practices for grantees</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H2BBC4087814E4CD89B442F1A8411BBC7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by striking <quote>to underserved populations</quote> and all that follows through the semicolon and inserting <quote>for individuals from racial and ethnic minority groups, Tribal populations, and other underserved populations, in the State planning process, and how the State plan addresses the unmet needs of such populations, including a certification and description of how the State or Indian Tribe will disseminate information about the national resource centers authorized under section 310;</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H00714C00103C4C62BFDB558EE95E8790"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in subparagraphs (E), (F), and (G), by striking <quote>Indian tribe</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Indian Tribe</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H56FC80EDBB684F0DB529A60D26B2FB0B"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking <quote>tribally</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribally</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H5CD7C3C717BE43F28BE6B3DC64075A94"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (H) and (I) as subparagraphs (I) and (J), respectively;</text></clause><clause id="H08C453D8F09042A7A7DC21DBA9C8B35C"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (G) the following:</text><quoted-block id="HB0710125C05C46B7B9B1B6A99597D696" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H348376F9260643C0AC900C2675ABEBF9"><enum>(H)</enum><text>describe how activities and services provided by the State or Indian Tribe are designed to promote trauma-informed care, autonomy, and privacy for victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, and their children and dependents, including in the design and delivery of shelter services;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H84DEE9419056455EB32E6E2D373686C5"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), as so redesignated—</text><subclause id="HB87844D175414378A52A940A8496D9EE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribe</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribe</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5108E568EEE14F11A170273B092B6D5E" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>an assurance</quote> and inserting <quote>a certification</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H93F206AF54A14714A342387953066DCB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, remove, or exclude</quote> after <quote>bar</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA8EF3BEFE7904DA68171AEA1FFE78B2E"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H2542F6992492442FAE4E46158701E574"><enum>(x)</enum><text>in subparagraph (J), as so redesignated, by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and </text></clause><clause id="H700B7FC7008B43FF90BB17B5D5070464"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HE766F3B32A3F4C42A41A9A5143736797" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H211EAE4A350445AEBF30C259FC102BE6"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide a certification that all funded entities demonstrate the ability to provide services for Deaf individuals and individuals with disabilities in compliance with the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 and section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H36861255568840D0907FD311B20DAF15"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H1BD3A13F05C444DEAE0684A3A1AAE8D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>tribe</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Tribe</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88911CAB0C7A4DC0917201C0A0655096"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>Indian tribes</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Indian Tribes</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section commented="no" id="H1C79DDF1A72A46FBBC18ADD604CFBF02"><enum>9.</enum><header>Subgrants and uses of funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 308 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10408">42 U.S.C. 10408</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H7D64466309294590A263351E2E731BE6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4D3B55E18CED4E64ABB7D4FACFF71768"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>that is designed</quote> and inserting <quote>that are designed</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA5B6D80854094ACFACF71405690A1E50"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>dependents</quote> and inserting <quote>children and dependents</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4A52BAEC69854671AB83AEC48B6EA698"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HFE30EFCB68864CD0A2594B4A1E165335"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause commented="no" id="HA73791E6F38D431DB1869C1AD1638686"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="H42C9EDCCCB7442B1980A6E6D43882466"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>shelter, supportive services, or prevention services</quote> and inserting <quote>shelter or supportive services</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="HBF6936D4522B4E498E0D691C356A66D7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or prevention services</quote> after <quote>dependents,</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HFC45BA9BFA8142A0AC0134EDDD404972" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by striking <quote>include—</quote> and inserting <quote>include making material improvements in the accessibility of physical structures, transportation, communication, or digital services, as well as—</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="H09AAA9C2473940DCA313580FECF0B8D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>developing safety plans</quote> and inserting <quote>safety planning</quote>;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H2075630041DB42E08B7CCA8977C9DC4E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by inserting <quote>for racial and ethnic minority groups</quote> before the semicolon;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H495DE6B9D0E34C9EA2C47BC84E3D0FB7"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (F) through (H) as subparagraphs (G) through (I), respectively;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HAFA83829241843FBB5EE56B9B2D7901B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (E) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA91B4CC34DF44B498A007291C6F9CD1E" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HFF600985FDA643059916ABE67BDF82B4"><enum>(F)</enum><text>provision of shelter and services to underserved populations;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause commented="no" id="H1C768DCD253A4FAAB5F7D1EC697D63B3"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subparagraph (H), as so redesignated—</text><subclause commented="no" id="HF3EAA3216D7342B0AF195A0F3AD59688"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>Federal and State</quote> and inserting <quote>Federal, State, and local</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H1AEB4C63163B47F6B0D267A700AC32DF"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in clause (iii), by striking <quote>mental health, alcohol, and drug abuse treatment), but which shall not include reimbursement for any health care services</quote> and inserting <quote>mental health and substance use disorder treatment)</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H10685BFBF99642519AD5B4BA0E2B6B0D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (v), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H4712D4E83E074BD39172934CE9F6A74C"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by redesignating clause (vi) as clause (vii);</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HABAC54303DB64D1EAF66B6E8E92C3C7B"><enum>(V)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (v) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0DF428095F5F4010A04100F745CCD6D2" style="OLC"><clause id="HEC9C2C0C0D8D47C3A9E76F63B25F76AC"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">language assistance, including translation of written materials and telephonic and in-person interpreter services, for victims with limited English proficiency, victims who are Deaf or hard of hearing, victims with sensory disabilities (including individuals who are blind or low vision), victims with speech-related disabilities, and victims with other disabilities; and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H2D68D87FDF384C9C8354F5A9E82455AE"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>in clause (vii), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H6C8ED7CD7A984281A698038CEDE09E92"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (I), as so redesignated, by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H67CEC9E2195845FAA918C3B39EE9A09C"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HABA542E6F6C944D4BA9E6411ACC845D1" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H54A9A97CA7D645A39668A5C0D0809EDB"><enum>(J)</enum><text>partnerships that enhance the design and delivery of services to victims and their children and dependents.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H793D1DEB6EE6410B8EC49824B85C27E8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause commented="no" id="H53F8FD6EF83E4563B114C957C4291CA8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>supportive services and prevention services</quote> and inserting <quote>supportive services or prevention services</quote>; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HFF25EE812BCE4E6FA644D59271BC46D2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>through (H)</quote> and inserting <quote>through (I)</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF9916802A9914D58961D9C8AC6B1BB95"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>dependents</quote> each place such term appears (other than in paragraph (1)(J)) and inserting <quote>children and dependents</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8CC067176A74EBAA7709C73999CFD4B" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H49BB2C83611249E885853F2AFD9D85FD" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H9632FD3B8E53416E870B497D5406BA6E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Sense of Congress regarding use of funds for removal of architectural barriers to accessibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that—</text><subparagraph id="H03CAB1A4BD184D86BB582F6D38A321D4" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Deaf individuals and individuals with disabilities experience domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence at disproportionate rates;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3025784D5AD47ED869602D8CEFA689E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>domestic violence shelters are often not equipped to provide effective services to Deaf individuals and individuals with disabilities, which can act as an impediment to victims seeking and receiving services; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA097A382D995477F81D264D3C23D508D" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary should allow subgrant funds received under this section to be used for making material improvements in the accessibility of physical structures, transportation, communication, or digital services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H025EC085A9C947EC8F81227876CFA676"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="H30471128D980437383AEED0A29631F99"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="HF801329C17EA4F0796B3ED3A9ADADA84"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>a local public agency, or </quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H5F221EECF6C8419587AD92545C61C845"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribal organizations, and voluntary associations),</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribal organizations and voluntary associations) or a local public agency</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HC09419C3BB20444CBBB62D88284DFFDB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>dependents</quote> and inserting <quote>children and dependents</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47E9780C795144EBA8DA2651E3F40E8A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (2) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5275BE32597949E9A98AEFD30E61E45A" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H9F64A316BA4F4198B3943B3D13EACEB6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an organization whose primary purpose is to provide culturally appropriate services to racial and ethnic minority groups, Tribal communities, or other underserved populations, that does not have a documented history of effective work concerning domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, but that is in partnership with an organization described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H8C3ECE24989344EE835C3A26DF126EF1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by amending subsection (d) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5C9DFBE92E724AF4887F245CE2AA3280" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H8D50DB0F33664C60980ACD5A6553B291"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Voluntarily accepted services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Participation in services under this title shall be voluntary. Receipt of the benefits of shelter described in subsection (b)(1)(A) shall not be conditioned upon the participation of the adult or youth, or their children or dependents, in any or all of the services offered under this title.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H5B465BE047F2440CAEF20A0A71CBD6FB"><enum>10.</enum><header>Grants for Indian Tribes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 309 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10409">42 U.S.C. 10409</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4C9B3FAEB5D14ED39F08BE9D7C421F53"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H25849BE2D1124EB1A49928953D54961B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>42 U.S.C. 14045d</quote> and inserting <quote>34 U.S.C. 20126</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28C9677F1B1B4A23B79C4D559D9F7AF4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>tribal</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribal</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63E2F776633545D0B2DD77B2FF303055"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Indian tribes</quote> and inserting <quote>Indian Tribes</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4120FF065A624E7789B8FDECF840AEB1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by striking <quote>section 303(a)(2)(B)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 303 and made available</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE29FB0049A014521BF4F530E3903B7E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H6B1026FB00574080BD9DF4F48E00E456"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Indian tribe</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Indian Tribe</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7784D218461A4F6C806AA85B17E7AAE9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribal organization</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Tribal organization</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H400C00145A744E62B200A1AD0D035081"><enum>11.</enum><header>National resource centers and training and technical assistance centers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 310 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10410">42 U.S.C. 10410</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1AA6AD84630A4CFC8E60B19854611676"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(2)—</text><subparagraph id="H448644F5BCC24C84BE4F02EDB259B7D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>under this title and reserved under section 303(a)(2)(C)</quote> and inserting <quote>under section 303 and made available to carry out this section</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA14C8E4780334BB38082E8194EAE06D3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H010A96E993F4491A8FC7EC7821946960"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></clause><clause id="H47CD2A3EA50D4EF581CD685EE25C1276"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (ii)—</text><subclause id="HE680017083634F7E95B7E850C7378EDC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>7</quote> and inserting <quote>11</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H19DAA9A216B54119A0916CE11F197513"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>dating violence, and family violence,</quote> after <quote>domestic violence,</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB3BA36A3CF474CDAB815547E7B075D88"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0727C52204D74C188FBCC219A84E8B81" style="OLC"><clause id="H33D665E195314B07918510F0BA8ED77F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an Alaska Native Tribal resource center on domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, to reduce disparities in the rate of such violence within the Alaska Native population; </text></clause><clause id="H93CDD23075774877A6F3B09AD30B2E45"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a Native Hawaiian resource center on domestic violence, to reduce Native Hawaiian disparities; and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB563656C3F1D4DEF8668D35646CD7E54"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><clause id="H91307A5EAC83479C8E7135BDDAE2CA25"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>grants, to</quote> and inserting <quote>grants to entities that focus on other critical issues, such as</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H215B8E7E9F88427BB3DB1CACCD28C123"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text><subclause id="HA8F22FC6AB04414AB3B148D2EA8D9071"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence,</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H23873DBD4E6C4395ADDE6FF51210AD38"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(including Alaska Native)</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H93E11CA2FD054105AD300E1F1DB70F75"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H941EE60E301F4BC6A095327E73C336F0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by amending clause (ii) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5A806E1F20E14A308CEBE54EE6669211" style="OLC"><clause id="H4D47FA57193A4B0D8BD16C7B0B90678A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>entities demonstrating expertise related to—</text><subclause id="HE532A3DD8BB64E9D969D5B7D702EE643"><enum>(I)</enum><text>addressing the housing needs of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence victims and their children and dependents;</text></subclause><subclause id="H1015D83D86894CE69EA9DA73DA7671B4"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing leadership and advocacy skills among individuals from underserved populations; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H8940918EC7C041CF810508E2F8DCC350"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">addressing other emerging issues related to domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C245BDAD6354E92BB4166BBBCA2E7EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="HD1B0A62A61A941BEB43E2972D77866A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H82411C45F34743D1A29958BFE883BAEC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="HC5C4A37FF52344B08E780FDCB4CB5077"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text><item id="HF4A1417AD84D487B9784933565580049"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote> each place such term appears; and</text></item><item id="H3B9A944B93DF4ECEB351369623C14C62"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and dependents</quote> after <quote>children</quote>; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H34020CA584C44397A642767745B1FE42"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii)—</text><item id="H88FBCC3DF2284B0D81AD92CAD6F0E2AF"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subclause (I), by inserting <quote>online</quote> after <quote>central</quote>;</text></item><item id="HC055829338C24D699040D256DFC78EE2"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in subclause (I), by striking <quote>family violence and domestic violence</quote> and inserting <quote>domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence</quote>; and</text></item><item id="HF93AA509186E4A8A9C0123A969677106"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>; and </text></item></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HC23740F9448E4CE9A4DFA34CA3C78744"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subclause commented="no" id="H45A1D751393949AEB0179FFEBF2D88A0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text><item commented="no" id="H84655E521C2D42F28370ECE171B01C43"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribes and tribal organizations</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribes and Tribal organizations</quote>;</text></item><item commented="no" id="HE1D73C915B7A4433BDBA82439EC9DB4C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by striking <quote>the tribes</quote> and inserting <quote>the Tribes</quote>;</text></item><item id="H40459366B5F047EEBD131C4B70CEF4C5"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>; and </text></item><item id="H289C47A23B934BB0980940B05D127931"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>by striking <quote>42</quote> and all the follows through <quote>3796gg–10 note</quote> and inserting <quote>34 U.S.C. 10452 note</quote>;</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H943B2A86D0EA41BCACE69A1D28696A68"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii)—</text><item id="H0DD5495D61104AC8B96DAC0B800308DD"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribes and tribal organizations</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribes and Tribal organizations</quote>;</text></item><item id="H9DFF51974E7E403489C26F8A9786BA48"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>; and</text></item><item id="H78481A6B073E4AE493F2C919D96D2AF1"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>by striking <quote>42</quote> and all that follows through <quote>3796gg–10 note</quote> and inserting <quote>34 U.S.C. 10452 note</quote>; and</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="H11EF7B6187764C2C8901F7785DAAFF18"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (iii)—</text><item id="H78129D27303E41C7AFCE554CCF027FDA"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>dating violence, and family violence,</quote> after <quote>domestic violence,</quote>; and </text></item><item id="HE55D3CA9E03D412190FD1EA621C960CA"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>the Office for Victims of Crime and</quote> after <quote>Human Services, and</quote>;</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5DFB542A1570452BB950DDA7036B6641"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H2E373050344248F1814870275C4D23A8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="H752D82932D5E48FC8DF89D024A35F588"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>State and local domestic violence service providers</quote> and inserting <quote>support effective policy, practice, research, and cross systems collaboration</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H737E2D8D55F54F55B7380F13820669E8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>enhancing domestic violence</quote>; </text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE4581DA0289645B68E87EDA89912C119"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="HA343F98D35764448B656AADB4D07A6AE"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>to domestic violence</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H193B553990F947F0B4BAA81765C1BBA1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>which may include the response to the use of the self-defense plea by domestic violence victims and the issuance and use of protective orders</quote> and inserting <quote>including the issuance and use of protective orders, batterers' intervention programming, and responses to charged, incarcerated, and re-entering domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence victims</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HABB229E9890549EF8ECF2B4EDB197B6B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subclause id="H81817A529C3140F693B5A427ABF67A9D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote> each place such term appears; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H24D3233770C24CB1BCF571F0E4A6FDB1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>dependents</quote> and inserting <quote>children</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H04280AD1455F458EB55FFCF90CDAAF40"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C)—</text><subclause id="H67DA96AD8FDD4686915820DDD701C605" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote> the first place such term appears; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H3E468108EF5E495896F5C5965DD3BB21"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, and the response of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence programs and other community organizations with respect to health advocacy and addressing the health of victims</quote> before the period;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H14D374861A594224B203BF7AE73CD1EA"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (D) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8C19A83D7C394B18AAA2521D11C247DD" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H69CCBA391C0240F2A426E0D50EAD57FE"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The response of mental health, substance use disorder treatment and recovery, domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and related systems and programs to victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and their children and dependents who experience psychological trauma, mental health needs, or substance-use-related needs.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H53B8BD9760CF4119A474CCEDF69C7385"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E); by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote> each place such term appears; and</text></clause><clause id="H37525424EA4447FE9E80E0ADD85A792C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3C0BCDF5E1F8406A93277EE7F938E730" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HBD762C767F2144B2A1E821731ECC7F12"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The response of the domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence programs and related systems to victims who are underserved due to sexual orientation or gender identity, including expanding the capacity of lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender organizations to respond to and prevent domestic violence.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H70106029838D4496BE9C2F6DDB5C6CE0"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Strengthening the organizational capacity of State, territorial, and Tribal domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence coalitions and of State, territorial, and Tribal administrators who distribute funds under this title to community-based domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence programs, with the aim of better enabling such coalitions and administrators—</text><clause id="HFEC927601DBB4AEE8A2D4DBE46A57A73"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to collaborate and respond effectively to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence;</text></clause><clause id="H7DAE53D71F07447A88776F1008C61D3D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to meet the conditions and carry out the provisions of this title; and</text></clause><clause id="H299484CB60514A179016E2FD691AC57F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to implement best practices to meet the emerging needs of victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and their families, children, and dependents.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA417C17F441D4B829E543C52DD93126C"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The response of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence service providers to victims who are Deaf and victims with disabilities, including expanding the capacity of community-based organizations serving individuals who are Deaf and individuals with disabilities to respond to, and prevent, domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7583E57290704D23842567C36264C548"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (3) as paragraph (4);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB00CBDDAD339472F9E24CF1953594CC3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6BDA847E3A8E499A84E2463B84B60FF4" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H7132458D87A0411093C22A22DB490ECB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Alaska Native Tribal resource center</header><text>In accordance with subsection (a)(2), the Secretary shall award a grant to an eligible entity for an Alaska Native Tribal resource center on domestic violence to reduce Tribal disparities, which shall—</text><subparagraph id="H5D02EC2F785C4100992F957C2552E0BC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>offer a comprehensive array of technical assistance and training resources to Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations, specifically designed to enhance the capacity of the Tribes and organizations to respond to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and the findings of section 901 and purposes in section 902 of the Violence Against Women and Department of Justice Reauthorization Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10452">34 U.S.C. 10452</external-xref> note);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA43ACDA67F534102B3F2471B0C56229A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordinate all projects and activities with the national resource center described in paragraph (1)(B), including projects and activities that involve working with non-Tribal State and local governments to enhance their capacity to understand the unique needs of Alaska Natives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A640EBD8415452CB6D396F9263BD793"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">work with non-Tribal State and local governments and domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence service providers to enhance their capacity to understand the unique needs of Alaska Natives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6DEFC17A058A4154B0258C1DE9B99C28"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide comprehensive community education and domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence prevention initiatives in a culturally sensitive and relevant manner; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9AABE51626644B02A1352BD72CEE431D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>coordinate activities with other Federal agencies, offices, and grantees that address the needs of Alaska Natives that experience domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, including the Office of Justice Services of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, the Indian Health Service, and the Office for Victims of Crime and the Office on Violence Against Women of the Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H498C73937B4C4BEF8D7F92A752B370ED"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), as so redesignated—</text><clause id="HC37995BCC5A34129BC064A3417FE39C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraphs (A) and (B)(i), by striking <quote>Indian tribes, tribal organizations</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Indian Tribes, Tribal organizations</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HB5B627BA379345BCA4145FE4E699E5F1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A) by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H7ACAF05E875E4458BAA2CD4F2801BB65"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subclause id="HFD3D07B637C14BC7A037F7CD1F7A05C1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>the tribes</quote> and inserting <quote>the Tribes</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H57D9737235DD4135B815EB2C91A5FD64"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>nontribal</quote> and inserting <quote>non-Tribal</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H8AF5A36064E3441BB2C6743F522E57A6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>; and </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H1C87242261904101B72A31ACA1B49EE6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by striking <quote>(including Alaska Natives)</quote> each place such term appears; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE067C4140DF47B7AF8454CD56A0669D"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H31BBC1037B7F41C19B607E0177827B2B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H627ED6321AE94AF19C5EDBFB13649ADD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Native Hawaiian resource center</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In accordance with subsection (a)(2), the Secretary shall award a grant to an eligible entity for an Native Hawaiian resource center on domestic violence to reduce Native Hawaiian disparities, which shall—</text><subparagraph id="HE236A52A22A74275A4357CBC8D40EA0D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer a comprehensive array of technical assistance and training resources to Native Hawaiian organizations, specifically designed to enhance the capacity of the Native Hawaiian organizations to respond to family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01113B92E0B547A8B74C4C8DE2F349BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate all projects and other activities with the national resource center described in paragraph (1)(B);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9433205D20AD4FB5A376F2D11A8A3EC4"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate all projects and other activities, with State and local governments, that involve working with the State and local governments, to enhance their capacity to understand the unique needs of Native Hawaiians;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H155E7E7491AA45D0A9A3183BE0C8495E"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide comprehensive community education and prevention initiatives relating to family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence in a culturally sensitive and relevant manner; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E116CD4E6424A2BB409EAF4EBE0994B"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate activities with other Federal agencies, offices, and grantees that address the needs of Native Hawaiians who experience family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence, including the Office for Victims of Crime and the Office on Violence Against Women of the Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FBDF11E49CC401295A8FE7BBDEDBD2B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="H572619D66F344F8DB39D4E31EFB4D2F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H2FE9F889FA0E42E9A4D3D9B80379A541"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="HDBC3F607673A4DAE9D730B54DC624363"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>; and </text></subclause><subclause id="HEDFB389C04AB4322B6980C0F1B4D6F1E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or (D)</quote> and inserting <quote>(D), (F), or (G)</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H09C03676FEB046F1959F0D05AEBA445C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>dating violence, and family violence,</quote> after <quote>domestic violence,</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HEBF889CED4A448E4821DC51CB25B9E25"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (B) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6F106D2A4C1D432E8087819DB363A34E" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HC0212BB809A8401E9C8519020293B7A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes individuals with demonstrated experience working in domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence programs, and, with respect to grantees described in subsection (b)(2)(F), individuals with demonstrated expertise in serving the targeted communities on the board of directors (or advisory committee) and on the staff; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B62508EE9004CFEBF231DF749D48546"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H157E76BC3660414FA54AB8B031820CA7"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote> each place such term appears;</text></clause><clause id="HCEB3EC75FBCE41E98953EAAF23E527FC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribal organization</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Tribal organization</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H47DE63ADA49648779DEAF9B9BF96EEBC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Indian tribes</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>Indian Tribes</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HD9B5C1F2199F4DB89F9C1B7D474BCEAE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by striking <quote>42</quote> and all that follows through <quote>3796gg–10 note</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>34 U.S.C. 10452 note</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H01E7843EABF641E0ACC2BD2417A9513C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribally</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribally</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H78A6B1D85FBA4FDB9E7EDE1945117845"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><clause id="H2BB80AABFEE2407891834652C7E5F3EA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="H70D58DB5E2F1493DB939AAE8EE7F0437"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote> the first place such term appears; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H21C16A78DDC44E05B9B248499A702C16"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, dating violence, or family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote> the second place such term appears; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H2AF74DF0EDCE4C8B979F8CD243BAED46"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subclause id="H1C3575CD41674A52B86FFC56075D0FC7" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i), by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC17638534F5D43BDB26E05C83308A1A8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subclause><subclause id="HE68B7560FDC048D78E5B569B5FF5E7DC"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H6EDF7B84377D4302B4A633DD9E27E37B"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A9DE1FF071A4C1D9EF781591D7A0D85" style="OLC"><clause id="H601BC4CC2CFE44A59943A4D8BCE6A3AC" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has a board of directors (or advisory committee) and staff with demonstrated expertise in serving the targeted community.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H017714A926BE4E45B276CD5BB8255FBA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (4) as paragraph (5);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H62F0703A9C5B44BA925662DB48356282"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (3) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4BC2CD4209164EEABDB57C25E343A8E9" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H75FF422EDC0245CD8D72F2F080F115B3"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Alaska Native Tribal Resource Center on Domestic Violence</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under subsection (b)(3), an entity shall be a Tribal organization or a nonprofit private organization that focuses primarily on issues of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence within Tribes in Alaska that submits information to the Secretary demonstrating—</text><subparagraph id="HE4392436019140B59D28965FBF88A4F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>experience working with Alaska Tribes and Tribal organizations to respond to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and the findings of section 901 of the Violence Against Women and Department of Justice Reauthorization Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/162">Public Law 109–162</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10452">34 U.S.C. 10452</external-xref> note);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD02C1F60467C44EDBDDC4A55C741AACA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>experience providing Alaska Tribes and Tribal organizations with assistance in developing Tribally based prevention and intervention services addressing domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and safety for Indian women consistent with the purposes of section 902 of the Violence Against Women and Department of Justice Reauthorization Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/162">Public Law 109–162</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/10452">34 U.S.C. 10452</external-xref> note);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5281FCBAD8764AC2A680EBABCD33DF2E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>strong support for the entity's designation as the Alaska Native Tribal resource center on domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence from advocates working with Alaska Tribes to address domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and the safety of Alaska Native women;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DCB0E5D3CCA46BD98A6CF84DEE182F0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a record of demonstrated effectiveness in assisting Alaska Tribes and Tribal organizations with prevention and intervention services addressing domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D71C4FFA0BE4B3FBC0925162B3B3367"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the capacity to serve Tribes across the State of Alaska.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H684EF87BBC6F4C61828B74577F3BBDC6"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (5), as so redesignated—</text><clause id="HD38C830A09124CA785250ABCC5856C20"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>(b)(3),</quote> and inserting <quote>(b)(4),</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H307E8FB361144C67BCBFE42298109C43"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="H0A7B0DF45CAF42E7AD4E2D81468C52DB"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>(including Alaska Natives)</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H71F908E1CE324118BC6D4BF38C8F8729"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii)—</text><item id="H7B1CCEE2F05444939FAB327B7A322B97"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Indian tribe, tribal organization</quote> and inserting <quote>Indian Tribe, Tribal organization</quote>; and</text></item><item id="H1A1A48424A834CA68025E6106EE1E21C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, dating violence, and family violence</quote> after <quote>domestic violence</quote>; and </text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66E5079382F0424986BC5557377A1A14" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8D3678A6E1B14276B3C6DCA91030AE6C"><paragraph id="H7DF7F487C2D54601BE4C67F89340FA2C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Native Hawaiian resource center</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under subsection (b)(3), an entity shall be a Native Hawaiian organization, or a nonprofit private organization that focuses primarily on issues of family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence within the Native Hawaiian community, that submits information to the Secretary demonstrating—</text><subparagraph id="H3FF58D34DD53446BB58EF93CB8941940"><enum>(A)</enum><text>experience working with Native Hawaiian organizations to respond to family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74D0C711F9434DAF8E7458F6346EEFFD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>experience providing Native Hawaiian organizations with assistance in developing prevention and intervention services addressing family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence and safety for Native Hawaiian women;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7442EAD4238D433891BE676B9199B4A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>strong support for the entity’s designation as the Native Hawaiian resource center on domestic violence from advocates working with Native Hawaiian organizations to address family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence and the safety of Native Hawaiian women;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0BF1A46FE704C21B7180A0F424F533F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a record of demonstrated effectiveness in assisting Native Hawaiian organizations with prevention and intervention services addressing family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90DDE802CE3B41339D74355F5BCE8188"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the capacity to serve geographically diverse Native Hawaiian communities and organizations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H9AF3063C652E4FB1B96CE2DE949E229A"><enum>12.</enum><header>Grants to State domestic violence coalitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 311 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10411">42 U.S.C. 10411</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H10BFAABE55DD4F5FA5B03560119CFBAB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1), by striking <quote>section 303(a)(2)(D)</quote> and inserting <quote>section 303 and made available to carry out this section</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F70641DCBB34A9485A471954BBFE436"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="H1993F73BD53D431DB40ADDBF70533C55"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>shall include</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DFC8113517C40B6A77DB52E1F5F7EAF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H1B085A3A94D241BFA695BC4E558BA4BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, and evidence-informed prevention of,</quote> after <quote>comprehensive responses to</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H95AC6357BDA34CC1892826167C617F94"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>working with local</quote> and inserting “shall include—</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H45AC4222BEDF4C23941C3720C2BA6E0C" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H099598186F034070BD009E683437C6AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>working with local</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04BACBB1AC4A4037A5463780F47F0A5F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (2) and (3) as subparagraphs (B) and (C), respectively, and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7AF7CC451C3C4148A07439DB83610CAA"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C) of paragraph (1), as so redesignated—</text><clause id="HFEEEB463ED824F79A91691B112E805CA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>dependents</quote> and inserting <quote>children and dependents</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H8BD21BE057C440F8BDC51455C065DBFC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H22E84F68A7BD4AD18B1D976561206E6D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (C) of paragraph (1), as so redesignated, the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA0717EDDCF948CDA7D4B79FBFA0CF48" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="HEBB957D7885D4F1AA6384C5FB19E3F04"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collaborating with Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations (and corresponding Native Hawaiian groups or communities) to address the needs of Indian (including Alaska Native) and Native Hawaiian victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, as applicable in the State; and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC3BAA5E7D1874DCFB9FA72BFFDD237B1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>collaborating with and providing</quote> and inserting “may include—</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB74DA9B3E0E04EF0A47D3C0F35323EED" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H519C666240084E788DF8BEF3B516C3C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>collaborating with and providing</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A279F7127B344C5B8FECBA1D292A72A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (4) as paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF447E2775B6B4299B1CCA1B3CAEB204A"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>health care, mental health</quote> and inserting <quote>health care (including mental health and substance use disorder treatment)</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FA5B802782E4F5FA5695E31883612FE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by redesignating subparagraphs (A) and (B) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively, and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE8C0D1911744A9F85A60E6D081B7B86"><enum>(J)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (5) through (7) as subparagraphs (B) through (D), respectively, and adjusting the margins accordingly;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD7044510B1D4486AA30F16D57C8AFAD"><enum>(K)</enum><text>in clause (ii) of subparagraph (C) of paragraph (2), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>child abuse is present;</quote> and inserting <quote>there is a co-occurrence of child abuse; and</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBAA1286526F4C5FA3D56FBB601E8717"><enum>(L)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (8); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88F59D9E771B46EEBDBF9D5E1C31FC54"><enum>(M)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D) of paragraph (2), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a period;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H524A201619EB48C195635B8D8F71FAE9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking subsection (e);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H358228B754FB4DF0AEB53CA4642632B3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (f) through (h) as subsections (e) through (g), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2376D1F4095D408BB8C23DC360FFCE67"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (g), as so redesignated, by striking <quote>Indian tribes and tribal organizations</quote> and inserting <quote>Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H062C6370AF1C4BDBA570C0466588CBC5"><enum>13.</enum><header>Grants to Tribal domestic violence coalitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Family Violence Prevention and Services Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10401">42 U.S.C. 10401 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 311 the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8DFBB9D9FB8A4D55B4998ADB9CB80DA7" style="OLC"><section id="H2A4C534018A949E7BF8D4A02A8B0D831"><enum>311A.</enum><header>Grants to Tribal domestic violence coalitions</header><subsection id="HC3C618FC53AE4DFE8618521A95636C0F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants authorized</header><text>Beginning with fiscal year 2024, out of amounts appropriated under section 303 and made available to carry out this section for a fiscal year, the Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities in accordance with this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H368F1052759D46C4BAF4E14E8F148880"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall be a Tribal domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence coalition that is recognized by the Office on Violence Against Women of the Department of Justice that provides services to Indian Tribes.</text></subsection><subsection id="H65B7421C6C0843079CE670C865ADB55C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Each Tribal domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence coalition desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. The application submitted by the coalition for the grant shall provide documentation of the coalition’s work, demonstrating that the coalition—</text><paragraph id="HA0FD57AA04C44FB3BB4ABEDF02623C21"><enum>(1)</enum><text>meets all the applicable requirements set forth in this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74491A558DA044AD9C468BDCEF56F541"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has the ability to conduct all activities described in this section, as indicated by—</text><subparagraph id="HF0F09542A0554BA28237703CF2BBEB8E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a documented experience in administering Federal grants to conduct the activities described in subsection (d); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD30EC56BBE4E46A0B521352867B4BDE9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a documented history of activities to further the purposes of this section set forth in subsection (d).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H57B0638A9C884B8BAE4DBBB3B244F765"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A Tribal domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence coalition eligible under subsection (b) that receives a grant under this section may use the grant funds for administration and operation to further the purposes of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence intervention and prevention activities, including—</text><paragraph id="H56620F2D2D5D497481547C54F0545A5F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>working with local Tribal domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence service programs and providers of direct services to encourage appropriate and comprehensive responses to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence against adults or youth within the Indian Tribes served, including providing training and technical assistance and conducting Tribal needs assessments;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B233EE5DC434433A4BB02D633AB8E35"><enum>(2)</enum><text>participating in planning and monitoring the distribution of subgrants and subgrant funds within the State under section 308(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A8CA3670EC648F79116199808A64946"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">working in collaboration with Tribal service providers and community-based organizations to address the needs of victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, and their children and dependents;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5A85D84EF3A43798E4A9214CFC0B541"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collaborating with, and providing information to, entities in such fields as housing, health care (including mental health and substance use disorder treatment), social welfare, education, and law enforcement to support the development and implementation of effective policies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC77B9AB7F754F4099202BD8A0661751"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting the development and implementation of effective policies, protocols, and programs that address the safety and support needs of adult and youth Tribal victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF7A10B3496CF4175A092A3242510A2AF"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encouraging appropriate responses to cases of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence against adults or youth, by working with Tribal, State, and Federal judicial agencies and law enforcement agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC77837C7ACB46AEA604FDE771D54E17"><enum>(7)</enum><text>working with Tribal, State, and Federal judicial agencies, including family law judges, criminal court judges, child protective service agencies, and children's advocates to develop appropriate responses to child custody and visitation issues—</text><subparagraph id="HC12E23BD61C148909FDBF365C34340DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in cases of child exposure to domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2025A0189DCC4CCEA9491EE68F793BF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in cases in which—</text><clause id="H13CD68583D1C4B31911766DCA3DC0D1D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence is present; and</text></clause><clause id="H289A6E17CE2B4321B67B7A2F03C96163"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>child abuse is present;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H859A334ACE6F42DE853109DB7E17A32C"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing information to the public about prevention of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence within Indian Tribes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9926CD8740ED4FC9A5FC280557C44789"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assisting Indian Tribes' participation in, and attendance of, Federal and State consultations on domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, including consultations mandated by the Violence Against Women Act of 1994 (title IV of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/103/322">Public Law 103–322</external-xref>), the Victims of Crime Act of 1984 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20101">34 U.S.C. 20101 et seq.</external-xref>), or this title; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H358BC6E882244012981031CD89BA092E"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing shelter or supportive services to Tribal adult and youth victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, and their children and dependents.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E0E1C8CE5624BD893C96B4E7988F5B8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reallocation</header><text>If, at the end of the sixth month of any fiscal year for which sums are appropriated under section 303 and made available to carry out this section, a portion of the available amount has not been awarded to Tribal domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence coalitions for grants under this section because of the failure of such coalitions to meet the requirements for such grants, then the Secretary shall award such portion, in equal shares, to Tribal domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence coalitions that meet such requirements.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H7BC84B9109674373A881A0E633B074C8"><enum>14.</enum><header>Specialized services for caregivers and their children who have been exposed to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 312 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10412">42 U.S.C. 10412</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HF72ABB39C1E34E228F4BCC0AD9EB8008"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">abused parents and their children</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">parents, caregivers and children and youth who have been exposed to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C8B133CED1C419B8A74C6F7095591B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H919161685733416F9D9C52A22AEEEE1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H7B114FBA1D1447AF999407360507940D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence service programs and community-based programs to prevent future domestic violence by addressing, in an appropriate manner, the needs of children</quote> and inserting <quote>domestic violence, dating violence, family violence, and culturally specific community-based programs to serve children and youth</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H52C31199D8E84DB3B4CA66243995A9A2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, and to support the caregiving capacity of adult victims or other caregivers</quote> before the period; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H869F80EAA36545829BBDDACF6CF55BC0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>more than 2</quote> the first place it appears and inserting <quote>less than 3</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF34C2787CF54B5BBF76ECFDA8D97935"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H428E2BBE16434FB88128BEFFF43FA0A7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or State domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence services</quote> after <quote>local</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9853D229606C4D889D06DEA09C475F89"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>a culturally specific organization, </quote> after <quote>associations),</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C4AF113067244009CC40BAAC1EB86A8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>tribal organization</quote> and inserting <quote>Tribal organization</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11DCBC5225BB45F29344BFAC15D99657"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>adult and child</quote> after <quote>serving</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H65311DB197C14F23ADB04C009BA53EFE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and their children</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H98B96DC81AB64CBA94523ED79713EEC3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="H97E0F72155FD4EEC9BE601790B27FD14"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (1) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HABAB5C5758C94D44BCB016958EBD3569" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HAE0FE0CF73EC4A95A58C9F3141DAD57F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how the entity will prioritize the safety of, and confidentiality of information about adult and child victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence;</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D170361F4B14D09837807F1554731D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>developmentally appropriate and age-appropriate services, and culturally and linguistically appropriate services, to the victims and children; and</quote> and inserting <quote>trauma-informed and age, gender, developmentally, culturally, and linguistically appropriate services to children and youth, and their caregivers;</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE72EA7E7C0D448F5B27D6B2872300057"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>appropriate and relevant to the unique needs of children exposed to family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence.</quote> and inserting <quote>relevant to the unique needs of children and youth exposed to domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, including children and youth with disabilities and children from underserved populations, and address the parent's or caregiver's ongoing caregiving capacity; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCEB02E363F084F17A49DD5D6CB5FF10A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2B2B09886F794097A9309191D3B8EDC1" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H9549A14383204189822691A5A12F4288"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a description of prevention activities targeting child and youth victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C105AC978D44225A2C82F29AB3952DE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="H62AAEAEEFBF64DBF8086E0E395636F6D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>community-based program described in subsection (a)</quote> and inserting <quote>culturally specific, community-based program</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84B1D9E266514FEFB5A4F0749E756569"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(A)—</text><clause id="H01F81B720D4340B4A3EBBF4454095CC7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence and their children</quote> and inserting <quote>child and adult victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence, including children and youth with disabilities and children and youth from underserved populations</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HF7925F2DCF6C484FB33EDA85E7EC00B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or the health system</quote> before the semicolon; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA111E861C29E4840B312CE86C83C5BE1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H967804D54AB743B48D329F83B67B9ADF"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>mental</quote> and inserting <quote>behavioral</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HFD7F012BFEF14191A2FF7DA50498B1B3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>community-based organizations serving victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence or children exposed to family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence</quote> and inserting <quote>health, education, or other community-based organizations serving adult and child victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H40A60EFEC6B04AD1944929F73885E952"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by inserting <quote>health,</quote> after <quote>transportation,</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H81939068A5E140D0B160A82A0F838EE0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in subsection (e)—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE66CC7420EFC47A4B3112822C4408336"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>shall participate in an evaluation and</quote> after <quote>under this section</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05F1648F341B44E2987AF2A793B413C0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>contain an evaluation of</quote> and inserting <quote>information on</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H4BFDCEAF2CDA4CEDAF4A3998AF4D9819"><enum>15.</enum><header>National domestic violence hotline grant</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 313 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10413">42 U.S.C. 10413</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H9A73FBC427E9411BBDA71F6228F2E23C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H217AF7EFC6E74101B03C96A30BD3376C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>telephone</quote> and inserting <quote>telephonic and digital services</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7E940C86DCA4114B91CC78D1512E660"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>a hotline that provides</quote> and inserting <quote>a hotline and digital services that provide</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59BBD9D653404D909099599CD1AD8735"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting before the period at the end of the second sentence the following: <quote>, and who provide information about healthy relationships for adults and youth</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D295194C3344A25A31F8BA018F627FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="H755F7C61EE0C4E2EA45DD193EF38391C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="HB9452ACCA86A46E0A97617D492BB8FD3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>and digital services</quote> after <quote>hotline</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H0EE492DD6189434B8F4730A74FA67FF0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraphs (A) and (B), by striking <quote>hotline personnel</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>advocacy personnel</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H4CC512EDD8454869BC43ADA19810782E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>are able to effectively operate any technological systems used by the hotline</quote> and inserting <quote>or digital services are able to effectively operate any technological systems used by the hotline or provide any digital services, as applicable</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H4BCB08B4FB9C4DD3851B498B7EFE7E7F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraphs (D), (E), and (F), by inserting <quote>and digital services</quote> after <quote>hotline</quote> each place such term appears;</text></clause><clause id="HB80700E2136F49EFB4BF88826409C02F"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>persons with hearing impairments</quote> and inserting <quote>individuals who are Deaf or hard of hearing, those with speech-related disabilities, those with sensory disabilities (including those who are blind or low vision), and individuals with other disabilities, including training for hotline personnel to support such access</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H42AD18925ED44E9CA2D821E42D0A5B85"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G), by striking <quote>teen dating violence hotline</quote> and inserting <quote>youth dating violence hotline and other digital services and resources</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEDEF73873C446FB918BDC873BEB7CA9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by inserting <quote>, digital services,</quote> after <quote>hotline</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H788F54335E494ED28DAFD08E1E4CFFA3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (5) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2725F72E99664600B70B5E04A26DE1E9" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H24DD666711FB4AB8950A18B8AD4405D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text>demonstrate the ability to—</text><subparagraph id="H61DB1D40C42E4459AA17C66A3C76AA12"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide information and referrals for individuals contacting the hotline via telephonic or digital services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H034DEB7EE1D84D3EA94BCDA0D3FBA7E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>directly connect callers or assist digital services users in connecting to service providers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8AD2965E66149588C3BE3906DD2AD28"><enum>(C)</enum><text>employ crisis interventions meeting the standards of family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence providers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H494548BE62194F3088D783723C189250"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (6) through (8) as paragraphs (7) through (9), respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BA9641B5D7F48809D4543DB3BCBAC15"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (5) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H42BB70FBB7104A588676685794C4A44E" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H603ADE3E85A04885BEC35E3998993D12"><enum>(6)</enum><text>demonstrate the ability to provide information about healthy relationships for adults and youth;</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8C9B98202724F22B45D0B13EFA1349E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (e)—</text><subparagraph id="HCAA281E410A0448AB121B1C45711D72D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">and digital services</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="subsection" style="OLC">Hotline</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H254122E045E8440786743F22348A5922"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H168C7705D69B4EB89A14A0987C4EB3D7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>telephone hotline</quote> and inserting <quote>telephonic hotline and digital services</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H10DDA192FFBD484BAA99763B6DDE6F83"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>assistance to adult</quote> and inserting <quote>for the benefit of adult</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7EC4ED91D47A457B9FE83EE2FC77E730"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H0EAB397F467744F48C48B314A9C6AD2F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>and an internet service provider for the use of operating digital services</quote> before the semicolon;</text></clause><clause id="HD8419EDF46F04367AE2E3571E77FD827"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>, provide counseling and referral services for callers on a 24-hour-a-day basis, and directly connect callers</quote> and inserting <quote>and digital services contracts, provide counseling, healthy relationship information, and referral services for callers and digital services users, on a 24-hour-a-day basis, and directly connect callers and digital services users</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HF58203CFB48B4099982CF8BE791CC6A5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by inserting <quote>or digital services users</quote> after <quote>callers</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H1AA4CB265F494F2986837FEA44CDE9C8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by inserting <quote>and digital services</quote> after <quote>hotline</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="HE4CCB08F370F47C3BD833629A059E930"><enum>(v)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by striking <quote>underserved populations</quote> and inserting <quote>racial and ethnic minority groups, Tribal and underserved populations,</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H77F425A751E147969F86781EEC0CD87D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F), by striking <quote>teen dating violence hotline</quote> and inserting <quote>hotline or digital services</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFAF4F2D76414C59B21F63BA5DF10FB1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5AEB3DCF97884F08B0E227413E686A0E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H785EA2D2641D4E47A836BCA061DF8393"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Administration, evaluation, and monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of amounts made available to carry out this section, not more than 4 percent may be used by the Secretary for evaluation, monitoring, and other administrative costs under this section.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HF5DCCB0CAA6643BAA6F0CF42151AB0A6"><enum>16.</enum><header>National Indian domestic violence hotline grant</header><subsection id="HC575AB5861284276A77952BBBB12228C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this section is to increase the availability of information and assistance to Indian adult or youth victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence, family and household members of such victim, and individuals affected by such victimization by supporting a national, toll-free telephonic and digital hotline to provide services that are—</text><paragraph id="HD50B2F78804840C383E35656B5A85923"><enum>(1)</enum><text>informed of Federal Indian law and Tribal laws impacting Indian victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H93AF82CF903F42C386BE1EA7E0D2F707"><enum>(2)</enum><text>culturally appropriate to Indian adult and youth victims; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C61D304DB58449A99DD01666CD2763B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>developed in cooperation with victim services offered by Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H290B9577B57E4578A843C4EDD176DBB4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grant program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Family Violence Prevention and Services Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10401">42 U.S.C. 10401 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 313 the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC9185742D6D44A3291D0F97AF646A70E" style="OLC"><section id="H7BB1F8C77E3F4772899BC75E2EB7BB48"><enum>313A.</enum><header>National Indian domestic violence hotline grant</header><subsection id="H75ECD7C9364F494DA29CD00FC0841D29"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award a grant to a Tribal organization or private, non-profit entity to maintain the ongoing operation of a 24-hour, national, toll-free telephonic and digital services hotline to provide information and assistance to Indian adult and youth victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence, family and household members of such victims, and other individuals affected by such victimization.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFCD15D6927794F128BA679912158435E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Term</header><text>The Secretary shall award a grant under this section for a period of not more than 5 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD90275C7A4314094A0A7ACD3750212C9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conditions on payment</header><text>The provision of payments under a grant awarded under this section shall be subject to annual approval by the Secretary and subject to the availability of appropriations for each fiscal year to make the payments.</text></subsection><subsection id="H870E5D6AB5514CEFBE83E70195C432E4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall be a Tribal organization or a nonprofit private organization that focuses primarily on issues of domestic violence as it relates to American Indians and Alaska Natives, and submit an application to the Secretary that shall—</text><paragraph id="H7A8E65B326CD4761AC9C241574872D6B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>contain such agreements, assurances, and information, be in such form, and be submitted in such manner, as the Secretary shall prescribe;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFE6BC7B95804F008721A4BC93B9F7EA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include a complete description of the applicant’s plan for the operation of a national Indian domestic violence hotline and digital services, including descriptions of—</text><subparagraph id="H52042E700E264370B55126A073D0917B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the training program for advocacy personnel relating to the provision of culturally appropriate and legally accurate services, information, resources and referrals for Indian victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H40C92623FE1844A39CBBCF9F47672A4C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the training program for advocacy personnel, relating to technology requirements to ensure that all persons affiliated with the hotline and digital services are able to effectively operate any technological systems required to provide the necessary services used by the hotline;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC83E3684E7B141669D35D2783BB650DD"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the qualifications of the applicant and the hiring criteria and qualifications for advocacy personnel, to ensure that hotline advocates and other personnel have demonstrated knowledge of Indian legal, social, and cultural issues, to ensure that the unique needs of Indian callers and users of digital services are met;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71BAF9AC3CB04BD0A834E1929990E42F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the methods for the creation, maintenance, and updating of a resource database of culturally appropriate victim services and resources available from Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD4D95167E5642AF88899DD9EFA0CE69"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a plan for publicizing the availability of the services from the national Indian hotline to Indian victims of domestic violence and dating violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20FBF0D91B8E4FB8AF7C5A6D26FCE2FE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a plan for providing service to limited English proficiency callers, including service through hotline and digital services personnel who have limited English proficiency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H817A25A5640A4F9997C5D525F1E690F1"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a plan for facilitating access to the hotline and digital services by individuals who are Deaf or hard of hearing, individuals with speech-related disabilities, individuals with sensory disabilities (including those who are blind or low vision), and other individuals with disabilities, including training for hotline personnel to support such access; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H326A8C1873A943758CC2B6E4BEBEB4F4"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a plan for providing assistance and referrals to Indian youth victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, and for victims of dating violence who are minors, which may be carried out through a national Indian youth dating violence hotline, digital services, or other resources;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H92CA456978B343ADA5FCD7803F5E274F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>demonstrate recognized expertise providing services, including information on healthy relationships and referrals for Indian victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence and coordinating services with Indian Tribes or Tribal organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACE73673326E48B5920421BDC01326DA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>demonstrate support from Indian victim services programs, Tribal coalitions recognized by the Office on Violence Against Women and Tribal grantees under this title;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39C56F7E4E304B91B45CF5B3D90B757D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>demonstrate capacity and the expertise to maintain a domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence hotline, digital services and a comprehensive database of service providers from Indian Tribes or Tribal organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H529E58AF6C6C45729735C9DE201A45D6"><enum>(6)</enum><text>demonstrate compliance with nondisclosure requirements as described in section 306(c)(5) and following comprehensive quality assurance practices; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H44F1667C73734701AC1153C1D7D7933A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>contain such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H15C33347B8764D9AB685CCA9FBF0ECBE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Indian hotline activities</header><paragraph id="HD5666E82995D4D2ABEDD5134CABEB085"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An entity that receives a grant under this section shall use funds made available through the grant for the purpose described in subsection (a), consistent with paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B03BB71A3AB4CCB8886FF620E81938D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>In establishing and operating the hotline, the entity—</text><subparagraph id="H9ECB3B1C40A94FBCAB31DD65718E3E56"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall contract with a carrier for the use of a toll-free telephone line and an internet service provider for digital services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H929F1FEA1BE649ED9B078C477A2E96E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall employ, train (including providing technology training), and supervise personnel to answer incoming calls and digital services contacts, provide counseling, healthy relationship and referral services for Indian callers and digital services users, directly connect callers, and assist digital services users in connecting to service providers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB8EAE9ACFC941DE972E68293ABE72F6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall assemble and maintain a database of information relating to services for Indian victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence to which Indian callers or digital services users may be referred, including information on the availability of shelters and supportive services for victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE49A4BACD5FF4684BF9D7C8F692D627A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>shall widely publicize the hotline and digital services throughout Indian Tribes and communities, including to—</text><clause id="HE288B055D38E4A7EA9C1BEE38800B2FE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>national and regional member organizations of Indian Tribes;</text></clause><clause id="H74BBD59275E14ECABA0F25C405A53251"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Tribal domestic violence services programs; and</text></clause><clause id="H810B0033D3C44D56AD77107517A21031"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Tribal non-profit victim service providers;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H137BF752173940AB868DB84091280B69"><enum>(E)</enum><text>at the discretion of the hotline operator, may provide appropriate assistance and referrals for family and household members of Indian victims of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence, and Indians affected by the victimization described in subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6E140518B734E31BC09C8701A52AA74"><enum>(F)</enum><text>at the discretion of the hotline operator, may provide assistance, or referrals for counseling or intervention, for identified Indian perpetrators, including self-identified perpetrators, of family violence, domestic violence, or dating violence, but shall not be required to provide such assistance or referrals in any circumstance in which the hotline operator fears the safety of a victim may be impacted by an abuser or suspected abuser.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC31DD450521464DA5C885BB7D0006A4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports and evaluation</header><text>The entity receiving a grant under this section shall submit a report to the Secretary at such time as shall be reasonably required by the Secretary. Such report shall describe the activities that have been carried out with such grant funds, contain an evaluation of the effectiveness of such activities, and provide such additional information as the Secretary may reasonably require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H06790A296B4545D88FC4896C96B91382"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Administration, evaluation, and monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of amounts made available to carry out this section, not more than 4 percent may be used by the Secretary for evaluation, monitoring, and other administrative costs under this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H3BD6D4BABF6D4618942F1ACCBD1FC879"><enum>17.</enum><header>Domestic violence prevention enhancement and leadership</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 314 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10414">42 U.S.C. 10414</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><pagebreak></pagebreak><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6CF4DD1C723E4253A59D1D6A324FB299" style="OLC"><section id="H0C0820BDD8F940558DEB33ED26039ED3"><enum>314.</enum><header>Domestic violence prevention enhancement and leadership</header><subsection id="H4D0411826F8C4DDB95207C90958AF61E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose and description of grants</header><paragraph id="HFA20497E75BD4372A597CA601B155534"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purposes of this section are—</text><subparagraph id="HC29F40008FF1407A998C0E098B20D1FD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to continue efforts to build evidence about effective primary and secondary prevention practices, programs, and policies that reduce and end family violence, domestic violence, and dating violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE092487411644E6083E141DD2646394F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to build capacity at the State, Tribal, territorial, and local levels to meet the objectives described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11DBF6A1AC92408B8FF9E5767861ADA1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to advance primary and secondary prevention efforts related to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence nationally.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HB7C0F86B100D42BB84DA74C1BB6F0FE0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Description of grants</header><text>From the amounts appropriated under this section, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HEE64CD0BB09C4FF3B792C90EEBDC5B09"><enum>(A)</enum><text>acting through the Division of Violence Prevention of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, in consultation with the Director of the Division of Family Violence Prevention and Services of the Administration for Children and Families—</text><clause commented="no" id="H0E0E0D6C5C75421F82C4C3DAE9FFFF43"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide core grants under subsection (b)(1) to support primary and secondary prevention of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H7F712A1B20434DEFADC7A9AC26D348D4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enter into cooperative agreements under subsection (b)(2) with State, territorial, and Tribal domestic violence coalitions that are in partnerships with entities carrying out local and culturally specific programs, to test, evaluate, or, as appropriate, scale up innovative domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence primary and secondary prevention models, particularly those programs serving culturally specific or traditionally underserved populations; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA5C4D9910C984B04995B3638096E53BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>acting through the Family Violence Prevention and Services Program of the Administration for Children and Families, award grants under subsection (c) to enhance the capacity of communities and systems to engage in effective primary and secondary prevention efforts.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H136BE534A8CD41FC96A615670FF320C0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical assistance, evaluation, and monitoring</header><text>Of the amounts appropriated under this section for a fiscal year the Secretary may use—</text><subparagraph id="H64A6C14CEAE343849ED9C041449F4D53"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not more than 7 percent of the amounts for each fiscal year for evaluation, monitoring, and other administrative costs under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0CA76F7C14942FBA96B25430350E92F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not more than 3 percent of the amounts for each fiscal year for technical assistance under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H470687E4E80948479CFFA715F33438FA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants to State, territorial, and Tribal coalitions</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H469695A7EE5444D0875CECE25AE87D91"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grants to build primary and secondary prevention capacity of domestic violence coalitions</header><subparagraph id="H2405AE5CE5994DCD858A6AFE0DBE6FD4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide a core grant for each eligible State, territorial, and Tribal coalition. The Secretary shall provide such a grant to build organizational capacity and leadership for primary and secondary prevention of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, including work with other systems central to primary and secondary prevention at the local, State, territorial, and Tribal levels.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3C582E9BBCE458892E00164FCCCB975"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this paragraph, a State, territorial, or Tribal coalition shall be a State domestic violence coalition, territorial domestic violence coalition, or Tribal domestic violence coalition, respectively, that has not entered into a cooperative agreement under section 314 of this title (as in effect on the day before the date of enactment of the Family Violence Prevention and Services Improvement Act of 2023) or under paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5F40C574C4C41B9802170ECA445E898"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Application</header><text>Each coalition seeking a grant under this paragraph shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. The application submitted by the coalition for the grant shall provide documentation of the coalition’s primary prevention work, satisfactory to the Secretary, demonstrating that the coalition—</text><clause id="H6EFEC30311BB4DF0AEB78F858A1AD913"><enum>(i)</enum><text>meets all of the applicable requirements of this paragraph; and</text></clause><clause id="HFD14A70A661642248CADF647BAFA7E2B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrates the ability to conduct appropriately the primary and secondary prevention activities described in this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H01725D1B7CCC431984913B9187080666"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Allotment of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the amounts made available to carry out this paragraph, the Secretary shall allot an equal share to each qualified entity receiving funds under section 311 or section 311A to carry out evidence-informed prevention activities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB4C71B9BDB8A422BAA6313637A267D04"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A coalition that receives a grant under this paragraph—</text><clause id="HB0BE4B9B2FE54A09A70D32390DE3CD7E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall use the grant funds to—</text><subclause id="HC66EA5E211224C4A866F486985EA1AEB"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">build the coalition's organizational capacity and enhance its State or Tribal leadership to advance evidence-informed primary and secondary prevention of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence;</text></subclause><subclause id="HDD0722C8D9A848FE9CDCF8D118141C46"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide primary and secondary prevention-focused training, technical assistance, peer learning opportunities, and other support to local domestic violence programs and other community-based and culturally specific programs working to address domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence;</text></subclause><subclause id="H82013AD572A74EFEB734361B478ECF92"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide training and advocacy to other State, Tribal, and local public and private systems on how to prevent domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence, and help victims, including through health services, housing and shelter services, early childhood programs, economic support programs, schools, child welfare, workforce development, community-based programs primarily serving racial and ethnic minority groups, community-based programs serving Deaf individuals and individuals with disabilities, community-based programs primarily serving other underserved populations, faith-based programs, and youth programs; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD347C410927140449CA1D2D77AB96B80"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support dissemination of primary and secondary prevention strategies and approaches throughout the State, territorial, or Tribal communities; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HF023AD84986D4E6B898D91F62472AD30"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may use the grant funds to provide subgrants to local programs to support the dissemination of primary and secondary prevention programs or initiatives.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H063B427B0DF14E439A3E929B5B6378E6"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Each coalition receiving a grant under this paragraph shall submit a report to the Secretary at such time as the Secretary requires. Such report shall describe the activities that have been carried out with such grant funds and the effectiveness of such activities, and provide such additional information as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BF07F4A4CF4496484918AC0E6B3686D"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Federal activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may use a portion of the funds provided under this paragraph to provide primary and secondary prevention-focused training, technical assistance, and other support to coalitions described in subparagraph (B) or State or local entities that are in partnerships with such coalitions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB03365E8E8784BC3AE9972E43F90F7AF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cooperative agreement for implementation and evaluation of primary and secondary prevention strategies</header><subparagraph id="H051BDB2CFBB64B14BEDF63B8AFD8EE59"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall enter into cooperative agreements with qualified State, territorial, and Tribal domestic violence coalitions that are in partnerships with entities carrying out local and culturally specific programs, to test, evaluate, or, as appropriate, scale up innovative domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence primary and secondary prevention strategies and models, particularly those serving culturally specific or traditionally underserved populations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H96C7EB42392C49BBB7393F2B99E785AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Qualification</header><text>To be qualified to enter into a cooperative agreement under subsection (a)(2)(A)(ii), an organization shall be a State, territorial, or Tribal domestic violence coalition and include representatives of pertinent sectors of the local community, which may include—</text><clause id="H8791E3F7451E44669501C6238937CB25"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">health care providers (including mental health providers and substance use disorder treatment providers) and Tribal, State, or local health departments;</text></clause><clause id="H242E9F21C2B147F7BE7416A8D918127D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the education community;</text></clause><clause id="H8E07AF280DBC454190BC94C5A8551DD0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a faith-based community;</text></clause><clause id="H78FA8D6E81B647C68E5F08EB0097E8E5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the juvenile justice system;</text></clause><clause id="HE1231D07830C4CF8AC4E5DBD17245A7D"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence service program advocates;</text></clause><clause id="H4003751EA4294A158F416A946EDBF51C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>public human service entities;</text></clause><clause id="H803B5F10724E498A9DA186B30EABA21B"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>business and civic leaders;</text></clause><clause id="HB2768EF0F9D74A908D244A4B2E4CCD7B"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>child and youth-serving organizations;</text></clause><clause id="H239AF2F2CCBC4D63A808FF902671CB90"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>community-based organizations whose primary purpose is to provide culturally appropriate services to underserved populations, including racial and ethnic minority communities; and</text></clause><clause id="HC5DFD63D197C4EABADCAF92962970732"><enum>(x)</enum><text>other pertinent sectors.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5EC08DF45DA40E0B6F6C20CB6C8A94E"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Term</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into a cooperative agreement under this paragraph for a period of not more than 5 fiscal years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7841406F7F154E01A227C404F7BA9A59"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Conditions on payment</header><text>The provision of payments under a cooperative agreement under this paragraph shall be subject to—</text><clause id="H03D3626A041F4C3CAFAD2C8DDBAB841C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>annual approval by the Secretary; and</text></clause><clause id="H41D91DFC1E3D421C93046C42F837BADB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the availability of appropriations for each fiscal year to make the payments.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB01D356591D9401FADE560206800CE8C"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>An organization that desires to enter into a cooperative agreement under this paragraph shall submit to the Secretary an application, in such form and in such manner as the Secretary shall require, that—</text><clause id="H6464CC7AF5734D55B96DDE56A83BF853"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies models and strategies to be tested and partner organizations who will be implementing programs to prevent domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence;</text></clause><clause id="H27FA27B30EF64BF5BCA23D41E27C96BF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>demonstrates that the applicant has developed effective and collaborative relationships with diverse communities, including with organizations primarily serving racial and ethnic minority populations or other underserved populations;</text></clause><clause id="HE9772752D173416886510B3551D6D444"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifies other partners and sectors who will be engaged to meet the primary and secondary prevention goals;</text></clause><clause id="HFAB432DD73C3445992D04D72B6B5021A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes a description of the expected outcomes from the primary and secondary prevention activities and how the strategy is expected to achieve those outcomes;</text></clause><clause id="H00AC727C64DA4A5595BC1838C58D9F0D"><enum>(v)</enum><text>describes the method to be used for identification and selection of project staff and a project evaluator;</text></clause><clause id="H8F469450D9F4471EA90DB7F68ADF9381"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>describes the method to be used for identification and selection of a project council consisting of representatives of the community sectors listed in subparagraph (B);</text></clause><clause id="H1E209E45B3574ECCAA9B0F93F1BFFE86"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrates that the applicant has the capacity to carry out collaborative community initiatives to prevent domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence;</text></clause><clause id="HD76D37F9D0E04F84BC29D493C49A23B1"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describes the applicant’s plans to evaluate the models and strategies it intends to implement, including demonstrating that the methods selected are rigorous;</text></clause><clause id="H0F56EA5F06FD46F9A7002DD07A685EF4"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">describes the applicant’s existing capacity to collect and analyze data to monitor performance and support evaluation and other evidence-building activities or how they will use the grant to develop such capacity; and</text></clause><clause id="HE5E37314633C451186276E20429221D5"><enum>(x)</enum><text>contains such other information, agreements, and assurances as the Secretary may require.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF3FC0217DBD4B8B85DB46944A633EAC"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Geographic dispersion</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into cooperative agreements under this paragraph with organizations in States, territories, and Tribes geographically dispersed throughout the Nation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB419876313FF4C5FA426B34670AC5D06"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><clause id="H3517643D433C4F708C9D8FBFEC7E63CF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An organization that enters into a cooperative agreement under this paragraph shall use the funds made available through the agreement to establish, operate, and maintain implementation and evaluation of coordinated community response to reduce risk factors for domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence perpetration and enhance protective factors to promote positive development and healthy relationships and communities.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H7123E359D0A74EECA17BF27C52A94348"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Evaluation, monitoring, administration, and technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may use a portion of the funds provided under this paragraph for evaluation, monitoring, administration, and technical assistance described in subsection (a)(3) with respect to the prevention projects. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B4F9E96DC454150A0194D488EEE9959"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In establishing and operating a project under this paragraph, an organization shall—</text><clause id="H677BAC5F16E448759BBA5990B3EADB7C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">utilize evidence-informed primary and secondary prevention project planning;</text></clause><clause id="H1DD9B7ACE7BB44B892CCECC58CA5DDC4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>recognize and address the needs of underserved populations, including racial and ethnic minority groups, and individuals with disabilities;</text></clause><clause id="H725B24728589488A9E13B6FE40A75F27"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>use not less than 30 percent or more than 50 percent of awarded funds to subcontract with local domestic violence programs or other community-based programs to develop and implement such projects;</text></clause><clause id="H0E4B7FD2B4B843A5B9A1193968FEF014"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in the case of a new grantee, use the funds for up to 1 year for planning and capacity building without subcontracting as described in clause (iii); and</text></clause><clause id="H2D2DA58FD3F4438494EFB6E7E8A7F184"><enum>(v)</enum><text>use up to 8 percent of the funds awarded under this paragraph to procure technical assistance from a list of providers approved by the Secretary and peer-to-peer technical assistance from other grantees under this paragraph.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DDF4B4EE3EA44E0A6325550F74C253C"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Each organization entering into a cooperative agreement under this paragraph shall submit a report to the Secretary at such time as shall be reasonably required by the Secretary. Such report shall describe activities that have been carried out with the funds made available through the agreement and the effectiveness of such activities, and provide such additional information as the Secretary may reasonably require. The Secretary shall make the evaluations received under this subparagraph publicly available on the Department of Health and Human Services internet website, and shall submit such reports to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Education and Labor of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8AB6CD0E5A954051A804775FBA4712D3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants To expand community-Based prevention</header><paragraph id="H17959305997A468086A095885980A5C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a grant program to expand the capacity of communities and systems to engage in effective primary and secondary prevention efforts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E1F86FD5E664476BE4160A2E8A8887C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Secretary may award grants to eligible entities through the program established under paragraph (1) for periods of not more than 4 years. If the Secretary determines that an entity has received such a grant and been successful in meeting the objectives of the grant application so submitted, the Secretary may renew the grant for 1 additional period of not more than 4 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3A121990F8B49489D3E1472C4AA6CFE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this subsection, an entity shall—</text><subparagraph id="H7C88403AD3FB420A87DC3915CD6DF867"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be a private nonprofit, nongovernmental organization (which may include faith-based and charitable organizations) or a Tribal organization that is—</text><clause id="H5699980D36234EBCAE3FF24E9178462B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a community-based organization whose primary purpose is providing culturally specific services to racial and ethnic minority groups or other underserved populations; </text></clause><clause id="HD997C67025DE4BD9B7841386ADEDC43C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a community-based organization with a program focused on serving youth or serving children and their parents or caregivers; or </text></clause><clause id="H91E9DCA0E0D4431987E19580EAD64982"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a community-based organization that offers legal services to help victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence and that works to serve the needs of racial or ethnic minority groups, other underserved populations, youth, or children and their parents or caregivers; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5874A4F43131448690E5178D692C45BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have a demonstrated record of serving victims of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence, or demonstrate a partnership with another organization that has such a record.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D354F7A782E482E8F46B91C0BA95447"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An entity seeking a grant under this subsection shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require, including—</text><subparagraph id="H39D1789C1EE446DC901925E4BE4516D9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how the entity will develop, expand, or replicate evidence-informed primary and secondary prevention strategies and approaches in their communities, including culturally and linguistically appropriate primary and secondary prevention programming;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDCC27A683C5846A79C5E40A6FB7BF49B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>documents that the entity meets all of the applicable requirements set forth in this subsection; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB36DE3DD61DA40D38013F26D693A54BB"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrates the ability to conduct appropriately the primary and secondary prevention activities described in this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CF995CDD6DB4511B1A8C86DA4715D5D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An entity that receives a grant under this subsection shall use the grant funds to—</text><subparagraph id="HE227992B4AA944F5B8BC323B457DEB64"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">build their organizational capacity and enhance their leadership of the organization within the community to promote community engagement in and advancement of evidence-informed primary and secondary prevention of domestic violence, dating violence, or family violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB800802983A4EC59887F6E177492664"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote strategic primary and secondary prevention partnership development, including between any of domestic violence programs and health programs, early childhood programs, economic support programs, schools, child welfare programs, workforce development, culturally specific community-based organizations, faith-based programs, community-based organizations serving Deaf individuals and individuals with disabilities, and youth programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H439F2DF3D7A24139A4B16D9BAFA50A1A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support dissemination of primary and secondary prevention strategies and approaches to States, territories, Tribal organizations, and Tribes; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H07569500B9CD43A7B4BB933F800FEBE0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>use up to 5 percent of funds awarded under this subsection to procure technical assistance from a list of providers approved by the Secretary, from peer-to-peer technical assistance from other grantees under this section, or from both.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B203F93CBD9401F959B2721B010A4E9"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Technical assistance, evaluation, and monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may use a portion of the funds provided under this subsection for evaluation, monitoring, administration, and technical assistance with respect to the prevention projects.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B4EBDBE29BC41F9ADAE7284DE472237"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Reports and evaluation</header><text>Each entity receiving a grant under this subsection shall submit a report to the Secretary at such time as shall be reasonably required by the Secretary. Such report shall describe the activities that have been carried out with such grant funds, contain an evaluation of the effectiveness of such activities, and provide such additional information as the Secretary may reasonably require.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HC12A1712378A44C9A47DBA4E7400DB2F"><enum>18.</enum><header>Additional grant programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Family Violence Prevention and Services Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/10401">42 U.S.C. 10401 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H540441AB36A6477E910AF41D7D3BEFD5" style="OLC"><section id="HED2DEA3375B746FA9896B1B8CA1BA0B6"><enum>315.</enum><header>Grants for underserved populations</header><subsection id="HB796E34BED2948F7B5D11DD735B126D8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the purpose of this section to provide grants to assist communities in mobilizing and organizing resources in support of effective and sustainable programs that will prevent and address domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence experienced by underserved populations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9A5D414F9D5245F8B41BA32FA76082D1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority To award grants</header><text>The Secretary, acting through the Director of the Division of Family Violence Prevention and Services, shall award capacity building, implementation, and evaluation grants to eligible entities to assist in developing, implementing, and evaluating culturally and linguistically appropriate, community-driven strategies to prevent and address domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence in underserved populations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6FD950CD2C23486DBFB75D242C7DAEBB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall—</text><paragraph id="H0312FDE7967F472E8292C35CCB080378"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to the programs under subsections (d) and (e), be—</text><subparagraph id="H8D986FED68D140D78653DE2894F7BA3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a population specific organization that has demonstrated experience and expertise in providing population specific services in the relevant underserved communities, or a population specific organization working in partnership with a victim service provider or domestic violence or sexual assault coalition; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2B80F47BCDF74140B4E946D8B54C4601"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a victim service provider offering population-specific services for a specific underserved population; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H99077DBC3E58442EBF2998214528AA2A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to the program under subsection (f), be an eligible entity described in paragraph (1) that is working in collaboration with an entity specializing in evaluation with documented experience working with targeted underserved populations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2C7B652613A04BF4A464C17D146B3B55"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Capacity building grants</header><paragraph id="HBCD8F309B49E4C2484BB890BE01974CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities to support the capacity building, planning, and development of programs for underserved communities that utilize community-driven intervention and prevention strategies that address the barriers to domestic violence services, raise awareness of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence and promote community engagement in the prevention of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence in targeted underserved populations. Such grants may be used to—</text><subparagraph id="H51F54D3FBE38449095D7F628D229FED9"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3480D502166742F0B20CAE17C3BB7585"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expand the collaboration with community partners who can provide appropriate assistance to the targeted underserved populations that are represented by the eligible entity through the identification of additional partners, particularly among targeted underserved communities; and</text></clause><clause id="HA6943B04C9F2495D8AF2B6310815C6C9" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>establish linkages with national, State, Tribal, or local public and private partners, which may include community health workers, advocacy organizations, and policy organizations;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E92586A448646D99AD17CF231B69CDE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish community working groups;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9727FBB6954414489D76474D95C15EE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>conduct a needs assessment of targeted underserved populations to determine the barriers to access and factors contributing to such barriers, using input from targeted underserved communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8737B2E5D4594DC6B16C442B5D061652"><enum>(D)</enum><text>participate in training and technical assistance sponsored by the Family Violence Prevention and Services program for program development, implementation, evaluation, and other programmatic issues;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2EDDE286F8F485D896F0F05D5629B7A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>use up to 5 percent of funds awarded under this subsection to procure technical assistance from a list of providers approved by the Family Violence Prevention and Services program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32A82ECD6701445FA8972B19DB0006D8"><enum>(F)</enum><text>identify promising intervention and prevention strategies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D7E1AC492844C61AE4D48029874A606"><enum>(G)</enum><text>develop a plan with the input of targeted underserved communities that includes strategies for—</text><clause id="HE38DA870B5964423BFFC9EA3B060193B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>implementing intervention and prevention strategies that have the greatest potential for addressing the barriers to accessing services, raising awareness of domestic violence, and promoting community engagement in the prevention of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence within targeted underserved populations;</text></clause><clause id="H9A820A4B5AC345B6BBE6D6D982F39BC5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identifying other sources of revenue and integrating current and proposed funding sources to ensure long-term sustainability of the program; and</text></clause><clause id="H0CCB6AEF76824C8384E5F0A762E60927"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conducting performance measurement processes, including collecting data and measuring progress toward addressing domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence or raising awareness of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence in targeted underserved populations; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85AE110BA039487BAF13C96483F89266"><enum>(H)</enum><text>conduct an evaluation of the planning and development activities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2FC52CA130E498D9C2C655F6F9BAE9B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The period during which payments may be made under a grant under paragraph (1) shall not exceed 4 years, except where the Secretary determines that extraordinary circumstances exist.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF7DE7B8A307841DF9841E95D59BC4246"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Implementation grants</header><paragraph id="H1E5B9817151F448987B1771445F36B13"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities that have received a planning grant under subsection (d) or who already have demonstrated experience and expertise in providing population specific services in the relevant underserved communities to enable such entities to—</text><subparagraph id="HEC7224E8FA4244448E08771A7DB80278"><enum>(A)</enum><text>implement a plan including intervention services or prevention strategies to address the identified barrier or awareness issue or initiate the community engagement strategy for targeted underserved populations, in an effective and timely manner;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H44CB1C9F06BE46E7B1D3C8AB4EE52F26"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">design and implement a plan to evaluate the program, including collecting data appropriate for monitoring performance of the program carried out under the grant;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5ACEC5461744CD897C848142DB9B5A2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>analyze data consistent with the evaluation design, including collaborating with academic or other appropriate institutions for such analysis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32CA37240D3343F580BD5E4A8544C52C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>participate in training for the purpose of informing and educating other entities regarding the experiences and lessons learned from the project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3907129C7EA3400FA5920FC3551BBDAA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>collaborate with appropriate partners to disseminate information gained from the project for the benefit of other domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32408764C87E415BB7CAF6179CD85932"><enum>(F)</enum><text>establish mechanisms with other public or private groups to maintain financial support for the program after the grant terminates;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD6947EF11A94CD1A1081343669849E2"><enum>(G)</enum><text>develop policy initiatives for systems change to address the barriers or awareness issue;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7FE9E37E16E49668141BBE827329067"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and implement community engagement strategies; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9E23805B0CF48B391BD82FC8679D1B1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>maintain relationships with local partners and continue to develop new relationships with national and State partners; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BF820D15CA04711B3175C994AD3AF34"><enum>(J)</enum><text>use up to 5 percent of funds awarded under this subsection to procure technical assistance from a list of providers approved by the Family Violence Prevention and Services program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5601D24F072349B7BE574775C85862D5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants under this subsection for 4-year periods.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA01E1F60105047CABB100C714C593209"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Evaluation grants</header><paragraph id="H5D876005F89D424D9A2FA40F15A3953C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may award grants to eligible entities that have received an implementation grant under subsection (e) and that require additional assistance for the purpose of executing the proposed evaluation design, including developing the design, collecting and analyzing data (including process and outcome measures), and disseminating findings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FB9A1509BA9470A8A4848AFC27F9079"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this subsection, the Secretary shall give priority to—</text><subparagraph id="H563EDA62BADC4646A9DECB2EFA44F452"><enum>(A)</enum><text>entities that in previous funding cycles—</text><clause commented="no" id="H55E9B1E35C844D48B659D5C2E260F41A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have received a grant under subsection (d); or</text></clause><clause id="HA28F5818750B45AEB420AE6D3CDDDCF2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>established population specific organizations that have demonstrated experience and expertise in providing population-specific services in the relevant underserved communities programs; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4622D727A23F4967AA151A923E48F1EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>entities that incorporate best practices or build on successful models in their action plan, including the use of community advocates.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7FC0BDA30B247A3B7A04AF77C75C3A6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>The period during which payments may be made under a grant under paragraph (1) shall not exceed 4 years, except where the Secretary determines that extraordinary circumstances exist.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44554F9B5528442AA2FE04C9E0649357"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Supplement, not supplant</header><text>Funds provided under this section shall be used to supplement and not supplant other Federal, State, and local public funds expended to provide services and activities that promote the purposes of this title.</text></subsection><subsection id="H28CE1FD360734AE5B024AE6B8D17F52F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Technical assistance, evaluation, and monitoring</header><paragraph id="H4580FCEFBA084262B05CD0335101D7FA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Of the funds appropriated under this section for each fiscal year—</text><subparagraph id="H977E472FCA7944A69569F1CD3081AE3A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>up to 5 percent may be used by the Secretary for evaluation, monitoring, and other administrative costs under this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE02C8CED2EB242BB8E7E81A9D8D4E0D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>up to 3 percent may be used by the Secretary for technical assistance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H469DA8749389446AA52C4D439D04D69C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Technical assistance provided by grantees</header><text>The Secretary shall enable grantees to share best practices, evaluation results, and reports using the internet, conferences, and other pertinent information regarding the projects funded by this section, including the outreach efforts of the Family Violence Prevention and Services program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E7489B756C54B31BA916567EB3D1F4F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reports and evaluation</header><text>Each entity receiving funds under this section shall file a performance report at such times as requested by the Secretary describing the activities that have been carried out with such grant funds and providing such additional information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4F187CC775474F04869BAA2620EF7233"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Administrative burdens</header><text>The Secretary shall make every effort to minimize duplicative or unnecessary administrative burdens on the grantees.</text></subsection></section><section id="HBD65F1BCD16944DABB94C469E5728BE7"><enum>316.</enum><header>Grants to enhance culturally specific services for racial and ethnic minority populations</header><subsection id="HF38BA4717C564D2B848C9406C6337F88"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a grant program to establish or enhance culturally specific services for victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence from racial and ethnic minority populations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H782E915B6859400192391D72A78004F2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><paragraph id="H750891F7C4004E249735BA7E29F70CA8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The purposes of the grant program under this section are to—</text><subparagraph id="HE14AF5D4E0A64999AFEA3D9651365D77"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and support innovative culturally specific community-based programs to enhance access to shelter services or supportive services to further the purposes of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence intervention and prevention for all victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence from racial and ethnic minority populations who face obstacles to using more traditional services and resources;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAFA58F337AE464485FDF073F3643D68"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strengthen the capacity and further the leadership development of individuals in racial and ethnic minority populations to address domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence in their communities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27A80BF4ABC74933BC3F35E6668C824F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote strategic partnership development and collaboration, including with health systems, early childhood programs, economic support programs, schools, child welfare, workforce development, domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence programs, other community-based programs, community-based organizations serving individuals with disabilities, faith-based programs, and youth programs, in order to further a public health approach to addressing domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5958650327924F478E3C18DA3AE2648C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="HBA6BDC7FB96A4732B9CF91594F55FDA0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants to programs based in the targeted community to establish or enhance domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence intervention and prevention efforts that address distinctive culturally specific responses to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence in racial and ethnic minority populations.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD9851D1F9804F48B37754B315B4006D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>New programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the Secretary may award initial planning and capacity building grants to eligible entities that are establishing new programs in order to support the planning and development of culturally specific programs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23FA23A9CE704D839951A9E30963F4D1"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Competitive basis</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that grants are awarded, to the extent practical, only on a competitive basis, and that a grant is awarded for a proposal only if the proposal has been recommended for such an award through a process of peer review.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H716CC72FE5D8445A9AA9DCDBDB1DFDF0"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Up to 5 percent of funds appropriated under this section for a fiscal year shall be available for technical assistance to be used by the grantees to access training and technical assistance from organizations that have entered into a cooperative agreement with the Director to provide training and technical assistance regarding the provision of effective culturally specific, community-based services for racial and ethnic minority populations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC82CD41024CC40BB9550F977810303CB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical assistance and training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall enter into cooperative agreements or contracts with organizations having a demonstrated expertise in and whose primary purpose is addressing the development and provision of culturally specific, accessible, community-based services to victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence from the targeted populations to provide training and technical assistance for grantees.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBCE3C6C03B7C4F13866DCDC81418972A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible for a grant under this section, an entity shall—</text><paragraph id="H9BF4DBBC4CA34D0BB0C0C0AABF19E78F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be a private nonprofit, nongovernmental organization that is—</text><subparagraph id="H5CFBA1EE0CF748E4B3E00F7E3F690453"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a community-based organization whose primary purpose is providing culturally specific services to victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence from racial and ethnic minority populations; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H291D2979A3A548888854C21F9EE46A01"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a community-based organization whose primary purpose is providing culturally specific services to individuals from racial and ethnic minority populations that can partner with an organization having demonstrated expertise in serving victims of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B2046B850A742398E40D8942BDFA877"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have a board of directors and staffing with demonstrated expertise in serving racial and ethnic minority populations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5BE3581F1D93436EB928BFA8941D0867"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cultural responsiveness of services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that information and services provided pursuant to this section are provided in the language, educational, and cultural context that is most appropriate for the individuals for whom the information and services are intended, and that information is made available in accessible formats as appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0FBD7C4D8B4A43C1BBE9CE0FF24AB197"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant period</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants for a 4-year period, with a possible extension of another 2 years to further implement the projects under the grant.</text></subsection><subsection id="H40B769E2566145A695F2CDFDF829F8A6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Nonexclusivity</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be interpreted to exclude linguistically and culturally specific community-based entities from applying for other sources of funding available under this title.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD6E67896B1054954B83BA710F5F7296F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Each entity receiving funds under this section shall file a performance report at such times as requested by the Secretary describing the activities that have been carried out with such grant funds and providing such additional information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9523975B1F2D4567A61977696F133BE0"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Administration, evaluation, and monitoring</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of amounts made available to carry out this section, not more than 4 percent may be used by the Secretary for evaluation, monitoring, and other administrative costs under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H151D5098709E499EA2FCC823A05595F8"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to allow a grantee to limit services to victims of domestic violence, dating, violence, or family violence on the basis of race or ethnicity.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H11AD6367B9E243D4A8D7AA1AB118D05D"><enum>19.</enum><header>Analysis of Federal support for financial stability among survivors of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study and issue a report that includes—</text><paragraph id="HB95B87C8B5634EF7A5474F27D7040EC5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a review of what is known about the number of survivors of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB47402C7B7BE49F389DD20A40EEE61A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>statistical data, where available, for recent fiscal years, on the number of survivors described in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H67840D93792E4041B375AA39B6E0E62A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the key Federal programs providing survivors described in paragraph (1) with financial and non-financial support;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2460FB8A211F45B4ACBBDD2676C97289"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an analysis of the gaps in current Federal programs, in terms of benefit adequacy and benefit coverage for the population of survivors described in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H816ABF1B25D94D45AADAEE87ABAF55D2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a demographic analysis of the distribution of the gaps described in paragraph (4), for groups including racial and ethnic minorities, individuals with disabilities, tribal populations, and individuals who are geographically isolated;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD49FFAA3CF8475E86718715DAB4CF51"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review of challenges that could affect program utilization by the population of survivors described in paragraph (1); </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47E654378EC5416E88883B52AE42F9E5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>an indication of the extent to which Federal agencies or departments currently administering programs described in paragraph (3) have taken steps to ensure that survivors of domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence have access to programs that will support their financial stability; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14BF083C24BD4824941E3A307CE112F8"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information on the outreach efforts conducted pursuant to section 308 on outreach to racial and ethnic minorities, individuals with disabilities, tribal populations, and individuals who are geographically isolated, to determine ways—</text><subparagraph id="H3F3C4E61416A40D0A9990A5730C3E4EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to increase the availability of services relating to domestic violence, dating violence, and family violence for such groups; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EE095A1BC3D4750A30444DC669F37F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to ensure access to such services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

