<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC47B115F351D4DBBBC0AEF2793279E97" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1076 IH: Preventing the Financing of Illegal Synthetic Drugs Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1076</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Comptroller General of the United States to carry out a study on the trafficking into the United States of synthetic drugs, and related illicit finance, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H6B45B07140D94DAC96AA5027AF64D9D9" style="OLC">
<section id="H98258A07E5AF4727AFDBDC81EDDAB900" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preventing the Financing of Illegal Synthetic Drugs Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H3E31D60677CB4E94966E3FB9DA641DD8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H5B8E6F950F2C400F9AB26FD776CA09CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the Center for Disease Control and Prevention, over 107,000 people in the United States died from drug overdoses or drug poisonings in the 12-month period ending January 2022, with 67 percent of those deaths involving synthetic opioids like fentanyl.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H68582852529A46DAAB0DE3D13CFFEA9E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the United National Office of Drugs and Crime (UNODC) in its <quote>Synthetic Drug Strategy 2021–2025</quote>, the number of synthetic drugs, also called New Psychoactive Substances, has increased 631 percent since 2009, with traffickers introducing an average of 80 new substances to the illicit drug market each year from 2009–2019.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H86909C248859450B9543D70CAFD57660"><enum>(3)</enum><text>In October 2022, F. Michael McDaniel, director of the Houston High Intensity Drug Trafficking Areas (HITDA) program testified in Congress that one kilogram of fentanyl can produce one million counterfeit pills containing one milligram of fentanyl, saying, <quote>Currently in Houston, Texas, you can buy a kilogram of fentanyl for an average price of $25,000 to $30,000. This same kilogram of fentanyl in Culiacán (Mexico) could be purchased at an average price of $13,500. Currently, the price of a fentanyl pill in Houston ranges from $6 to $65. Therefore, an illicit investment of $30,000 or less could result in a return of $6 to $32.5 million.</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEE3E2C3BBAB54C0888D6014F6AF082C7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to Celina B. Realuyo, Adjunct Professor, The George Washington University Elliott School of International Affairs, in March 2022 Congressional testimony, <quote>Financing is essential to support and sustain the command and control, personnel, arms, communications, logistics and operations of organized crime groups. For this reason, following the money trail and depriving criminals of illicit financial flows can disrupt and disable these networks.</quote>.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H244A99BB77104B0EA4EF888402B7C442"><enum>3.</enum><header>GAO study on synthetic drugs trafficking</header>
<subsection id="H00789B67610A455B9AB4752D09F6BB27"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall carry out a study on illicit financing in connection with the trafficking of synthetic drugs, including fentanyl and methamphetamine, fentanyl- and methamphetamine-related substances, Captagon, and fentanyl and methamphetamine precursors, including—</text> <paragraph id="HFB6AB5E418994E5988493762426E2C87"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the business of the trafficking of synthetic drugs and related illicit finance, such as the participation of transnational criminal organizations and terror syndicates and their notable trafficking corridors, including source and transit countries;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H622E761B88554E02BA7B4E6590B14825"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the business models used by these transnational criminal organizations, including U.S. domestic and foreign activities for precursor purchase or production, movement along the supply chain, manufacture of the completed product, marketing, distribution, sales, and return of proceeds;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H708A68E6A7114A47A101A31F826B4C1F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the overlap of the business model of human trafficking and the trafficking of synthetic drugs and related illicit finance;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBDAE70A373A045A398574649E09BC72D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the use of online illicit drug markets and the use of social media for the marketing, sale, and payment for synthetic drugs;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8B0C83F61802486594F10A3C44F59CAC"><enum>(5)</enum><text>financial methods used by such transnational criminal organizations, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1BBA443FA34E4049AE2F55F03B8593D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>payment;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA7A4E14C7FE342099E28D67086109B85"><enum>(B)</enum><text>money laundering; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HFBE3C737693B45708D153D3C964DFABC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>repatriation of proceeds;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H056205A8A56F4B48831AFFE76CD99736"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the use of social media applications like Snap Chat, Discord, and Facebook and payment applications like CashApp to facilitate financial transactions for synthetic drug trafficking, especially among young people; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2193E13CE8E144A8A9F23A1A5C86902A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>U.S. Government activities to combat illicit finance related to the trafficking of synthetic drugs, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HFD81A909739E4BA3B5DB41F56DD3DE55"><enum>(A)</enum><text>interagency collaboration, including personnel detailed to other agencies to support the effort to combat synthetic drugs trafficking and related illicit finance;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA165DED809294BFC8AFC368D542024B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>intergovernmental collaboration;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H26D86BCB574844D096F44845BEFFD6DD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>intersectoral collaboration with the private sector, including the business and non-governmental communities; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB8E2A1B792D841588EC84CC47442CE15"><enum>(D)</enum><text> identified gaps or resource deficiencies in combating the trafficking of synthetic drugs and related illicit finance in the coordination and collaboration activities described in subparagraphs (A) through (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H465DF2040E2447939D2F821223B3E133"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the end of the 1-year period beginning on the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall issue a report to the Congress containing all findings and determinations made in carrying out the study required under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


