<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H91939B8D972C47B0A58492DBC910C2E9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2574 IH: EMS Counts Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2574</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230410">April 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Labor to revise the Standard Occupational Classification System to accurately count the number of emergency medical services practitioners in the United States.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7AC261B4A63B427F8E99C46C3FAA969A" style="OLC"><section id="H2A28C50DD6974F0DB99C9FBA4048EA35" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>EMS Counts Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H91F8F80910E84FE4962CA69CF3C3CD94"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H8FA9956A74D544ADA601500F03C13A8B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Emergency Medical Services (in this Act referred to as <quote>EMS</quote>) personnel provide a critical role in emergency response. EMS consists of a diverse group of health care practitioners, such as paramedics, emergency medical technicians (in this Act referred to as <quote>EMTs</quote>), dual-role firefighter/EMTs, firefighter/paramedics, and volunteer personnel serving in each of such roles.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3F0F6C54E1445C0AD6954C81262911E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>EMS is an integral component of the response capacity of the United States to disasters and public health crises, such as outbreaks of infectious diseases, bombings, mass shootings, earthquakes, tornadoes, and hurricanes. EMS personnel respond to more than 22,000,000 emergency calls each year including strokes, heart attacks, cardiac arrest, and trauma.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17E7ABDE54504D07AF9E64A9B430418B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Bureau of Labor Statistics compiles information on the number of individuals working in roles across the entire United States workforce. The Bureau of Labor Statistics completes this work by maintaining the Standard Occupational Classification system which classifies workers and jobs into occupational categories for the purpose of collecting, calculating, analyzing, or disseminating data.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H342953E0E86640C5B859C4164BCD5D18"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The BLS fails to accurately count EMS practitioners because of its failure to include dual-role firefighter/EMTs and firefighter/paramedics in their count of EMS personnel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8DCA5DCA49E4188B232A7C66527F16E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Accurately counting the EMS workforce is critical for government agencies in determining the needs of EMS agencies and practitioners. These data are also crucial for informing many aspects of policy including preparedness for natural disasters, public health emergencies, and acts of terrorism.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H96C7D4638D2F40068C342F6D3931739A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Recognition of dual-role firefighters as EMS practitioners</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall revise the broad description under the occupational series <quote>33–2011 Firefighters</quote> of the 2018 Standard Occupational Classification System of the Bureau of Labor Statistics to include the following detailed occupations:</text><paragraph id="H2BA1F68D8B32485396400A9471815A02"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Firefighters.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7AED85431CF045B48F18DD259B3286EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Firefighter/EMTs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H76573E67E5814FEEBD1DF0C35260DB7E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Firefighter/Paramedics.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEACFEB12EB2B4B1B8724861CBFE63AD5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Firefighters, All Other.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HFD0A91DD8192476B915DBCFB7509C67A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Labor shall submit to Congress a report that details—</text><paragraph id="HEA746EA1E49148D882A008D913D820D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the actions taken in 2015 to expand the definition <quote>29–2040 Emergency Medical Technicians and Paramedics</quote> to separately account for the numbers of EMTs and paramedics; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E840966F2674F86B794B330ADEEAA6B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the implementation of the revisions under section 3.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

