<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA3F888440EA54851B4877FEC3EA2797A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3970 IH: LGBTQI+ Data Inclusion Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3970</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000273">Ms. Leger Fernandez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To improve Federal populations surveys by requiring the collection of voluntary, self-disclosed information on sexual orientation, gender identity, and variations in sex characteristics in certain surveys, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA321E4D31A9F459EB60A9D281E5AF8A3" style="OLC"><section id="H10434937CA504DD59D947581B31E213A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>LGBTQI+ Data Inclusion Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H77CEB4C9BF574115BAC8B0F333708FA0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HABBAE409E7EF45128B6EA7C8131B553F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In its 2023 Federal Evidence Agenda on LGBTQI+ Equity, the Subcommittee on Sexual Orientation, Gender Identity, and Variations in Sex Characteristics (SOGI) Data that operates as part of the Subcommittee on Equitable Data of the National Science and Technology Council found that SOGI data collection can and should become part of standard demographic data collection throughout Federal agencies and that the collection of quality data on LGBTQI+ populations is essential for evidence-based policymaking and programmatic decision making.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD201371D33A745D592C377AB227904CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The National Academies on Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (NASEM), in their 2022 report, found that complete and accurate demographic information on the LGBTQI+ community should be standardized and collected.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88B7EE432F68426296C492CCEBC01F99"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Comprehensive statistics are needed to inform public policy and Federal programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5B074EAC86E4669931A76B51832BBE3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The availability of data also has a critical role in ensuring that any disparities in areas like health outcomes, housing, education, and employment can be addressed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H357B03A1D3F54F03A75B18512AA1A5A2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>As of the March release of the NASEM report, limited Federal surveys collect data on sexual orientation and gender, with none currently measuring intersex populations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAFB926C6567B4B0ABC9F5B2D539965EB"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The integrity of the Federal statistical system relies on the ability of agencies to determine the content of their statistical surveys based on considerations of relevance, timeliness, accuracy, objectivity, and ability to maintain confidentiality. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HE811549F50014ADFA507D5635CDB0A98"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requirement to collect data on sexual orientation, gender identity, and variations in sex characteristics</header><subsection id="H158D95ACD677426AAEB3ABC5D7D38C95"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Survey requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 360 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the head of any agency that collects information through a covered survey for statistical purposes shall establish data standards that require, with regard to the survey, the following:</text><paragraph id="H4AC40EF35F9040FCAE473E667ACCD9CF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The review of covered surveys to determine in which surveys information about sexual orientation, gender identity, and variations in sex characteristics is not included.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE29504AAA6B945B3980569EB0D5F0999"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Methods</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification of appropriate methods to include questions on sexual orientation, gender identity, and variations in sex characteristics in covered surveys that facilitate categorization and voluntary participation and preserve privacy and confidentiality, including protocols for anonymizing data collected and destroying personally identifiable information at the appropriate time and not later than three years after the date on which the information is collected.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4909E17E93D147939AB75A13D948E100"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Data collection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The use of the appropriate methods identified in paragraph (2) to gather data on sexual orientation, gender identity, and variations in sex characteristics for any survey identified in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84FA92B15AC84825AA925972FA5777A5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>The implementation of a process to routinely assess needed changes in covered survey methods related to asking questions on sexual orientation, gender identity, and variations in sex characteristics.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD990B402CC4A4B22ADE50695EC50D4E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Data reports; waiver</header><paragraph id="HCA42FA5C8AAD42649669C9A779F98823"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Data reports</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, any report published by an agency that relies on covered survey demographic data shall include information on sexual orientation, gender identity, and variations in sex characteristics.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC583EEEACBC4280951230B2182809A6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The statistical official (as described in section 314 of title 5, United States Code) of each agency, or the head of the agency, for any agency that does not have a statistical official, may waive the requirement under paragraph (1), on a case-by-case basis, if the standards and policies in subsection (c) can not be met, or if adding such information to the survey would impair the ability of the agency to preserve the utility, accuracy, or objectivity of the survey while also generating relevant evidence about the LGBTQI+ community.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE277F2CACA2A48458BB0A4C5F8F5B5C2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text>Any information collected relating to the sexual orientation, gender identity, or variations in sex characteristics of a covered survey participant shall be maintained in accordance with applicable confidentiality and privacy laws, policies, and standards.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4A5EF26BD1CB43CAB83B61978022B332"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to require an individual to disclose their sexual orientation, gender identity, or variations in sex characteristics to an agency.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE2B8541C4E524DDBA93653A37F44C9E1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall provide a report to Congress on the implementation of the requirements of this Act by agencies, including how the implementation of such requirements by agencies affected the provision of services to persons according to the gender identity, sexual orientation, and variations in sex characteristics of the persons. </text></subsection><subsection id="HB8DE95A3755B4712908EA83624DB0870"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to permit the use of information collected under this section in a manner that would adversely affect any individual, or that is inconsistent with disclosure limitations established in any other law.</text></subsection><subsection id="H464BAFC69F7847DE9B5B907033CF334A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H8FDA30B52D77415D8E9EFE9027EC2814"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <quote>agency</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFD1FE0D388B4E7A81FC27071F7CFA75"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered survey</header><text>The term <quote>covered survey</quote> means a survey that includes demographic data in which—</text><subparagraph id="H10A6C2C0C31F422691D559C8551B84A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a subject self-reports information; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H12D0DD1F04F14BDF8A45D859119176F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a knowledgeable proxy (including a proxy of a deceased individual, if applicable) provides information about the subject or responds for all individuals in a household.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H48FBECB441294017BC81A23410FA0352"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Demographic data</header><text>The term <quote>demographic data</quote> means information about the race or ethnicity, sex, and age of a survey participant or population.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC341324EC6C64D4DABA9F27CDC2E2158"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Gender identity</header><text>The term <quote>gender identity</quote> means the gender-related identity, appearance, mannerism, or other gender-related characteristic of an individual, regardless of the designated sex at birth of the individual.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B19123ED4B34E959A61852ED264908A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Sexual orientation</header><text>The term <quote>sexual orientation</quote> means how a person identifies in terms of their emotional, romantic, or sexual attraction, and includes identification as straight, heterosexual, gay, lesbian, or bisexual, among other terms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H392401F2116A4AF58898213B7C63CE2A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Survey</header><text>The term <quote>survey</quote> means a data collection activity involving a questionnaire for a sample of a population and includes the decennial census.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H520E9B66C33C4386B7119C3E188E4FBD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Variations in sex characteristics</header><text>The term <quote>variations in sex characteristics</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="HAE6075F119904D7B9F9BF2706FB9820D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a physical trait present at birth or naturally occurring at a later time (including genitals, gonads, hormone function, and chromosome patterns), that differ from normative expectations for male or female bodies regarding the development, appearance, or function of sex-related characteristics; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C6993CF34F5411A955DAD1B7B4F464A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is sometimes referred to as intersex traits.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

