<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC380870C69BC436A93A30C087617FD2C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5646 IH: Stop Campus Hazing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5646</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to require institutions of higher education to disclose hazing incidents, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA0BC8599B7D54F95BD55C3A673012F55" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H245FDF5531DD478F95860AEF88199107"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Campus Hazing Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF31B29815D5141E8A1BD29A0ABDD297E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inclusion of hazing incidents in annual security reports</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 485(f)(1)(F) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1092">20 U.S.C. 1092(f)(1)(F)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HA0E5E1885B95425291C6D589AD89D7A4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i)(IX), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1414DE14F97439BAFEA03FC0C387720"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H63A646DC768046B3B43DD726523625C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H16996D321C2847FE897495560AC3B06C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAF61621DFB4E4820BCC7F306EC12A3B8">
<clause id="HB679297B68D1471EB9176CBFEF8D5847" indent="up1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">of hazing incidents that were reported to campus security authorities or local police agencies.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HE9634CEFA79140389D9DA8303742D27C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definition of hazing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 485(f)(6)(A) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1092">20 U.S.C. 1092(f)(6)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="HD5E26B2B350D48B09F518EFF278C55FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating clauses (iii) through (v) as clauses (iv) through (vi), respectively; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4C8D10768CC64584B6516AA9ED21A07F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after clause (ii) the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35F6F9F9AC364241A76C1F2D9FEF5130">
<clause id="H64F175DF2A884A85BBF20FA31C2539C6" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>hazing</term> means any intentional, knowing, or reckless act committed by a person, whether individually or in concert with other persons, against a student regardless of that student's willingness to participate, that—</text> <subclause id="H7AFEC06D76BD43608A9B131294C66E91"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">was committed in connection with an initiation into, an affiliation with, or the maintenance of membership in, an organization (such as a club, society, association, athletic team, fraternity, sorority, or student government); and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HE61C379D2B524587B12A3C6F1DAECAD8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>causes or is likely to contribute to a substantial risk, above the reasonable risk encountered in the course of participation in the institution of higher education or the organization (such as the physical training necessary for participation in an athletic team), of physical injury, mental harm, or degradation.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="H601C93472B7D4A14B6BA042156E35CF7"><enum>4.</enum><header>Recording of hazing incidents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 485(f)(7) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1092">20 U.S.C. 1092(f)(7)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after the second sentence the following: <quote>For hazing incidents, such statistics shall be compiled in accordance with the definition of that term in paragraph (6)(A)(iii).</quote>.</text></section>
<section id="HD60B5007BBFD4B73A477D49CB765DBEE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Hazing education and reporting</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 485(f) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1092">20 U.S.C. 1092(f)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4F19206AE7574D8AA0A5D91C4FAA2F1A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (9) through (18) as paragraphs (10) through (19), respectively; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8541FB6D2797437CB9FC49146D50B7B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (8) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8CB0AF21883140999CB9BC724E92248E"> <paragraph id="H75C5E40AF38A4185AF52642BB065A6CE"><enum>(9)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H09C4E65AED7F41A59AEF3A93525E0ACA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Each institution of higher education participating in any program under this title, other than a foreign institution of higher education, shall develop and distribute as part of the report described in paragraph (1) a statement of policy regarding the following:</text>
<clause id="H56A5488DDF0E4BC38C6E172D53D41D93" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A comprehensive program to prevent hazing that shall—</text> <subclause id="HC890DA3F4A174FF99BD8FCC849C61EAD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be a campus-wide program for students, staff, faculty, and other campus stakeholders, such as alumni and families of students;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HC496156E9D2147E3999697D0B21A827F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>be a research-based program;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H855463CCEC9C4B9C9703492E6A2CD4B0"><enum>(III)</enum><text>be designed and implemented in partnership with a broad coalition of campus stakeholders, including leadership of the institution, faculty, staff, students, alumni, and families of students;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H15638D7286C94900A3894E5F6778F032"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>include information on hazing awareness, hazing prevention, the institution's policies on hazing, how to report hazing, and the process used to investigate hazing; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HBE10A0BEC29B4BE4BA0D412B754016A7"><enum>(V)</enum><text>include skill building for bystander intervention, information about ethical leadership, and the promotion of strategies for building group cohesion without hazing. </text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HAC7063D4B149471B86699AE69E02CB67" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The institution’s current campus policies relating to hazing, which shall include procedures that comply with the following: </text> <subclause id="HEE4A1AF68FE244228A1B996FAA76BCDA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The institution shall—</text>
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H981E659AF81545A3A8F69F76DC54A1FA"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collect information, beginning not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Stop Campus Hazing Act</short-title>, with respect to hazing incidents and hazing prevention policies of the institution;</text></item> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8FE3B769C06B425AAFCB89AD882B75E0"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prepare, in accordance with this clause, a report (which shall be referred to as the <term>Campus Hazing Transparency Report</term>) containing the information required under this clause; </text></item>
<item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0BD680BEA4694B5F82DDFA0EECE3C06E"><enum>(cc)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">make the Campus Hazing Transparency Report publicly available not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Stop Campus Hazing Act</short-title>; and</text></item> <item id="H6A65573F891C4D66B5DF4529BA86D6B9"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>update the Campus Hazing Transparency Report not less frequently than on January 15 and July 15 of each year, with, for each such update, each incident for which a formal finding has been issued, as described in subclause (II), during the period preceding such update that ends 15 days before the date of such update.</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="H9EF1E14C249A40699B4C5A1ECAF813BB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The Campus Hazing Transparency Report shall include each incident involving a student of the institution for which a formal finding of guilt, responsibility, or culpability is issued that either of the following was committed:</text> <item id="H7A16C70773A344868019D10E033AF657"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>A violation related to hazing—</text>
<subitem id="H1527C1CD410A47ABA9507A1E5CDE2E28"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>of the institution’s standards of conduct; or</text></subitem> <subitem id="H458F1C806F514641BF97CDA16B3B8074"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>of Federal, State, or local law.</text></subitem></item>
<item id="HF61935B8965042CEA51E09CD4DFF7F8F" commented="no"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>When committed in connection with a violation reported under item (aa) and that threatened a student’s physical safety (including a violation involving the abuse or illegal use of alcohol or drugs), any violation of—</text> <subitem id="H9ADCDF280E2B4CABB82822763D2CF368" commented="no"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the institution’s standards of conduct; or</text></subitem>
<subitem id="H480036CE0F2E44768A23D67C31058F17" commented="no"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>Federal, State, or local law.</text></subitem></item></subclause> <subclause id="HF205E0A802CC4AA59ADDC62053ECFA30"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The Campus Hazing Transparency Report shall include, for each formal finding under subclause (II), the following:</text>
<item id="H016EE404220B4482B34FC89B0620530C"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>The name of the organization with which the violation that resulted in a formal finding of guilt, responsibility, or culpability, was committed in connection.</text></item> <item id="H583F5EBFA8BA4567B053592AB3627675"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>A general description of the violation that resulted in a formal finding of guilt, responsibility, or culpability, the charges, the findings of the institution, and the sanctions placed on the organization.</text></item>
<item id="H49420421A26D4A30B19C3B4E18614CF4"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>The dates on which—</text> <subitem id="HE6A7AF9CAA394BF9A1C082BF6EB57D1B"><enum>(AA)</enum><text>the incident was alleged to have occurred;</text></subitem>
<subitem id="H14843864A51F4C89AD07D4E7AA808B08"><enum>(BB)</enum><text>the violation that resulted in a formal finding of guilt, responsibility, or culpability was charged;</text></subitem> <subitem id="H6EA1D93948BB4E92AD03D7DAF8C771B2"><enum>(CC)</enum><text>the investigation was initiated; and</text></subitem>
<subitem id="HF0EEA54E2A604AC698D610854A16BEBC"><enum>(DD)</enum><text>the investigation ended with a finding that a violation occurred.</text></subitem></item></subclause> <subclause id="H98B41B3C940E4096B54647A8D52457CC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The Campus Hazing Transparency Report shall not include any information that would reveal personally identifiable information about any individual student.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HE72713958A834FC299E3E40E69ADC2C0"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The institution shall provide, in a prominent location on the institution's public website, a link to the webpage that contains the Campus Hazing Transparency Report. Such webpage shall include— </text> <item id="HC7980150BE744EACA55E77CE5CA8F991"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a statement notifying the public of the availability of information including findings or sanctions, except information protected under section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (commonly known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>);</text></item>
<item id="H4586AF87CB9D403DA5054E7F81F472A6"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a description of how a member of the public may obtain such information;</text></item> <item id="H976F560448D44E529039142A2EECE0A3"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>a statement that the institution is required to provide such information pursuant to this clause;</text></item>
<item id="HF82F95FC3DD84DE591FA562F16C7244C"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>a statement notifying the public of the availability of the statistics required to be made available under paragraph (1)(F); and</text></item> <item id="H171EFFBCFB5443B58C493BC6DD9C9BD3"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>information about the institution’s anti-hazing policy.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF2F010069A8E4F1EB0D63F75D858887A" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Each institution shall maintain each Campus Hazing Transparency Report on its website for a period of 7 academic years. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9AEF0CE30CD348D09BC4D5A9A24535D5" commented="no" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>In the case of an allegation that a multi-institution organization was involved in a hazing incident, the requirements of this subsection shall apply only to the institution or institutions at which the persons involved in such allegation are enrolled or were formerly enrolled, including any student who was a victim in the alleged incident.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section>
<section id="H962FDA4126EB42B9847DC627D930D173"><enum>6.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or an amendment made by this Act, shall be construed to alter legal standards regarding, or affect the rights (including remedies and procedures) available to individuals under the Constitution of the United States or other Federal laws that establish protections for freedom of speech or expression.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

