<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H74CD22EA7D0D4CC6AFC04E75F2EE94BB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3713 IH: Mental Health Services for Students Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3713</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000579">Mr. Ryan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000136">Mr. Vasquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001090">Mr. Harder of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to revise and extend projects relating to children and to provide access to school-based comprehensive mental health programs.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H33C0B8693337431C9DFF440B0A2396C0" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9B5C99EA2E074B9D94A5053FE99C7E76" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mental Health Services for Students Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H0A2BDF0925AE438995D4259AC62C94A4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Amendments to the Public Health Service Act</header> <subsection id="H18045F32332948FBB6290A2752698416"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Technical amendments</header><text>The second part G (relating to services provided through religious organizations) of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290kk">42 U.S.C. 290kk et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2C46282101FE49639AD895082A4A4E59"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating such part as part J; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H73B530CA2CC24596A0516FB4C14B684D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 581 through 584 as sections 596 through 596C, respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H541F8B96B3AE45C3AE6936DC38057DB3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>School-Based mental health and children</header><text>Section 581 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290hh">42 U.S.C. 290hh</external-xref>) (relating to children and violence) is amended to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA795893A7C345829EAE5F41B29B84D9" style="OLC"> <section id="H815E5CD0C6A74747942BF1F9DF935E26"><enum>581.</enum><header>School-based mental health; children and adolescents</header> <subsection id="H4D161E23A74C475E94CC1B5E0A8FCAB1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, shall, through grants, contracts, or cooperative agreements awarded to eligible entities described in subsection (c), provide comprehensive school-based mental health services and supports to assist children in local communities and schools (including schools funded by the Bureau of Indian Education) dealing with traumatic experiences, grief, bereavement, risk of suicide, and violence. Such services and supports shall be—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6C3E6DE5487E4B279035D8023045DF07"><enum>(1)</enum><text>developmentally, linguistically, and culturally appropriate;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H12CA3FF5849F4FCC85C65A75809DD283"><enum>(2)</enum><text>trauma-informed; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H65DE396CC40E4F9E8434B1FD8EE9F439"><enum>(3)</enum><text>incorporate positive behavioral interventions and supports.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5AE7B9E97C1A426A90D735BD615F61CF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>Grants, contracts, or cooperative agreements awarded under subsection (a), shall, as appropriate, be used for—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3FB3B17E958C45F8BA0F9E96F3195FBE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>implementation of school- and community-based mental health programs that—</text> <subparagraph id="HDE160EA9F7BE42F48C7ACFD2D2D39439"><enum>(A)</enum><text>build awareness of individual trauma and the intergenerational, continuum of impacts of trauma on populations;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCB5E0FB8094B426D919E80FE2ABD25FC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>train appropriate staff to identify, and screen for, signs of trauma exposure, mental health disorders, or risk of suicide; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H38D700F7B2CC426A84AB390491C5143C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>incorporate positive behavioral interventions, family engagement, student treatment, and multigenerational supports to foster the health and development of children, prevent mental health disorders, and ameliorate the impact of trauma;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H698F1448195243E4AC53F2E50A18B5B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>technical assistance to local communities with respect to the development of programs described in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAC6817B7BE5B44E5A73ED36BE4663D92"><enum>(3)</enum><text>facilitating community partnerships among families, students, law enforcement agencies, education agencies, mental health and substance use disorder service systems, family-based mental health service systems, child welfare agencies, health care providers (including primary care physicians, mental health professionals, and other professionals who specialize in children’s mental health such as child and adolescent psychiatrists), institutions of higher education, faith-based programs, trauma networks, and other community-based systems to address child and adolescent trauma, mental health issues, and violence; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B02F24C87194048B1844DE67E02C741"><enum>(4)</enum><text>establishing mechanisms for children and adolescents to report incidents of violence or plans by other children, adolescents, or adults to commit violence.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD88453A9BA104B3E8DEC877798CC57CB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header> <paragraph id="H48C3499466D543ABBF9AEF691A25B427"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be eligible for a grant, contract, or cooperative agreement under subsection (a), an entity shall be a partnership that includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H200DAB83E08A47DDAE67394978BCF0A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State educational agency, as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, in coordination with one or more local educational agencies, as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965, or a consortium of any entities described in subparagraph (B), (C), (D), or (E) of section 8101(30) of such Act; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB17CFB425BBD44B09B59C4F3BEB5AA78"><enum>(B)</enum><text>at least 1 community-based mental health provider, including a public or private mental health entity, health care entity, family-based mental health entity, trauma network, or other community-based entity, as determined by the Secretary (and which may include additional entities such as a human services agency, law enforcement or juvenile justice entity, child welfare agency, agency, an institution of higher education, or another entity, as determined by the Secretary).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H52165F18F5C6421A8C5B41B8B1583865"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compliance with HIPAA</header><text>Any patient records developed by covered entities through activities under the grant shall meet the regulations promulgated under section 264(c) of the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3C67846F48F44E06937C093D8E9072E0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compliance with FERPA</header><text>Section 444 of the General Education Provisions Act (commonly known as the <quote>Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974</quote>) shall apply to any entity that is a member of the partnership in the same manner that such section applies to an educational agency or institution (as that term is defined in such section).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8188192C9E6C4104A8BB0743B8E1147F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Geographical distribution</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that grants, contracts, or cooperative agreements under subsection (a) will be distributed equitably among the regions of the country and among urban and rural areas.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6476384A94B24EAE9FB7FE3F13BE7390"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Duration of awards</header><text>With respect to a grant, contract, or cooperative agreement under subsection (a), the period during which payments under such an award will be made to the recipient shall be 5 years, with options for renewal.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCE01A7A8B61C419494275AE0AAC3E1AF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Evaluation and measures of outcomes</header> 
<paragraph id="HE4A38EF4C50E4460909C256B83CE1865"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Development of process</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall develop a fiscally appropriate process for evaluating activities carried out under this section. Such process shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="HCBEBBD43164E4E8E9BE540D8C075217C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the development of guidelines for the submission of program data by grant, contract, or cooperative agreement recipients;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H345FDC4C870B432EA198655AE5C33656"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the development of measures of outcomes (in accordance with paragraph (2)) to be applied by such recipients in evaluating programs carried out under this section; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC98296822D72408DB75BD8018FEEF363"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the submission of annual reports by such recipients concerning the effectiveness of programs carried out under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA3985330665D4BB9999D4B57FB37C908"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Measures of outcomes</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall develop measures of outcomes to be applied by recipients of assistance under this section to evaluate the effectiveness of programs carried out under this section, including outcomes related to the student, family, and local educational systems supported by this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H09A3AB8200714870BA017002D7B54362"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Submission of annual data</header><text>An eligible entity described in subsection (c) that receives a grant, contract, or cooperative agreement under this section shall annually submit to the Assistant Secretary a report that includes data to evaluate the success of the program carried out by the entity based on whether such program is achieving the purposes of the program. Such reports shall utilize the measures of outcomes under paragraph (2) in a reasonable manner to demonstrate the progress of the program in achieving such purposes.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H57151CDB601444FCB127937881AA95CA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Evaluation by assistant secretary</header><text>Based on the data submitted under paragraph (3), the Assistant Secretary shall annually submit to Congress a report concerning the results and effectiveness of the programs carried out with assistance received under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H42F34807930C4974B12104338574437C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An eligible entity shall use not more than 20 percent of amounts received under a grant under this section to carry out evaluation activities under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD0636D92F7854A12BDB74B89F559F7E9"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Information and education</header><text>The Secretary shall disseminate best practices based on the findings of the knowledge development and application under this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBC81DC049E4B4951A5E2A5AF70F74EF6"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Amount of grants and authorization of appropriations</header> <paragraph id="H0A02FD69E36043788728E8FD802A8565"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amount of grants</header><text>A grant under this section shall be in an amount that is not more than $2,000,000 for each of the first 5 fiscal years following the date of enactment of the <short-title>Mental Health Services for Students Act of 2023</short-title>. The Secretary shall determine the amount of each such grant based on the population of children up to age 21 of the area to be served under the grant.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9D24E46AAE374B969132646C94A4641F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section, $300,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2027.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HF3C1FB2FFC2844B68FA6ACC2E4E06A2B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part G of title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290hh">42 U.S.C. 290hh et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (b), is further amended by striking the part designation and heading and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD260309CC5B94646AFD259D9B397EC2A" style="OLC"> 
<part id="HEE4B8547F3504AC2BFB21216915BC088"><enum>G</enum><header>School-based mental health</header></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


