<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7CBD6167E88B49C0B689F86092CD6531" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5700 IH: Federal Assistance for Streamlining Travel Passports Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5700</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230926">September 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to develop and submit to Congress a strategy to improve the processing of passport applications.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H12E16F81A26D4F93A0355EB5C6348431" style="OLC"><section id="H54300F366583477D9F9C43E8E29D5895" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Assistance for Streamlining Travel Passports Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FAST Passports Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H19911A5ECA1C4D87B64FD2E939C729DF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strategy to improve communication relating to the processing of passport applications</header><subsection id="H4173375EF3E441DC975B5FD986B1E042"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall develop and submit to the relevant congressional committees a strategy to improve the processing of passport applications.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1992DBBA7DFB46B584A96829EEB77391"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters To be included</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The strategy required by subsection (a) shall, within 360 days after the date of submission of the strategy, seek to achieve the following:</text><paragraph id="H6741D52E8A5D4334B8EF71AB2BAAB61A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Improve communication within the Department of State, including among all passport agencies and centers, relating to the processing of passport applications.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC342CB62D6754FC29CECDE0A5645E961"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Ensure that United states citizens and congressional offices inquiring on behalf of such citizens are able to contact the Department of State, including a passport agency or center, regarding the status of requests for passport applications and receive updates within a reasonably short period of time.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H54AC55CF89194AEDB1AA95543C1A647A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Relevant congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>relevant congressional committees</quote> means the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

