<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7475EB10B2F94A2581031DB84377DBC2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3134 IH: Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3134</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to establish insulin assistance programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4411D8C24FC544B799AD2724E44FA473" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HA1401887FAF54BE3B71AA50F4F97CAAA"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H60E398DE3DDD49A3808C483222F62DDB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Insulin assistance programs</header><subsection id="H92E082C5C6A4456296C0B5F20F3A0BB9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part B of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/243">42 U.S.C. 243 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF6213A9872514EBAB808B1B5695BB411"><section id="H0767F9B07EDF4B5F97417C94C51F7B24"><enum>320C.</enum><header>Insulin assistance programs</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8ABA1CADEF334C0B9E11684E71CC8AA5"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of program of grants to States, Indian tribes, and tribal organizations</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2E00947CFDEF47DD995C37CBE12C8193"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, make grants to States, Indian tribes, and tribal organizations for the purpose of carrying out programs to assist eligible individuals in obtaining insulin in accordance with paragraph (4).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H68108D704B574099903E76A8943BBCB5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grant and contract authority for States, Indian tribes, and tribal organizations</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAE3F280DB0F94EF0BD7377E74A47A819"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization receiving a grant under paragraph (1) may, subject to subparagraph (B), expend the grant to carry out the purpose described in such paragraph through grants or contracts to public or private entities, including local governments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0902E2E42AAE413AB0AB027FC874C792"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Certain applications</header><text>If a nonprofit private entity and a private entity that is not a nonprofit entity both submit applications to a State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization to receive an award of a grant or contract under subparagraph (A), the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization shall give priority to the application submitted by the nonprofit private entity in any case in which the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization determines that the quality of such application is equivalent to the quality of the application submitted by the other private entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35EC189D69D74010AA5B11C1CB840551"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Allotment</header><text>Each State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization that applies for a grant in accordance with subsection (e) shall receive a grant under this section in an amount that is equal to the sum of—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDC53DB355AEF4FF287E837D7385776A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a minimum amount determined by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB0FDF70213DF4107AEBD81D27BEB4B08"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an additional amount based on criteria established by the Secretary, which may include the ability of the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization to successfully assist individuals in seeking eligibility for Federal or State-funded programs as described in paragraph (4)(A)(ii)(II).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA05ED496BC154632BEC3FD25EEC66E00"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Program components</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H04513B5827E64316954AA21D01F9ECD9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization carrying out a program supported by a grant under this subsection—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB001EBA5EE5147E48F77C6ECB6A32B48"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall use the grant funds to—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA736E022C6354183A2E3BD7E7021458B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>issue insulin cards to eligible individuals in accordance with subparagraph (B); and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35A3A2F4552448CB8E6FEB62DE31BA7D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>enter into agreements with pharmacies—</text><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5EBAD5F2C8D04CFCA2D589BF810DFAE8"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>for such pharmacies to fill prescriptions for individuals displaying valid insulin cards that are issued in accordance with subparagraph (B) at no cost to such individuals; and</text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7ADF1D5A1F854140B75CC5C992E4663B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization to pay such pharmacies for insulin filled for a prescription described in item (aa); and</text></item></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD173A8C21CBC485BB752760223053819"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may use the grant funds to—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H89609E91BF3346C7BEF28791BDF3C56D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>purchase insulin; or</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1F275CB0F394963A6536C3CAA0E2ED0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>assist individuals in seeking eligibility for Federal or State-funded programs which may provide coverage for insulin or otherwise assist such individuals in obtaining insulin.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4DCE6CDAD95C462D8FD3DDA53F96F01D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Insulin cards</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC07DD5CCCC642678710A84E704056F4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible individual seeking an insulin card through a program supported by a grant under this subsection shall submit an application to the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization receiving the grant, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization may reasonably require for purposes of this subsection, including—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H509A112A5AB449DEA684FDE8E7E92C87"><enum>(I)</enum><text>documentation indicating proof of—</text><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3169EEB8E5AB48BBAE871E557AE2BAA8"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>in the case of a grant awarded to a State, residency in the State;</text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H03D235A674D0461F96D052482265D947"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>in the case of a grant awarded to an Indian tribe, membership in the Indian tribe; or</text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H287BE46600A643F88ECD53F9E00168A7"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>in the case of a grant awarded to a tribal organization, membership in the Indian tribe or Indian community served by the tribal organization;</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4664DCF5835D43BD984A4F377C036640"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a prescription for insulin that is prescribed to the individual;</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB159BD01F3DD47E788DD49C7D3D234B5"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a statement that, to the best of the individual's knowledge, the individual is an uninsured individual or an underinsured individual; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H11FD6ED7C9B04FC8B4270D0290CD9881"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>if the individual is an underinsured individual, the name of the high-deductible health plan in which the individual is enrolled and any unique identifier of the plan, such as a policy number.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4144695A82874CD9AE875490E69BB074"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Initial card</header><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4EA8A4E7AC2349E094BBEB89281EC83E"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization carrying out a program supported by a grant under this subsection shall issue an initial insulin card to each individual that submits an application to the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization meeting the requirements under clause (i).</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA4D80B50F014254941D83865E2060A3"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>A State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization that receives an application under clause (i) from an individual shall issue an initial insulin card to such individual not later than 5 business days after receiving such application.</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDE755FBB7D66473DB43EDF258299322D"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Supply</header><text>An initial insulin card issued to an individual under this clause shall be valid for an approximate 7-day supply of insulin that is appropriate for the individual based on the prescription for the individual provided in the application under clause (i) and packaging and processing practices for insulin.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4505744685E6410CBE310E17D98B9083"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>3-month cards</header><text>Not later than 12 business days after an individual submits an application under clause (i) to a State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization, the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization shall—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02087318A02D43C69F75D0F9F1D26125"><enum>(I)</enum><text>determine whether the individual is an eligible individual; and</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5760A873728A463D9B48788F782DF647"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if the individual is an eligible individual, issue the individual an insulin card that is valid for an approximate 90-day supply of insulin that is appropriate for the individual based on the prescription provided in the application under clause (i) and packaging and processing practices for insulin.</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H29EBCC3E53C446479744F566D3033784"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Renewal of cards</header><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H92C81EE663F84FBBA6DF56BF349CDB6F"><enum>(I)</enum><header>3-month cards</header><text>An eligible individual that is issued an insulin card under clause (iii) may apply to renew such card in accordance with a process established by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization.</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE8AC40AE9104A998B825707DA21CB28"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An individual that submits an application under clause (i) and is denied an insulin card under clause (ii) or (iii) may not submit another application under clause (i) for the 1-year period beginning on the date on which the individual is denied such card.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8F72CEB7C78D452EBD99765EF7C2B79D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirement of matching funds</header><paragraph id="H8D49FD33D1214453B5AC83A1130D9384"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved agrees, with respect to the costs to be incurred by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization in carrying out the purpose described in subsection (a)(1), to make available non-Federal contributions (in cash or in kind under paragraph (2)) toward such costs in an amount equal to not less than $1 for each $3 of Federal funds provided in the grant. Such contributions may be made directly or through donations from public or private entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H800983E2568D464986C1E56868C0CC6A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination of amount of non-federal contribution</header><subparagraph id="HB9B65449A3E14D1183CE1F8ADF32A553"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Non-Federal contributions required in paragraph (1) may be in cash or in kind, fairly evaluated, including equipment or services (and excluding indirect or overhead costs). Amounts provided by the Federal Government, or services assisted or subsidized to any significant extent by the Federal Government, may not be included in determining the amount of such non-Federal contributions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA32E7B25A0BD4BE194DD9D322322593C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Maintenance of effort</header><text>In making a determination of the amount of non-Federal contributions for purposes of paragraph (1), the Secretary may include only non-Federal contributions in excess of the average amount of non-Federal contributions made by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved toward the purpose described in subsection (a)(1) for the 2-year period preceding the first fiscal year for which the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization is applying to receive a grant under subsection (a).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD7AF700D0C3451CA413231D6B781366"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Inclusion of relevant non-federal contributions for medicaid</header><text>In making a determination of the amount of non-Federal contributions for purposes of paragraph (1), the Secretary shall, subject to subparagraphs (A) and (B) of this paragraph, include any non-Federal amounts expended pursuant to title XIX of the Social Security Act by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization related to insulin dispensed to individuals eligible for medical assistance under such title.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA2B537C01D544757AA21ADB1C3211611"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Additional required agreements</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H48B0EF55CC2D4232A64E40E134D8929F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Statewide provision of services</header><subparagraph id="H47F220342B1B42ACB07F8233EE841014"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved agrees that services and activities under the grant will be made available throughout the State (including availability to members of any Indian tribe or tribal organization in the State), Indian tribe, or tribal organization.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1E1A4EDF292A4AB5B81414ADE8CECFFE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Waiver</header><clause id="H779A7A0C2D4C4641AC637CA9A84C1C2E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may waive the requirement established in subparagraph (A) for a State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization if the Secretary determines that compliance by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization with the requirement would result in an inefficient allocation of resources with respect to carrying out the purpose described in subsection (a)(1).</text></clause><clause id="H0D22A29B39E4462E95B9D1C5A651298D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Indian tribes and tribal organizations</header><text>If an Indian tribe or tribal organization is receiving a grant under subsection (a) and the State in which the tribe or organization is located is receiving a grant under subsection (a), the requirement under subparagraph (A) for the State regarding availability to the tribe or organization is deemed to have been waived under this subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF63936FAD9F944AB913B8055C2515C3B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Relationship to items and services under other programs</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF2824130E7924EF3A67CCDF2B6847647"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved agrees that the grant will not be expended to make payment for any item or service to the extent that payment has been made, or can reasonably be expected to be made, with respect to such item or service—</text><clause id="H7E1D927715064F17B947E3EFDDD22910"><enum>(i)</enum><text>except as provided in subparagraph (B), under any State compensation program, under an insurance policy, or under any Federal or State health benefits program; or</text></clause><clause id="H86CF231992844366ABEF0ED647000BC2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by an entity that provides health services on a prepaid basis.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF89C28EC09C4AE7BAE6D3E2FB3D65BE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The requirement under subparagraph (A)(i) shall not apply with respect to coverage under a high-deductible health plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC83FC004215A435A83E847505C852534"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation on administrative expenses</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved agrees that not more than 10 percent of the grant will be expended for administrative expenses with respect to the grant.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H38752615836440B6A5F7F9F3D70AB4C6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Records and audits</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved agrees that—</text><subparagraph id="HB508BC898642431885EB6ABF3E26F64C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization will establish such fiscal control and fund accounting procedures as may be necessary to ensure the proper disbursal of, and accounting for, amounts received by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization under such subsection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2767D4D763B4B2398EBAC14630F7033"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization will keep such records as the Secretary shall prescribe, including—</text><clause id="HF8481217E12940099CAAFCD05C7ABE46"><enum>(i)</enum><text>records that fully disclose—</text><subclause id="HF8ABBBA863EE4DB08D999872A38250A8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount and disposition by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization of the proceeds of such grant;</text></subclause><subclause id="H53033845D55F416A9BB62A337E737C64"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total cost of the project or undertaking intended to be carried out through the grant; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H28AD4DC03DA841E694DCB049F69A263C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the amount of that portion of the cost of the project or undertaking supplied by sources other than the grant; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H93566F27A99D459C85EFE8D7DBA8662B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such other records as the Secretary determines appropriate for facilitating an effective audit of grants awarded under this section; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97E7F4E90584442583916E7630ABBF24"><enum>(C)</enum><text>upon request, the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization will provide records maintained pursuant to subparagraphs (A) and (B) to the Secretary or the Comptroller General of the United States for purposes of auditing the expenditures by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization of the grant. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBCBAA2E84B78427186DE96FF94D8B849"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Reports</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H394DE80610F24D8A9CD287CFAF30A1EF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Reports to the Secretary</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved agrees to submit to the Secretary such reports as the Secretary may require with respect to the grant, including a report on—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H789E836199F441A4AEC0259B178183BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the types of problems and inquiries encountered by individuals applying for or receiving insulin through a program supported by such grant;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H70146480800E43A29FF89D505C046499"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of insulin products dispensed through such program and the unit costs for those products during the period covered by the report;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H564E02C311364EAEBF76850E236BF64B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of pharmacies participating in the program during the period covered by the report;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3924BCCA69004E1399B6FAE073B11115"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>summary data on the individuals applying for or receiving insulin through the program; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9662402656074AE0ACF0F060110B9DDF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>any other information the Secretary shall determine necessary to provide oversight of the grants made under this section.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H22D2F7451B754E459B769FB55293B377"><enum>(B)</enum><header>High-deductible health plans</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved agrees to, as soon as practicable after each time the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization provides payment to a pharmacy for insulin for an underinsured individual, submit to the high-deductible health plan in which the individual is enrolled information on the amount of such payment in order for such plan to comply with the requirements under section 2710.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H577A3EB8F2A54262A32C4A5CD45500D3"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Description of intended uses of grant</header><text>The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H2399F591A040443CBEDDD2AB9FCFF027"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved submits to the Secretary a description of the purposes for which the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization intends to expend the grant;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6EC984E0EBD64873A1278103143137BC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the description identifies the populations, areas, and localities in the State, or under the jurisdiction of the Indian tribe or tribal organization, with a need for a program to assist individuals in obtaining insulin in accordance with subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0F5F90B7042A4F50B3038C40609796EF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the description provides information relating to the services and activities to be provided, including a description of the manner in which the services and activities will be coordinated with any similar services or activities of public or private entities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE9E9A9A3710342D39848CB4629B0DEB7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the description provides assurances that the grant funds will be used in the most cost-effective manner.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDEE40F08FE5144CDADCB511BC4FE6D5E"><enum>(e)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Requirement of submission of application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may not make a grant under subsection (a) unless an application for the grant is submitted to the Secretary, the application contains the description of intended uses required under subsection (d), and the application is in such form, is made in such manner, and contains such agreements, assurances, and information as the Secretary determines to be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1BED13B3521B476192314125549B444A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Technical assistance and provision of supplies and services in lieu of grant funds</header><paragraph id="H12206D930BEF40CB9A7B6DB0A2B7B6AB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary may provide training and technical assistance with respect to the planning, development, and operation of any program or service carried out pursuant to subsection (a). The Secretary may provide such technical assistance directly or through grants to, or contracts with, public or private entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC1D10E53EA74ADDB7640B1713072DDD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Provision of supplies and services in lieu of grant funds</header><subparagraph id="H1BA1F60DB3E241A7BD79A5CC6596EA07"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon the request of a State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization receiving a grant under subsection (a), the Secretary may, subject to subparagraph (B), provide supplies, equipment, and services for the purpose of aiding the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization in carrying out such subsection and, for such purpose, may detail to the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization any officer or employee of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8A4B198EF47473887AB415E6BC0B159"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Corresponding reduction in payments</header><text>With respect to a request described in subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall reduce the amount of payments under the grant under subsection (a) to the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization involved by an amount equal to the costs of detailing personnel (including pay, allowances, and travel expenses) and the fair market value of any supplies, equipment, or services provided by the Secretary. The Secretary shall, for the payment of expenses incurred in complying with such request, expend the amounts withheld.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H47C80562F5D347208C73564E793EDD66"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Evaluations and reports</header><paragraph id="H137A5114A00C4E5481ECC0261E6A16F2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Evaluations</header><text>The Secretary shall, directly or through contracts with public or private entities, provide for annual evaluations of programs carried out pursuant to subsection (a). Such evaluations shall include evaluations of—</text><subparagraph id="H7B4DCE9E34DC49EA96766D965D53C77C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the extent to which States, Indian tribes, and tribal organizations carrying out such programs are in compliance with subsection (a) and with subsection (c)(1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CB82EB1938847FB935191DD2ECDB5DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the extent to which each State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization receiving a grant under this section is in compliance with subsection (b), including identification of—</text><clause id="HB6C7D14F0A33498A9B6852A865AB7880"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the amount of the non-Federal contributions by the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization for the preceding fiscal year, disaggregated according to the source of the contributions; and</text></clause><clause id="H962ABD506A134BFD831F1DF263E5C777"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the proportion of such amount of non-Federal contributions relative to the amount of Federal funds provided through the grant to the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization for the preceding fiscal year.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H006963DF09BE42128A5C8C4588AF411E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports to Congress</header><text>The Secretary shall, not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</short-title>, and annually thereafter, submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report summarizing evaluations carried out under paragraph (1) during the preceding fiscal year and making such recommendations for administrative and legislative initiatives with respect to this section as the Secretary determines to be appropriate, including recommendations regarding compliance by the States, Indian tribes, and tribal organizations with subsection (a) and with subsection (c)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEFC03E4DBEA449809CB412A733B7C984"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Funding for general program</header><paragraph id="H55931FB4126C4FE59DAA75AA18B8F8D4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>For the purpose of carrying out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC99BB211B39E40C3BD5378F5CCD737C6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Set-aside for technical assistance and provision of supplies and services</header><text>Of the amounts appropriated under paragraph (1) for a fiscal year, the Secretary shall reserve not more than 20 percent for carrying out subsection (f).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5F2071B1C95149ABA8890E54420CD254"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority to award grants under subsection (a) shall be effective beginning on the date of enactment of the <short-title>Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</short-title> and ending on the date that is 5 years after such date.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF64EC049B9648918CEFE2DB8BD1E7A9"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D8FB0721D06492E83D85C2AE0CA25A3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible individual</header><text>The term <term>eligible individual</term>, with respect to a program supported by a State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization receiving a grant under this section, means an uninsured individual or an underinsured individual—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H772CC922EB3B40F28C63EE4E3555BB70"><enum>(A)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H82EB50886EA541E796E8A2F3C4A7AE02"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a grant to a State, who is a resident of the State;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H64F3378554914EB8924C8FF9123F04DF" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a grant to an Indian tribe, who is a member of such tribe; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H081AF548C258414385183672106C0BA0" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of a grant to a tribal organization, who is a member of the Indian tribe or Indian community served by the tribal organization; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H90C9BAA2470C4EB2932CD7122A1E2315"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who has a valid prescription for insulin that is prescribed to such individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBE4B6928D5F74D20B18C13B6B8FE19CF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Group health insurance coverage; group health plan; health insurance issuer</header><text>The terms <term>group health insurance coverage</term>, <term>group health plan</term>, and <term>health insurance issuer</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 2791.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02B7795B7D8F404E9A16CD269CCF6AC5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>High-deductible health plan</header><text>The term <term>high-deductible health plan</term> means a group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage (offered by a health insurance issuer) that meets criteria established by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3A3461C00EB64B7DB7BB07A7FCCECC66"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian tribe</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1603">25 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1CC5E9DC14E7489DA518CB09F2018610"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Individual health insurance coverage</header><text>The term <term>individual health insurance coverage</term> has the meaning given such term in section 2791.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF16197889C4C44A187504ED1A458F4BA"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Tribal organization</header><text>The term <term>tribal organization</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1603">25 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2EA1179553B145E6ABB3866FA9B814B5"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Underinsured individual</header><text>The term <term>underinsured individual</term> means an individual who is enrolled in a high-deductible health plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9068AA331FC04FDB88C3AF3572F0B7DC"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Uninsured individual</header><text>The term <term>uninsured individual</term> means an individual who does not have minimum essential coverage as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5000A">section 5000A(f)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 or coverage under a medical care program of the Indian Health Service or of a tribal organization or urban Indian organization.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H038C9113C74141C6A95A88048F60FC04"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Urban Indian organization</header><text>The term <term>urban Indian organization</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H927CEC4528BC4377B455034610BA8747"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exempting prices used under an insulin assistance program from best price and average manufacturer price under the Medicaid drug rebate program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1927 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396r-8">42 U.S.C. 1396r–8</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H2000523F53CD4F63948CDA365602F55A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c)(1)(C)(i)(III), by inserting <quote>or under an insulin assistance program supported under section 320C of the Public Health Service Act</quote> after <quote>State pharmaceutical assistance program</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CA0B4DB64354AF6A232712EC89DB7AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (k)(1)(B)(i)—</text><subparagraph id="H04DD6058AA3B46ABB97757AFC614FDE8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subclause (IV), by inserting a semicolon at the end; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED005B709DC542268844AF07D55456F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subclause (VII), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H097D9FC268F74487A479D583B9A673F0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subclause (VIII), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BB2081B40EE4BF7A7F4A54B311F5F2A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text><quoted-block style="traditional" display-inline="no-display-inline" act-name="" id="H1FE05DBC8E91415593F53878DADB9321"><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H19FB79A31C2C4333B4C273815BF5D577"><enum>(IX)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any prices used under an insulin assistance program supported under section 320C of the Public Health Service Act.</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEFD6902AE7C34AA49F725DB7D7E8846D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deductibles for underinsured individuals participating in insulin assistance programs</header><text>Subpart I of part A of title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg">42 U.S.C. 300gg et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7FBA62987C784A559D08F8B353EC690A"><section id="H7C23443929DB4F0BAA3163DB553E48B3"><enum>2710.</enum><header>Deductibles and other out-of-pocket expenses for underinsured individuals participating in insulin assistance programs</header><subsection id="H9E6DDFBCDDF3491C8708C80D474BA95F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A group health plan that is a high-deductible health plan and a health insurance issuer offering a high-deductible health plan shall, with respect to any individual who is enrolled in such plan and obtains insulin during a plan year through an insulin card issued to the individual by a State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization carrying out an insulin assistance program under section 320C, count the amount the State, Indian tribe, or tribal organization pays a pharmacy for insulin for such individual for such plan year towards any deductible or other out-of-pocket expenses required to be paid under the plan.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0193B63251DD402BB7E4F8BA9151A2FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>High-Deductible health plan</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>high-deductible health plan</term> has the meaning given such term in section 320C(j).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H41B9C5BF9BF94AD48E4526250B301DB9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Annual fees applicable to insulin manufacturers</header><subsection id="H9D72F38525BE45C280ACECC64834B47D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section:</text><paragraph id="H40317F111F9D4D21B62FA8A562E4CE56"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual payment date</header><text>The term <term>annual payment date</term> means, with respect to a calendar year, the date determined by the Secretary, but in no event later than September 30 of such calendar year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H730A24F06F854C0980F62EC28CFF760C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <term>covered entity</term>, with respect to a calendar year, means an entity that—</text><subparagraph id="HE334D97E658843A8A60CA7DDD39AD72F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is the holder of an application approved under subsection (c) of section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref>), or of a license issued under subsection (a) of section 351 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>), for an insulin product; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03B6A9126F3A4E43AF70B81D0BAA5DB9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>during the preceding calendar year, manufactured any insulin product that was sold in commerce and covered by a Federal health program at least once during such preceding calendar year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5E41209E55C4661A5D01B9E31C947C4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inspector General</header><text>The term <term>Inspector General</term> means the Inspector General of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE142B71B23E44FEFBD57EDA984F4F835"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4507F7D7C88C4977B8443A2F298529B3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Imposition of fee</header><text>Each covered entity for a calendar year, beginning in 2024 and ending in 2028, shall pay to the Secretary not later than the annual payment date of such calendar year a fee in an amount determined under subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="H5F71C5F3FB3D4314BE0B944860E313BC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Amount of fees</header><paragraph id="HB91876FC56024B23A5AF223010F07111"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Total amount</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that the total amount in fees assessed under subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H6AD0E8C88F40473E928AFB8C9CD2132D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for calendar year 2024, equals the total amount the Secretary estimates as the total expenditures for carrying out section 320C of the Public Health Service Act for such calendar year; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4767E623DDFE4A2F97789CDFCED3080D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for each of calendar years 2025 through 2028, equals the total amount of expenditures the Secretary determines for carrying out such section for the preceding calendar year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H16F66C5B6BB84726AF1AB712D07631C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Determination of fees for each manufacturer</header><subparagraph id="H1424DAC9553C4C60822A18DBBEEF43F3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Formula</header><text>With respect to each covered entity, the fee under this section for a calendar year shall be equal to an amount that bears the same ratio to the total amount assessed under subsection (b) for such year as the covered entity's sales of insulin products taken into account during the preceding calendar year bears to the aggregate sales of insulin products of all covered entities taken into account during such preceding calendar year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1380B1469024B3C8FE2164D18359022"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Sales of insulin products</header><clause id="HE8B96C5DBB054ED5BE0D0817F9271040"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the sales of insulin products taken into account during any calendar year with respect to any covered entity shall be determined based on the total number of units of the insulin product which were sold in commerce in the preceding calendar year based on—</text><subclause id="HB6A63E33775149C1B841B25914B92A8C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>for a fee assessed for calendar year 2024, information obtained by the Secretary under clause (ii); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7DD15716047240A08DDDE3B0B4C6CE11"><enum>(II)</enum><text>for a fee assessed for each of calendar years 2025 through 2028, the information provided in the annual reports issued by the Inspector General and made public under section 4(e)(1).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE6BD70353C534A3FBAAFE4EA70FAF302"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Fees assessed for calendar year 2024</header><text>For purposes of clause (i)(I), the Secretary shall require each covered entity to submit to the Secretary information on the total number of units of the insulin product manufactured by the entity that were sold in commerce in calendar year 2023.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE64294932F524535A8C625DE799213C9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deposit</header><text>The Secretary shall deposit amounts received through fees assessed under subsection (b) into the general fund of the Treasury.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H2610EF67CDB44E0992E06F9AE67ED3C9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>The Secretary may bring an action in any court of competent jurisdiction to recover the amount of any fee that is assessed under subsection (b) for a calendar year and not paid by the annual payment date.</text></subsection></section><section id="H28C3C13E3B0642888911C015C25E4174"><enum>4.</enum><header>Identification of insulin price spikes; application of excise tax</header><subsection id="H4A57E370C3EE4E1B94D1914A3B52B5CC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HA850FA0F48364B7D94866AE27FEF4D8D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicable entity</header><text>The term <term>applicable entity</term> means the holder of an application approved under subsection (c) or (j) of section 505 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref>), or of a license issued under subsection (a) or (k) of section 351 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>), for an insulin product.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H28D357961C0F44F989B07B22E7414A3C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commerce</header><text>The term <term>commerce</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/44">15 U.S.C. 44</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FF3562BD8764C5BB8859E9397B7B1BB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Inspector General</header><text>The term <term>Inspector General</term> means the Inspector General of the Department of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H561523BDD8B24630BA14ACF1AA9FA44D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Price spike</header><subparagraph id="H5209C8848F9B49E882566DB8B99A9F82"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>price spike</term> means an increase in the wholesale acquisition cost in commerce of an insulin product for which the price spike percentage is equal to or greater than the applicable price increase allowance.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H34640162A9F143F3B1B854563B17ED95"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Price spike percentage</header><text>The term <term>price spike percentage</term> means the percentage (if any) by which—</text><clause id="H29537A1AEB404536A85DD384D1AE5E2A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost of an insulin product in commerce for the calendar year; exceeds</text></clause><clause id="H226AFB06E3554ADE8873BB9F248D7CD2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost of such insulin product in commerce for the calendar year preceding such year.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5CFD5951952A42EA912327CF5E7038CB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Applicable price increase allowance</header><text>The term <term>applicable price increase allowance</term>, with respect to a calendar year, means the percentage (rounded to the nearest one-tenth of 1 percent) by which the C–CPI–U (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1">section 1(f)(6)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) for that year exceeds the C–CPI–U (as so defined) for the preceding calendar year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9166A5BFDF64AFBA19EAC91C6F9796D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Price spike revenue</header><subparagraph id="HBC0158522AAD4A98B3C86C14570143B0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>price spike revenue</term>, with respect to a calendar year, means an amount equal to—</text><clause id="HDEC17CEAB6A24910B4BE5F3B5E25BBA2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the gross price spike revenue, minus</text></clause><clause id="HBD65778FE42E4F5596677AB405BB69F7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the adjustment amount.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19BC39D813774289BE337E47237F184F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Gross price spike revenue</header><text>The term <term>gross price spike revenue</term>, with respect to a calendar year, means an amount equal to the product of—</text><clause id="HEB20918E5E8D4E5EA0D3223653C51D89"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an amount equal to the difference between clause (i) of paragraph (4)(B) and clause (ii) of such paragraph; and</text></clause><clause id="HBE826812D7C64804B2ECD4CDE839FEB8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total number of units of the insulin product which were sold in commerce in such calendar year.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4ED860185A74342ADA4335524076543"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Adjustment amount</header><text>The term <term>adjustment amount</term> means the amount, if any, of the gross price spike revenue which the Inspector General has determined is due solely to an increase in the cost of the inputs necessary to manufacture the insulin product subject to the price spike.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF6257915F37549CB9C29ECB92DA36854"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Submission by pharmaceutical companies of information to Inspector General</header><paragraph id="H02A53078280C49ACA976930E7A62C25C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For each insulin product, the applicable entity shall submit to the Inspector General a quarterly report that includes each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H0BD1292306CE4C2EB3BD56DAF98D7BB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>For each insulin product of the applicable entity—</text><clause id="H533C24D63D8F455BA0DD876A29A4ECE0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total number of units of the insulin product which were sold in commerce in the preceding calendar quarter;</text></clause><clause id="H80881EA6E99447C6B051BCA6A77757C3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the average and median wholesale acquisition cost per unit of such insulin product in commerce in the preceding calendar quarter, disaggregated by month; and</text></clause><clause id="H2D92B5C3EA6F435888760625300D54AD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the gross revenues from sales of such insulin product in commerce in the preceding calendar quarter.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E548E9F71644E4A9D5DAF10B3F62347"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Such information related to increased input costs or public health considerations as the applicable entity may wish the Inspector General to consider in making a determination under clause (ii) of subsection (c)(2)(B) or an assessment in clause (iii) of such subsection for the preceding calendar quarter.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84839C331FF54C80BADF5941065AA1FC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Such information related to any anticipated increased input costs for the subsequent calendar quarter as the applicable entity may wish the Inspector General to consider in making a determination under clause (ii) of subsection (c)(2)(B) or an assessment in clause (iii) of such subsection for such calendar quarter.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H70E2BDE0A5794080A1D1140101135D5D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalty for failure to submit</header><subparagraph id="HCBBA032EF9F74C3A8C2A5444572D2ECC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An applicable entity described in paragraph (1) that fails to submit information to the Inspector General regarding an insulin product, as required by such paragraph, before the date specified in paragraph (3) shall be liable for a civil penalty, as determined under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4EE3540EE21D4B66BE6D858F9141F92A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Amount of penalty</header><text>The amount of the civil penalty shall be equal to the product of—</text><clause id="HD7503526370046BE8F605F2D8A3FE5F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an amount, as determined appropriate by the Inspector General, which is—</text><subclause id="H6F61287119B64DE68851103627822FDE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>not less than 0.5 percent of the gross revenues from sales of the insulin product described in subparagraph (A) for the preceding calendar year; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H43EC7B2A3DE341DA92571ECA2FA96BC1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>not greater than 1 percent of the gross revenues from sales of such insulin product for the preceding calendar year; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0AFC5D213A6E42888DF019D861127DB8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of days in the period between—</text><subclause id="H8DBAEE53B9E946918CFD6D29AFF49466"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the applicable date specified in paragraph (3); and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD31DFEECE2E443FC9FF089A1D1F4151E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the date on which the Inspector General receives the information described in paragraph (1) from the applicable entity.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C9C2A0C156046B2851BB1C8D88874F6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Submission deadline</header><text>An applicable entity shall submit each quarterly report described in paragraph (1) not later than January 17, April 18, June 15, and September 15 of each calendar year.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5625B2519BBE44AC9792E68AFD278496"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assessment by Inspector General</header><paragraph id="HC88E2217173040B1B235F84A58BE954C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than the last day in February of each year, the Inspector General, in consultation with other relevant Federal agencies (including the Federal Trade Commission), shall—</text><subparagraph id="H9C1A4BE6BEC74F98B904DC11FA5E38C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>complete an assessment of the information the Inspector General received pursuant to subsection (b)(1) with respect to sales of insulin products in the preceding calendar year; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDBE1E553BF44CBCAA972E439D42BAE5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of any insulin product which satisfies the conditions described in paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (d), submit a recommendation to the Secretary of Health and Human Services that such insulin product be exempted from application of the tax imposed under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4191">section 4191</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by subsection (g)) for such year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H176424A3FA6F4FE39CAB8B1D527ED8A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The assessment required by paragraph (1)(A) shall include each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HA2CE6D263F704915A229259B4A70A23D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Identification of each price spike relating to an insulin product in the preceding calendar year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03DC124F7CB14F42AEB262FEE46F0BC0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For each price spike identified under subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H9EFADB489C3B4104B808A3918286A84F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a determination of the price spike revenue;</text></clause><clause id="H6E5717A9A7564DE2BEFBE523C7260FEE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a determination regarding the accuracy of the information submitted by the applicable entity regarding increased input costs; and</text></clause><clause id="H3A840CA2970141399A8B0B3A6D248183"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an assessment of the rationale of the applicable entity for the price spike.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H192C257B1EB04819B9B75925D9ECA270"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exemption of certain insulin products</header><paragraph id="H1DA0AEE6DB174BBC898373F1E5E89F14"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services, upon recommendation of the Inspector General pursuant to subsection (c)(1)(B), may exempt any insulin product which has been subject to a price spike during the preceding calendar year from application of the tax imposed under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4191">section 4191</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 for such year, if the Secretary determines that, based on information submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1)(B), a for-cause price increase exemption should apply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6382F7112E16487F9E2563F663D922C6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>In considering, under paragraph (1), information submitted pursuant to subsection (b)(1)(B), the Secretary—</text><subparagraph id="H02DF639797FC4F6DAA3BACFD601595CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has the discretion to determine that such information does not warrant a for-cause price increase exemption; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDFE695013B8D4D7F87749729D10B024A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall exclude from such consideration any information submitted by the applicable entity threatening to curtail or limit production of the insulin product if the Secretary does not grant an exemption from the application of the tax under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4191">section 4191</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB34ED2B82A27486CB4C6F39AA23589A8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports by Inspector General</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5468917C9D8E44FEB1D608D32E7A11AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Public report</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H20488999C8E144469A2C2C454EF47DE2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than the last day in February of each year, subject to subparagraph (C), the Inspector General shall issue a report containing the information described in subparagraph (B) to be made available to the public, including on the internet website of the Inspector General.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H135C8A8DAA624045898C737258AD2478"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report issued under subparagraph (A) shall include each of the following:</text><clause id="HE69536AF8C444D64ABCCBAC73F80D6EB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The information received under subsection (b)(1) with respect to the preceding calendar year.</text></clause><clause id="H0A2A8F390B9E4BB7A4BD5C6A555566F6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The price spikes identified under subparagraph (A) of subsection (c)(2).</text></clause><clause id="H44347DF9E0E74F4CAB23CCE952AB5859"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The price spike revenue determinations made under subparagraph (B)(i) of such subsection.</text></clause><clause id="HFB16C22CE7844C3A9DD7AC696748BE52"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The determinations and assessments made under clauses (ii) and (iii) of subparagraph (B) of such subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5628C8C392614EB4906B1AD762B2B580"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Proprietary information</header><text>The Inspector General shall ensure that any information made public in accordance with subparagraph (A) excludes trade secrets and confidential commercial information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2ED7AA25BB29476CA8BED379F9F6235B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to Internal Revenue Service</header><subparagraph id="H282C88B0CE17465798489E51D686B526"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (C), not later than the last day in February of each year, the Inspector General shall transmit to the Internal Revenue Service a report on the findings of the Inspector General with respect to the information the Inspector General received under subsection (b)(1) with respect to the preceding calendar year and the assessment carried out by the Inspector General under subsection (c)(1)(A) with respect to such information.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B97F251888C4A9FA6D134CC72F73695"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report transmitted under subparagraph (A) shall include the information described in paragraph (1)(B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46743F09A7764833A281F84B4043AF61"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity for hearing</header><clause id="HED963ACAF8E848B2BC2EA69AAD76D76A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No report shall be transmitted to the Internal Revenue Service under subparagraph (A) with respect to an insulin product unless the Inspector General has provided the applicable entity with—</text><subclause id="HD1D081781DED4BE3BD3711C5BC7D3104"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the assessment of such insulin product under subsection (c)(1)(A); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H334328FAC1B44BABB929BFC280ECD1AA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>notice of their right to a hearing in regards to such assessment.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H4838C3267D7C41D7B4AE225BCBEEDF05"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>The notice required under clause (i) shall be provided to the applicable entity not later than 30 days after completion of the assessment under subsection (c)(1)(A).</text></clause><clause id="HAFDB9DFF08FB4935842CEAA768CE1B4E"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Request for hearing</header><text>Subject to clause (v), an applicable entity may request a hearing before the Secretary of Health and Human Services not later than 30 days after the date on which the notice under clause (ii) is received.</text></clause><clause id="H7FE5330731C749CCB8FC0E21449C0D23"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Completion of hearing</header><text>In the case of an applicable entity which requests a hearing pursuant to clause (iii), the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall, not later than 12 months after the date on which the assessment under subsection (c)(1)(A) was completed by the Inspector General—</text><subclause id="HBEAA7636FD4F48BF9E2C6F10931F35A8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>make a final determination in regards to the accuracy of such assessment; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H29BA9FDEB9EC40F8906195138E4BFDA3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>provide the report described in subparagraph (B) to the Internal Revenue Service.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H1BF3C3A7DD4740B689E397277A0E6B64"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>An applicable entity may request a hearing under clause (iii) with respect to a particular insulin product only once within a 5-year period.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B73BEC6BBB34615BF691BA4B9096E35"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall notify, at such time and in such manner as the Secretary of the Treasury shall provide, each applicable entity in regard to any insulin product which has been determined to have been subject to a price spike during the preceding calendar year and the amount of the tax imposed on such applicable entity pursuant to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4191">section 4191</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subsection><subsection id="H40EA70D5B0C74D94974AAE9184BCB297"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Excise tax on insulin products subject to price spikes</header><paragraph id="HD2AF684DCA2C4781959F7F849E80349D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/32">Chapter 32</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after subchapter D the following new subchapter:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43E16A9141574D04AABC132FA9F68DB6"><subchapter id="H85536F572BB94B30B0D6E389DE59B0F4" style="OLC"><enum>E</enum><header>Certain insulin products</header><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="HB90536EE982844BEBB7F194E20BED49C">Sec. 4191. Insulin products subject to price spikes.</toc-entry></toc><section id="HB90536EE982844BEBB7F194E20BED49C"><enum>4191.</enum><header>Insulin products subject to price spikes</header><subsection id="H06F379C52F154D028C65824E82CE7C9E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Imposition of tax</header><paragraph id="HC20A226FBD5C4498B0A7C6B0CE7FCEEA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (3), for each taxable insulin product sold by an applicable entity during the calendar year, there is hereby imposed on such entity a tax equal to the greater of—</text><subparagraph id="HD095B96CAEE14BA9984515F35FA6F74B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the annual price spike tax for such insulin product, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF2CBF21729F42F28ED03D89B05702BB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (2), the cumulative price spike tax for such insulin product.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CED0A718746416AB874FD1E6CF8DA09"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>In the case of a taxable insulin product for which the applicable period (as determined under subsection (c)(2)(E)(i)) is less than 2 calendar years, the cumulative price spike tax shall not apply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E41729A35AD44C1A2361AC555711398"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>For any calendar year in which the Secretary of Health and Human Services has provided an exemption for a taxable insulin product pursuant to section 4(d) of the <short-title>Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</short-title>, the amount of the tax determined under paragraph (1) for such insulin product for such calendar year shall be reduced to zero.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08EA3578A06D499A8E48DE32D2562587"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual price spike tax</header><paragraph id="H820950BCEDA943C89E05BAE78D7E13B7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amount of the annual price spike tax shall be equal to the applicable percentage of the price spike revenue received by the applicable entity on the sale of the taxable insulin product during the calendar year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE554466048DB4BF0B9E3EBC796253B4A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable percentage</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the applicable percentage shall be equal to—</text><subparagraph id="H6FFDB0E382A74741A2C87E767690319A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the case of a taxable insulin product which has been subject to a price spike percentage greater than the applicable price increase allowance (as defined in section 4(a)(4)(C) of the <short-title>Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</short-title>) but less than 15 percent, 50 percent,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF204973282D8467E9ED42B04C93A6D77"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of a taxable insulin product which has been subject to a price spike percentage equal to or greater than 15 percent but less than 20 percent, 75 percent, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDD1F6F596224049B49A0932A7D9ADEE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the case of a taxable insulin product which has been subject to a price spike percentage equal to or greater than 20 percent, 100 percent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6E1A98F4611649F891430DDE9F0E450E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cumulative price spike tax</header><paragraph id="H4AA0B6E7C96B4BB5A37DB17FF55B7832"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amount of the cumulative price spike tax shall be equal to the applicable percentage of the cumulative price spike revenue received by the applicable entity on the sale of the taxable insulin product during the calendar year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE67181CBA5A42D394C02EE1C64F5A94"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable percentage</header><subparagraph id="H6764E4FB9D154783A45BFEA9079907FD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the applicable percentage shall be equal to—</text><clause id="H085291CB934242A597BB082A5AEF0862"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of a taxable insulin product which has been subject to a cumulative price spike percentage greater than the cumulative price increase allowance but less than the first multi-year percentage, 50 percent,</text></clause><clause id="H0E2C39B40C89433BB254A5335A0201A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a taxable insulin product which has been subject to a cumulative price spike percentage equal to or greater than the first multi-year percentage but less than the second multi-year percentage, 75 percent, and</text></clause><clause id="H9F5A97ABAD8F42C5ABFC4A7CAB161D94"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of a taxable insulin product which has been subject to a cumulative price spike percentage equal to or greater than the second multi-year percentage, 100 percent.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE0961C3AE09948C281DAD6DE0A37B293"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Cumulative price spike percentage</header><text>The cumulative price spike percentage is the percentage (if any) by which—</text><clause id="HCC97A84CB1A342EF8335F4B57178CE50"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost of the taxable insulin product in commerce for the preceding calendar year, exceeds</text></clause><clause id="H38E2ACC00DE541DCA5D03003CE73B99C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost of such insulin product in commerce for the base year.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD710E9AA526B4D4683039475A2FB60C2"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Cumulative price increase allowance</header><text>For purposes of clause (i) of subparagraph (A), the cumulative price increase allowance for any calendar year is the percentage (rounded to the nearest one-tenth of 1 percent) by which the C–CPI–U (as defined in section 1(f)(6)) for that year exceeds the C–CPI–U for the base year.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD01AC15E77594BA9A5D25E19A2B6A4E9"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Multi-year percentages</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), the first multi-year percentage and second multi-year percentage shall be determined in accordance with the following table:</text><table blank-lines-before="1" align-to-level="section" colsep="1" frame="topbot" line-rules="hor-ver" rowsep="0" rule-weights="4.4.4.0.0.0" table-template-name="Generic: 1 text, 2 num" table-type=""><tgroup cols="3" grid-typeface="1.1" rowsep="0" thead-tbody-ldg-size="10.10.12"><colspec coldef="txt" colname="column1" colwidth="202pts" min-data-value="180"></colspec><colspec coldef="fig" colname="column2" colwidth="136.69pt" min-data-value="10"></colspec><colspec coldef="fig" colname="column3" colwidth="97.06pt" min-data-value="10" rowsep="0"></colspec><thead><row><entry align="center" colname="column1" morerows="0" namest="column1" rowsep="1">Number of years in applicable period</entry><entry align="center" colname="column2" morerows="0" namest="column2" rowsep="1">First<linebreak></linebreak> multi-year<linebreak></linebreak> percentage</entry><entry align="center" colname="column3" morerows="0" namest="column3" rowsep="1">Second<linebreak></linebreak> multi-year<linebreak></linebreak> percentage</entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">2 years</entry><entry align="right" colname="column2" rowsep="0">17.5</entry><entry align="right" colname="column3" rowsep="0">22.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">3 years</entry><entry align="right" colname="column2" rowsep="0">20.0</entry><entry align="right" colname="column3" rowsep="0">25.0</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">4 years</entry><entry align="right" colname="column2" rowsep="0">22.5</entry><entry align="right" colname="column3" rowsep="0">27.5</entry></row><row><entry align="left" colname="column1" rowsep="0" stub-definition="txt-ldr" stub-hierarchy="1">5 years</entry><entry align="right" colname="column2" rowsep="0">25.0</entry><entry align="right" colname="column3" rowsep="0">30.0.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H419037FF62074251B7D8C52B2C98BD1D"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Applicable period and base year</header><clause id="H017FBC669CA74C1CAB8A525E64B30B75"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Applicable period</header><text>The applicable period shall be the lesser of—</text><subclause id="H4BFEF114C3CE46EC8BC655176788A938"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the 5 preceding calendar years,</text></subclause><subclause id="HD30CF1AE4534478DBCB03632B9A875CF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>all calendar years beginning after the date of enactment of this section, or</text></subclause><subclause id="H2C98C39CA2BB4307A7D2E9161598A718"><enum>(III)</enum><text>all calendar years in which the taxable insulin product was sold in commerce.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9726B7A99E4A44C2A166E4AC81963E5A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Base year</header><text>The base year shall be the calendar year immediately preceding the applicable period.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCCE676BF0A243AA9DB40AAA211F8077"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cumulative price spike revenue</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the cumulative price spike revenue for any taxable insulin product shall be an amount equal to—</text><subparagraph id="HC2F7077EF5D94BDC80B2022D39A879BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an amount equal to the product of—</text><clause id="H74DEB0A68AB04DEBB3367CC4A5A41A5E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an amount (not less than zero) equal to—</text><subclause id="H93C1EBB6B5914E51BBFC87D8E8552D10"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost of such insulin product in commerce for the preceding calendar year, minus</text></subclause><subclause id="H311F1E8755354EA481FD47091D255771"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost of such insulin product in commerce for the base year, and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HCBEEDE99E9A04F9B8A17666D696BD67C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total number of units of such insulin product which were sold in commerce in the preceding calendar year, minus</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C0086234467414897E8BE1246647EF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an amount equal to the sum of the adjustment amounts, if any, determined under section 4(a)(5)(C) of the <short-title>Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</short-title> for each calendar year during the applicable period.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBC8C392C834249E3A0188A0EEB858ACA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="HD5247E6B1BE5423A843BB02404FA974C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Taxable insulin product</header><text>The term <term>taxable insulin product</term> means an insulin product which has been identified by the Inspector General of the Department of Health and Human Services, under section 4(c)(2)(A) of the <short-title>Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</short-title>, as being subject to a price spike.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23412CC8D1614370A14259C4CBB4DE90"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other terms</header><text>The terms <term>applicable entity</term>, <term>price spike</term>, <term>price spike percentage</term>, and <term>price spike revenue</term> have the same meaning given such terms under section 4(a) of the <short-title>Emergency Access to Insulin Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></subchapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C6A3F7B218049CABB4D780764932484"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of subchapters for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/32">chapter 32</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after the item relating to subchapter D the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H68B2FDD9FFFD49EEB04A0DE73CE86AB3"><toc><toc-entry level="subchapter" idref="H85536F572BB94B30B0D6E389DE59B0F4">SUBCHAPTER E—Certain insulin products</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H8676D4D717B34D638BE43DEAC82148A1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to sales after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5A5DF5A9B08849A1A7A37492C361F56F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Biological product exclusivity</header><subsection id="H0BE4B33D9BE74E99B62494C4ACD02C19"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 351(k)(7)(A) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(k)(7)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>12 years</quote> and inserting <quote>7 years</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H72C7839D6A0040CF9509A12CE51AA338"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text>Paragraphs (2)(A) and (3)(A) of section 351(m) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(m)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>12 years</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>7 years</quote>.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

