<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H653553ADA05F449185C54577E93A2D20" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1761 IH: Let Experienced Pilots Fly Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1761</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000048">Mr. Pfluger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001212">Mr. Moore of Alabama</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001095">Mr. Hunt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000603">Mr. Rouzer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000626">Mr. Davidson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000609">Mr. Rutherford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 49, United States Code, to raise the retirement age for pilots engaged in commercial aviation operations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB99C1BD6E0C244418428E66C3E0FD155" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H63BC064A015E4F8FB59AB99B1E6D3CA3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Let Experienced Pilots Fly Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB7B9AD4202D044E5A696D2CFDD5D2310"><enum>2.</enum><header>Increased retirement age for pilots</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 44729 of title 49, United States Code, as amended by section 107 of division Q of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>), is further amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1102974ED9B4CE8AD0039ECC163BAC3"> 
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H784FA725148A4D76B552F4CC8A5D9467" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>44729.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Age standards for pilots</header> 
<subsection id="HC99B12C189304D01997E554BBDC7E1C1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A pilot may serve in multicrew covered operations until 67 years of age.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HAF76B1DAA1C940928E4473F98A054F39" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered operations defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered operations</term> means operations under part 121 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, unless the operation takes place in—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD0359054AA2644A7B5D76F91D96FB66C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the territorial airspace of a foreign country where such operations are prohibited by the foreign country; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7BE6AE42D88A48EBB89BC5773AEBB265" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>international airspace where such operations are not in compliance with the Annexes to the Convention on International Civil Aviation.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2380DD385F9D409A954930AF811E460A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>On and after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Let Experienced Pilots Fly Act of 2023</short-title>, subsections (d) and (e) of section 121.383 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, shall be deemed to have been amended to increase the age listed in such subsections to 67 years of age. </text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H86DA82478D3E4134B7CC765D9E85532C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applicability</header> <paragraph id="H86A6E35D7CB644F49E8168041F58ED82"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Retroactivity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A pilot who is over 65 years of age on the date of enactment of this bill may return to service in multicrew covered operations until 67 years of age. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3477022E246E420A80EE1BAC517AC5D0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Protection for compliance</header><text>An action taken in conformance with this section, taken in conformance with a regulation issued to carry out this section, or taken prior to the date of enactment of the <short-title>Let Experienced Pilots Fly Act of 2023</short-title> in conformance with subsection (d) or (e) of section 121.383 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect before such date), may not serve as a basis for liability or relief in a proceeding, brought under any employment law or regulation, before any court or agency of the United States or of any State or locality.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H527D537ED34D41BBACDACEFBF1F08D57"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Amendments to labor agreements and benefit plans</header><text>Any amendment to a labor agreement or benefit plan of an air carrier that is required to conform with the requirements of this section or a regulation issued to carry out this section, and is applicable to pilots represented for collective bargaining, shall be made by agreement of the air carrier and the designated bargaining representative of the pilots of the air carrier.</text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36C6BA0EF071439FB399CF2B96C04002"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Medical standards and records</header> 
<paragraph id="H946DC6171EFC4B32B0C77DBC952CFBB3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Medical examinations and standards</header><text>Except as provided by paragraph (2), a person serving as a pilot for an air carrier engaged in covered operations shall not be subject to different medical standards, or different, greater, or more frequent medical examinations, on account of age unless the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration determines (based on data received or studies published after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Let Experienced Pilots Fly Act of 2023</short-title>) that different medical standards, or different, greater, or more frequent medical examinations, are needed to ensure an adequate level of safety in flight.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A477D159E3C48FAA7B60BE03C8D19D7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration of first-class medical certificate</header><text>No person who has attained 60 years of age may serve as a pilot of an air carrier engaged in covered operations unless the person has a first-class medical certificate. Such a certificate shall expire on the last day of the 6-month period following the date of examination shown on the certificate.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8FB5ECAEE7A8427889CCE23B826E4CEB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Safety training</header><text>Each air carrier engaged in covered operations shall continue to use pilot training and qualification programs approved by the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H38585D9522D544A7B2CD84C1CFFC8B91"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on further increasing the age limitation described in subsection (a). </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

