<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HA60D566F1C8F463FA7AF991E0BDD7DCB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3836 RH: Medicaid Primary Care Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 134</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3836</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–170]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230606">June 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001199">Mr. Smucker</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on June 6, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To facilitate direct primary care arrangements under Medicaid.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HIF00" reported-display-style="italic" id="HE7C721B0CEE04A5DA365D793E301AF23"><section id="H9B6E2C4274964617B4C6771E4BC97DDC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Medicaid Primary Care Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5485A5A68C634E8E8F59CEB702457D7E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Clarifying that certain payment arrangements are allowable under the medicaid program</header><subsection id="H92674210C4A542D79DF5172755C8BFD3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) shall be construed as prohibiting a State, under its State plan (or waiver of such plan) under such title (including through a medicaid managed care organization (as defined in section 1903(m)(1)(A) of such Act)), from providing medical assistance consisting of primary care services through a direct primary care arrangement with a health care provider, including as part of a value-based care arrangement established by the State. For purposes of the preceding sentence, the term <quote>direct primary care arrangement</quote> means, with respect to any individual, an arrangement under which such individual is provided medical assistance consisting solely of primary care services provided by primary care practitioners, if the sole compensation for such care is a fixed periodic fee.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBA578068799D4DE88E194BED1D879B88"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall—</text><paragraph id="HBBCE34711D6C452E86FF02ACC5BD930F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">convene at least one virtual open door meeting to seek input from stakeholders, including primary care providers who practice under the direct primary care model, state Medicaid agencies, and Medicaid managed care organizations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7AB8B3E58234641BE60372725B73CF2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>taking into account such input, issue guidance to States on how a State may implement direct primary care arrangements (as defined in subsection (a)) under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H29EC07DE0CAF47AB8F4CA9063C32C576"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall submit to Congress a report containing—</text><paragraph id="H263C9684A5E34D75AACBA03AEF5DDD7C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an analysis of the extent to which States are contracting with independent physicians, independent physician practices, and primary care practices for purposes of furnishing medical assistance under State plans (or waivers of such plans) under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29CDC2B1F3CE4EB38622DFD4F6E5D270"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an analysis of quality of care and cost of care furnished to individuals enrolled under such title where such care is paid for under a direct primary care arrangement (as defined in subsection (a)) through a medicaid managed care organization (as so defined).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE804EE93765247D88013C090C23C4247"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to alter statutory requirements under the State plan (or waiver of such plan) under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) for cost-sharing requirements or be construed to limit medical assistance solely to those provided under a direct primary care arrangement.</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

