<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H79A2877AF3364C838103033A52CCD5E8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6325 IH: Stop Stealing Like There’s No Tomorrow Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6325</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231109">November 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To identify Ukrainian government officials in violation of the End-Use Monitoring agreement and to prohibit their entry into the United States.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H453C4169CAC0498F8DC7944F587BCA11" style="OLC"><section id="H4DFB43416CF04191ABACBD5FF9B157B3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Stealing Like There’s No Tomorrow Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HABB17D61B11349BDBBD625CBF104233A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Identifying violators of End-Use Monitoring and prohibiting such individuals from United States entry</header><subsection id="HAC95AB6D6E004533BD61DE1A58B5D9DE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Certification of end-Use monitoring compliance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 120 days thereafter, the Secretary of Defense and Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that contains the following:</text><paragraph id="H942186F7CD874C528619D16F819295AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A thorough analysis of the manner and extent to which the Government of Ukraine has been in compliance with end-use monitoring for all defense articles sold, leased, and exported under the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2751">22 U.S.C. 2751</external-xref>) as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H6D7CF1F103BB4B48AEEFB51C9D86F7CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Compliance with the Blue Lantern Program of the Department of State on and after February 24, 2022.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC08FD58E9E04F1685DDC08473583F03"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Compliance with the Golden Sentry Program of the Department of Defense on and after February 24, 2022.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5770201114764372AD2DDA99E49B4130"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A list of each official of the Government of Ukraine that the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of State determine have acted in violation of either end-use monitoring program described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEBF50072440044AEAFB8D1590006BD2B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visas</header><text>Each alien included on the list described in subsection (a)(2) shall be—</text><paragraph id="H167D4B3FB69B45F29B3FE859E23476D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA71F05EC34A646A2B1A63E83B453E298"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF001546D9B9F4612A2518C86FBD07CF3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD24E58ED9C8940E4BB5558A738ECE198"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Revocation of current visas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The visa or other entry documentation of any alien included on the list described in section (a)(2) is subject to revocation regardless of the issue date of the visa or other entry documentation. Such revocation shall, in accordance with section 221(i) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1201">8 U.S.C. 1201(i)</external-xref>), take effect immediately and cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the possession of the alien.</text></subsection><subsection id="H404CD266383F4E64A3FACD0BF7017FCE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>In this Act, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H32551F0A713044AE98A40B1E3C2106C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87A2552095AD4FD982FFD103660408A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

