<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H10888B9DBC634612A2B6DD07D6ABCA8C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3144 IH: Prairie Band Potawatomi Nation Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation Settlement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3144</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the settlement of claims relating to the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation in Illinois, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBB287C04B61F4D5491BA4BE2CEDD5C3C" style="OLC"><section id="HFBB4C077C478412A96D05FF461F40D02" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Prairie Band Potawatomi Nation Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation Settlement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3ED01AE94A234ABCA599350C7C349D5A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purposes</header><subsection id="HB37A5812B2904D9CA213BE4EB85A9D1B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds that—</text><paragraph id="H72F0296198F746F0AB44A5A535CB38FD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>pursuant to the Treaty of July 29, 1829, made and concluded at Prairie du Chien (7 Stat. 320) (commonly known as the <quote>Second Treaty of Prairie du Chien</quote>), the Potawatomi and other affected Indian Tribes ceded certain land in northern Illinois, except for 2 parcels totaling 1,280 acres for Potawatomi Chief Shab-eh-nay and his Band at their village near Paw Paw Grove, Illinois;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3440D35F66F4462BD337F0DFDFEF86D"><enum>(2)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H6C4E4784F37F4A9DAC25ED07D21636AA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>pursuant to the Treaty of September 26, 1833, made at Chicago (7 Stat. 431) (commonly known as the <quote>Treaty of Chicago</quote>), the Potawatomi and other Indians ceded approximately 5,000,000 acres of land, including the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation; but</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F7E402B960D4B9CA4608673C0268E14" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Senate rejected the provision that ceded that reservation, with the effect of affirming the Indian-held title and boundaries of the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CB6207D3900480BA8CCB4BBB5524360"><enum>(3)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HF2C05FD16DD8461AA298DEA5DBDB835F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in 1849, while Chief Shab-eh-nay was visiting his relatives in Kansas, the Commissioner of the General Land Office of the United States sold the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation at public auction to non-Indians who erroneously believed that they had acquired good title to the land on which the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation is located; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF538AC3467C4EF6B731C2A5FECE4DE1" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation is illegally occupied as of the date of the enactment of this Act;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BC6ECA8EDDA4621A5B405BC2E3095A3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation continues to exist;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8318D8E6BE464A5187ED975F603E6F8E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>there is no evidence that Chief Shab-eh-nay and his band abandoned the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation which, even if true, could not be the basis for extinguishing the treaty-recognized Indian title to the Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C9475425E3C4B778CD78144838D956D"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Shab-eh-nay Band held recognized title to the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF4059592DE0437FACBC859FF4A2A6DB"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Congress has never acted by treaty or statute to extinguish the recognized Indian title to the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H981B6EDFA0E440B2A03804964112479A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Tribe is the successor in interest to Chief Shab-eh-nay’s Band and the rightful owner and occupant of the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H350AC504B45B41F696CD4B1F8A47A05D"><enum>(9)</enum><text>the United States continues to bear a trust responsibility to the Tribe for the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H965C74517D5D4832944BA556B5D58355"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Tribe pursued a claim against the United States under the Act entitled <quote>An Act to create an Indian Claims Commission, to provide for the powers, duties, and functions thereof, and for other purposes</quote>, approved August 13, 1946 (commonly known as the <quote>Indian Claims Commission Act</quote>) and was paid for the loss of certain lands in northern Illinois, but the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation was specifically excluded by the Commission from the lands for which it awarded additional compensation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7103EC2E1B244D8DB233A6539CEF1880"><enum>(11)</enum><text>the Federal Government, through the actions of the General Land Office, has deprived the Tribe of the right of exclusive use and occupancy of the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation without legal authorization or just compensation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H625F289CB3654C21B9A548B844565855"><enum>(12)</enum><text>certain non-Indian individuals, entities, and local governments occupying land within the boundaries of the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation as of the date of the enactment of this Act, including the State and the County—</text><subparagraph id="HA08DC28C12DD47978B1901CCA5EAC58B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>acquired ownership interests to the land in good faith; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H043E04F8128E41F582AE73EDA38DF87B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>should be able to possess clear title to the land; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FA4566F4E59438596C33124023028F4"><enum>(13)</enum><text>the United States has a moral and legal responsibility—</text><subparagraph id="H047BA5D0B2F44C829351BEE80525929B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to help secure a fair and equitable settlement of past inequities to the Tribe; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A7819CD091046BF9F9CB2E2CC03FF55"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to ensure protection of the ownership interests of non-Indian occupants of the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H053D4B2A51574CBC8476ABFCCEC39000"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of this Act are—</text><paragraph id="H9BA6250301D64DFA920E18711941D6BF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to acknowledge the unlawful sale by the Federal Government of the valuable right held by the Tribe to the exclusive use and occupancy of the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3060A9827C14098904F91A6AF551166"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to reaffirm Federal recognition of the ownership by the Tribe of, and jurisdiction over, land that the Tribe owns within the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A75F6F3FD1745A69DBF0DB3A2479D44"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to promote the economic self-sufficiency of the Tribe and the members of the Tribe;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9027B67437F47438EFA5B4851EE490B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to extinguish the Indian title to, and confirm the ownership by the State, the County, and certain individuals and entities of, certain land within the boundaries of the Shab-eh-nay Band Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F683F5A42824134BF8C380EB7DFEBC1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to provide stability and security to the State and residents of the State, the local governments and the areas over which the local governments exercise jurisdiction, and businesses regarding the ownership and use by the Tribe of the Reaffirmed Reservation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H710F5F1FE44343B0917BC5798A420122"><enum>(6)</enum><text>to extinguish potential claims by the Tribe against the United States, the State, the local governments, and private individuals and entities that could be a direct consequence of not reaching a settlement with the Tribe;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78B880EFFD2C4382AF6DF3726ADD8400"><enum>(7)</enum><text>to require the Secretary to preserve and protect, but not manage, the Reaffirmed Reservation in furtherance of the trust responsibility of the Federal Government; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE9E384787D84B94A8F870533EFF5FE0"><enum>(8)</enum><text>to authorize the Secretary—</text><subparagraph id="H89104A88CA264679B53510DBA83301B8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to execute the waiver and release of claims and compensate the Tribe; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H38DE4E9E9DAD46ECB7964D0E960B8882"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to take any other action necessary to carry out this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5FD2A5D6CDAD4C01B1DD1298E149B500"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H7D004003658B451CBC779981757136B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>County</header><text>The term <term>County</term> means Dekalb County in the State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5D57AF9CE93483C93F6E765F0C63150"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Local government</header><text>The term <term>local government</term> means any unit of local government that exercises authority over land located within the Reservation as of the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H823495AC73E74E1FB0D86B05F6BF88CF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reaffirmed reservation</header><text>The term <term>Reaffirmed Reservation</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H71E6BAC1783646DEA0B287FF0160CE37"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Reservation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA2A1CED5EF74257870DDE6D03841A14"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any land located within the Replacement Area that is held in trust after being taken into trust by the Secretary of the Interior for the benefit of the Tribe after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H99D3F4CE04834D628E97DFA88EE76271"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Replacement area</header><text>The term <term>Replacement Area</term> means the aboriginal territory of the Tribe, located in the State near Shabbona, which is all of the approximated land that is bounded as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H7473C9D818C44875BA4E392B83101619"><enum>(A)</enum><text>On the north by Interstate 88.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H91D699FB764A4477A6565F63D319F35B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>On the west by Interstate 39.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57972E07BFA94C9F8DB0FA39E8C3C380"><enum>(C)</enum><text>On the south by State Route 30 and Preserve Road.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H92D0F1F35590442D839C49467408CA2B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>On the east by South 4th Street and State Route 23.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B5A59EAF2D2400CB885F7A6F6250951"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Repurchased Lands</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Repurchased Lands</term> means the approximately 129 acres of land purchased and owned by the Tribe within the Reservation as of the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H38CE26B79B93471B80F15A44CF1ADCF2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Reservation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Reservation</term> means the approximately 1,280 acres of land in the State reserved in the treaty of July 29, 1829 (7 Stat. 320) and the Treaty of September 26, 1833 (7 STAT. 431) and described as follows: sec. 23, the W\1/2\ of sec. 25, and the E\1/2\ of sec. 26 in T. 38 N., R. 3 E., Third Principal Meridian.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF12AAC9ADE6442FFB34544C0CCF315C8"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FCC6A058C5042DAA700C4F88F0452C2"><enum>(8)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means the State of Illinois.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AE489C5CD5846B5B08D3E1357686814"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Tribe</term> means the Prairie Band Potawatomi Nation, a federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF3B75F5D476747678447080A10831DA1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reaffirmation of shab-eh-nay band reservation</header><subsection id="H1E95D6E970A74D59A7B204F1EC52518E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reaffirmation of reservation status</header><text>The Repurchased Lands is reaffirmed as Indian Country (as that term is defined in section 1151 of title 18, United States Code).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0139EA41539547D8BAD534AC3FAFC0C5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transfer of lands into trust</header><text>If, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Tribe transfers title to any or all of the Repurchased Lands to the United States, the Secretary, not later than 180 days after such transfer, shall take the transferred land into trust for the benefit of the Tribe.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDEB029ED6392408CA0AEAD65571C171C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>Repurchased Lands transferred under subsection (b) shall be part of the Reaffirmed Reservation and administered in accordance with the laws and regulations generally applicable to land held in trust by the United States for an Indian tribe.</text></subsection></section><section id="HCC0EF153D5DA44AC9BF5C443F188955E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Extinguishment of Indian title; confirmation of land ownership</header><subsection id="H60BB599B80C74BED881CE409A54C3172"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Extinguishment of Indian title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Tribe’s Indian title to all lands within the exterior boundaries of the reservation as of the date of enactment of this Act, except for the Repurchased Lands, is extinguished.</text></subsection><subsection id="H329BC336700944B09F4F3DC8EAB2C857"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Confirmation of land ownership</header><text>Title to lands and interests in lands within the exterior boundaries of the Reservation held by the State, the local governments, or any individual or entity on November 5, 1849, is recognized and confirmed.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE2627D0A2B6948D8A18AF1F745B2FDA1"><enum>6.</enum><header>Waiver and release of claims</header><subsection id="H2B41273160BA4DE38FBDCE350744E821"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Claims against united states, state, local governments, and other parties</header><text>The Tribe and the Secretary shall execute appropriate documents providing for the relinquishment by the Tribe of all claims against—</text><paragraph id="HFBCAC432C9B4424BA6ED374F0B77F6FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the United States for a breach of the trust responsibility associated with any sale of any portion of the Reservation; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A01127F51A24D439FF40CB71EE43D11"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the State, the local governments, and any individuals or entities occupying the Reservation for any trespass and related damages in connection with the occupation and use of the Reservation during the period beginning on November 5, 1849, and ending on the effective date described in subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1CE5519DD2CB4B51BA5630FC814F065E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The relinquishment of claims under subsection (a) shall take effect on the later of—</text><paragraph id="H63AE545EE6DA4E0CAAEB0F34E861FDEC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which the Tribe receives payment of all of the settlement funds under section 7; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H73775F8BDB2E4F03A7BAFC341585BA45"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date on which the Secretary publishes in the Federal Register a notice that the documents described in subsection (a) have been executed by the Secretary and the Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H5E4F7BFC5F604E2491E78071588F55D3"><enum>7.</enum><header>Settlement funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subject to the appropriation of funds, the Secretary shall pay to the Tribe $50,000,000 over 5 years in full settlement of the claims of the Tribe, to be managed, invested, and used by the Tribe to promote economic development and land acquisition, as determined by the Tribe in accordance with the constitution and laws of the Tribe.</text></section><section id="H295B8051B0BE48749CFFC3F186888E46"><enum>8.</enum><header>Land acquisition; tribal authority to enter into agreements; no use of condemnation or eminent domain</header><subsection id="H0157DF40BEAE41DB948F4CAC63E8BC86"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Land acquisition</header><paragraph id="H192075A00B614E35AA5F92749B17B68D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After the date of the enactment of this Act, the Tribe may acquire from one or more willing sellers not more than a total of 1,151 acres of land within the exterior boundaries of or abutting the Reservation, or within the exterior boundaries of the Replacement Area using the settlement funds received by the Tribe under section 7 or other funds of the Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B62935E300041B4A55E42EACA630929"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transfer of additional lands into trust</header><text>At the request of the Tribe, the Secretary shall take into trust for the benefit of the Tribe any lands acquired under paragraph (1) not later than 180 days after the Tribe transfers title to such lands to the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H57C98BA95E834973AFE5787AA52178FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recognition of tribal government authority To enter into agreements with state and local governments</header><text>The Tribe may enter into agreements with the State and any local government regarding the Reaffirmed Reservation and activities occurring on the Reaffirmed Reservation, including agreements relating to jurisdiction, land use, and services.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3AC97CB0212F40BA8DA026845BF337E5" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No use of condemnation or eminent domain</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Land or interests in land within the exterior boundaries of the Reservation or the Replacement Area—</text><paragraph id="H938387014E7B4AC7A71DE2A7A91F1D08" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>may not be acquired by condemnation or eminent domain under this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2F9524C4B014DA78B1860E9C57FF739" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall be acquired only by purchase with payment of fair market value.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9577B75EE9734E1EA9387A0795099907"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cultural and historic preservation of reservation</header><text>Land owned by the State and the local governments located within the boundaries of the Reservation shall be managed to protect any human or cultural remains, consistent with applicable Federal and State law and subject to the consent of the Tribe.</text></subsection></section><section id="H604A8C29028F41F0BDC4CD2BCF0FA350"><enum>9.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this Act $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

