<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6BC8E6FB4B784197AF441947E4A2E5CD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2542 IH: Infrastructure Expansion Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2542</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230406">April 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000600">Mr. Langworthy</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To preclude absolute liability in any action against a property owner or contractor for projects receiving Federal financial assistance for infrastructure and transportation development, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H64A7133BC6AB43F0894EEE9199D653E1" style="OLC"><section id="H85BA0812032D44AC9FDE99CEF7C83C66" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Infrastructure Expansion Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9B3AC01F4D504AF18DE6D2F15CEA416F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Preservation of Federal financial assistance for infrastructure and transportation development</header><subsection id="H8B3537892EE5431A88881E12864264E7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>No absolute liability on certain projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For any project for which Federal financial assistance is used, directly or indirectly, no action on the basis of absolute liability may be instituted by a covered person against a property owner or a party to a contract relating to the property that is the subject of the project for any injury associated with an elevation or gravity related risk occurring on that project.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8EAC8A9F15F94A799CA90FB7BB7E0267"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Comparative negligence liability standard for certain claims</header><text>For any project for which Federal financial assistance is used, a State shall apply to any claim brought by a covered person against a property owner or contractor for an injury associated with an elevation or gravity related risk a comparative negligence liability standard that considers the comparative negligence of the injured person for any claim in which—</text><paragraph id="HC3C75C645CF14C11A21136F356EDC669"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such negligence is a proximate cause of an injury to a person; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69C45C7108E8461691A98BCC7C5AA819"><enum>(2)</enum><text>State law would otherwise apply absolute liability as the basis for such claim.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H329E1F966A584228AFB8779AD7F581E5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HA2339D30F9404957A9CFCF875A0CFD1F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>absolute liability</term> means liability for a personal injury or death that is imposed without consideration of the responsibility of the injured person, including failure to follow safety instructions or safe work practices in accordance with training provided, failure to utilize provided safety equipment or devices, impairment by the use of drugs or alcohol, or involvement in a criminal act, when such failure, impairment, or act is a proximate cause of an injury to such person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E26AA60A4C84995B6B5975D72567753"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered person</term> means any person who supervises or performs any work on or who is otherwise affiliated with a project.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80EFA97A49524028B97EAD01C060B49B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>elevation or gravity related risk</term> means a hazard related to the effects of gravity either due to the difference between the elevation level of the required work and a lower level or a difference between the elevation level where the worker is positioned and the higher level of the materials or load being hoisted or secured.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E60F568719442DABEBDD2A7933442BD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>project</term> means the erection, demolition, repairing, altering, painting, cleaning or pointing of a highway, bridge, tunnel, airport, railway, bus or railroad station, depot, pier, building, or any other structure owned or operated by the Federal Government or for which Federal financial assistance is used.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DD474FCD0924B7FA77CDF82316A2937"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The term <term>State</term> includes a port authority, transit agency, public toll authority, metropolitan planning organization, or other political subdivision of a State or local government.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCFA4B87E88CB42F88184278461B3A5C1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Workers’ compensation laws</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to preempt any law of a State providing for workers’ compensation.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDF0FD76338364EB4A842AFC41B93D358"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section applies to claims arising from projects in which a State or local government accepts Federal financial assistance on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

