<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H44C491B3BDEC46FDB4114673A13C6A62" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3263 IH: Support Faculty and Expand Access to Nursing School Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3263</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to authorize grants to increase and support nurse faculty and clinical preceptors, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2FA24F2FCB044CA99BBCF98CD68D5A71" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5740673263F74B40A17D2EECB403CA73" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Support Faculty and Expand Access to Nursing School Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA844B1AA7C8145FDAEF4D9A46D1561B2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grant program To increase and support nurse faculty and clinical preceptors</header> <subsection id="HAC17E23B71FB4B7192A391F7F633B857"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title VIII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/296">42 U.S.C. 296 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after part F (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/297t">42 U.S.C. 297t</external-xref>) the following new part:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7738F8BD30D741989125A55467F8208A" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<part id="HCCD4A3E1F2C340F3AC29728AEB911BF3"><enum>G</enum><header>Nurse faculty and clinical preceptors</header> 
<section id="HA2E61016A55A4CF2B9065E126BA4031D"><enum>861.</enum><header>Increasing and supporting nurse faculty and clinical preceptors</header> 
<subsection id="H88109E49A4C24F2E92FCFF2EBC14B0AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants to schools of nursing to support the recruitment and retention of nurse faculty and clinical preceptors who supervise nursing students to help educate the future nursing workforce.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H842DD7C5A7AE4E6A8611EAD380304F39"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>In order to be eligible to receive a grant under this section, a school of nursing shall submit an application to the Secretary that includes—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8BA607A94734480B8BF1A24D2D167E0C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>documentation that such school is experiencing a shortage of faculty or clinical preceptors; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8B4FD558AC2D446B9AA9FE5DEEBA5F38"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how such school will utilize funds received through the grant to recruit and retain faculty or clinical preceptors, as applicable.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB118BC6DAA404DD7B79F62D786DC04DC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to any school of nursing that—</text> <paragraph id="HF186A43486714C95AFA23D6936223EC1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrates that the school’s shortage of teaching faculty or clinical preceptors is a reason that the school has not accepted all qualified applicants into the respective school’s programs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2EBD58C7E8A247F289EACF4B8660E5BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>demonstrates that the school is located in a State or city whose schools of nursing experience above-average shortages of teaching faculty or clinical preceptors;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB4A66CE284D3415DBFA4D659FD8504D1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prioritizes the recruitment and retention of nurse faculty from disadvantaged backgrounds (including racial or ethnic groups underrepresented in the nursing workforce), low-income individuals, and first-generation college students;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8422D743F2AE4A42B507AA03FF98FE5B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prioritizes the recruitment and retention of full-time nurse faculty and clinical preceptors; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97D692D1B3064BC190AD0D243C639575"><enum>(5)</enum><text>demonstrates in its application an intent to sustain gains realized through the grant. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1E0036FF70F04E91B4E73B649E1E4C40"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A school of nursing that receives a grant under this section may use the funds awarded through such grant for activities that include—</text> <paragraph id="H696BA24A47504F53AAD49CBC6C86C923"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hiring additional nurse faculty or clinical preceptors;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDC12D7B47A9D4E9993ED4446FCF142BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>increasing pay or benefits to retain or recruit nurse faculty or clinical preceptors;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF518043186714C80BFB1530D0B0084D2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">partnering with a health care facility, nurse-managed health clinic, community health center, or other facility that provides health care in order to provide educational opportunities for the purpose of increasing the number of clinical preceptors and clinical rotation sites;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H98F3C62602E1425088EB31BFF6822C7F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing and disseminating information to educate nursing students about opportunities to serve as clinical preceptors or nursing school faculty throughout their careers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB8E3970A35DF4C178BF509870EFB31F6"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offering education opportunities to promote the growth and development of nursing students and registered nurses into roles as clinical preceptors and teaching faculty;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H36F45231F29A4AFC95BF026A32706A7D"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting the recruitment and retention of diverse faculty members; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD3D9DFD07CB84C62ADCDBAE40F492890"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinating programs with another health care facility.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H266BA67960A546759CF3FB5826728534"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports to Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each school of nursing awarded a grant under this section shall submit an annual report (in such form and manner as the Secretary may require) to the Secretary containing—</text> <paragraph id="H4DAB43A1923C49DD9E9661996C570D00"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information on programs and activities funded through such grant;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB4B056AE9DD5415CB85F2FA76551F092"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information related to the outcomes of such programs and activities, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H7B2BF73F035F4D6F95480E37C245A973"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the total number of nurse faculty or clinical preceptors who were hired or retained through such grant;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE56D17DD191441B58F0E52E5E26E34DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number of students enrolled in such school of nursing before and after the implementation of programs and activities funded through such grant; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H78B4C7B13BD94F58AFE832DD63EF0481"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to the extent such information is available, deidentified and disaggregated data by race, ethnicity, age, sex, geographic region, disability status, and other relevant factors regarding nursing students enrolled in such school of nursing; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6B71BF4F4CBC4373A50635B345DC1B2A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>other information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection> </section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HC4CDA547EB7743788B667DD2F442D1F8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 871 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/298d">42 U.S.C. 298d</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8576E222B3C34CA5AFFE9E00EA24433A" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H3955421984A747A38BC994DD87CBA1D2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Part G</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of carrying out part G, there are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2025.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H54937E76FB1849088B49721CC32EE193"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Technical correction</header><text>Effective as if included in the enactment of the CARES Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/136">Public Law 116–136</external-xref>), paragraph (12) of section 3404(a) of such Act is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H77AD476C55D74740BA40AEEAF3E81BEC" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HF0C62BFAD46E4F5ABED98C2E029B8701"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking part G (42 U.S.C. 297w and 297x); and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

