<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDD78828ECBF6499F8E5042FDE1D91632" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6075 IH: Grace Hopper Code for Us Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6075</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231026">October 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a program to make grants to institutions of higher education to provide courses relating to critical legacy computer languages, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE191CA212E074D4AB57E194CE9E604FB" style="OLC"><section id="HA79D85F2448846C7BA722D8F1240E0D8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Grace Hopper Code for Us Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF1614AF984F94EFDB5DF3D6F0BFEAB83"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HE75B61BFDA7F46FFA5A7393A20D5F921"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorizing committees</header><text>The term <term>authorizing committees</term> has the meaning given such term in section 103 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1003">20 U.S.C. 1003</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H73655376A29F4849ACE8201058483B34"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information system</header><text>The term <term>information system</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3502(8) of title 44, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB23D257468F1491B84331A27145983B9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAB12E27A31D4C9AB53A17D378DABA8C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A6000072B0C4009ACBDF2537FCF35B2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> has the meaning given the term in section 311 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H745459CD1C014A6E86B3625C1AB98FF9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report concerning critical legacy computer languages used by Federal Government</header><subsection id="H19D58702B4524A91B860F35327D8F54F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the authorizing committees a report identifying not fewer than 3 computer languages, in addition to COBOL, Assembly, and PL/I, and to be known as <quote>critical legacy computer languages</quote>, that are—</text><paragraph id="H66BBDF69199F4A5BA35E5EF4579DF3B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>used by, and necessary to support the needs and national security of, the Federal Government; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F6E7EABAF57466C8AB46B6B95EA5ABF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>computer languages not commonly taught in a course at an institution of higher education.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAE6391DF5B0945319348166512307B19"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General shall make the report publicly available, including by publishing the report on the internet website of the Government Accountability Office.</text></subsection></section><section id="H06F5C98948D6444B8D5807042B8AE55D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grace Hopper Sustainment and Modernization Grant Program</header><subsection id="H75BE2A90831C4F0DB632A96496C3A1E2" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established a program to award grants to institutions of higher education, to be known as the <quote>Grace Hopper Sustainment and Modernization Grant Program (in this section referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>)</quote>, to support the development and implementation of courses of instruction regarding maintaining, developing, and modernizing information systems utilizing critical legacy computer languages identified in the report required under section 3.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6C3B38DBAFA74DFC834AD24F11E2764A" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants</header><paragraph id="H9C55FA9DDFEC4231B6F683FFDD4F3A41" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During fiscal year 2024 and each of the 3 succeeding fiscal years, the Secretary annually shall award grants to 5 institutions of higher education to carry out the activities described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H445A7C21B13C4AA9AE7FB59DD85B47FF" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>2-year institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each fiscal year, at least 2 of the grants awarded under paragraph (1) shall be awarded to 2-year institutions of higher education that—</text><subparagraph id="HC0C79FC55E2545D4A492725AEB13F7FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>award an associate’s degree; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6206E3A05297459DB06BC91DDDDA67FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>offer university-based continuing education programs for information technology professionals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44E0D456CA1A429E9B52B77206C30048" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">When awarding grants under the Program, the Secretary will give priority to applications that—</text><paragraph id="HD38F5EC4C57A4280BC3E4B91984AEEA9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrate a plan to continue their efforts to carry out the activities described in subsection (a) after the end of the grant period;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H669C6719CDF5480BBD66DFDAAC4549EA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>demonstrate plans to recruit and include the participation of women and other under-represented minority groups;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H488AA0BD7A014BAAABC849D48E0D6666"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrate plans to engage with local students in grades 6 through 12 regarding career opportunities relating to critical legacy languages;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC7682F08FC04503B909A5BFF6066E0E" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offer scholarship or other support, which may include books and supplies (including hardware, software, and connectivity), to students enrolled in projects supported by the Program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H956966115C994810857227EF4C6F96D1" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>incorporate perspectives into the challenges of modernizing legacy information technology systems from disciplines such as history, public policy, public administration, political science, business administration, management, economics, sociology, or other humanistic or social science disciplines;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5577BAACB5D849D3838D537E6AF41816"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address the extent to which the grant recipient intends to utilize and support open source technology and other best industry practices in software development, software maintenance, and software modernization in connection with the Program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50574B9A97A54D77ADBAF689D7CB0E71" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>demonstrate the ability to make agreements to place students in the projects funded by the grant in paid internships or similar arrangements with Federal, State, local, or private sector organizations where they can ensure that each such student works with computer programmers in maintaining, developing, or modernizing information systems utilizing critical legacy computer languages, with a preference for such placements lasting longer than 60 days.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE36EDE82DAC2467B9FBD80F69D2C969E" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Special rule related to geography</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recipients of a grant under the Program may not be located in the same State. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4E9EDED7C24546F3AFC21372B9136BF1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under the Program, an institution of higher education shall submit to the Secretary an application in such form, and containing such information, as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF7E56A651D854BE19C1C5530A9DB9DD2"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Grant amount</header><text>The amount of a grant under this section may not exceed $5,000,000.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3805BC4C8B6C4D08B9AB5B79E148461E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Period of a grant</header><text>The period of a grant under this section may not exceed 3 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5B6EB285B6B049A18D5478999C0AD7A9"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HB9343CA2805844CF9D419A2DDDCE37EE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual reports by institutions of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each institution of higher education that receives a grant under the Program shall annually submit to the Secretary a report on the activities pursued under the Program, including to the extent practical, the employment outcomes of students who complete the program (including earnings, job placement type, and employment rate). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19458797E99D4199B9620AB23AAFA793"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual reports to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall annually submit to the authorizing committees a report relating to the use of grants awarded under the Program. The Secretary shall make each such report publicly available, including by publishing each such report on the internet website of the Department of Education.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAC98B98C9E6F41BAB22AFD243F4B2D51"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated $100,000,000 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

