<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6D06AA9FFD51422BABDB6D553ACACECC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5971 IH: Study on Improving Lands Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5971</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231017">October 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Agriculture to direct a study on soil health of Federal lands, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0DA32E6734BB41EBA922B66D4AD12AE4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9433E33BB0A84357A81B2A4B26CC9899" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Study on Improving Lands Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H1E952387812642D09A7D79AEE520C796" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture, in consultation with the Secretary of the Interior, shall direct the National Academies of Science to study and report on the state of soil health on Federal lands in the United States.</text></section>
<section id="HDA964735F15B4E1DBB678719777FFC54"><enum>3.</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The National Academies of Science shall determine the parameters by which to measure soil health, including—</text> <paragraph id="HE89DF872D7B44D7CB63295915C242FA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>soil organic matter and other measurements;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2194A2BCAB9C463BB3A8FAAA0EDC695B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>soil qualities that lead to the sequester of carbon; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAD0198BB624148BE88BAFEFF00A526FC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>soil qualities that support strong ecosystems and resilient environments.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="HE14E200F5FB84C2FBDE63223F3F669E9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Database</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture, in coordination with the Secretary of the Interior and the National Academies of Science, shall—</text> <paragraph id="HA50345EB882B48CF8282EFF024BE6A7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>commence a study on the state of soil health on Federal lands that determines impacts such as grazing, wildfire, recreation, invasive species, and other relevant impacts on soil health on Federal lands; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAC1ED6BECB174ED69BA020E4F12249F2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>create a database of the information collected during the study.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HF3C5E13FC4C843629BB6AB99DF00AF48"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report to Congress</header> <subsection id="H4154EDB2C990480FB518B8A9665D20B9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the commencement of the study under section 4, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of Agriculture shall evaluate the progress of that study and report any short-term findings to the Committee on Natural Resources and the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H24E48FD6AE804625A52C2D9DBDDDCACF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report and recommendations</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the commencement of the study under this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture shall submit to the Committee on Natural Resources and the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate a report summarizing the results of the study together with any recommendations for legislative or regulatory action to improve soil health, increase carbon sequestration, and improve community benefits of soil health programs on Federal lands.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

