<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H99E3B563E390432AA1B472B0B1C241BD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4992 IH: Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4992</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, to ensure that all firearms are traceable, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H994C34B433C7423FA58A901ABF7C5FFF" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H6A775A767C8540FEA01B537D3CAE8470"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H71C4F3BD7BE44DDCA815D3AF65E5C987"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H129E05057C354C2CBC57E1196B28DEBE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>irrespective of the enactment of this Act, the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives has the authority to regulate ghost guns (as defined in section 921(a) of title 18, United States Code, as amended by section 3 of this Act) and unfinished frames and receivers; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF0670607DBA4262A809B1047B6B3F3A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the purpose of this Act is to clarify and strengthen such authority.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HD0A72497DF7D4DFDB74AB721B48059D9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requirement that all firearms be traceable</header> 
<subsection id="H9C41FE9FD3C344DDBD4A5D6B43DA7129"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 921(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HC5F239A2D79F446BBC7107FC03402A15"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (10), by adding at the end the following: <quote>The term <term>manufacturing firearms</term> shall include assembling a functional firearm or molding, machining, or 3D printing a frame or receiver, and shall not include making or fitting special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms.</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE8DAA07803D841F5BA57C9BE49BE84C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (30) the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE0978C2197B453181830B3304FC23A4"> <paragraph id="HD69BC82BA0E74F138B47FFF7EAA0F586"><enum>(31)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H3C2F26D2D1C44074B09E2733A8FE9A54"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <term>frame or receiver</term>—</text> 
<clause id="HB450F169E5054E4A8BD7936D9CC18C9D" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>means a part of a weapon that provides or is intended to provide the housing or structure to hold or integrate 1 or more fire control components, without regard to whether pins or other attachments are required to connect those components to the housing or structure; and</text></clause> <clause id="H8C20EAFDCADE4E09B9B7ED0D38A5B26C" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>includes—</text> 
<subclause id="H37C661D1E1654AC8BC2400D9C43DB3B6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a forged, cast, printed, extruded, or machined body or similar article that is designed to, or may readily be completed, assembled, or otherwise converted to, provide the housing or structure, without regard to whether the housing or structure has been indexed, drilled, or machined in any way, and without regard to whether the article is sold, distributed, or marketed with or for any associated template, jig, mold, equipment, tool, instructions, or guide; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H082C9EAD55274BC3BDB71635778DC590"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an object that is marketed or sold to become or be used as the frame or receiver of a functional firearm once completed, assembled, or converted.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B557714D26E4E268279FC9AAB6853E2" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A)(i), if a weapon has more than 1 part that provides the housing or a structure designed to hold or integrate 1 or more fire control or essential components, each such part shall be considered a frame or receiver, unless the Attorney General has provided otherwise by regulation with respect to the specific make and model of weapon on or before January 1, 2024.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H31E62C4D4CE14078BCD3B71A8B5BD549"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9614E2D2C56B4F68B6A0001B2262E312"> 
<paragraph id="HA5C88D05FC3044359D39244D555C3680"><enum>(38)</enum><text>The term <term>ghost gun</term>—</text> <subparagraph id="H330D52BE2070419DB707EEC28F522065"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a firearm, including a frame or receiver, that lacks a unique serial number engraved or cast on the frame or receiver by a licensed manufacturer or importer in accordance with this chapter; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H96E3E0F1564B4E18B9D2CAB0FC617CAB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include—</text> <clause id="HC2DF3DDC7BF74002ACE84087757C415C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a firearm that has been rendered permanently inoperable;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H6ACBC5491F1E406F995C841409D3DA27"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a firearm identified by means of a unique serial number assigned by a State agency and engraved or cast on the frame or receiver of the weapon before the effective date of the Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023 in accordance with a State law;</text></clause> <clause id="HF0321769EB914087A6BB6B2B450C021C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a firearm manufactured or imported before December 16, 1968; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFEA0E404D7F44C7E92F1447BC463804B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a firearm identified as provided for under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5842">section 5842</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H08AF37A7359A40718BA8CCE0C4B71371"><enum>(39)</enum><text>The term <term>fire control component</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H24EDDE1DE77A484EA97F957496193D40"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a component necessary for the firearm to initiate or complete the firing sequence; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA353216833394EC5B9F573D6E6768F46"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a hammer, bolt or breechblock, cylinder, trigger mechanism, firing pin, striker, and slide rails.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H206DD12CD7964D6FBD84416DA53519EC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition; requirements</header><text>Section 922 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDD5A094855C1476AAAF42552B0EC6F47"> <subsection id="H83007E4B82D74A558E1735C6FB42DE74"><enum>(aa)</enum> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HE3EA576860704432B6312644588D9DA1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Congress finds and declares the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H85D552F2EAC64876BA745F9BE19601D3" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Firearms tracing is the systematic tracking of the movement of a firearm recovered by law enforcement officials from the first sale of a firearm by the manufacturer or importer through the distribution chain (including the wholesaler and retailer) to the first retail purchaser.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC0CBE945298B481DAE58D81B6DA99CF8" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Law enforcement agencies across the country work with the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives to trace firearms and thereby obtain investigative leads in the fight against violent crime and terrorism.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEF4D39EB718E4D69B869F781FB8FE78E" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The ability of law enforcement agencies to trace a firearm is dependent on the serial number or other marks on the firearm that identify the manufacturer or importer who manufactured or imported the firearm and that are unique to the firearm.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H377334EC8D84483890961A249BC93D11" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Interstate gun trafficking interferes with lawful commerce in firearms and significantly contributes to gun crime. Of the 361,587 firearms traced by the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives in 2021, 99,172 of those firearms were originally sold by a licensed firearms dealer in a State other than the State where the firearms were recovered. These guns made up 27.4 percent of all firearm recoveries in 2021.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H45646FBF5D9D40B8B35F08C10B1FB03A" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Even before the sale of a firearm, the gun, its component parts, and the raw materials from which they are made have considerably moved in interstate commerce.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2CDE5AFE642C457894C0EB08EC40A46A" indent="up1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>If unserialized and untraceable firearms may be constructed and transported freely from State to State, ordinary citizens and foreign visitors may fear to travel to or through certain parts of the country due to concern about violent crime and gun violence, and law enforcement agencies may be unable to address it.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFDAA5402D7E1451FBF092D7BC5EE8978"><enum>(2)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HB6EEF3A2A4D14BD2B3864E117FE014BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), it shall be unlawful for any person to manufacture, sell, offer to sell, transfer, purchase, or receive a ghost gun in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph indent="up1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H37D33AED3F1747128C38034E02C5DB0F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to—</text> 
<clause id="H693E6A8937134C44BDD65C2709930A26"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the manufacture of a firearm by a licensed manufacturer if the licensed manufacturer complies with section 923(i) before selling or transferring the firearm to another person;</text></clause> <clause id="H20366B47BEFD4C6594B2AB150A19B2C4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the offer to sell, sale, or transfer of a ghost gun to, or purchase or receipt of a ghost gun by, a licensed dealer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed importer before the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of the Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2325F3B1671D4E9E87D1BB2DBA63E150"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>transactions between licensed manufacturers and importers on any date.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD44404119BD54E7BBF302AEF608F34A0" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>It shall be unlawful for a person other than a licensed manufacturer or importer to engrave or cast a serial number on a firearm in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce unless specifically authorized by the Attorney General.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAD340D81741A45D282879DEEBB902A8D" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of the Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023, it shall be unlawful for any person other than a licensed manufacturer or importer in the conduct of their business to knowingly possess a ghost gun in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA59D64BD062441AAA1BB4B0F3420773E" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of the Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023, it shall be unlawful for any person other than a licensed manufacturer or importer to possess a ghost gun in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce with the intent to sell or transfer the ghost gun with or without further manufacturing or to manufacture a firearm with the ghost gun.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H93D9A2BF07A44774A6A1F6F23C1968B7" indent="up1"><enum>(6)</enum> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H61FDD79D7A4B437EA4A654396AA79949"><enum>(A)</enum><text>It shall be unlawful for any person to sell, offer to sell, or transfer, in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, to any person other than a licensed manufacturer a machine that has the sole or primary function of manufacturing firearms.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0FE299798A574D208CDAD7040A3B00E0" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraph (D), beginning on the date of the enactment of the Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023, it shall be unlawful for any person other than a licensed manufacturer to purchase or receive, in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, a machine that has the sole or primary function of manufacturing firearms.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFDD2DFB864F04BFEBBA0D47182036298" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (D), beginning on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of the Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023, it shall be unlawful for any person other than a licensed manufacturer to possess, in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce, a machine that has the sole or primary function of manufacturing firearms.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H23BAC462551D4DD9AE0C07C2C48D36B6" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraphs (B) and (C) shall not apply to a person who is engaged in the business of selling manufacturing equipment to a licensed manufacturer who possesses a machine that has the sole or primary function of manufacturing firearms with the intent to sell or transfer the machine to a licensed manufacturer.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9569997714D5490BAFA50750C86467D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="H411EAC3E6D754ADCABBC3432B36AD2C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Removal of serial numbers</header><text>Section 922(k) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H3BE87671C5E34CC4B5DADDCB71A3FFD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>importer’s or manufacturer’s</quote> each place it appears; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7F62A101CB954013960F4CDE8C01E948"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>required by this chapter or under State law</quote> before <quote>removed</quote> each place it appears.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H557D98AE4F214F529B34991BC31F1FFA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Licensed importers and manufacturers</header><text>Section 923(i) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H458FB33BBC124F53B4DBDC4599CBDE06"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(1)</quote> before <quote>Licensed</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3DA7721C278E440884CA7B17C537EA7F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: “The serial number shall be engraved or cast on the frame or receiver in a manner sufficient to identify the firearm and the manufacturer or importer that put the serial number on the firearm.</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1E92B84DF40B47D68E977B4DA8A4F4AB"> 
<paragraph id="H656A78563E694658A43663485FDB8CE0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of the Ghost Guns and Untraceable Firearms Act of 2023, the Attorney General shall update the regulations for engraving a unique serial number onto a ghost gun so that, after the date that is 1 year after such date of enactment, a licensed dealer or gunsmith shall no longer have the authority to engrave a serial number onto a ghost gun.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H309B8DC3971E4A20AEA55F493BEE3102"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Section 924 of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5EB67520EA28451B89B0AD0456C80364"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)(B), by striking <quote>or (q)</quote> and inserting <quote>(q), (aa)(2), (aa)(3), (aa)(5), or (aa)(6)</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6F713DF3F8FD49A2AB282AFD7F50A421"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5C45349B0E8D4925A1CC506B6CB899D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <clause id="HCE48FA353CFC4E848F573885F87575EA"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), in the matter preceding clause (i), by inserting <quote>functional</quote> before <quote>firearm</quote> each place it appears;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H360F3303C69144B4B72285B2A5364539"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), in the matter preceding clause (i), by inserting <quote>functional</quote> before <quote>firearm</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H56BDE3EAE4FF4F2FA57C2BDE2E8CBFDE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D)(ii), by inserting <quote>functional</quote> before <quote>firearm</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0575BAB479C24990AB0868D87DD45A0E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>all or part of the firearm</quote> and all that follows through <quote>person.</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>all or part of the functional firearm, or otherwise make the presence of the functional firearm known to another person, in order to intimidate that person, regardless of whether the functional firearm is directly visible to that person.</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9AF78659BC564876A87EE47EF6B9CE8D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(1), by striking <quote>or (k)</quote> and inserting <quote>(k), (aa)(2), (aa)(3), (aa)(5), or (aa)(6)</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDA2F0F1316FC41F2BAF52B58130B9E88"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (e)(1), by inserting <quote>through the possession of a functional firearm</quote> before <quote>and has three</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEEE63447733B4C18BB3EE3F4C0291687"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H118EA199997A4921ABD3292092315274"> 
<subsection id="H1C625A1E3763468DAB0B28B0A25D3237"><enum>(q)</enum><text>A person who violates section 922(aa)(4) shall—</text> <paragraph id="H372F545C4C364543A2E3AEB5F849AF3C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of the first violation by the person, be fined under this title, imprisoned not more than 1 year, or both; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA7D861D4EE0C400C9EB927E9BF938DAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of any subsequent violation by the person, be fined under this title, imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H02D92D7F4A854B839C97A8623F7EFDF5"><enum>4.</enum><header>Modernization of the prohibition on undetectable firearms</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 922(p) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H4F6A9196BC254A229CE10CE6982EA72C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="HEA25C647E9554D9384823ED4A695312F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>any firearm</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD63FCFE92C1C41EDB0728B3C7D6F60E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (A) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD633472873C04135BD2A87C9ED2BDB1A"> <subparagraph id="H9A452E2A904B46F683635F77BB1C2F6E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an undetectable firearm; or</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6019A4C7E902425CB7EC3E368FD05819"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>any major component of which, when subjected to inspection by the types of x-ray machines commonly used at airports, does not generate</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>a major component of a firearm which, if subjected to inspection by the types of detection devices commonly used at airports for security screening, would not generate</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA2CC96F632B14AF2A5B4E51C879CA15F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4B5B244006364F649F04AD50F1B7A270"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (A) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H84DD654E18604FADA7DFDF8EED0F2090"> <subparagraph id="H92436F6FC5684E75B6CA100F38EBF9BE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>undetectable firearm</term> means a firearm, as defined in section 921(a)(3)(A), of which no major component is wholly made of detectable material;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB549B83492E34C44A1E60BFAFE80F380"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3022F1065F2C4FEBB6DCE64E3359709F"> <subparagraph id="H767D959173274332B82DCEF0313A2112"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the term <term>major component</term>, with respect to a firearm—</text> 
<clause id="H64A74F5C7AA04BB18BD73B66D09E9B7C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>means the slide or cylinder or the frame or receiver of the firearm; and</text></clause> <clause id="H3E3993315A9047D2B76B537E0190FC2D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a rifle or shotgun, includes the barrel of the firearm; and</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4C09A4F44708499BBEF2BB5F2A7DC854"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (C) and all that follows through the end of the undesignated matter following subparagraph (C) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H971EE68323234FABBBA756C782549298"> <subparagraph id="H25814D3830F84DF69880617C17500289"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the term <term>detectable material</term> means any material that creates a magnetic field equivalent to or more than 3.7 ounces of 17–4 pH stainless steel.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H083EABB2E95241C8BD1091648E8E9DB7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <subparagraph id="HB12E1E2860ED46CD90E3865FEBA2BE1A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the first sentence, by inserting <quote>, including a prototype,</quote> after <quote>of a firearm</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFBCFB049CD2F440796F5497AB2875977"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the second sentence; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB35EE20A3D894BCD89710BD9E54D136F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking <quote>shall not apply to any firearm which</quote> and all that follows and inserting the following: “shall not apply to—</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE824962238814DDB9128FA0490B85AFF"> 
<subparagraph id="H59C6A0079C364176A73961DB07B9A0A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any firearm received by, in the possession of, or under the control of the United States; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9FB1085F09484F288045950BC197C6C3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the manufacture, importation, possession, transfer, receipt, shipment, or delivery of a firearm by a licensed manufacturer or licensed importer pursuant to a contract with the United States.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

