<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H010994649B614DC5BAEDAAD06A95CA7B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2679 IH: Pharmacy Benefits Manager Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2679</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230418">April 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act, the Employee Retirement Income Security Act, and the Internal Revenue Code of 1984 to increase oversight of pharmacy benefits manager services, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2EE5CE70269D4B8DBCD104DB69C176CD" style="OLC"><section id="H58CEEAA1B46A44048AC120FFC175629C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pharmacy Benefits Manager Accountability Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H6D43CC006A8E43FEAE8A2FC625709463"><enum>2.</enum><header>Oversight of pharmacy benefits manager services</header><subsection id="H43C20AF7CC8B473592897388E28AE1E1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>PHSA</header><text>Title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg">42 U.S.C. 300gg et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HBA8F137B63AA439AB5EB842460AB75D2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in part D (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-111">42 U.S.C. 300gg–111 et seq.</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC9047E35C934B9BBFFF6E4E74D4FC80"><section id="HF06E032346BB4FE1B3FE93FE38501AAD"><enum>2799A–11.</enum><header>Oversight of pharmacy benefits manager services</header><subsection id="HF28DFCCCED4C4DC4A1B94E780E8D3758"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025, a group health plan or health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage or an entity or subsidiary providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of such a plan or issuer shall not enter into a contract with a drug manufacturer, distributor, wholesaler, subcontractor, rebate aggregator, or any associated third party that limits the disclosure of information to plan sponsors in such a manner that prevents the plan or issuer, or an entity or subsidiary providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a plan or issuer, from making the reports described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC81E091A6554F929C14DD7AD3219C1B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HD2A00417E6E44BB4986212747CAF1CC1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025, not less frequently than annually, a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage or an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan or an issuer providing group health insurance coverage shall submit to the plan sponsor (as defined in section 3(16)(B) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974) of such group health plan or health insurance coverage a report in accordance with this subsection and make such report available to the plan sponsor in a machine-readable format. Each such report shall include, with respect to the applicable group health plan or health insurance coverage—</text><subparagraph id="HBAB6B4595D954406A24E02086813AC86"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as applicable, information collected from drug manufacturers by such issuer or entity on the total amount of copayment assistance dollars paid, or copayment cards applied, that were funded by the drug manufacturer with respect to the participants and beneficiaries in such plan or coverage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5EF7B75618C74E848A6C91CA063103E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of each drug covered by such plan, issuer, or entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that was dispensed during the reporting period, including, with respect to each such drug during the reporting period—</text><clause id="H84878170035148EA8C6DD9AFD3051FF0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the brand name, chemical entity, and National Drug Code;</text></clause><clause id="H56AB5E1696D2410B81B52EC72A9A42CF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of participants and beneficiaries for whom the drug was filled during the plan year, the total number of prescription fills for the drug (including original prescriptions and refills), and the total number of dosage units of the drug dispensed across the plan year, including whether the dispensing channel was by retail, mail order, or specialty pharmacy;</text></clause><clause id="HB82DA3AEA499490084E32CEAB47204C6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost, listed as cost per days supply and cost per pill, or in the case of a drug in another form, per dose;</text></clause><clause id="HDDB0CFBA56464AD89681A8B5A4356D09"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total out-of-pocket spending by participants and beneficiaries on such drug, including participant and beneficiary spending through copayments, coinsurance, and deductibles; and</text></clause><clause id="HD79A5DEE55BB4B1A91E1F6592A757DC0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for any drug for which gross spending of the group health plan or health insurance coverage exceeded $10,000 during the reporting period—</text><subclause id="H4FDE0F2C634F4F71BAB92D08CBD040BD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a list of all other drugs in the same therapeutic category or class, including brand name drugs and biological products and generic drugs or biosimilar biological products that are in the same therapeutic category or class as such drug; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7618AB75C0AB4AA78342D55145E8A16E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the rationale for preferred formulary placement of such drug in that therapeutic category or class, if applicable;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB42404443CCE4C2DB13FE5CE0E2E2064"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a list of each therapeutic category or class of drugs that were dispensed under the health plan or health insurance coverage during the reporting period, and, with respect to each such therapeutic category or class of drugs, during the reporting period—</text><clause id="H37E91927B75E4758BC6D2B9945B7A0BF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>total gross spending by the plan, before manufacturer rebates, fees, or other manufacturer remuneration;</text></clause><clause id="HAC6FE30D7AD74458B5FC7D33CEB277D7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of participants and beneficiaries who filled a prescription for a drug in that category or class;</text></clause><clause id="H31926BCDE1D24941965E62BD9E5168A3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if applicable to that category or class, a description of the formulary tiers and utilization mechanisms (such as prior authorization or step therapy) employed for drugs in that category or class;</text></clause><clause id="HEA055AF65F0A4AD99866F932ABDA655C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total out-of-pocket spending by participants and beneficiaries, including participant and beneficiary spending through copayments, coinsurance, and deductibles; and</text></clause><clause id="H9EF58164772C4B47855C566CDE6BB27A"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for each therapeutic category or class under which 3 or more drugs are included on the formulary of such plan or coverage—</text><subclause id="H74D3CE2C596747B4B6B0B010577736B6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount received, or expected to be received, from drug manufacturers in rebates, fees, alternative discounts, or other remuneration—</text><item id="H02FF1B3CCAAE44ECB9652C75931AFCDC"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>that has been paid, or is to be paid, by drug manufacturers for claims incurred during the reporting period; or</text></item><item id="H5137F75125904492B2B90C6B61E02D6C"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>that is related to utilization of drugs, in such therapeutic category or class;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H329C4E0AA9364E5E86900A087B997EE3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total net spending, after deducting rebates, price concessions, alternative discounts or other remuneration from drug manufacturers, by the health plan or health insurance coverage on that category or class of drugs; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD526E55229924AF1B18BB48434E8C8E5"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the net price per course of treatment or single fill, such as a 30-day supply or 90-day supply, incurred by the health plan or health insurance coverage and its participants and beneficiaries, after manufacturer rebates, fees, and other remuneration for drugs dispensed within such therapeutic category or class during the reporting period;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H686474D6871C4DF3889424EB0CA87112"><enum>(D)</enum><text>total gross spending on prescription drugs by the plan or coverage during the reporting period, before rebates and other manufacturer fees or remuneration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD50F84A214045339938DE605370AB54"><enum>(E)</enum><text>total amount received, or expected to be received, by the health plan or health insurance coverage in drug manufacturer rebates, fees, alternative discounts, and all other remuneration received from the manufacturer or any third party, other than the plan sponsor, related to utilization of drug or drug spending under that health plan or health insurance coverage during the reporting period;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16DE7A53CB6B49A397E57907D04D6EC7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the total net spending on prescription drugs by the health plan or health insurance coverage during the reporting period; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H611DDE7ACFA74CF198D90F39C5B89931"><enum>(G)</enum><text>amounts paid directly or indirectly in rebates, fees, or any other type of remuneration to brokers, consultants, advisors, or any other individual or firm who referred the group health plan's or health insurance issuer's business to the pharmacy benefits manager.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H57E4A26C9D874F4582AFFFF3499A3E0D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Privacy requirements</header><text>Health insurance issuers offering group health insurance coverage and entities providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan shall provide information under paragraph (1) in a manner consistent with the privacy, security, and breach notification regulations promulgated under section 264(c) of the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996, and shall restrict the use and disclosure of such information according to such privacy regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5864116781C458C9EB493238F859866"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disclosure and redisclosure</header><subparagraph id="H9CD45BE97B844BC0816C0911DA35A540"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Limitation to business associates</header><text>A group health plan receiving a report under paragraph (1) may disclose such information only to business associates of such plan as defined in section 160.103 of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95BA6783C491458E8A646B809EF50F75"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clarification regarding public disclosure of information</header><text>Nothing in this section prevents a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage or an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan from placing reasonable restrictions on the public disclosure of the information contained in a report described in paragraph (1), except that such issuer or entity may not restrict disclosure of such report to the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Labor, the Department of the Treasury, the Comptroller General of the United States, or applicable State agencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8483C6EA01674B6B8C80DA6F891FE4FA"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limited form of report</header><text>The Secretary shall define through rulemaking a limited form of the report under paragraph (1) required of plan sponsors who are drug manufacturers, drug wholesalers, or other direct participants in the drug supply chain, in order to prevent anti-competitive behavior.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA631212B951347658084096265DE4B6A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report to GAO</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage or an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan shall submit to the Comptroller General of the United States each of the first 4 reports submitted to a plan sponsor under paragraph (1) with respect to such coverage or plan, and other such reports as requested, in accordance with the privacy requirements under paragraph (2), the disclosure and redisclosure standards under paragraph (3), the standards specified pursuant to paragraph (5), and such other information that the Comptroller General determines necessary to carry out the study under section 2(d) of the Pharmacy Benefits Manager Accountability Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H698C7E093AE64E909C928A0AD2C0532C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Standard format</header><text>Not later than June 1, 2023, the Secretary shall specify through rulemaking standards for health insurance issuers and entities required to submit reports under paragraph (4) to submit such reports in a standard format.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HD13827F840EB4D48A50EEF4DF6C52BFE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H01F73B3980AC499C888972727EB236F0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor and the Secretary of the Treasury, shall enforce this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7D812D0A270648389973B1AB9541EC96"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Failure to provide timely information</header><text>A health insurance issuer or an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that violates subsection (a) or fails to provide information required under subsection (b) shall be subject to a civil monetary penalty in the amount of $10,000 for each day during which such violation continues or such information is not disclosed or reported.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HD3D288A51B544226A8FA57E0F2AE6925"><enum>(3)</enum><header>False information</header><text>A health insurance issuer or entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that knowingly provides false information under this section shall be subject to a civil money penalty in an amount not to exceed $100,000 for each item of false information. Such civil money penalty shall be in addition to other penalties as may be prescribed by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H25B82E1B03D14BD38B150B1DA9FF6423"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>The provisions of section 1128A of the Social Security Act, other than subsection (a) and (b) and the first sentence of subsection (c)(1) of such section shall apply to civil monetary penalties under this subsection in the same manner as such provisions apply to a penalty or proceeding under section 1128A of the Social Security Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H7997B751A9324CD0A83332A33A0770D2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Waivers</header><text>The Secretary may waive penalties under paragraph (2), or extend the period of time for compliance with a requirement of this section, for an entity in violation of this section that has made a good-faith effort to comply with this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE2226E70723448CFBC566014AB633647"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to permit a health insurance issuer, group health plan, or other entity to restrict disclosure to, or otherwise limit the access of, the Department of Health and Human Services to a report described in subsection (b)(1) or information related to compliance with subsection (a) by such issuer, plan, or entity.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4EB9B58B393C415596FBE7755A62105C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>wholesale acquisition cost</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1847A(c)(6)(B) of the Social Security Act.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB06835E0CA4477FA16CDDCBC0465C80"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 2723 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-22">42 U.S.C. 300gg–22</external-xref>)—</text><subparagraph id="H937D1E1790174F4080B8CDA755E997DA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><clause id="HA2F2632E337441DD8D23D683E12626C6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>(other than subsections (a) and (b) of section 2799A–11)</quote> after <quote>part D</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H85D012547981490EAA44126107E367C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>(other than subsections (a) and (b) of section 2799A–11)</quote> after <quote>part D</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD162C9F233F8482E89E2801A33FBFD73"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><clause id="H6F70EFE7EDAE458897612699F1A0EA4C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>(other than subsections (a) and (b) of section 2799A–11)</quote> after <quote>part D</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H30AA244985264D21BC8F92E88595DE3B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A), by inserting <quote>(other than subsections (a) and (b) of section 2799A–11)</quote> after <quote>part D</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HC06FA0B5434B4B5A9DF7E2B9D295E4F3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(C)(ii), by inserting <quote>(other than subsections (a) and (b) of section 2799A–11)</quote> after <quote>part D</quote>.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0DB309C7A9D6405E931BAF2893B89EC8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>ERISA</header><paragraph id="H6E2A57841DFC4F108C0F88B47CE4DE2B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subtitle B of title I of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1021">29 U.S.C. 1021 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HFEE6EA500CDF4E5998AC1FE007315D18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subpart B of part 7 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1185">29 U.S.C. 1185 et seq.</external-xref>), by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAC7445B252034F39876E87BC29DCE7A9"><section id="H027A8C71727F4B5A9E5A8296EB2C6B0C"><enum>726.</enum><header>Oversight of pharmacy benefits manager services</header><subsection id="H9571A6FAD1D0489FA66D14AB141C2652"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025, a group health plan (or health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage in connection with such a plan) or an entity or subsidiary providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of such a plan or issuer shall not enter into a contract with a drug manufacturer, distributor, wholesaler, subcontractor, rebate aggregator, or any associated third party that limits the disclosure of information to plan sponsors in such a manner that prevents the plan or issuer, or an entity or subsidiary providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a plan or issuer, from making the reports described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HEF10984D45D2460FBCE0600E304E4B29"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H85F8F2B92AFF4B2D9BB23CFC23331E88"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025, not less frequently than annually, a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage or an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan or an issuer providing group health insurance coverage shall submit to the plan sponsor (as defined in section 3(16)(B)) of such group health plan or group health insurance coverage a report in accordance with this subsection and make such report available to the plan sponsor in a machine-readable format. Each such report shall include, with respect to the applicable group health plan or health insurance coverage—</text><subparagraph id="HEDAECC2C918B4F47AD901855A6E51792"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as applicable, information collected from drug manufacturers by such issuer or entity on the total amount of copayment assistance dollars paid, or copayment cards applied, that were funded by the drug manufacturer with respect to the participants and beneficiaries in such plan or coverage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65B75115BD9C405E92D2718058522783"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of each drug covered by such plan, issuer, or entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that was dispensed during the reporting period, including, with respect to each such drug during the reporting period—</text><clause id="H50EE0EEEC97D46479F241DB3A70824A4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the brand name, chemical entity, and National Drug Code;</text></clause><clause id="H0E6D2D929EC64384BC40AC1AE11A1F7B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of participants and beneficiaries for whom the drug was filled during the plan year, the total number of prescription fills for the drug (including original prescriptions and refills), and the total number of dosage units of the drug dispensed across the plan year, including whether the dispensing channel was by retail, mail order, or specialty pharmacy;</text></clause><clause id="H1E699CF2768F40EA8D1087FB518966D6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost, listed as cost per days supply and cost per pill, or in the case of a drug in another form, per dose;</text></clause><clause id="H71819B891A4344379F6C0ADCBA620966"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total out-of-pocket spending by participants and beneficiaries on such drug, including participant and beneficiary spending through copayments, coinsurance, and deductibles; and</text></clause><clause id="HC965F8A9C54940609A9D93A0EE46C24C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for any drug for which gross spending of the group health plan or health insurance coverage exceeded $10,000 during the reporting period—</text><subclause id="HC45E3B9D390F4CBF9286B831B455CB48"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a list of all other drugs in the same therapeutic category or class, including brand name drugs and biological products and generic drugs or biosimilar biological products that are in the same therapeutic category or class as such drug; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H39306D26C26A43DCA8962061B15E63DA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the rationale for preferred formulary placement of such drug in that therapeutic category or class, if applicable;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1D9D3D1410A4913AD39B66174877550"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a list of each therapeutic category or class of drugs that were dispensed under the health plan or health insurance coverage during the reporting period, and, with respect to each such therapeutic category or class of drugs, during the reporting period—</text><clause id="H65B3690FCFC1413BA2C726444564CE00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>total gross spending by the plan, before manufacturer rebates, fees, or other manufacturer remuneration;</text></clause><clause id="H6724D3A5110145ABAD8B44CEC9205D8E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of participants and beneficiaries who filled a prescription for a drug in that category or class;</text></clause><clause id="H1AA7E70ADCB34AD2BCBAC6D819BBBB08"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if applicable to that category or class, a description of the formulary tiers and utilization mechanisms (such as prior authorization or step therapy) employed for drugs in that category or class;</text></clause><clause id="H4E46FD14010B458FB2D9A01E3FB1448A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total out-of-pocket spending by participants and beneficiaries, including participant and beneficiary spending through copayments, coinsurance, and deductibles; and</text></clause><clause id="HC75666D12A0B4D5FB3550EEF7BBC439B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for each therapeutic category or class under which 3 or more drugs are included on the formulary of such plan or coverage—</text><subclause id="H7345E5BBE7E9437B934C5E98C9E0AD85"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount received, or expected to be received, from drug manufacturers in rebates, fees, alternative discounts, or other remuneration—</text><item id="HC1DFE51BABCB4BD086CB4A395667900D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>that has been paid, or is to be paid, by drug manufacturers for claims incurred during the reporting period; or</text></item><item id="HA135E10E02DF44479F907621C515F3B2"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>that is related to utilization of drugs, in such therapeutic category or class;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H4588A452A4CE4FD08BC07AA7FA52562B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total net spending, after deducting rebates, price concessions, alternative discounts or other remuneration from drug manufacturers, by the health plan or health insurance coverage on that category or class of drugs; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H1540A5BBB59040169A53474383E8E2BA"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the net price per course of treatment or single fill, such as a 30-day supply or 90-day supply, incurred by the health plan or health insurance coverage and its participants and beneficiaries, after manufacturer rebates, fees, and other remuneration for drugs dispensed within such therapeutic category or class during the reporting period;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDCF7F98B45B48B48B2285DE10CD13D1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>total gross spending on prescription drugs by the plan or coverage during the reporting period, before rebates and other manufacturer fees or remuneration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H32449E7E4B924E709993925F42C25575"><enum>(E)</enum><text>total amount received, or expected to be received, by the health plan or health insurance coverage in drug manufacturer rebates, fees, alternative discounts, and all other remuneration received from the manufacturer or any third party, other than the plan sponsor, related to utilization of drug or drug spending under that health plan or health insurance coverage during the reporting period;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB09E45E95B7A4D2AADE7422A3139F414"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the total net spending on prescription drugs by the health plan or health insurance coverage during the reporting period; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE563887016CB4D318DA435FFD86C2720"><enum>(G)</enum><text>amounts paid directly or indirectly in rebates, fees, or any other type of remuneration to brokers, consultants, advisors, or any other individual or firm who referred the group health plan's or health insurance issuer's business to the pharmacy benefits manager.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H739582009EED4C3296B7831B2D8F2D1F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Privacy requirements</header><text>Health insurance issuers offering group health insurance coverage and entities providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan shall provide information under paragraph (1) in a manner consistent with the privacy, security, and breach notification regulations promulgated under section 264(c) of the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996, and shall restrict the use and disclosure of such information according to such privacy regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37192D53136D4E3AAAFC59C2B01C3022"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disclosure and redisclosure</header><subparagraph id="H6CBD29A521FE4B269C05DBBB66B2C3B1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Limitation to business associates</header><text>A group health plan receiving a report under paragraph (1) may disclose such information only to business associates of such plan as defined in section 160.103 of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0D18887568A4D318633D5F829D938C0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clarification regarding public disclosure of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section prevents a health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage or an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan from placing reasonable restrictions on the public disclosure of the information contained in a report described in paragraph (1), except that such issuer or entity may not restrict disclosure of such report to the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Labor, the Department of the Treasury, the Comptroller General of the United States, or applicable State agencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H320A17AF720244408D94DE10F7457DBA"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limited form of report</header><text>The Secretary shall define through rulemaking a limited form of the report under paragraph (1) required of plan sponsors who are drug manufacturers, drug wholesalers, or other direct participants in the drug supply chain, in order to prevent anti-competitive behavior.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC153DE1D1EC04EDA9866A7B20602E569"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report to GAO</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A health insurance issuer offering group health insurance coverage or an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan shall submit to the Comptroller General of the United States each of the first 4 reports submitted to a plan sponsor under paragraph (1) with respect to such coverage or plan, and other such reports as requested, in accordance with the privacy requirements under paragraph (2), the disclosure and redisclosure standards under paragraph (3), the standards specified pursuant to paragraph (5), and such other information that the Comptroller General determines necessary to carry out the study under section 2(d) of the Pharmacy Benefits Manager Accountability Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE28B2968A7C4A3396032C8DF74E1430"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Standard format</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than June 1, 2023, the Secretary shall specify through rulemaking standards for health insurance issuers and entities required to submit reports under paragraph (4) to submit such reports in a standard format.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9705D97BF40948D99ACDD53C0CFD0AA5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to permit a health insurance issuer, group health plan, or other entity to restrict disclosure to, or otherwise limit the access of, the Department of Labor to a report described in subsection (b)(1) or information related to compliance with subsection (a) by such issuer, plan, or entity. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6919CF6112D74E52BDC0C54A7ED9E32D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>wholesale acquisition cost</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1847A(c)(6)(B) of the Social Security Act.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53CB80A0D8764C0FA86C73B116EF669D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 502 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1132">29 U.S.C. 1132</external-xref>)—</text><clause id="HD1B4A4BBB77543F99587BD172861A2AF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subclause id="H70DB68F47EB447C3ADD8ED25E1CA895C" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in paragraph (6), by striking <quote>or (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>(9), or (13)</quote>; </text></subclause><subclause id="HF0DE8205E45D46F5B03E4E5879E77A33"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in paragraph (10), by striking at the end <quote>or</quote>;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5FA70F21C6E143F68365D44AC3CC2099"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in paragraph (11), at the end by striking the period and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H70780B250D5746A29580C07EC570A30A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD1D098627F4E45658EF9E95BA2BE25E8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H2B8E4D6EDD04412898F6741CF7DFD74A"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, and the Secretary of the Treasury, to enforce section 726.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H1D95594A16D14062875F7C88E511710C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(3), by inserting <quote>and subsections (a)(12) and (c)(13)</quote> before <quote>, the Secretary is not</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HD342E462F7874B5DBA68C25E27B5CF0A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7D498318170D411381EC21216931AF2A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HF0ECCC8B566349AA932A39A216D542DF"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Secretarial enforcement authority relating to oversight of pharmacy benefits manager services</header><subparagraph id="H06E0CA0F863B490385CE19E936467147"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Failure to provide timely information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of the Treasury, may impose a penalty against any health insurance issuer or entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that violates section 726(a) or fails to provide information required under section 726(b) in the amount of $10,000 for each day during which such violation continues or such information is not disclosed or reported.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4D386DD412B4573B1DA4465AA16704E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>False information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of the Treasury, may impose a penalty against a health insurance issuer or entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that knowingly provides false information under section 726 in an amount not to exceed $100,000 for each item of false information. Such penalty shall be in addition to other penalties as may be prescribed by law.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7E4B6E46D3F840E9B114D468E2D5C058"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Waivers</header><text>The Secretary may waive penalties under subparagraph (A), or extend the period of time for compliance with a requirement of section 726, for an entity in violation of such section that has made a good-faith effort to comply with such section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FED12ED6BEE4E29A2DC22384EEC2F5C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents in section 1 of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1001">29 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 725 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H978BCBD9422E4EEBA362EB53CEB7A766"><toc><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 726. Oversight of pharmacy benefits manager services.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H94DCF8E1790B47AEB719E9AD7C9510A8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>IRC</header><paragraph id="H0277C193AFC94BD9A823CF57BB3D530C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/100">chapter 100</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7E9FE004F52F49ADBA39166685A15186"><section id="HE9BFCC69578F4D358B01E229F4FAF3CE"><enum>9826.</enum><header>Oversight of pharmacy benefits manager services</header><subsection id="HE055883E887E469083B5E6CF4C0F7340"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025, a group health plan or an entity or subsidiary providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of such a plan shall not enter into a contract with a drug manufacturer, distributor, wholesaler, subcontractor, rebate aggregator, or any associated third party that limits the disclosure of information to plan sponsors in such a manner that prevents the plan, or an entity or subsidiary providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a plan, from making the reports described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="HA2423E28BD21411F96980FF3A9AB1234"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HE71164AF838B4D5CB11E303E9CCBA1F3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025, not less frequently than annually, an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan shall submit to the plan sponsor (as defined in section 3(16)(B) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974) of such group health plan a report in accordance with this subsection and make such report available to the plan sponsor in a machine-readable format. Each such report shall include, with respect to the applicable group health plan—</text><subparagraph id="H7CBA7A74AAB64C328A893E72D64D2116"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">as applicable, information collected from drug manufacturers by such entity on the total amount of copayment assistance dollars paid, or copayment cards applied, that were funded by the drug manufacturer with respect to the participants and beneficiaries in such plan;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08DC0D473E044ABAA397F04CB3E0E768"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of each drug covered by such plan or entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that was dispensed during the reporting period, including, with respect to each such drug during the reporting period—</text><clause id="HCAB1089375CB478CB8551DF2EFEA26CF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the brand name, chemical entity, and National Drug Code;</text></clause><clause id="H9B68EDCBACFC414CAA878783A0ADD835"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of participants and beneficiaries for whom the drug was filled during the plan year, the total number of prescription fills for the drug (including original prescriptions and refills), and the total number of dosage units of the drug dispensed across the plan year, including whether the dispensing channel was by retail, mail order, or specialty pharmacy;</text></clause><clause id="H787FC1F20DD34D4A8B053505E627AB96"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the wholesale acquisition cost, listed as cost per days supply and cost per pill, or in the case of a drug in another form, per dose;</text></clause><clause id="HEFFDF33D437C446A98FC885EE8B419EC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total out-of-pocket spending by participants and beneficiaries on such drug, including participant and beneficiary spending through copayments, coinsurance, and deductibles; and</text></clause><clause id="H02ED9CCD6F6048348E1C18D8A8A682A6"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for any drug for which gross spending of the group health plan exceeded $10,000 during the reporting period—</text><subclause id="HB32BFE9A52854DB39CF7E7A68D609B5A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a list of all other drugs in the same therapeutic category or class, including brand name drugs and biological products and generic drugs or biosimilar biological products that are in the same therapeutic category or class as such drug; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H334AD1460D854758B9F6E58045057C32"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the rationale for preferred formulary placement of such drug in that therapeutic category or class, if applicable;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F77A8B71C7F4183A4B0C8E1BAE537C3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a list of each therapeutic category or class of drugs that were dispensed under the health plan during the reporting period, and, with respect to each such therapeutic category or class of drugs, during the reporting period—</text><clause id="H46A9AE5471A04A8E80EB738CEF8BE492"><enum>(i)</enum><text>total gross spending by the plan, before manufacturer rebates, fees, or other manufacturer remuneration;</text></clause><clause id="H4E591619CD234FE8A3C9DEFDC1B63008"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of participants and beneficiaries who filled a prescription for a drug in that category or class;</text></clause><clause id="H6DBE02467A4A4B44A960FF8004E44EF8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if applicable to that category or class, a description of the formulary tiers and utilization mechanisms (such as prior authorization or step therapy) employed for drugs in that category or class;</text></clause><clause id="H79367E46C2CA473186CBA7AF463F816C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total out-of-pocket spending by participants and beneficiaries, including participant and beneficiary spending through copayments, coinsurance, and deductibles; and</text></clause><clause id="H82402137FD2446C8ADA69FFB1FC8922B"><enum>(v)</enum><text>for each therapeutic category or class under which 3 or more drugs are included on the formulary of such plan—</text><subclause id="HC9FBD6D316DC442CA68DA84749245501"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the amount received, or expected to be received, from drug manufacturers in rebates, fees, alternative discounts, or other remuneration—</text><item id="H3BECDD0E7EB546819924916FBA401CFE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>that has been paid, or is to be paid, by drug manufacturers for claims incurred during the reporting period; or</text></item><item id="HCADD233CA17143DBB3FEA06F577E4CE4"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>that is related to utilization of drugs, in such therapeutic category or class;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H05BE0BA9A40C4C55BE7C42E429CC6851"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the total net spending, after deducting rebates, price concessions, alternative discounts or other remuneration from drug manufacturers, by the health plan on that category or class of drugs; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H49F0A172FBF24D5C889874D4ABA9EA0A"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the net price per course of treatment or single fill, such as a 30-day supply or 90-day supply, incurred by the health plan and its participants and beneficiaries, after manufacturer rebates, fees, and other remuneration for drugs dispensed within such therapeutic category or class during the reporting period;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5FE82013CD894DD7B4E5D409F576DBFE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>total gross spending on prescription drugs by the plan during the reporting period, before rebates and other manufacturer fees or remuneration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE04ACF3A36CC4C52B42EA08669894721"><enum>(E)</enum><text>total amount received, or expected to be received, by the health plan in drug manufacturer rebates, fees, alternative discounts, and all other remuneration received from the manufacturer or any third party, other than the plan sponsor, related to utilization of drug or drug spending under that health plan during the reporting period;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4AA4C0B540641B6884434675DE6A428"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the total net spending on prescription drugs by the health plan during the reporting period; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BA78E1C320F4B9AADA3BFDC34E6A532"><enum>(G)</enum><text>amounts paid directly or indirectly in rebates, fees, or any other type of remuneration to brokers, consultants, advisors, or any other individual or firm who referred the group health plan's business to the pharmacy benefits manager.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H2A5813B0B0C04C39BCC61F509C62521B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Privacy requirements</header><text>Entities providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan shall provide information under paragraph (1) in a manner consistent with the privacy, security, and breach notification regulations promulgated under section 264(c) of the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996, and shall restrict the use and disclosure of such information according to such privacy regulations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CF7243558D94AF19570BC7E09FF9565"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disclosure and redisclosure</header><subparagraph id="H9010FC7998814C9A8BB750372D7F1CF3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Limitation to business associates</header><text>A group health plan receiving a report under paragraph (1) may disclose such information only to business associates of such plan as defined in section 160.103 of title 45, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H459BAB46997F41B9A78EEC76B003F7D7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clarification regarding public disclosure of information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section prevents an entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan from placing reasonable restrictions on the public disclosure of the information contained in a report described in paragraph (1), except that such entity may not restrict disclosure of such report to the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Labor, the Department of the Treasury, the Comptroller General of the United States, or applicable State agencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDD178B245C204FB488B6E101416577AE"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limited form of report</header><text>The Secretary shall define through rulemaking a limited form of the report under paragraph (1) required of plan sponsors who are drug manufacturers, drug wholesalers, or other direct participants in the drug supply chain, in order to prevent anti-competitive behavior.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFD9A41CB44A404DA5EF23BF1877B49E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Report to GAO</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An entity providing pharmacy benefits management services on behalf of a group health plan shall submit to the Comptroller General of the United States each of the first 4 reports submitted to a plan sponsor under paragraph (1) with respect to such plan, and other such reports as requested, in accordance with the privacy requirements under paragraph (2), the disclosure and redisclosure standards under paragraph (3), the standards specified pursuant to paragraph (5), and such other information that the Comptroller General determines necessary to carry out the study under section 2(d) of the Pharmacy Benefits Manager Accountability Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E721EBA87A84070BC3A16D7C8F8BEFD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Standard format</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than June 1, 2023, the Secretary shall specify through rulemaking standards for entities required to submit reports under paragraph (4) to submit such reports in a standard format.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HE37546EB258647138423B265C490AF69"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H15462B58C7E042D49540CF3BFCAAA319"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor and the Secretary of Health and Human Services, shall enforce this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HAFC0ABA3ADA7441CA738B3462B82DC87"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Failure to provide timely information</header><text>An entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that violates subsection (a) or fails to provide information required under subsection (b) shall be subject to a civil monetary penalty in the amount of $10,000 for each day during which such violation continues or such information is not disclosed or reported.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HDD7D6BE55BBB40B791AB594CA84F9CA4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>False information</header><text>An entity providing pharmacy benefits management services that knowingly provides false information under this section shall be subject to a civil money penalty in an amount not to exceed $100,000 for each item of false information. Such civil money penalty shall be in addition to other penalties as may be prescribed by law.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCBCC316008BA4B169EECCFECF42DA5F8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>The provisions of section 1128A of the Social Security Act, other than subsection (a) and (b) and the first sentence of subsection (c)(1) of such section shall apply to civil monetary penalties under this subsection in the same manner as such provisions apply to a penalty or proceeding under section 1128A of the Social Security Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HA4A714613E29493693D6B0E76F937C79"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Waivers</header><text>The Secretary may waive penalties under paragraph (2), or extend the period of time for compliance with a requirement of this section, for an entity in violation of this section that has made a good-faith effort to comply with this section. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H36BACED5A4AF4DA0A501A6D269A1446E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed to permit a group health plan or other entity to restrict disclosure to, or otherwise limit the access of, the Department of the Treasury to a report described in subsection (b)(1) or information related to compliance with subsection (a) by such plan or entity. </text></subsection><subsection id="H9DF08927AE0F4DF2A25EC5F5E3301322"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>wholesale acquisition cost</term> has the meaning given such term in section 1847A(c)(6)(B) of the Social Security Act.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F1C02B48A574DA6B67D5278EB7476AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/100">chapter 100</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new item: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE274A30E62F24440BD565B6EAAD05CCB"><toc><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 9826. Oversight of pharmacy benefits manager services.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H084BBEF9489748AD9B53899BAA99A269" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>GAO study</header><paragraph id="HF971BAD8CD7D4BACB9EEF8B9CDC10EC7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on—</text><subparagraph id="HB72BD3B1F78145E6A90D858BEDAC04BC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>pharmacy networks of group health plans, health insurance issuers, and entities providing pharmacy benefits management services under such group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage, including networks that have pharmacies that are under common ownership (in whole or part) with group health plans, health insurance issuers, or entities providing pharmacy benefits management services or pharmacy benefits administrative services under group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61A42587E97F49AABAEBE75313353387" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>as it relates to pharmacy networks that include pharmacies under common ownership described in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="HBEF88CAA25BE492FA60139C12661C24C" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>whether such networks are designed to encourage enrollees of a plan or coverage to use such pharmacies over other network pharmacies for specific services or drugs, and if so, the reasons the networks give for encouraging use of such pharmacies; and</text></clause><clause id="H3132BCE1DDB845C79254C98596C22B60" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whether such pharmacies are used by enrollees disproportionately more in the aggregate or for specific services or drugs compared to other network pharmacies;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58FFEAD611E742C9854FA4D6C98C42A1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>whether group health plans and health insurance issuers offering group or individual health insurance coverage have options to elect different network pricing arrangements in the marketplace with entities that provide pharmacy benefits management services, the prevalence of electing such different network pricing arrangements;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3254220D24C74F84BBA48212D6D37C1E" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>pharmacy network design parameters that encourage enrollees in the plan or coverage to fill prescriptions at mail order, specialty, or retail pharmacies that are wholly or partially-owned by that issuer or entity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15C6F8609D6E4789A798E5D19B82F36A" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the degree to which mail order, specialty, or retail pharmacies that dispense prescription drugs to an enrollee in a group health plan or health insurance coverage that are under common ownership (in whole or part) with group health plans, health insurance issuers, or entities providing pharmacy benefits management services or pharmacy benefits administrative services under group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage receive reimbursement that is greater than the median price charged to the group health plan or health insurance issuer when the same drug is dispensed to enrollees in the plan or coverage by other pharmacies included in the pharmacy network of that plan, issuer, or entity that are not wholly or partially owned by the health insurance issuer or entity providing pharmacy benefits management services. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H935460FEAC2540F6B2295D958013F8FB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall ensure that the report under paragraph (1) does not contain information that would allow a reader to identify a specific plan or entity providing pharmacy benefits management services or otherwise contain commercial or financial information that is privileged or confidential. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BA72C913104479891A0393E4B9367B9" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection, the terms <term>group health plan</term>, <term>health insurance coverage</term>, and <term>health insurance issuer</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-91">42 U.S.C. 300gg–91</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

