<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1072702CDF8D48C686C68FF209C330F3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 35 IH: Close the Medigap Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 35</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001090">Mr. Cartwright</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to provide for certain reforms with respect to medicare supplemental health insurance policies.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3541D8FDB0BC4CA687D97343E353588F" style="OLC"><section id="HCC114C308F884A4EBBAEF4EA4578F3CF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Close the Medigap Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC743C0F0BBD64EDFBB83A4DBA8853085"><enum>2.</enum><header>Guaranteed issue</header><subsection id="H306104FFC9804CB795700F951AF37087" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1882(s) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ss">42 U.S.C. 1395ss(s)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE4213526D4C546A29A8E94A88296C664" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H3BD07FED496847CEA592E2585B19F225"><enum>(s)</enum><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H989DCC23BBEF4ECEB1AC06BA58E3968D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), the issuer of a medicare supplemental policy may not, in the case of an individual entitled to benefits under part A and enrolled under part B—</text><subparagraph id="HBECEECAC87B647CC96A9EFE10F127CA0" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">deny or condition the issuance or effectiveness of a medicare supplemental policy, or discriminate in the pricing of the policy, because of health status, claims experience, receipt of health care, or medical condition;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8464A11BBE1D48609126759EC708C0C7" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>exclude benefits based on a preexisting condition;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8724552A5473410EB73E825F9CE0F767" indent="up1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide any time period applicable to preexisting conditions, waiting periods, elimination periods, and probationary periods for any benefit;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1F502BBC4D146B5AB50C4416661B663" indent="up1"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">deny or condition the issuance or effectiveness of the policy (including the imposition of any exclusion of benefits under the policy based on a preexisting condition) or discriminate in the pricing of the policy (including the adjustment of premium rates) of an individual on the basis of the genetic information with respect to such individual; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE019A7BDFB6C464FABA31CAAF96D30C5" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">deny or condition the issuance or effectiveness of a medicare supplemental policy that is offered and is available for issuance to new enrollees by such issuer; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBCF2C68CF8AC468EA8681F14B7267938" indent="up1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>establish any period limiting enrollment under a medicare supplemental policy to such period for any individual. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H49FCAE37E7FB4C0A8F05E72234AB34B5" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to an individual entitled to benefits under part A solely by reason of section 226A.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0265B03A3A16479FB2AD2C89F7E4C030" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection or in subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (x)(2) shall be construed to limit the ability of an issuer of a medicare supplemental policy from, to the extent otherwise permitted under this title—</text><subparagraph id="H8B5CDE65D01C447CB314ECAF6F39766D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">denying or conditioning the issuance or effectiveness of the policy or increasing the premium for an employer based on the manifestation of a disease or disorder of an individual who is covered under the policy; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16F285B979814062996F2FCCA54AD0A5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the premium for any policy issued to an individual based on the manifestation of a disease or disorder of an individual who is covered under the policy (in such case, the manifestation of a disease or disorder in one individual cannot also be used as genetic information about other group members.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H2FB38E793B6E4205ACEFF09DEF5EE30E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Outreach plan</header><paragraph id="HF64E31288C30416494B8C669C52A059E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall develop an outreach plan to notify individuals entitled to benefits under part A or enrolled under part B of title XVIII of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395">42 U.S.C. 1395 et seq.</external-xref>) of the effects of the amendment made by subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2A4D44FF0024B6FAC25664D5BED4A63"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In implementing the outreach plan developed under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consult with consumer advocates, brokers, insurers, the National Association of Insurance Commissioners, and State Health Insurance Assistance Programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5570D145EF9046B79B7C3FE65D989993" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective date; phase-In authority</header><paragraph id="H98D23B73CB3C4D47A3AA9B44C9F5B048" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), the amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply to medicare supplemental policies effective on or after January 1, 2024.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBCB488B6D5F441F8F5DF8EBA91D0F28" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Phase-in authority</header><subparagraph id="HB776B638046F400F92A7E0238C94F11F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (B), the Secretary of Health and Human Services may phase in the implementation of the amendment made under subsection (a) (with such phase-in beginning on or after January 1, 2024) in such manner as the Secretary determines appropriate in order to minimize any adverse impact on individuals enrolled under a medicare supplemental policy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7ECA6AAF6074C9B9077360BDF4CB6E2" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Phase-in period may not exceed 5 years</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall ensure that the amendment made by subsection (a) is fully implemented by not later than January 1, 2029.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7E921B423CB14AFFAED0D364761E6C26" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Medical loss ratio</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1882(r)(1)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ss">42 U.S.C. 1395ss(r)(1)(A)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H70124212590A4F6FAA0F977DE5785922"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and periodically reviewed</quote> after <quote>developed</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4AD5B1B89954ED085D4028175321D87"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>policy, at least 75 percent of the aggregate amount of premiums collected in the case of group policies and at least 65 percent in the case of individual policies; and</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HECC5D498244C4448B34AAD7CF6EDD2E8" style="OLC"><text>policy—</text><clause id="H4AD1B5FFB864456A9DA5C51DB4A06D09" indent="up1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to periods beginning before January 1, 2024, at least 75 percent of the aggregate amount of premiums collected in the case of group policies and at least 65 percent in the case of individual policies; and</text></clause><clause id="H185738AED525488E8AAB3102B33A4FAE" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to periods beginning on or after January 1, 2024, a percent of the aggregate amount of premiums collected that, in the case of group policies or individual policies, as applicable, is equal to or greater than both—</text><subclause id="H6D93CF4EFE1842B0982DF814892AA40F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the applicable percent specified in clause (i) with respect to such policies; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H35C2B2F7F81E46ED9C00329BCB8CAA19"><enum>(II)</enum><text>such percent as the National Association of Insurance Commissioners may recommend to the Secretary with respect to such policies for purposes of this paragraph; and</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H022F3F0150574968B00CE6EC6005B4CD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Limitations on pricing discrimination</header><subsection id="HFC9F514CE61747E0822133087E3A7BD3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1882 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ss">42 U.S.C. 1395ss</external-xref>), as amended by section 6, is further amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H183121DCCE194E7DA348FFB92B480A39" style="OLC"><subsection id="H2A7760BA3CD44824B0B7DE5484AE202A"><enum>(aa)</enum><header>Development of new standards relating to pricing discrimination</header><paragraph id="H29B2E87EC816422FB4F610D501187D5E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall request the National Association of Insurance Commissioners to review and revise the standards for all benefit packages under subsection (p)(1), including the core benefit package, in order to provide coverage consistent with paragraph (2). Such revisions shall be made consistent with the rules applicable under subsection (p)(1)(E) (with the reference to the <quote>1991 NAIC Model Regulation</quote> deemed a reference to the NAIC Model Regulation as most recently updated by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners to reflect previous changes in law and the reference to <quote>date of enactment of this subsection</quote> deemed a reference to the date of enactment of this subsection).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65D352FB5AE349F2A1111C6067C2BE18"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Changes in cost-sharing described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the revised standards, coverage shall not be available under a Medicare supplemental insurance policy unless the issuer of the policy, in addition to conforming to the other applicable requirements of this section—</text><subparagraph id="H827C56476A524941B0AD286A935F5C50"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not discriminate in the pricing of the policy because of the age of the individual to whom the policy is issued;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0718BBE92804A5784DC31B4AA063DC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not, to an extent that jeopardizes the access to such policy for individuals who are eligible to participate in the program under this title because the individuals are individuals described in paragraph (2) or (3) of section 1811, discriminate in the pricing of the policy because the individual to whom the policy is issued is so eligible to participate in such program because the individual is an individual so described in such a paragraph; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H100A521E427E4DF9A261674CB48A3355"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not establish premiums applicable under such policy on a basis that would apply to a portion of, but not the entirety of, a county or equivalent area specified by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC3A6EA6B0C7452EAEE6192B608EFE0D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Application date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The revised standards shall apply to benefit packages sold, issued, or renewed under this section to individuals who first become entitled to benefits under part A or first enrolls in part B on or after January 1, 2024.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H34269BF0FB7546BDA5E46E99381B6916"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1882(o)(1) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ss">42 U.S.C. 1395ss(o)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>, and (y)</quote> and inserting <quote>(y), and (aa)</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H35717BAD63E846E4A7BEBA55F67FF08D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Clarifying beneficiary options on the Medicare plan finder website</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1804 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395b-2">42 U.S.C. 1395b–2</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsections:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5550B58735143A2976D5D727E40A340" style="OLC"><subsection commented="no" id="HC66D0AAEE7F14F099E1F2F9D6D5091DC"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case that the Secretary provides for a Medicare plan finder internet website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (or a successor website), the Secretary shall, with respect to such website and in accordance with subsection (f)—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HC2451B997BB84E3EA2A4388B0F83D9F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make available on such website—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3D0133D28F094F4583F307A40BFE53E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">access to provider networks in order to provide to individuals entitled to benefits under part A or enrolled under part B information to assist such individuals in understanding the restrictions on providers and potential costs entailed by their decisions regarding enrollment under parts A and B, under part C, and in medicare supplemental policies under section 1882;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HFD978BA7808645ABA2A44281903172EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review of out-of-pocket expenditures, including deductibles, copayments, coinsurance, monthly premiums, and estimated annual out-of-pocket costs, displayed overall and by components, based on the best available information as determined by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF3F7A8870EFF404EBE7296326F8E5C64"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during the period prior to January 1, 2024, information regarding the rules that, in each State, pertain to guaranteed issue of medicare supplemental health insurance policies prior to implementation of the provisions of the <short-title>Close the Medigap Act of 2023</short-title> and, in the case that a State has no such rules pertaining to guaranteed issue of such policies, clear language explaining the implications of such lack of rules for individuals with pre-existing conditions;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6302A4BF6E40422DA769A602E1371AB0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than January 1, 2024, and periodically thereafter, perform a review of such website in order to ensure that such website makes available to individuals entitled to benefits under part A or enrolled under part B the information that the Secretary determines is necessary for such individuals to make informed choices regarding their options under the program under this title; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB787DD872BA04A698465483D5131BB28"><enum>(3)</enum><text>not later than 12 months after the last day of each period for the request for information under subsection (e), update such website, taking into consideration the information collected pursuant to such subsection, to clarify the presentation of consumer options for medicare supplemental health insurance policy options, including by presenting such information in a manner calculated to be understood by the average consumer and in a manner that—</text><subparagraph id="HA5A4B881792644529481A1DB4BDBEAB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improves consumer access to information regarding the applicable premiums under such policy options as of the date on which such website is so updated;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H397A9427447949488BCC3B6F5B331B16"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">facilitates consumers’ ability to compare and sort policy options and premium information across plan offerings in a given location;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDE4C4CE0A682480D873F277C25A49F18"><enum>(C)</enum><text>clarifies and explains differences in policy value;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF716AA56D3F74174B6C7D6F618220A15"><enum>(D)</enum><text>rates and explains the financial stability of issuers of such policies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2FA0642211A44855A883F7369373A5D5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>provides data on the inflation rate of different policies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B4A2C27AF354A76A137ADC197509D1D"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides information regarding the guaranteed issue requirements that apply to medicare supplemental health insurance policies under section 1882(s)(3); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C936D79D9B64F5588394708C0B39113"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes such general information as is determined by the Secretary to be necessary for individuals entitled to benefits under part A or enrolled under part B to understand costs under MA plans available pursuant to part C and prescription drug plans available pursuant to part D.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H21BADC7B0A544649B90E90B160C6A0F4"><enum>(e)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this subsection and beginning on December 7 of each year thereafter, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall provide an opportunity for public comment during which the Secretary requests information, including recommendations, from stakeholders regarding potential improvements to the presentation of medicare supplemental health insurance policy options under section 1882 on the Medicare plan finder internet website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (or a successor website).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0186EF497B9340D0BA2444EC1B650B0C"><enum>(f)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any information that the Secretary makes available on the Medicare plan finder internet website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (or a successor website) pursuant to subsection (d), the Secretary shall, prior to making such information available—</text><paragraph id="H540E77D1DE7D4DC0846470F6AD3E12FC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide, in consultation with the National Association of Insurance Commissioners, an opportunity for consumer testing of such information;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05DE710B891B4DA2A5FF22769E8C1BD8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>share the results of such consumer testing of such information with interested stakeholders; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6769FBFEF78D4D8E9C6AC4630CF31525"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide a 60-day public comment period with respect to such information.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section commented="no" id="H86F27DB634834EC88A458C9655B6F9E0"><enum>6.</enum><header>Restoring access to first-dollar Medigap coverage</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1882 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ss">42 U.S.C. 1395ss</external-xref>) is amended by striking subsection (z).</text></section><section id="H9A51B90599AB4FE4B13E3245C24080E7"><enum>7.</enum><header>Broker transparency</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1128G of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320a-7h">42 U.S.C. 1320a–7h</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H6265E679196D423E928736486CB03439"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(1)(A), by striking <quote>2011,</quote> and inserting <quote>2011 (or, with respect to information required to be submitted under subsection (f)(1), not later than six months after the date of the enactment of such subsection),</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B8B2636E0604EDE854736CE9E80F99B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9FBD5B7955BE46329C75364DD6A3DD72" style="OLC"><subsection id="H60732E6D2E1D4F27A040EB29BDD7BA38"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Application to Medigap insurance brokers</header><paragraph id="H7BFD457690984C659F3599E0E9A9443E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this subsection, each issuer of a medicare supplemental health insurance policy shall annually submit to the Secretary a report regarding payments or other transfers of value made during the previous year to agents, brokers, and other third parties representing such policy. Each such report shall include the following information, with respect to such a payment or other transfer of value:</text><subparagraph id="HD5267793422544B1B12A59AA7E6DE669"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The name of the recipient of the payment or other transfer of value.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD68576FF98034E3094381340FF0EF920"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The business address of the recipient.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A7970F3B65F433083C194AB5FBCEA12"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The amount of the payment or other transfer of value.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1E8652DA3FF4DB8A93C901A88B166BC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The dates on which the payment or transfer of value was provided.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF1098B593516411DAB437C15D67849F9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of the form of the payment or transfer of value.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EF9A457C6294DB59C1CEB2B52046297"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Any other categories of information the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4046DA3BCFC43E99060A7886D9F2F94"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Application of transparency system</header><text>The provisions of subsections (b) through (d) shall apply to an issuer described in paragraph (1), information required to be reported under such paragraph, and agents, brokers, and other third parties described in such paragraph in the same manner and to the same extent as such provisions apply to an applicable manufacturer, information required to be reported under subsection (a), and a covered recipient.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

