<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4DBC6F70B6B9438E9E14278BEE1AB138" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4736 IH: Investing in Rural America Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4736</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000470">Mrs. Fischbach</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act to provide support for facilities providing healthcare, education, child care, public safety, and other vital services in rural areas.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4886973CAF294A458F82730BE6AD30A9" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5CA2085FB972469D9AE78D050670EBB3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Investing in Rural America Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H8F5172E0C8C44A5B869EE7F6D6B85CE5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Authority of Farm Credit System institutions to provide financial support for essential rural community facilities projects</header> <subsection id="H557B0576FB234AEF8C4208760BD01A2D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 306(a) of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1926">7 U.S.C. 1926(a)</external-xref>) by adding at the end of the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE21725A220154912B0C85ABA200A11E2" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H009FF0A323DF44308F1CAFFF8DD13AB2" indent="up1"><enum>(27)</enum><header>Support for essential rural community facilities projects</header> 
<subparagraph id="H34D42E790BF64B3E8AA5CE23F01C0186"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to make available capital to develop, build, maintain, improve, or provide other support for essential community facilities in our Nation’s rural communities, institutions chartered and operating under title I, II, or III of the Farm Credit Act of 1971 may provide financing and technical assistance for projects eligible for financing under this subsection for community facilities, subject to subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD0EEA81A32194159A4B65A4EB10C2682"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text>An institution referred to in subparagraph (A) shall not provide financing under subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<clause id="HFF7D69B548974490B074A7AA99C04101"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in an amount that exceeds 15 percent of the total assets of the institution; or</text> </clause> <clause id="HBAA4D17A86504605820910C25320D8D1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">unless the institution—</text> 
<subclause id="HF92D19C03E9B4150B8023C9CA3D88694"><enum>(I)</enum><text>has offered, under reasonable terms and conditions acceptable to the borrower involved, an interest in the financing to at least 1 lending institution not referred to in subparagraph (A); and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H29C1EA2C179E47229576D42B107E44C5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>has reported the offer to the Farm Credit Administration.</text></subclause> </clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2B98FD57EE9048ABB2EEA86BF8AEBBDC"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Annual reports to Congress</header><text>Within 1 year after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, and annually thereafter, the Farm Credit Administration shall provide a report on the activities undertaken under this paragraph by Farm Credit System institutions during the period covered by the report, including through partnerships between such an institution and other lending institutions, and a copy of each report provided pursuant to subparagraph (B)(ii)(II) during the period, which shall also be posted on the website of the Farm Credit Administration.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H8EEF5ADAB4A747E9A80DE1B01DE854DF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect on October 1, 2023.</text> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

