<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA88FA6699A034801B6A7ED8657880BB2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6708 IH: Dredging to Ensure the Empowerment of Ports Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6708</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231211">December 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Army, acting through the Chief of Engineers, to propose a new nationwide permit under the Federal Water Pollution Control Act for dredging projects, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD3C07D51E4CB4EF9A128D0A7A6E0F866" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H1EA2CE4EDDC34D758F675828FAEA0E71"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Dredging to Ensure the Empowerment of Ports Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>DEEP Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4C3CDE8630EF47DABAC2725C2F4F53C4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H763178D4184547CDA70FECC2B992F551"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Certifying authority</header><text>The term <term>certifying authority</term>, with respect to an activity for which a certification is required under section 401 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1341">33 U.S.C. 1341</external-xref>) from a State or interstate water pollution control agency, means the State or interstate water pollution control agency, as applicable, from which the certification is requested.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00080ECE0EF544528CC9F43B39E6E0BF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Dredging project</header><subparagraph id="H33C598E565C64430BB590A05CE2592EC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>dredging project</term> means a project permitted or solicited by the Secretary that involves the dredging of a port or a navigation channel of a port within the navigable waters of the United States.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCF01873B79D46B7A77E4CEADE9C50E0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Dredging of ports</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), a dredging project that involves the dredging of a port includes dredging for the purposes of—</text><clause id="H551CDB0598CF4BB5ABD7E1E16530F120"><enum>(i)</enum><text>maintaining the port;</text></clause><clause id="H70D84B0CBC6841D185AD7F1C927B9261"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>expanding the port; or</text></clause><clause id="H23E7A656189E4204B10E543526C77813"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>deepening the port up to a depth of 60 feet.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H02EC507F231F4BF8B3E2104DBB567214"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Navigable waters of the United States</header><text>The term <term>navigable waters of the United States</term> has the meaning given the term in section 2101 of title 46, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3479D74F07C443BA197DB47BA523266"><enum>(4)</enum><header>NWP</header><text>The term <term>NWP</term> means the new nationwide permit required to be proposed by the Secretary under section 3(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H36852D8718444FA58408A9620BC3FAFF"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Permittee</header><text>The term <term>permittee</term> means an individual or entity that proposes an activity under section 4(a)(1) to be carried out under the NWP.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H893C31E84780435D8EFF9BBB4ADFB8C3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Army, acting through the Chief of Engineers.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HFD1D1C2DA15E4829817710EA64AE3375"><enum>3.</enum><header>Dredging project nationwide permit</header><subsection id="H580FF98990AF4D8183CECD5AE70E059E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Proposal</header><paragraph id="H7FC873CE1A124FAFB9D57871D1172E6C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall propose a new nationwide permit under section 404(e) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1344">33 U.S.C. 1344(e)</external-xref>) relating to Federal and non-Federal dredging projects within the navigable waters of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H140DEB0CFCF64BCEB087AC30BDA22F54"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In proposing the NWP under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall require each Division Engineer to propose regional conditions for inclusion in the NWP.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7A3E9EE755BB474EBB81D20D02CCB070"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>Notwithstanding section 404(e)(2) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1344">33 U.S.C. 1344(e)(2)</external-xref>), the NWP shall be valid for a term of not more than 10 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H13CD0605779F42AEA599F93EDAA84365"><enum>(c)</enum><header>NEPA</header><paragraph id="H5A0BDFE7B4804536B5E9D8C555C03D11"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the requirements of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) with respect to the issuing of the NWP, the Secretary or a cooperating agency, as applicable—</text><subparagraph id="HA9373BED1CA94E509E0E16EB7E4E11CB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall—</text><clause id="H387823736E3C4E11B097D5FC2558D4D5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>complete the requirements under that Act for the NWP not later than 2 years after the date on which the Secretary proposes the NWP under subsection (a);</text></clause><clause id="HA891EC654D594584944562A1D0F15A82"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>subject to paragraph (2), ensure that there is produced, with respect to the NWP, not more than 1—</text><subclause id="H30DCD4480B224D39B2B7292E5BE8DFFF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>environmental impact statement;</text></subclause><subclause id="H7F45B7C4FF5D4156B0AA7DC7444CC5B1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>record of decision; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H32D63AEA51684947B5BFC95498A3B47B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>if necessary, environmental assessment; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H74242B17216942A6957726568ED523D4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>consider mitigation standards and metrics, including standards and metrics other than just compensation, to ensure that the impacts of the NWP on the environment are minimal; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H949D7DFD288D4FF6A62A1FB6522402BA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall not consider—</text><clause id="H9FB2A44E27D34DFA8386695CCC79EE92"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an alternative or condition of the NWP if it is not technically or economically feasible to permittees; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAE562F0A34FB4A719935B60148CAD6BF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an alternative to the NWP that is not within the jurisdiction of the Secretary or the cooperating agency, as applicable.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDF37570F1794FE6A6F0B14A97EE851F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Division Engineers</header><text>Each Division Engineer that proposes regional conditions for inclusion in the NWP under subsection (a)(2) may prepare not more than 1 environmental document required under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6DD47FF00C2942778FD9F7F24A8CBC90"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Final NWP</header><text>The Secretary shall issue the final NWP not later than 60 days after the date on which the Secretary completes the requirements with respect to the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H6EA7DCC116464804BE5EA7144457D8D5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>State or interstate water pollution control agency certifications</header><paragraph commented="no" id="HB88EAB6E386B4544B7A717E6E9ADACDE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Certification required</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD7BE089FFAC94AF09B0C6E059A296F64"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If, in developing the NWP, the Secretary is required to seek a water quality certification from a certifying authority under section 401 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1341">33 U.S.C. 1341</external-xref>), the certifying authority shall, within a reasonable period of time (which shall not exceed 14 days) after the date on which the Secretary submits the certification application pursuant to that section, make a determination on whether or not the application submitted by the Secretary is complete.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3C1B4FE137C14E248B59B21AB78B54FC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No response</header><text>If a certifying authority fails or refuses to make a determination with respect to a certification application submitted pursuant to subparagraph (A) within the timeframe referred to in that subparagraph, the certification shall be considered to be complete.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HFD03C25A878A4D29A25E6696FD8B99B0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Incomplete application</header><text>If a certifying authority determines that an application referred to in paragraph (1) is incomplete, the certifying authority shall, not later than 14 days after that determination, issue to the Secretary a detailed list of items required in order for an application to be considered complete.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCB7209C3FED846AF974F881DEBBC8D19"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Complete application</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7A159D58D2434ABD8C6DC704AF2FFD68"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a certifying authority determines that an application referred to in paragraph (1) is complete, the certifying authority shall, notwithstanding section 401(a)(1) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1341">33 U.S.C. 1341(a)(1)</external-xref>), act on the application within a reasonable period of time, which may not exceed 1 year from the date on which the certifying authority determines the application is complete.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4983157120304B0BACCC5A03C62F6C41"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No re-filing</header><text>If a certifying authority determines that an application submitted by the Secretary is complete, the certifying authority may not require the Secretary to re-file an application for the same proposed activity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H951E2384558844849A527229BF37C483"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Permits for dredged or filled material</header><paragraph id="HC1B8370C8D5D430E9F29A8F3EBFCB875"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out the requirements under section 404 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1344">33 U.S.C. 1344</external-xref>) with respect to activities carried out under the NWP, the Secretary shall only issue guidelines that are technologically and economically feasible for a permittee.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58C2821C65764D4CB6F05820B6C9D5FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certain disposal sites</header><text>Notwithstanding section 404(c) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1344">33 U.S.C. 1344(c)</external-xref>), the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency may consult with the Secretary on a defined disposal site or the application of guidelines, but may not—</text><subparagraph id="H2AD37058F22C49CF8B96BBDD40EBE3D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>prohibit the disposal site determination made by the Secretary; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H903071E42AC84CE48E3EEAD7F56E8C4B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>exercise any enforcement authority for a determination made by the Secretary, or against a permittee, in compliance with the NWP.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H64EFEFD4F1FF41218A6E29613DE8ACEA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Grant of permission</header><text>For purposes of the NWP, full compliance with section 404 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1344">33 U.S.C. 1344</external-xref>) shall be deemed to be a grant of permission under section 14(a) of the Act of March 3, 1899 (commonly known as the <quote>Rivers and Harbors Act of 1899</quote>) (30 Stat. 1152, chapter 425; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/408">33 U.S.C. 408(a)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD39071309F8C409A800D6290151EFD24"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act requires an additional permit under section 10 of the Act of March 3, 1899 (commonly known as the <quote>Rivers and Harbors Act of 1899</quote>) (30 Stat. 1151, chapter 425; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/403">33 U.S.C. 403</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="HE41394D4DC5B4633B51D5350BE67ED44"><enum>4.</enum><header>Proposed activities under the nationwide permit</header><subsection id="H78ECFC8776CB4C7B93A6FB68523493F1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorized activities</header><paragraph id="H804C62C7C74543F6A4D5CAA8C8AFC554"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a permittee seeks to carry out an activity authorized under the NWP, the permittee shall—</text><subparagraph id="HAAE91D004A514F41BF050DDC6A42586C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>notify the Secretary of that proposed activity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B5483AB958F4E4D826880DAC200CEBB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>seek approval, in writing, from the Secretary that the proposed activity complies with the NWP.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8580F7A3F25424984A26B364773C7E9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Decision</header><text>Not later than 14 days after the date on which the Secretary receives a written notification from a permittee under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall notify the permittee whether or not the application of the permittee is complete.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77BD0C7DE3A64714A8996729EC5B3E00"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Incomplete application</header><text>If the Secretary determines that an application submitted by a permittee under paragraph (1) is incomplete, the Secretary shall, not later than 14 days after that determination, provide to the permittee a list of information missing from that application in order for the application to be considered complete.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B790C75453D4E70ADBCDFB2B9C188C1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Complete application</header><subparagraph id="HBB8B56CF7F8C448FAA003108E58BC06B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Secretary determines that an application submitted by a permittee under paragraph (1) is complete, the Secretary shall, not later than 30 days after that determination, approve or deny the proposed activity of the permittee.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H178E8E5D369E4E7B9182D9674BB3E7AE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Denied proposed activities</header><text>If the Secretary denies the proposed activity of the permittee under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall, not later than 14 days after that denial, provide to the permittee, in writing—</text><clause id="HEA059ECAF4A54540A7A1DB621F6FAEB9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a list of reasons for that determination; and</text></clause><clause id="H66B18FEF1B25469A94EFE51E39E93E01"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>recommendations on how to improve the proposed activity to be in compliance with the NWP.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF52B531A13C94F66A1CD67D13EC88BE6"><enum>(5)</enum><header>No response</header><text>If the Secretary does not comply with a deadline described in paragraph (2), (3), or (4), or fails to respond to an application submitted by a permittee, the proposed activity of the permittee, as described in that application, shall be deemed in compliance with the NWP.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC5B622077FF54EADA0AF5E9390E921A2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Mitigation flexibility</header><text>In considering mitigation-specific requirements for a proposed activity for which approval is sought under subsection (a)(1), the Secretary, acting through the applicable Division Engineer, shall have the flexibility to determine which mitigation is needed with respect to the proposed activity, on the condition that each mitigation requirement is—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE6D6C64C562B42AFB80548DCB93AC788"><enum>(A)</enum><text>technically and economically feasible; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF38FFFAA04F046D39571D6CDCE4026B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>within the jurisdiction of the Secretary, acting through the applicable Division Engineer, to require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HACFF89C6D878416999C3D173B0DC5501"><enum>(b)</enum><header>NEPA</header><text>If a proposed activity for which approval is sought under subsection (a)(1) includes 1 or more activities that may likely have a significant effect on the quality of the human environment, as determined by the Secretary, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H0C2DC4D37F6F48239725E099881AD9E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>consider whether mitigating the circumstances or conditions of the proposed activity is sufficient to avoid the significant effects on the quality of the human environment that may result from that circumstance or condition of that proposed activity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E5994433CBF4C09AC79365B87B77A04"><enum>(2)</enum><text>if the Secretary determines under paragraph (1) that the significant effects that may likely result from the circumstance or condition of the proposed activity can be avoided, mitigate the circumstances or conditions of the proposed activity without—</text><subparagraph id="H83DDB31F13544A6A93D2C2670F07F30C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>denying the proposed activity; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21A3CBCDE4324698B4DE77B25B3F864D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>requiring the permittee to carry out the requirements of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4321">42 U.S.C. 4321 et seq.</external-xref>) for the proposed activity (or any portion of the proposed activity).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5F827327E7E5485C871730355333C42D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>State or interstate water pollution control agency certifications</header><paragraph id="H0C44F130E7214ACDABDEB76B4A751215"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Certification required</header><subparagraph id="H5BE933935D3646A8A57448653076D772"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the NWP requires a permittee to request a water quality certification from a certifying authority under section 401 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1341">33 U.S.C. 1341</external-xref>), the certifying authority shall, within a reasonable period of time (which shall not exceed 14 days) after the date on which the permittee submits the certification application pursuant to that section, make a determination on whether or not the application submitted by the permittee is complete. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDC36C06C72B4203982763E1A27F97A4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No response</header><text>If a certifying authority fails or refuses to make a determination with respect to a certification application submitted pursuant to subparagraph (A) within the timeframe referred to in that subparagraph, the certification shall be considered to be complete.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DA8C464A43C4FFDA83441C61081AB8E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Incomplete application</header><text>If a certifying authority determines that an application referred to in paragraph (1) is incomplete, the certifying authority shall, not later than 14 days after that determination, issue to the permittee a detailed list of items required in order for an application to be considered complete.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF33220518A7241839B017E0C20DE312B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Complete application</header><subparagraph id="H32B3C6C323DA40A18FC650124947B495"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If a certifying authority determines that an application referred to in paragraph (1) is complete, the certifying authority shall, notwithstanding section 401(a)(1) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1341">33 U.S.C. 1341(a)(1)</external-xref>), act on the application within a reasonable period of time, which may not exceed 1 year from the date on which the certifying authority determines the application is complete.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD25151547B8D4185819CD3467E525ED5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>No re-filing</header><text>If a certifying authority determines that an application submitted by a permittee is complete, the certifying agency may not require the permittee to re-file an application for the same proposed activity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9A1D48D939064348A67306F3A2ED6E5A"><enum>5.</enum><header>Dredging; dredged material</header><subsection id="H4928417FE37E42EFBA6051201B43C2EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Repeal</header><paragraph id="H91D247523DFF4428B82D99A1F2E5BBCB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 55109 of title 46, United States Code, is repealed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC4272DE719F4F85BBC155B057140825"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, is amended by striking the item relating to section 55109.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H50FAB04DBF444066954AE753B294FD01"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Excluding dredged material from transportation requirements</header><paragraph id="HC4F6490E87A84B499917B904E935898A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 55110 of title 46, United States Code, is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H71AFD7E0F210437EBDFEF847FD5B4845"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">or dredged material</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="section" style="OLC">(excluding dredged material)</header-in-text></quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC59F9EA61F3F4DB39BE2FBDA1001B4CA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or dredged material</quote> and inserting <quote>(excluding dredged material)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C3F6D7761CB4DACAA6944264373B938"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/46/551">chapter 551</external-xref> of title 46, United States Code, is amended by striking the item relating to section 55110 and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H62216E02EF004F0583E0ECCCA4CF200C"><toc><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">Sec. 55110. Transportation of valueless material (excluding dredged material).</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

