<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H178EB9D9FB24445C8E9F59101DC51906" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5443 IH: AACE Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5443</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230913">September 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a policy regarding appraisal and valuation services for real property for a transaction over which the Secretary of the Interior has jurisdiction, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H997E9F4773E940E09309A4A79813B525" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H886741679D88451ABFF84575D42AE595" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Accelerating Appraisals and Conservation Efforts Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>AACE Act</quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4FD120DD8C8E4A3986791E6EB5BE6B77" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Appraisal and valuation services for real property</header> <subsection id="H7FDDABDA064F4E9DBDB7B23F0AF0D488"><enum>(a)</enum><header>License, certification requirement</header><text>A covered appraiser needs to be licensed or certified in only 1 State to perform appraisal or valuation services for real property in any State for a transaction over which the Secretary has jurisdiction.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3A5987A0F2F54E75BE33D28193E9E70F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of non-Federal covered appraisers</header><text>If the Secretary uses a non-Federal covered appraiser to perform appraisal or valuation services for real property for a transaction described in subsection (a), the Secretary—</text> <paragraph id="H5FB724548DA544BD901D2DEFD5CB64F2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall, to the maximum extent practicable, use a non-Federal covered appraiser who is a certified general real property appraiser licensed in a State in which the real property that is the subject of the transaction is located; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBF992DBCF52048D5BFD7FB731FEE62DD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may only use a non-Federal covered appraiser who is a certified general real property appraiser licensed in a State other than one in which the real property that is the subject of the transaction is located if a non-Federal covered appraiser described in paragraph (1) is, as determined by the Secretary—</text> <subparagraph id="H97F3F95F46B5436BBB974795D92635EA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>unavailable;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9EC304B1C3E64F0FB81D7CC3F104E3CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not assignment qualified; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H619A1D4DD25B494BAB35F03ECB49752D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>not cost competitive.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3311FE78032D42C1BEDA6A4759E5B50B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, and annually thereafter for at least the following 4 years, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes the following:</text> <paragraph id="H79F3CA9AB7A54111ABC8BA8B5BC7C090"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A comparison using quantitative data of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H892A35B0997E41FCBC7F2CEA2A3A20C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of requests for appraisal and valuation services received by the Department during the reporting period and the number of requests for such services received by the Department in each of the 5 years before the reporting period; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H230B25C633094AA19EB76D94727A19F2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount of time required for the Department to complete a request for appraisal or valuation services before the date of the enactment of this section and after the date of the enactment of this section.</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H27FC15B85F7A42C8A76A67ECB1C34972" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A qualitative assessment of the impact of subsection (a) in providing flexibility to the Secretary when contracting with non-Federal covered appraisers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H08CC1052194D4B68914D72ACE86BF72C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Recommendations, if any, for congressional action that could help the Department operate more efficiently or overcome challenges with respect to timely completion of requests for appraisal or valuation services while ensuring the independence, impartiality, and objectivity of such services.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3798496F8D524ACAA0806F9AAB63FBD8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An overview of the workforce of the Department with regard to appraisal and valuation services provided by the Department, including hiring and staffing during the reporting period with respect to employees and contractors of the Department.</text></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="HC982DCDB216D46FBA294773544156A7D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Statutory clarifications</header> <paragraph id="H7887697895094337BD74B1E6FDDC1AF8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicability of relevant laws and regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (3), nothing in this section shall be interpreted to affect the application of any Federal or State law or regulation to a non-Federal covered appraiser with regard to the performance by such non-Federal covered appraiser of appraisal and valuation services for real property.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE8DD342C4D31435EBA3650D14B1A516D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Jurisdiction requirement</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be interpreted to authorize a non-Federal covered appraiser to perform appraisal and valuation services for real property in a State in which such non-Federal covered appraiser is not licensed or certified to perform such services except to the extent that such services are performed for a transaction over which the Secretary has jurisdiction.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="HE59C52B7FB5946F98A1E63022DC0ADCB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of certain relevant laws and regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any provision of a Federal or State law or regulation enacted before the date of the enactment of this section that requires a covered appraiser to be licensed or certified in a specific State to perform appraisal or valuation services for real property in that State shall not apply to any transaction over which the Secretary has jurisdiction.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0B985639795B49D48230ADB2D5096D8B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H16550ED30BE74CF7AA36FFAEF72AC2D2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered appraiser</header><text>The term <term>covered appraiser</term> means a State-licensed or -certified real property appraiser.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H803E496995014FBD89A6DF19459B3B68"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Department</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of the Interior.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H83961BE6DF9C4F4A930683F64FBCCE17"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reporting period</header><text>The term <term>reporting period</term> means the 1-year period before the date on which a report is submitted under subsection (c). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H835E8CD718104688B2EAE125A1182A3D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Interior.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBB99A4F4F0B94BA084367EF130BC1D4F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, and each territory and possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

