<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2993CD40608F4492A73299546EA4298B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 91 IH: One Bill, One Subject Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 91</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To require that each bill enacted by Congress be limited to only one subject, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H61AE540377F5402692E3D8C1D0DD049F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6E7839921CA3442A997E4B2A05E8B571" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>One Bill, One Subject Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H741B29C15F47450092D491FA3D741210"><enum>2.</enum><header>One subject per bill</header> <subsection id="H21144BA8B02F41CD9A90C5B04DF2A99B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>One subject</header><text>Each bill or joint resolution shall embrace no more than one subject.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H639FDC15AD8D406284256BDA7773E91A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Subject in title</header><text>The subject of a bill or joint resolution shall be clearly and descriptively expressed in the title.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB6256438C5C84FE9AB8F66E484B8B0DC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriation bills</header><text>An appropriations bill shall not contain any general legislation or change of existing law provision which is not germane to the subject matter of the underlying bill. This subsection does not prohibit any provision imposing limitations upon the expenditure of appropriated funds.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HA107E79AFD4F46B08FD60862FBDF2AFB"><enum>3.</enum><header>Enforcement</header> 
<subsection id="HE7DF0145B97A488995CC3F3D8C66FA19"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Multiple subjects in title</header><text>If the title of an Act or joint resolution addresses two or more unrelated subjects, then the entire Act or joint resolution is void.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H30AF2D8228E24A5A87C232EE5272EE54"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provisions not expressed in title</header><text>If an Act or joint resolution contains provisions concerning a subject that is not clearly and descriptively expressed in its title, those provisions shall be void.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4AAA35047054475BAF5631B0DACBC712"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriation provisions outside subcommittee jurisdiction</header><text>If an Act appropriating funds contains a provision outside of the jurisdiction of the relevant subcommittee of the Committees on Appropriations of the House and of the Senate, and therefore outside the subject of the bill, then such provision shall be void.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5E0C2A8974BD466A98B0CDA9A47E2A49"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Provisions of appropriations bills not germane to subject matter</header><text>If an Act appropriating funds contains general legislation or change of existing law provision not germane to the subject matter of the underlying bill, then every such provision shall be void.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H22B6EAAA7F7C42119A8D93A580ABC635"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Commencement of an action</header><text>Any person, including a Member of the House of Representatives or a Member of the Senate, aggrieved by the enforcement or threat of enforcement of Acts that do not comply with section 2 shall have a cause of action under sections 2201 and 2202 of title 28, United States Code, against the United States to seek appropriate relief, including an injunction against the enforcement of any law, the passage of which did not conform to section 2 or this section. The cause of action only applies to an Act or joint resolution signed into law on or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H75346A86169F4A3CA74B92FF408AE499"><enum>(f)</enum><header>State of review</header><text>In any judicial action brought pursuant to subsection (e), the standard of review shall be de novo.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


