<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C59BDE45D504FEE9993B8E78F7D4808" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 229 IH: World Deserves To Know Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 229</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To impose sanctions with respect to members of the Chinese Communist Party and heads of Chinese health agencies relating to the COVID&#8211;19 pandemic, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0CA0CE5B0F944F4FB8F857B19B9F7A14" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H81DD02D4593F49118CC50313A4C1326D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>World Deserves To Know Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB0BC251FC07D4BB1AC156895E7725F95"><enum>2.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to certain members of the Chinese Communist Party and heads of Chinese health agencies relating to the COVID–19 pandemic</header> <subsection id="HA81F1BF195E34F8E933061F1C58BF050"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Chinese Communist Party members</header> <paragraph id="HE954F97DAF224AE68CE204D148E79653"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall impose the sanctions described in section 1263 of the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2656">22 U.S.C. 2656</external-xref> note) with respect to any foreign person who is an official of the Chinese Communist Party that the President determines is knowingly responsible for, complicit in, or has directly or indirectly engaged in—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5A2AC0E32F0649CD9EAB561BD79C33F9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the disappearances of whistleblowers and citizen journalists in the People’s Republic of China relating to the COVID–19 pandemic; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2E4BCC89A46049AF8E0553DAABFCE117"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the establishment of limits on freedom of speech and academic freedom in the People’s Republic of China relating to the COVID–19 pandemic.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCBC5909A33E24C1B950F7051AD601CE3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The President shall coordinate with the intelligence community for purposes of identifying foreign persons under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4BAFA8D776D0400D96364D7C31DAB4B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Chinese health agencies heads</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall impose the sanctions described in subsection (c) with respect to the following foreign persons:</text> 
<paragraph id="HBADBA2381DB041469FFEED38431FDEA9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Gao Fu, also known as George Fu Gao, the Director of the Center for Disease Control and Prevention of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H35BFF89D0FF74BA68C2A05E9145572DA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ma Xiaowei, Minister of the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H018FFE9875FE4123A2F6AED1B1C9C854"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this subsection with respect to a foreign person are the following:</text> <paragraph id="HD224D36E5BE14ACC92F5BA2DD8042882"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall exercise all of the powers granted to the President under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) (except that the requirements of section 202 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in property and interests in property of the person if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H45FDFEC1989D4A3A82B0223A685B4EB8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inadmissibility to the United States and revocation of visa or other documentation</header> 
<subparagraph id="HEEEC53E2DBE84F62A8A84F642490BFE7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visa, admission, or parole</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The foreign person is—</text> <clause id="H6F2B6D975CB64E4B941D9068E08ED638"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H80BD171E97C44DD08B35A8E0D49FC0B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></clause> <clause id="H86FA87C3D8504CD1880CF305666373B8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H81D78215824F4069BE97C220A4CF5E2A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Current visa revoked</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The visa or other entry documentation of the foreign person shall be revoked, regardless of when such visa or other entry documentation is or was issued. A revocation under this subparagraph shall take effect immediately and automatically cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the person’s possession.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H14E38D8931FF42C4958F55F98B7301F6" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> <paragraph id="H2367530B2A29438F901892FC7A4C9447" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>To comply with United Nations Headquarters Agreement</header><text>Sanctions under subsection (c)(2) shall not apply with respect to a foreign person described in subsection (b) if admitting or paroling the foreign person into the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0B8B3B0212724A40AAD25A87D5056069" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>To carry out or assist law enforcement activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions under this section shall not apply to a foreign person, if admitting or paroling the foreign person into the United States is necessary to carry out or assist law enforcement activity in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFB1EEBF122CF40D28C48291C613EC32C" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Implementation; penalties</header> <paragraph id="H644BE1CA0D56436AB1BC287EDACEBFF4" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may exercise all authorities provided under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to carry out this section and shall issue such regulations, licenses, and orders as are necessary to carry out this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H038B93D7C592430394CBC396AAA17246" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Any person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of this section or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out paragraph (1) shall be subject to the penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE69DF02C18A64EBDA02A13EA7FC87806" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may waive the application of sanctions imposed with respect to a foreign person under this section if the President—</text> 
<paragraph id="H69DE5E2A1BD3428384BAD5BD58B9D6E0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determines that a waiver is in the national interest of the United States; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H814850FABFA94B33A60740C8EFCA321B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than the date on which such waiver will take effect, submits to the appropriate congressional committees a notice of and justification for such waiver.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H244E68DB2BC04130A72A9D1200670B56" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination of sanctions with respect to a foreign person</header> 
<paragraph id="H743CA95016A24B5D860BA36AEE3909D0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may terminate the application of sanctions imposed with respect to a foreign person under this section if the President makes a determination that—</text> <subparagraph id="H4D534D75ED104E12AC6A69D86A757205" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>credible information exists that the person did not engage in the activity for which the sanctions were imposed; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H99B35DCBB08C4C4D8F7502C4A9A5A206" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the person has—</text> <clause id="H295CA39A71B540E0BAB54F2FB28F5BE1" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>credibly demonstrated a significant change in behavior; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB3EEAB832E3D4AF0AAE37837821C1929" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>been subject to an appropriate consequence for the activity for which the sanctions were imposed.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCE35EBA723AE4921A9CA6A5743C5B425" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>Not later than 15 days before the date on which the application of sanctions imposed with respect to a foreign person is terminated under paragraph (1), the Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1DEFAA8431F34DD2A6F7D0DAA0520BDB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>describes the evidence and justification for the necessity of the termination; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H21AEEB6FDDF04FEB81E0916702D3E123" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>explains how the termination of the application of sanctions is in the national security interests of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H54263464291347BA974AFD702A25978B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Termination of authority To impose sanctions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority to impose sanctions under this section with respect to a foreign person described in subsection (b) shall terminate on the date on which the President certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that an independent, unimpeded investigation into the potential origin of COVID–19 from the Wuhan Institute of Virology has taken place.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H08841A09A31B4992831D7F4DCE384B67" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Exception relating to importation of goods</header> <paragraph id="H1C0A3C2431CD4EA181F6C15AD892B4C8" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authorities and requirements to impose sanctions under this section shall not include the authority or requirement to impose sanctions on the importation of goods.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD8379376039C408C8BDBE2AD1CDC1278" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Good defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>good</quote> means any article, natural or man-made substance, material, supply or manufactured product, including inspection and test equipment, and excluding technical data.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H8369C106ABE445A3B9A02760019B3D16" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on new contracts</header> <subsection id="HA72F7E65C1C64DF68E7C1F09B5437723"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Institutions of higher education</header> <paragraph id="H6E92C3DBF6C14520A907D505DFA1CCBC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds may be made available to an institution of higher education (as defined in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>)) that enters into a contract with—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF6D1ACD56CAC4DC69CBD476B54FBE4D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any element or department of the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H34019330269E4D97998BB49A2AD8F4B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any agency or office that reports to the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE89DF13327184CD9B5F3A5880B5EF190"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any Chinese-based entity affiliated with the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD7FD67C884B64E79BCFF7D3FFFE32D81"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Program participation agreements under the Higher Education Act of 1965</header><text>Section 487(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1094">20 U.S.C. 1094(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0CC84216604C4B37AA32E4F4924D2FD2" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="H432AA63B6B2F4B738ADCB7243F9707EB"><enum>(30)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The institution will not enter into a contract with—</text> <subparagraph id="H98530833253E49DEBEF147AC2AC4DC92"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any element or department of the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF9E93D133B064CD5B47631362AB393E0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any agency or office that reports to the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE97B8A837C644CB3A303281F2D66F7FC"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any Chinese-based entity affiliated with the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1F44CF7F53E54470A430343720EAC3B7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National Academy of Sciences</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No Federal funds made available to the National Academy of Sciences may be used to enter into a contract with—</text> <paragraph id="H4F1428DCFCEB47B0A4EA218E18207758"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any element or department of the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9599BC591DF94D4791B6BE5B4485E34E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any agency or office that reports to the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA8C683EA9CF4705920A6D3369327843"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any Chinese-based entity affiliated with the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HC902C000989347CBAA966F9FE14CB0D1" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Review of NIH funding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States, in consultation with the Director of National Intelligence, shall—</text> <paragraph id="H50982467C8874C9FBA53A9272C01F4A0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct a full review of all funds made available by the National Institutes of Health, directly or indirectly, during or after fiscal year 2010, to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HFB07831D3182430BAB9E9EC562F114EC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2D30426F688F48618B42A70D954BC00F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any agency or office that reports to the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H72D541DB8DFA484491444CFC4C6A39D1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any Chinese-based entity that is affiliated with the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC7D3DAB99E61402C8B195401CD47B3B7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>make publicly available, and submit to the Congress, a report on the results of such review; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9CF2D2B4C1DA4D228B1C42D0AA8A94EA" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in such report, clearly identify any funds described in paragraph (1) that were used for gain of function research.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H76F7FEC7139C4D5F9D6FB9D32E76851E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that given Taiwan’s early alerting to the global health community on the dangers of COVID–19 while senior officials in the Chinese Communist Party downplayed COVID–19 Taiwan should be granted observer status in the World Health Assembly (WHA).</text></section> 
<section id="H4E1981BC8E1C43E19E0AC4E902BE07CE"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act: </text> <paragraph id="H694CC280EC4F475B9B83C353A3740834" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Admitted; alien</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>admitted</quote> and <quote>alien</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 101 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1001">8 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H474BE52326CC4FF49DB1D6207E86DB6D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H3C08A8A53D4A488B916E7C1A6DE60D7D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAE4F5E6A07D0423BB7AEF11690050341"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H32A466C1F32745BBBBF91958313FD9A3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign person</header><text>The term <quote>foreign person</quote> means a person that is not a United States person.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC49565E8797C430E97CA5EEB2C63622B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Intelligence community</header><text>The term <quote>intelligence community</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 3(4) of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003(4)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5A691BECE10453D84108716B42996BB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Knowingly</header><text>The term <quote>knowingly</quote> means, with respect to conduct, a circumstance, or a result, that a person has actual knowledge, or should have known, of the conduct, the circumstance, or the result.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7ABBD8D98BF54E54B93EF883274D8548"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Person</header><text>The term <quote>person</quote> means an individual or entity. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H04E7089356EE47E8843E6B1EAFEF4126"><enum>(7)</enum><header>United States person</header><text>The term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7C9B7686ECCD4544A8579F6E809E36A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen, an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States, or any other individual subject to the jurisdiction of the United States; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB9A670FD38DD41D3BFCF6DC313B614EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such entity; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA88F6B98AAB84C08A0859B1BCB19C0E7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any person in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

