<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H854CED3C85284965890A2FCF96416398" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3178 IH: Grayfield Redevelopment and Economic Advancement Through Effective Repurposing and Revitalization of Shopping Centers Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3178</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 to authorize grants to assist in redeveloping abandoned shopping centers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6A36CE588A894253A191605211772549" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HBF423F3D32444EC3A1DA5B1BA8F20936"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Grayfield Redevelopment and Economic Advancement Through Effective Repurposing and Revitalization of Shopping Centers Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>GREATER Revitalization of Shopping Centers Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H996297098CB449D5AE58AC90DF4D3D5D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grayfields shopping centers redevelopment grants</header> <subsection id="H2922661C303947C182BFAA4F170A766C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 108 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5308">42 U.S.C. 5308</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC4566510231F4CED976F339D8708633B">
<subsection id="HDF66799483B64D5391290E7536F425BB"><enum>(s)</enum><header>Shopping center redevelopment grants</header>
<paragraph id="H23B6D457FB6142A4B2E677BE41A89F15"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conjunction with notes or other obligations issued by eligible public entities or designated public agencies for the purpose of financing projects that meet the criteria under paragraph (2) and that are guaranteed under this section, the Secretary may make grants to those eligible public entities or designated public agencies in connection with those guarantees for the purpose of enhancing the security of the notes or obligations or improving the viability of projects financed with those notes or obligations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6EDB73AB7BB04F0BBFE23006B0E1A0F3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Project requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A project meets the criteria under this paragraph only if the project—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1A4DC8C6FC3248B791A9050B2500677D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is designed to eliminate blight, including on a spot basis, through redevelopment and revitalization of facilities that—</text> <clause id="H11633A78C3B2432FAE1A01EFDDA06281"><enum>(i)</enum><text>were originally developed as shopping centers,</text></clause>
<clause id="H21543664B418493FA1797B08AFFAF06A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>consist of an enclosed facility covering not less than 20 acres,</text></clause> <clause id="H341C35394D534E4383D49C1F09ED0D4C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>contain—</text>
<subclause id="H82ADAF9E74854B4884B84D501C425FFF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>not less than 40 individual storefronts of which less than 30 percent are occupied at the time the grant is awarded, or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H912B7A56B7D1474A8006F9A8EEDD4572"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">2 or more vacant major department stores, grocery stores, or other large chain stores having substantial economic strength and occupying substantial square footage of the facility, and</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="H0D735A84E7CA4A218CD150EBE5DBEC4D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>include a common parking area;</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">except that the Secretary may establish alternative criteria to the requirements under this subparagraph for eligibility of shopping centers for assistance as the Secretary considers appropriate; and </continuation-text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H52D18A379CC045568791C7E5DB675512"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meets such requirements as the Secretary shall establish to ensure that the project promotes—</text>
<clause id="HCFB4B13D1EDC406BB15E0F08043986C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>transit-oriented development;</text></clause> <clause id="HEC97549C45DA4C4BB777C0136682A23D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reclaiming and re-use of grayfields;</text></clause>
<clause id="H13BCB31148BF47C6A35372C09BBDCD30"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>development of affordable housing;</text></clause> <clause id="HDDD2763B1DDD46F0AC87D2AA1A4E226C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>removal of existing grayfield infrastructure;</text></clause>
<clause id="HCDF8F9AE0AEA41099D9555E87F10E6A4"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">such other priorities as the Secretary considers appropriate, including with respect to smaller jurisdictions and non-metropolitan areas; or</text></clause> <clause id="H3B71CFB1B3344161A191648BCCE83088"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>any 2 or more of the priorities specified in or pursuant to this subparagraph.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAF1F67EB2DB44FEC8EFE15E03EF8AE35"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of a grant pursuant to this section may not exceed $5,000,000.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF5B58CC99B554AC29E35AA63C80E27A5"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Matching requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall require each eligible public entity or designated public agency to which a grant is made pursuant to this subsection to contribute to the project for which the grant is made an amount from sources other than the grant, including local and State tax abatements, in-kind contributions, and Federal tax incentives, that exceeds 50 percent of the amount of the grant.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8BC8DB9701354971B86394434D3F7BEE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Preference</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In making grants pursuant to this section, the Secretary shall give preference to eligible public entities and designated public agencies based on the extent to which—</text> <subparagraph id="H882358FFB4D14EACAD0730E058BE4DFA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the amount proposed to be contributed pursuant to paragraph (4) exceeds the minimum amount required by such paragraph to be contributed;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H18BC34C5811047EBA53A8DFCA2A212F5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the project reflects the results of extensive community engagement; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF91DE7671F324F49B6EA54D76FEE9ADB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the project would benefit lower-income, underserved communities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H047711D0D2D840EA88FD20FFA0027542"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header>
<subparagraph id="HA2579DA9FAA34FADBA93F5942058E851"><enum>(A)</enum><header>HUD</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, in accordance with section 102 of the Department of Housing and Urban Development Reform Act of 1989 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3545">42 U.S.C. 3545</external-xref>), provide technical guidance and assistance to applicants for grants under this subsection regarding—</text> <clause id="H4DD70BA650CE482BAF06922E19B456BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>how to apply for grants under this subsection; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H3FBC00D3647D45BB8AD5D26BAEA8799F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>how to avoid conflicts relating to using funding pursuant to this section in conjunction with Federal tax-exempt financing.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H73899FDF8AD5497E8EA53CC9019A6B41"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Local</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible public entity or designated public agency receiving a grant under this subsection may use not more than 25 percent of the grant amounts to obtain technical assistance from local qualified service providers regarding combining that assistance with other financing with—</text>
<clause id="H63EEC250A8DB4EE1B474FDC9E8296C66"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other Federal assistance, including the New Markets Tax Credits program and Low-Income Housing Tax Credit program under sections 45D and 42, respectively, of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; and</text></clause> <clause id="HC18F4F8F2D6B440F9F43831FA97843AF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>other State assistance, tax credits, and incentives, including tax-increment financing and other bonding instruments.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H86B8CAF603F54C358A7D0A14E697EC0C"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Reports</header>
<subparagraph id="H458544EE266F4E8FA98CCC7B4E5FBF2A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>HUD</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each fiscal year for which grants are made under this subsection, the Secretary shall submit a report to the Congress, not later than 90 days after the end of such fiscal year, that identifies—</text> <clause id="H8B52C6AEE1C54576B320E296F10D77C9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>each project assisted with such grant amounts;</text></clause>
<clause id="H0E671767BF0347CF8282D39E26A62544"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount of non-Federal funds contributed to the project; and</text></clause> <clause id="H0604FC36D9F34B889F08A567C14E219B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>how the grant amounts were used.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC6780A04D61D4BE693FC3884F4F8915C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>GAO</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit a report to the Congress analyzing the effectiveness of the program for grants under this section and making recommendations to improve future outcomes among shopping mall redevelopment and revitalization projects and similar subsidy programs administered in conjunction with Federal loan guarantees.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3F9DB4F940184C8C96B5D0839AA3D6C4"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection:</text>
<subparagraph id="HF5391A78D4BB4FC4A830219DCC0E9F51"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Transit-oriented development</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>transit-oriented development</term> means a project that—</text> <clause id="HEA569C4653024E638A9EBA2701E44F97"><enum>(i)</enum><text>enhances economic development and achieve other goals established during the project development and engineering processes;</text></clause>
<clause id="H4E36484036B14725B8CF140F81533EA6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>facilitates multimodal transportation connectivity and accessibility;</text></clause> <clause id="HC99637F896AE49DFA8194332800DBC71"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>increases access to transit hubs for pedestrian and bicycle traffic;</text></clause>
<clause id="H029060A7654042E4AF574372C4763B02"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>enables mixed-use development;</text></clause> <clause id="HE033A992B25948158AC228AFA9643C63"><enum>(v)</enum><text>identifies infrastructure needs associated with the project; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H7907FB97AA23445DA2515AD0920203AA"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>includes private sector participation.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC6B2E6CD60B745FABC85FE9D91DEA96A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grayfield</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>grayfield</term> means an economically obsolescent, outdated, failing, moribund, or underused real estate asset.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H874F656639F149649FBA11EE51B1AA5A"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated for grants under this subsection $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 and 2025, which amounts shall remain available until expended.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HD5C2BD1411D14E77A95A57E97545F34B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>CDBG loan guarantee cap</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to section 502 of the Congressional Budget Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/661a">2 U.S.C. 661a</external-xref>), during each of fiscal years 2024 and 2025, commitments to guarantee loans under section 108 of the Housing and Community Development Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5308">42 U.S.C. 5308</external-xref>), any part of which is guaranteed, shall not exceed a total principal amount of $500,000,000, notwithstanding any aggregate limitation on outstanding obligations guaranteed in subsection (k) of such section 108.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

