<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5E958C7981514C94893BB5CBAC18607B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6220 IH: Adoption Deserves Oversight, Protection, and Transparency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6220</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231103">November 3, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="A000055">Mr. Aderholt</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to criminalize unlawful adoption practices.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H31B84DB648374B369BA78DF32CAABB84" style="OLC">
<section id="H12C7CB62A58C4E2AA8F7EDA5F05CFE68" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Adoption Deserves Oversight, Protection, and Transparency Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>ADOPT Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H28DD54B934A74389A9CC5998E3AD57D2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to:</text>
<paragraph id="HF0756DA6E6C44E0AA9C65252540A9EBE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Protect individuals and families impacted by private domestic adoption from exploitation by unlicensed adoption intermediaries.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4632693AA0474370B7679C42A554C5CD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Ensure that individuals seeking assistance with domestic adoption have ready access to licensed and regulated adoption providers in their communities. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H17CC9E70AFE34D7586F66990CE7D8DCD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Prevent the commodification of children. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="H381635444D5C4118B83B638737E398C6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Adoption offense</header> <subsection id="H91975C462B5E42678B283B9674720AAF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/11A">Chapter 11A</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H5A033F2EBAA04F7CAE3E25CA3359475C" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="HFCACA066910148339094786222A88197"><enum>228A.</enum><header>Unlawful adoption practices</header>
<subsection id="HE2DD491F110E4A0CAA07BECA83927A1B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Adoption intermediary services</header>
<paragraph id="H3285E2A32ECA45F989DFD3D94D03EF43"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Offense</header><text>Whoever, in any circumstance described in subsection (d), knowingly provides or offers to provide adoption intermediary services shall be punished as provided in accordance with subsection (e).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7159A3A1AA654EFC9E114FD26EDB4208"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H35C041464E144EA6AA06DD86C7405AFA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a public child-placing agency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H53C72F79BC55462D8C1C0D31EF109F48"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a private licensed child-placing agency; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD80535D5EA314EF0B209EC93523614E3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a licensed attorney.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H458FFC501CB745C9A0C900AE94C7FC9F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Adoption advertising</header> <paragraph id="HBACC935A2A374DBFA5FEF4E54AD151AE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Offense</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever, in any circumstance described in subsection (d), knowingly places an adoption advertisement shall be punished in accordance with subsection (e).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC94D4BD08A2645FA93E89644858C087F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to—</text> <subparagraph id="H894993D4E567498E9D00B21B18D9B7AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a public child-placing agency or private licensed child-placing agency licensed to provide services in the State wherein the advertisement appears; </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H4DDC9BF8C6D44063B75EC7CBF4E35B25"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an attorney licensed in the State wherein the advertisement appears; or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4E5B47D7367547289BD1E72E7764396A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an adoption service provider accredited or approved in accordance with the Intercountry Adoption Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1490">42 U.S.C. 1490</external-xref> note) advertising an intercountry adoption program. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H18B1E4D2CD7148F6ADCC4ADD1B886F94"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Unauthorized payments to or on behalf of a placing parent</header>
<paragraph id="H8A638EFB95BD45CAB2A2AAD190496E1E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Offense</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whoever, in any circumstance described in subsection (d), knowingly provides anything of value, including money, property, or services, whether payment is made directly or indirectly for the benefit of the placing parent in furtherance of an adoption in an amount exceeding $500, shall be punished in accordance with subsection (e).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA3E4F3EBE894A4AA477EC990CFFD4A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (1) shall not apply with respect to payments made by or in cooperation with—</text>
<subparagraph id="HE202B9E67FDC4EF492CED836B23CBDE5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a private child-placing agency licensed in the State where the placing parent resides or is located; or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H61363B78405F4B99A775FA09D75D75D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an attorney licensed in the State where the placing parent resides or is located.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7E6221FF093240F68B812564D2EC4DD2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>For the purposes of sections (a), (b), and (c), the circumstances described in these subsections are that—</text> <paragraph id="H97B25E7651E3463CA151F78972FD54EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the offender or victim traveled in interstate commerce, or traveled using a means, channel, facility, or instrumentality of interstate commerce, in furtherance of or in connection with the conduct described in subsections (a), (b), or (c);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB2A9FB1282AB484E86EBBDAB3396C1E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the offender used a means, channel, facility, or instrumentality of interstate commerce in furtherance of or in connection with the conduct described in subsections (a), (b), or (c);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H928C5E0ADC6C49EFAED6A10AE99DBCDC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any payment of any kind was made, directly or indirectly, in furtherance of or in connection with the conduct described in subsections (a), (b), or (c) using any means, channel, facility, or instrumentality of interstate commerce or in or affecting interstate commerce; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCA88AD6953C145FAA6B3A643EDFB3C02"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the offender transmitted in interstate commerce any communication relating to or in furtherance of the conduct described in subsections (a), (b), or (c) using any means, channel, facility, or instrumentality of interstate commerce or in or affecting interstate commerce by any means or in manner, including by computer, mail, wire, or electromagnetic transmission; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB4002447CA7147B7A7385FABE79460D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the conduct described in subsection (a) otherwise occurred in or affected interstate or foreign commerce.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFC915A01F8B142549ABA00AAEDE17470"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Whoever violates subsection (a), (b), or (c)—</text> <paragraph id="H8D4CD9AAFBC34C228276DF74F917C5EA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of an individual, shall be fined $100,000, imprisoned for not more than 5 years, or both, per violation; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD3BE251AC51F4844BCC9A529C4BA8A28"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of an organization, shall be fined $250,000 per violation. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAADB508FD3F24E3DB6FF63C2CF93BC9B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to affect the application of the Indian Child Welfare Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1901">25 U.S.C. 1901 et seq.</external-xref>) or limit the provision of intercountry adoption programs and services authorized under the Intercountry Adoption Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/14921">42 U.S.C. 14921</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H37A348EC57FC4B12AE6715F1E4E76E09"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H9601669D9A174125B11BB1AC8AED417C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Adoption advertising</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>adoption advertising</term> means a paid advertisement, article, notice, or other paid communication published in any newspaper, magazine, or on the internet, on a billboard, over radio or television, or other similar media that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H79B273254D7B4DB79B343FAD23643EFD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>solicits prospective adoptive parents for the purpose of acting as a link between a placing parent and a prospective adoptive parent, or the prospective adoptive parent’s representative, attorney, or agency, for the transfer of legal or physical custody of a child, including adoptive placement;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0999CF8D26BD4BA8AC2C8D5079B44A39"><enum>(B)</enum><text>solicits placing parents for the purpose of acting as a link between a placing parent and a prospective adoptive parent, or the prospective adoptive parent’s representative, attorney, or agency, for the transfer of legal or physical custody of a child, including adoptive placement; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6B959DEAF80847A99A2C6BA63582B43E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>offers to pay a placing parent’s living expenses in connection with any transfer or potential transfer of legal or physical custody of a child, including adoptive placement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD6634E217DD14CAC87473EAC6DAAEFE9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Adoption intermediary services</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>adoption intermediary services</term> means the provision of any of the following services, in exchange for direct or indirect compensation:</text>
<subparagraph id="HB4D3671A95E54362AA0CA0377FA479A2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Soliciting placing parents, whether through adoption advertising or other means, for the purposes of acting as a link between a placing parent and a prospective adoptive parent, or the prospective adoptive parent’s representative, attorney, or agency, for the transfer of legal or physical custody of their child, including adoptive placement. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9D1F28EEE6E84BBD9D4E9C1801FDE094"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Soliciting prospective adoptive parents, whether through adoption advertising or other means, for the purpose of acting as a link between a placing parent and a prospective adoptive parent, or the prospective adoptive parent’s representative, attorney, or agency, for the transfer of legal or physical custody of a child, including adoptive placement.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD8D7091018DC4E59ADDC815B456DA894"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Acting as a link between placing parents of a child and prospective adoptive parents, whether directly or through the prospective adoptive parents’ representative, agency, or attorney, for the purpose of the transfer of physical or legal custody of the child, including adoptive placement. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA92A91051084541AB9CB0F0A666E7F9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Placing parent</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>placing parent</term> means a parent with legal authority to place the child for adoption.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H793A6AC5D5B749EC822E2E6D6D1B275B" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Public child-placing agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>public child-placing agency</term> means any government child welfare agency or child protection agency that has the legal authority to place children for adoption.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0642105DBAA746689A8E38447FB2B6C0" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Private licensed child-placing agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>private licensed child-placing agency</term> means a licensed or State approved agency that has the legal authority to place children for adoption.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H6C3DBCDB02A04D0AB23FCADEE2C2CD84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header>
<paragraph id="H8506244E4B1447C496E3E65E162AA6F1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Chapter heading</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The chapter heading for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/11A">chapter 11A</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="chapter" style="USC">and unlawful adoption practices</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="chapter" style="USC">child support</header-in-text></quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H498D76A1C1184FDE8AE2625FB5A0A7D6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Table of sections</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/11A">chapter 11A</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding after the item relating to section 228, the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HFEAB683144414FAA8A3228A942C5F531" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">228A. Unlawful adoption practices.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H961A9532FBEC44329929550D6577D589"><enum>4.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by this Act shall take effect on the date that is 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

