<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7328D14581E9477A8799C6B48D523E69" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5060 IH: Women's Retirement Protection Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5060</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="U000040">Ms. Underwood</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 to provide for greater spousal protection under defined contribution plans, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFDCD7F07610E4F4CB5809EB6C460F627" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H285FF8B91326421F9AD0940B6F1DBB2F"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Women's Retirement Protection Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H11B447112E7D42B181519E1339EBD748"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HCF9B8C8BE0754303A007174AFC663C74"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Approximately 25 percent of non-retired adults have no defined benefit plan or retirement savings, according to 2021 data from the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9BCBF6DD5AF448B7ADAB8C93754622FC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In 2021, approximately one-third of the private sector workforce did not have access to a retirement plan at the workplace, and only half of the workforce actually participated in a retirement plan.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3293E3195A0143C29EE32A1D39CC1695"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Women’s retirement preparedness often lags significantly behind their male counterparts', resulting in the median income for women aged 65 and older in 2022 being just 83 percent of the median income of men aged 65 and older, including income from social security, pension plans, investments, and earnings.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H715609D8BED14B65907E6B63E0F5A24F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Women aged 80 and older had the highest poverty rate among older persons in all age groups, with 14.7 percent of women aged 80 and older living in poverty while 10.3 percent of men in the same age group live in poverty.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8BC3592328B94A14A5958729821F3022"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Women make up two-thirds of low-wage workers, even though they comprise less than half of all workers, and low-wage workers are less likely than other workers to participate in a retirement plan at work.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFB2AED243E6F46EFA0B3DD17BF103675"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Because of the pay gap, women working full-time, year-round typically lose $398,160 over a 40-year career thereby requiring the average woman to work almost a decade longer than her male counterpart to make up that career wage gap.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4784D4D010A1443BAA1D21B569EAAAF7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Due to the lower lifetime wages stemming from unequal pay and caregiving duties, the average Social Security benefit in 2021 for a woman was $1,484 a month, while for men such average monthly benefit was $1,838.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5E04D825292F4B449E908BC75B39F841"><enum>(8)</enum><text>While the SECURE 2.0 Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>) will go a long way to address this coverage gap, just 1 in 5 part-time workers who work a full year are eligible for a retirement plan, and women are almost twice as likely to work part-time as men.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDB544E14D5A044E391FB5D32B5F1E61C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>While traditional defined benefit retirement plans have spousal protections, defined contribution retirement plans, which have become increasingly common, currently provide no similar spousal protections.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C9598B81EA14B98BE75318BF4C906E4"><enum>(10)</enum><text>The Thrift Savings Plan of the Federal Government, the largest defined contribution plan in the world with approximately 6,500,000 participants, requires its married participants to have their spouses consent for withdrawals and loans.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA0513BAF047C498982BDD621B6AAC5AE"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There were almost 700,000 divorces in the United States between 2020 and 2021. After the family home, retirement savings tends to be the largest asset to be divided in a divorce.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE89CCFD5A98148569387DD4B8F0FA9C8"><enum>(12)</enum><text>While fees and expenses associated with retirement plans have been in decline, participants have seen direct charges for processing qualified domestic relations orders increase significantly.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H213457339D0847C1ACF414DD7E34249B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Increasing spousal protection under defined contribution plans</header> 
<subsection id="H5E5C308630CA496DA3AB959249B81EF6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment of Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974</header> 
<paragraph id="H68C08244739945EE91AB6F34EE3AF2FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part 2 of subtitle B of title I of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1051">29 U.S.C. 1051 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 205 the following new section:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="HF46FCD6EA5114D36B151C202B54614C7"> <section id="H21DDC284444E4A25BBA05F9C11B70FD3"><enum>205A.</enum><header>Additional spousal consent requirements</header> <subsection id="HE3A0C5F22CE74D65A0C43FDE35D8CDC4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each individual account plan to which section 205 does not apply shall provide that, except as provided in subsections (c) and (d), no distribution may be made under the plan unless the spousal consent requirements of subsection (e) are met.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H430AA1C4EF1B47FDAD7214EE38A309F1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Coordination with section 205</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to exempt an individual account plan from the requirements of paragraph (1)(B), (1)(C), or (2) of section 205(b) with respect to any participant.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H1A4A96895A75436B9480BDA6069579B0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions for certain distributions</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC087BB3A77F24BE180911ACDBB8EE33D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any distribution that is—</text> <subparagraph id="H6544E81333B44DC19137492866B1E7C1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a minimum required distribution described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4974">section 4974(b)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3A6D37713C75424CA7F3037D9907D359"><enum>(B)</enum><text>permitted under section 203(e)(1) to be made without the consent of the participant; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8C3D2FC36CC427FA81711432C5B127A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in an amount that is less than 25 percent of the account balance;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H2EA702978117494D8F45111BC3FA24E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any distribution in the form of a qualified joint and survivor annuity (as defined in section 205(d)(1)), a qualified optional survivor annuity (as defined in section 205(d)(2)), a qualified preretirement survivor annuity (as defined in section 205(e)), or a series of substantially equal periodic payments (not less frequently than annually) made for the joint lives (or life expectancies) of the participant and the participant's spouse; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H13CECBEE3A4F4344BE74C7B42C0A2674"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the case of a participant who does not elect a form of benefit described in paragraph (2) under the plan or who is participating in a plan that does not provide such a form of benefit, any distribution of the participant's entire nonforfeitable accrued benefit if 50 percent of such accrued benefit is transferred to an individual retirement plan (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7701">section 7701(a)(37)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) of the spouse of the participant.</text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">A transfer described in paragraph (3) to an individual retirement plan shall be treated in the same manner as a transfer under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/408">section 408(d)(6)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</continuation-text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3887CA1375B0493D80FD3B17551D1D37"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exceptions for certain rollover contributions</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to any distribution, involving a participant who has a spouse, that is an eligible rollover distribution (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/402">section 402(f)(2)(A)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) made in the form of a direct trustee-to-trustee transfer within the meaning of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/401">section 401(a)(31)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986—</text> <paragraph id="H2CA9556902C54235A1286A0C1863D966"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to a plan to which this section or section 205 applies; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5C75BE02320540B8BE3356391324AA40"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to an individual retirement plan (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/7701">section 7701(a)(37)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986) if—</text> <subparagraph id="H32909A12774D4A4F8AE45DDDE15A0EA4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the beneficiary of such plan is the spouse of the participant, or the spousal consent requirements of subsection (e) are met with respect to any designation of 1 or more other beneficiaries; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H53EC4926F99E45DB81CC2F19E5EA6E7D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>under the terms of the individual retirement plan, the beneficiary of such plan (whether the spouse or other beneficiary designated under paragraph (1)) may not be changed unless—</text> <clause id="H4F7FDE43B68B4318AE338E2DD7F593CD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the spousal consent requirements of subsection (e) are met with respect to any such change, or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H56CFBB328B4B41A9AD702FE28109FCCE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the spousal consent under subparagraph (A) to the designation of a beneficiary other than the spouse expressly permits such designation to be changed without the further consent of the spouse.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7F802BE37E1449F98F0AFBAA34BD353D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Spousal consent requirements</header> <paragraph id="H53DD2979B3524BFEABA3BC3613F8C1B5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this section, except as provided in paragraph (2), the spousal consent requirements of this subsection are met with respect to any distribution or any designation or change of beneficiary if—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7BD7C524648540CDADE5D884B3159696"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the plan provides to each participant, within a reasonable period of time before such distribution or designation or change of beneficiary is made and consistent with such regulations as the Secretary of the Treasury may prescribe, a written explanation of the rights of the participant and the participant's spouse under this section;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDC9ED2CDFFEF4BC686DEA050DDE52B9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the spouse of the participant consents in writing to the distribution or designation or change of beneficiary;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF35899DAA7984138B241BDA4A14EE5F1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the case of a distribution, the written consent under subparagraph (B) is made during the consent period; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAC5BC1EC7AEE4101A4F1A8A9CFA563D0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the written consent under subparagraph (B)—</text> 
<clause id="H051922C655BA46AEBDB124F3720E0A1F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>acknowledges the effect of such distribution or designation or change of beneficiary; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA5CB85AF5CE544348E22E38E64B0B355"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is witnessed by a plan representative or a notary public.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6CE57379387C435386F6956DC13C3298"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions under section 205(c)(2)(B) to apply</header><text>The requirements of paragraph (1) (other than subparagraph (A) thereof) shall not apply with respect to any distribution or designation or change of beneficiary if a participant establishes to the satisfaction of the plan administrator that—</text> <subparagraph id="H872647F068F846C3ADD13552D46A0A04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>there is no spouse;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3EAAA7103A024D5CBFDFEC89F8526183"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the participant and the participant's spouse have not been married for at least 1 year as of the date of the distribution or designation or change of beneficiary; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA6C891CADDA947B3AA99F1259760848C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>such consent cannot be obtained because—</text> 
<clause id="H248B8610642046109A46589110A0EDF4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the spouse cannot be located; or</text></clause> <clause id="HDC1D6974CFEF4767854EF39D28D3C4E7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>of such other circumstances as the Secretary of the Treasury, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor, may by regulations prescribe.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1BBD51F07A07485C9F963B374C04F564"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consent limited to spouse and event</header><text>Any written consent by a spouse under paragraph (1), or the establishment by a participant that an exception under paragraph (2) applies with respect to a spouse, shall be effective only with respect to that spouse and to the distribution or designation or change of beneficiary to which it relates.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3351A2AC7FDC4DAF96305C45B858FA85"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consent period</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>consent period</term> means, with respect to any distribution—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE45836EF804A4DC8B7BDA5CBAB58B738"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the 90-day period immediately preceding the date of such distribution; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8D857C5BF63F4616B22571B777514933"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such other period as the Secretary of the Treasury may provide.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4BC2C2323F0442099C0EF2BF6F9D5DC1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Discharge of plan from liability</header><text>Rules similar to the rules of section 205(c)(6) shall apply for purposes of this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA9296FEF07D64D5A93463A028FB2D927"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections of part 2 of subtitle B of title I of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 205 the following new item:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9B16C5FB31924F11A5FB68407C5A2C08"> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry idref="H21DDC284444E4A25BBA05F9C11B70FD3" level="section">Sec. 205A. Additional spousal consent requirements.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H240848153E9F451CBF1BA922D3480936"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Right of action</header><text>Section 502(a) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1132">29 U.S.C. 1132</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="HF163F7E0F20C46B5A4A4468BFADA9E28"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of paragraph (10);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD120A119AB5A4398B952BA896D2660E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of paragraph (11) and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5EE0633A42384DAD8F843672ADC62694"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" act-name="" id="HBEBB5AF1EA3A447481BD7D80A65A8836"> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H59979514A69D480198CC54715E34339C"><enum>(12)</enum><text>by an individual for appropriate relief in the case of a violation of the individual's rights under section 205A.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H70B6EA67EEAA407287BB1DE1DE2E4C67"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Parallel amendment to section 205</header><text>Section 205(c)(2)(B) of the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1055">29 U.S.C. 1055(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, because due to exceptional circumstances requiring the participant to seek the spouse's consent would be inappropriate</quote> after <quote>located</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC1777FAE75534BBF8509B8D621764EA1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment to Internal Revenue Code of 1986</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/401">Section 401(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after paragraph (17) the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" act-name="" id="HCA474430259E439E81A176A77BC8E878"> <paragraph id="H03A6EFD2B51040FA89EA4557B3ADAEBF"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Additional spousal consent requirements</header> <subparagraph id="H6F41A4EA3EAE4B16B9E5E86EDB262676"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a defined contribution plan to which paragraph (11) does not apply, except as provided in subsections (c) and (d), a trust forming part of such plan shall not constitute a qualified trust under this section unless no distribution may be made under the plan unless the spousal consent requirements of subparagraph (E) are met.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBAB28807C5A9423ABCB2F7B7E95CC31D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Coordination with paragraph (11)</header><text>Nothing in this paragraph shall be construed to exempt a defined contribution plan from the requirements of subparagraph (B)(ii), (B)(iii), or (C) of paragraph (11) with respect to any participant.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5E30281C41014CC88255EEF55235865D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exceptions for certain distributions</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to—</text> 
<clause id="H6B72A324FDB1430FB4D129158DB474BB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any distribution that is—</text> <subclause id="H7CB5B593F079409CBAAF57958FC0B290"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a minimum required distribution described in section 4974(b), </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H61182407D8BA40DF81F49526CAD421FE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>permitted under section 411(a)(11) to be made without the consent of the participant, or</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBCBFF6DF71FD4AA0921CD790DCEBD6BD"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in an amount that is less than 25 percent of the account balance,</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HC91EC181183441A48F7CF514DA3EBCF4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any distribution in the form of a qualified joint and survivor annuity (as defined in section 417(b)), a qualified optional survivor annuity (as defined in section 417(g)), a qualified preretirement survivor annuity (as defined in section 417(c)), or a series of substantially equal periodic payments (not less frequently than annually) made for the joint lives (or life expectancies) of the participant and the participant's spouse, or</text></clause> <clause id="H4CB8661C81AA4A4C8AE4F3B66A4ECCB7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the case of a participant who does not elect a form of benefit described in clause (ii) under the plan or who is participating in a plan that does not provide such a form of benefit, any distribution of the participant's entire nonforfeitable accrued benefit if 50 percent of such accrued benefit is transferred to an individual retirement plan of the spouse of the participant.</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">A transfer described in clause (iii) to an individual retirement plan shall be treated in the same manner as a transfer under section 408(d)(6).</continuation-text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HAE89179313AA467D9610B1181B3D3D06"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Exceptions for certain rollover contributions</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to any distribution, involving a participant who has a spouse, that is an eligible rollover distribution (as defined in section 402(f)(2)(A)) made in the form of a direct trustee-to-trustee transfer within the meaning of paragraph (31)—</text> <clause id="H0F0C71B663DA4419A052DEA65A7FA24C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to a plan to which this paragraph or paragraph (11) applies; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="H74E4CD74F6B34C47B153826AF34E911C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to an individual retirement plan if—</text> <subclause id="HADDB342CD7A7470CB0B22889ECA276D6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the beneficiary of such plan is the spouse of the participant, or the spousal consent requirements of subparagraph (E) are met with respect to any designation of 1 or more other beneficiaries; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H0B4671CAC9D948738C6B58D736AC7B07"><enum>(II)</enum><text>under the terms of the individual retirement plan, the beneficiary of such plan (whether the spouse or other beneficiary designated under clause (i)) may not be changed unless—</text> <item id="HBA650A1572194734AF65137B0BE4F4FE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the spousal consent requirements of subparagraph (E) are met with respect to any such change, or</text></item> 
<item id="H392B851E52DB45A797FA4AB5B1A1B69B"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the spousal consent under subclause (I) to the designation of a beneficiary other than the spouse expressly permits such designation to be changed without the further consent of the spouse.</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7DEDCDFCED2B4422B87E9F401EEDED30"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Spousal consent requirements</header> <clause id="H14320488CCC143E5A15BDBD610F29526"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, except as provided in clause (ii), the spousal consent requirements of this subparagraph are met with respect to any distribution or any designation or change of beneficiary if—</text> 
<subclause id="H2544DC6CAC274F608C284531ACDED17D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the plan provides to each participant, within a reasonable period of time before such distribution or designation or change of beneficiary is made and consistent with such regulations as the Secretary may prescribe, a written explanation of the rights of the participant and the participant's spouse under this paragraph,</text></subclause> <subclause id="H5C9DF708B51D4A7E8FA31875560E1A27"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the spouse of the participant consents in writing to the distribution or designation or change of beneficiary,</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H5A1CCFFAA86345918D9213A146E45DCA"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in the case of a distribution, the written consent under subclause (II) is made during the consent period, and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9A8764C09EF94AC0B9E947DD7C44F7F8"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the written consent under subclause (ii)—</text> 
<item id="HAE421A05C0974BDF934E0858F4B165C9"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>acknowledges the effect of such distribution or designation or change of beneficiary, and</text></item> <item id="H0C06E24BFCEF47E2AA552CC7B830E730"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is witnessed by a plan representative or a notary public.</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H64CBAF72E8034676B4E0252A622C4507"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exceptions under section 417(a)(2)(B) to apply</header><text>The requirements of clause (i) (other than subclause (I) thereof) shall not apply with respect to any distribution or designation or change of beneficiary if a participant establishes to the satisfaction of the plan administrator that—</text> <subclause id="H0843A50BB8DD40EEA0441339FB2B0C9F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>there is no spouse,</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HACC3EBFCB06E4EABBE6A26CABCFD141F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the participant and the participant's spouse have not been married for at least 1 year as of the date of the distribution or designation or change of beneficiary, or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H97F77B01DA1347858A981C06BCAA2BC9"><enum>(III)</enum><text>such consent cannot be obtained because—</text> 
<item id="H9BC4198360FF464E9838B6CA116D0854"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the spouse cannot be located, or</text></item> <item id="H65921A6F880C490395C895EA66EF4141"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>of such other circumstances as the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Labor, may by regulations prescribe.</text></item></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="HE68DCB881A5D4064AB024B0BC3DFDA3D"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Consent limited to spouse and event</header><text>Any written consent by a spouse under clause (i), or the establishment by a participant that an exception under clause (ii) applies with respect to a spouse, shall be effective only with respect to that spouse and to the distribution or designation or change of beneficiary to which it relates.</text></clause> <clause id="HC8F55C283DA4453E82CA51446F99C898"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Consent period</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>consent period</term> means, with respect to any distribution—</text> 
<subclause id="HE246D538157541C2A89D8D20D0A53000"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the 90-day period immediately preceding the date of such distribution, or</text></subclause> <subclause id="H9CB5D6F444BC4CF7BE250005EA38DFB7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>such other period as the Secretary may provide.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="HDE0CCA40F15C49CCBAFECB6A9E79D5F3"><enum>4.</enum><header>Effective dates</header> 
<subsection id="H7A6C223AAB764D4FAF4E8F5CB6BA1A4C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Increasing spousal protection under defined contribution plans</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), the amendments made by section 3 shall apply to distributions and rollover contributions made in plan years beginning after the date that is 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H99AEC734368945738BFF8D54DA981C52"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provisions relating to plan amendments</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF29BC228FFEF43D99A425B903DB10B06"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If this paragraph applies to any plan or contract amendment, such plan or contract shall be treated as being operated in accordance with the terms of the plan during the period described in paragraph (2)(C).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1ECD2C37E920471F81ADE15719A1819A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amendments to which paragraph (1) applies</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0DC8941D88E745EAAB3AD7238B92EF66"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall apply to any amendment to any plan or annuity contract which is made—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H62723C2CFC7745409E5E6B3CDA9F1F57"><enum>(i)</enum><text>pursuant to the amendments made by section 3 or pursuant to any regulation issued under either such section; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H77F33D8E14BE485BB2E5E07FEFEE67E4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>on or before the last day of the first plan year beginning on or after the date that is 3 years after the applicable day described in subsection (c)(1)(B).</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">In the case of a governmental plan (as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/414">section 414(d)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986), this subparagraph shall be applied by substituting <quote>5 years</quote> for <quote>3 years</quote> in clause (ii).</continuation-text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC58C3C4BC5274F4794B822A6EA9111C4"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to any amendment unless—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAE2E6EC4DE134BF486D0B164DC831F5B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the plan or contract is operated as if such plan or contract amendment were in effect for the period described in subparagraph (C); and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B630822097D4168A5DF8CA28A4BC187"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such plan or contract amendment applies retroactively for such period.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9AF8F8724A5D49C498E40B059DA40DC1"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Period described</header><text>The period described in this subparagraph is the period—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4BE20A1247324F238CB3DF6FCA8C263C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>beginning on the effective date specified by the plan; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B3F35BE3F904D61952C579D0784C926"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ending on the date described in subparagraph (A)(ii) (or, if earlier, the date the plan or contract amendment is adopted).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H90B2A34D666B4A34A60D75997E61E3D7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Access to independent consumer information and understanding</header> <subsection id="H209AA36F3315445289B7DED494A8851F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8229040C34094E85B0A873509C3D5E9E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>consumer</term> means any person who purchases or acquires any goods, products, services, or credit related to the retirement or later life economic security of the consumer; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB2DCCA28B95141E0BB9E70146FEBB638"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>financial product or service provider</term> means any person who engages in the business of providing any retirement financial product or service to any consumer.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HD70F77A3AD1E4AFF8B119981718FAFF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Required link to consumer awareness information</header><text>In any offer for the sale, exchange, or other transfer of a retirement financial product or service to a consumer carried out by a financial product or service provider, such provider shall provide, in a manner consistent with subsection (c), an easily accessible link to the website of the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection (referred to in this section as the <quote>CFPB</quote>) at which the consumer may access information, literature, guides, programs, tools, strategies, or any other resource produced by the CFPB or other Federal agency relating to retirement planning or later life economic security.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H47F2F336D46440328E4D0040276B9F3A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>In order to ensure that the requirement under subsection (b) is effectively carried out, the Financial Literacy and Education Commission shall determine and publish on its website the appropriate link to the CFPB’s website for access to the CFPB’s and other Federal agencies’ consumer education materials, the preferred format of such link, and any accompanying description of the CFPB and the consumer education materials associated with such link.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HAB6E919DDA5A42CCBC84A31DF8607C05"><enum>6.</enum><header>Grants to promote financial literacy for women</header> 
<subsection id="H33F7B3D03C3E4EB2AE16A74CE29C7093"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of grant awards</header><text>The Secretary of Labor, acting through the Director of the Women's Bureau, shall award grants on a competitive basis to eligible entities to enable such entities to improve the financial literacy of women who are working age or in retirement, to increase the likelihood of the women realizing a secure and stable retirement.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA0E3A0DBB303411D8C23F9E7D62C86FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition of eligible entity</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means a community-based organization with proven experience and expertise in serving working-age or retired women.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H561ABE54CDE34AA18D63D595C909FE94"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible entity that desires to receive a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary of Labor at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as such Secretary may require.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBA29138CB2FD47EBA117BD3B24E225CC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Minimum grant amount</header><text>The Secretary of Labor shall award grants under this section in amounts of not less than $250,000.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE209245307374113BDD3F23AF568D8A7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to develop and implement financial literacy education, and related activities including outreach, awareness building, and counseling to increase women's knowledge of retirement planning and consumer, economic, and personal financial concepts.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H381F559806384ACC901FCB12E9302E58"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $100,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HB6240E433EC24D7E8DD38CC8ACFEED21"><enum>7.</enum><header>Grants to assist low-income women and survivors of domestic violence in obtaining qualified domestic relations orders</header> 
<subsection id="H5BF4721B5D354BDAB31837D629717651"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of grant awards</header><text>The Secretary of Labor, acting through the Director of the Women’s Bureau and in conjunction with the Assistant Secretary of the Employee Benefits Security Administration, shall award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to enable such entities to assist low-income women and survivors of domestic violence in obtaining qualified domestic relations orders and ensuring that those women actually obtain the benefits to which they are entitled through those orders.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HCD3759EC9A324AF391FE1F1AFD69192A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition of eligible entity</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible entity</term> means a community-based organization with proven experience and expertise in serving women and the financial and retirement needs of women.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2D28B1A9977F44F684D76DB5B18BC17D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible entity that desires to receive a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary of Labor at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary of Labor may require.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H592F85146130480787762915BAC45401"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Minimum grant amount</header><text>The Secretary of Labor shall award grants under this section in amounts of not less than $250,000.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5BAFCA84D4AD4C289B1D90D553FF927D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>An eligible entity that receives a grant under this section shall use the grant funds to develop programs to offer help to low-income women or survivors of domestic violence who need assistance in preparing, obtaining, and effectuating a qualified domestic relations order.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H590441828BAB4DC186B314578CDCD160"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $100,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 and each succeeding fiscal year.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

