<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0CD09192D3FA4E9ABCF384BD9857BAE0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6130 IH: University Centers for Growth, Development, Prosperity (GDP) Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6130</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 to establish university centers to encourage certain economic development, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H16913EC3348740E797115C665A80C658" style="OLC"><section id="H464D48F3907C4975B654112D3E1E3C3F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>University Centers for Growth, Development, Prosperity (GDP) Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H8AAF0CB5653541C49F64351103F4227F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Economic development agency university centers</header><subsection id="H6CC83332445841D58EF9EA116CE015C8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title II of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3141">42 U.S.C. 3141 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H6E0851DD8AC24F2D9A2FE25D44F33FE2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H2D212D5EFCC04495BE064F24CDE5B80C"><enum>219.</enum><header>University centers</header><subsection id="H9A6B7FADC5384C959DF2B385FF043572"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make awards to institutions of higher learning for such institutions to serve as university centers. </text></subsection><subsection id="H4F1ACF4F5FD54D489ECD030C23F5E862"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Geographic coverage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall ensure that one university center is established in each State to provide services in such State.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF6C08FFF04284BCD99F606CA48EB5D82"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prioritization of historically Black colleges and universities, Tribal colleges and universities, Hispanic-Serving institutions, and minority-Serving institutions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing university centers under this section, the Secretary shall prioritize institutions of higher education that are eligible to receive funds under section 371(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1067q">20 U.S.C. 1067q(a)</external-xref>). </text></subsection><subsection id="HCD1CE8A91C2F41CAB8344B664897A72A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The university centers established under this section, to the extent practicable, shall—</text><paragraph id="H33DEB47F26AB4EF0BFA55688603D3432"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collaborate with other university centers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H72BE21403DDF47CC84972472C6327B5A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collaborate with economic development districts, trade adjustment assistance centers, Hollings Manufacturing Extension Partnership Centers of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, Business Centers and Rural Business Centers of the Minority Business Development Agency, and other relevant Federal economic development technical assistance and service providers to provide expertise, applied research, and technical assistance to develop, implement, and support regional strategies that assist in job creation, high-skilled regional talent pools, and business expansion in a region’s innovation cluster;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AC363BD1E6E4A5D95C9D5401A1657E1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide technical assistance, business development services, and technology transfer services to businesses in the service area of the university center;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4671138A577F4CAC9ADB5C8D83A25B09"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish partnerships with one or more commercialization intermediaries that are public or nonprofit technology transfer organizations eligible to receive a grant under section 602(d)(1)(B) of the American Innovation and Competitiveness Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1862s-9">42 U.S.C. 1862s–9(d)(1)(B)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1CEBF1FB1D09463B9FA4DCF7977FBE2A"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide to communities and regions assistance relating to data collection and analysis and other research relating to economic conditions and vulnerabilities that can inform economic development and adjustment strategies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7663A45A89984FA980F44C89308FACAE"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may provide to each university center under this section for each fiscal year an amount that is not less than $500,000 and not more than $1,000,000.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H15E7140CA1234030B970AD969AEED9C4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 3(12) of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3122">42 U.S.C. 3122(12)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>a university center established under section 219 or</quote> after <quote>means</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H8C6BDB57B4A04CD680A74907FE74506F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents in section 1(b) of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3121">42 U.S.C. 3121</external-xref> note) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 218 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H44E6109F103B41DCA5AF1C9AE17EFF61" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 219. University centers.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

