<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2EA2DF907D7A40DC81CB1DCB3B1C5A5F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3383 IH: Employee Equity Investment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-16</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3383</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230516">May 16, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001213">Mr. Moore of Utah</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 to establish an employee equity investment facility, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H599C4790C7024621A7517D300ACCBF41" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H3DDCE894096A4D0F8C1178E418B3FB37"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Employee Equity Investment Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HDCBA04CC7B4A4ABC9C4B98CB537C13F2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Employee equity investment facility</header><subsection id="HB5E679C042F547E4B54362FE7725DF53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 103 of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/662">15 U.S.C. 662</external-xref>) is amended— </text><paragraph id="H25538B5D7CEE4E9BBEFC05A0CFC12E80"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (19), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H269B06D428E24932B1B46A2025866E79"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (20), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF83B8ADE9CC422EB002436B0BD274FF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H42956AE78A654203B8BFC245B764B87D"><paragraph commented="no" id="HCEB391FBBEE0479285BD6BD39BAA853B"><enum>(21)</enum><text>the term <term>covered investment</term> means, with respect to an investment in a covered small business concern—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE4F936781AAB4B359187A4D3E0DF0EBC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the provision of capital to finance the sale of an ownership interest of a covered small business concern, including a covered small business concern created as a result of a corporate divestiture, to an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative if such sale results in—</text><clause id="H1F42FC394AD94E6BACDC557F32257727"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative, respectively, holding a majority interest of the outstanding stock of the covered small business concern; and</text></clause><clause id="HE34CDA4338194B01B8D7708BDABF6A1B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to such a sale to an employee stock ownership plan, the appointment of an independent trustee for the transaction; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D9F03FBA885410BA93294E202A2BEF0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the provision of capital to finance a covered small business concern if—</text><clause id="HD1C72AE6FC074DB3A10C45AB7ECD1B4F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative holds a majority interest of the outstanding stock of the covered small business concern, prior to and immediately following the provision of capital; and</text></clause><clause id="H134B66441EFC40219939B88020EFD6DA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the provision of capital does not reduce the percentage of stock of the covered small business concern held by the employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative (as applicable), excluding any synthetic equity; </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A7ED71A2B8E41429C2971051852F51C"><enum>(22)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>covered small business concern</term>—</text><subparagraph id="HF0425F99B3FC478E8F71AEAF20507B14"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a small business concern; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H055F6E5A620E4BCB9F4E70B6D41E3E96"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to an employee equity investment company that is not a Protege EEIC, includes an entity that is not more than 300 percent larger than the size standards established for categorizing a business concern as a small business concern under section 3(a) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632(a)</external-xref>); </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CB03CEADF394B38B198AA78B755538C"><enum>(23)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>eligible worker-owned cooperative</term> has the meaning given that term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1042">section 1042(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF5AF71FB16AA4ABFAB50150A059DFF2C"><enum>(24)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>employee equity investment company</term> means a small business investment company—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE86CC4FEB482456584990CF7F71E9516"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that identifies at the time of application for licensure under section 301 an intent to be licensed as an employee equity investment company; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H57D9B9B3CFB64AE6BFC99916365E3D1D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which—</text><clause id="H4253813B809C40E1AFD83B5E99C53847"><enum>(i)</enum><text>not less than 75 percent of the total capital managed by the investment firm shall be invested in covered investments;</text></clause><clause id="H1EA0831435F341FB96FCD34A70FA7BAF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not less than 50 percent of the total capital managed by the investment firm shall be invested in covered investments described in paragraph (21)(A);</text></clause><clause id="H54DD450985AC4F1FBEA24A6B1AE5646B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">covered investment returns are obtained from debt, synthetic equity, or a combination thereof, including returns obtained from cash interest, payment-in-kind interest, and stock warrants; and</text></clause><clause id="HF21B0A70908C43E8857C7BE09B698ABE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any investment that is not a covered investment is an investment in a small business concern; </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H946A6F789D9C44EBA38BE7ECDB45A9AF"><enum>(25)</enum><text>the term <term>employee stock ownership plan</term> has the meaning given that term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4975">section 4975(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C781FAD07344BC8B7B18A3A0D972B1B"><enum>(26)</enum><text>the term <term>independent trustee</term> means a trustee that— </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H60C4FE7D63E545DC96660107A0783BB8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is in the profession of serving as a fiduciary for employee stock ownership plans; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3ABEED06BF314890A9807F6487E1B352"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has never—</text><clause id="H5E64E99C69874249B58B7713C0420A45"><enum>(i)</enum><text>performed services for or on behalf of any party selling an ownership interest in the covered small business concern to the employee stock ownership plan involved in the transaction the trustee is considering; or</text></clause><clause id="H29125FBBAD264DFDA53131402392898D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>been a director, officer, or employee of the covered small business concern;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H835801EA991147F797B9ED667C376231"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has not performed services for or on behalf of the covered small business concern at any time during the 5-year period ending on the date of execution of the transaction the trustee is considering, unless such services solely consisted of acting as a fiduciary of an employee benefit plan (including an employee stock ownership plan) under the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1001">29 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3249A05B1503464886D500448AE36DAD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>has not performed services related to the transaction the trustee is considering, for or on behalf of—</text><clause id="H28184CD1A86C42F08D4485A08C9A728B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the employee equity investment company that is preparing to or has already allocated capital to the covered small business; or</text></clause><clause id="H86C1721467CA417C96F61A08653CE178"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other entity that is structuring or financing the transaction for any party other than the employee stock ownership plan; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04B6FD59DF0A4EAD99007A15A2768C0A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>does not have a familial or corporate relationship (such as a parent-subsidiary relationship) to any person or entity described in subparagraph (B), (C), or (D); </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0F9222D302924A13B00C7EE3A3202C7E"><enum>(27)</enum><text>the term <term>independent financial advisor</term> means a financial or valuation advisor that— </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H26664413F4FB46519869A22AA7F151D6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is in the profession of serving as a financial or valuation advisor for transactions involving employee stock ownership plans;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49C0C5B5196E4222AC66CEEB2A4C2FB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has never—</text><clause id="H0E52F5B0412542EB99AF033D56C68B26"><enum>(i)</enum><text>performed services, including a preliminary valuation, for or on behalf of—</text><subclause id="H3400EEB0CFF246F2BCDA1B06D3660A2B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any party selling an ownership interest in the covered small business concern to the employee stock ownership plan involved in the transaction the advisor is evaluating; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HD004EFC7619D4CF4AC094DF36ACDB33A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the covered small business concern, unless the services were provided solely to an existing employee stock ownership plan sponsored by the covered small business concern; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HBA4D894C86D84D53AD7DBE8BAC8254E8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>been a director, officer, or employee of the covered small business concern;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA91709870BC741A6836EB0391C3F9D77"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has not performed services related to the transaction the advisor is evaluating, including a preliminary valuation, for or on behalf of—</text><clause id="H3D244532FB064F69B66F11028219BF95"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the employee equity investment company that is preparing to or has already allocated capital to the covered small business; or</text></clause><clause id="H7C185D81410B46BD8DFEC1CCA5BE4F03"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other entity that is structuring or financing the transaction for any party other than the employee stock ownership plan; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB7FB58A36F64DFF8A4AF2248581FD67"><enum>(D)</enum><text>does not have a familial or corporate relationship (such as a parent-subsidiary relationship) to any of person or entity described in subparagraph (B) or (C); </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F366EDE16E5415D95C04C4B76880650"><enum>(28)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>non-EEIC company</term> means a small business investment company that— </text><subparagraph id="H480F45C9D0564F50BA74C92EB6D3E4D1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is licensed under section 301; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA414325960B4A87A8B8C909CBFCBC18"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is selected to receive leverage from the facility established under section 321; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B3461BF04244FADA838C1279EA310BF"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is not an employee equity investment company; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H18C261DF57394A7BA3675A41E0C7B883"><enum>(29)</enum><text>the term <term>outstanding stock</term> means shares of stock, including synthetic equity; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB12CFF9AA8F4777843E048A7EF98450"><enum>(30)</enum><text>the term <term>Protege EEIC</term> means an entity licensed under section 301 as an employee equity investment company and selected in accordance with section 322(c)—</text><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAEFFB49C42634E31A4ED3171E9C03774"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for which the managers of the firm have a documented record of successful business experience; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83394F4B3FC749ECA31EA10CBA727A52"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that has an investment track record that does not meet the requirements to be licensed under section 301; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5AAE3782C184A24BEDA3622319D5A84"><enum>(31)</enum><text>the term <term>synthetic equity</term> has the meaning given that term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/409">section 409(p)(6)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4AE324B6CF1F45878E6ABFCB122D261E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Employee equity investment facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part A of title III of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5AAD41E98700476F9F103FF1EBE9B71A"><section id="H37309929D8A7477389AC6719576C2E6A"><enum>321.</enum><header>Employee equity investment facility</header><subsection id="HF53507723FC04F5F962A5FAF8C11A061"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>facility</term> means the facility established under subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H66C66487266F4887B69C15CB15042D57"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, acting through the Associate Administrator of the Office of Investment and Innovation of the Administration, shall establish and carry out a facility to provide leverage to licensed employee equity investment companies and non-EEIC companies for the purpose of encouraging covered investments.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HFD656C17701244FE8DFF061565F6A400"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H7F9DC610A47A4773A9366FE6F6706132"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An investment firm desiring to participate in the facility shall submit to the Administrator an application— </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCB95294ED95F401885F869D64E7C1820"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to be licensed to participate in the facility as an employee equity investment company (including as a Protege EEIC); or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1E306139EDC4DC8B4AFDCD0D8D44FF9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to be selected to participate as a non-EEIC company.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF5BE955381EA4FE296FC05788B3D35C7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rolling basis</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall accept applications under paragraph (1) on a rolling basis.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H39C58C42B345468BB1610128EC119BE0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Electronic submissions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall allow an applicant under this section to electronically submit any document required by this section and to provide an electronic signature for any signature that is required on such a document.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H303A2AD3603D499A95D67460011C2B9D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Application process</header><text>An investment firm shall identify an intent to be licensed as an employee equity investment company at the time the investment firm applies to be licensed as a small business investment company under section 301. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HCCB6A228A2074D469B845C3804EF001D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Provisional approval</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may provide provisional approval for a license to participate in the facility as an employee equity investment company for a period not to exceed 1 year to an investment firm submitting an application under subsection (c)—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HA84A35D49E954B0D8B4EC4AE1771B634"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that does not meet the minimum private capital requirements under section 302 necessary for licensing under section 301 at the time of application;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HC7970B6462674349BE7E10C458B135B6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that states an intent to more effectively raise capital commitments in private markets with a license; and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H07FCB8C226D446458A9DFF52CAE2D033"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that states an intent to more precisely request the desired amount of leverage contingent on securing capital from private market investors.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC6897551F95349E184B105403250354D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Combined leverage</header><text>The Administrator may not provide leverage to employee equity investment companies and non-EEIC companies under the facility in a total amount that is more than $5,000,000,000 for a fiscal year. Not more than 20 percent of such total amount may be provided to non-EEIC companies.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H4898693C0E0347F794A6067BEFBC6706"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Transaction requirements</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4A69A73AF25047C9AA6E4914F60E0B61"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a covered investment described in section 103(21)(A) involving a sale to an employee stock ownership plan, an independent trustee for the employee stock ownership plan shall be appointed before the execution of the covered investment for a period of time that is sufficient for the independent trustee to fully evaluate the proposed transaction.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2AD851B414984DBABE6F77845B586A2F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fairness opinion</header><text>An independent trustee appointed under paragraph (1) shall obtain a fairness opinion on the proposed covered investment from an independent financial advisor, which shall evaluate whether the price, terms, and cost of financing of the proposed covered investment are financially fair to the employee stock ownership plan. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFBEDA24F5C2340EABF88F39147F40BFB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><paragraph id="H6D425B750C6243E68FF426E67D94CB0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Financing</header><subparagraph id="HE0B84844AA214042BC4A6C9486C9ECBD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An employee of a covered small business concern may not provide personal financing of any kind for a covered investment, including through a wage concession or rollover of a retirement plan.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5348FA0C5F7B4F6296352240C9109EBF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (A) shall not apply to— </text><clause id="H1CBB948792114E1C9CBEDC9C19815236"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">financing provided by an employee for the sale of an ownership interest held by the employee in a covered small business concern; or</text></clause><clause id="H8832872FE1034EC68645416F3C51D081"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>employee capital contributions or membership fees paid by members of an eligible worker-owned cooperative, if such amounts are reasonable and customary and not used for the purchase of the covered small business concern.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9E206D706834A7EA4376D7A0475E595"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Control</header><text>An employee equity investment company or non-EEIC company shall not exercise control over a covered small business concern in which the employee equity investment company or non-EEIC company, respectively, has made a covered investment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC0C231DF561A4130B670506AD08420D5"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Employee allocations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a covered investment described in section 103(21)(A) made by an employee equity investment company that involves an employee stock ownership plan, the employee stock ownership plan shall include a requirement that in the event of a sale to a third party of the covered small business concern in which the covered investment is made, the proceeds that the employee stock ownership plan receives from the sale shall be distributed as though all shares of stock held by the employee stock ownership plan prior to the sale were fully allocated.</text></subsection><subsection id="H89E0E1C2E05748D9A91EB6829D298CB5"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Recirculation of shares</header><paragraph id="H9485E1554F584CB8941A0D7DADE85FE5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Share count</header><text>With respect to a covered investment described in section 103(21)(A) made by an employee equity investment company that involves an employee stock ownership plan, the number of shares held by the employee stock ownership plan on the final date of each plan year shall not be less than the number of shares held by the employee stock ownership plan on the execution date of the covered investment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD11AFBF8F9224EE9AD1E0848C085D2CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The requirements under paragraph (1) shall apply only with respect to the period during which the employee equity investment company has an interest in the covered small business concern.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEADCE690A2C84B09B7ECAB80A408FD90"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The requirement under paragraph (1) may be waived by the independent trustee for the applicable employee stock ownership plan.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEE98BBD051E248429ABB421C857C3C6E"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Independent trustees</header><text>With respect to a covered investment described in section 103(21)(A) made by an employee equity investment company that involves an employee stock ownership plan, the employee stock ownership plan shall have an independent trustee during the period that the employee equity investment company has an interest in the covered small business concern.</text></subsection><subsection id="H992D78C5DE824A0D90887A543A3D78D7"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Smaller enterprises</header><paragraph id="H1E5F386A1A4144E4B90F6512A0540533"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), section 303(d) shall not apply to employee equity investment companies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BD4094A74434DC8941A2895440DCFE9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Protegee EEICs</header><text>Section 303(d) shall apply to a Protege EEIC.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7918817AB283490D9327574FD2D9B4E5"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Procedures related to a sale of a covered small business concern</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE59E577C205A4AE28A77B2C19EEC6BB8"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (2), an employee equity investment company shall require as a condition of making a covered investment described in section 103(21)(A) involving an employee stock ownership plan that— </text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H44B0AB051A644306AF0D9E29B2588940"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">before any stock sale or the execution of any corporate matter listed in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/409">section 409(e)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, the employee stock ownership plan shall—</text><clause id="HF95D67E11FA84ED5ACFB145AFC4C33AF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>appoint an independent trustee for the transaction; and</text></clause><clause id="H66EAC2E108BA407BAEAFA64899B67163"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>require that the independent trustee obtain a fairness opinion from an independent financial advisor, which shall evaluate whether the price, terms, and cost of financing of the proposed covered investment are financially fair to the employee stock ownership plan; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3C470F0441C4DF48B0ADE5DE27627F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the employee stock ownership plan requires that—</text><clause id="H0DAA5CEFEC89487887C72D26A89C94D2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in addition to the corporate matters listed in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/409">section 409(e)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, each participant or beneficiary in the employee stock ownership plan is entitled to direct the employee stock ownership plan as to the manner in which voting rights under securities of the employer which are allocated to the account of such participant or beneficiary are to be exercised with respect to the approval or disapproval of any stock sale;</text></clause><clause id="H34EFC7C42FF94B08951E1B6F7433942C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the requirements of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/409">section 409(e)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and clause (i) of this subparagraph shall be met using the procedures described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/409">section 409(e)(5)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986;</text></clause><clause id="H6525D212CE17452F8647A0FEE6B19D78"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>unless the parties agree otherwise, with respect to unallocated shares, the independent trustee shall be directed to vote or tender such unallocated shares in the same proportion as allocated shares for which the independent trustee has received voting or tender instructions from participants in the employee stock ownership plan; and</text></clause><clause id="H33BE5CE73DE0488B827809A8E37BCFF2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>with respect to allocated shares that the independent trustee does not receive voting or tender instructions from participants in the employee stock ownership plan, the independent trustee shall have voting discretion over such shares.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7EEC594F0A0449E385937922C92C3414"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Voting discretion</header><text>Nothing in paragraph (1)(B) shall limit the ability of an independent trustee to exercise voting discretion in accordance with the fiduciary obligations of the independent trustee under the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/1001">29 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4D0B4DDE77C428DAC54F68A34E7B9CD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The requirements under paragraph (1) shall apply only with respect to the period during which the employee equity investment company has an interest in the covered small business concern. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDC4D56CF774D4E1D9B33514B72DC6E41"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the reporting requirements in 310(b), each employee equity investment company (including each Protege EEIC licensed to operate as an employee equity investment company) and each non-EEIC company that has outstanding leverage received from the facility shall submit to the Administrator an annual report, which shall include, for the year covered by the report, the following information, disaggregated by covered investments made under subparagraph (A) and (B) of section 103(21):</text><paragraph id="H9AD0A99AF9B943A3AED12948EA207AB6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whether the covered investment was made with respect to an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AC9EBEFFCC74A11AFB01CE72B949981"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For an employee stock ownership plan—</text><subparagraph id="H24A5083996594BE6849018E09948E087"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the effective date of the plan;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD143B0F024944D6E80A5C0BAD0D46C66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of active plan participants;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8AFA5F2E6B44FB884243D7304B2675C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the number of employees of the covered small business concern for which the employee stock ownership plan is established; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CA9839E4D4941BF9889527EC430B8E5"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total value of employer securities, as determined by an independent appraiser hired by the independent trustee of the employee stock ownership plan;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBECBF9FB622456480AAC6A29961FF68"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the total plan assets;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8FFF64483A88450B9343E6A2E640368A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the total contributions during the plan year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H074BB770834B4022A3D9EDA7A1EFE720"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the total distributions during the plan year;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE72515DA7CD24CB090ACEB6CB111FE25"><enum>(H)</enum><text>the median account asset balance; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H246545EDAE92481098620AF87AB0E342"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demographic information of plan participants, disaggregated by race, gender, and State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H000FC945B3E040EA984846E451D9B7E8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>For an eligible worker-owned cooperative—</text><subparagraph id="H3C43CB1C28E14F9BB1E2CDD686B7C421"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of member-owners;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8487730676B84016A7EA9C864C77DFAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of employees of the covered small business concern for which the eligible worker-owned cooperative is established; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CFF97E8A0F74222A8542D0ED6B4D8C9"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total value of employer securities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F3792203A1C4A4FA1A2F3C972283205"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the aggregate assets of all membership accounts of the cooperative;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBEBAD29B476546C888A09C53AE22C976"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the median membership account balance; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7195CD0F63374B10A0A7749B853E80BE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>demographic information of membership base, disaggregated by race, gender, and State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1E2C978802A54EC9A3864D2D81290E5E"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Implementation milestones</header><paragraph id="HB81EEB7062904B18A7CED1413DC46081"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall begin accepting applications to be licensed to participate in the facility as an employee equity investment company (including as a Protege EEIC).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H467CB0B0C02D408F9E1190C038D4F72D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exclusion of leverage</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall begin excluding from the calculation of outstanding leverage, as described in section 303(b)(2)(F), covered investments described in clause (iii) of such section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H026969A5F99D493F97EDC72FF3D723B7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>License timeline</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator shall approve the first tranche of licenses to participate in the facility as an employee equity investment company (including as a Protege EEIC) with respect to applicants that satisfy the applicable eligibility criteria. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7ECAE006B6ED4BDB8513A187B0F941B8"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Sunset</header><paragraph id="H726192FCA40F460FA9480126FDC90602"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this subsection, the term <term>sunset date</term> means the first day of the twentieth calendar year that begins after the date on which the Administrator approves the first license to participate in the facility as an employee equity investment company (including as a Protege EEIC).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H347F6861A23D434B8D03E8B7D021F091"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Termination of authority</header><text>On and after the sunset date, the Administrator may not license an entity to participate in the facility as an employee equity investment company (including as a Protege EEIC) or select an entity to participate in the facility as a non-EEIC company.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE047AA6B6E6044328CE55126198033DB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Continued participation by existing entities</header><text>Nothing in paragraph (2) shall be construed to prohibit—</text><subparagraph id="HD7B7B6890699419A844EEA45ECDF0241"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an employee equity investment company from continuing to draw leverage on and after the sunset date that was committed to the entity through the facility before the sunset date; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H59228D51D31B41759C60498262449ACC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a non-EEIC company from continuing to receive an exclusion in the calculation of outstanding leverage by the Administrator, as described in section 303(b)(2)(F), for covered investments described in clause (iii) of such section made to a covered small business before the sunset date. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H216A16A1B9264AFFABBB8966EF5650ED"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The Administrator shall not consider paragraph (2) as a factor in the decision to license an entity to participate in the facility as an employee equity investment company (including as a Protege EEIC) or to select an entity to participate in the facility as a non-EEIC company before the sunset date.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H4B4F08E918614B3387A8D1FD0D5B02CF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Employee equity investment company procedures</header><text>Title III of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H584117E227D54FC78C114E2936594084"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 301(c) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681(c)</external-xref>), by striking paragraph (3) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B46E1CCBA624ADBBC2213676FA17A68"><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3B50116F0BD540318F31B893D26707B6"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Matters considered</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D7FA8153B4A40C2AD0113034316EE44"><enum>(A)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In reviewing and processing any application under this subsection, the Administrator—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC74628E907E348659D4A205075D61DB9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall determine whether—</text><subclause id="HF2E6DE44F6184AF3B4DFFA62039329AD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the applicant meets the requirements of subsections (a) and (c) of section 302; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H79AFCCB10F4B4F0ABEAD1E7B518ECAD1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the management of the applicant is qualified and has the knowledge, experience, and capability necessary to comply with this Act;</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3DC1584FF2EC461E9C401F563C0BE23D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall take into consideration—</text><subclause id="H0D0A8B5AE2BD4DF0AE723C43B7D998C1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the need for and availability of financing for small business concerns in the geographic area in which the applicant is to commence business;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB5127C1B5F0846E0808FB90B9FFB0DA2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the general business reputation of the owners and management of the applicant; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H8070B07547D741F6B0C38C9385C4D6EB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the probability of successful operations of the applicant, including adequate profitability and financial soundness; </text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H545F571C8F964B3C9E722BE16DBB5EB2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>shall not take into consideration any projected shortage or unavailability of leverage; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA4F620EF9EA41789DB09E0670C0AC14"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>shall give first priority to an applicant that is located in an underlicensed State with below median financing, as determined by the Administrator.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6235B350D6564F2ABBCBE19BEBE8AF8D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional matters considered for employee equity investment companies</header><clause id="H19F08FC826184013B9F78D4FB6625AFB"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Investment track record</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), an applicant for a license to operate as an employee equity investment company shall submit to the Administrator proof that the managers of the applicant have a track record of managing investments, including structured investments, realized or unrealized, in an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative.</text></clause><clause id="HBCD442ACC0F240BC96C03DBFBEC469BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Advisory requirement</header><text>An applicant that does not have an investment track record described in clause (i) or that is a Protege EEIC shall submit to the Administrator evidence that the applicant has retained or will retain a legal, accounting, or financial advisory firm with at least 5 years of experience in structuring employee stock ownership plans or eligible worker-owned cooperatives.</text></clause><clause id="H3A6D2689E47C4872B50BAD949C7BCFE6"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Administrator may not reject an applicant for a license to operate as an employee equity investment company solely because the applicant lacks a sufficient track record in realized investments if the applicant demonstrates an otherwise successful investment track record that includes unrealized covered investments.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H80639898614249CEAF75BDFAD74ADA1A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 303(b)(2) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/683">15 U.S.C. 683(b)(2)</external-xref>)— </text><subparagraph id="HE1CF6ECEF72848BBBC054AD5E4FC1E9A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), in the matter preceding clause (i), by striking <quote>The maximum</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided otherwise in this paragraph, the maximum</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79B5DA41F039419A8C073CA890BC0373"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following—</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0C6A7D056C3B4D28AA02D32042162D19"><subparagraph id="H447105F48F0C45819E29C4C6804D60F7"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Employee equity investment companies</header><clause id="H3713988B456240DB9006B41038FC97AD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (G), the maximum amount of outstanding leverage made available to any 1 employee equity investment company may not exceed the lesser of—</text><subclause id="HFAE3CB2DAE6143CB9B73B88158633365"><enum>(I)</enum><text>100 percent of the private capital of such company; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H91678F7D9AC7445A87ECDC4D7F5D4F2E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>$350,000,000.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HA01A7B4B75BC47E3BE4947A4E46756C7"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Multiple licenses under common control</header><text>The maximum amount of outstanding leverage made available to 2 or more employee equity investment companies that are commonly controlled (as determined by the Administrator) and not under capital impairment may not exceed $700,000,000.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9647449F45634EDE99ED2AC81670D5D6"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Non-EEIC company employee ownership investments</header><clause id="H5D8EB9EED19745228C6042667273633C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A non-EEIC company may access leverage from the facility established under section 321 in addition to any leverage such non-EEIC company is otherwise eligible to receive solely for the purpose described in clause (ii) and subject to the limitation under clause (iv).</text></clause><clause id="H1902177D16564AAF9441092B40A06536"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose described in this clause is for the purpose of making covered investments described in section 103(21)(B) (excluding synthetic equity). </text></clause><clause id="H0316767293BB41A0963E07A9F798A7F7"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Outstanding leverage</header><text>Subject to the limitation under clause (iv), in calculating the outstanding leverage of a non-EEIC company for purposes of subparagraphs (A)(ii) and (B), the Administrator shall exclude the amount of leverage outstanding to covered small business concerns for a covered investment described in section 103(21)(B) (excluding synthetic equity) made by such non-EEIC company.</text></clause><clause id="H09D2F1C3E2E048469B05F42AC9DB9B14"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The amount of leverage provided under clause (i) that is excluded under clause (iii) may not exceed $50,000,000.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9AB6BE3BF744849A5D4831EAE8FB8E8"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Protege EEICs</header><text>The maximum amount of outstanding leverage made available under the facility established under section 321 to any 1 Protege EEIC may not to exceed the lesser of—</text><clause id="HD497AF47129240CFAEE051C35FB1DCA3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>100 percent of the private capital of the Protege EEIC; or</text></clause><clause id="H91C29DBE83944D3D9E181FEACC9D0FAF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$100,000,000.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H663A4AEF14534D60A4A119C539BF0668" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 308(g) of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/687">15 U.S.C. 687(g)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA2B0625226B8471986A4EC85D34DF1B1"><paragraph id="H6EE288D33284472A9D7B34C07037DE05" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In its annual report for the year ending on December 31, 2023, and in each succeeding annual report made pursuant to section 10(a) of the Small Business Act, the Administration shall include full and detailed aggregate data regarding—</text><subparagraph id="H895D4ECE61EC427D82AF17C5642079A1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">employee stock ownership plans created by an employee equity investment company, including—</text><clause id="HF2F9B4808EDE4611BBDE1E1B34A018D1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total number of active plan participants;</text></clause><clause id="H905E6913348C4A32AE4D0BD412D714FE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total number of employees of the covered small business concerns with such employee stock ownership plans; </text></clause><clause id="H30BC9A1440DB47DEB4C591EAB635F9C1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the total value of employer securities, as determined by the independent appraisers hired by the independent trustee of each employee stock ownership plan;</text></clause><clause id="H26E213D98F524E8EA3DD6E27371A6A10"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the total plan assets;</text></clause><clause id="H6D196F49FA4A42E98DCA8EE4D4EE09B5"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total contributions during the plan year;</text></clause><clause id="H80A923B8E0CD4AF7B6BAF126B9682484"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total distributions during the plan year;</text></clause><clause id="H8CA802A2534B4EF5A6063D0B9C129DDA"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the median account asset balance; and</text></clause><clause id="H15DA637C591C4D5D90FAFD2E6B340AB5"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>demographic information of plan participants, disaggregated by race, gender, State;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D720C0D653B4F70A1D579AE24479D0F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">eligible worker-owned cooperatives created by employee equity investment companies, including—</text><clause id="H650C36829D7A412E9C0C7A62FB5F4EBD"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of member-owners;</text></clause><clause id="HE9C56A6F4E2C4970A58DA1878B6DB82C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total number of employees of the covered small business concern with such eligible worker-owned cooperatives; </text></clause><clause id="H54FF669CD59E4C9C8C5F7BACF55390B4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the total value of employer securities;</text></clause><clause id="HEB51247AEF9E401D9195DAE7E47564B8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the assets of all membership accounts;</text></clause><clause id="HFBD6913F8C3A425E8A0DF7A60AC840C8"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the median membership account balance; and</text></clause><clause id="HD8608E50513D405AA8DA1FE87FD9E289"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demographic information of membership base, disaggregated by race, gender, and State; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B457DE14AA24FA5A04D3B80017A29D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">non-EEIC companies that received leverage from the facility, including—</text><clause id="H860C298E805E42BC974FAA3065319226" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the total amount of such leverage excluded by the Administrator pursuant to section 321(e)(3)(C); </text></clause><clause id="H453F550F2A63468D8A7AABC0F8156690"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of employee stock ownership plans and eligible worker-owned cooperatives that received capital from a non-EEIC company during the year covered by the report; and</text></clause><clause id="HA58F8F333EBE4E4A80DE35B134E6A383"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the geographic location of each employee stock ownership plan and eligible worker-owned cooperative described in clause (ii).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HAC350FC525E1462F83697B7250213CAD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Protege EEIC program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title III of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/681">15 U.S.C. 681 et seq.</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF270845FA17D44878BE82ED2D4A3231C"><section id="H24F34B8B5781464782E44F33D517A0BF"><enum>322.</enum><header>Protege EEIC program</header><subsection id="H3AC9108535064F73B5B66CC11805B886"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall establish a program to be known as the <quote>Protege EEIC Program</quote> under which a manager with substantial experience in operating small business investment companies may enter into a written agreement approved by the Administrator to provide guidance and assistance to a Protege EEIC with respect to—</text><paragraph id="H1B106DA0360F4C5D86847C77168F8996"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">applying for a license for the Protege EEIC to operate as an employee equity investment company; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0969AE69CD5D4B86AA936AB762D0111F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">management of the employee equity investment company after licensure.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H59C7731D5B1C4A5D9BB66994957E8544"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After entering into a written agreement described in subsection (a), the Protege EEIC shall apply for a license under section 301.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0029120E8D9F4E0398A697F81FF98145"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may grant a license to a Protege EEIC to operate as an employee equity investment company under section 301 based on the investment track record of one or more of the managers that have entered into a written agreement described in subsection (a) with the applicant Protege EEIC. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC0CF4BC755524A2E8DFDC0F6BA7073B2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements for managers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a manager enters into a written agreement described under subsection (a)—</text><paragraph id="H2DFE7BFC31604670ACBA0109FD65D2E4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the manager may hold a minority financial interest in the employee equity investment company that is to be managed by the Protege EEIC; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA1CB9A29D6446BF8970BD230B10C6FA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the otherwise applicable maximum amount of outstanding leverage that may be made available to any one licensed company of the manager under section 303(b)(2)(A) shall be increased by $17,500,000; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADE02D52B3E64099AD15802C0751437D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the otherwise applicable maximum amount of outstanding leverage that may be made available to any two or more licensed companies that are commonly controlled by the manager under section 303(b)(2)(B) shall be increased by $35,000,000.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section commented="no" id="H5A2AF9BBDEDE421DA88D282B768CA073"><enum>4.</enum><header>Office of Employee Ownership</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part A of title III of the Small Business Investment Act of 1958 (15 U.S.C. 681 et. seq.), as amended by section 3, is further amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H86E6658502F6444299AC1EEED7714242"><section commented="no" id="HBB6D1F28BF08488F98B60BCE5705112A"><enum>323.</enum><header>Office of Employee Ownership</header><subsection commented="no" id="H91E6248CF02A4326B8502E0716E90996"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Administration an Office of Employee Ownership (in this section referred to as the <quote>Office</quote>) which shall be responsible for—</text><paragraph id="H1152C6AD2696441FBBA0189337AAA1BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing expertise in employee stock ownership plans and eligible worker-owned cooperatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03E54C65C1644D80A4060B88D6654872"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assisting small business concerns in processes relating to a sale of such concerns to an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H889FA96D79D94C0D8D7F20DA856FD624"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Office shall—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HDBD24F814210447D9D80D415A90525DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide outreach and educational materials to small business investment companies about the facility established under section 321;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FD3A8C631254575B3AC504122FA367E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maintain and publish a list of legal, accounting, or financial advisory firms with at least 5 years of experience in structuring employee stock ownership plans or eligible worker-owned cooperatives;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HC086236CC87644D7B0BB3DFD2BCE0343"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish a Small Business Employee Ownership and Cooperatives Promotion Program to offer technical assistance and training to employee-owned business concerns (as defined in section 21(c)(3)(U) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/648">15 U.S.C. 648(c)(3)(U)</external-xref>) on the transition to employee ownership; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0A13AE608D144FE4A7FE3688601171D3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>coordinate with small business development centers on implementing the requirements relating to employee-owned business concerns under section 21(c)(3) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/648">15 U.S.C. 648(c)(3)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B4FB7B7881A496D9B2EA6F79C156760"><enum>(5)</enum><text>coordinate with leaders in the field, as determined by the Administrator, to develop outreach and educational materials on employee ownership in multiple languages.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section commented="no" id="H84C14E016BE640E9B4FB89807CC28BC3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Modifying unconditional ownership and control requirements for certain employee-owned small business concerns</header><subsection id="H4521FD9BC0414669A1DF08E479E191A0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report on ownership and control through an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-Owned cooperative relating to set-Aside procurement</header><paragraph id="H51205C1BFFDE49AF830FA90CC3F92DE7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="HF7F66DAA390747ABB92D7A1DE5BEFA02"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Small Business Administration; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AF832D888A14D74A537EDC905ACDA43"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>eligible worker-owned cooperative</term> has the meaning given that term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1042">section 1042(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEAF180A1C19A429DAA02CDFC85374C51"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the term <term>employee stock ownership plan</term> has the meaning given that term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4975">section 4975(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DF2AE72F31A494A82A9A312A3FC13E4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><subparagraph id="H045EBC61D4C14F22ABF87634652CD6A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>employee stock ownership plans and eligible worker-owned cooperatives have unique ownership structures that create barriers to accessing set-aside procurement programs due to unconditional ownership and control requirements; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26484BC5E56B45CC9308165C797FF70C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the ownership structures of an employee stock ownership plan or an eligible worker-owned cooperative should not prevent an otherwise eligible entity from accessing set-aside procurement programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1654D8AB88094ECA83E6B34802333071"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Study and report</header><subparagraph id="HCD8FD95F40104E01914480E8BFECADD7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Administrator, in coordination with stakeholders, including women-owned small business third-party certifiers and relevant Federal agencies, shall study and recommend alternatives to unconditional ownership and control requirements for employee stock ownership plans and eligible worker-owned cooperatives that would enable access to set-aside procurement programs.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H757A89DFF81A4B6DBE3F8E6ED4137FCD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to Congress the recommendations developed under subparagraph (A) and a plan to implement the recommendations for all set-aside procurement programs, including identifying any applicable statutory changes necessary to implement such recommendations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H72EDB96C99E8485CB34A82994F166141"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the submission of the report required under subsection (a)(3)(B), the Administrator of the Small Business Administration shall issue or revise any applicable rules to carry out the recommendations formed in the report.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3F178FEE7381400EBC03F2D6BE6681D7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grace period</header><paragraph id="H61338CF8B1F44BBFA8F97BEEA33B85DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Small business concerns owned and controlled by socially and economically disadvantaged individuals</header><text>Section 8(a) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/637">15 U.S.C. 637(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H38ADEB3247E64855802A4F020B3C832B"><paragraph id="H8245D15604E943919563E1F022661A82"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Concerns owned by employee stock ownership plans or eligible worker-owned cooperatives</header><subparagraph id="H0E05D022B424462DB59BE960D9B4B8F8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purposes of determining ownership and control of a concern under this subsection for award of a contract through a competition restricted to small business concerns owned and controlled by socially and economically disadvantaged individuals, any interest in such concern held by an employee stock ownership plan or an eligible worker-owned cooperative shall be treated in the same manner as an interest held by the socially and economically disadvantaged individuals upon whom eligibility is based if—</text><clause id="H8EBBBABCEC7B4BC5A3B47521D96B09B5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such concern was a socially and economically disadvantaged small business concern prior to the sale to an employee stock ownership plan or an eligible worker-owned cooperative; and</text></clause><clause id="HA25B6B66DE8F45D4AC6F1C8E0A841C15"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the chief corporate officer and a majority of the board of directors of such concern are socially and economically disadvantaged individuals.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB49872E63E24403903C49BFF56ACE06"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The requirements of subparagraph (A) shall apply for the 2-year period beginning on the date on which the majority of the stock of such concern was acquired by an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H779066457F614E96B39ACACCA653D98A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Small business concerns owned and controlled by women</header><text>Section 8(m) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/637">15 U.S.C. 637(m)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8733D32989FD4E5585E98AD234163DAE"><paragraph id="H78B952EA5F124D06803A5A3C6DFC90B5"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Concerns owned by employee stock ownership plans or eligible worker-owned cooperatives</header><subparagraph id="H7F986B92889A4517A26AE2EB0E96B8CD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, for the purposes of determining ownership and control of a concern under this subsection for award of a contract through a competition restricted to small business concerns owned and controlled by women, any interest in such concern held by an employee stock ownership plan or an eligible worker-owned cooperative, shall be treated in the same manner as an interest held by the women upon whom eligibility is based if—</text><clause id="H46031018FDA4455689072E8972CD9D40"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such concern was a small business concern owned and controlled by women prior to the sale to an employee stock ownership plan or an eligible worker-owned cooperative; and</text></clause><clause id="H23825E7C426242368F114C1177BD6DED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the chief corporate officer and a majority of the board of directors of such concern are women.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE95EC32040464C18964E520F8F5BED4B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The requirements of subparagraph (A) shall apply for the 2-year period beginning on the date on which the majority of the stock of such concern was acquired by an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H08BBAC61F08C46E788D3018CC87BAB58"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Small business concerns owned and controlled by service-Disabled veterans</header><text>Section 36 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/657f">15 U.S.C. 657f</external-xref>) by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDC697D2E4824795BCC69924490F8F86"><subsection id="H48C86432E09D4EE3AE859277338DC05B"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Concerns owned by employee stock ownership plans or eligible worker-Owned cooperatives</header><paragraph id="H06B5C65631A448488904F29B03496D55"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, for the purposes of determining ownership and control of a concern under this section for award of a contract through a competition restricted to small business concerns owned and controlled by service-disabled veterans, any interest in such concern held by an employee stock ownership plan or an eligible worker-owned cooperative, shall be treated in the same manner as an interest held by the service-disabled veterans upon whom eligibility is based if—</text><subparagraph id="H4000E7BA68644D278DC00CA84FD93D73"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such concern was a small business concern owned and controlled by service-disabled veterans prior to the sale to an employee stock ownership plan or an eligible worker-owned cooperative; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4FBF2A7EAB304182AB19E97901226F81"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the chief corporate officer and a majority of the board of directors of such concern are service-disabled veterans.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C771EA312F54420A3E65D63CD75192B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The requirements of paragraph (1) shall apply for the 2-year period beginning on the date on which the majority of the stock of such concern was acquired by an employee stock ownership plan or eligible worker-owned cooperative.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HB5136DBF85424A33B45B18D53A4CED37"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 3 of the Small Business Act is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7F2CE681B530415CA7FCF8808A593F14"><subsection id="H6BB6916BB17346C7B8108FDBFED77DCF"><enum>(gg)</enum><header>Employee stock ownership plan</header><text>In this Act, the term <term>employee stock ownership plan</term> has the meaning given that term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4975">section 4975(e)(7)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/4975">26 U.S.C. 4975(e)(7)</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H8F23DB05F3CA4EAA859558627340511E"><enum>(hh)</enum><header>Eligible worker-Owned cooperative</header><text>In this Act, the term <term>eligible worker-owned cooperative</term> has the meaning given that term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1042">section 1042(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

