<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H559B19CCDDEE499099856307DDCF336A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4327 IH: Converting Our Waste Sustainably (COWS) Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4327</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230623">June 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Agriculture to establish the alternative manure management program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3E68C914E1A54F588AB24FA621E33132" style="OLC"><section id="H9F3A470597254018B6A42503043A3D86" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Converting Our Waste Sustainably (COWS) Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA65CF52B9218490F96551F8B5B4C091B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Alternative Manure Management Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Chapter 5 of subtitle D of title XII of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3839bb">16 U.S.C. 3839bb et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8D4C6A92C3EC487385E37615D47C202E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HB9702913C132481296A9133192F8E52F" commented="no"><enum>1240S.</enum><header>Alternative Manure Management Program</header><subsection id="H2816C866E6CC4243A6EA71358B0A98C9" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HAE3AAE44FA6A48F4B934DCE0A72EF285"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Alternative manure management program</header><text>The term <term>alternative manure management program</term> means the program established under subsection (b). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E232EC125D94B3ABA13A4CAE3C76121" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered management measure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered management measure</term> means a dairy or livestock operation method that is used by an eligible producer to reduce baseline methane emissions and, where applicable, improve carbon sequestration on the operation of such eligible producer, including the measures described in subparagraphs (A) through (D) in subsection (f)(2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43C9F27014E0497988C157B50AF28666"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible producer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible producer</term> means a dairy or livestock producer—</text><subparagraph id="H250425C0A0C7469FAAAE90F4D5FF8EB4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who agrees to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by adopting at least 1 covered management measure as an alternative or complement to anaerobic systems that capture methane emissions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2A792534FFC43CE924A274D1E4CA949"><enum>(B)</enum><text>whose baseline manure management practices prior to enrollment in the alternative manure management program include the anaerobic decomposition of volatile solids stored in a lagoon or other predominantly liquid anaerobic environment; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H535C232E491C464A998AF392D0645C30"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in the case of a dairy or livestock producer whose baseline manure management practices prior to enrollment in the alternative manure management program includes an anaerobic system that captures methane emissions, that can replace or complement such anaerobic system with a covered management measure.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H526A0592CB284D7CB77B11268EC6D2BA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Pasture-based management</header><text>The term <term>pasture-based management</term> means a dairy or livestock production system—</text><subparagraph id="H8190C167E7384EDE96630DA75898EDE4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that eliminates or reduces the quantity of manure stored in anaerobic conditions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8AD80595C2D44F71AA076298532D9C4C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in which the livestock spend all or a substantial portion of time grazing on fields in which some or all of the manure is deposited and left in the field to decompose aerobically.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA530A92AEE1440EBA987A1D41AD6C2E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Solid separation system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>solid separation system</term> means a system that is designed to separate liquid components of manure from mineral and organic solid components of such manure.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08A13EA6BB544915B8B0D09583981D4A" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish an alternative manure management program to award contracts to eligible producers to support carbon sequestration and greenhouse gas emissions reductions by implementing covered management measures.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5837DC60FDEB435C93183F294ADC1C3F" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Submission of individual contract offers</header><text>To be eligible to participate in the alternative manure management program, an eligible producer shall submit to the Secretary a contract offer that details any covered management measure to be used on the operation of such eligible producer.</text></subsection><subsection id="H23073A4AC75449B591A3600D89BCA863" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cluster contract offers</header><text>The Secretary shall establish procedures under which—</text><paragraph id="HEE9158DD6BE2483494F768077F6C7936" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a group of producers may submit a joint contract offer for a shared composting facility; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD79B1D713E14027B939B3B4592A5F30" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary will allocate payments to each eligible producer associated with such joint contract.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H904CF08A86C245C1BC9EB79CFFC00F53" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Duties of Secretary</header><paragraph id="HC8A58BC45D7049BFA3FEBF33C2C8DA05" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Evaluation criteria</header><text>The Secretary shall develop criteria for evaluating and ranking contract offers to prioritize contract offers that will maximize—</text><subparagraph id="H19C61F6A35DF4164823EC25D2459F580" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>carbon sequestration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECE9DCB44633464A886A078C1329B0E5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>greenhouse gas emissions reductions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41888652ACE9490BA3FB18BFDED1B0ED" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the overall environmental and public health benefits.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C859BD65B4F466AA909B96D0C4B220E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding contracts under this section, the Secretary, using the criteria developed under paragraph (1), shall give priority to contract offers that address air quality, water quality, or other public health concerns associated with dairy and livestock operations located near low-income or underserved communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED50C898907E4189A901FC669BE8900E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grouping of contract offers</header><text>The Secretary may group and evaluate contract offers relative to other contract offers for similar farming operations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD12773863CA4C54BFFBFF6A851D4EB4" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Geographical diversity</header><text>In awarding contracts under this section, the Secretary shall ensure geographical diversity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H623339687C734CB0A5A9E79ED8FEFC9F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Contract provisions</header><paragraph id="H416415D75A064E88BBD4FC9DF93C4FB9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Term</header><text>A contract awarded under this section shall have a term that does not exceed 3 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68A2F26DC35F435F92B19F6EAA863A20" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered management measures</header><text>Each eligible producer requesting funding under the alternative manure management program shall implement at least one of the following: </text><subparagraph id="H363AFE04B0C847E38ABC51660536861B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>With respect to pasture-based management—</text><clause id="H435699884C1446C3A29084C45C0231B2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>adopting pasture-based management;</text></clause><clause id="H187758A2515145F7AA3FFA77715FEA87" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>converting a non-pasture dairy or livestock operation to pasture-based management;</text></clause><clause id="H48FB0DDB523D40848504F5323A126F12" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>increasing the amount of time livestock spend at pasture at an existing pasture operation; or</text></clause><clause id="H1D1CD8D07A88406FAC93DE48B76FB57E" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>improving pasture-based management, including transitioning to management-intensive rotational grazing, as defined in section 1240L(d).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C65FCEEBAFA4D0DAF7C5A155AACD9A3" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Adopting alternative manure treatment and storage practices, including—</text><clause id="H41C1A1BB98CC42C5BE6F4F3511EFDF1A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the installation of a compost-bedded pack barn that composts manure;</text></clause><clause id="H334B6E84894540F49D8A8CA0954DAD60" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the installation of a slatted floor pit storage manure collection that is cleaned out at least once a month; or</text></clause><clause id="H3F8034C8CB2544E0BE25641CDD168F97" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>other similar practices, as determined by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB348BB8F152944BEB8BD5405D7E0CBAB" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Adopting a solid separation system—</text><clause id="HA0302B7516E24A37BE631F6955892D6B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>or—</text><subclause id="H28945CC13AA7411282DB0D7CCFF88C7A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>installing a new solid separation system that has a significantly higher separation efficiency than any existing solid separation system; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HF7F26A8363714902901A74ACE204AE11"><enum>(II)</enum><text>developing or retrofitting a manure management system that primarily avoids wet handling infrastructure; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE4EDC9BEEDC540F7BFD9C64C45A97C4F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in conjunction with one or more of the following management measures:</text><subclause id="H37718ED28927419FA77A9B5529E3FE3F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Open solar drying or composting of manure onsite.</text></subclause><subclause id="HB80EA460B64E4423ADB03613E349490A" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Solar drying in an enclosed environment.</text></subclause><subclause id="HEA359EBC25CF42B5A5E2AF8D0E55488E" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Forced evaporation with natural-gas fueled dryers.</text></subclause><subclause id="HDFA66EBFE91F4373A7B1F09117EF2145" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Storage of manure in unconfined piles or stacks.</text></subclause><subclause id="HFD5ABE73830A4257BCDB9552ED30BA8F" commented="no"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Composting in an enclosed vessel, with forced aeration and continuous mixing.</text></subclause><subclause id="H25058AF3FC3147C4A57128063D5BE842" commented="no"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>Composting in piles with forced aeration without mixing.</text></subclause><subclause id="H9E6B311BCA5D4E6E98F16C045CA85E72" commented="no"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>Composting in intensive windrows with regular turning for mixing and aeration.</text></subclause><subclause id="H79B1A4D2E1D14F2FB706D08C1EFB1C3B" commented="no"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>Composting in passive windrows with infrequent turning for mixing and aeration.</text></subclause><subclause id="H8EB1630015E24858A37F39782A57511F"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>Vermiculture or Vermifiltration.</text></subclause><subclause id="H7B2876592DD54111BE5B550C5A03B7A3" commented="no"><enum>(X)</enum><text>Other similar management measures, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H640DD64EFE7649C599A08FF34A028FCE" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Adopting scrape technologies, including vacuum technologies, in conjunction with one of the management measures listed in subclauses (I) through (IX) of subparagraph (C)(ii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H447366C286D84403B5AD79BA719BECE9" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties of eligible producers under contract</header><text>To receive payments under the alternative manure management program, an eligible producer shall—</text><subparagraph id="H763319A98EBA4F91B0C183822CB9AB6B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>implement one or more covered management measures;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10B9A7BE08474BEF973CE34009CBB41E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>supply information as required by the Secretary to determine compliance with the requirements of the alternative manure management program; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H470190AC6867427991C539B8F298503F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>comply with such additional provisions as the Secretary determines are necessary to carry out the alternative manure management program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H47C78F776BCA4B3F88E0751444D3C4FF" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Payments to eligible producers</header><paragraph id="H794BCAD7BC9A4677A53E6D7404E9B2FF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the fiscal years 2024 through 2029, the Secretary shall provide payments to eligible producers that enter into contracts with the Secretary under the alternative manure management program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E6CFF151B6D4195AAB58EEDB77CD388" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Availability of payments</header><text>Payments provided to an eligible producer under this section may be used to implement one or more covered management measures.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H79EEEBBCC26449D6831534DEAAF262C3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Cost-sharing</header><subparagraph id="H52F0079B079745B48E079352C452E0F3" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>The Federal share of the costs associated with planning, design, materials, equipment, installation, labor, management, maintenance, and training related to implementing a covered management measure under the alternative manure management program shall not exceed 90 percent.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EA674742BE74DB4B92DCAB99A5E0F71" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Non-Federal share</header><text>The non-Federal share of the costs described in subparagraph (A) may include in-kind contributions from eligible producers that enter into a contract under the alternative manure management program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD7840AD40F24B599D1452DE63B0ECC0" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation on payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person or legal entity (including a joint venture and a general partnership) may not receive, directly or indirectly, payments under the alternative manure management program that exceed $825,000 during any 5-year period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D7C1E42840841778AE412DEB5713289" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Advanced payments</header><text>The Secretary shall provide at least 50 percent of the amount of total payments to an eligible producer in advance for all costs related to—</text><subparagraph id="H092D4B3DC6984ECDA973D12BAA5DD7E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>purchasing or contracting materials and equipment; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC3D2A64FED74570866251FECDB335B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any technical assistance provided by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44B76158635A465090D78B4FED7778F4" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Modification or termination of contracts</header><paragraph id="HE1AF65C961A543479EC6F484E4255575" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Voluntary modification or termination</header><text>The Secretary may modify or terminate a contract entered into with an eligible producer under the alternative manure management program if—</text><subparagraph id="H10A6007405E74C82B100CF913AD7B4E6" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such eligible producer agrees to such modification or termination; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7717C506E1648DCBD2249E94F614AAA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary determines that such modification or termination is in the public interest.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9853B89F8E3046C7A65AE523C1E70388" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Involuntary termination</header><text>The Secretary may terminate a contract under the alternative manure management program if the Secretary determines that an eligible producer violated such contract.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H44FC181AB2C34DD2B291EA8EA0975349" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Duties of the Secretary</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H6166A2EF0E044AA5A3D09D807216D135" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determine and publish factors for estimating the carbon sequestrations and greenhouse gas emissions reductions for each covered management measure, including the management measures listed in subclauses (I) through (IX) in subsection (f)(2)(C)(ii);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAB0413A76ADA430CB59B806364E5DAF3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assist an eligible producer in achieving the carbon sequestration, greenhouse gas emissions reduction, and other environmental and public health goals of the alternative manure management program by—</text><subparagraph id="H2BF1194FA2BB40058F51A4C23992FA7B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing payments for developing and implementing one or more covered management measures, as appropriate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDD669EFAC574F4AB346E110CF54CE6F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>providing such eligible producer with information, technical assistance, and training to aid in implementation of the covered management measures; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB74866FFC4B7415F9C6D69EF50C2787F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review the adequacy of existing conservation practice standards for supporting the covered management measures and, if necessary—</text><subparagraph id="H9B83491350074A139D408C9870CD7F76" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>revise existing conservation practice standards; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8C52D0D14BE45888D14A57C11669F50" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>develop new conservation practice standards.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDF899062D2C94883823B6ECBF757830C" commented="no"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>In providing technical assistance under the alternative manure management program, the Secretary shall apply the provisions in subsection (c) of section 1241 and section 1242, except that the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H7CACEF3C66B444FEB45A38D24922CD50" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">apportion not more than 15 percent of the total funding available for the alternative manure management program for the provision of technical assistance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A87E80685B44055931BE9320D2367D0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enter into cooperative agreements with third-party providers with relevant expertise in the covered management measures to ensure adequate technical services are available to alternative manure management program applicants.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA50BB415B1D948559BC4780EF2D3DE82" commented="no"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Funding</header><paragraph id="HCC90FB16D5EF4D4C8B5020A805739F2B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall use the funds, facilities, and authorities of the Commodity Credit Corporation to carry out the alternative manure management program (including the provision of technical assistance described in subsection (i)) using $1,500,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33137ED345AF4FD38C9006FC66C87069" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reservation of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall reserve a majority of the funds made available by paragraph (1) for —</text><subparagraph id="HE741D5A3219749C38C84AA3175C47A04" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>beginning farmers or ranchers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD2D21EED9D59425092C57B840AD060E2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>limited resource farmers and ranchers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H868C8CB780884C849321E9825CBB7F41" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>socially disadvantaged farmers and ranchers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H739434CBCC6A4369B6FED731F0183C5F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>farmers and ranchers that continue to transition towards enhanced methods of sequestering carbon dioxide, methane, or nitrous oxide emissions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H41E56AE90600475484CF0C01666931B4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Erodible land and wetland conservation and reserve program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1201(a) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3801">16 U.S.C. 3801(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HB7C0C536F6224F5889971C5B8ABB5518"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (3) through (27) as paragraphs (4) through (28), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCFE7764ED0145B193266F39E751505A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (2) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0F94C1B0CC9648678D5BD8462F3BF20A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H35F241F7330646EFA48938A7D23D004D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Composting practice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>composting practice</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H2EC0236024944DD79C215E170C1449AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an activity (including an activity that does not require the use of a composting facility) to produce compost from organic waste that is—</text><clause id="H03A1466C5EC7418DA51A3E229587400B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>generated on a farm; or</text></clause><clause id="H573701B9D03F4209875CF3F25E0076F5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>brought to a farm from the nearby community; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE5749FB4683475EADE72AE41D843D00"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the use and active management of compost on a farm to improve water retention and soil health, subject to the condition that such use shall be in compliance with applicable Federal, State, and local laws.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H0E90FB379FE241758CC46DFC9755B9A1" commented="no"><enum>4.</enum><header>Environmental Quality Incentives Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1240A(6)(A)(ii) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3839aa-1">16 U.S.C. 3839aa–1(6)(A)(ii)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>and composting practices</quote> before the semicolon.</text></section><section id="H7D226CF77DBD487C8F10E8047F392A16"><enum>5.</enum><header>Conservation stewardship program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1240I(2)(B)(i) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3839aa-21">16 U.S.C. 3839aa–21(2)(B)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>and composting practices</quote> after <quote>drainage management systems</quote>.</text></section><section id="H6A181BB7608441939FC04B07D264AECC"><enum>6.</enum><header>Delivery of technical assistance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1242(h) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3842">16 U.S.C. 3842(h)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H550EADC27E194AD4904CEC7B742019E4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HBE3BBD6EB3E746C884B942AD1ECBF4B5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Development of composting practice standard</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph id="H2986C39446824A2A81C7912AE05D2458"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct a review of the composting facilities practice standard and the soil carbon amendment practice standard to determine their adequacy in advancing alternative manure management and on-farm composting generation and utilization; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE47EB03272114B97A778C6F5F10D6469"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and implement a new conservation practice standard for the on-farm production of compost.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

