<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCFE691ABABB14A559D2CE91E94CA5382" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6048 IH: Confronting and Correcting Historical Injustices Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6048</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a Commission for Review and Correction of Historical Injustices, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H19C17BC12089496F895F3251E324339F" style="OLC"><section id="H3EF3AC29DB094342B48348BB3703158D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Confronting and Correcting Historical Injustices Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC3794AB70E87468792B741ABFA63991E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Commission for Review and Correction of Historical Injustices</header><subsection id="H47035E1AB8214FA8837BF2B8CE6637AC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established a commission to be known as the Commission for Review and Correction of Historical Injustices (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Commission</quote>). </text></subsection><subsection id="H8B220B37B38F415D94E1055D303DAEE6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties of Commission</header><text>The Commission shall—</text><paragraph id="H8138924EE7C240139EF7CB1FD4C213AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify and review each instance of historical injustice;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0725D5C4D5B244AA922485BF9AC2142C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify and review any instance in which a Federal agency has unjustly discriminated against an individual or group protected by the Civil Rights Act of 1964 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2000a">42 U.S.C. 2000a et seq.</external-xref>), by the Rehabilitation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/705">29 U.S.C. 705</external-xref>), and members of the uniformed services as defined by section 101 of title 10, United States Code, that led to a discriminatory charge, conviction, or dismissal of that individual or group;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA441180A91C14C3193F5A5A96B3332C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify and review any instance where an individual or group has been discriminated against and has not received compensation for the discriminatory act of the Federal agency; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B0E85E88A594C7C954D90B1CBF2ECC3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, establish a mechanism for the public to submit and be heard on each instance of discrimination by a Federal agency for consideration by the Commission; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0465A23AAB7C4D48B6D2C7EC7EFDED56"><enum>(5)</enum><text>not later than 180 days after a public submission described in paragraph (4) is submitted, the Commission shall review the submission or decline to consider the instance of discrimination.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0A9AC39166B34B4993CD538150D9EA5A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><paragraph id="HD45F42E625F643DB8FF573A0EB1AC880"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Number</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall be composed of 12 members appointed as follows:</text><subparagraph id="HC10C496971C24E2A93695DA6CAF9A14C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Four members shall be appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFB524B076F24A78ADE224B3605BB190"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Two members shall be appointed by the minority leader of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26BE4FB6E6584B78BA4FE062B2DF2DBA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Four members shall be appointed by the majority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0CA55B20AEDD4B13B873C102FE49E233"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Two members shall be appointed by the minority leader of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC229B9EE79C4BF59631C8EC5EB294E6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Members of the Commission shall be appointed to the Commission not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37B86079BA5C47ABB8226FD7152E6617"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Member qualifications</header><subparagraph id="H9FCFD3B337E14D61AF4AFE503827A382"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Members of the Commission appointed shall be civil rights leaders, historians, lawyers, or judges with expertise or academic experience in—</text><clause id="H0743A3FDFEB741C4947BCD4594FBB8B3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>civil rights;</text></clause><clause id="H38D007CE68D7420598000A13BDE83F33"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>social justice;</text></clause><clause id="H3844D1CD969F4125BBBBF3FA14B7C01E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>civil law;</text></clause><clause id="H36829F26BB9E4116834C808E2005E3BA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>criminal law;</text></clause><clause id="HC257685FE6434346BB678D17D000E167"><enum>(v)</enum><text>constitutional law; or</text></clause><clause id="HBCF7C91368AC48A5B04CBC1D75D0F905"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>history.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F252856E4E34743844B3564DC98092A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The Speaker of the House of Representatives, minority leader of the House of Representatives, majority leader of the Senate, and minority leader of the Senate may solicit and receive recommendations from civil rights groups and submit such recommendations to the Commission for review.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2D2A594FDBB44658A4837B727389819"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Terms</header><subparagraph id="H6889F8624416487CAEB26CF737773754"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each member appointed after the initial appointments described in subparagraph (B) shall be appointed for three years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BC46490948945E18E56C05F14DA7E0F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A vacancy in the Commission shall be filled in the manner in which the original appointment was made. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA55924971559461196DF9A3839908906"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Basic pay</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The rate of pay for members of the Commission shall be set by the Chairperson of the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F43EDA703254E44BC2E1CE29E804006"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>9 members of the Commission shall constitute a quorum and are required to conduct the duties of the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE676895724DC4D04A4274A0528DF5532"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text>One member shall be elected to serve as the chair of the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE72582B2667D4D57AC4ABC63598B9724"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act and quarterly thereafter, the Commission shall hold a meeting. Additional meetings may be called by a majority of the members.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H49CCD88AEB2D4852B02FA527BAEADA33"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Director; Staff of Commission</header><paragraph id="HDD9366D198F84553BB038BEB28B2904A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall have a Director who shall be appointed by a majority vote of the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB6E6C1466D64A9AA58F24BCF4661159"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Staff</header><text>Subject to rules prescribed by the Commission, the Commission shall appoint and fix the pay of at least 11 additional personnel as the Director considers appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D8D137164504FFFA8432FF491B5C645"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Civil service protection</header><text>The Director and staff shall qualify for civil service protection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H63247FCD3AA94778A893CB1CC6965C39"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may collaborate with historians, sociologists, researchers, graduate students, doctoral students, law students, community members, formerly incarcerated or exonerated individuals, or other individuals directly impacted by discrimination by any Federal agency to identify any appropriate instance to be reviewed by the Commission.</text></subsection><subsection id="H558CFE9F98C34BBFA69BED5E701B400A" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may investigate any instance brought to the attention of the Commission as described in subsection (e) and may issue a subpoena to any agency that a majority of the Commission determines is necessary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H886729E071FE41C4B9F7F655AF788B82"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and at least quarterly thereafter, the Commission shall submit to Congress and the appropriate congressional committees, a report including the following:</text><paragraph id="H5E68F6E27EBE4BBE9941659D2FEC2E02"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Information on any alternative to the pardon process, including exoneration or other forgiveness.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CB6F72BEF144D87B5ADA3E0E6490693"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Each instance reviewed during the quarter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6A68FD355AE4C86AA874381C2D9E6EE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Recommendations on legislative or executive action with respect to each instance reviewed by the Commission. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD0DCB65D5E64964A50C2583E688DC55"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Exception for termination of Commission</header><text>Section 14(a)(2) of the Federal Advisory Committee Act (5 U.S.C. App.) does not apply to the Commission.</text></subsection><subsection id="H548300CAFFA044EEA632028E6F6A1600"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the following:</text><paragraph id="H2F738F3F0E3546DF9A5CAF87553C185C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA87ADA46A67A4DF19D1CCAE05A81AC08"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

