<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8A08FC72AB6C44D6895A9187BAC38DB4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 4871 IH: Atrocity Prevention Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4871</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To modify and expand the annual report required under the Elie Wiesel Genocide and Atrocities Prevention Act of 2018 and require additional review of United States assistance provided to certain countries identified as being at risk of atrocities by such report, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6B4A9FB101B24CA19328B3DAB42E7180" style="OLC"><section id="H19F575A1E7884B6682557910DC930822" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Atrocity Prevention Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H4D8C0849A0CE48A8BB8A7C9FA02212BC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Extension and modification of annual report requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 5(a) of the Elie Wiesel Genocide and Atrocities Prevention Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2656">22 U.S.C. 2656</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3F28EF17865B4034A3A762DCECD5C69D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>for the following six years</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC00C019396584B5DB6DB9692FAB1303B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(E), by inserting <quote>(ranked as high-, medium-, or low-risk)</quote> after <quote>countries and regions at risk of atrocities</quote>.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HCEDCB6A3E550468C85C2496C1C948F47"><enum>3.</enum><header>Review of security assistance provided to countries</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Elie Wiesel Genocide and Atrocities Prevention Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2656">22 U.S.C. 2656</external-xref> note) is amended by inserting after section 5 the following:</text><quoted-block id="H8A7439C2CC4C49ECBFB84C8EBDD3B03B" style="OLC"><section id="HE6B47B668ECA45B893083A4E392DF70A"><enum>5A.</enum><header>Security assistance and cooperation review</header><subsection id="H9BCCADB304EF461996E0BAF3E85CED26"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review required</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the submission of each annual report required by section 5, the Secretary of State (acting through the Department of State officials listed in subsection (c)), in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report consisting of the results of a review of the risks related to the provision of security assistance and cooperation in countries identified in the most recent annual report (including in the classified annex to such report) pursuant to such section 5 as being at high- or medium-risk for atrocities. Such report shall also include, for each such country, the following:</text><paragraph id="HB1CEB50C793B4F72A446B0B1E9A0991F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>With respect to a country newly identified as being at such risk, an assessment of the risks associated with providing security assistance and cooperation to the governments of such countries, including the risks of whether security assistance and cooperation—</text><subparagraph id="H759AE812114D4ECBAFDA3D903904E42C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may be used for perpetrating atrocities; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49D9CAB5E2874622B8627EEF9C60FBB6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may exacerbate identified relevant risk factors for the commission of such atrocities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1F2BA014B2645BB941F3F7289B06887"><enum>(2)</enum><text>With respect to a country identified as being at high- or medium-risk for atrocities for which an assessment described in paragraph (1) has previously been submitted pursuant to this section, an assessment of whether such risk factors, the current or planned security assistance and cooperation provided by the United States, or other relevant context have changed in the intervening period since the prior submission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DBD7D80E35B46F4A41E5CB3E41828B0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A determination, including a justification, on whether current or planned United States security assistance and cooperation should be continued, terminated, paused, or otherwise delayed in light of the risks assessed pursuant to paragraph (1) or (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA8C01228C6C54739906D2EECFB2CD4D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of the review required by subsection (a)—</text><paragraph id="HDDE1D532D99741C89409D4F7398C220B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H11BD6BFA67E5465082AB49130A984F00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Armed Services, and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF78CF1BF18264BCA81BC691568D94EAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Armed Services, and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE404EADAA8DC45298755E7D78FF3FE6A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>security assistance and cooperation</term>—</text><subparagraph id="H709E3AA76AFF4995B7966539D06E3000"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means—</text><clause id="H39E5994FCBC943CA965AD765108731F5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>assistance meeting the definition of <quote>security assistance</quote> under section 502B of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2304">22 U.S.C. 2304(d)(2)</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H798D3D59489E48D0AE414D99B294FAF7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">programs and activities meeting the definition of <quote>security cooperation programs and activities of the Department of Defense</quote> under section 301 of title 10, United States Code; and</text></clause><clause id="H458CADEC8D3A452D96EB587A11F9547B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">activities authorized pursuant to—</text><subclause id="HF249808969D34ED182D75DC378D14506"><enum>(I)</enum><text>127(e) of title 10, United States Code; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H2D216E640650446DADB29BF99D982F8B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>section 1202 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/91">Public Law 115–91</external-xref>; 131 Stat. 1639); and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA5877F978864228BDDD29ECAB421F6F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes any use of amounts made available to the Department of Defense—</text><clause id="HA29A42CE189A4BCA8B1FC4053FE9BBE0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to increase the capacity or capability of a unit of a foreign security force, a member of such a unit, or an irregular force, group, or individual; or</text></clause><clause id="H80494366F35A4165B9AFED618B29F75D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to support foreign security forces, irregular forces, groups, or individuals to operate with United States forces in coalition, combined operations or other operations.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5D060EDD64E1483997715D89207F9DF3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Department of State officials</header><text>The Department of State officials listed in this subsection are the Assistant Secretary of the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor working jointly with the Assistant Secretary for Conflict and Stabilization Operations, and in consultation with the Assistant Secretary of the Bureau of Political-Military Affairs Bureau.</text></subsection><subsection id="H929B33A1B47F43BCA3BB8145E0FEE19D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form and may include a classified annex.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

