<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDBBBD52DDD8240EB8782DD8234BE65F3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1464 IH: Eradicate Crossing of Illegal Tunnels Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1464</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230308">March 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Immigration and Nationality Act to clarify that the Secretary of Homeland Security may waive certain environmental requirements to permit U.S. Customs and Border Protection and U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement to search for unlawful border crossing tunnels on private land to prevent the illegal entry of aliens into the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H13887A374EB444DE8A2B8FB4AC0549D6" style="OLC"><section id="H8FFA57EA86174B03AE40B944BCECCC23" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Eradicate Crossing of Illegal Tunnels Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>EXIT Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF6D684F34E95470F8C4BAA03B54B6634"><enum>2.</enum><header>Unlawful border crossing tunnel search and remediation</header><subsection id="H2BEC2185A13C40A1B63A4D7BB21E7DBA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Waiver authority of certain environmental requirements regarding tunnel actions on private land</header><text>Section 287 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1357">8 U.S.C. 1357</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD4AA04CEA4BE464F903D9362C95B6296" style="OLC"><subsection id="H2CE9EE7337464E99B451FA00F7E133E1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Waiver authority of certain environmental requirements regarding tunnel actions on private land</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall have the authority to waive all requirements relating to Federal, State, or local environmental permits and reviews such Secretary, in such Secretary’s sole discretion, determines necessary to search for and remediate unlawful border crossing tunnels pursuant to subsection (a)(3). Any such determination by the Secretary shall be effective upon being published in the Federal Register.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H2EA2D88C5B6345B383AFDF30AA6800FE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contract authority</header><paragraph commented="no" id="HA07DCD878A2F48598179B97779DB4E34"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To search for and remediate unlawful border crossing tunnels in accordance with section 287 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1357">8 U.S.C. 1357</external-xref>), the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection and the Director of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement are authorized to enter into indefinite delivery, indefinite quantity contracts.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H065DDDBE3D344CE8AD14DC96B9F4464B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>indefinite delivery, indefinite quantity contract</term> means a contract that is entered into by the head of a Federal agency with two or more sources pursuant to the same solicitation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H64CA1061B7E444259FC8698A3666CFC9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clarification regarding actions on private land</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (3) of section 287(a) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1357">8 U.S.C. 1357(a)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, including to search for and remediate unlawful border crossing tunnels,</quote> after <quote>patrolling the border</quote>.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

