<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1E4249A16E3A4190AE630F9B45DA2CA3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2996 IH: Safe Leave for Victims of Domestic Violence, Sexual Assault, and Stalking Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2996</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230428">April 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 to permit leave for an employee to meet their needs related to being a victim of dating violence, domestic violence, sexual assault, sex trafficking, or stalking, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2C4387AC97EB4B889FBB320847B4DD55" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H55DD1B15B35648979E78011A5E9B9006" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safe Leave for Victims of Domestic Violence, Sexual Assault, and Stalking Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HE1377DA0E5C14EC58BC1438CB45E80F2"><enum>2.</enum><header>Entitlement relating to being a victim of dating violence, domestic violence, sexual assault, sex trafficking, or stalking</header> <subsection id="HB1E88A6FA3C5422E86D470BE9829ED8E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Leave requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 102(a)(1) of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2612">29 U.S.C. 2612(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H697E3F899EE04884A1575A1F057F89EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (F) as subparagraph (G); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5D4C06C637804FEB9EB7A70A4919E41C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (E) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB94471CBDBDC43E6AC0410CB85DE1AD5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H17C013A958B5472188CBDBEB8D2772F8"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to meet the needs of the employee related to the employee, or a family member of the employee, being a victim of dating violence, domestic violence, sexual assault, sex trafficking, or stalking to—</text> <clause id="H21C342743DC34CE49D545C1FA04FBE37"><enum>(i)</enum><text>seek medical attention or treatment for physical or psychological injuries related to domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, stalking, or trafficking;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9D80EE9A9B034F7F8FC9B0F9AAC504CF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>seek mental health or counseling services for injuries and trauma related to domestic violence, dating violence, sexual assault, stalking, or trafficking; </text></clause> <clause id="H1E136AE3BAB746388A00AB4CE3D0A0CD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>seek services from a victim services organization, including, but not limited to, a domestic violence program, a sexual assault victim service provider, a stalking victim service provider; </text></clause> 
<clause id="H58C21979A6C5479492C439FAC8FB7357"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>seek civil or criminal legal services to prepare for and participate in legal proceedings related to domestic violence, sexual assault, dating violence stalking, or trafficking;</text></clause> <clause id="HF5EA1E69C60A470A9A9B1842AD300855"><enum>(v)</enum><text>secure safe housing, including searching for new housing, relocating, and installing additional safety measures; or</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBD8BCD4197A94225B980CD597E3E5312"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in a case in which a family member of the employee has been a victim of dating violence, domestic violence, sexual assault, sex trafficking, or stalking, to assist the family member in any of the activities described in clauses (i) through (v).</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7E4EACDFDC164B5C8D86152EA5418763"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Schedule</header> <paragraph id="H8161C3168CBF4B75818EACA436555D21"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 102(b)(1) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2612">29 U.S.C. 2612(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after the third sentence the following new sentence: <quote>Subject to paragraph (2), subsection (e)(2), and subsection (b)(5) of section 103, leave under subparagraph (F) of subsection (a)(1) may be taken intermittently or on a reduced leave schedule.</quote></text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCBC4750B8FC44D3EB8A5687D676587A1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 102 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2612">29 U.S.C. 2612</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H1F48983BF1E345AAAE6A4DB623FAF62D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(2), by striking <quote>or (D)</quote> after <quote>subparagraph (C)</quote> and inserting <quote>, (D), or (F)</quote>; and </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBD1285FEFC474AB3AF795BDECA785D2B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (e)(2), by striking <quote>or (D)</quote> after <quote>subparagraph (C)</quote> and inserting <quote>, (D), or (F)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCCCDFDB1E5DC45A7B3AE3B75CFAEDC27"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Substitution of paid leave</header><text>Section 102(d)(2) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2612">29 U.S.C. 2612(d)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7AD66D24087543A38AD8DF9C63BE1DEB" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="HC6F9DBE2445A4AAA9F1387913D4B406D"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Meet needs relating to being a victim of dating violence, domestic violence, sexual assault, sex trafficking, or stalking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible employee may elect, or an employer may require the employee, to substitute any of the accrued paid vacation leave, personal leave, or medical or sick leave of the employee for leave provided under subparagraph (F) of subsection (a)(1) for any part of the 12-week period of such leave under such subsection, except that nothing in this title shall require an employer to provide paid sick leave or paid medical leave in any situation in which such employer would not normally provide any such paid leave. </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H0151D56633FD424E8596DE07F37744CE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Section 103 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2613">29 U.S.C. 2613</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H57F59EC66DFC49FD8347DF7F56F542E0" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="HE273E0689B7E492E863B75242975494A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Certification relating to being a victim of dating violence, domestic violence, sexual assault, sex trafficking, or stalking</header> 
<paragraph id="HE266495565F94C95BA961EDC8D7C7B12"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Subject to paragraph (2), an employer may require that a request for leave under section 102(a)(1)(F) be supported by a certification issued at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may by regulation prescribe.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFEC61EF544F84F5A846EB944A7F73A45"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the case of an employee requesting leave under section 102(a)(1)(F) who has not yet received a certification as described under paragraph (1), such employer shall accept a sworn statement on a form prescribed by the Secretary that such employee has requested such certification.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H06516C9738F7446A88893E1E7896455B" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 101 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2611">29 U.S.C. 2611</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraphs: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4BD942CB26E547C282E9F3636845463D" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HEE1AD25F7AA8455D8F6A2E9D9AF0DCE6" commented="no"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Dating violence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>dating violence</quote> means violence committed by a person—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HAE45ABEDC02A4D899CFD8ED2BD47CF0E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who is or has been in a social relationship of a romantic or intimate nature with the employee; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6229EA50DBB444A6B46855C3630AAF1B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>where the existence of such a relationship shall be determined based on a consideration of the following factors:</text> 
<clause id="H2B34EA2D1F1746A9B8AA242BDBFE2798"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The length of the relationship.</text></clause> <clause id="H237DD639D39E43A5A1FE16638582AFD0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The type of relationship.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB3D70F6F0F774C20B1A736710C3F7BA4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The frequency of interaction between the persons involved in the relationship.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA4891465F4D249C798887B17B48F5192"><enum>(21)</enum><header>Domestic violence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>domestic violence</quote> includes felony or misdemeanor crimes committed by a current or former spouse or intimate partner of the employee under the family or domestic violence laws of the jurisdiction receiving grant funding and, in the case of victim services, includes the use or attempted use of physical abuse or sexual abuse, or a pattern of any other coercive behavior committed, enabled, or solicited to gain or maintain power and control over an employee, including verbal, psychological, economic, or technological abuse that may or may not constitute criminal behavior, by a person who—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCAD0583F25954663B1F7EDA966DF1FC3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a current or former spouse or intimate partner of the employee, or person similarly situated to a spouse of the employee;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE8AAF44CE01546779C3050B1AACA2F2C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is cohabitating, or has cohabitated, with the employee as a spouse or intimate partner;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H586EC2E471B144478EB525E9258B8072"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shares a child in common with the employee; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8BD78EB7676241DD98F8A80C14C852AB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>commits acts against a youth or employee who is protected from those acts under the family or domestic violence laws of the jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCEF2EA4CCCFF441CA647ED043C8084CB"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Family member</header><text>The term <quote>family member</quote> means a spouse, son, daughter, parent, or next of kin.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDB50CCA802194D0E8DE34E2C6D874DF5"><enum>(23)</enum><header>Sex trafficking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>sex trafficking</quote> means any conduct proscribed by section 1591 of title 18, whether or not the conduct occurs in interstate or foreign commerce or within the special maritime and territorial jurisdiction of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H142D6769BA6D4DC58C36E07A206AD20C"><enum>(24)</enum><header>Sexual assault</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>sexual assault</quote> means any nonconsensual sexual act proscribed by Federal, Tribal, or State law, including when the employee lacks capacity to consent.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBCC352528B8946FAA46108BDDA61F726"><enum>(25)</enum><header>Stalking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>stalking</quote> means engaging in a course of conduct directed at a specific person that would cause a reasonable person to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE8CB777BB8F34C65AF5C0E9FE3AE027C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>fear for his or her safety or the safety of others; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H32DC1B59A986455AA11A19A82F5C658A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>suffer substantial emotional distress.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC606E980688C41359C006EF8DB13A76C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Technical amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title I of the Family and Medical Leave Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/2611">29 U.S.C. 2611 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HA57F498A10564AC3AEC8D0EA993E5FC3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 102(c), by striking <quote>subsection (a)(1)(F)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (a)(1)(G)</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC49ACAE00A564DADAAE0745270FAF745"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 110—</text> <subparagraph id="HAAA160C4331C4827A7030F83438294B0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>section 102(a)(1)(F)</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>section 102(a)(1)(G)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA29B2F3596AD4401BBC16A97F70E4EDF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1)(A), by redesignating the second clause (ii) as clause (iii).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

