<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0F7B5D46FC7541B095F877D2CCCFCBB8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2370 IH: Access to AEDs Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2370</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230329">March 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000197">Ms. Pelosi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000602">Ms. Lee of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Health and Human Services to award grants to eligible entities to develop and implement a comprehensive program to promote student access to defibrillation in public elementary schools and secondary schools.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2F3012FC474B4501921FFE168471E625" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HC2C4B8AAFF9746889E39A42CEA82F844"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Access to AEDs Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H0C724144A82743799953A61FECDA3C0A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="HA445D5D51D8347DD8A21CB2AFA562439"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Heart disease is the leading cause of death in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D5C292DBB9F404CA9D905A6B258B55C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Sudden cardiac arrest (referred to in this section as <quote>SCA</quote>) is a life-threatening emergency that is caused by a malfunction in the heart’s electrical system or structure, which is caused by an abnormality from birth or one that develops over time.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA491210FC75B4079A1D5F6405AEA44AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Studies show that 1 in 300 youth has an undetected heart condition that puts them at risk.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4243A9764B543ADB311E0EED8259DB6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>SCA is the leading cause of death for student athletes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC5030B478964F39A43D5A1332D8E22B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Sports-related SCA account for 39 percent of SCAs among children 18 years old or younger.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B0AF803A6F741AB8A029DD9343F4D28"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 2018, there were nearly 394,000 sudden cardiac arrests that occurred in the United States, with 9 out of 10 being fatal. Only 1 in 10 victims survive a sudden cardiac arrest.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11450CDF3DB6422DB950785C5774EDFA"><enum>(7)</enum><text>An estimated 7,000 to 23,000 young people are stricken by SCA annually.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H206D497550BE487181369375A0E4E18B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The American Heart Association estimates that 5 in 10 victims of SCA could survive if bystanders gave CPR and used an AED immediately.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF23E63C3E54A4AE78BF9C5A4F597D575"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The chain of survival includes prompt notification of emergency services and early CPR, defibrillation, and advanced cardiac life support.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF86EEDB197FA49E793B9F23AF6E6F5E4"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Health education should include basic emergency lifesaving skills. Incorporating these lifesaving training programs into the health curriculum of public elementary and secondary schools will give children and youth these skills.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H5AA31419C1354F31ACA4E3FD55119936"><enum>3.</enum><header>Promoting student access to defibrillation</header><subsection id="HBC3309BDF47E4024959729E4C60643EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities to develop and implement a comprehensive program to promote student access to defibrillation in public elementary schools and secondary schools. </text></subsection><subsection id="HF72AA3D0B2934E2281981E3C09123406"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity receiving a grant under subsection (a) may use funds received through such grant to carry out any of the following activities:</text><paragraph id="H959E4AED3F2B4E679A7AE773731E05D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing and providing comprehensive materials to establish AED and CPR programs in public elementary schools and secondary schools.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H767746FF676B4DF6BCF510D884C5FEED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Providing support for CPR and AED training programs in such schools for students, staff, and related sports volunteers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD73870541804013BDC83A2A1A75A2AB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Providing support for developing a cardiac emergency response plan within such schools.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE85832E599E54E83AC812D0A0B7FE9AB"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Purchasing AEDs that have been approved under section 515 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360e">21 U.S.C. 360e</external-xref>), cleared under section 510(k) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360">21 U.S.C. 360(k)</external-xref>), or authorized under section 513(f)(2) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/360c">21 U.S.C. 360c(f)(2)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD73AF82A743B482F827FCA34056073FA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Purchasing necessary AED batteries and performing necessary AED maintenance (such as by replacing AED pads) in accordance with the labeling of the AED involved.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7E4CF97B5E54EF7807BF8EF542EEAE3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Replacing old and outdated AED and CPR equipment, machinery, and educational materials.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49A553D53BAD4681B7A8E46A06300C30"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Fostering new and existing community partnerships with and among local educational agencies, nonprofit organizations, public health organizations, emergency medical service providers, fire and police departments, and parent-teacher associations to promote the importance of defibrillation in such schools.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H114D5B9510C84BA588074ECE405E121D"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Aiding school athletic departments to screen student athletes for risk of sudden cardiac arrest, consistent with guidelines of the American Heart Association and the American College of Cardiology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27CBA93EEF094163BFE34251EEDF4313"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Further developing strategies to improve access to AEDs in such schools.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H955EDF3F0EEE4A829D6BCF50D9C2BC87"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Eligibility; application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible for a grant under subsection (a), an entity shall—</text><paragraph id="HEAC92F6B9F094A428628F1E137115446"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be a local educational agency (including a public charter school operating as a local educational agency under State law), in consultation with a qualified health care entity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FB6478AF244477ABAB10456746F6BC5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the Secretary an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may reasonably require.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA5BA9A69E2C148F78D058860DDFCA8A7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Clearinghouse</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish a clearinghouse database—</text><paragraph id="HCBE0F15164764502B18DE6C9A9298417"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to collect and make available information, including through voluntary reporting by local educational agencies, State educational agencies, and manufacturers, relating to student access to defibrillation in public elementary schools and secondary schools, including with respect to the costs of providing AEDs and CPR training; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C37C6F5A9BA4007AEA78C158FF6FFF8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to gather information in a central location to facilitate research regarding sudden cardiac arrest in the pediatric population.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA63C6374C9164D51A83839D0FA7767B3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H590929E07E2A4FC7B29D3EB5321C76E8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>By grantee</header><text>Not later than 4 years after receipt of a grant under this section, the recipient of the grant shall submit to the Secretary a report that describes the activities carried out with funds received through the grant.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19DCDBCAC0B24B40BA951B39A7E52AB4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>By Secretary</header><text>Not later than one year after receiving the reports required by paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce and the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives a consolidated evaluation of the activities carried out pursuant to grants under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7C4CEAEC57F94FDC9D270BD05D1CD5A8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text><paragraph id="HDB37FDC368A64F478B8C9869BE51C2E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>AED</quote> means an automated external defibrillator;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D63BD83AFDB4AC6B21B7CA4DD11B8C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>CPR</quote> means cardiopulmonary resuscitation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6511A37532734FCB94E3DA9786414ED9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the terms <quote>elementary school</quote>, <quote>local educational agency</quote>, and <quote>secondary school</quote> have the meanings given to such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4509C52F31F34B6580FC18C7B72F129A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>qualified health care entity</quote> means a health care entity that—</text><subparagraph id="H3460D30253324B379F4CC3D36F8D55AC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is—</text><clause id="HC07C9C1DA0534FBE8603E9C33FA0A778"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a public entity; or</text></clause><clause id="H390FB98161DA49548054940C05C2D152"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an organization that is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7EA4BE6A0944992A88FE5F366BD921B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>demonstrates an ability to develop, train, and implement a comprehensive program to promote student access to defibrillation in elementary and secondary schools; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A2192E59A394D718FBEAB20B7066385"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is qualified in providing technical assistance in AED and CPR training; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA96EFBF2B5E8429F842BE1D9A097AD89"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF36CA3129DBF4710BF8657472437601A"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $25,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

