<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF041BF6AEA614E4484BF5416F1250E50" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5381 IH: Reforestation, Nurseries, and Genetic Resources Support Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5381</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Agriculture to provide assistance in support of nurseries and seed orchards, to establish a grant program in support of nurseries and seed orchards, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H898256557E614687B301E6573D54D656" style="OLC"><section id="H0F93A69233D446938373F4917515403C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reforestation, Nurseries, and Genetic Resources Support Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>RNGR Support Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HAAC253845D064404A0DAB5DD2FF27DA5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Nursery and seed orchard support</header><subsection id="HA181CF89BF73437999D1589D61EA11A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Partnerships, collaboration, and other assistance in support of nurseries and seed orchards</header><text>The Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service, shall—</text><paragraph id="H1E155389F3634D958D3B820B60B07B1C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">partner with Federal and State agencies, Indian Tribes, and private nurseries to provide training, technical assistance, and research to nursery and tree establishment programs that support natural regeneration, reforestation, agroforestry, and afforestation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD114BFE3F83F44888F66FF7E83018C34"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promote information sharing to improve technical knowledge and practices and understand demands, climate change impacts, and other issues as necessary to address all facets of the reforestation pipeline;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB876C5D86B0749869F6F0317A4495C72"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide technical and financial assistance to international nursery and tree establishment programs through the Forest Service International Programs, the Institute of Pacific Islands Forestry, and the International Institute of Tropical Forestry;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4DF2C1BC22C437CA67D58F5B3B7A63E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collaborate with other relevant Federal departments and agencies, including the Foreign Agricultural Service of the Department of Agriculture, the United States Agency for International Development, the United States Fish and Wildlife Service of the Department of the Interior, and international organizations, including the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, to provide technical and financial assistance related to nurseries and reforestation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37B97ADA174B4D8B812253942785F7A8"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate the efforts of the Department of Agriculture to—</text><subparagraph id="HF06C456B44C44E31A9BFDC7990CD88E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>address the challenges associated with the reforestation pipeline; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE8FEF1ECBF38458480DAA54EBC6633A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>leverage economic development assistance for work with private nurseries; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF97B30AA67DF48FD808A094EBB0C4400"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expand climate-informed reforestation supply chains through science and research, seed collection and storage, and nursery infrastructure and operations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9DCB8543B002452FAF0B81B9EE4A1CC0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Nursery and seed orchard grants</header><paragraph id="HE570DC2D1BE04627925C26AA674D80EF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary of Agriculture shall establish a program to provide grants to eligible recipients to support nurseries and seed orchards.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03CA0C439B324634A2BA7FE9CEDEE8EB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may make a grant under this section to an eligible recipient for a project to do at least one of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HE3EC026DEC1D45B2BC2207D356F4C108"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Develop, expand, enhance, or improve nursery production capacity or other infrastructure to—</text><clause id="H8E12237AECE84E82868D3DA262E1B2BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>improve seed collection and storage;</text></clause><clause id="H60B66C2249404D66ADDFA87F89526A1B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>increase seedling production, storage, and distribution; or</text></clause><clause id="HC35BA787BD014D29B986FD0FB954531D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>enhance seedling survival and properly manage tree genetic resources.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B6373A7260D4E749F71BBA5A6C57ACA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish or expand a nursery or seed orchard, including by acquiring equipment for such nursery or seed orchard.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H14CB87373F4141C6B688401D8FED45CC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Develop or implement quality control measures at nurseries or seed orchards.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87371F3AA0704A83A412C2E80362AAD2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Promote workforce development within any facet of the reforestation pipeline.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF7960D3511E4AC59016145E23D1ECCA"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Carry out such other activity as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB83E4D61845F49B8A02E5966E47945EC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HD5143274D5EE436F80E364B8861CBC78"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible recipient</header><text>The term <quote>eligible recipient</quote> means— </text><subparagraph id="HFB62E5592B034692A595BDDEA7D79D76"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State forestry agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD46C8E46B8BC42CE98783711306CA64A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an Indian Tribe; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFED1680D28C94919BC5F7184C3A70C81"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a private nursery that has experience growing high-quality native trees of appropriate genetic sources in bareroot or container stocktypes specific for reforestation, restoration, or conservation, including native plants and seeds that are of cultural significance to Indian Tribes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H445B7CD1B6B441B680D15942641D5412"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nursery</header><text>The term <term>nursery</term> means a tree or native plant nursery.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E8318556EE0483E865C2B3D9131ED6B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Seed orchard</header><text>The term <quote>seed orchard</quote> means a tree or native plant seed orchard. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8821F23DF6BF4087ACC55318EC3A816D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and any territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1A17436FB8A54D6E895DB9CE4253DD4E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $25,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

