<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE689D51255954D31824428A8378E809F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3726 IH: Student Mental Health Rights Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3726</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Education to study student mental health at institutions of higher education and to issue guidance on compliance with the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 for mental health and substance use disorder policies of institutions of higher education, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H86CF2BA74E1F4937B3F37C48329F511D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF8E2F47D74DD46CEB093F88CD02756D8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Student Mental Health Rights Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H4DBFE1BC3D0942779CC0B5B464BC6812"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD910FBCE3D8A440B80221227ABDF13D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nearly all institutions of higher education are subject to—</text> <subparagraph id="H45EAEC9D12CE4E29A00942FD1EE2E2AD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5300F11C5FCE4C19B09AD10708BCA01B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBB069E8B430D4E78B47152E5F307F564"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Fair Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3601">42 U.S.C. 3601 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H76C9B23AAE13418B83B1C04A28F3AABF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The laws described in paragraph (1) prohibit discrimination on the basis of disability, defined as <quote>with respect to an individual, a physical or mental impairment that substantially limits one or more major life activities of such individual, a record of such an impairment, or being regarded as having such an impairment</quote> under section 3(1) of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12102">42 U.S.C. 12102(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H537C57EA458C4DD4B915AB9E737F448F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under section 2(a)(3) of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101(a)(3)</external-xref>), Congress found that <quote>discrimination against individuals with disabilities persists in such critical areas as employment, housing, public accommodations, education, transportation, communication, recreation, institutionalization, health services, voting, and access to public services</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8A9CDC359DC64087BFE1478BAD78AE44"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The laws described in paragraph (1) prohibit institutions of higher education from discriminating against students with disabilities, including by failing to provide reasonable accommodations or reasonable modifications to such students so that such students are able to fully participate in postsecondary life.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF563480ED79548A590B26B7E56440394"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The laws described in paragraph (1) prohibit institutions of higher education from discriminating against students with mental health disabilities, including by failing to provide reasonable accommodations or reasonable modifications to such a student.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1CAF2D897F264A5F9A9400D942877B0B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The vast majority of institutions of higher education lack a comprehensive plan for addressing and preventing discrimination against students with mental health disabilities or who are experiencing crises, in many cases—</text> <subparagraph id="H8736B2CCDF7844D8AF2DDB729E6B3D13"><enum>(A)</enum><text>requiring such students to leave the institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H05BBE8270C054FBDBD5A72B332B1E2AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>evicting such students from on-campus housing; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H630456810AE646C1A649863A4317ACD4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>establishing excessive and unnecessary impediments to the re-enrollment of such students to the institution of higher education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H193568BC3A804A54803FD2033FC6FF7E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Study and report</header> 
<subsection id="HEB9361A1B93C407CA0FE73AECBF7378A" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Voluntary reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall solicit from students at institutions of higher education, on a voluntary basis and in a manner that protects the confidentiality of such students, information with respect to mental health disabilities and substance use disorders at such institutions of higher education.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H37EB1FE763AF4E978DCFCF0584F8D258"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study and report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD828EB19471E454C91B1272E47B49DAC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>complete a study on mental health disabilities and substance use disorders at institutions of higher education, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H23935C84FE5A4EEC84239E0DCC277353"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">using the information voluntarily reported by students under subsection (a), the prevalence of such disabilities and disorders, disaggregated by type of disability or disorder (including disabilities and disorders related to hearing, vision, cognition, ambulatory, self-care, independent living, mental health, and any other category determined appropriate by the Secretary), among students at institutions of higher education and policies to support students with respect to such disabilities and disorders;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB727782D891D4C66BDFE71E4FE50B4DA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the policies of institutions of higher education with respect to students who, due to such a condition, are considering a voluntary leave of absence or are required to take a mandatory or involuntary leave of absence, or return from such an absence, and compliance by institutions of higher education with such policies; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2062FE0F7B8344C8BDB3528B5B0F096E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">best practices for supporting students at institutions of higher education in managing such disabilities and disorders, including the effect such practices have on graduation rates and degree completion; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8896737BA01340778F6A345F1F0D4104"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor and Pensions of the Senate a report on the findings of the study completed under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> </subsection> </section> <section id="H1180684FE2C14FB8BCC40B50016FECF8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Guidance</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date on which the report is submitted under section 3(b), the Secretary shall, in consultation with the Assistant Attorney General of the Civil Rights Division of the Department of Justice, issue guidance on—</text> 
<paragraph id="H3B32329762D34706A3F35BA3B967CAF2"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the compliance of institutions of higher education with the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12101">42 U.S.C. 12101 et seq.</external-xref>) and section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>) with respect to students with mental health disabilities;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA8933F7FB05F43DBB9B297A4535B672D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the legal obligations of institutions of higher education with respect to accommodating students with mental health disabilities and students with substance use disorders; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H929EF2CEF542437FB8D6C0A77667763F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">policies of institutions of higher education which may have a discriminatory impact on students with mental health disabilities and students with substance use disorders.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H2C7A8461A71846BB94C9D6319E37F835"><enum>5.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> 
<paragraph id="H5A66620E09404E73BC50C5E67D3642D8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Institution of Higher Education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F8BE49157694DC0BB90C183D287CEB1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education. </text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


