<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HDC228956E78A4B179654253B048B9CDE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>107 HR 4866 RH: Fire Weather Development Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 174</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4866</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–214]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230725">July 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000061">Mr. Mike Garcia of California</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001134">Ms. Caraveo</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230922">September 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on July 25, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to establish a program to improve fire weather and fire environment forecasting, detection, and local collaboration, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HSY00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H27A8DCB837A04EC8BC638A98206FEF37"><section id="HC72684161EDA4BE4B676250CB3B2667B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fire Weather Development Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE1C8D0FA58A94C33B1C74DB4AE468CD8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Fire weather forecasting and detection</header><subsection id="H23A38CFC87E3420A9BE900F692FF3C5D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, shall establish a program (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Program</quote>) to improve fire weather and fire environment forecasting, detection, and delivery of products or services through collaboration with Federal and State agencies or departments, local emergency mangers, and relevant entities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H136040B84D844145B5B4F51C32D2A9D4" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Goals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The goals of the Program shall be to develop and improve accurate fire weather and fire environment forecasts and warnings in order to reduce loss of life, reduce injuries, protect property, and reduce damage to the economy from wildfires. The Program shall seek to improve the assessment of fire weather and fire environments, the understanding and prediction of wildfires, and the communications regarding such assessments with State and local emergency officials in a timely and streamlined fashion, with a focus on improving the following:</text><paragraph id="H348B168543604A408D7C15403240B327" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The prediction of ignition, intensification and spread of wildfires.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90B25B600F8E418FA1FC06C1C77E6593"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The observation and monitoring of fire weather and fire environments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31554169DE894B509E489DA457D23E9C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The forecast and communication of smoke dispersion from wildfires.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFE6796FB86543A78611245CAEEFE729" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Information dissemination and risk communication to develop more effective watch and warning products relating to wildfires.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68AD8F8746B44DA986D524DC03CEBE80" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The early detection of wildfires, including pre-ignition analysis and ground condition characterizations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05E5E99BFACE481BA519234EE9DA3855" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The development, testing, and deployment of novel tools and techniques related to understanding, monitoring, and predicting fire weather and fire environments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F2072C29CC1480BBF5B6E0F7FFA00A2"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The understanding and association of climate change and its impacts on fire weather and fire environments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4FC49A02787460B80457BB3934C838D"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The unique characteristics, including observation or modeling requirements, related to fires at the wildland-urban interface.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA76BEB2F6B9C4A63BE7F497BC23F312B" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The forecasting and understanding of the impacts of prescribed burns (as such term is defined in section 2 of the Prescribed Burn Approval Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/551c-1">16 U.S.C. 551c–1</external-xref> note)).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC18BABC8A34A4D178A81317201CB6427"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Collaboration with stakeholders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In developing the Program required under this section, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall solicit and take into consideration input from the weather industry, such academic entities as the Administrator considers appropriate, and other relevant stakeholders.</text></subsection><subsection id="H32BF0A821FA146ED8B8BF51639FC0D6E" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To achieve the goals specified in subsection (b), the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration may conduct research, development, testing, demonstration, and operational transition activities related to fire weather and fire environments, including regarding the following:</text><paragraph id="H138D41178DB74B5D8C511E30F6491366" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Tools and services to inform, support, and complement active land management, local emergency personnel, the United States Forest Service, and State, local, and Tribal entities during their response and mitigation efforts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H088C54947BA6405C9B120DFBF96588C2" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Sensing technologies, such as infrared, microwave, and active sensors suitable for potential deployment on spacecraft, aircraft, and unmanned aircraft systems, to improve the monitoring and forecasting of fire fuel and active wildfires, wildfire behavior models and forecasts, mapping efforts, and the prediction of wildfires and the impacts of such.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEAA605AE95ED4A7A94D9F0A82D134B05" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Grid-based assessments and outlooks of fuel moisture and danger levels.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08ED7766FC654C6198163D7BF4C27C5A" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Social and behavior sciences related to fire weather and fire environment warning products.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A6D30C4DB294DADBDAE79219A977623" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Advanced satellite detection products coupled with atmosphere and fire weather modeling systems.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4DB9D1B973A439686527F9A53A2F096" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Education and training to expand the number of students and researchers in areas of study and research related to wildfires, fire weather, and fire environments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5356E45F40E44568D4936E0DD1D83C1" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Modeling systems to link long-term climate predictions to localized or general land management decisions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H433F73B72F52439B9BF55291EC0815DD" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Communication and outreach to communities, energy utilities, owners and operators of critical infrastructure, and other relevant stakeholders regarding fire weather and fire environment risk.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H626768B819F04A55BE261D197EF6FABF" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Stewardship and dissemination, to the extent practicable, of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration scientific data and related products and services in formats meeting shared standards to enhance the interoperability, usability, and accessibility of such data in order to better meet the needs of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, other Federal agencies, and relevant stakeholders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA086573EB4B943609BFFBA7D74B09E58" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Improvement of spatial and temporal resolution observations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2144B8CF10E147AA8611FCBA14F2AD74" commented="no"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other topic or activity the Administrator determines relevant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2125288050ED4DF0823AFEFADD5BCFF2" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Novel tools for monitoring and prediction</header><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, in consultation with the heads of the agencies specified in section 3, or other appropriate stakeholders, including commercial partners, shall develop novel tools and technologies to support the activities of the Program and which may be applied to broader wildland fire research, monitoring, and mitigation activities, as practicable and appropriate.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCDBD16904190461A877D0D2428C201CD" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Extramural research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall collaborate with and support the non-Federal wildland fire research community, which includes institutions of higher education, private sector entities, nongovernmental organizations, and other relevant stakeholders, by making funds available through competitive grants, contracts, and cooperative agreements.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDA0FB653DDB142A28028C0DBD3028E74"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Commercial data</header><paragraph id="H886CA3C807F04E4CB141AE7F5D1FA151" display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, in consultation with the heads of other Federal agencies and relevant stakeholders, may enter into contracts with one or more private sector entities to obtain additional airborne and space-based data and observations that may enhance or supplement the understanding, monitoring, and prediction, of fire weather and fire environments, and the relevant Program activities under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43546562D25242D594A9B285AFC83242" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out activities under paragraph (1), the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall consult with private sector entities through the National Advisory Committee on Wildfires under section 4 to identify needed tools and data that can be best provided by National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration satellites and are most beneficial to wildfire and smoke detection and monitoring.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H97FA9A3ED8D14ADAACBD14BD8381629D" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Nonduplication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the maximum extent practicable, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall consult with the National Interagency Fire Center, including the Joint Fire Science Program, to avoid duplication of activities under this section and ensure the Administration’s focus on unique research activities best suited for transition to operations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6A85E9CA99074061BB3C82F8F6606B5D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Unmanned aircraft systems</header><paragraph id="H47CAB34F4C994127B16CE2994658A762" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall—</text><subparagraph id="H1A7754092A344F949846C421C8E20DB2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assess the role and potential benefits of unmanned aircraft systems to improve data collection in support of fire weather and fire environment modeling, meteorological observations, predictions, and forecasts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0111983035B148DEBF747E2A6A239A92"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify objectives for testing such systems’ use for obtaining fire weather and fire environment observations, and other relevant activities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E5DA059B4784CEB9D2A4811278889A3" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>transition unmanned aircraft systems technologies from research to operations as the Administrator considers appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A6E7CEFD9344A1D86FF2CD30705CE8F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the date of enactment of the Act, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall brief the appropriate committees of Congress on the activities under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0C408AF534C4D2E8480D372B1C5CF7E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pilot programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 18 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration may conduct pilot programs of unmanned aircraft systems for fire weather and fire environment observations, including relating to the following:</text><subparagraph id="H3E0CBF89B01C42F0B46574DD40282979" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Testing of unmanned aircraft systems in approximations of real-world scenarios.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A104C9A3A724EED8A2EB6410B26A452" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Assessment of the utility of meteorological data collected from fire response and assessment aircraft.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB22DAEEDF9CF492DA687B01D3C4F3295" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Input into appropriate models of collected data to predict fire behavior, including coupled atmosphere and fire models.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A97BFA3DDBF45018C723C79ADB3EC1F" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Collection of best management practices for deployment of unmanned aircraft systems for fire weather and fire environment observations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CF66F27B7B448D885C8223C8DBD5A2E" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><subparagraph id="HAA54557C5E8E4C1FAD3FB307C1A1F1B3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided under subparagraphs (B) and (C), the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration may not procure any unmanned aircraft system that is manufactured or assembled by an entity in a foreign country of concern.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAA6E7BF6695497CABCDC84EE276C771" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prohibition under subparagraph (A) shall not apply to the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration if the Administrator determines, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, that the procurement of an unmanned aircraft system is necessary for the sole purpose of marine or atmospheric science or management.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H319C3C6DFE3848FFB29B5CD36FD75C82"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration may waive the prohibition under subparagraph (A) on a case-by-case basis—</text><clause id="H176042B54E52464D94CED69617AFBCE9" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with the approval of the Secretary of Homeland Security; and</text></clause><clause id="H3FD3B9C3BDE64E63888004D3F062E2A3" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">upon written or electronic notification to appropriate committees of Congress not later than 30 days after any such waiver.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4435EBC4A6BF4680BB0BE03558B4141F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Airspace operations system</header><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, in cooperation with the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, shall utilize the capabilities of unmanned aircraft systems as appropriate for fire weather and fire environment observations, and may use a wildfire airspace operations system that accounts for piloted aircraft, unmanned aircraft systems, and other new and emerging capabilities after such airspace operations system is developed and determined ready for operational use by the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8413AA9AE3D743E1BC9E38330D7464E3" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From amounts made available for Procurement, Acquisition, and Construction of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, there is authorized to be appropriated $5,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 to carry out this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE0CE90CE6BA4B489E344EB8C707E637"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HCE56E2BEB5424D2497FA2CF3F78B914C" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate committees of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>appropriate committees of Congress</quote> means the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology and the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3A8C1D798D440F8AE46CD7F17C6640E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>critical infrastructure</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 1016(e) of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/107/56">Public Law 107–56</external-xref> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c(e)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7150DFD9DAF54D23AC52483AC40B684D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign country of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>foreign country of concern</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 9901 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/4651">15 U.S.C. 4651</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3C8D15D04F6D4AFABCFE63649544F632"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE563EA0919A4204B282C24EA65D0486"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Unmanned aircraft system</header><text>The term <quote>unmanned aircraft system</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 44801 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D229E6ACCAD48888985F87976E8C548"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Weather industry</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>weather industry</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Weather Research and Forecasting Innovation Act of 2017 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/8501">15 U.S.C. 8501</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4971482FD0694236B0EED2D217622E6D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Interagency Coordinating Committee on Wildfires</header><subsection id="H903E3CC208E14620AC6460700D97C859"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall establish an interagency coordinating committee to be known as the <quote>Interagency Coordinating Committee on Wildfires</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Committee</quote>). The chair of the Committee shall be the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9D3A969AB64F458FB5037226B29FC654"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee shall coordinate the development of accurate and timely wildfire forecasting, detection, monitoring, and delivery of related products or services that best assist State and local emergency officials while avoiding duplication of activities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H78D20230DBBF419CA67394FFC2B3F7AF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>In addition to the chair, the Committee shall be composed of the heads or appropriate designees of the following program agencies:</text><paragraph id="HD6520C3FC1C84561AA5B4FA19C661613"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Federal Emergency Management Agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA32B38B79F6B495C908A493427D66D7F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The United States Fire Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C264ADA338D4FF8BC38AC76F5A596AF" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United States Forest Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6EDAF690BEFE4CD191DF89AA4C66C181"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC17B76C34288413CA7B2C2425A1E02D0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Department of the Interior.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5B8898A5BAC46B58EF1F8AAB075768F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Department of Agriculture.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27F34D146B744150B77D51C91754C895"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The United States Geological Survey.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9B16CD0A14A41E5B4F2DB3A21D1B16C"><enum>(8)</enum><text>The Office of Science and Technology Policy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83BDE2852BB34D5B9D0CAD348A760DC6"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any other Federal department or agency the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8175A2CEC7694DE5A33257D2613FACD0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Strategic plan</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Committee shall submit to Congress a strategic plan for the Program that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="H2DAD72138E534D0E83A887E2BB9471D9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of short-term, mid-term, and long-term objectives to achieve the purpose specified in subsection (b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA018F2F4A584E77BF53DAE673CF35A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of how agencies specified in subsection (c) will collaborate with stakeholders and take into account stakeholder needs and recommendations in developing such objectives.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C3B1CC0E5074313A39D91181DE0B7D7"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of existing and new observational and data infrastructure needed to accomplish such objectives.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EDF3E55780B43CD9C9D5D467F00BE9D" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of the role of each such agency in achieving such objectives.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E1D3ACB9AC54C9BBBC921AC63C07E94" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Guidance regarding how the Committee’s recommendations are best used in climate adaptation planning for Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D1D5B8DD6AE4928A8E9AEAAE6E00D9B" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Interagency agreements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The heads of agencies specified in subsection (c) may enter into one or more interagency agreements providing for cooperation and collaboration in the development of wildfire forecasting, detection, and monitoring tools, instruments, technologies, and research to accomplish the purpose described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0C5D3B034A934A7BB3B198D00FA827C3" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>The head of each agency specified in subsection (c) shall, to the extent practicable, increase engagement and cooperation with international, academic, State, and local communities regarding the infrastructure, data, and scientific research necessary to best advance the forecasting, detection, and monitoring of and preparation for wildfires.</text></subsection></section><section id="H06D1F6A3DC7A4EED9A196BE36D797FE0"><enum>4.</enum><header>National Advisory Committee on Wildfires</header><subsection id="H27DEFBCE0A334435882128FB3FC95DC2" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><paragraph id="HB7CCFFA45412456FB6741C26E07BDFA6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the submission of the strategic plan required by section 3(d), the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall establish a national advisory committee to be known as the <quote>National Advisory Committee on Wildfires</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Advisory Committee</quote>). The Advisory Committee shall consist of not fewer than seven and not more than 15 members who are qualified to provide advice regarding wildfire forecasting, detection, monitoring, and delivery of related products or services, including from the following entities:</text><subparagraph id="H4C0D7933D6B946B983B96B1183759662" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Research and academic institutions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9367B5E2DCD34A5FB902A72997233817" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Public communication or broadcast entities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9BD1F471EB54288BA297ECB5EFFFB0B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Emergency management agencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3A5D51B81A747F1B0FF1969D17D0136" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>State, local, or Tribal governments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE7C70D5A542143A0B6589EE24207BB38" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The National Association of State Foresters.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21398A97A0574B26B5E05224E5327B1B" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Business communities.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BB29EF26DBF4D28B3BA3A903C4A6DF1" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other entities as designated by the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD20ABF8CCD64880AE1CF9F51BB3CD0E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>Members of the Advisory Committee may not be employees of the Federal Government.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6A12DD79BC404681B180300175E25023"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall offer assessments and recommendations relating to the following:</text><paragraph id="H4AC54382E9B64A3EA7194101360817B1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Tailored forecasting, detection, and monitoring products and tools.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85B83DBD1A464DAEAE5D00F339C7A8BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Communication and delivery methods of wildfire forecasting, detection, and monitoring information.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1016633548324F03826310E1528FE2C4"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Opportunities to streamline Federal forecasting, monitoring, and detection information to local emergency personnel and communities. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35156E9D398D4F078D09DE602CB5939C" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The management, coordination, implementation, and activities of the Interagency Coordinating Committee on Wildfires under section 3.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H084B383D05D145238357B96902DFC839" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The effectiveness of the Interagency Coordinating Committee on Wildfires in meeting its purposes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA772B5DCA38D4F5F95FB2E24DDA8FA13"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>Members of the Advisory Committee shall serve without compensation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9FFEE5D4FEB54980AB82FFB3BBD69C7D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less frequently than biennially, the Advisory Committee shall report to the Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy on the assessments carried out under subsection (b) and its recommendations for ways to improve the coordination and dissemination of wildfire forecasts, warnings, and detection and monitoring information.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC187862E5A824B289E2E657F229CB610" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Charter</header><text>Notwithstanding section 1013(b)(2) of title 5, United States Code, the Advisory Committee shall not be required to file a charter subsequent to its initial charter, filed under section 1008(c) of such title, before the termination date specified in subsection (f) of this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1BCD40BD0CF1472DAF9A9ADDD8DB46A5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall terminate on September 30, 2028.</text></subsection><subsection id="H091D97B57B2F4D57BB7D1383D2F34C98"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Conflict of interest</header><text>An Advisory Committee member shall recuse himself or herself from any Advisory Committee activity in which he or she has an actual pecuniary interest.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4BDEEAD12C51468FA014A80B4383B8FE"><enum>5.</enum><header>Establishment of fire weather testbed</header><subsection id="H740CB78376D14F4CB313526EDFF047F9" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall establish a fire weather testbed to enable engagement across the Federal Government, State and local governments, academia, private and federally funded research laboratories, the private sector, and end-users in order to evaluate the accuracy and usability of technology, models, fire weather products and services, and other research to accelerate the implementation, transition to operations, and use of new capabilities by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, Federal and land management agencies, and other relevant stakeholders.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDFF09161117C4137A6B8565CFDAFC10D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out this section, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration may not transfer or reprogram any funds, detail any personnel, or make use of any infrastructure from cooperative institutes of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in existence as of the date of the enactment of this Act for the fire weather testbed established under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H7DC182FA2AA644AAB8B74D73E9C03027"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From amounts made available for Procurement, Acquisition, and Construction of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, there is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for fiscal year 2024 to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE340A8380C3F4BFDBC964D7A52B4E7B4" commented="no"><enum>6.</enum><header>Incident meteorologist workforce</header><subsection id="H538224AEA92A402DBA8DCB9572648918"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Workforce and training assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than six months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate the results of an assessment of National Weather Service workforce and training challenges for Incident Meteorologists, and a roadmap for overcoming such challenges. Such assessment shall take into consideration information technology support, logistical and administrative operations, anticipated weather and climate conditions, and feedback from relevant stakeholders, and shall include, to the maximum extent practicable, an identification by the National Weather Service of the following:</text><paragraph id="H065F346B1D7A4A7A8E88E1874B251A3E" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The expected number of Incident Meteorologists needed over the next five years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3E47D4D7BDD4E39A249BBFFE0E779C2" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Potential hiring authorities necessary to overcome any identified workforce and training challenges.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5CAB0F42C774557B5615FAFB4564C77" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Alternative services or assistance options the National Weather Service could provide to meet operational needs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H38AB788A96D541A197F1316B9425AD78" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Overtime pay</header><paragraph id="H5FCCA70FE3214AE29DEC1F4D2B529930"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any premium pay for services performed by Incident Meteorologists of the National Weather Service that are determined by the Secretary of Commerce to be primarily related to emergency wildland fire suppression activities shall be disregarded in calculating the aggregate of such employee’s basic pay and premium pay for purposes of a limitation under section 5547 of title 5, United States Code, or under any other provision of law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AD27CD229B14FB9AAF175F166F67D9B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5542(a)(5) of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting <quote>, the National Weather Service,</quote> after <quote>Interior</quote>. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HEB508256B99F4402AA8C5C4CB1E33E1C" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>7.</enum><header>Research on wildland fire communications and information dissemination</header><subsection id="HDD80FA7C3C4D49DEB548562AF4E0CAA1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="HFB03CA01F9A64120BC09E16273B9DF4F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Public safety research</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director, acting through the head of the Public Safety and Communications Research Division and in consultation with the Fire Research Division and technology manufacturers, shall carry out research on the following:</text><subparagraph id="H7D8E17F24DF248C7B9C2925507BF1A1D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Public safety communication coordination standards among Federal, State, Tribal, and local wildland firefighters, fire management response officials, and member agencies.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE155F5309A3244C5B7BF61BF07B39761"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Improving and integrating existing communications systems to transmit secure real-time data, alerts, and advisories to and from fire management response officials and wildland firefighters.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H385AFAF122FC4C849F72D65837380C35"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Field testing and measurement of information dissemination and technology</header><text>The Public Safety and Communications Research Division, in consultation with the Fire Research Division and member agencies, shall conduct both live and virtual field testing of equipment, software, and other technologies to determine current times of information dissemination and develop standards for the delivery of useful and secure real-time data among member agencies, fire management response officials, and wildland firefighters, based on findings from research under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2E6D891090547F3868BA2729F3B6B08"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><paragraph id="H8919702B269544F597C73EA2B7744DBD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall develop and publish recommendations to improve public safety communication coordination standards among wildland first responders and fire management response officials.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFA73297AA4F491EAF4B7D97B38A1372"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transmittal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall transmit the recommendations under paragraph (1) to the Office of Management and Budget and the Office of Science and Technology Policy for member agencies to implement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B3E37DE6F28495D8E7F57A2C89A8F2E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header><subparagraph id="H4FE8F9B64A2744D5AFD3CA4832D21B29"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report containing the recommendations published under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5850845A4178447A93CC923F497CE03F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the publication of the Director’s recommendations under paragraph (1), the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report on the extent to which member agencies have implemented such recommendations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H06DB7A03025C4AB5A0D152552538E9B3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From amounts made available to the National Institute of Standards and Technology, the Director shall allocate $3,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA365B64124F24F7DBB515D68435CC87C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H0837D74AC020463584E76949F72BFC2B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA63D7821B2364EC9832A007C72A9CAE4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Member agency</header><text>The term <term>member agency</term> means a member agency of the National Interagency Fire Center, including the Bureau of Indian Affairs, Bureau of Land Management, National Park Service, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Forest Service, United States Fire Administration, and the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6B0908C8FA2420A8F24528E93ECF391"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Wildland firefighter</header><text>The term <term>wildland firefighter</term> means any person who participates in wildland firefighting activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5F5B809D95E4B8BBD7DED43F7DB7708"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Fire management response officials</header><text>The term <term>fire management response officials</term> means regional fire directors, deputy regional fire directors, agency officials who directly oversee fire operations, fire management officers, and individuals serving on incident management teams.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90A1C41739A243B4B57D58406B37AB5F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Technology manufacturers</header><text>The term <term>technology manufacturers</term> means private sector entities that manufacture communications technologies used by Federal, State, Tribal, or local wildland fire authorities.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4E3AE9F968014BFEB5EBCF77CEC8EFB5"><enum>8.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H4D82F61AE0D44C978352F2A622ED8F75"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Fire environment</header><text>The term <quote>fire environment</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H755BB4B25C414611BD2E322218F0FEC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the environmental conditions, such as soil moisture, vegetation, topography, snowpack, atmospheric temperature, moisture, and wind, that influence—</text><clause id="H7EB36A6CFB1E425C9C95DA2B555A89D1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>fuel and fire behavior; and</text></clause><clause id="HDA9F6A3B926846169FC1C892757BE19B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>smoke dispersion and transport; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEF79FA3382564D01AABF7EE98C2F3E3E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the associated environmental impacts occurring during and after fire events.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B0B0009773D4AACA0D03AF0D6155965"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fire weather</header><text>The term <quote>fire weather</quote> means the weather conditions that influence the start, spread, character, or behavior of wildfires or fires at the wildland-urban interface and relevant meteorological and chemical phenomena, including air quality, smoke, and meteorological parameters such as relative humidity, air temperature, wind speed and direction, and atmospheric composition and chemistry, including emissions and mixing heights.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230922">September 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

