<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCFB68D74B1B1469183B246F6B0C5FFE4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3135 IH: LPOE Modernization Trust Fund Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3135</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000136">Mr. Vasquez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Land Port of Entry Modernization Trust Fund, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBF6E0352B38A4A75A8C7A2872FF0725C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA192A0C497994F5BB801C92CCAC52F3C" section-type="section-one" commented="no"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>LPOE Modernization Trust Fund Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HFC8387F4546849C383557E2E7B7D5697" commented="no"><enum>2.</enum><header>Land Port of Entry Modernization Trust Fund</header> <subsection id="H5345EC903C1B46AE8F8EA7CE931C607B" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Creation of trust fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Treasury of the United States a trust fund to be known as the <quote>Land Port of Entry Modernization Trust Fund</quote> (referred to in this section as the <quote>Trust Fund</quote>), consisting of amounts transferred to the Trust Fund under subsection (b) and any amounts that may be credited to the Trust Fund under subsection (c). </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAF43910C26E449BD882CA9E3147EA620" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deposits into trust fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be deposited into the Trust Fund as discretionary offsetting collections, for fiscal year 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter—</text> <paragraph id="H5D8DD6DF90BC465EA518A252F4BD9F30" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">twenty-five percent of all fees collected pursuant to section 13031(b)(9)(A)(ii)(I) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c(b)(9)(A)(ii)(I)</external-xref>); </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FA81010F5E54D238358F458EEDD144D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">up to $1,600,000,000 of the Merchandise Processing Fees collected pursuant to section 13031(a)(9)(B)(i) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c(a)(9)(B)(i)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H29196B64F1A1420C98AEE4811E17A91E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">twenty-five percent of all surcharges collected under subsection (h)(3) of this Act related to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDCB0753828D241139DD0FDEFD75F04D4" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>immigrant user fee established under section 286(m) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S.C. 22 1356(m));</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4FC8BB07D3B64CEA8892B05ACD16DBEF" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>land border inspection fees established under section 286(q) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1356">8 U.S.C. 1356(q)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7B57143ADEF64BB9A6FC0A7F9AF1A26B" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the machine-readable visa fee established under section 103 of the Enhanced Border Security and Visa Entry Reform Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1713">8 U.S.C. 1713</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE54586AB5828452CB3F5CEEB684642A8" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Investment of amounts</header> <paragraph id="HA5AAADF3FB5540D991AEF5387A57B568" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall invest such portion of the Trust Fund as is not required to meet current obligations in interest-bearing obligations of the United States or in obligations guaranteed as to both principal and interest by the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3A5E9409560F42A685198F4E46E8F013" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interest and proceeds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The interest on, and the proceeds from the sale or redemption of, any obligations held in the Trust Fund shall be credited to the Trust Fund as discretionary offsetting collections, and shall form a part of the Trust Fund. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4B1B5C5E9BFA4F56978016E32D20C677" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of Trust Fund</header> <paragraph id="HDA9BF1B0900B45D79EB4BF5233AAA713" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amounts in the Trust Fund, including amounts described in subsection (c)(2), shall be made available to the Secretary for the purposes described in paragraph (2) only to the extent and in the amounts provided in advance in appropriations Acts.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H79FA7834E3C94E4AAD7DE9B41B912DFD" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (1), amounts in the Trust Fund shall be made available for the following purposes:</text> <subparagraph id="H35E2460199FB47C8B989051B0697273D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The construction of new United States ports of entry.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H07489D4B66434637934D27B025CEFD75" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The expansion and improvement of existing United States ports of entry infrastructure to accommodate high volumes of commercial, vehicle, and pedestrian traffic.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H113B09B53F8442EDA2642444ADAECCF5" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The procurement of technology and supporting infrastructure for United States ports of entry, and related cargo and commercial inspection facilities, to facilitate the inspection and processing of commercial, vehicle, and pedestrian traffic.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9FCA24D0BC6D4CC392E38D7D2E469221" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The facilitation of major repairs and alterations of United States land ports of entry.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H828A51CB6B1C4D26ACF12FC94476154C" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Hiring U.S. Customs and Border Protection officers, agricultural specialists, and professional staff to support the trade and revenue mission of such agency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HEF653FBB32AF46CFBC09DBE02386FF90" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header> 
<subparagraph id="H56EC37FE5D9C4495858AFECE40919FCD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purposes described in paragraph (2) shall be carried out by the Secretary, in consultation with the Administrator of General Services, the Chief of Engineers and Commanding General of the United States Army Corps of Engineers, State, local, and Tribal governments, organizations that represent the interests of commerce, and relevant advisory committees under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H063D3AD06B92494D96FF3905119DEFBB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consideration of transportation plans</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Board established pursuant to subsection (g)(1), shall consider regional bi-national transportation master plans to carry out the purposes described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBC61F74397D44EB3B9507E7A6C577110" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Limitations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of the Treasury and the Secretary of State, shall not seek to increase fees as a measure to offset amounts deposited into the Trust Fund.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="H4FFFB3C4B90A46FBB76AF5A708E041CC" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than March 10 of each year, the Secretary, in coordination with the Administrator of General Services, shall submit to the Committees on Appropriations of the House of Representatives and the Senate and the Board a report on the status of the implementation of this section that includes a description of—</text> 
<paragraph id="H2BC49C6FEC484932A235F0E10A395265" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how, and to which recipients, amounts have been obligated and expended from the Trust Fund in the immediate previous fiscal year; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9FFB1810FEFB478BB42C97C7CEEC107E" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how, and to which recipients, amounts are planned to be obligated or expended from the Trust Fund in the upcoming fiscal year;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H582F127B1A4A4A72AA5ADF77406CA12F" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the amount remaining in the Trust Fund; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8FBE57C4211747B1B82C7FEFC4053897" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the expected dates of completion for purposes described in subsection (d).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8EDF43ABD11949D988AC662982421DEE" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Land Port of Entry Modernization Oversight Board</header> 
<paragraph id="HDA81EACDA3634BB292C9DE9F1A24C4AD" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish an oversight board to be known as the <quote>Land Port of Entry Modernization Oversight Board</quote> (referred to in this section as the <quote>Board</quote>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABB5D4C7F55C42D4A7963A5487677452" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties of Board</header><text>The Board shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8E0EB477C7524F39BA447F3B55036EAC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>advise the Secretary with respect to the prioritization of purposes described in subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC5DCB7B29BF84948B33FCF2CEA868EA2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>review the expenditure of funds from the Trust Fund.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCB3E1509B64049228C5F847AE22B54A0" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<subparagraph id="HB2BDDD44330C49C28FADA1F7286D2CC3" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall be composed of 9 members, as follows: </text> <clause id="H283E0E8545D64C3C9FD7529F28123EB3" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security or the Secretary’s designee.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF38D61F6D97140E2964DBB12B55DCB89"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of General Services or the Secretary’s designee.</text></clause> <clause id="H74D11F6997B040AF9D0DECF522D7E38D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Commerce or the Secretary’s designee.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA45138BC08AB48DD93A434D72D5DB079"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State or the Secretary’s designee.</text></clause> <clause id="H3D27957A83424943A7E997FEF2AF5CC2"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation or the Secretary’s designee.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HBDB331869806421CB6F36FECC128021C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>A representative of the United States trucking industry, appointed by the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></clause> <clause id="H5E7E8B9D88C84F5A8AC238D3D9AAEA4A" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A representative of the United States land ports of entry or rail sectors located on the southwest land border, appointed by the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H613F807E45B247168595807BCED42893"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>A representative of the United States land ports of entry or rail sectors located on the northern land border, appointed by the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></clause> <clause id="HEC49951BD86C4C4CAF854BD4D7D90C99" commented="no"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>A representative of a State or local transportation authority, appointed by the Secretary of Homeland Security. </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEAAC29311DDE4B3A8A317A9A72FDE363" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing of appointments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member appointed under clauses (vi) and (vii) of subparagraph (A) shall be made not later than 3 months after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H86AFC7B660C1400E985842A459EB7A98" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Terms</header> <clause id="HCDE3655796094269AF6E67C07D774B75" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member appointed under clauses (vi), (vii), and (viii) of subparagraph (A) shall serve for a term of 2 years.</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9DA1BA8FC29B4066B313021B08BBBBAF" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member appointed to fill a vacancy of a member appointed under clauses (vi), (vii), and (viii) of subparagraph (A), occurring before the expiration of the term for which the member’s predecessor was appointed, shall be appointed only for the remainder of that term. A member may serve after the expiration of that term until a successor has been appointed.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H62B8AA5B34504FF3B1AFCE6711C27AE6" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Chairperson</header><text>The Chairperson of the Board shall be the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF1693EC4EF134F0C8A5886158BF10D7D" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Meeting</header> 
<subparagraph id="HF22EA6C1E7344A269AE69852E0D5A466" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial meeting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Board shall hold its initial meeting not later than 30 days after the final appointment of members under clauses (vi), (vii), and (viii) of paragraph (3)(A).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0F48912DA52347D18B773E5EA8E0B8EB" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Meeting</header><text>The Board shall meet not fewer than 1 time each year at the call of the Chairperson.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H68D182F0EAB84D70AB31A547ED9C5B43" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Quorum</header><text>Four members of the Board shall constitute a quorum. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HACDA657463714977897834C51746868D" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Compensation</header> <subparagraph id="H7689D374D90A455DB15280129D1ECF98" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Prohibition of compensation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), members of the Board may not receive additional pay, allowances, or benefits by reason of their service on the Board.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6A57589BFCCE40FBB268EA4E6398E02E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>Each member shall receive travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFE6CA59E2DFA49C9AF180EAEF8CDE80A" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later January 31, 2024, and annually thereafter, the Board shall submit to the Secretary a report containing a detailed statement relating to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6A4F9B85B218403284157AEF171FC545" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the prioritization of activities described in subsection (d); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8DDD2DB63FE0434E8FE53D2D555431DD" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations with respect to the expenditure of funds from the Trust Fund.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H71E3A31E6A8F4999A7A2126164EDF222" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of certain advisory committee rules</header><text>Notwithstanding section 1013 of title 5, United States Code, the Board is authorized for a period commensurate with the LPOE Modernization Trust Fund authorization.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H990F389B77394F5E9AB79922CE7F841A" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Customs fees</header> <paragraph id="H54FCDA528867479993167388D8E92E4B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Land port of entry maintenance fees transfer</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, up to $1,600,000,000 of the amount in the Customs User Fee Account established pursuant to paragraph (1) of section 13031(f) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c(f)(1)</external-xref>) and not otherwise appropriated shall be transferred to the Trust Fund, subject to paragraph (3) of such section 13031(f). Notwithstanding paragraph (2) of such section 13031(f), amounts transferred from the Customs User Fee Account to the Trust Fund pursuant to the preceding sentence shall be available only to the extent and in the amounts provided in advance in appropriations Acts to carry out the purposes specified in subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAF4CAFB1787B4117ABF0B7D2F7E28F9B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fees collected for express consignment operations</header><text>Section 13031(b)(9) of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c(b)(9)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <subparagraph id="H255152CBC5644E869B55BC4F9E479C2A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)(iii)(III), to read as follows: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H280D08F943DC4D93A70F1D7C470E7B0F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subclause id="H2D53169FBCDC42C58CC44381343B7631" commented="no" indent="up2"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The remaining 25 percent of the amount of payments received under subparagraph (A)(ii) and clause (ii) of this subparagraph shall be deposited into the Land Port of Entry Modernization Trust Fund and shall be available only to the extent and in the amounts provided in advance in appropriations Acts to carry out the purposes specified in section 2(d)(2) of the LPOE Modernization Trust Fund Act;</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2CCC2E0757D24A99993BF9AC746A8467" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by adding at the end the following: </text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7EC32DE80578406C8F52689B91EC88B9" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<clause id="HA375C829B07345CB984C0F399176B513" commented="no" indent="up2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>individual air waybill</term> and <term>bill of lading</term> mean a document or other tracking mechanism representing an individual shipment, that is not a consolidated or master document—</text> <subclause id="H3361BCC39EEB4DA881F5A5BD8B9D0AF4" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>having its own unique bill number, unique tracking number, or other unique identifier; </text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HB3A06B386BA24528B32921429B888732" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text>assigned to a single ultimate consignee; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H2DD26B4876F14C008E3712A3A777B88E" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text>with respect to which no lower tracking unit exists.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H09D2CFDE578048D4A06447D16D2FA130"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Surcharge of fees collected</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law—</text> <subparagraph id="H5D3F63A4E9304D1699C8DDBA12686B1D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Secretary shall charge a surcharge of—</text> 
<clause id="H6CD340191BD24FB8B3F47BDCA7F0EBC2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>$40 on the immigrant user fee established under section 286(m) of the Immigration and Naturalization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1356">8 U.S.C. 1356(m)</external-xref>); and</text></clause> <clause id="HE0FDC791C07A48BD80BD1E9888098AF8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>$6 on the land border inspection fee established under section 286(q) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1356">8 U.S.C. 1356(q)</external-xref>); and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2D579B6E57AC449A8F15F4BE3021B520"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Secretary of State shall charge a surcharge of $20 on the machine-readable visa fee established under section 103 of the Enhanced Border Security and Visa Entry Reform Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1713">8 U.S.C. 1713</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="HFA456652A9D54BF3A3ADD60F7F4D076C" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HABCDCBF945284243999D6E608B7A79CD" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H45A931C6F5604340878DB32B4BF55270" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security, the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure, and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H89F2F0DD842F423493F8A7AED494A95C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation, and the Committee on Finance of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9FBF70EF5DEF47B697916FC26CA5EAF0" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian tribe</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4(e) of the Indian Self-Determination Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304(e)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H05C1A760CCC746F1956AF5BDF02505B3" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>Except as otherwise specified in this section, the term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Homeland Security.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF879E95F3EA9445AAA10D331E5674042" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <term>Tribal government</term> means the government of an Indian tribe. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

