<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFB17C89E1B674DC193A08287E92A5E05" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 503 IH: No TikTok on United States Devices Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 503</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230125">January 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To impose sanctions with respect to TikTok, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H796219B0406B49499E322FAD3320A44C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H706216041F0947FE8B6B7C0BD1CED96B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No TikTok on United States Devices Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE070A214D0B44AF3B4800E871D53BB2A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to TikTok</header> <subsection id="H6842D934FE894893AD61DB85CDDC2CCE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text>On and after the date that is 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall exercise all the powers granted to the President under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in all property and interests in property of a covered company if such property and interests in property—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6F62323123B24829BD7C45617FC2AA69"><enum>(1)</enum><text>are in the United States or come within the United States; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1642C56B51884296ADD3B9918C5BDF0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the extent necessary to prevent commercial operation of the covered company in the United States, are or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5C4EC0969FA3443B82E8FF0EE772DF1C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inapplicability of national emergency requirement</header><text>The requirements of section 202 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply for purposes of this section. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H63FA2FBC03DE4631A235B0CEDBA80DF0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation</header> <paragraph id="HFA34AD53B1B540BB9EC17D6E53A4B36C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the President may exercise all authorities provided under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to carry out this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H933EDF9473AF4B3B9E61FFC89F1C3185"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>The exceptions under subsection (b) of section 203 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1702">50 U.S.C. 1702</external-xref>) shall not apply to the use by the President in carrying out this section of the authorities under such section 203.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HADC9A3BDBB194F38ABBF59D9108054E1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>A person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of this section or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out this section shall be subject to the penalties set forth in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H868581139AE641A9A3E71AA1BC3A6649"><enum>(e)</enum><header>National security and research exceptions</header><text>Sanctions under this section shall not apply with respect to law enforcement activities, national security interests and activities, and security research activities, as provided under the standards and guidelines developed by the Director of the Office of Management and Budget under section 102(b)(1) of the No TikTok on Government Devices Act (division R of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H03103D9335CA4F5C9F68181E51577962"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Covered company defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered company</term> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="H8AC2A06BC0F843C79D1FE05A12BD83EB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ByteDance Limited, or any successor entity to ByteDance Limited, if ByteDance Limited or the successor entity—</text> <subparagraph id="H43F774FF5AE742158AD40DA9FFBEB9F4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is involved in matters relating to the social networking service TikTok, or any successor service; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC3A48A4538214F22923EC7E48E44CAC9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is involved in matters relating to any information, videos, or data associated with such service; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCFCBD728A8464A13B2AF297679F6FBC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any entity owned by ByteDance Limited or the successor entity that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H8E4E542C40D2485A85FB444293B0FD5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is involved in matters relating to the social networking service TikTok, or any successor service; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF2AE2DC8341F42E08E77F3B3922DE073" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is involved in matters relating to any information, videos, or data associated with such service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H0F89C7138DBC489F92946CAC12F46A65"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on threats to national security posed by TikTok</header> 
<subsection id="H19028E9A78CD4E18BD562F0D6A0C43F8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of National Intelligence, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense, the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency, the Secretary of Homeland Security, and the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, shall submit to Congress a report on the threats to national security posed by TikTok, including the following:</text> <paragraph id="H93F7BC98134B459992B2DFCDE69E2B09"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The ability of the Government of the People’s Republic of China to access, directly or indirectly, data of users in the United States via TikTok.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3D7EE2B7DB13472F95486D7AF0A4AAF0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The ability of the Government of the People’s Republic of China to use data of users in the United States, including that of members of the Armed Forces, accessed via TikTok for intelligence or military purposes, including surveillance, microtargeting, deepfakes, or blackmail.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H26A6A80197524F8782464007AAB6644F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any ongoing efforts by the Government of the People’s Republic of China to monitor or manipulate United States persons using data accessed via TikTok, including a detailed account of any data employed for those purposes.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H77EF50FD23BD496B85432368C287E52C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report required by subsection (a) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HE6AD2968E26E407BB45FE55AB03FB0ED"><enum>4.</enum><header>Briefing</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of National Intelligence shall provide to Congress a classified briefing on the implementation of this Act, which shall include a briefing on the report required by section 3(a).</text></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


