<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBCF6018F40A548EFA127BF17B8B1D349" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6143 IH: American Security Drone Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6143</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide for drone security.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H4754B2518AC04BDA8A1DF78C44390CD9" style="OLC">
<section id="H68F2C8E905ED4D83A0E536019535476B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Security Drone Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA0016B09E0DA4BF286DCF4E56AF6D28B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HEA93CCCDAB5945ADB74B032DF7265925"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered foreign entity</header><text>The term <term>covered foreign entity</term> means an entity included on a list developed and maintained by the Federal Acquisition Security Council and published in the System for Award Management (SAM). This list will include entities in the following categories:</text> <subparagraph id="H41A60ECBB09747D09025C401E16E7F6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An entity included on the Consolidated Screening List.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H68A0C99AA70441D8869B5CDE22878841"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Any entity the Secretary of Homeland Security, in coordination with the Secretary of State, the Attorney General, Director of National Intelligence, and the Secretary of Defense, determines poses a national security risk.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HC6DED4A211CD447299FC7686AEA635DF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any entity domiciled in the People’s Republic of China or subject to influence or owned or controlled by the Government of the People’s Republic of China or the Communist Party of the People’s Republic of China, as determined by the Secretary of Homeland Security, in coordination with the Secretary of State.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H46B58D6B0FE14B229287DB5CC6B374E7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Any subsidiary or affiliate of an entity described in subparagraphs (A) through (D).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD2198B1B1F95468F8DC6356CA67712D8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered unmanned aircraft system</header><text>The term <term>covered unmanned aircraft system</term> has the meaning given the term <term>unmanned aircraft system</term> in section 44801 of title 49, United States Code.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFC7CD33849A243B9B3D678A468F27E91"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Intelligence; intelligence community</header><text>The terms <term>intelligence</term> and <term>intelligence community</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></section> <section id="H9A36760DC9E44750BA002334CCA7EB8A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on procurement of covered unmanned aircraft systems from covered foreign entities</header> <subsection id="H373FC1ED818B438BB0F2F92887124EAB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided under subsections (b) through (f), the head of an executive agency may not procure any covered unmanned aircraft system that is manufactured or assembled by a covered foreign entity, which includes associated elements related to the collection and transmission of sensitive information (consisting of communication links and the components that control the unmanned aircraft) that enable the operator to operate the aircraft in the National Airspace System. The Federal Acquisition Security Council, in coordination with the Secretary of Transportation, shall develop and update a list of associated elements.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H521F2B77F27F4D508EB96E9FC8495642"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Defense, and the Attorney General are exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the procurement is required in the national interest of the United States and—</text> <paragraph id="H88408B4587524F7F9436D7ED4A8D08DE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is for the sole purposes of research, evaluation, training, testing, or analysis for electronic warfare, information warfare operations, cybersecurity, or development of unmanned aircraft system or counter-unmanned aircraft system technology;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6DAF84226FBA4CE89CAA050A3011C099"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is for the sole purposes of conducting counterterrorism or counterintelligence activities, protective missions, or Federal criminal or national security investigations, including forensic examinations, or for electronic warfare, information warfare operations, cybersecurity, or development of an unmanned aircraft system or counter-unmanned aircraft system technology; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H497FA76F76674628B75E0A636C01C6EC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is an unmanned aircraft system that, as procured or as modified after procurement but before operational use, can no longer transfer to, or download data from, a covered foreign entity and otherwise poses no national security cybersecurity risks as determined by the exempting official.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8BEA373C2DC54BD093F1ABE204320583"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Department of Transportation and Federal Aviation Administration exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation is exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the operation or procurement is deemed to support the safe, secure, or efficient operation of the National Airspace System or maintenance of public safety, including activities carried out under the Federal Aviation Administration’s Alliance for System Safety of UAS through Research Excellence (ASSURE) Center of Excellence (COE) and any other activity deemed to support the safe, secure, or efficient operation of the National Airspace System or maintenance of public safety, as determined by the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H89D95C30193542EEA93B66EB160C0088"><enum>(d)</enum><header>National Transportation Safety Board exemption</header><text>The National Transportation Safety Board, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, is exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the operation or procurement is necessary for the sole purpose of conducting safety investigations.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HEACE886C5F51446FBBCC147080BB3116"><enum>(e)</enum><header>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration exemption</header><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, is exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the procurement is necessary for the purpose of meeting NOAA’s science or management objectives or operational mission.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF77205F346604E1BA570A7A87F64DEF8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The head of an executive agency may waive the prohibition under subsection (a) on a case-by-case basis—</text>
<paragraph id="H03DEB7CB30B04A40A0303D42AF7C370F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with the approval of the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, after consultation with the Federal Acquisition Security Council; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE22CDB26AEE41FD8B3A9B6E606384D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>upon notification to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H3803E0C25D944327957D25007C8D8460" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE71870B2832D4378B6EA3D5517A217E2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Oversight and Accountability in the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0F4B43E1E6DF45858E2787754CE4CBD0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other appropriate congressional committees of jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HA5BF3C473BA84B44846F701F705125FD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on operation of covered unmanned aircraft systems from covered foreign entities</header> <subsection id="H2C6605F4A07E429883C68FD33B627828"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header> <paragraph id="H0449F75F1D544F24B0802645BFC21F95"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning on the date that is two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, no Federal department or agency may operate a covered unmanned aircraft system manufactured or assembled by a covered foreign entity.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H897CC3337F1F47BB9888CF4225C337E3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability to contracted services</header><text>The prohibition under paragraph (1) applies to any covered unmanned aircraft systems that are being used by any executive agency through the method of contracting for the services of covered unmanned aircraft systems.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H26BB8901305245858FF61C72372722BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Defense, and the Attorney General are exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the operation is required in the national interest of the United States and—</text>
<paragraph id="H093CB1A17BCF438C94E1639CADBC6A89"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is for the sole purposes of research, evaluation, training, testing, or analysis for electronic warfare, information warfare operations, cybersecurity, or development of unmanned aircraft system or counter-unmanned aircraft system technology;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFFDCF95F31F0498C9830B2802357B9D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is for the sole purposes of conducting counterterrorism or counterintelligence activities, protective missions, or Federal criminal or national security investigations, including forensic examinations, or for electronic warfare, information warfare operations, cybersecurity, or development of an unmanned aircraft system or counter-unmanned aircraft system technology; or</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCB29C4AC229E460BB886FCC599477B4F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is an unmanned aircraft system that, as procured or as modified after procurement but before operational use, can no longer transfer to, or download data from, a covered foreign entity and otherwise poses no national security cybersecurity risks as determined by the exempting official.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H313C55498201423E8A38187BEA030AB6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Department of Transportation and Federal Aviation Administration exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation is exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the operation is deemed to support the safe, secure, or efficient operation of the National Airspace System or maintenance of public safety, including activities carried out under the Federal Aviation Administration’s Alliance for System Safety of UAS through Research Excellence (ASSURE) Center of Excellence (COE) and any other activity deemed to support the safe, secure, or efficient operation of the National Airspace System or maintenance of public safety, as determined by the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H580C4518A19C437C8D0CD13969871D3F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>National Transportation Safety Board exemption</header><text>The National Transportation Safety Board, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, is exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the operation is necessary for the sole purpose of conducting safety investigations.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6A78CE36B4D8404785C6FE4731A7FDA4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration exemption</header><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, is exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the procurement is necessary for the purpose of meeting NOAA’s science or management objectives or operational mission.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HBDFF6D7CFA8B454CA10765F278DB9758"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The head of an executive agency may waive the prohibition under subsection (a) on a case-by-case basis—</text> <paragraph id="H5D708CFE487F43CC8B2CFF77EFED96BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with the approval of the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, after consultation with the Federal Acquisition Security Council; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF78EAAECE7A14FDD973493B827EBBB37"><enum>(2)</enum><text>upon notification to—</text> <subparagraph id="H25356D6319F94D7899FCB53E5A53D5FE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCA31521BD2D04C77BCA5AE0D83620B58" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Oversight and Accountability in the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCB6C42DFF51C41AEAC1A97C2F30148F0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other appropriate congressional committees of jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H254F1E23E7F34671A39AF376E6DBBC5F"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Attorney General, the Secretary of State, and the Secretary of Transportation, shall prescribe regulations or guidance to implement this section.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H9797DA2539FD4A16973A6E319DB9A611"><enum>5.</enum><header>Prohibition on use of Federal funds for procurement and operation of covered unmanned aircraft systems from covered foreign entities</header> <subsection id="H08826585C2C24DE3AF35EF9A8917263D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning on the date that is two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, except as provided in subsection (b), no Federal funds awarded through a contract, grant, or cooperative agreement, or otherwise made available may be used—</text>
<paragraph id="H0531B5C3B8174C0A82EFBDF737222899"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to procure a covered unmanned aircraft system that is manufactured or assembled by a covered foreign entity; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9CE8B28C5173406BA6F94B7BFF70778F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in connection with the operation of such a drone or unmanned aircraft system.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HEDD867A274DC47F389366BAE7F05EE31"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security, the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Defense, and the Attorney General are exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the procurement or operation is required in the national interest of the United States and—</text> <paragraph id="H56DD487AC5B140A581B2C801BBA49AFF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is for the sole purposes of research, evaluation, training, testing, or analysis for electronic warfare, information warfare operations, cybersecurity, or development of unmanned aircraft system or counter-unmanned aircraft system technology;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD448695B674B419381E1418EEA522DA8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is for the sole purposes of conducting counterterrorism or counterintelligence activities, protective missions, or Federal criminal or national security investigations, including forensic examinations, or for electronic warfare, information warfare operations, cybersecurity, or development of an unmanned aircraft system or counter-unmanned aircraft system technology; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBA47CB398C744002A1F31AF15A56D4D7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is an unmanned aircraft system that, as procured or as modified after procurement but before operational use, can no longer transfer to, or download data from, a covered foreign entity and otherwise poses no national security cybersecurity risks as determined by the exempting official.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC551A88686E2462DBD6C392609C727BC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Department of Transportation and Federal Aviation Administration exemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation is exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the operation or procurement is deemed to support the safe, secure, or efficient operation of the National Airspace System or maintenance of public safety, including activities carried out under the Federal Aviation Administration’s Alliance for System Safety of UAS through Research Excellence (ASSURE) Center of Excellence (COE) and any other activity deemed to support the safe, secure, or efficient operation of the National Airspace System or maintenance of public safety, as determined by the Secretary or the Secretary’s designee. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H6DD4BB68005C44FE9700DDE1576A56C4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration exemption</header><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, is exempt from the restriction under subsection (a) if the operation or procurement is necessary for the purpose of meeting NOAA’s science or management objectives or operational mission.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HA5FADC959F6E44A1B5C6F6704C4107F4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>The head of an executive agency may waive the prohibition under subsection (a) on a case-by-case basis—</text> <paragraph id="H775D57BE31874B53A5EEE438675F99FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with the approval of the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, after consultation with the Federal Acquisition Security Council; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H46A2DA74C8E84B4E921A84F92E545FBC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>upon notification to—</text> <subparagraph id="HB6CC743261804E47AC36C6D9576DA0AE" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HA54DD66D0E604A75B7CF448D5477BD90" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Oversight and Accountability in the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H40B84E092146451AAA49622DEB2873C4"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other appropriate congressional committees of jurisdiction.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H4329FDFC4B054A8C982DD6D892096ED1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Acquisition Regulatory Council shall prescribe regulations or guidance, as necessary, to implement the requirements of this section pertaining to Federal contracts.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H9EF4A761BAFF42B39C78CE4900CB2F42"><enum>6.</enum><header>Prohibition on use of Government-issued Purchase Cards to purchase covered unmanned aircraft systems from covered foreign entities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Effective immediately, Government-issued Purchase Cards may not be used to procure any covered unmanned aircraft system from a covered foreign entity.</text></section>
<section id="HC7430BACBE0C4610AB2DF210CB819F1B"><enum>7.</enum><header>Management of existing inventories of covered unmanned aircraft systems from covered foreign entities</header>
<subsection id="H8D070FA8A56944A5BB0B453EE9ED4972"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>All executive agencies must account for existing inventories of covered unmanned aircraft systems manufactured or assembled by a covered foreign entity in their personal property accounting systems, within one year of the date of enactment of this Act, regardless of the original procurement cost, or the purpose of procurement due to the special monitoring and accounting measures necessary to track the items’ capabilities.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H20741BA12AE84DB18DEF7290804829FE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Classified tracking</header><text>Due to the sensitive nature of missions and operations conducted by the United States Government, inventory data related to covered unmanned aircraft systems manufactured or assembled by a covered foreign entity may be tracked at a classified level, as determined by the Secretary of Homeland Security or the Secretary’s designee. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="HC7328D3140C14F689693AF6A05DB0E96"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>The Department of Defense, the Department of Homeland Security, the Department of State, the Department of Justice, the Department of Transportation, and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration may exclude from the full inventory process, covered unmanned aircraft systems that are deemed expendable due to mission risk such as recovery issues, or that are one-time-use covered unmanned aircraft due to requirements and low cost.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB77626A8599944B9BB14D56E2E1684B5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Intelligence community exception</header><text>Nothing in this section shall apply to any element of the intelligence community. </text></subsection></section>
<section id="HF63C9A251E9347AF85A0EAF15DE5F871"><enum>8.</enum><header>Comptroller General report</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 275 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to Congress a report on the amount of commercial off-the-shelf drones and covered unmanned aircraft systems procured by Federal departments and agencies from covered foreign entities, except that nothing in this section shall apply to any element of the intelligence community. </text></section> <section id="H2AB6F4103B9443619463F834E7294495"><enum>9.</enum><header>Government-wide policy for procurement of unmanned aircraft systems</header> <subsection id="HCCD8C043DAA647AEB60BB24A6FC6BD3D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, in coordination with the Department of Homeland Security, Department of Transportation, the Department of Justice, the Department of State, and other Departments as determined by the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, and in consultation with the National Institute of Standards and Technology, shall establish a government-wide policy for the procurement of an unmanned aircraft system—</text>
<paragraph id="H86E5296CD5F44999BF2E1543DC7F5BC7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>for non-Department of Defense and non-intelligence community operations; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9B7A76AC4EF34914AA306675E6F1D038"><enum>(2)</enum><text>through grants and cooperative agreements entered into with non-Federal entities.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H38A05C829B1D4D6E91D66A1DF77BC1EB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information security</header><text>The policy developed under subsection (a) shall include the following specifications, which to the extent practicable, shall be based on industry standards and technical guidance from the National Institute of Standards and Technology, to address the risks associated with processing, storing, and transmitting Federal information in an unmanned aircraft system:</text> <paragraph id="HE30579DC4FD248CDB7CDCDBC9083F2B1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Protections to ensure controlled access to an unmanned aircraft system.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H87278255A42544AD8FC482FF4EDD85BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Protecting software, firmware, and hardware by ensuring changes to an unmanned aircraft system are properly managed, including by ensuring an unmanned aircraft system can be updated using a secure, controlled, and configurable mechanism.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H768BCF78B254436CA7BAE83F6E9EF9F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Cryptographically securing sensitive collected, stored, and transmitted data, including proper handling of privacy data and other controlled unclassified information.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1D8D8A938241465E9BAEE140E224FBEE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Appropriate safeguards necessary to protect sensitive information, including during and after use of an unmanned aircraft system.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFFC5B0B726924034BE8FEAE3A1A8E90F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Appropriate data security to ensure that data is not transmitted to or stored in non-approved locations.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H34BA196D28D04F6C84BB11A1E25E34BC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The ability to opt out of the uploading, downloading, or transmitting of data that is not required by law or regulation and an ability to choose with whom and where information is shared when it is required.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA718410552A84BD08B8FC621BF926C1B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The policy developed under subsection (a) shall reflect an appropriate risk-based approach to information security related to use of an unmanned aircraft system.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H8D7F6126A9A4427B9A3159327CB11D2F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Revision of acquisition regulations</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the policy required under subsection (a) is issued—</text> <paragraph id="HEBA19FCBB4484D2192ADB0677B835EE5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Federal Acquisition Regulatory Council shall revise the Federal Acquisition Regulation, as necessary, to implement the policy; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFF982F4158FB4F08853F95261EA9BE6B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any Federal department or agency or other Federal entity not subject to, or not subject solely to, the Federal Acquisition Regulation shall revise applicable policy, guidance, or regulations, as necessary, to implement the policy.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H17A2897E46474055A2D225F395CA4225"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>In developing the policy required under subsection (a), the Director of the Office of Management and Budget shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H1B793F23C6804557A92517E01292902E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>incorporate policies to implement the exemptions contained in this Act; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H846F742613754E52ACAC2163B28CF338"><enum>(2)</enum><text>incorporate an exemption to the policy in the case of a head of the procuring department or agency determining, in writing, that no product that complies with the information security requirements described in subsection (b) is capable of fulfilling mission critical performance requirements, and such determination—</text>
<subparagraph id="H086470FB306B4F73A5EA6610EAC4E12B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may not be delegated below the level of the Deputy Secretary, or Administrator, of the procuring department or agency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE0B20345BEE440B0A13325799F72575D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall specify—</text>
<clause id="HFDC5C990C8A64C7387F67A693A2EF555"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the quantity of end items to which the waiver applies and the procurement value of those items; and</text></clause> <clause id="H28A3B559F9564EB98C4014123937F32F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the time period over which the waiver applies, which shall not exceed three years;</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H10C40A6FA7F54719AD34FBBFFE9AD7A6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall be reported to the Office of Management and Budget following issuance of such a determination; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H321A69259CA4401BA98B10D7B549DF84"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 30 days after the date on which the determination is made, shall be provided to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HCAABFA364B6F4A02AB0545719A7B69E5"><enum>10.</enum><header>State, local, and territorial law enforcement and emergency service exemption</header>
<subsection id="H029859A778DC41BE87B79F090AA8AE6C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall prevent a State, local, or territorial law enforcement or emergency service agency from procuring or operating a covered unmanned aircraft system purchased with non-Federal dollars.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC7844F50AD1E46109235634BBE51B461"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Continuity of arrangements</header><text>The Federal Government may continue entering into contracts, grants, and cooperative agreements or other Federal funding instruments with State, local, or territorial law enforcement or emergency service agencies under which a covered unmanned aircraft system will be purchased or operated if the agency has received approval or waiver to purchase or operate a covered unmanned aircraft system pursuant to section 1095.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="HBBBDF6AFBA084F4D8FC5DD53FCECD97F"><enum>11.</enum><header>Study</header>
<subsection id="HE2FB163BEBBC4234AE31FFE7A51E6998"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study on the Supply Chain for Unmanned Aircraft Systems and Components</header>
<paragraph id="H977C2BF83F7148E0851CE6171F04603C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment shall provide to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the supply chain for covered unmanned aircraft systems, including a discussion of current and projected future demand for covered unmanned aircraft systems.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7FACA37F9FB54207B884C128C647645A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The report under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="HA90465BD0DC241EC9ECED25C8656C84E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A description of the current and future global and domestic market for covered unmanned aircraft systems that are not widely commercially available except from a covered foreign entity.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0C3A2DCC0B1D4206A4660218E40F7131"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the sustainability, availability, cost, and quality of secure sources of covered unmanned aircraft systems domestically and from sources in allied and partner countries.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HAB05A59C0CFA44BDB3B53ED0FC8512DA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The plan of the Secretary of Defense to address any gaps or deficiencies identified in subparagraph (B), including through the use of funds available under the Defense Production Act of 1950 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/4501">50 U.S.C. 4501 et seq.</external-xref>) and partnerships with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and other interested persons.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8C1B9C1CE4BE422EA3E76F605AE0A3B9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Such other information as the Under Secretary of Defense for Acquisition and Sustainment determines to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE58C4D929CE24A50864152E8125DFBDA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means:</text> <subparagraph id="H0298EDC646A34C339BD68289E607395C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9D47D28AC5474F86A04BD7400A43B745" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H14561C8BCC9F4783A3CD056B9B5F5660" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HABE991B54B844F3AA00857AD9D1EBB59"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H5B3D7E0E3A684119B4C496430067D96C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives. </text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H511FC0FE20C3447FB3382D21F59B9044"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7F8FF3A0820E47738F336A72410A2BD3"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section commented="no" id="H4B253CECEEAC42D7B524A8CB2AB33F7B"><enum>12.</enum><header>Exceptions</header>
<subsection commented="no" id="HB5E33B34F4674068893B340B2873EA2A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Exception for wildfire management operations and search and rescue operations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The appropriate Federal agencies, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, are exempt from the procurement and operation restrictions under sections 3, 4, and 5 to the extent the procurement or operation is necessary for the purpose of supporting the full range of wildfire management operations or search and rescue operations. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H0DEDFCC0CAD645EC98A95D425837F31D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception for intelligence activities</header><text>Sections 3, 4, and 5 shall not apply to any activity subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>), any authorized intelligence activities of the United States, or any activity or procurement that supports an authorized intelligence activity.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HABB51F2B4CDF4C4B9E646145F9A62544"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exception for Tribal law enforcement or emergency service agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tribal law enforcement or Tribal emergency service agencies, in consultation with the Secretary of Homeland Security, are exempt from the procurement, operation, and purchase restrictions under sections 3, 4, and 5 to the extent the procurement or operation is necessary for the purpose of supporting the full range of law enforcement operations or search and rescue operations on Indian lands. </text></subsection></section> <section id="H2272358F78044A2AB0CCD1E749F33D95" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>13.</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Sections 3, 4, and 5 shall cease to have effect on the date that is five years after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


