<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8AF2220B3F3143A193B6E67294EE8C7B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3137 IH: American Isotope Security Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3137</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230509">May 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Energy to submit a report on radioactive isotope dependency and how advanced nuclear reactors can reduce such dependency.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF21C12422AFD4DBA909EC7F43430F096" style="OLC"><section id="H831BC4419F0948D18A8E1A9AEECB5866" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Isotope Security Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9B63B66F07F24A96BA81A89D76BB638F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on radioactive isotopes</header><subsection id="H5B1545F713EA4A4F9087B82967A8289C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate, and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report on radioactive isotopes that includes—</text><paragraph id="H6A49E9B7AD414FB7A062FD6268709CC7"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of each radioactive isotope that can only be produced by a foreign government or foreign non-government person determined to be a foreign adversary under section 7.4 of title 15, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor regulation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H464AD52EFD41417792A57BBAECE23B2E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of each radioactive isotope listed under paragraph (1), including how such radioactive isotope is produced and the potential uses of such radioactive isotope;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FB486D348AE4E7EAB13BEC0EABB36DC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an examination of how reliance on any radioactive isotope listed under paragraph (1) may impact the national security of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43339FD07C6E458A8B3CB345ABF451DE"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">policy recommendations for bolstering production of radioactive isotopes in the United States, including recommendations relating to the advancement of advanced nuclear reactors and other technologies, including spent nuclear fuel recycling technologies, that may increase the potential to produce radioactive isotopes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2D8E018CC46A41AB9F329B8EE7F4EEB0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>radioactive isotope</term> means any—</text><paragraph id="H9FF37161A63C484CAD99CF73A0F2909D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>critical radioactive and stable isotope (as defined in section 311(a) of the Department of Energy Research and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18649">42 U.S.C. 18649(a)</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD04642DEA074AF685ECF11E7AB431AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>medical isotope (as defined in section 134 of the Atomic Energy Act of 1954 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/2160d">42 U.S.C. 2160d</external-xref>)). </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

