<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAD1B5F1BDF024888B6DED7D459BA2DA8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 371 IH: Defund Planned Parenthood Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 371</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230117">January 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000470">Mrs. Fischbach</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001039">Mrs. Cammack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001052">Mr. Harris</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001116">Mr. Clyde</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000612">Mr. Rose</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001115">Mr. Cloud</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001306">Mr. Balderson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000055">Mr. Aderholt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000798">Mr. Walberg</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000809">Mr. Womack</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001054">Mr. Carl</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000388">Mr. Kelly of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000189">Mr. Newhouse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000585">Mr. LaHood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000372">Mr. Allen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000609">Mr. Palmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001291">Mr. Babin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001199">Mr. Smucker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001093">Mrs. Houchin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000134">Ms. Van Duyne</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for a moratorium on Federal funding to Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5A915A8A9B8F4612A7557A0C8F98C446" style="OLC"><section id="HBFA3982C79E3419BBDE0C36347490FFE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Defund Planned Parenthood Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF8718AE3BDCB40098961A7B4B2E983A5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HE7F9605641894706BD29BDEFE0A7F98B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>State and county health departments, community health centers, hospitals, physicians offices, and other entities currently provide, and will continue to provide, health services to women. Such health services include relevant diagnostic laboratory and radiology services, well-child care, prenatal and postpartum care, immunization, family planning services (including contraception), cervical and breast cancer screenings and referrals, and sexually transmitted disease testing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H852BFF7B610E45148F2C13CEBFCF2C1D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Many such entities provide services to all persons, regardless of the person’s ability to pay, and provide services in medically underserved areas and to medically underserved populations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4183FB52DF146BD917018349E6B0C3F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All funds that are no longer available to Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc., and its affiliates and clinics pursuant to this Act will continue to be made available to other eligible entities to provide women’s health care services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0182A6A5E2BC47CD97C727514F956120"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Funds authorized to be appropriated, and appropriated, by section 4 are offset by the funding limitation under section 3(a).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H086A2DB7F5A44543A9FBCAE177F9FD86"><enum>3.</enum><header>Moratorium on Federal funding to Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc</header><subsection id="H8A14EA7AABD846E699FE05BF04208EBE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the one-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, subject to subsection (b), no funds authorized or appropriated by Federal law may be made available for any purpose to Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc., or any affiliate or clinic of Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc., unless such entities certify that Planned Parenthood Federation of America affiliates and clinics will not perform, and will not provide any funds to any other entity that performs, an abortion during such period.</text></subsection><subsection id="H41F8F066422042EF91BB7EBD4490350F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to an abortion—</text><paragraph id="H52FA3348327142059EA46103E234B111"><enum>(1)</enum><text>if the pregnancy is the result of an act of rape or incest; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FBBB61547204C8DB8F8FCD23FA818A0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case where a woman suffers from a physical disorder, physical injury, or physical illness that would, as certified by a physician, place the woman in danger of death unless an abortion is performed, including a life-endangering physical condition caused by or arising from the pregnancy itself.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D8FCB432C1B4BC28CEF57DD9CBECDE1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Repayment</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of Agriculture shall seek repayment of any Federal assistance received by Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc., or any affiliate or clinic of Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc., if it violates the terms of the certification required by subsection (a) during the period specified in subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><section id="H5216FD59194C4C33B38DA3994AC6772A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Funding for community health center program</header><subsection id="H001306F0B4BE4F238CD258DDA6E49D3F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated, and appropriated, $235,000,000 for the community health center program under section 330 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/254b">42 U.S.C. 254b</external-xref>), in addition to any other funds made available to such program, for the period for which the funding limitation under section 3(a) applies.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC53495A3D6EA411CBD24AF433D671894"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds authorized or appropriated pursuant to subsection (a) may be expended for an abortion other than as described in section 3(b).</text></subsection></section><section id="HA0D24758B03742168DAC86B4982680D3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act shall be construed to reduce overall Federal funding available in support of women’s health.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

