<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF4AC837D70B647708C2477CF962FAEF4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2789 IH: American Cooperation with Our Neighbors Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2789</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to develop a strategy on efforts to strengthen subnational cooperation between the United States and Mexico, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7A51FB1E76BB4720A7E5559A162038E0" style="OLC"><section id="HABAB098A0EA4436187E1570E0F390067" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Cooperation with Our Neighbors Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7175BFD6ED164D0DA7EA1B902D372103" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Subnational Cooperation Strategy</header><subsection id="H19C35B5E30044F46A682BFDBABC262DE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State, in coordination with the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a strategy on efforts to strengthen subnational cooperation between the United States and Mexico for the purposes of—</text><paragraph id="H35F200497B8B40139761C0ACB9B26DD0"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enhancing law enforcement cooperation at a subnational level for the purpose of curbing fentanyl trafficking and other synthetic opioids, including activities such as—</text><subparagraph id="HA399AE71AE9842FFB7FE63BFF9E107A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">bolstering technical assistance for law enforcement agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H55D3F203078C4EC4BEF9358BFF189076"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">carrying out exchange programs for the purposes of professional development; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A39503EF91D4FDDB9273E032CD007B7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enhancing data sharing, as appropriate;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD861E95F58E04A65B42BFC235DCB6A40"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">bolstering subnational dialogue between local governments, civil society, faith-based organizations, and business community leaders and integrating issues faced by local communities, including with respect to trafficking of fentanyl and other synthetic opioids; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1476FAD5CBDC495D8668023DDE425BF2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strengthening capacity building and provide resources for border towns and organizations within those towns that attempt to meet the needs of local communities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1165A0410317437F81141BC74E35ED18"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Update</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of the submission of the strategy under subsection (a), the President shall submit to the congressional committees specified in subsection (a) an update containing an assessment of the implementation and effectiveness of the strategy, lessons learned from the past year with respect to the strategy, and planned changes to the strategy.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA5A1B1C9DFAD4B76AD858902F0311A59"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The strategy under subsection (a), and the update under subsection (b), shall be submitted in unclassified form.</text></subsection></section><section id="HDE47350229274B0A98CC34173719F92F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Low-earth orbit satellite technologies feasibility study and report</header><subsection id="H60F37AA01BDE453C91F2506BEE158D0A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Feasibility study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Commerce, the Administrator of the United States Agency for International Development, the Director of the United States Trade and Development Agency, and the heads of other Federal agencies as appropriate, shall conduct a feasibility study for the countries of Mexico, Central America, and the Caribbean on the possibility of low-Earth orbit satellites, high altitude platforms systems, or other trusted space-based telecommunications technologies to—</text><paragraph id="H31464AE12BC945028A44A10BD0BD83E4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide broadband connection to remote areas that lack access to network service;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H595092CB84DC47348A1D7D5C81C9BEE1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide mobile and internet services without the use of untrusted telecommunications equipment or services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37FB1FE881A549B182656D4AE1A96F94"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide uncensored internet access to the people of such countries the governments of which use firewalls to prevent their populations from freely accessing information.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF65DB70FE54547AF8551D5246F091D08"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the completion of the feasibility study under subsection (a), the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the results of the feasibility study under subsection (a) that includes an analysis of the—</text><paragraph id="H69F8B5A5BFF94553B0769A17C300A0AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">scalability of the implementation of the technologies described in subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DB771E35A644F208EBC42EB8E68404A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">economic viability of using space-based technologies to reach remote areas, including the cost of space-enabled broadband service per newly connected person;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5FD4052549245AF9772181E023D35CB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>feasibility of using such technologies to limit or phase out the use of untrusted telecommunications equipment or services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7483F0BCF0C4546A3F25E330106FAAA"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">capability of satellite internet technologies to provide uncensored internet to people in countries where open internet access is forbidden or curtailed.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF6C54995073047C588198F7307B27A98"><enum>4.</enum><header>Department of State review of access to finance in the countries of the Caribbean</header><subsection id="H5C70FAF7FD59435E9F5AF9F77E5302E8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State, in consultation with the Secretary of Treasury, shall conduct a review to determine any steps, balancing costs and benefits, that the Secretaries could take to expand financial access to the countries of the Caribbean, including through a review of—</text><paragraph id="HD2E96C003129408FB5AA6B51F40AF65E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sanctions enforcement laws and compliance standards;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08B03E2149354E19BF99E4C76A8F6F54"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reporting requirements pertaining to narcotics trafficking and illicit finance thereof;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBC8186CC512482EA8567453F670A5CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">possible expansion of embassies and consulates in the region; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54FD518061FF4CE4911A2D595273ABB7"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">programming or lack thereof pertaining to access to capital in the region.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H119CE26E86C2492EAB496D61469D6AF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the findings of the Secretary pertaining to the review under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H0E01D4EFE2B94FACB1E49F3CF6DB8C7D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H43424844844740E7BF3E47285CB679FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED471F58C6CD4A009942D54A5DD4347F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

