<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB9B56244A8B945F08A4E109846E48076" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 940 IH: Information Security Investment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 940</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001224">Mr. Moran</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require each Member of Congress and the President and Vice President to complete a program of training in handling and safeguarding classified information, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H348903B6C99A4B4E883120A2B5C7EC89" style="OLC"><section id="H52FC8BE442B9464DA913233CDEBEC7B2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Information Security Investment Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H71F0A4735CFC470AAB20DAE43081427B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Mandatory completion of classified information training for Members of Congress</header><subsection id="HE75E9B4B43BF46F389C3D37D49CE8378"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate shall issue regulations to require each Member of the House of Representatives and each Member of the Senate, respectively, to complete a program of training in handling and safeguarding classified information during each Congress.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2D3B087666E8493AAE66B78BD1741FB6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline</header><paragraph id="H521FF7DCDDC54B6FAAC41FCB5FEA08C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the regulations issued by the Committee on House Administration of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Rules and Administration of the Senate under <internal-xref idref="HE75E9B4B43BF46F389C3D37D49CE8378" legis-path="1.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>, an individual shall complete the program of training required under such subsection and file a certificate of completion of such training—</text><subparagraph id="H5A542E6366554B1BAD606AF7066A59A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an individual who is serving as a Member of the House of Representatives or the Senate as of the date of the first day of the first session of a Congress, not later than 90 days after such date; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13AC73D7DA144F0DB5FA24835D067862"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any other individual, not later than 90 days after the date the individual first becomes a Member of the House of Representatives or the Senate during a Congress.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6C599EC484C462699F4FBDFA5F76319"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Special rule for first session of One Hundred Eighteenth Congress</header><text>In the case of the first session of the One Hundred Eighteenth Congress, an individual described in subparagraph (A) of paragraph (1) shall complete the program of training required under <internal-xref idref="HE75E9B4B43BF46F389C3D37D49CE8378" legis-path="1.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4FCB7C162DE7448EBD0E874ED6C053B5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Member of the House of Representatives defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>Member of the House of Representatives</term> includes a Delegate or Resident Commissioner to the Congress. </text></subsection><subsection id="H809DB37D02BA4B9D83084AC36083F151" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exercise of rulemaking powers</header><text>The provisions of this section are enacted by the Congress—</text><paragraph id="HC4D8C92904C94EF1A599D3A948E062D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>as an exercise of the rulemaking power of the House of Representatives and the Senate, respectively, and as such they shall be considered as part of the rules of each House, respectively, or of that House to which they specifically apply, and such rules shall supersede other rules only to the extent that they are inconsistent therewith; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FB56DD5F76247148A096DD7E0E24E1D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with full recognition of the constitutional right of either House to change such rules (so far as relating to such House) at any time, in the same manner, and to the same extent as in the case of any other rule of such House.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9F3DD24570FB42D7A04C7CDB7273C99B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Mandatory completion of classified information training for President and Vice President</header><subsection id="HC9970B1250FA40B1B4A25A60E74CF95E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Personnel Management shall designate an appropriate agency or department of the Federal Government to develop and provide a program of training in handling and safeguarding classified information to the President and Vice President.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC244C6E714944C069B3D3FCB848CE106"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline</header><paragraph id="HA8B0C6FF12EF445EA0B0A0E4A89D049C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President and Vice President shall each complete the program of training described in <internal-xref idref="HC9970B1250FA40B1B4A25A60E74CF95E" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref> not later than 30 days after the date each such individual begins serving a term as President or Vice President, and every two years thereafter while each such individual continues to serve as President or Vice President.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC93A76248FC4316A9387C95A97E0C70"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Special rule for first training</header><text>The President and Vice President shall each, not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, complete the program of training described in <internal-xref idref="HC9970B1250FA40B1B4A25A60E74CF95E" legis-path="2.(a)">subsection (a)</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

