<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6F7CA7067F5B4E2A885416DCC99FA60E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3987 IH: Leveraging Quantum Computing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3987</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for enhanced use of quantum computing, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6A4D33A5C7C84DA39FFDCC93159E4A9F" style="OLC"><section id="HBE94A01C82094B0DBF88B6FE2AF1DC57" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Leveraging Quantum Computing Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC1AB43784617451FBB2E426A78F70EAA"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Quantum Coordination Office activities</header><subsection id="H8FCF190515DF4B448618CDD90723CB95"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Quantum use cases</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Quantum Coordination Office of the Office of Science and Technology Policy shall establish a program of engagement with Federal agencies to identify potential use cases with respect to which quantum computing could advance the missions of such agencies, including through on-premises, cloud-based, hybrid, or networked approaches.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAB5A11E04B094B43A809176098DCE865"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Quantum on-Ramp</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For each potential use case identified pursuant to subsection (a), the Director of the National Quantum Coordination Office, in consultation with the head of the relevant Federal agency and, if appropriate, the appropriate officer, official, or other employee of the relevant private sector entity, shall develop a plan to enable such agency to address each such potential use case.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCCEFC7803B194852837C21BF045DA242"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Quantum Coordination Office shall annually submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report regarding the Office’s progress in carrying out the activities under this section, including information relating to the following:</text><paragraph id="H13C04936A47F4594B1C8B6EDBF8DE91E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The extent and nature of the Office’s outreach activities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H760D2FD8A19B49F4B4DAA2AD29CE1BF5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The potential use cases identified pursuant to subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B56377FA6FE484DB481255D7F9CAA30"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The status of plans to address such potential use cases, including through acquisition or lease of quantum computers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6FB69C2E1C1471685C00BBEE95CFD7F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any obstacles to addressing such potential use cases, including lack of funding.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

