<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9D171AA206204C2DAB032CA12BFDC0ED" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2955 IH: Stop Institutional Child Abuse Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2955</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230427">April 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To study and prevent child abuse in youth residential programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6A1114D5D4524325B05309FD9AEBDB9A" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H71A25A0484AB459280A40C05ED38B42D"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Institutional Child Abuse Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1001878DFC3745F08EB60E99D440EA72"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improving national data collection and reporting for youth in youth residential programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title V of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290aa">42 U.S.C. 290aa et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after part I (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290jj">42 U.S.C. 290jj et seq.</external-xref>) the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23913E6ABBE04D03BA1C5E27C8C05A29"><part id="HF50F1CA1C6C245419D56FF5DC867356D"><enum>J</enum><header>Improving national data collection and reporting for youth in youth residential programs</header><section id="H8C0A311778A6410DA6DA0AC02072C4B6"><enum>596.</enum><header>Federal Work Group on Youth Residential Programs</header><subsection id="H209653A8E9284ED2B12342696F418BF3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish the Federal Work Group on Youth Residential Programs (referred to in this section as the <quote>Work Group</quote>) to improve the dissemination and implementation of best practices regarding the health and safety (including with respect to the use of seclusion and restraints), care, treatment, and appropriate placement of youth in youth residential programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="H744DF48E26A74A8F9CC48CE378031D1F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Composition</header><paragraph id="H8F5409402E58406FAAF94DEF7EEA8C0E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall appoint 9 representatives to the Work Group from the Administration for Children and Families, the Administration for Community Living, the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration, the Department of Education, the Department of Justice, the Indian Health Service, and the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5336C61E2C16480E94D7261FF4FB4827"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other Federal agencies</header><text>The Work Group may include representatives from other Federal agencies, as the Secretary determines appropriate, appointed by the head of the relevant agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE13C883DEDDA483197343A832A359D58"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out the duties described in subsection (d), the Work Group shall consult with—</text><paragraph id="HC22CED36623E4D05BEFCF3C0829998F8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>child advocates, including attorneys experienced in working with youth overrepresented in the child welfare system or the juvenile justice system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A349602231149EAB4BFF97C3435FF36"><enum>(2)</enum><text>health professionals, including mental health and substance use disorder professionals, nurses, physicians, social workers and other health care providers who provide services to youth who may be served by residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91DEB5455FE6449A8E3A5722D8F28E24"><enum>(3)</enum><text>protection and advocacy systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92061E3B37B34DA4998C392BE181BCA9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>individuals experienced in working with youth with disabilities, including emotional, mental health, and substance use disorders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48A58DCDAB884D56A0E76B7B44541CB9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>individuals with lived experience as children and youth in youth residential programs, including individuals with intellectual or developmental disabilities and individuals with emotional, mental health, or substance use disorders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7FDE67F564844E25988AB1CF4C69FFA1"><enum>(6)</enum><text>representatives of State and local child protective services agencies and other relevant public agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8228EDC2F5541238EF3937862A50105"><enum>(7)</enum><text>parents or guardians of children and youth with emotional, mental health, or substance use disorder needs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABEB3F6BA4484D61856A7321AE6017EF"><enum>(8)</enum><text>experts on issues related to child abuse and neglect in youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H843E0D2EF4F340D3A214035BD1DB0169"><enum>(9)</enum><text>administrators of youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85F15508390E42DB888EA2B21342A589"><enum>(10)</enum><text>education professionals who provide services to youth in youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H377A087B0FCA45319CF535A7C9932654"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Indian Tribes and Tribal organizations; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD0148F7950B4C669E070E770D5EE839"><enum>(12)</enum><text>State legislators;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD32E6E99C9064C428E281360B1F9934C"><enum>(13)</enum><text>State licensing agencies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F7AFF0342E943E6A031D152BD898EEF"><enum>(14)</enum><text>others, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA0B11B9826304B0AB4233CBB5D7F13BE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Work Group shall—</text><paragraph id="HE4EDFC71B6BC48438416693BDE463D1D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop and publish recommendations regarding a national database that aggregates data, including process-oriented data such as length of stay and use of restraints, and seclusion and outcome-oriented data such as discharge setting and ability to be safety maintained in school and community at least 6-months after discharge;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BE677E29736449AB5A0267AAC88081D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>beginning not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Stop Institutional Child Abuse Act</short-title>, and every 2 years thereafter, submit to the Secretary and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions and the Committee on Finance of the Senate, and the Committee on Education and the Workforce, the Committee on Energy and Commerce, and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives, a report containing policy recommendations designed to—</text><subparagraph id="HDB75BB2CE0CC40C7B8FF93E1F23CF839"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improve the coordination of the dissemination and implementation of best practices regarding the health and safety (including use of seclusion and restraints), care, treatment, and appropriate placement of youth in youth residential programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H720E27EE76CF44D592C34F4B9B0F871D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>promote the coordination of the dissemination and implementation of best practices regarding the care and treatment of youth in youth residential programs among State child welfare agencies, State Medicaid agencies, and State mental and behavioral health agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB95C9AD69D9742ADADC0BE0A39D49823"><enum>(C)</enum><text>promote the adoption and implementation of best practices regarding the care and treatment of youth in youth residential programs among child welfare systems, licensing agencies, accreditation organizations, and other relevant monitoring and enforcement entities;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5738D172BC9A4649A1B1C2D86EB6528F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop and utilize risk assessment tools, including projects that provide for the development of research-based strategies for risk assessments relating to the health, safety (including with respect to the use of seclusion and restraints), and well-being of youth in youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D25D555C5A34C77A3C0D042A487AD72"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support the development and implementation of education and training resources for professional and paraprofessional personnel in the fields of health care, law enforcement, judiciary, social work, child protection (including the prevention, identification, and treatment of child abuse and neglect), education, child care, and other relevant fields, and individuals such as court appointed special advocates and guardians ad litem, including education and training resources regarding—</text><subparagraph id="H214CE3D1260141CF9E0CDA7853073166"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the unique needs, experiences, and outcomes of youth overrepresented in youth residential programs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF21E872D3E9540C9AEE008E471438491"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the enhancement of interagency communication among child protective service agencies, protection and advocacy systems, State licensing agencies, State Medicaid agencies, and accreditation agencies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H41D2C94C450547C6923E7014C5BCEE1C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>best practices to eliminate the usage of physical, mechanical, and chemical restraint and seclusion, and to promote the use of positive behavioral interventions and supports, culturally and linguistically sensitive services, mental health supports, trauma- and grief-informed care, and crisis de-escalation interventions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H153AB7E6F45949979D97ECC12059F171"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the legal duties of such professional and paraprofessional personnel and youth residential program personnel and the responsibilities of such professionals and personnel to protect the legal rights of children in youth residential programs, consistent with applicable State and Federal law;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFF03A749EB841529901049AF01A980F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>improve accessibility and development of community-based alternatives to youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H219A1E6AD73C4AE58947528D03928F68"><enum>(6)</enum><text>provide recommendations for innovative programs designed to provide community support and resources to at-risk youth, including programs that—</text><subparagraph id="HFE93486D13D246EE90E3DFFEBAF93B90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>support continuity of education, including removing barriers to access;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1F7D309D2A944AB5938A93D2D5EC8375"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide mentorship;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE647B26B65A43EDBD58AA17FE820A12"><enum>(C)</enum><text>support the provision of crisis intervention services and in-home or outpatient mental health and substance use disorder treatment; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C8468D413544DB6B75B2649E84FC529"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide other resources to families and parents or guardians that assist in preventing the need for out-of-home placement of youth in youth residential programs;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6A37778B5D94DBBA21FD6FE279FC2F7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>perform other activities, such as activities relating to development, dissemination, outreach, engagement, or training associated with advancing least-restrictive, evidence-based, trauma and grief-informed, and developmentally and culturally competent care for youth in youth residential programs and youth at risk of being placed in such programs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB9BA95A191A24F789EF18460A5ED0F62"><enum>(8)</enum><text>provide recommendations on best practices to convey Work Group recommendations to States. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB5A4C0AE4E544B08A93FC615EAE37F9E"><enum>596A.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part:</text><paragraph id="H3FAABD92EE5F4AF1B544E2C775A33F79"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Child abuse or neglect</header><text>The term <term>child abuse or neglect</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3 of the Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91019DD3C84A4D57BA5354C4B549E46F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Culturally competent</header><text>The term <term>culturally competent</term> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H486D5BAD99034A03B8AE12C2DE315C86"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Indian Tribe; Tribal organization</header><text>The terms <term>Indian Tribe</term> and <term>Tribal organization</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H04628E92EC92466E82B8B7ECA5431D6B"><enum>(4)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Protection and advocacy systems</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>protection and advocacy system</term> means a system established by a State or Indian Tribe under section 143 of the Developmental Disabilities Assistance and Bill of Rights Act of 2000. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA14AA887385A48DBBD6C29605ACA9798"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2F3691B614A48F8A9B3E4BAAEF25BCA"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Youth</header><text>The term <term>youth</term> means an individual who has not attained the age of 22.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FDC344868024C26B6BE172667E0F546"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Youth residential program</header><subparagraph id="HDEDDE29985F8435D919B78DC7A48CDC3"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>youth residential program</term> means each location of a facility or program operated by a public or private entity that, with respect to one or more youth who are unrelated to the owner or operator of the facility or program—</text><clause id="H0033FEEC1A1E4FDE9675534E5B5933A0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provides a residential environment, such as—</text><subclause id="HE0E5758538B34ADBBAF9DBFB4E51AFB7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a program with a wilderness or outdoor experience, expedition, or intervention;</text></subclause><subclause id="HCAC0507AB89C487A9D97B92B14D3E0F0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a boot camp experience or other experience designed to simulate characteristics of basic military training or correctional regimes;</text></subclause><subclause id="H51A949E744774F4396297628DD46DFF7"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an education or therapeutic boarding school;</text></subclause><subclause id="H0A54C1ADB16641E2A412678149D6A3A9"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>a behavioral modification program;</text></subclause><subclause id="H5E452B4111154D34A96157461D45AD16"><enum>(V)</enum><text>a residential treatment center or facility; </text></subclause><subclause id="HE8FBF941E0D846AA8808778076A1E7CF"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>a qualified residential treatment program (as defined in section 472(k)(4) of the Social Security Act); </text></subclause><subclause id="H99B83B256F2E436691503101FF26D004"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>a psychiatric residential treatment program that meets the requirements of subpart D of part 441 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulations); </text></subclause><subclause id="HC12AFB0A526D4C2692230ED6CF86B30A"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>a group home serving children and youth placed by any placing authority; </text></subclause><subclause id="H8F7F651C3F5945078A88F411A851C52F"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>an intermediate care facility for individuals with intellectual disabilities; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H3DC6988D2BC74D7AB84A3884840BA5DF"><enum>(X)</enum><text>any residential program that is utilized as an alternative to incarceration for justice involved youth, adjudicated youth, or youth deemed delinquent; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HEAC3A411A9134383A10AFC75F2ED7155"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>serves youth who have a history or diagnosis of—</text><subclause id="HF09FD3D4A23748E4A9AD6CA4D904F1AF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an emotional, behavioral, or mental health disorder;</text></subclause><subclause id="H959ECB1160D64B3D90116E463D3BC806"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a substance misuse or use disorder, including alcohol misuse or use disorders; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H07495AE0B65A4ACD8EB221E2D377A5A0"><enum>(III)</enum><text>an intellectual, developmental, physical, or sensory disability.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF870567B9E164157BEF9F952E3FF1389"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>The term <term>youth residential program</term> does not include— </text><clause commented="no" id="H56FEC7B7FE9E4AA49C9694E5EA09A664"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a hospital licensed by the State; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H93A53E432DB047E89D378BEFB8BAC3C6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a foster family home that provides 24-hour substitute care for children placed away from their parents or guardians and for whom the State child welfare services agency has placement and care responsibility and that is licensed and regulated by the State as a foster family home.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section commented="no" id="HEFAFBD6E3B944CF49A79680FBF9AED84"><enum>3.</enum><header>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine Study</header><subsection commented="no" id="H13C1E16293644ECA9345878EEABEFB86"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 45 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall seek to enter into a contract with the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (referred to in this section as the <quote>National Academies</quote>) to conduct a study to examine the state of youth in youth residential programs and make recommendations.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H1B09C226D4E44EB0B23443E4A5DF511D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study components</header><text>Pursuant to the contract under subsection (a), the National Academies shall, not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Stop Institutional Child Abuse Act</short-title>, issue a report informed by the study conducted under such subsection that includes—</text><paragraph id="HBA944E4BBD6B4A1B93C326EF10B70903"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identification of all Federal and State funding sources for youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H63ABB1C2FE1D41C39E2E5FC8C96F641D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identification of Federal data collection sources on youth in youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57F5663CFA8345AD98AB6BEB17B7AF0A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identification of existing Federal and State regulation of youth residential programs, including alternative licensing standards or licensing exemptions for youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0CC5332C84E64F98BFDAD7B6735FE930"><enum>(4)</enum><text>identification of existing standards of care of national accreditation entities that provide accreditation or certification of youth residential programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2B87E42CD5440CB80EF8732777F940B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>identification of existing barriers in Federal and State policy for blending and braiding of Federal and State funding sources to serve youth in community-based settings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1A9E686CC024976896D53619385DAF5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>recommendations for coordination by Federal and State agencies of data on youth in youth residential programs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2ACDC0B561D4E03BB4B81665867DC6D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>recommendations for the improvement of Federal and State oversight of youth residential programs receiving Federal funding.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBB0DC3AFF0174D05A062A90C6441D181"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>youth residential program</term> has the meaning given such term in section 596A of the Public Health Service Act, as added by section 2.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

