<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC7C4AEE18C3E4DEC81438C110660C63A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2816 IH: Pharmacy Benefit Manager Sunshine and Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2816</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XI of the Social Security Act to strengthen transparency requirements with respect to pharmacy benefit managers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEA4D6620AC984F09A7FEA3DC936D1ADC" style="OLC"><section id="H81BC9DF01F3E4CB294EC4B74EAF52E62" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pharmacy Benefit Manager Sunshine and Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3D9A09C15D8D442CA9997FB799E3A3CE" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strengthening pharmacy benefit manager transparency requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1150A of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-23">42 U.S.C. 1320b–23</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7E8695F0B16842E890D0E836A8C59087"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H802612B890C54265A55541ADF7E59DD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC83644DA09D4B60B66E7FC26304D663"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking the comma at the end and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H05E3460C03B64E2682D01ED65D1086DB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H09F0DF4CCC3545CDB25237C94FE594F8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H1F7DD3D95EAB42E7AA42826E1621128B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a group health plan or health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage (as such terms are defined in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act),</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC52676D4F05647D99C3CD78B5ECFD0AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by amending subsection (b) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB9B982415EEF4F06B68189265A3C6D01" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H66BADD44F7CF474680A8659045F5AA08"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information described in this subsection is the following with respect to services provided by a health benefits plan or PBM for a contract year:</text><paragraph id="HCFB3FBF31FDD411AAF3516EF7BC9BA60"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a contract with each entity described in paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a), the aggregate dollar amount of all—</text><subparagraph id="H279972F5A28B44A4BAEEEF8ABC2710DC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">rebates that a PBM or health benefits plan received under each such contract from all drug manufacturers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06DB18620B7B451FA612CAE530B16985"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">administrative fees that a PBM or health benefits plan received under each such contract with from all drug manufacturers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC472E914DEC84363A8089CC3E2E3E9C7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">administrative fees that a PBM or health benefits plan received under each contract from each such entity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF972F12373744BCCB1853F5AECEACDBF"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">rebates that a PBM or health benefits plan received under each contract with each entity from all pharmaceutical manufacturers that were not passed through to such entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1BD0B3F58AE94811910727969B77DD8B"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">administrative fees that a PBM or health benefits plan received under each contract from all pharmaceutical manufacturers and did not pass through to such entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29FBF7E5FF8F4CC98A715436B0AA62FD" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">total post-claim adjudication payments that a PBM or health benefits plan collected from a pharmacy under each contract, including any fees, reimbursements, or other claw backs including generic effective rate and brand effective rate contracts; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DC6E549F89549AABFD5A00533538A16" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any post-claim adjudication payments that a PBM or health benefits plan collected from a pharmacy under each contract, including any fees, reimbursements, or other claw backs including generic effective rate and brand effective rate contracts that were not passed through to such entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5ABE929F12174B648F45B57E272A1CA1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The aggregate retained rebate percentage under each contract (that is the value in paragraph (1)(D) divided by the value in paragraph (1)(A)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC813AD6A06474D9194AA46A614F4FCEC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Across all contractual relationships for each PBM whereby such PBM is managing prescription drug coverage for a entity described in in paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a), the highest retained rebate percentage and lowest retained rebate percentage for each contract under which such PBM provided services.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H70C9318B04444766911651885F23A37C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="H3BE594F2D3F44D9187C2EA6D0CD118C2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>, plan, or prices charged for drugs,</quote> and inserting <quote>or plan, the prices charged for a specific drug or classes of drugs, or the amount of any rebates provided for a specific drug or classes of drugs,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC155D8E8D45144DCBC18D6E9FFFCBD83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H18F55C99BB594129AD7E23CBE5E06204" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HEB156A32436043E7B6EEF21C6C07BD22"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out the reporting requirement under subsection (e).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE7661E5B17C4CF1BB87E8E11F21791E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsections:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBFECE34FB2D14BCFA0A4DD69AC394871" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H664255851B354D8FB34BC69C7DF3857F" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Public reporting requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the first calendar quarter following the first full plan year beginning on or after the date of enactment of this subsection, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall publish on a public website of the Department of Health and Human Services the information reported under subsection (b), in accordance with the confidentiality requirements described in subsection (c).</text></subsection><subsection id="HE8A336000C6146ED8EFA31DD0C178EDE" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H68C749E82C4F4536B4282AF3AC12E309" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Brand effective rate</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>brand effective rate</quote> means the claim reimbursement for a brand name drug, expressed as a percentage discount from the average wholesale price of such drug.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H755301E5470F4B6C93FA8CCB307B326B" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Generic effective rate</header><text>The term <quote>generic effective rate</quote> means the claim reimbursement for a generic drug, expressed as a percentage discount from the average wholesale price of such drug.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8665005AED8494FA6D8AEF7633CD10C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pharmacy benefits manager</header><text>The term <quote>pharmacy benefits manager</quote> or <quote>PBM</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HA98B330E2035485FAC13FC33B0F7CA2E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an entity that manages prescription drug benefits on behalf of an entity described in paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9CD78211FCD54B53A24580E321E96FB3" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for purposes of this section, includes any other organization that—</text><clause id="H624AC49E094246CD8BE17B18CD3C7158" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">has directly or indirectly (as determined by the Secretary in regulations), an ownership interest of 5 percent or more in the PBM;</text></clause><clause id="HC14DA0BFEE67454392EF7820BB5D83EE" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shares, or is otherwise a part of, the same organizational structure as the PBM;</text></clause><clause id="H9E214C486CE343439C384FE27DCE44BD" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">exercises operational, financial, or managerial control over the PBM or a part thereof, or provides policies or procedures for any of the operations of the PBM, or provides financial or cash management services to the PBM; or</text></clause><clause id="H5F59E0CF5C4746599FC7E1F9656453A6" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides management or administrative services, management or clinical consulting services, or accounting or financial services to the PBM.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE29BF53ABD7841EABF4FD43820577572" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Organizational structure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>organizational structure</quote> means, in the case of—</text><subparagraph id="HBE243978DCF849D18003E71E4F1D731E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a corporation, the officers, directors, and shareholders of the corporation who have an ownership interest in the corporation which is equal to or exceeds 5 percent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H603216D1915A48C688F8779B58F69A31" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a limited liability company, the members and managers of the limited liability company;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BDB0C039B714243990A13E379CD2945" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a general partnership, the partners of the general partnership;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H604BAD2D8D7A4F3C91222E4933762E97" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a limited partnership, the general partners and any limited partners of the limited partnership who have an ownership interest in the limited partnership which is equal to or exceeds 5 percent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H197CB234040147CF9F263C011CDD90CB" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a trust, the trustees of the trust; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDC229B7F30574E41A51B534C70E4047F" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other person or entity as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

