<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4C34D391231F48E78B854EDC352CFD41" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4979 IH: Fairness for Small-Scale Farmers and Ranchers Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4979</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000530">Mr. Deluzio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To regulate market concentration and competition in the food and agriculture industry, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE7A85150530C43C6BF2A7E2D646C9717" style="OLC"><section id="HCA3CF58D301D40148D0B655106985B15" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H81AC16945CAB4AB48EAE8E9AEF3D1A98"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fairness for Small-Scale Farmers and Ranchers Act</short-title></quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="HC49B0D5C33F5488392B6E7F59212A261"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" lowest-level="section" regeneration="yes-regeneration" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded"><toc-entry idref="HCA3CF58D301D40148D0B655106985B15" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HADBD343E2CAA40948FAF291E3E8C0DB8" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H85D7FC4054D74F5EB4C49B3A07C461A5" level="section">Sec. 3. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB05042FA7861400693F805AE635C9347" level="title">Title I—Moratorium on and review of large agribusiness, food and beverage manufacturing, and grocery retail mergers</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE3FAB4384AC34C25A066AD55C9882B7A" level="section">Sec. 101. Moratorium on large agribusiness, food and beverage manufacturing, and grocery retail mergers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE9A918AD17E3431A877A465959D5E212" level="section">Sec. 102. Retroactive review of large agribusiness, food and beverage manufacturing, and grocery retail mergers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF62560054524488B8925F9572398459C" level="title">Title II—Farm system reforms</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2A2B47E927DF4603A881442E1CAAD40D" level="section">Sec. 201. Local agriculture market program.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H943C6F47F941473CBAEF6565201DBB40" level="section">Sec. 202. Restoration of mandatory country of origin labeling for beef and pork; inclusion of dairy products.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H569F1A1909674E20BAAB346DF2B53156" level="section">Sec. 203. Definitions in Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8043414FD3E8473C856578255BF0231F" level="section">Sec. 204. Unlawful practices.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0FCB279494764831AF54A73292770A4F" level="section">Sec. 205. Spot market purchases of livestock by packers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H58A14F2970C24CB298EB8FBFFDA82E18" level="section">Sec. 206. Investigation of live poultry dealers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H1B2018B8F6D7438981D5A54FF268290C" level="section">Sec. 207. Ensuring fair practices in agriculture.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9F5D768B557C44A9A67A3A9951D364AE" level="section">Sec. 208. Award of attorney fees.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H12EC59DD6201457FA473F216609116AA" level="section">Sec. 209. Review and report on fragility and national security in the food system.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE2FF6E3A1EB9406B879A62F7D8013457" level="section">Sec. 210. Technical amendments.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7D46A342550240729D0E349D0632875E" level="title">Title III—Providing resources for beginning, retiring, and socially disadvantaged farmers and ranchers</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H582E3EB226FB45BF9BC8F4258EFB586D" level="section">Sec. 301. Reauthorization and increased funding for beginning, retiring, and socially disadvantaged farmers and ranchers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H5DEE67BD59F941CCB2BD9D70321BF638" level="title">Title IV—Livestock, dairy, and poultry supply chain infrastructure</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H254310AA78FF44A3B9B02107CB4331E3" level="section">Sec. 401. Livestock, dairy, and poultry supply chain infrastructure grants and loans.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8F78DF9C42994B839FB9EC8923692686" level="section">Sec. 402. Pilot program for increased accessibility to inspection and technical assistance for eligible processing facilities.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HADBD343E2CAA40948FAF291E3E8C0DB8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HB75DB16C089345CDB453000E8314D5EC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Concentration in the food and agricultural economy, including mergers, acquisitions, and other combinations and alliances among suppliers, packers, integrators, other food processors, distributors, and retailers has been accelerating at a rapid pace since the 1980s, and particularly since the 2007 through 2009 recession.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0800BD62C3148C6960D3FD6959CB8E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The trend toward greater concentration in food and agriculture has important and far reaching implications not only for family farmers, but also for food chain workers, the food we eat, the communities we live in, the integrity of the natural environment upon which we all depend, and for our collective public health.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BC94051A33640429C77CC75F4AC1CFE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The infant formula industry, for example, has reached an alarming level of corporate concentration with 4 companies now controlling nearly 90 percent of the infant formula market. A disruption in the supply of just 1 infant formula producer now presents a grave risk to infant health in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H45032573C26249629203DF689C3DD102"><enum>(4)</enum><text>In the past 4 decades, the top 4 largest pork packers have seized control of 70 percent of the market, up from 36 percent. Over the same period, the top 4 beef packers have expanded their market share from 32 percent to 85 percent. The top 4 flour millers have increased their market share from 40 percent to 64 percent. The market share of the top 4 soybean crushers has jumped from 54 percent to 79 percent, and the top 4 wet corn processors control of the market has increased from 63 percent to 86 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA8D74F00214432382FFAC4E697BACD0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Today the top 4 sheep, poultry, and fluid milk processors now control 62 percent, 54 percent, and 50 percent of the market, respectively.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75740EFC1B164EC8988690ECB5676FD2"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The top 4 grain companies today control as much as 90 percent of the global grain trade.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H068F03D5CE2F4328A11ACAA18C1F1876"><enum>(7)</enum><text>During the past 5 years there has been a wave of consolidation among global seed and crop-chemical firms, 3 companies now control nearly 2⁄3 of the world’s commodity crop seeds. Those same 3 companies now also control nearly 70 percent of all agricultural chemicals and pesticides.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H628F7C9AF60240C48369EA432CCCE23A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>In the United States, the 4 largest corn seed sellers accounted for 85 percent of the market in 2015, up from 60 percent in 2000. Over the past 20 years, the cost for an acre’s worth of seeds for an average corn farmer has nearly quadrupled, and the cost of fertilizer has more than doubled. Yet corn yields increased only 36 percent over that time, and the price received for the sale of a bushel of corn increased only 31 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACFCD8525915452C81739E3C475E3195"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A handful of firms dominate the processing of every major commodity. Many of them are vertically integrated, which means that they control successive stages of the food chain, from inputs to production to distribution. The growing number and scale of cross-border agribusiness and food mergers have put foreign firms, often with considerable government backing, into prominent and even dominant positions in the United States beef, hog, poultry, seed, fertilizer, and agrichemical sectors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1E5E8AD761B4DF795473168321DF007"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Growing concentration of the agricultural sector has restricted choices for farmers trying to sell their products. As the bargaining power of agribusiness firms over farmers increases, concentrated agricultural commodity markets are stacked against the farmer, with buyers of agricultural commodities often possessing regional dominance in the form of oligopsony or monopsony relative to sellers of such commodities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA23C613EF6C4ECEB7638BA4F81C4631"><enum>(11)</enum><text>The high concentration and consolidation of buyers in agricultural markets has resulted in the thinning of both cash and future markets, thereby allowing dominant buyers to leverage their market shares to move those markets to the detriment of family farmers and ranchers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28BD057F310D4545A3273F561CCA9417"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Buyers with oligopsonistic or monopsonistic power have incentives to engage in unfair and discriminatory acts that cause farmers to receive less than a competitive price for their goods. At the same time, some Federal courts have incorrectly required a plaintiff to show harm to competition generally, in addition to harm to the individual farmer, when making a determination that an unfair, unjustly discriminatory, deceptive, or preferential act exists under the Packers and Stockyards Act of 1921.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7661FA6B3A6744CBA69B84C924A87DCA"><enum>(13)</enum><text>The farmer’s share of every retail dollar has plummeted from 41 percent in 1950, to less than 15 percent today, while the profit share for farm input, marketing, and processing companies has risen.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4649A7DD4370433A9C678E789F6D3385"><enum>(14)</enum><text>While agribusiness conglomerates are posting record earnings, farmers are facing desperate times. Since 2013, net farm income for United States farmers has fallen by more than half and median on farm income was negative in 2020.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C4A9A96F54F4A5CB07A12EEF53C5074"><enum>(15)</enum><text>The benefits of low commodity prices are not being passed on to American consumers. The gap between what shoppers pay for food and what farmers are paid is growing wider.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D257CAC29A04AD4A2F0C4B8FCA57EAD"><enum>(16)</enum><text>The steadily rising price of food has outpaced growth in incomes for typical workers. Since the Great Recession, the annual growth of real prices for food at the supermarket have risen nearly 3 times faster than typical earnings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HABF0761DCC9F46CEB9C017EC4CF35BC8"><enum>(17)</enum><text>There is a growing consensus that economic consolidation contributes to the widening gap in economic opportunity in the United States and bigger, more dominant firms are more likely to deliver profits to investors than to raise wages or benefits. Mega-mergers in the food and agribusiness industries can lead to growing monopsony power abuse resulting in wage suppression, along with massive layoffs as companies shutter factories and facilities, harming working families and communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CB7198944984BFAABB90C0C47D6CCD7"><enum>(18)</enum><text>Concentration, low prices, anticompetitive practices, and other manipulations and abuses of the agricultural economy are driving small family farmers out of business. Farmers are going bankrupt or giving up, and few are taking their places; more farm families are having to rely on other jobs to stay afloat. Seventy-nine percent of farm household income came from off farm work in 2020, up from 53 percent in 1960.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE896D2F23053490FB78A6D57B90D57DD"><enum>(19)</enum><text>Eighty-one percent of America’s farmed cropland is now controlled by 15 percent of farms, and the number of farmers leaving the land will continue to increase unless and until these trends are reversed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24EF6A0E33C142D8B89CE8CD9E9CC738"><enum>(20)</enum><text>The decline of small family farms undermines the economies of rural communities across America; it has pushed Main Street businesses, from equipment suppliers to small banks, out of business or to the brink of insolvency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E8A779393994EAD8D534EDD48591207"><enum>(21)</enum><text>Increased concentration in the agribusiness sector has a harmful effect on the environment; corporate hog farming, for example, threatens the integrity of local water supplies and creates noxious odors in neighboring communities. Concentration also can increase the risks to food safety and limit the biodiversity of plants and animals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4FDD5B803F6B40558C036FAEED36A4EC"><enum>(22)</enum><text>The decline of family farming poses a direct threat to American families and family values, by subjecting farm families to turmoil and stress. Farm advocates across the country are reporting an increase in farmer suicides over the past several years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0484B73A778A49189CB9599E41C39C3A"><enum>(23)</enum><text>The decline of family farming causes the demise of rural communities, as stores lose customers, churches lose congregations, schools and clinics become under-used, career opportunities for young people dry up, and local inequalities of wealth and income grow wider.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5438691ED8740828009280F4FFD271D"><enum>(24)</enum><text>These developments are not the result of inevitable market forces. Its problems arise rather from policies made in Washington, including farm, antitrust, and trade policies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4510C9276F8B4106B0CDD371786B9C98"><enum>(25)</enum><text>Past congressional action to remediate market failure, such as enacting country-of-origin labeling to provide transparency for domestic farmers, ranchers, and consumers regarding agricultural commodity origins, have been overturned for key commodities by oligopolistic conglomerates that use undifferentiated imports to reduce domestic farm prices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1CAC0557D304CF29F15C76BEEAE7973"><enum>(26)</enum><text>To restore competition in the agricultural economy, and to increase the bargaining power and enhance economic prospects for family farmers, the trend toward concentration must be reversed.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H85D7FC4054D74F5EB4C49B3A07C461A5"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HDD602E8FB1794CAC87D7590A868B4509"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agricultural input supplier</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agricultural input supplier</term> means any person (excluding agricultural cooperatives) engaged in the business of selling, in interstate or foreign commerce, any product to be used as an input (including seed, germ plasm, hormones, antibiotics, fertilizer, and chemicals, but excluding farm machinery) for the production of any agricultural commodity, except that no person shall be considered an agricultural input supplier if sales of such products are for a value less than $10,000,000 per year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CD9DA2543B24F0D8AB74B2B8A22856E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Broker</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>broker</term> means any person engaged in the business of negotiating sales and purchases of any agricultural commodity in interstate or foreign commerce for or on behalf of the vendor or the purchaser, except that no person shall be considered a broker if the only sales of such commodities are for a value less than $10,000,000 per year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC42EE500644E4D629EDD07F0713B0C3C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Commission merchant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>commission merchant</term> means any person engaged in the business of receiving in interstate or foreign commerce any agricultural commodity for sale, on commission, or for or on behalf of another, except that no person shall be considered a commission merchant if the only sales of such commodities are for a value less than $10,000,000 per year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF37C3358D87A4B96A3953254C9D725E8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Dealer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>dealer</term> means any person (excluding agricultural cooperatives) engaged in the business of buying, selling, or marketing agricultural commodities in interstate or foreign commerce, except that—</text><subparagraph id="H6A5EC776D86F4BE6AB2527CF105B8964"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no person shall be considered a dealer with respect to sales or marketing of any agricultural commodity of that person’s own raising; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0848F2DA8B0B49F3AE7E71ED3A8E02BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no person shall be considered a dealer if the only sales of such commodities are for a value less than $10,000,000 per year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H94904673614140D4AAA73E89EF4B4616"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Distributor</header><text>The term <term>distributor</term> means any entity engaged in the business of distributing agricultural products from producers or manufacturers to consumers, restaurants, or retailers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF1AA71D1C3EB476487AB4BCA88F65AF0"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Integrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>integrator</term> means an entity that contracts with farmers for grower services to raise chickens or hogs to slaughter size and weight. The integrator owns the chickens or hogs, supplies the feed, slaughters, and further processes the poultry or pork.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF5055D8BC3645A39F239C6FF4F288AD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Processor</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>processor</term> means any person (excluding agricultural cooperatives) engaged in the business of handling, preparing, or manufacturing (including slaughtering and food and beverage manufacturing) of an agricultural commodity, or the products of such agricultural commodity, for sale or marketing for human consumption, except that no person shall be considered a processor if the only sales of such products are for a value less than $10,000,000 per year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB83226E22D984778AC8D79FFC94BDFDE"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Retailer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>retailer</term> means any person (excluding agricultural cooperatives, cooperative retailers, and cooperative distributers) licensed as a retailer under the Perishable Agriculture Commodities Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/499a">7 U.S.C. 499a(b)</external-xref>), except that no person shall be considered a retailer if the only sales of such products are for a value less than $10,000,000 per year.</text></paragraph></section><title id="HB05042FA7861400693F805AE635C9347"><enum>I</enum><header>Moratorium on and review of large agribusiness, food and beverage manufacturing, and grocery retail mergers</header><section id="HE3FAB4384AC34C25A066AD55C9882B7A"><enum>101.</enum><header>Moratorium on large agribusiness, food and beverage manufacturing, and grocery retail mergers</header><subsection id="HBBE8D8AACB46461EA70486CFE08BA009"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H7B13D144F5674040BD07B95270402C20"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Moratorium</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Until the date referred to in paragraph (2) and except as provided in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="H541C657E5C3F4FBA9C203FCDCC9C2C8E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no dealer, processor, commission merchant, agricultural input supplier, broker, or operator of a warehouse of agricultural commodities or retailer with annual net sales or total assets of more than $222,000,000 shall merge or acquire, directly or indirectly, any voting securities or assets of any other dealer, processor, commission merchant, agricultural input supplier, broker, or operator of a warehouse of agricultural commodities or retailer with annual net sales or total assets of more than $22,000,000; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A653E692B1F4CFF8C2FAECB5F5AD31D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no dealer, processor, commission merchant, agricultural input supplier, broker, or operator of a warehouse of agricultural commodities or retailer with annual net sales or total assets of more than $22,000,000 shall merge or acquire, directly or indirectly, any voting securities or assets of any other dealer, processor, commission merchant, agricultural input supplier, broker, or operator of a warehouse of agricultural commodities or retailer with annual net sales or total assets of more than $222,000,000 if the acquiring person would hold—</text><clause id="H1BF15307B2AF422997CD7EBB759A2D4D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">15 percent or more of the voting securities or assets of the acquired person; or</text></clause><clause id="HBB8833529CEC4CCBAD3346996DAA5D53"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an aggregate total amount of the voting securities and assets of the acquired person in excess of $21,000,000.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5820B829DB05492F93E99C915F9099C3" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The date referred to in this paragraph is the effective date of comprehensive legislation enacted on or after the date on which the reviews referred to in section 102(a) are completed—</text><subparagraph id="H06666BA4FA26444289531222E519479C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for addressing the problem of market concentration in the food and agricultural sector; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19CEAF06B56D4937B5386A1F96E70569" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that terminates the moratorium under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5809F1FA6F544B96862324CF3557131D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Waiver authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall have authority to waive the moratorium imposed by subsection (a) only under extraordinary circumstances, such as insolvency or similar financial distress of 1 of the affected parties.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEC05F103B7C142FD8FB1A91DA592D3BB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exemptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The classes of transactions described in section 7A(c) of the Clayton Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/18a">15 U.S.C. 18a(c)</external-xref>) are exempt from subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6C7CE637658B4F1B905EAECF2D557EC8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Avoidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any transaction or other device entered into or employed for the purpose of avoiding the moratorium contained in subsection (a) shall be disregarded, and the application of the moratorium shall be determined by applying subsection (a) to the substance of the transaction.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF31F1EC8200648458FAFBB14799DFCAB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General shall promulgate regulations that the Attorney General determines are necessary to implement this section. In making the determination under the preceding sentence, the Attorney General shall consult with the Federal Trade Commission.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE9A918AD17E3431A877A465959D5E212"><enum>102.</enum><header>Retroactive review of large agribusiness, food and beverage manufacturing, and grocery retail mergers</header><subsection id="H684EB350F5BF4371A29B2DCB6D1F0BFA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General and the Federal Trade Commission shall review each merger that the Attorney General and the Federal Trade Commission have reviewed since January 1, 2006, that was subject to a premerger notification and waiting period pursuant to section 7A of the Clayton Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/18a">15 U.S.C. 18a</external-xref>) in which a dealer, processor, distributor, commission merchant, agricultural input supplier, broker, or operator of a warehouse of agricultural commodities or retailer merged or acquired, directly or indirectly, any voting securities or assets of any other dealer, processor, distributor, commission merchant, agricultural input supplier, broker, or operator of a warehouse of agricultural commodities or retailer.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA49B76BE4AAE4E8A9CCC6CB45A7B49B6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Unwinding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General and the Federal Trade Commission shall consider whether to unwind a merger reviewed under subsection (a) to restore competition, and may so unwind such merger, if the Attorney General or the Federal Trade Commission determines that the merger brought material harm to—</text><paragraph id="H90C9C5772CB04B318E07B8C23BABEE03"><enum>(1)</enum><text>competition nationally or in local markets;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA12A3ABE6C40402C8E553FB6B161E988"><enum>(2)</enum><text>farmers and ranchers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1E2293E578A431CBE9ACB2250A167E8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>workers; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B28D138E3494D91BE55232E16ED1AA2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>consumers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD0701B8CFA57421399B52CAE00153A45" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Investigative authority</header><text>In conducting a review of a merger under subsection (a), the Attorney General shall have the same power as the Federal Trade Commission under section 6(b) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/46">15 U.S.C. 46(b)</external-xref>) with respect to such review.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBC846AD18C484249ABAD55AE2B104AFC" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to such other amounts as may be made available to the Federal Trade Commission and the Antitrust Division of the Department of Justice, there is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section for fiscal year 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter—</text><paragraph id="H92229DBF6897413EBC680B75D306DAA0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$50,000,000 for the Federal Trade Commission; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68E31C72612446629E5DB219A048D117" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$50,000,000 for the Antitrust Division of the Department of Justice.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2D2D7C662B4A49EBA7F997613811E1E1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Fines and penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Trade Commission and the Antitrust Division of the Department of Justice may use any funds from fines, penalties, and settlements not returned to consumers for their respective future operations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H51719B7712454CD09A5B1DC121D1AD05"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Additional appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To the extent there are insufficient funds from fines, penalties, settlements, and fees received by the Federal Trade Commission and the Antitrust Division of the Department of Justice for the costs of their respective programs, projects, and activities, there are appropriated, out of monies in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, for fiscal year 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter such sums as are necessary for the costs of such programs, projects, and activities.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="HF62560054524488B8925F9572398459C"><enum>II</enum><header>Farm system reforms</header><section id="H2A2B47E927DF4603A881442E1CAAD40D"><enum>201.</enum><header>Local agriculture market program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 210A(i)(1) of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1627c">7 U.S.C. 1627c(i)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>fiscal year 2019</quote> and inserting <quote>each of fiscal years 2024 and 2025, and $500,000,000 for fiscal year 2026</quote>.</text></section><section id="H943C6F47F941473CBAEF6565201DBB40"><enum>202.</enum><header>Restoration of mandatory country of origin labeling for beef and pork; inclusion of dairy products</header><subsection id="H0A99B6FFADC1462F99824777B3A20ECC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 281 of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1638">7 U.S.C. 1638</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H416C11E9300F4628BEB32DC83D9EFC2E"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraphs (1), (2) through (5), (6), and (7) as paragraphs (2), (4) through (7), (9), and (10), respectively;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C6D125C67D64B32841EA0A94C56C0B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting before paragraph (2) (as so redesignated) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3722101B51644F6EBCFB01F2728F76FC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H6319929F72E94E21A071D10545281825"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Beef</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>beef</term> means meat produced from cattle (including veal).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2A0C539F927416CB1590F1654DD600F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2) (as so redesignated)—</text><subparagraph id="HA635D7C40BC54605B78A41E461782046"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A)—</text><clause id="H87991D408EC24D56A98322FC63B948B2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in clause (i), by striking <quote>lamb</quote> and inserting <quote>beef, lamb, pork,</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H7625032FCFAC4910A52C4B7E3E253F83"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in clause (ii), by striking <quote>ground lamb</quote> and inserting <quote>ground beef, ground lamb, ground pork,</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H3CF0A0FCEB40454CA5B41480FC46770D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in clause (x), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause><clause id="HD9A1EC4221DA4D4BB97489E69FE5943A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in clause (xi), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H399F384BD2C245CC87D568CC4950ACA0"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HB18503C730054A15B5434FD8F2CA3FA6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="HB157F9CB6CE3423A90932951D825D383"><enum>(xii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">dairy products.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31DA6FCBBA2C41408DEE6D0BBAE63724"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (B), by inserting <quote>(other than clause (xii) of that subparagraph)</quote> after <quote>subparagraph (A)</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H34F1AFDAA1A645219AD817479C41B939"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after paragraph (2) (as so redesignated) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H75F2E61E155F424F956384006550249B" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HFDDCD6A8724847EA80DEB94360EA7D40"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Dairy product</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>dairy product</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HA63EA3F82FDA4CD29B8827B6C1B7D9D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fluid milk;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD6F4532F37240E483642AB968B009AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">cheese, including cottage cheese and cream cheese;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04AA1A10AE59485BA65F17ACB13B6997"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">yogurt;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8D0AE9AA6870415E83BBB0E890889118"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ice cream;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCEBA6E713BC040DD95FB0AFA165391D8"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">butter; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF376E37CA40945248C57EC5B2CE70453"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other dairy product.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE70DE18FEA44230B3536935E29EB016"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after paragraph (7) (as so redesignated) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0220458703D84453B87C0A3C7DF15047" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H93D20C37FFD045ECAB5B6705A8861D2D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Pork</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>pork</term> means meat produced from hogs. </text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H632C9A4A9AB847C8A9B89DCD3BAAF9A5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notice of country of origin</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 282(a) of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1638a">7 U.S.C. 1638a(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4C954F87B7D94ACEB823557A72FFD4C1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H2BAE472477AE44EC97B8656CBE86BE43"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Designation of country of origin for dairy products</header><subparagraph id="HD2D0DABF877741569CAAAE6838A22FFB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A retailer of a covered commodity that is a dairy product shall designate the origin of the covered commodity as—</text><clause id="HCD0F73D59F1D4567B4B2FE0943445872"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each country in which or from which the 1 or more dairy ingredients or dairy components of the covered commodity were produced, originated, or sourced; and</text></clause><clause id="H3BF76F5EA1E448A495A4FC9C9D430C2B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">each country in which the covered commodity was processed.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBEEB77B63E44B858286154F6D771667"><enum>(B)</enum><header>State, region, locality of the United States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to a covered commodity that is a dairy product produced exclusively in the United States, designation by a retailer of the State, region, or locality of the United States where the covered commodity was produced shall be sufficient to identify the United States as the country of origin.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H569F1A1909674E20BAAB346DF2B53156"><enum>203.</enum><header>Definitions in Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2(a) of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/182">7 U.S.C. 182(a)</external-xref>), is amended—</text><paragraph id="HFECF1378AB2B40989086D5293096562D" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the matter preceding paragraph (1), by striking <quote>When used in this Act—</quote> and inserting <quote>In this Act:</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FD748FAB1504B0B8B5796C671172CE8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (8), by striking <quote>for slaughter</quote> and all that follows through <quote>of such poultry</quote> and inserting <quote>under a poultry growing arrangement, regardless of whether the poultry is owned by that person or another person</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7859AB0584A24493B41795B8106EB9EB"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (9), by striking <quote>and cares for live poultry for delivery, in accord with another’s instructions, for slaughter</quote> and inserting <quote>or cares for live poultry in accordance with the instructions of another person</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FA68075C3CD4468940ED41831BFF4B0"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in each of paragraphs (1) through (9), by striking the semicolon at the end and inserting a period;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H395CF0A22FB549A2BCF130E9CC3B3EDE"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in paragraph (10)—</text><subparagraph id="H33767E77D19E4636BE09CD8204C61375"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>for the purpose of either slaughtering it or selling it for slaughter by another</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA6B9B57F8844B7F94A561DD5FC480B0"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>; and</quote> at the end and inserting a period; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C73961A597C40B3823C871FB76D04D0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H42F60AB5CAB144C49EE361739F5CFE50" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H840A875F905C4C40A1FF6F9154A283C7"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Formula price</header><subparagraph id="H28FD8A76894D454682C15E598A97E08B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>formula price</term> means any price term that establishes a base from which a purchase price is calculated on the basis of a price that will not be determined or reported until a date that is after the date on which the forward price is established.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9225C3D017C24D60A1ED3268FB5A7993"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text>The term <term>formula price</term> does not include—</text><clause id="HC53B64007682411EADC9495C32A4F3B4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any price term that establishes a base from which a purchase price is calculated on the basis of a futures market price; or</text></clause><clause id="HAA3743E0BB234FAF957B354C38E1B603"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any adjustment to the base for quality, grade, or other factors relating to the value of livestock or livestock products that are readily verifiable market factors and are outside the control of the packer.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCDA6861C9BC49079FD547DC26602170"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Forward contract</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>forward contract</term> means an oral or written contract for the purchase of livestock that provides for the delivery of the livestock to a packer at a date that is more than 7 days after the date on which the contract is entered into, without regard to whether the contract is for—</text><subparagraph id="HCD6B009EB78042DFAB5BEFEBE97F418F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a specified lot of livestock; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H475113ACEE0F42368535FE04735A5C50"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a specified number of livestock over a certain period of time.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H8043414FD3E8473C856578255BF0231F" commented="no"><enum>204.</enum><header>Unlawful practices</header><subsection id="H04C01E781E0C40D0B2EBB596C1958B96" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 202 of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/192">7 U.S.C. 192</external-xref>), is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H24ADC206F59E4867A84E448E59E9A46A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H078E384E578449E1A4D8623F8D288BD1" commented="no"><enum>202.</enum><header>Unlawful acts</header><subsection id="HD62B4981AE2A4CDAB06739579C9666E9" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HE86428BB8F1C41D3AA08023735EDA638" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Base price</header><subparagraph id="H9CD820E8305B4E08A5D8B05C3773423F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>base price</term> means the price established in a poultry production contract that corresponds to the stated value provided by the independent contract producer under the terms of the contract, prior to the assessment of any performance-based premium or penalty.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04506183BBA84AD18AD6C7C3FE4F1B67" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Square footage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The price described in subparagraph (A) may be established using the price per square foot of contracted farm infrastructure or price per pound of poultry production.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H649480A647F74FF3AE0B89DB3B9BDE5A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cooperative association of producers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>cooperative association of producers</term> means a cooperative association (as defined in section 15(a) of the Agricultural Marketing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1141j">12 U.S.C. 1141j(a)</external-xref>)) engaged in marketing, bargaining, shipping, or processing agricultural products.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H710ED533C6B8493DA18A9D4093DDCBC8" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Expected performance standard</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>expected performance standard</term> means, with respect to a poultry production contract, a standard established in the contract for the growth and health performance of live poultry under the management of an independent contract producer, which may include expected mortality, weight gain, or feed conversion efficiency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2224B26E74684FF9884432CCCCB0958D" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Independent contract producer</header><text>The term <term>independent contract producer</term> means an agricultural producer that—</text><subparagraph id="H7208311F61624DDF83BD66E4BC39A045" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enters into a contract to manage the production of an agricultural commodity owned by a live poultry dealer or another contracting party; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB77C854CFAA84928A0409BAC18F44CF9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is not a member of a cooperative association of producers that has engaged in bargaining with the other contracting party.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AE929268F0B4B8F9B38C9B9951F0541" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Minimum price</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>minimum price</term> means a contractually guaranteed price floor within a poultry production contract below which the final price delivered to an independent contract producer may not be reduced, including by performance-based penalties.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06942F44FF704634BA19930ABE666CAE" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Performance-based incentive formula</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>performance-based incentive formula</term> means a formula designed to compare the real performance of live poultry being managed by an independent contract producer relative to an expected performance standard.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H689D5E58E7584E888E1FA9DE4A5CFF7A" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Poultry production contract</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>poultry production contract</term> means an oral or written contract established between a live poultry dealer and an independent contract producer in which the independent contract producer provides the land, farm infrastructure, or management labor of the independent contract producer to house and raise live poultry owned by the live poultry dealer.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE7B24355B1E54C2EAFA9487179C63CE7" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>General rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any packer or swine contractor with respect to livestock, meats, meat food products, or livestock products in unmanufactured form, or for any live poultry dealer with respect to live poultry, to do any of the following:</text><paragraph id="H5AEB7D75C45F47E688DC1C87C5B061C6" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Engage in or use any unfair, unjustly discriminatory, or deceptive practice or device.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFF0C00524894F7183B32EB1B438FE78" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Make or give any undue or unreasonable preference or advantage to any particular person or locality in any respect, or subject any particular person or locality to any undue or unreasonable prejudice or disadvantage in any respect.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H739F65A9207B4D45A407393C1DA84ED5" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sell or otherwise transfer to or for any other packer, swine contractor, or any live poultry dealer, or buy or otherwise receive from or for any other packer, swine contractor, or any live poultry dealer, any article for the purpose or with the effect of apportioning the supply between any such persons, if such apportionment has the tendency or effect of restraining commerce or of creating a monopoly.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21D0099F79DB48639EE2C0DDC6826667" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sell or otherwise transfer to or for any other person, or buy or otherwise receive from or for any other person, any article for the purpose or with the effect of manipulating or controlling prices, or of creating a monopoly in the acquisition of, buying, selling, or dealing in, any article, or of restraining commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14715FD27F5342818F8225798F1788BA" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Engage in any course of business or do any act for the purpose or with the effect or manipulating or controlling prices, or of creating a monopoly in the acquisition of, buying, selling, or dealing in, any article, or of restraining commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBA1C18C24944777A7C5F2CB0F4EA809" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conspire, combine, agree, or arrange with any other person—</text><subparagraph id="H4036042A02EF40FAB5C5A28AA7232F75"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to apportion territory for carrying on business;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3EDCDE15F9F64D708DDDD4BDAB1E3288"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to apportion purchases or sales of any article; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5408A16109144448BC023807167A107B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to manipulate or control prices.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A3B2D4BB75345DD90F075E29D82949C" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Use, in effectuating any sale of livestock, a forward contract that—</text><subparagraph id="H6BB6A5EBF7CA438AB61FD8E47A579193" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not contain a firm base price that may be equated to a fixed dollar amount on the date on which the forward contract is entered into;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95214AC413A84C0587F1EA606DC8EAF5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is not offered for bid in an open, public manner under which—</text><clause id="HB0B8BD3F094249548C2A6DF3BD9AFD10" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">buyers and sellers have the opportunity to participate in the bid;</text></clause><clause id="HE3918DF5FA6E4AED888CB2A870ADB7B9" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">more than 1 blind bid is solicited; and</text></clause><clause id="H34DC534D6792474CA4F6D5A5577F6BEA" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">buyers and sellers may witness bids that are made and accepted;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB67FEE6232A448B99306B78F3DC83E75" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is based on a formula price; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB88179291E5B4C61B45806821AE6BFD0" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provides for the sale of livestock in a quantity in excess of—</text><clause id="HB61DC7E288B54C2990FD64D81187C12D" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of cattle, 40 cattle;</text></clause><clause id="H1007FC980E2E4538B51B0F5E6787D62A" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of swine, 30 swine; and</text></clause><clause id="HDBED9A969EF042E7A64A4C9633649B84" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of another type of livestock, a comparable quantity of that type of livestock, as determined by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2194A11B932B4CD6B598B8563ECCA124" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Own or feed livestock directly, through a subsidiary, or through an arrangement that gives a packer operational, managerial, or supervisory control over the livestock, or over the farming operation that produces the livestock, to such an extent that the producer of the livestock is not materially participating in the management of the operation with respect to the production of the livestock, except that this paragraph shall not apply to—</text><subparagraph id="H13A3E8A637B24875BB4166506D633E25" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an arrangement entered into not more than 7 business days before slaughter of the livestock by a packer, a person acting through the packer, or a person that directly or indirectly controls, or is controlled by or under common control with, the packer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H670F316A26D442EA91A6E2E28264E412" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a cooperative or entity owned by a cooperative, if a majority of the ownership interest in the cooperative is held by active cooperative members that—</text><clause id="H4268DF129A9B4A44A8C828EEED05DD2E" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">own, feed, or control the livestock; and</text></clause><clause id="HECBC19ED15244D86B0BA6FCB52473CF1" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide the livestock to the cooperative for slaughter;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7557ED688F484CC3929FF4240A5E386E" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a packer that is not required to report to the Secretary on each reporting day (as defined in section 212 of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1635a">7 U.S.C. 1635a</external-xref>)) information on the price and quantity of livestock purchased by the packer; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97E64F9220C94512B957538A272BDA91" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a packer that owns only 1 livestock processing plant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6396E86E7C4B4F109D43F1DC4E5BB1C4" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Take any action that adversely affects or is likely to adversely affect competition, regardless of whether there is a business justification for the action.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF394CF0C524417FB2E9E58C9AD398F1" commented="no"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conspire, combine, agree, or arrange with any other person to do, or aid or abet the doing of, any act made unlawful by paragraphs (1) through (9).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC8BA84FFCA8747C0B9A345D8B7200169" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Unfair, discriminatory, and deceptive practices and devices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Acts by a packer, swine contractor, or live poultry dealer that violate subsection (b)(1) include the following:</text><paragraph id="H6F9371D0E8794732A1B296A5E42CFECF" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Refusal to provide, on the request of a livestock producer, swine production contract grower, or poultry grower with which the packer, swine contractor, or live poultry dealer has a marketing or delivery contract, the relevant statistical information and data used to determine the compensation paid to the livestock producer, swine production contract grower, or poultry grower, as applicable, under the contract, including—</text><subparagraph id="H34645D947A29404FABF3FC148CC53202" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">feed conversion rates by house, lot, or pen;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB199E853BA8C497A95750EFE52F47E0F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">feed analysis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H813EAB9C90DA49CEB4E9758D2D58AFC1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">breeder history;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF8DF26CD5764B3B90288EC640370884" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">quality grade;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H994663D5F9584898A326D6BC8E1AFB61" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">yield grade; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD4C444BF3D8489AB75BE9FA86F15667" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">delivery volume for any certified branding program (such as programs for angus beef or certified grassfed or Berkshire pork).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CEFCDEF5BA548999D5AED34910F2100" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conduct or action that limits or attempts to limit by contract the legal rights and remedies of a livestock producer, swine production contract grower, or poultry grower, including the right—</text><subparagraph id="H0FED32EC31C14B199606567F47FF0FA5" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to a trial by jury, unless the livestock producer, swine production contract grower, or poultry grower, as applicable, is voluntarily bound by an arbitration provision in a contract;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC110273D47E47DEA4CCA70C9E02066D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to pursue all damages available under applicable law; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD4EB4C6D0FB473C9B8C2E401AFB4162" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to seek an award of attorneys’ fees, if available under applicable law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD15545D7BDB462EBA5B7C5912884BFB" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Termination of a poultry growing arrangement or swine production contract with no basis other than an allegation that the poultry grower or swine production contract grower failed to comply with an applicable law, rule, or regulation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB40FE3D8EFAA4A889C94ECE7646C8FDD" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A representation, omission, or practice that is likely to mislead a livestock producer, swine production contract grower, or poultry grower regarding a material condition or term in a contract or business transaction.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H39EB718812784F36868C30F3CBDA693E" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Undue or unreasonable preferences, advantages, prejudices, and disadvantages</header><paragraph id="HA00F59DED2974045BE3B8235C0A3291B" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Acts by a packer, swine contractor, or live poultry dealer that violate subsection (b)(2) include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H73B8B19E7D014DFD9349217E985E48EB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The execution, termination, extension, or renewal of a contract or agreement that materially disadvantages a livestock producer, swine production contract grower, or poultry grower unless the packer, swine contractor, or live poultry dealer can show, by a preponderance of the evidence, that the acts were predominantly motivated by—</text><clause id="H4C7ABE0D42C94221BB55E0ABCC261998" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text>compliance with applicable regulations;</text></clause><clause id="H12433AEC48734104A86E745085DA3C11" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a distinct and materially disadvantageous change to the financial relationship with the livestock producer, swine production contract grower, or poultry grower; or</text></clause><clause id="H6784DFF210F04F2CB34E754B7EFBF314" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the termination of operations in the geographic region by the packer, swine contractor, or live poultry dealer.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8713F92CBB642759B92EF78A8723A75" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The failure to meet the requirements described in paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A1001196D54429BA0DDDB01A834D497" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a poultry production contract that contains a performance-based incentive formula, the failure to meet the requirements described in paragraph (3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5061D296F5B44A6C9901E6C83A119B3A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Payment by square footage</header><text>The requirements described in this paragraph are as follows:</text><subparagraph id="H6F0BFB256F18403DAB894B664FBD03B0" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subparagraph (B), a live poultry dealer shall structure any poultry production contract in a manner that provides for payment by the square footage of the barn or facility space in which the live birds that are subject to the contract are reared and raised.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9ACC6FEA3A364ED0B240FAB9041EB183" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In lieu of providing for payment by the square footage of the barn or facility space in which the live birds that are subject to the contract are reared and raised, a live poultry dealer may meet the requirement specified in subparagraph (A) if the dealer includes in the poultry production contract an alternative base price provision that was obtained through negotiations with a cooperative association of producers representing the individual independent contract producer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H52A8D9205B4C4D7BB5EEAB662950C5BE" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Use of performance-based incentive formula</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements described in this paragraph are as follows:</text><subparagraph id="HEB2B6C7BC17A49BFA43C85D9BDEA3284" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The poultry production contract shall guarantee a minimum price.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16993A5633974DC6A6D8A240D4B89EB9" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The expected performance standard in the poultry production contract shall be based on at least a 6-month rolling performance average of all producers in the complex of the independent contract producer.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1BCA623F48E4576979DD69745E53D03" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The performance-based incentive formula shall not assess a premium or penalty percentage that exceeds the percentage difference between the performance of the independent contract producer and the expected performance average.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H537ADD8A063143AB8434DD521A4D9D24" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The expected performance standard in the poultry production contract shall be mathematically adjusted to account for expected performance with respect to expected mortality, weight, or feed conversion efficiency, with differences relative to—</text><clause id="HA6372C62BB1B49A3B94D7313CB53147B" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">layer flock age and health;</text></clause><clause id="H979C4770E25245BAB07B566B4773B08C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">predelivery health issues;</text></clause><clause id="H17A59708BA394A74800CB9243586B325" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">flock breed;</text></clause><clause id="H00632F44BE6C4470A5581F4F8C000598" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">flock pick-up age;</text></clause><clause id="H5E5FE58F07EA4E3AB0048E134E645E76" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">feed type;</text></clause><clause id="HFE4632B518924902B135A17E511D88E3" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">feed disruption of 6 hours or more; and</text></clause><clause id="H78792D9F33A14279AAEB7645001FC3CD" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">medical care protocols (such as an antibiotic-free protocol).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF3EDB7589EB54FE1B226A9F1158F9B97" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The poultry production contract shall include a procedure for settling payment outside of the performance-based payment formula, through a performance average of at least the last 5 flocks of the independent contract producer, in the case of the independent contract producer bringing an appeal related to input quality or provision issues.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H27E0C824F8C0448CB70105F24089F2AB" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Harm to competition not required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining whether an act, device, or conduct is a violation under paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (b), a finding that the act, device, or conduct adversely affected or is likely to adversely affect competition is not required.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H234FCEE56B824B4299C582D66BE58BB9" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><paragraph id="H967814B0428C48A38388986E7ABE2273" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to paragraph (2), paragraph (8) of section 202(b) of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/192">7 U.S.C. 192</external-xref>) (as designated by subsection (a)), shall take effect on the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2DF1A3183A84CAF882780488C167B1F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Transition rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a packer that, on the date of enactment of this Act, owns, feeds, or controls livestock intended for slaughter in violation of paragraph (8) of section 202(b) of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/192">7 U.S.C. 192</external-xref>) (as designated by subsection (a)), that paragraph shall take effect—</text><subparagraph id="H6F3B83C1E51248E5AF1C5669DD9DC3A2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a packer of swine, beginning on the date that is 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA078CB1795FB400B8618EEB94DA83966" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a packer of any other type of livestock, beginning not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0FCB279494764831AF54A73292770A4F"><enum>205.</enum><header>Spot market purchases of livestock by packers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921, is amended by inserting after section 202 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/192">7 U.S.C. 192</external-xref>) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE16E78D34F584D66B63D5A42AB6D46B0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H2573DD8CFE054F9F9A4FFC7E73E01F8D"><enum>202A.</enum><header>Spot market purchases of livestock by packers</header><subsection id="HFD85066F9131434F948DAAB50716B221"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HFECD0BEF25464E3EAF35B82971CDBB89"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered packer</header><subparagraph id="H11430DE8890D4A908026675527753DA9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered packer</term> means a packer that is required under subtitle B of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1635">7 U.S.C. 1635 et seq.</external-xref>) to report to the Secretary each reporting day (as defined in section 212 of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1635a">7 U.S.C. 1635a</external-xref>)) information on the price and quantity of livestock purchased by the packer.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4AECEBC4925F4EA9BB73A05FC519CB1F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term ‘covered packer’ does not include a packer that owns only 1 livestock processing plant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB079E70088E4AFAB35C7B70BF46A3C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Nonaffiliated producer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term ‘nonaffiliated producer’ means a producer of livestock—</text><subparagraph id="H8063BD5A95D04B89B232D6E0CC91632D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that sells livestock to a packer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C3A3546DB74488B8FF6A71DEFD70D63"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that has less than 1 percent equity interest in the packer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9DBEEC1892E4FF49E9070374530F603"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that has no officers, directors, employees, or owners that are officers, directors, employees, or owners of the packer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B3814118AA64C4CB3ABF358F88BFD72"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">that has no fiduciary responsibility to the packer; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1982DD99BB7E4043B7458F7840E529E0"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in which the packer has no equity interest.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4348420787D4E76BC45862419D742D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Spot market sale</header><subparagraph id="H96618C38C5BE41AB97EBA0D818C58E13"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>spot market sale</term> means a purchase and sale of livestock by a packer from a producer—</text><clause id="H420D814AED5B41CA98400B47EE4B39B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">under an agreement that specifies a firm base price that may be equated with a fixed dollar amount on the date the agreement is entered into;</text></clause><clause id="HBBF395A74AAA4C40A8A810E21941BC08"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">under which the livestock are slaughtered not more than 7 days after the date on which the agreement is entered into; and</text></clause><clause id="HA32C889A9A95451B8D8480C8FC527AEC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">under circumstances in which a reasonable competitive bidding opportunity exists on the date on which the agreement is entered into.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H470C2CF6A8E9468CAE0F5154A3DC3846"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reasonable competitive bidding opportunity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of subparagraph (A)(iii), a reasonable competitive bidding opportunity shall be considered to exist if—</text><clause id="H61A1A7CA0567417E8AE9DD46062D8B52"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no written or oral agreement precludes the producer from soliciting or receiving bids from other packers; and</text></clause><clause id="H98BB1A66736148E0AC84DD734EC39537"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">no circumstance, custom, or practice exists that—</text><subclause id="H7A7E2AFE3CFD4F4496E7C0552C8F380A"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishes the existence of an implied contract (as determined in accordance with the Uniform Commercial Code); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H2B0E708DCC964EB0B460AF28054621A9"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">precludes the producer from soliciting or receiving bids from other packers.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB5DA2B3FC38D43068075B781302D9512"><enum>(b)</enum><header>General rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the quantity of livestock that is slaughtered by a covered packer during each reporting day (as defined in section 212 of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1635a">7 U.S.C. 1635a</external-xref>)) in each plant, the covered packer shall slaughter not less than the applicable percentage specified in subsection (c) of the quantity through spot market sales from nonaffiliated producers.</text></subsection><subsection id="H793BD48B7D0C4C10AA4AE5A3976766F0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicable percentages</header><paragraph id="HE185C15C63774634978BCE646C44BE1D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), the applicable percentage shall be 50 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19ECF85A0B8E41E78B892EB298DC9A00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a covered packer that reported to the Secretary in the 2020 annual report that more than 60 percent of the livestock of the covered packer were committed procurement livestock, the applicable percentage shall be the greater of—</text><subparagraph id="H8592599C87EC4DBCB931D94BF9ED932D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the difference between the percentage of committed procurement livestock so reported and 100 percent; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E9C04BA00D14D7690D16E1681E46D9A"><enum>(B)</enum><clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H49210CB190F4496EB40F86AA6BB6FA1D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during each of calendar years 2024 and 2025, 20 percent;</text></clause><clause id="HE6BAB29366AF4EBDAF6E273476ED4324" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during each of calendar years 2026 and 2027, 30 percent; and</text></clause><clause id="HD1F1467BBB7046BB92DCAF350FCFF908" indent="up1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">during calendar year 2028 and each calendar year thereafter, 50 percent.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD546AC1919A94F1DAACB08B9C5477EAA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Nonpreemption</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section does not preempt any requirement of a State or political subdivision of a State that requires a covered packer to purchase on the spot market a greater percentage of the livestock purchased by the covered packer than is required under this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H58A14F2970C24CB298EB8FBFFDA82E18"><enum>206.</enum><header>Investigation of live poultry dealers</header><subsection id="HD11332076A46498B8A0EB6CFA6A317AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Administrative enforcement authority over live poultry dealers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sections 203, 204, and 205 of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/193">7 U.S.C. 193</external-xref>, 194, 195), are amended by inserting <quote>, live poultry dealer,</quote> after <quote>packer</quote> each place it appears.</text></subsection><subsection id="H61D7D3198E9A4337A45A29B90077DEBB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authority To request temporary injunction or restraining order</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 408 of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/228a">7 U.S.C. 228a</external-xref>), is amended by inserting <quote>or poultry care</quote> after <quote>on account of poultry</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFDB2EDA8AE594CF380326D98F9881061"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Violations by live poultry dealers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 411 of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/228b-2">7 U.S.C. 228b–2</external-xref>), is amended—</text><paragraph id="H989B27001CE44DBDA8F22EAD30029BF1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), in the first sentence, by striking <quote>any provision of section 207 or section 410 of</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H975EDCDA466B4287BCD6ACA0A058C9D0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b), in the first sentence, by striking <quote>any provisions of section 207 or section 410</quote> and inserting <quote>any provision</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H1B2018B8F6D7438981D5A54FF268290C"><enum>207.</enum><header>Ensuring fair practices in agriculture</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture shall implement, without amendment, the final rule titled <quote>Unfair Practices and Undue Preferences in Violation of the Packers and Stockyards Act</quote> and published in the Federal Register by the Department of Agriculture on December 20, 2016 (81 Fed. Reg. 92703).</text></section><section id="H9F5D768B557C44A9A67A3A9951D364AE"><enum>208.</enum><header>Award of attorney fees</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 204 of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/194">7 U.S.C. 194</external-xref>), is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5F110DEC712647739EFF7E1EC1FE2E15" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H576B0E5587DD436F8B9266093BEF96F4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Attorney’s fee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The court shall award a reasonable attorney’s fee as part of the costs to a prevailing plaintiff in a civil action under this section.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H12EC59DD6201457FA473F216609116AA"><enum>209.</enum><header>Review and report on fragility and national security in the food system</header><subsection id="H17938A5572884979BEE6A61A16B3BE1D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text><paragraph id="HCF84B1DAEC2C4277B42971F909137265"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct a review of the fragility of the food system in the United States with respect to meat, poultry, and dairy; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H050C62497BA14ACE9059F5E3FBDAD757"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to Congress a report containing the results of such review.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE43C0B7B57A43E18B4DA64F61AABE41"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report under subsection (a) shall include information on, and an analysis of—</text><paragraph id="H1F9E500546A9415B98E2EA78E437E90F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the reach of corporate consolidation and corporate control of the meat, poultry, and dairy supply chain, including animal feed, inputs for animal feed, processing, and distribution;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AD0B99804554CFE87B339B9B693BED6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effects of corporate consolidation and corporate control of the meat, poultry, and dairy supply chain on—</text><subparagraph id="H10BAC97E71EC4AC9B0774D5242B742FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consumers, farmers, rural communities, and meat, poultry, and dairy processing workers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA7AD867247C4CC385787BA81EB1AF09"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">greenhouse gas emissions, climate change, and costs borne by communities to adapt to climate change;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H608F459C91BB4EA390C1B104DF526BE3"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">water quality, soil quality, air quality, and biodiversity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HECE997070C5748E795879A4229301C11"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">politics and political lobbying;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1041E2414E464FA698374FC573320D34"><enum>(3)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HC3B7D570DC624D9386B71C2AA24C434D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which Department of Agriculture rules and regulations designed for large covered establishments are applied to small- and medium-sized covered establishments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97802C2FCFD44AE09C1415580499390A" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the need for the Secretary of Agriculture to adapt rules and regulations to benefit small- and medium-sized covered establishments;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H16C66648DB334AADA51E6F74C48D7D62"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effects of the COVID–19 pandemic on meat, poultry, and dairy exports; meat, poultry, and dairy cold storage inventories; processing rates of meat, poultry, and dairy; and the net profits earned by owners of covered establishments;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DCAD5BFB03B4BB3855459B3A31BB59F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effect of the COVID–19 pandemic on meat, poultry, and dairy prices paid—</text><subparagraph id="H8E4B9454A7F1455F8403EC0BD8A72284"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to farmers; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBE8E1D8C9FC48B3AD2C63ED89632F4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by consumers;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H28E055CAAF8D4401B7CC021461DEAA2F"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Federal support for the corporations that control the largest percentage of the meat, poultry, and dairy industry through contracts, procurement, subsidies, and other mechanisms;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9854F366E8164F8D891639FAC33A04FB"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the risk of disruption caused by corporate consolidation among covered establishments, including an analysis of food supply chain issues resulting from the COVID–19 pandemic; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H111B432FEBA44BB3941B73949DF40ADC"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the extent to which breaking up the meat packing oligopoly and the dairy processing oligopoly would increase food system resiliency for the next pandemic.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3FE78E0F5A4C4E90AD8E1C515C2889CF" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Covered establishment defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered establishment</term> means—</text><paragraph id="HF558A60341F449CF91FFF9CA25D92C70" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an establishment that is subject to inspection under the Federal Meat Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/601">21 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D91F0E35DC64C3B8CCA904E26910BCA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an establishment that is subject to inspection under the Poultry Products Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/451">21 U.S.C. 451 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0488CAADA2C14F0C93D201F995E4C2BF" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an establishment—</text><subparagraph id="H8C211643EAAD41FDBBF6EC78DF948931"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that is a dairy operation (as defined in section 1401 of the Agricultural Act of 2014 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/9051">7 U.S.C. 9051</external-xref>)); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFB5F9AF1E9FC49A285CE6A80E5758458"><enum>(B)</enum><text>that processes dairy.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE2FF6E3A1EB9406B879A62F7D8013457"><enum>210.</enum><header>Technical amendments</header><subsection id="H4F8A291B7D864CE5B23A0AFD65934DC9"><enum>(a)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 203 of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/193">7 U.S.C. 193</external-xref>), is amended—</text><paragraph id="H154A9624DDE14BA38377DA85249326DC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), in the first sentence—</text><subparagraph id="H229E77EDBE134A11AAAFA2CB6F4DE63C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>he shall cause</quote> and inserting <quote>the Secretary shall cause</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H845704AA786C47A58B5A96DCE130CBD4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>his charges</quote> and inserting <quote>the charges</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43ACC0DDFE034A7CB3054F199B6B31EB"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>evidence introduced against him</quote> and inserting <quote>evidence introduced against the packer, live poultry dealer, or swine contractor</quote>; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H67AC35A2B2854193B2F61B1B0D975B84"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b), in the first sentence, by striking <quote>he shall make a report in writing in which he shall state his findings</quote> and inserting <quote>the Secretary shall make a report in writing in which the Secretary shall state the findings of the Secretary</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B728EFF43B94449B146D6E742E5233E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c), by striking <quote>he</quote> and inserting <quote>the Secretary</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D1AE27FB92945E28B238CB393798822"><enum>(b)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 204 of the Packers and Stockyards Act, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/194">7 U.S.C. 194</external-xref>), is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC48F6E03B36E4A52AD70B4EFB09FE942"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), by striking <quote>he has his</quote> and inserting <quote>the packer, live poultry dealer, or swine contractor has its</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H925C1054382143449FD22AB40A8C4E58"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c), by striking <quote>his officers, directors, agents, and employees</quote> and inserting <quote>the officers, directors, agents, and employees of the packer, live poultry dealer, or swine packer</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBE44DF6023F491CBE52EBE0C24F5262"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (f), in the second sentence—</text><subparagraph id="H1ED4263C074042F2B0B338E07BE8007E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>his findings</quote> and inserting <quote>the findings of the Secretary</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC953CCEED763487796C03E6DBE8E4062"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>he</quote> and inserting <quote>the Secretary</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1AC913C47193445E96E3FD94479EED2A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (g), by striking <quote>his officers, directors, agents, and employees</quote> and inserting <quote>the officers, directors, agents, and employees of the packer, live poultry dealer, or swine packer</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title id="H7D46A342550240729D0E349D0632875E"><enum>III</enum><header>Providing resources for beginning, retiring, and socially disadvantaged farmers and ranchers</header><section id="H582E3EB226FB45BF9BC8F4258EFB586D"><enum>301.</enum><header>Reauthorization and increased funding for beginning, retiring, and socially disadvantaged farmers and ranchers</header><subsection id="HAC440148D968492F867F7832F9E0B1D0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mandatory funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2501(l)(1) of the Food, Agriculture, Conservation, and Trade Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2279">7 U.S.C. 2279(l)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HA795A630913A4AE5A9A1F0E17D69A888"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking <quote>and</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDCD44F01AB541B0A6D40F5802220B0D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>2023 and each fiscal year thereafter.</quote> and inserting <quote>2023; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5383A357AEC24B9C8CFD521A6D4CB48F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD9223ED0571D41B5AE852F7283F77915" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H904E0087EA1045FDAE02B7A9D90B01C1"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA3156F825C7147589BF31C1EC9D9F269"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 2501(l)(2) of the Food, Agriculture, Conservation, and Trade Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2279">7 U.S.C. 2279(l)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>$50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2019 through 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>$100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028</quote>.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="H5DEE67BD59F941CCB2BD9D70321BF638"><enum>IV</enum><header>Livestock, dairy, and poultry supply chain infrastructure</header><section id="H254310AA78FF44A3B9B02107CB4331E3"><enum>401.</enum><header>Livestock, dairy, and poultry supply chain infrastructure grants and loans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subtitle D of title III of the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1981">7 U.S.C. 1981 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7F60E86F642E45B1943BE0B536AA9C4A" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H838E610FAD834868880BE738175ECC85"><enum>379I.</enum><header>Livestock, dairy, and poultry supply chain infrastructure</header><subsection id="H5D4A1D6D08C843AA9291B483E30D6241"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary is authorized to provide grants or make or insure loans under any of the programs authorized by this Act, the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1621">7 U.S.C. 1621 et seq.</external-xref>), or the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/901">7 U.S.C. 901 et seq.</external-xref>), as the Secretary determines to be appropriate, to assist farmers and rural businesses and cooperatives to maintain or increase the production, aggregation, processing, distribution, and marketing of value-added, niche, or regionally marketed meat, dairy, and poultry products.</text></subsection><subsection id="H149ABE07493846229A5E9A6854301B82"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In implementing subsection (a), the Secretary shall give priority to grants or loans that will help increase or enhance the availability and geographic distribution of small processing facilities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBA70FF063EF6496984B8FF72C025C3EA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Small processing facility defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>small processing facility</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H7E2AC8A343B64068A0D1363D06B1451D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a selected establishment (as defined in section 501(a) of the Federal Meat Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/683">21 U.S.C. 683(a)</external-xref>));</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C2A25D68BE3414A8626A536A0354264"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a selected establishment (as defined in section 31(a) of the Poultry Products Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/472">21 U.S.C. 472(a)</external-xref>)); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B20151D051649F185AFA969421D534C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an establishment that—</text><subparagraph id="H5C9C2991E09F48F987012C42D685815E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>specializes in processing milk, cream, or dairy products; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AA8F91BEAA84131A156A2022E1C754B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>processes fewer than 100,000 pounds of milk, cream, or dairy products per day.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H8F78DF9C42994B839FB9EC8923692686"><enum>402.</enum><header>Pilot program for increased accessibility to inspection and technical assistance for eligible processing facilities</header><subsection id="HAEAC41A38EF14D79BFEC2997AD0157E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out a 5-year pilot program within the Food Safety and Inspection Service—</text><paragraph id="H4EA4B17F3091409AAB8AA142DA304462"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to expand the availability of processing inspectors, technical assistance, and onsite inspection for eligible processing facilities, including no-cost overtime inspections; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCFBD1207BBD141EFA035E02417263F9C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to identify and train part-time inspectors and technical assistance providers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2AFBA3C5CFF46CDB17FD7C477711694"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Professional experience</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall determine the appropriate professional experience of inspectors and providers described in subsection (a)(2), which shall include individuals with expertise in veterinary medicine, public health, food service management, and animal science, as applicable.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9336FFDC2F294A6A97CD8CA4E2840737"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H3677E63682FA4FDDA7EF399EF6EA9AC9" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible processing facility</header><text>The term <term>eligible processing facility</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HB5D2FE926F6247FB860E705EAF496854" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an eligible facility described in section 764 of division N of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/473">21 U.S.C. 473</external-xref>), that has a labor peace agreement in place; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE82B4C67485D4E39A6F2EEA7E734877D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a dairy processing facility that has a labor peace agreement in place.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0B8C86B84034BFC9838688D0031F8C9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Labor peace agreement</header><text>The term <term>labor peace agreement</term> means an agreement—</text><subparagraph id="H0F2928ACEE5B4F8F986C3D544F57680C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">between an employer and a labor organization that represents, or is actively seeking to represent, the employees of the employer; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE63CE1CA000431796838D53B56147F6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>under which such employer and labor organization agree that—</text><clause id="HB2EAD637B6614A3B9E893FA11A7D4FA8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the employer—</text><subclause id="HF2F210AAEABD421EB377D3C1AC9BCC7C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>will not hinder any effort of an employee to join a labor organization; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H11E221CAC29A4E299CC7327D391E4584"><enum>(II)</enum><text>will not take any action that directly or indirectly indicates or implies any opposition to an employee joining a labor organization;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0A723FE66F144425B6A9856F990A15A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the labor organization agrees to refrain from picketing, work stoppages, or boycotts against the employer;</text></clause><clause id="H73D27E3864374A03BAEC989B436D1A6A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the employer provides the labor organization with employee contact information, and facilitates or permits labor organization access to employees at the workplace, including facilitating or permitting the labor organization to meet with employees to discuss joining the labor organization; and</text></clause><clause id="HB3F5C08575E647A68A904EC098380195"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the employer shall, upon the request of the labor organization, recognize the labor organization as the bargaining representative of the employees if a majority of the employees choose the labor organization as their bargaining representative.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

