<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCC3DCD77388D493EA0F810799D3572A3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3546 IH: Study To Observe and Prevent (STOP) Human Trafficking Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3546</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Attorney General, in coordination with the President’s Interagency Task Force to Monitor and Combat Trafficking in Persons, to study the prevalence and instances of human trafficking at adult entertainment clubs in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1838770284CD4ECDAC78E82BC3050781" style="OLC"><section id="H47F1223FC1AE4F66AC0AFCB56DD0AF80" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Study To Observe and Prevent (STOP) Human Trafficking Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H72494DCD134948B69829666A5343FA04"><enum>2.</enum><header>Study on the prevalence and instances of human trafficking at adult entertainment clubs</header><subsection id="H9D002706D773476DA261CB8CB62FAE51"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study Required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General, in coordination with the President’s Interagency Task Force to Monitor and Combat Trafficking in Persons, shall conduct a study on the prevalence and instances of human trafficking at adult entertainment clubs in the United States. In conducting the study, the Attorney General shall collaborate with non-governmental entities with demonstrated expertise in studying human trafficking.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2EB4342CAD7A4E039A38C4939E900E52"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Study Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In conducting the study required under subsection (a), the Attorney General shall gather information on—</text><paragraph id="H69C7E7CB4B264C2AA76668BA56BB5187"><enum>(1)</enum><text>demographic characteristics of victims, including age groups of victims;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H389FB61859874B198374306064D4AEC5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any relationship between victims of human trafficking and adult entertainment clubs, including victims’ status as an employee, contractor, or licensee; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H994DB51CFDB546E3A0CEE5CB6AFFA3EC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any methods of fraud, force, or coercion used by human traffickers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE214E3351AC149F08A74934A32BB3586"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 15 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall submit to Congress a report on the findings of the study required under subsection (a) and any recommendations of the Attorney General relating to such findings.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1D19816E8D4E4255B56F493B0C8C8FF1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HC38688B14BC645E2902094AD6811F85A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>adult entertainment club</quote> means an establishment that offers or provides live performance, display, or dance of any type involving any actual or simulated performance of sexual activities and nude or seminude exposure. Such an establishment may include one that features entertainment of an erotic nature, including exotic dancers, strippers, male or female impersonators, or similar entertainers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA97CBB8F717E443C9400FE3F1F162F1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>human trafficking</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>severe form of trafficking in persons</quote> in section 103 of the Victims of Trafficking and Violence Protection Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/7102">22 U.S.C. 7102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

