<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H956EACF609DD4405A8DA1B30771C905D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6500 IH: Promoting Reentry through Education in Prisons Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6500</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231129">November 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to establish an Office of Prison Education, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H357E5282D7324448A3C8C4B97D950262" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H4BAB9B5D52694BD59B7AB09B17E0AC0A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Reentry through Education in Prisons Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PREP Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDE0A29B8BA954EED906A654F6F20DD40"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; purpose</header><subsection id="H0818E4A17026418B8494B7C12B63ADEC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text>Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H53CE7FDAB9564812BF8EBCD2D95B1AC0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Over the course of an 8-year period following the release of individuals from Federal prisons, the United States Sentencing Commission found that 49.3 percent of such individuals were rearrested, 31.7 percent were reconvicted, and 24.6 percent were reincarcerated.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B2EAB39DD1045999FB109D94C5DE953"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Bureau of Justice Statistics found that, over a similar time period as described in paragraph (1), 83 percent of people released from State prisons were rearrested.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D87D81F517E47FBBA8C494D20578018"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A broad spectrum of prison education programming can prepare individuals for the contemporary workforce pre-release, ensuring that upon release the individuals are best situated to be productive members of their communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17057DDA65EC4BECBC400B5B29453BE3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Education for people in prisons has a clear public safety benefit, reducing recidivism rates by over 43 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H669698765137483D895F26D961C20005"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Employment is 13 percent higher for individuals who participated in either academic or vocational programs in prison, and 28 percent higher for individuals who participated in vocational programs alone.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC51432F62E104FB58BA584A299B77ECE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>During the first 3 years after an individual is released, each dollar spent on funding prison education programs reduces incarceration costs by 4 to 5 dollars.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91B901EC55F044D08F71A96E8D66A379"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Prison education helps to improve the safety of the prison environment, not only for incarcerated individuals, but also for correctional officers and prison staff.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54B1C9CFFD83435D85E3A614B392592A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>A 2016 analysis of the Bureau of Prisons education programs found that the Bureau of Prisons spends 20 percent as much on inmate education as the nearest-sized State prison systems and experiences a proportionally low return.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F70F135F6A047F694BCCB09DA970E59"><enum>(9)</enum><text>The 2016 analysis described in paragraph (8) also found that the Bureau of Prisons lacked the staff, programmatic strategy and alignment, budget, assessment, and educational support to effectively administer educational programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1703DC8BCC2F49B892F3711D7A5E8149"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text>The purpose of this Act is to create a dedicated office within the Bureau of Prisons to—</text><paragraph id="H61511B02BD4A4CD986393C874CB2831A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>improve the prison education programs provided by the Bureau of Prisons;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B8C85B6BB48456AA7F3D13B35684813"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure access to quality education programs across all Federal penal and correctional institutions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H045D7E9DDE734D499AF2E03D3FD433B5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>create partnerships with education providers to offer quality programs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35946817AFF94577A3D7884C14634BC4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>create a repository of research and best practices for State and local correctional institutions on quality education programs.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HEA6BCCAF18AF49D0AB1AEDEF534DCCC9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H29A7B0CA062D4DB28391047C413433FF"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assistant Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Assistant Director</term> means the Assistant Director for Prison Education appointed under section 4142(b) of title 18, United States Code, as added by this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H705220348664468691C3A7CD1E607D36"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Bureau of Prisons.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H207BB0BDA7E74D609559541D67A64E6A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Office of Prison Education</header><subsection id="HCB4ADA9FC11745C189277F2E2B259B05"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part III of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after chapter 307 the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC1961555B1CB4B23A64C87DBE1263D14"><chapter id="H5A5A48E75AF64D0F949251A09FA6E10C"><enum>308</enum><header>Education</header><toc><toc-entry level="section">Sec. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">4141. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">4142. Office of Prison Education.</toc-entry><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">4143. Federal Prison Education Program.</toc-entry></toc><section id="H89FF6EE809DF41558E31DAB5B2BC6B6D"><enum>4141.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this chapter:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE08868BB2C0F4DDEB2FC303AB91D0CEE"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assistant Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Assistant Director</term> means the Assistant Director for Prison Education appointed under section 4142(b).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB5EA7A4EBAE746AAB4E8B99B81211926"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Bureau of Prisons.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33E3DD6B987F48E8BF58B74C96E4619B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disability</header><text>The term <term>disability</term> has the meaning given the term in section 3 of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12102">42 U.S.C. 12102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA86D139062A463D9BFCFF71A5D8D123"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Regular high school diploma</header><text>The term <term>regular high school diploma</term> has the meaning given the term in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H69C18E175C254A0FBC5CD388442A20C7"><enum>4142.</enum><header>Office of Prison Education</header><subsection id="H8D5231418E5741D584E179FFFAA9FCE9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of this chapter are to—</text><paragraph id="HDE670ACC336B4A188DA00846A58F17D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ensure that all Federal penal and correctional institutions provide quality educational programs for incarcerated individuals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27610C329BA04745B2C4B951AB064D0B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish an office that will be a nationwide repository for research, policies, and best practices on education in prison; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20B9C1024D3E4947BF293657B453E0A7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>establish an office that will offer training and technical assistance for State prison systems in implementing and administering education programs in prison.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H33630FD69E1446A18BFE1856DB623290"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of the Office of Prison Education</header><text>The Director shall establish within the Bureau of Prisons an Office of Prison Education, which shall be headed by an Assistant Director for Prison Education appointed by the Director.</text></subsection><subsection id="H003537CD810A4DA294ADC7F36F275B3D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Functions of the Office of Prison Education</header><text>The Office of Prison Education required to be established under this section shall ensure the provision of educational services for incarcerated individuals in all Federal penal and correctional institutions, including programs such as adult literacy, basic skills development, education toward a regular high school diploma or its recognized equivalent, postsecondary education, workforce development that leads to an industry-recognized credential, a certificate, or an associate degree, pre-apprenticeships, registered apprenticeships, career and technical education, and expanded opportunities for individuals with a disability, including by—</text><paragraph id="HAD8D3CC24985457EAE46BDBE536E918C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>implementing the Federal Prison Education Program under section 4143;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9159E1D4FFB345E7B4AC27A4E9312162"><enum>(2)</enum><text>coordinating and standardizing quality, evidence-based, and effective education programs in prison and services across all Federal penal and correctional institutions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H075AA92497F04EABB53664547262BFCB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>coordinating relevant Federal agencies in providing quality educational services, including by consulting with the Office of Career, Technical, and Adult Education of the Department of Education;</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE07B38F1947D4B43AEDC546D858E90C9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>coordinating with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to identify and provide information to incarcerated veterans regarding potential eligibility for educational assistance under laws administered by the Secretary, including educational assistance under chapters 30 and 33 of title 38, United States Code;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF9BF121AE474BB4B0665475D79CCA3F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>conducting research and issuing reports on education programs in prison, including on best practices, particularly as it relates to pedagogy and instruction of incarcerated people;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7C3FF4BB50C487F8145EA249ABFB8AE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>providing training and technical assistance for State prison systems to improve education programs in prison; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58DDC89D85E94C5199A4B4EEB97F40EC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>coordinating with the Bureau of Justice Statistics, the National Institute of Justice, National Center for Education Statistics, the National Institute of Corrections, and other relevant agencies as designated by the Assistant Director in collecting and reporting Federal and State data on—</text><subparagraph id="H36E692976FBC4F6EB08B04199B87AB59"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of individuals who enroll in and complete an education program in prison, including a regular high school diploma or its recognized equivalent, a career and technical education sequence, or a postsecondary degree or certificate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H955D37F507574DA1B54E7508DBF3C7E6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of individuals who do not complete an education program in prison and the reasons for non-completion;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7012749B44A4599A04738D1A6BE3BEE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any State or Federal prohibitions or limitations on employment for individuals with felony convictions who complete an education program in prison;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD448F68BB3E4D21AB9B10B346BB9B2A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the correlation between participating in or completing an education program in prison and continued educational enrollment, both in-custody and post-release;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A00CB8717584180A2A51D165D61CB19"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the correlation between participating in and completing an education program in prison with post-release outcomes, including job placement, job retention, and recidivism;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9F0E70A2B2C45D798DB8F931CDF8DA7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the correlation between participating in and completing an education program in prison with in-custody outcomes, including enrollment in other education or training programs and reduction in citations; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3E18890A4C364067B90682FFC2246E91"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the impact of the correlations described in subparagraphs (C) through (F) on overall corrections spending through factors such as—</text><clause id="H773E6B8DC4154E7B8B663419E1E3F3B0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>impacts on recidivism;</text></clause><clause id="HB3F083924C9749B2B321D4AA3F1542EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>spending on Federal penal and correctional institutions and State prisons; and</text></clause><clause id="H81C5567D5E754FBB88CC4305852ADB94"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>other relevant factors; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6FA2344FB23441198EB21A166AF6550"><enum>(H)</enum><text>other relevant data.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H2E09F588DBEF4A7E9288D62D6BD692EC"><enum>4143.</enum><header>Federal Prison Education Program</header><subsection id="H069CB69827964520AA9C6C3C4817C7C2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF05965E1EDF649DFBF5844968FDFAF78"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Community-based organization; Local educational agency</header><text>The terms <term>community-based organization</term> and <term>local educational agency</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27601C2AEBDB47E1BE8E28423A36A4FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Demonstrated effectiveness</header><text>The term <term>demonstrated effectiveness</term> means the past effectiveness of an eligible provider demonstrated by providing—</text><subparagraph id="H7598DD1D2E1646D0BCACB29A85C9F722"><enum>(A)</enum><text>performance data on its record of improving the skills of eligible students, particularly eligible individuals who have low levels of literacy, in the content domains of reading, writing, mathematics, English language acquisition, and other relevant subject areas; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC10013EC95224751B96DA0856DBDB733"><enum>(B)</enum><text>information regarding its outcomes for participants related to program completion, employment attainment, pursuit of additional education, and other relevant factors.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E3FBBFC6087447FAB02A29B0F91AC9B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible provider</header><text>The term <term>eligible provider</term> means an organization that has demonstrated effectiveness in providing programs such as adult literacy, basic skills development, education toward a regular high school diploma or its recognized equivalent, postsecondary education, workforce readiness, apprenticeships, career and technical education, and programing individuals with learning disabilities, which may include—</text><subparagraph id="H37DE3E3500064B318FBBEAD776E94FBD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF884B35BAE094167A0859F0D41183971"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a local educational agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4771BE6B658C446DAF1E925CC3476502"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a community-based organization or faith-based organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99A83D15AD7D474CBFB9CA589D7AFAEB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a volunteer literacy organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H951C6ACB978045DD903F8CDC102CFC14"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a public or private nonprofit agency;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72FC1AE12B994DCAB89A0C0684AEC766"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a nonprofit institution that is not described in subparagraphs (A) through (E) and has the ability to provide adult education and literacy activities to eligible individuals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5678D138448343128B81B355483F73DA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a consortium or coalition of the agencies, organizations, and institutions described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (F); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCCB20E6D672F4ED39340F9AF09555390"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a partnership between an employer and an entity described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (G).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H192C7F37C1E74069854E48FA6E3A15EF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible student</header><text>The term <term>eligible student</term> means an individual who is incarcerated in a Federal correctional facility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H673C91983BF6446DB1DB077AD2432343"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE6D4AE6DFAE40E98F1DC08A37307EF3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>Program</term> means the Federal Prison Education Program required to be established under subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF390B03EC7D54DF8802B02AF57C1256F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Authorization</header><paragraph id="HE8638DDD56DE47EC9769456DBBD741C3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Assistant Director shall establish a Federal Prison Education Program to develop and support partnerships between eligible providers and Federal correctional facilities to provide quality educational opportunities to facilitate successful community reintegration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EF252DFF36348D2AE67D592D9DB4539"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of eligible providers</header><text>The Assistant Director shall select eligible providers to partner with Federal correctional facilities to develop quality education programs for eligible students, such as—</text><subparagraph id="H4E2F2F770C36435FBB98816C256B3B6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>adult literacy;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H657F99AEDF6A4C99B9508600D195F054"><enum>(B)</enum><text>basic skills development;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DFE2094C6194FE290E6861C27F6DA19"><enum>(C)</enum><text>education toward a regular high school diploma or its recognized equivalent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBE267702AC242ACA509F2EE56C28D2C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>postsecondary education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD68B4F16A44146DB9336D4E760EDECA0"><enum>(E)</enum><text>workforce development that leads to an industry recognized credential, a certificate, or an associate degree;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE12C35B8DBA4FF0A4A63F0B6985FD10"><enum>(F)</enum><text>apprenticeships; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H592179F77B1A46E29928FD79844DE2BC"><enum>(G)</enum><text>career and technical education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H14B7601432394442948334716C1CD189"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Quality programs</header><text>When determining which eligible providers will be selected for participation in the Program, the Assistant Director shall—</text><subparagraph id="H6296341B8AB34B0484483584104F18B3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consider the evidence that an eligible provider demonstrates a strong record on student outcomes and successful community reintegration, which shall include—</text><clause id="HA179B04C61A54B5DAA31EE32A6FB8129"><enum>(i)</enum><text>high rates of program completion;</text></clause><clause id="HDC3EBC9DC924404B83403355616AA6A4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a demonstrated record of a reduction in recidivism rates, if available;</text></clause><clause id="H32AC3F46C154460C8B639CB7DE7FBA98"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>success in securing employment, if available;</text></clause><clause id="H6978498700A949B6883EB95477ACFEE2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>employment retention, if available;</text></clause><clause id="HCE03193AD0134F3DACAB2436D122F343"><enum>(v)</enum><text>housing stability, if available; and</text></clause><clause id="HC9F840B7B9214F798F8708B08C095217"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>other relevant factors; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBF5FECDBF7C64C6197A5CA69D776C188"><enum>(B)</enum><text>give preference to eligible providers that demonstrate success in the categories described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H4004435D08294AE4A333F4A768635BD2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Diploma mills</header><text>The Assistant Director will prevent diploma mills (as defined in section 103 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1003">20 U.S.C. 1003</external-xref>)) from participating in the Program.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F25839498814D6DAFAB86DD5DA0A3D4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Participation by eligible providers</header><paragraph id="H6F537096E3BF4576B437D47579E151A5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible provider that desires to participate in the Program under this section shall—</text><subparagraph id="H4C11F3EED77546D69183FE7D7B0845DD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>develop a quality program, in coordination with the Federal correctional facility with which the institution is in partnership, for eligible students, in which the Federal correctional facility shall administer the logistics of the program, such as—</text><clause id="H5196F47F36BE43D19F0B31A05BD6A6BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>scheduling;</text></clause><clause id="H6845EFBC9889413FBABB39CAABF96055"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>location and space;</text></clause><clause id="HCF70FC65CF314CF88BFE41E060F8AB4F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>security; and</text></clause><clause id="HEAA79C9EF640429C8B7D1A8D94438E36"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other logistical factors;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90E87A30628F4CF2BC51A9BCFFB14748"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that all eligible students without a regular high school diploma or its recognized equivalent receive adult literacy, basic adult education, skills development, and education toward a regular high school diploma or its recognized equivalent; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0B28B21DDC194AC6AE611C201E7F66C2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>prioritize workforce development programs that prepare eligible students for in-demand sectors or occupations from which they are not legally barred from entering due to restrictions on formerly incarcerated individuals obtaining any necessary licenses or certifications for those occupations, and in doing so, providers shall—</text><clause id="HB7FE53E34C204796A49DC46277B96567"><enum>(i)</enum><text>consider State licensing requirements, administrative barriers, and waiver provisions that will impact eligible students in certain occupations when designing their programs; and</text></clause><clause id="H4676D7199CAC4204A467BBBD45288B14"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>inform eligible students prior to participation in programs of potential prohibitions or limitations to licensing or employment upon release depending on the program offered and the States in which eligible students settle.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA471471B43AD42D0AD11A91314AAA1AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information to eligible students</header><text>Eligible providers that participate in the Program under this section shall, as applicable—</text><subparagraph id="H16F29B6B0BD3400C85F6ECECF9471106"><enum>(A)</enum><text>disclose to eligible students and the Office of Prison Education information about any part of the academic program developed under this section that, by design, cannot be completed while a student is incarcerated, as well as the options available for an eligible student to complete any remaining program requirements post-release;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF60BAA905B214CC8B203C5D49D57D7CA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>offer eligible students who are released while enrolled in an education program in prison education the opportunity to continue the students’ enrollment in the academic program and transfer credits earned;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA8C8EE1A5CB429FB5DAE9E77F68B97B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>inform eligible students of the academic and financial aid options available if the eligible students are not able to complete the academic program while incarcerated, including whether the eligible students can continue in the program after release, transfer credits earned in the program to another program offered by the institution, or transfer credits earned in the program to another institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7A28B13724F4D1798CFBE7059A51F08"><enum>(D)</enum><text>for eligible students who wish to continue their education upon release—</text><clause id="H1214269A6F16479AB8F5CF0A9248D9DB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>offer academic advising; and</text></clause><clause id="H501ED22C03524F3CA17A0FF7CEDC5893"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>offer appropriate financial aid counseling, including Federal and State financial aid and student loan counseling; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDD15AC1050948E5B66F6070E1C44FB2"><enum>(E)</enum><text>offer eligible students career counseling and job placement assistance upon completion of an education program in prison and release from custody.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7894F00F9AAA48C9856562242B40A45E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Information to the Office of Prison Education</header><text>An eligible provider that participates in the Program under this section shall submit to the Assistant Director—</text><subparagraph id="H2DAD27A390A044AB803444B0B2B753AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a plan for providing academic and career guidance to eligible students, as well as transition services, to support successful community reintegration of such students; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H143DBE240D8B4464872D4E08FE434A5F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>relevant information about the eligible students participating in the Program it relates to subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD34D63FB5ADB4356B8BEC3947D740957"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Assistant Director shall work with relevant Federal agencies to provide technical assistance to eligible providers, and the Federal correctional facilities with which they are in partnership, developing new quality academic programs for eligible students, or expanding existing programs.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEBBA7CFF84C44BA68A587A1C6D35E746"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual report</header><paragraph id="HD550956773464949B7A8D7C99D2AA2C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An eligible provider that participates in the Program, working with the Federal correctional facility with which it is in partnership, shall submit to the Assistant Director an annual report on the provider’s academic program for eligible students, including implementation and results.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22C8ADAF1ED6474A9378B6B788976E7F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents of report</header><text>Each annual report submitted under paragraph (1) shall include information on—</text><subparagraph id="HF61AE33890BE403FB5DC8DF8FB4B3898"><enum>(A)</enum><text>courses and programs offered;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCD5D01F37EBC46B38FA4DB7B478650BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>numbers, rates, and types of certificates and degrees awarded;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7BAE8614B1F945F2BE4BCF4AD18086D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the partnership with the Federal correctional facility, including information on space allocation, resources, staffing, and other relevant information on effective collaboration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H974DF530ACC44FC8B1C443A8A9D8338F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the effectiveness of the various education program’s length, and the value of credentials or degrees earned with different credit length;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9C2C5343967F493486480549C9AD7F8B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the variance of different doses or credit length by educational program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A7CAA5716594DDBA25BC457AEE9566A"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the models of instruction, curriculum, and other characteristics of program delivery that are most effective in a correctional environment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B0BF9B7D38A4E4B80AFBD53A45DBEA9"><enum>(G)</enum><text>challenges in providing programs and courses in the prison settings;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A77DC44B0BA4B8CB1280324E6B10BD9"><enum>(H)</enum><text>how such challenges were addressed;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68D2968D126F459C95B0A8E7D02F2BF1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>suggestions for the agency to assist in addressing such challenges;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFBCE926DC30441C92B9E228F0A3D792"><enum>(J)</enum><text>impacts on the environment and safety of the correctional facility;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D31CF044BE34E6ABAAA8624915812E2"><enum>(K)</enum><text>average and projected costs, overall and per student, of the programs and courses offered by the eligible provider;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF22DEA5B223E4F88A1872BFC05F66D24"><enum>(L)</enum><text>student demographic data, including age, gender, race, ethnicity, and security or custody level; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB4797D169DA47BCA2DDFE808836DF7F"><enum>(M)</enum><text>other relevant data.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H253F79A5FEA8457AA420EA811B8D0B6A"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><paragraph id="H2BDA201217184354A73E3C146E55C3F7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Assistant Director, in coordination with the National Institute of Justice, the Bureau of Justice Statistics, the National Institute of Corrections, and the Secretary of Education, shall conduct an evaluation of the Program that assesses—</text><subparagraph id="H37967785B5AC45E0840852DAF994752B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in-custody outcomes, including impacts on tickets, segregation, program participation outside of education, and continued enrollment in the Program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD9DD3A5C60244E5B4EEA7FD32CDF97F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>post-release outcomes of the Program, including—</text><clause id="HCB5733AD81DE48CA9CC78BB46E68C194"><enum>(i)</enum><text>postsecondary enrollment and continuance of education by eligible students after release;</text></clause><clause id="H4266B29CB75B408E82EEEBE0DF7D92A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>degree attainment from an institution of higher education;</text></clause><clause id="H568DC08B8EDB4D9D8C45169C7D76AC39"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>progress toward a degree in credits or time;</text></clause><clause id="H7B5D52A8BD754BE5A87CBABD1809684A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>continued participation in educational programs after release;</text></clause><clause id="HB0CCA7B587224BA8804A3867E56ED33E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>factors related to the pursuit of education, such as housing attainment; and</text></clause><clause id="HD7A0FA940E3149088CBFC5DFA4CFAB36"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>other relevant factors;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFC65E9AC80264F6AB7EFAE5574CF63A8"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the impact of the Program on safety in correctional facilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68A18B3F699146A1AEDDBE3FCF54CE8B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the demand for participation in the Program, including the size of waiting lists;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D24782E168E49B08A7793D2D44827AF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>employment outcomes of participants in the Program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H29A9CC4BD4074525B67F458CBBF34CBA"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the impact of the Program on recidivism; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BF0C52A544B4409ACF7AFDBAD684A5D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>other relevant data.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H52606E563E54482BAEDA782C161BF83E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Disaggregation</header><text>The data collected through the evaluation required under paragraph (1) shall, to the extent practicable, be disaggregated by eligible provider, to facilitate selection of eligible providers under subsection (b) by the Assistant Director in subsequent years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA61883D50AB94F0CAB67A0040337C2CA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Student outcomes</header><text>The evaluation described in paragraph (1) shall gather data on eligible students while incarcerated and for the 3- and 5- year periods post-release from incarceration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E55E00DAFDB492DAABC402C7F5D7905"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Partnership</header><text>The evaluation described in paragraph (1) shall be conducted in partnership with one or multiple external evaluators.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57E109C9EEFC4DEFB8CCCFA9F20595B5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the evaluation required under paragraph (1) is completed, the Assistant Director shall—</text><subparagraph id="H9588A75C3CCC4B088B33B7637B99498E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>submit the evaluation, including recommendations for Program improvements, to Congress; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1DE9CB0A0B74B4B9C8409F675F3F71F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>publish the evaluation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBC36E07B6B0A4F3DB4EDF822534D935B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Matching funds</header><text>The Federal share of the cost of an academic program carried out under this section may not exceed 75 percent of the total cost of the academic program.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE0F8A2725A2A4D8793BD671E7CC70D52"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Allocation of funds</header><text>For fiscal years 2024 through 2030, of the amounts appropriated to the Bureau of Prisons, $170,000,000 shall be used to carry out subsection (b).</text></subsection></section></chapter><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H280D58DC98A34B4793B530B5CAA8E4AF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendment to duties of the Bureau of Prisons</header><text>Section 4042(a) of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8B7100B61B054DBAB479EC936DFFE11D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (6)(C), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05948F3F4F1642A7A5723EF815887DDA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraph (7) as paragraph (8); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H772DD8333026427091458F662E404EEE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (6) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC5B346E83B39429685D88777BBB980C7"><paragraph id="H5B21E9D32F4249E3852E3A65F897028A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>establish the Office of Prison Education required under section 4142; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBC9E284C74A34E3699D95AA438A1E35D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Table of chapters amendment</header><text>The table of chapters for part III of title 18, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to chapter 307 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD85E5BB9637D44AB9483034FA244F1FA"><toc><multi-column-toc-entry level="section" bold="on"><toc-enum>308.</toc-enum><level-header level="section">Education</level-header><target>4141</target></multi-column-toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H0840674B7EC7433B8B11494DA1E0875B"><enum>5.</enum><header>Prison education research, polices, and best practices</header><subsection id="HAB1A3286646C4839B2D9F03C3E4ADC01"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Assistant Director, in collaboration with relevant Federal agencies, including the Department of Education, State correctional agencies, State and local correctional institutions, civil rights organizations, criminal justice organizations, and research agencies and organizations, shall establish and maintain a clearinghouse for research, policies, and best practices on quality education programs in prison.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA962FF28EC56470B9FEC880D1FDBC225"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information to the public</header><text>The Assistant Director shall maintain information and resources on the public-facing website of the Bureau of Prisons.</text></subsection></section><section id="H1FAC2BA10BC44F7892A25AE00361520A"><enum>6.</enum><header>Training and technical assistance</header><subsection id="HD19F7C144082488498F9B4CEEE41B9B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Assistant Director shall use funds available to the Bureau of Prisons to provide State correctional institutions with training and technical assistance on developing and implementing policies and procedures for quality education programs in prison.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB5EEB840CF3A49A582DE0CC5A72608F6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Partnership</header><text>Federal correctional and penal institutions with education programs in prison established under section 4143 of title 18, United States Code, as added by this Act, may partner with State and local correctional institutions and education providers located in the same State or region to facilitate training and technical assistance to improve the quality of correctional education offered in State prisons.</text></subsection></section><section id="HEF00126B97214391A136391235C9EB21"><enum>7.</enum><header>Prison education for incarcerated veterans</header><subsection id="HC4E3E088543F4BF4872EBFA0A5D8AAA2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in coordination with the Director and State correctional agencies, shall—</text><paragraph id="H707612A561224F6D886D0592CCEA7D0F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out a program of outreach to inform veterans incarcerated in a Federal or State correctional facility about potential eligibility for educational assistance under laws administered by the Secretary, including educational assistance under chapters 30 and 33 of title 38, United States Code;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDA621C0F7C94AF08D47C51F16D8D49B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that educational assistance under laws administered by the Secretary is available to a veteran who is incarcerated as described in paragraph (1) and otherwise eligible for the assistance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4E079B43A894C2CB8DBBDD61B601161"><enum>(3)</enum><text>assist each veteran who is incarcerated as described in paragraph (1) and eligible for educational assistance under a law administered by the Secretary by connecting the veteran to one or more quality education programs in prison, including the Federal Prison Education Program established under section 4143 of title 18, United States Code, as added by this Act, when the veteran is incarcerated in a Federal or State correctional facility that provides one or more education programs in prison that are approved for the use of such assistance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD569D237B58F4B69BD55346CC042A481"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide financial aid counseling related to continued educational enrollment and matriculation post-release; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CC0C984DEA7423BB7BE0F7DC1E6BF25"><enum>(5)</enum><text>compile and make available to incarcerated veterans a resource guide for incarcerated veterans that includes general information about the availability, post-release, of—</text><subparagraph id="HAA1BC7035A04417E8B1BA182EAA1EB5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>educational assistance available under laws administered by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H81C2274F5D8745FC92E43A5239AC2EA7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>job counseling, training, and placement services available under chapters 41 and 42 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H23740E4F4C624700B063477C1692636E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation on provision of educational assistance</header><paragraph id="H97E7295906D649068BD25E185797B7F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Monthly housing stipend</header><text>A veteran with a felony conviction who is incarcerated in a Federal or State correctional facility may not receive, while so incarcerated—</text><subparagraph id="H174FC27DED544871989CAF0EBE268F49"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any monthly housing stipend under section 3313 of title 38, United States Code; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE133EF7A195344A99B2D2AF3DCACDE09"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any amount under section 3014 of such title otherwise payable to help meet the veteran's subsistence costs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2685DE26D6854D9A90C26EA0F86DBBBD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Costs covered by other programs</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary shall reduce the amount of educational assistance that the Secretary would otherwise provide to a veteran described in paragraph (1) under a law administered by the Secretary for costs of tuition, fees, supplies, books, equipment, and other educational costs relating to pursuing a program of education while incarcerated by an amount equal to the amount that such costs are paid by another Federal, State, or local program.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

