<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC9D598F63131406A8023CB1480FBA908" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 3440 IH: Protecting Rural Telehealth Access Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3440</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230517">May 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to protect access to telehealth services under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H082DA283A4FB46909EEF2EAF49EE2D67" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HF6D7947A718142089C5994DB9D5134C4"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Rural Telehealth Access Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA9BD37E762CD4E189C8BBE138E1B1D5B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Elimination of restrictions relating to telehealth services</header><subsection id="HF041F319E9CE4F399413692E0149D3AE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Elimination of geographic requirements for originating sites</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1834(m)(4)(C) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)(4)(C)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8CB83F30B0964983A2E550CCF37122A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i), in the matter preceding subclause (I), by striking <quote>clause (iii)</quote> and inserting <quote>clauses (iii) and (iv)</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA92B3CD081AE49029D490B29EC58ED45"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEADA061C3696490AAB104098561356CA"><clause id="H43CDECFEDD4045FAB60CB432337D327B"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Elimination of geographic requirements for originating sites</header><text>The geographic requirements described in clause (i) shall not apply with respect to telehealth services furnished on or after January 1, 2025.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBDB77E7D0C0B4B67BEF9A8AC9A41801F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elimination of restrictions in which telehealth services may be furnished in the home</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1834(m)(4)(C)(ii)(X) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)(4)(C)(i)(X)</external-xref> is amended to read as follows:.</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H94E45FFAE0554678BBF243B2B3C3CE5C"><subclause id="H286FA5C4116C4107A6488964FF463973"><enum>(X)</enum><item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7A9BAC44356E48F39791B7707F5000A9"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>For the period beginning on the date of the enactment of this subclause and ending on December 31, 2024, the home of an individual but only for purposes of section 1881(b)(3)(B) or telehealth services described in paragraph (7).</text></item><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6CBE4010F4ED400794763E6D83E17894" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>For the period beginning on or after January 1, 2025, the home of an individual.</text></item></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H265184A536754CAEB973556CDAA8167B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Elimination of restrictions on store-and-Forward technologies</header><text>The second sentence of section 1834(m)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>in the case of any Federal telemedicine demonstration program conducted in Alaska or Hawaii,</quote>.</text></subsection></section><section id="HCD2ACF63796540688A95AC985F951759"><enum>3.</enum><header>Telehealth flexibilities for critical access hospitals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1834(m) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC50AE78A55A94EE8BCEF322EAA9FD461"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the first sentence of paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and (9)</quote> and inserting <quote>(9), and (10)</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H30C938DA492E4E9D9FAD0692831A93B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2)(A), by striking <quote>paragraph (8)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (8) and (10)</quote>; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7985200D634C428F9F47CCB7A7A790B2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (4)—</text><subparagraph id="H9BBFAF0C7AF648D6A86C45E3B4401A4E"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>paragraph (8)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (8) and (10)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2ACF4091A6684F72B8854458858F2188"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (F)(i), by striking <quote>paragraph (8)</quote> and inserting <quote>paragraphs (8) and (10)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7850978B22C54EAF8FD6083FCB7617D6"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following new paragraph: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1B082995012042009FCDB7D5517F7C32"><paragraph id="HC58D2C945E9A482DBFD611B81B5C0276"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Telehealth flexibilities for critical access hospitals</header><subparagraph id="HC473C83BDB7045369B8EA1938D31C1D4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On or after the date of the enactment of this paragraph—</text><clause id="HBB18198ADF0F4FD79A63013336BD9F17"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary shall pay for telehealth services that are furnished via a telecommunications system by a critical access hospital, including any practitioner authorized to provide such services within the facility, that is a qualified provider (as defined in subparagraph (B)) to an eligible telehealth individual enrolled under this part notwithstanding that the critical access hospital providing the telehealth service is not at the same location as the beneficiary, if such services complement a plan of care that includes in-person care at some point, as may be appropriate;</text></clause><clause id="H41DEB1D38AD448EA84AD1BCA4A11BD97"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the amount of payment to a critical access hospital that serves as a distant site for such a telehealth service shall be determined under subparagraph (C); and</text></clause><clause id="HC67F2306B10A45F0BE81EAC244F6972E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for purposes of this subsection—</text><subclause id="HA4FFDCB8A62B4E9F8E8B4FC54B4AE947"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the term <term>distant site</term> includes a critical access hospital that furnishes a telehealth service to an eligible telehealth individual; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA45DCD2F019049E58C33D9E4887A346F"><enum>(II)</enum><text> the term <term>telehealth services</term> includes behavioral health services and any other outpatient critical access hospital service that is furnished using telehealth to the extent that payment codes corresponding to services identified by the Secretary under clause (i) or (ii) of paragraph (4)(F) are listed on the corresponding claim for such critical access hospital service.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2CB6071DD8F7497EB41707A40E6B0545"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Definition of qualified provider</header><text>For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>qualified provider</term> means, with respect to a telehealth service described in subparagraph (A)(i) that is furnished to an eligible telehealth individual, a critical access hospital that has an established patient relationship with such individual as defined by the State in which the individual is located.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B1251F6C06742DE9A8ECE7A653356D8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Payment</header><text>The amount of payment to a critical access hospital that serves as a distant site that furnishes a telehealth service to an eligible telehealth individual under this paragraph shall be equal to 101 percent of the reasonable costs of the hospital in providing such services, unless the hospital makes an election under paragraph (2) of section 1834(g) to be paid for such services based on the methodology described in such paragraph. Telehealth services furnished by a critical access hospital shall be counted for purposes of determining the provider productivity rate of the critical access hospital for purposes of payment under such section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H375EA350CB1B40EC842CB0D9FD2A9E5E"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary may implement this paragraph through program instruction, interim final rule, or otherwise.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H3561BC37187E4C01B3F745FDD11BF200"><enum>4.</enum><header>Extending Medicare telehealth flexibilities for Federally qualified health centers and rural health clinics</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1834(m)(8) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)(8)</external-xref>), as amended by section 4113(c) of division FF of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H561F2C9FDFD94A5DBD55F5DAB10984C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), in the matter preceding clause (i), by inserting <quote>, and on or after January 1, 2025</quote> after <quote>December 31, 2024</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6F9EEA637AC4AD187A9AE5D9575AD58"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking subparagraph (B) and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B00509D0039442198D5313C6204825E"><subparagraph id="H1A8AC182BC0842818CBA78E01421917B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Payment</header><clause id="H896D687D57344DE7B2C6351AB282B213"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A telehealth service furnished by a Federally qualified health center or a rural health clinic to an eligible telehealth individual pursuant to this paragraph or after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph shall be reimbursed under this title at a separate telehealth payment rate as determined under the methodology established by the Secretary pursuant to clause (ii).</text></clause><clause id="H41F40769E085406396ED6862DD76F9CB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Payment methodology</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a methodology for determining the appropriate payment rate for telehealth services described in clause (i). Such methodology shall consider—</text><subclause id="HCA1CAE180D8A49198F079F2FCFB9F724"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the geography of Federally qualified health centers and rural health clinics;</text></subclause><subclause id="HEBD5C79393F94DEA931AD0D9AF1566A9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>costs associated with the delivery of such telehealth services as allowable costs for the center or clinic; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H2484B4214FFA4C33B6A39FC53C7C2B54"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the full cost of providing the services via telehealth.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H33F087E738454601B81C479CD887219B"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Implementation</header><subclause id="H679092C879B64C3890E1237B30A6103B"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Coding system</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an effective coding system for telehealth services described in clause (i) that is reflective of the services provided at a center or clinic.</text></subclause><subclause id="HBAB8D3B78887483E98A31EA88A19FE09"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary may implement this subparagraph through program instruction, interim final rule, or otherwise.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1265CE9362A448A998811C4DAC0D08AB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBB44CB9524744B71902C94826E22B791"><subparagraph commented="no" id="H57F8D4C5053D44909B15D7154CC273CA"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Requirement during additional period</header><clause commented="no" id="H89639993CA77420C8710827647D83E69"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning on January 1, 2025, payment may only be made under this paragraph for a telehealth service described in subparagraph (A)(i) that is furnished to an eligible telehealth individual if such service is furnished by a qualified provider (as defined in clause (ii)).</text></clause><clause id="H9188125F3E4A4981B350095FF4B8B55F"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Definition of qualified provider</header><text>For purposes of this subparagraph, the term <term>qualified provider</term> means, with respect to a telehealth service described in subparagraph (A)(i) that is furnished to an eligible telehealth individual, a Federally qualified health center or rural health clinic that has an established patient relationship with such individual as defined by the State in which the individual is located.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H120B996D0DEB48ED9204E0D47BC1D469"><enum>5.</enum><header>Allowance of certain telehealth services furnished using audio-only technology</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1834(m)(4) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)(4)</external-xref>) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)(4)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAEBB2E4223574626B00CAA7A9C555D7F"><subparagraph id="HF181C8418D2348E89DC138FBABCA3E00"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Telecommunications system</header><clause id="H8BFEBD3E13464256960FF7ECF0B4D336"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraph (1) and section 410.78(a)(3) of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation), subject to clause (v), on or after January, 2025, the term <term>telecommunications system</term> includes, in the case of the furnishing of a specified telehealth service (as defined in clause (ii)) a communications system that uses audio-only technology.</text></clause><clause id="H98D3BF176D38483D9CDE399157516457"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Specified telehealth service</header><text>In this subparagraph, the term <term>specified telehealth service</term> means a telehealth service described in clause (iii) that is furnished by a qualified provider (as defined in clause (iv)).</text></clause><clause id="HBDB955012E2E4C169A619C0C2951110A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Telehealth service described</header><text>Subject to clause (vi), a telehealth service described in this clause is a telehealth service consisting of—</text><subclause id="HF6E2DD7AB1E74E92889DC9C29ACD18BD"><enum>(I)</enum><text>evaluation and management services;</text></subclause><subclause id="H472C0DA35C3A408FB2C616CD92587000"><enum>(II)</enum><text>behavioral health counseling and educational services; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H88872D3648294755867D5FCB1AD33481"><enum>(III)</enum><text>other services determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H2B06373724164B6DA803CBBABB086BEA"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Qualified provider defined</header><text>For purposes of clause (ii), the term <term>qualified provider</term> means, with respect to a specified telehealth service that is furnished to an eligible telehealth individual—</text><subclause id="HE5AF2E0A1E214D34A76C0FE02ECBDF1B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a physician or practitioner who has an established patient relationship with such individual as defined by the State in which the individual is located; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H89B9BD2D590C4566971F3E9682D1F07C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a critical access hospital (as defined in section 1861(mm)(1)), a rural health clinic (as defined in section 1861(aa)(2)), a Federally qualified health center (as defined in section 1861(aa)(4)), a hospital (as defined in section 1861(e)), a hospital-based or critical access hospital-based renal dialysis center (including satellites), a skilled nursing facility (as defined in section 1819(a)), a community mental health center (as defined in section 1861(ff)(3)(B)), or a rural emergency hospital (as defined in section 1861(kkk)(2)).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H048647188A664221B7780089E1DBC9F2"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subparagraph, the Secretary may determine whether it is clinically appropriate to furnish a specified telehealth service via a communications system that uses audio-only technology and whether an in-person initial visit (in addition to any requirement with respect to the furnishing of an item or service in person pursuant to clause (iv)(I)) is required prior to the furnishing of such service using such technology.</text></clause><clause id="H3846D121DD33477382330F7D777AE8CD"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Review</header><subclause id="HE2A22FB21E3941D9834A876B3A0F25D8"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph, the Secretary shall conduct a review of the furnishing of specified telehealth services through audio-only technology pursuant to this paragraph. Such review shall include an analysis of the impact of the roll out of broadband technology and whether the use of audio-only technology is necessary to ensure access to such telehealth services.</text></subclause><subclause id="HDA150403F64948F4B3E7092A046819FC"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Redetermination of specified telehealth services</header><text>The Secretary may, based on the review conducted under subclause (I), provide for the addition or deletion of services (and HCPCS codes), as appropriate, to those specified in clause (ii) that may be furnished using audio-only technology and authorized for payment pursuant to this subparagraph.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HFBE17785EF044251938EB4DF8126C086"><enum>(vii)</enum><header>Clarification regarding payment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of payment for a specified telehealth service that is furnished using audio-only technology shall be equal to the amount that would have been paid for such service under this subsection had such service been furnished via any other telecommunications system authorized under this subsection.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="HE3DED5FDC06347BBBF1400E2EAE4801E"><enum>6.</enum><header>Sense of Congress regarding expansion of eligible practitioners that may furnish telehealth services</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the expansion of eligible practitioners that may furnish telehealth services (as defined in section 1834(m)(4)(F) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395m">42 U.S.C. 1395m(m)(4)(F)</external-xref>)) during the emergency period described in section 1135(g)(1)(B) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-5">42 U.S.C. 1320b–5(g)(1)(B)</external-xref>) should be extended on a permanent basis. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

