<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5366029906A745F09C72952C57831F7D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4796 IH: Reproductive Health Patient Navigator Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4796</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Mrs. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000468">Mrs. Fletcher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001223">Mrs. Sykes</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a grant program to fund reproductive health patient navigators for individuals seeking abortion services.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9758F000AC9B4499962BD6E3239F8EB1" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HE6130274716C40E69663EBD4B7A4E63C"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reproductive Health Patient Navigator Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDDAF08697CAC42DC97B00162F4F1E02A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="H7FA9535C934A4EC2924AB34D4AD29839"><enum>(1)</enum><text>As the legal hurdles to abortion services increase, so does the complexity of navigating access to these essential reproductive health services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4235FD8C34C848A3823785A42A70E7A9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Community-based organizations like abortion funds are connecting people to abortions, by working with individuals to navigate an ever-evolving landscape of reproductive health care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF582161761A04C438656F103E6E172A8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Abortion funds have been helping individuals navigate the complexity of abortion services for decades and are well placed to lead patient navigation programs. </text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="H6501F7C486034470B6973F07834EB2DB"><enum>3.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment of grant program for reproductive health patient navigators</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subpart V of part D of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/256">42 U.S.C. 256 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3FA3187A1EC94C7787272D250608511E"><section id="H7F238E2145034737BA640279B108D4CA"><enum>340A–1.</enum><header>Establishment of grant program for reproductive health patient navigators</header><subsection id="H58B721F4741340E28E3C7FE001D05795"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a grant program to support eligible entities for purposes of serving as reproductive health patient navigators for individuals seeking to access abortion services in order to connect those individuals to abortion services. </text></subsection><subsection id="H23A38A792E61493DB02C82089A37F4F2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under this section, an entity shall—</text><paragraph id="H99B3A18A59954B329FBAF0711A885AEA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be an abortion fund or other nonprofit organization, a community-based organization, a State, local governmental entity, or Tribal government that, through programs, services, or activities that are unbiased and medically- and factually-accurate, assists individuals seeking abortion services; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6B0EB5A69184C368770F76819268F12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit an application to the Secretary, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including a plan for—</text><subparagraph id="H21B8E000EA42461BB4E6768B99EB60F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establishing and operating a program of patient navigator services to help individuals seeking abortion services access abortion services, as described in subsection (c); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDAB243BE69B40C8A5B1FDE66FDEA44C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensuring that any personally identifiable patient data obtained through the operation of such program is kept confidential.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC3C42C1E8EEE41EFB2222631663E40B2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under this section shall use such funds for one or more of the following activities related to abortion services:</text><paragraph id="H3350A3BD14DE49678BA77FEF9755755D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Offering individuals seeking abortion services medically-accurate, culturally- and linguistically-appropriate services and resources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H600E4217CA2A466B83A4FF925A0EDB06"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Coordinating financing resources for travel-related costs, including transportation, childcare, and lodging.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B5D8826BD574FD6A171CBA2F48A954F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Coordinating abortion services, including identifying available abortion providers and scheduling appointments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5BD21338D8442DA867C442E4C45A8C0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Providing emotional wellness and doula support to individuals accessing abortion services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50ED19EF32AA4E66A61140A0F4190B9B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Providing individuals seeking abortion services with unbiased and medically and factually accurate reproductive health information to support individuals' informed decision-making.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88EF11C27FBD438CB273EF9106AFE61A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Developing partnerships with local community organizations providing services for which eligible entity provides assistance, abortion service providers, and other patient navigators, such as patient navigators receiving grants under section 340A.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H044EF23292C447D59A0E936DC4A87061"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Assisting with understanding reimbursement and health insurance coverage options, including completing eligibility and enrollment forms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1563700B3BD949A29D2B8A85E766F772"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Assisting with understanding where abortion services are legal and the ways in which abortion services may be restricted.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H3F6005E644E04612A5B231EFE9712B01"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Patient navigator protections</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H7240F5486BED4D7C8F8A95236A53E78F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No individual, entity, or State may prevent, restrict, impede, or disadvantage an entity eligible to receive a grant under this section by nature of delivering services described in subsection (c), or any affiliate of such an entity or individual or other entity collaborating with such an entity, from—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H6A1C78FE2044434C9254B8D963080D64"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing or assisting a health care provider, or any other person, with eligible services described in subsection (c) related to reproductive health care services—</text><clause commented="no" id="H17AE41EF5FF443FC8B2F9313BCBA6D7C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>lawful in the State in which services are to be provided; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H6683A4B074C34BADA78809EAAB184EBB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provided for an individual who does not reside in the State in which the services are to be provided; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4403A8FBBED14199BFFB69450BBED703"><enum>(B)</enum><text>carrying out the activities described in this section in any State, including any State in which abortion services are not lawful. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDDE2BB192E54E0C877D7E8CFFE5549B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><subparagraph id="H51ECE26563D54E97A5F9D8517B982AE7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Attorney General</header><text>The Attorney General may commence a civil action on behalf of the United States against any State, or against any government official, individual, or entity that enacts, implements, or enforces a limitation or requirement that violates paragraph (1). The court shall hold unlawful and set aside the limitation or requirement if it is in violation of paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H31B66601212B4E2C9421003A6DF73399"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Private right of action</header><text>Any reproductive health patient navigator adversely affected by an alleged violation of paragraph (1) may commence a civil action against any State that violates this subsection, against any government official that enacts, implements, or enforces a limitation or requirement that violates paragraph (1), or against any individual who, pursuant to State law, prevents, restricts, impedes, or disadvantages the entity from carrying out activities in violation of paragraph (1). The court shall hold unlawful and enjoin the limitation or requirement if it is in violation of paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H61B208C856C246B59163C17872CC47EB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Equitable relief</header><text>In any action under this subsection, the court may award appropriate equitable relief, including temporary, preliminary, or permanent injunctive relief.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27FC202C6A2246949ADC37BE42499843"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Costs</header><text>In any action under this subsection, the court shall award costs of litigation, as well as reasonable attorney’s fees, to any prevailing plaintiff. A plaintiff shall not be liable to a defendant for costs or attorney’s fees in any nonfrivolous action under this subsection.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0973B05C6AB742D6B07D26A2DAEEDA00"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>The district courts of the United States shall have jurisdiction over proceedings under this subsection and shall exercise the same without regard to whether the party aggrieved shall have exhausted any administrative or other remedies that may be provided for by law.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD136A02146F34A2BB9180D372E1B50B3"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Abrogation of State immunity</header><text>Neither a State that enforces or maintains, nor a government official who is permitted to implement or enforce, any limitation or requirement that violates paragraph (1) shall be immune under the Tenth Amendment to the Constitution of the United States, the Eleventh Amendment to the Constitution of the United States, or any other source of law, from an action in a Federal or State court of competent jurisdiction challenging that limitation or requirement.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77EFB3723D42438184760D76BDBE66C9"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Right to remove</header><text>Any party shall have a right to remove an action brought under this subsection to the district court of the United States for the district and division embracing the place where such action is pending. An order remanding the case to the State court from which it was removed under this paragraph may be immediately reviewable by appeal or otherwise. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H71B5FC45B2B34F60B2C311DAC312C2D8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>There are appropriated, for fiscal years 2023 through 2027, out of amounts in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, such sums as may be necessary for purposes of carrying out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

