<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC71D058703164AA3A3367DAAB57D80E9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3192 IH: PFAS Registry Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3192</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to establish and maintain a registry for certain individuals who may have been exposed to per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances due to the environmental release of aqueous film-forming foam on military installations.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4ED551905D7E46C7804A0C386D79ECC3" style="OLC"><section id="H22F78280EDA045AABB1D0780B373ADF9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>PFAS Registry Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H02B8F1CC531D427DA6DB3062EE4533B1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Registry of individuals exposed to per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances on military installations</header><subsection id="H089F5D5A345F43DB9336D91F113C9896"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of registry</header><paragraph id="HDE615AA277704E1AB89EE3AF1DDFCBB1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall—</text><subparagraph id="H851EAEFE99E9487A8FDA61875303F541"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish and maintain a registry for eligible individuals who may have been exposed to per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (in this section referred to as <quote>PFAS</quote>) due to the environmental release of aqueous film-forming foam (in this section referred to as <quote>AFFF</quote>) on military installations to meet the requirements of military specification MIL–F–24385F;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5013432BDF14298925BDD35C44FA70D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>include any information in such registry that the Secretary of Veterans Affairs determines necessary to ascertain and monitor the health effects of the exposure of members of the Armed Forces to PFAS associated with AFFF;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52227D8C420F4E63BA2655A03745C9C7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>develop a public information campaign to inform eligible individuals about the registry, including how to register and the benefits of registering; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB83A02E09172408FBE5FB78B1340B735"><enum>(D)</enum><text>periodically notify eligible individuals of significant developments in the study and treatment of conditions associated with exposure to PFAS.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H66FD9D8CB8FC463FB3E62800BDEA1E76"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall coordinate with the Secretary of Defense in carrying out paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H54169DC1D9F144FBA3BCC3FB32B89C01"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="HBD26046699BE4787BB11B0D6BD31C079"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date on which the registry under subsection (a) is established, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to Congress an initial report containing the following:</text><subparagraph id="H8AEF97F08CD547F389AE203F1D3850E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An assessment of the effectiveness of actions taken by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Secretary of Defense to collect and maintain information on the health effects of exposure to PFAS.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF40DD0C33E9B43E9B1DABCA8E6307C1D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Recommendations to improve the collection and maintenance of such information.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC775D43B4C5244EF92EEAE2E21285D7F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Using established and previously published epidemiological studies, recommendations regarding the most effective and prudent means of addressing the medical needs of eligible individuals with respect to exposure to PFAS.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A18146214754C13A40BD2448DD19531"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Follow-up report</header><text>Not later than five years after submitting the initial report under paragraph (1), the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to Congress a follow-up report containing the following:</text><subparagraph id="H21D3D43A21E941BF9E6F96540CC823FA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>An update to the initial report submitted under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCA925342E638406281867B39AB3FB378"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An assessment of whether and to what degree the content of the registry established under subsection (a) is current and scientifically up-to-date.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HABFFD444C14F4B96B75C394FE575F60F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Independent scientific organization</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall enter into an agreement with an independent scientific organization to prepare the reports under paragraphs (1) and (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDE8B8E1A364B49C2830B68273454FD17"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Recommendations for additional exposures To be included</header><text>Not later than five years after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every five years thereafter, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense and the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, shall submit to Congress recommendations for additional chemicals with respect to which individuals exposed to such chemicals should be included in the registry established under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC31D4AEA28F4DD8B36328E9ED627216"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible individual defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible individual</term> means any individual who, on or after a date specified by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs through regulations, served or is serving in the Armed Forces at a military installation where AFFF was used or at another location of the Department of Defense where AFFF was used.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

