<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H51A636C167434E76B53F488A4C18483E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5834 IH: Johanna’s Law Reauthorization Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5834</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230929">September 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to reauthorize Johanna&#8217;s Law, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB8500D6FE62547029166E1A5E51CAACB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H395F80B0925F4F99943378C57CB39AAB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Johanna’s Law Reauthorization Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HCAD6BA5A438043708FBE505C68B5B2B7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reauthorization and enhancement of Johanna’s Law</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 317P(d) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247b-17">42 U.S.C. 247b–17(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H187CF7F6F40F4E34AF792C90FE303C0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HB54214C06C99465E90053AFC07A745FD" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="HA9CB0E23251E479399A1F57D1B25C5FB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Activities under the national campaign under subparagraph (A) shall include public service announcements using traditional or digital media under subparagraph (C) targeted to specific higher-risk populations of women based on race, ethnicity, level of acculturation, and family history, including the African-American and Ashkenazi Jewish populations.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44FD3468E3B941FEA0DE20094263481C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (6) to read as follows:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1D29D434E66B434BBB08152EFD975D3E" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H5EBBF8755CB24050A94CE59923C1CBF4"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose of carrying out this subsection, there is authorized to be appropriated $45,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2026.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H13C90D8B2DDB4C2DB7BC84F4876C8550"><enum>3.</enum><header>Demonstration projects regarding outreach and education strategies relating to gynecologic cancer</header> 
<subsection id="HF67656BC2222471A851DC92E08B8319D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 317P(d) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247b-17">42 U.S.C. 247b–17(d)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after paragraph (4) the following new paragraph:</text> <quoted-block id="HB4A9FB62363847E691AC1B308E723914" style="OLC"> <paragraph id="H7B2C0C17AD0145329966AF391EBA9F69"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Demonstration projects regarding outreach and education strategies</header> <subparagraph id="H9F70C6A1C50E4BF39A68D9D580850DA4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header> <clause id="H2489652CB53C4704877121DC2AA737FE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The Secretary may carry out a program to award grants or contracts to public or nonprofit private entities for the purpose of carrying out demonstration projects to test, compare, and evaluate different evidence-based outreach and education strategies to increase the awareness and knowledge of women and health care providers with respect to gynecologic cancers, including with respect to early warning signs, risk factors, prevention, screening, and treatment options. Such strategies shall include efforts directed at women and their families, physicians, nurses, and key health professionals.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HAAFC2F1318674DA08F2585D252DDC9AC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Science-based resources</header><text>In making awards under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall encourage awardees to use science-based resources such as the Inside Knowledge About Gynecologic Cancer education campaign of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7D5FD7CAE00F48EDB64126C6C57A9CA5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Preferences in awarding grants or contracts</header><text>In making awards under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall give preference to—</text> 
<clause id="H3D7398A35AF3489E89F3C4ED997AE988"><enum>(i)</enum><text>applicants with demonstrated expertise in gynecologic cancer education or treatment or in working with groups of women who are at increased risk of gynecologic cancers; and</text></clause> <clause id="H1974A680088D49ECAA375FB68485EC2F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>applicants that, in the demonstration project funded by the grant or contract, will establish linkages between physicians, nurses, and key health professionals, health profession students, hospitals, payers, and State health departments.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7205B32FE7384D1DB7BA36F6508BEB92"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Application</header><text>To seek a grant or contract under subparagraph (A), an entity shall submit an application to the Secretary in such form, in such manner, and containing such agreements, assurances, and information as the Secretary determines to be necessary to carry out this paragraph.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAED875962E0B4DFB9F94C2B26A4543A4"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Certain requirements</header><text>In making awards under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall—</text> 
<clause id="HD76B7F6926BD4DE1A872A711571874D3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>make awards, as practicable, to not fewer than five applicants; and</text></clause> <clause id="H5E733E016A1D42D3B0CF4EA9CDA100FC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure that information provided through demonstration projects under this paragraph is consistent with the best available medical information.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H6C9E1D6C44DF4B7693930080C7F6CD1F"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Report to congress</header><text>Not later than 24 months after the date of the enactment of this paragraph, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress a report that—</text> <clause id="H512EBBD240EF48C78D7DDD2E736C197C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>summarizes the activities of demonstration projects under subparagraph (A);</text></clause> 
<clause id="H3A333C5BB5D34456818A7560B43C7254"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>evaluates the extent to which the projects were effective in increasing awareness and knowledge of risk factors and early warning signs in the populations to which the projects were directed; and</text></clause> <clause id="HA9A5A382C8CF44FC9A4EA3BAB1DA89D8"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>identifies barriers to early detection and appropriate treatment of such cancers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H440162122FFD46CCAEA576A46358FB3F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 317P(d)(3)(A) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247b-17">42 U.S.C. 247b–17(d)(3)(A)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>(other than paragraph (5))</quote> after <quote>this section</quote>.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

