<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H056ECA852C2C4FF4B9F8D61884AB5F75" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4703 IH: Health Impacts of Nuclear War Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4703</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230718">July 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require research into the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB5615D4F7F7140A98D88E0E25A85FD10" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H5D017AB2679E4709B83C541B322F5273" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Health Impacts of Nuclear War Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H45ADE835819843D8AA5358D2FFFCEF3F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text>
<paragraph id="H225969EDDD424A0DA5E4EB0F35C767D7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>nuclear weapons explosions would have devastating health impacts, including immediate radiation exposure, thermal burns, and blast injuries;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H46110A99D52C4B7BA1E37ED63B765958"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a large body of scientific literature suggests that the impacts of wide-spread nuclear weapons explosions are likely to extend well beyond the immediate effect of the explosions and may include long-lasting and catastrophic environmental effects, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H00701CA0173E46EBAD6D47C699829C0D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the generation of vast quantities of soot as a result of firestorms generated by nuclear explosions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3D7A1660E9CC478697B51E0972DECFA8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the injection of such soot into the stratosphere;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H90D1BE3CA4AA4C608EEEB927BCEAC6F6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a significant reduction in sunlight reaching the Earth’s surface as a result of such soot, causing a significant reduction in Earth’s surface temperatures, substantial changes to precipitation and ocean circulation patterns, and a dramatic decrease in crop and fisheries yields; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H908E19CC92094647AAFFD20888B835F1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>damage to the ozone layer as a result of such soot, causing increased ultraviolet radiation at the Earth’s surface;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H62F33291D190409DB9EC44EAE2E3BA1C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such an environmental catastrophe could impact the United States even if the nuclear weapons explosions were outside the United States;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4BF0222698AE4D6FA2E19B823BB15D0A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the health consequences of such an environmental catastrophe would be severe and long-lasting and may include—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9018A29BD2C04F9499F5FE77DD5716BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increased cancer rates as a result of higher ultra-violet radiation levels or radioactive fallout;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA52B50997B72426DAAA2AFEBF14F38F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>malnutrition as a result of decreases in agricultural and fisheries productivity after an abrupt reduction in sunlight;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC7915B70F7A34FEF94CF75703D71602A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>infectious disease spread due to deteriorated public health concerns and compromised immunity; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H60AF1E8444EE48EDB82FC7F84A77297B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>hypothermia, frostbite, and other consequences of exposure to extreme cold; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2B4016C39EFE46018856A7C38208F31A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>other, cascading effects, such as consequences of widespread damage to critical infrastructure;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63CEFC6C31334B69A67C3C86426776B0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>such health consequences may be even more damaging and long-lasting than the initial impact of nuclear explosions, and the prospects for recovery from such consequences are currently unclear;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF001FF27020D4F03A71B28B66FBD8741"><enum>(6)</enum><text>such health consequences should be considered when preparing all-hazards emergency plans as a component of chemical, biological, radiological, and nuclear threats;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3609028F3E59459A942E078901E9B293"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the focus of existing Federal Government preparedness and planning for nuclear threats has primarily been on individual nuclear detonation incidents, and not on responding to the long-term environmental and health impacts; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0975DDCD02D24B2399E5133CDAFF2F05"><enum>(8)</enum><text>research into, and preparedness for, the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war is of critical importance to the national security of the United States. </text></paragraph></section> <section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="H707D1CDFB120433F87522CE6902A2C04"><enum>3.</enum><header>Health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subtitle C of title XXVIII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300hh-31">42 U.S.C. 300hh–31 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H76B97907207E435E9361A55DC585E3E2">
<section id="HC5C9E6DD5E914B1686F727ECF8C85977"><enum>2827.</enum><header>Health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war</header>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCFFD3CDD947749E587241B10F1D30512"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HCA9F682145634A1C88912C66A8D368F5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Environmental impacts of nuclear war</header><text>The term <term>environmental impacts of nuclear war</term> means changes to the environment resulting, either directly or indirectly, from the explosion of nuclear weapons, including — </text>
<subparagraph id="H462EA0EB3D2D4C7D8924CE70552F4FA4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the generation of vast quantities of soot as a result of firestorms generated by nuclear explosions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEC936C515F2E46FCAEB95BFDAE43F0F3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the injection of such soot into the stratosphere;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE1FD2B85F72F414586C17C6E482594A9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a significant reduction in sunlight reaching the Earth’s surface as a result of such soot, causing a significant reduction in Earth’s surface temperatures, substantial changes to precipitation and ocean circulation patterns, and a dramatic decrease in crop and fisheries yields; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H37FAA71B761348F19B5E18BD06B73157"><enum>(D)</enum><text>damage to the ozone layer as a result of such soot, causing increased ultraviolet radiation at the Earth’s surface; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAC8A1457B3DD4F00813C8ECAEA1470DF"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other impacts, as determined by the Secretary. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H99543B7BD10C4F0D8A5DB2E36CD5D3B7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war</header><text>The term <term>health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war</term> means adverse effects on the physical or mental well-being of individuals resulting, either directly or indirectly, from environmental impacts of nuclear war, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5DD0D9593B6046E39EDC5055EC8D801E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increased cancer rates as a result of higher ultra-violet radiation levels or radioactive fallout;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H194052494DA74DC7BE98354023A86DC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>malnutrition as a result of decreases in agricultural and fisheries productivity after an abrupt reduction in sunlight;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6C8B9B8201A4439C8C4C59B71AABC6D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>infectious disease spread due to deteriorated public health conditions and compromised immunity, including due to malnutrition;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H42BA436913D04A4E9D79CA84F7930E20"><enum>(D)</enum><text>hypothermia, frostbite, and other consequences of exposure to extreme cold; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H59468A7F1CF740F3891F5A6BE4D0B0EF"><enum>(E)</enum><text>other consequences, as determined by the Secretary. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8FFAD75000A48AF9B0330CBAB21FE3D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Nuclear war</header><text>The term <term>nuclear war</term> means military conflict involving the detonation of multiple nuclear weapons.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD53616F088BD465CA90CCB88FAA82420"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Research grants to study the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war</header>
<paragraph id="H6F2B7FADF302419081570BA5C45C2E08"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Research and preparedness program</header><text>The Secretary, in collaboration with the Director of the National Institutes of Health, the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and the Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response, shall develop and implement a 5-year research and preparedness program, which may include activities carried out by the Secretary, as well as grants, contracts, and cooperative agreements awarded to eligible entities, to address the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H94F08CD3F798440B8E617008721E8F91"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Components of research and preparedness program</header><text>The program may include—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0137F6DC16554A7C962B6A13834D8EB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>scientific study of the potential health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, including the longevity of such effects and the prospects for recovery;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1930BE1FA2984F94B308B8668CEFCE25"><enum>(B)</enum><text>exercises and drills to understand possible health system response to the environmental impacts of nuclear war;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB074028AA8364E4E881F8C4FC23DAF79"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identifying and addressing capability and capacity gaps for health system response to the environmental impacts of nuclear war; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H605045770E5A4B6EB97E7179145B07AE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>developing countermeasures to combat the health effects of the environmental impacts of nuclear war.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H130323C43D6B4BD387ED2885EA0CEA3A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant, contract, or cooperative agreement described in paragraph (1), an entity shall—</text> <subparagraph id="H4D5CB2693D1441E3B072148F936C2BB3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5FB32F0615B74382A00FDC867A9929E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a nonprofit entity;</text></clause> <clause id="H3F007D7EA3ED415FB21A356A54B20714"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a nonprofit research institution; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HFB1C1280CE384F1587947A40306791AF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an institution of higher education (as defined in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965); and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H80746CCB460F4FEFA25FBEB7586C2768"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit an application to the Secretary, at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H09E4737254D84550A8BCEC6B8161931B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out this subsection, there are authorized to be appropriated $10,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H356F3545FFC24A86B326FEF7F70383DF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assessment and recommendations by the Secretary</header> <paragraph id="H3A6CFD91C9004197A062812866097513"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>The Secretary shall conduct an assessment of the ability of the health systems of the United States to respond to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB5E78C38862E4AB5829E9A7FF0637254"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the possible health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H321AAD9A9672451BBC3A0DC8993E39D6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an assessment of existing State and Federal governmental preparedness and response authorities, capabilities, protocols, and plans to respond to the likely health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H87764D1040BE4212B68FF17427A6D417"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assessment of current countermeasures to address the range of likely health impacts in the event of environmental impacts of nuclear war;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6611CD0174D0485185716D75F13991A9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an assessment of the current scientific uncertainties relating to the environmental consequences of nuclear war, their health consequences, and their implications for preparedness;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H5156B724ACF84139A897D7B68EE41A72"><enum>(E)</enum><text>recommendations for further scientific research to address any uncertainties identified under subparagraph (D); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H61B3E5702CA244D48AE53D88A10919C2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>identification and prioritization of the most critical preparedness and response gaps of the United States to address the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H32D8568A5FEF4DF8B9BFBBA88480572D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assessment report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Health Impacts of Nuclear War Act of 2023</short-title>, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report that contains the findings of the study conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4C597ECD47A74762A9C919B539F829EC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In carrying out the assessment under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall coordinate with the following:</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6EF00E37C176462FB9146D4447CBC974"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each of the following heads of agencies or departments (or the designees of such heads): </text> <clause id="HCF559EB1600D4F6BA302D1D345A4056D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Director of the National Institutes of Health.</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA912AD331D2547D1B9B4C4C64A0CD701"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary for Preparedness and Response.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7569C76C60944A9E96A34B1A4C5AF076"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></clause>
<clause id="H363BC28B3DF04754A1FEB6D1B0EA730D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs.</text></clause> <clause id="HA5345D395BD5426D9EDB581D584D8E15"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The Director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy.</text></clause>
<clause id="H46C49CD5E2554102A91305209C3820BE"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>The Secretary of Energy.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4108F3BD66A94ACFAB62EF46568D22D5"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary of Energy for Nuclear Security.</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H340A8FF9E0E04E18816EF45602E7162C"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Nuclear Security Administration.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A46258962654139A6D9633065D92B36"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Office of Science of the Department of Energy.</text></clause>
<clause id="H7A05034D559241669618C8171C301DB4"><enum>(x)</enum><text>The Secretary of Commerce.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA946AB7232124F059972C12A4A08BDFB"><enum>(xi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere.</text></clause>
<clause id="HA3D7549ABF3341F08C588C6416CF3150"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>The Director of the National Center for Atmospheric Research.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFB87F1A650434360AFE9AAD18340742C"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Interior.</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA09BE84D84A24C2DA207EB03C1B75A35"><enum>(xiv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the United States Geological Survey.</text></clause> <clause id="H0A4E0DE681FE490DBCD4388932C2D80A"><enum>(xv)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</text></clause>
<clause id="H106561B90AA5444F9F90B70086C10F9B"><enum>(xvi)</enum><text>The Director of the National Science Foundation.</text></clause> <clause id="H9BC10C2B97644BECAC636974F6EF0053"><enum>(xvii)</enum><text>The Secretary of Defense.</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H18E3F2E42FA24AFDBBFE1A490632F1AF"><enum>(xviii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the Defense Threat Reduction Agency.</text></clause> <clause id="HE047FBB6F5E74133B14210F66081531C"><enum>(xix)</enum><text>The Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</text></clause>
<clause id="H988F3A1645394CDB91CFB7D3D767E52A"><enum>(xx)</enum><text>The Secretary of State.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H26B0B35F248244F0A7E0D5794958F4DB"><enum>(xxi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Under Secretary of State for Arms Control and International Security.</text></clause>
<clause id="H51F04E2325174F36B47BB53834551BD7"><enum>(xxii)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Authority.</text></clause> <clause id="H96B6AA9036804505B24E06E6D1F7F74E"><enum>(xxiii)</enum><text>The Secretary of Agriculture.</text></clause>
<clause id="H042FD09AEED5446080452654A88D3351"><enum>(xxiv)</enum><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAEAEB509743B45119FFF5276A95189B7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>other stakeholders, as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section>
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section" id="H590B8F7280C645268D66D82DE8AE31AB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Scope of nuclear threats</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HFB35B49F746E40CCA34664F7E79B4181"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in section 319C–1 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d-3a">42 U.S.C. 247d–3a</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC27DA41B5654FD0BA33A74DE9593C38"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(2)(A)(i), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>nuclear threats</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H919C4A26B4B84A1BAE62AF5BE5267D54"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (g)(1)(A), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>nuclear threats</quote>; </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2E298EA12FE0406EBBF0BBE0E9F12400"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in section 319C–2(c) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d-3b">42 U.S.C. 247d–3b</external-xref>), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>nuclear threats</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB19504454A094C3FA84B8559F67B8012"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 319C–3(c)(1) (42 U.S.C. 247d–3c(c)(1)), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>infectious diseases</quote>; </text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36C2847791F544839ED2F9DC6E0496C1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in section 319F(d)(3)(A) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d-6">42 U.S.C. 247d–6(d)(3)(A)</external-xref>), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>infectious diseases</quote>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBDB0004E763545ECAC2C26D0CC03AEEA"><enum>(5)</enum><text>in section 319L(c)(4)(F)(i) (42 U.S.C. 247d–7e(c)(4)(F)(i)), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>infectious diseases</quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCDB6F5DC2D7545A7AA96075B79CDDA8B"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in section 2801(d)(3) (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300hh">42 U.S.C. 300hh(d)(3)</external-xref>), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> before the semicolon; </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3FE1EC16A2664B5088B0FF5E4E0BF0A7"><enum>(7)</enum><text>in section 2811 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300hh-10">42 U.S.C. 300hh–10</external-xref>)—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5B5E4785002B43A98B74C817E940B703"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b)(4)(J)(i), in the matter preceding subclause (I), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>infectious diseases</quote>; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA0B3582CF204A02A300371AEC0D1C21"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d)(1), by inserting <quote>, including the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>nuclear threats</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8641C3F737144FF99A9741339CD7A528"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (d)(2)(A), by inserting <quote>, including with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827,</quote> after <quote>Nation</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H94FCD091585C48819B93C29691EDB695"><enum>(8)</enum><text>in section 2811–1(c) (1)(A)(42 U.S.C. 300hh–10a(c)(1)(A)), by inserting <quote>and with respect to the health consequences of the environmental impacts of nuclear war, as defined in section 2827</quote> after <quote>infectious diseases</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

