<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD7384ACE5F144E71A91A46F41805C63A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3772 IH: Aviation Workforce, Opportunity, Recruiting, Knowledge, and Supply Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3772</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230531">May 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000560">Mr. Larsen of Washington</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 to extend the aviation workforce development program and provide grants to develop aviation manufacturing and supplier workforce, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE6FE032D1C754A14851D7B917A00FD4D" style="OLC"><section id="HDD08586EDE8F4E7D8A8F2ED32004EAB2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Aviation Workforce, Opportunity, Recruiting, Knowledge, and Supply Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Aviation WORKS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB66C4BC0734F40CB8107BDE51BAE22A7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Extension and expansion of aviation workforce development programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 625 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/40101">49 U.S.C. 40101</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H032749BD070C4E25A412A5FE25174292"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H1296DF75934542BC8B93B3334A0598A5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9538B76C67CD4FF28D7728D425555F94" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="H98F75C168FFD49358AC33489A7AE1A25"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1550450E871D4AA8916B17878A58ED52"><paragraph id="H81C6B68C31494A7DB8FE4F274C424B26"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a program to provide grants for eligible projects to develop and support the education of the aviation manufacturing and supplier workforce; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H885D74A05ABB4692935AB5B848BAD244"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a program to provide grants for eligible projects to plan, establish, and expand workforce development partnership programs in the aviation and aerospace industry sector.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" commented="no" id="HC97B2041DFAD44EBA5A3B9EF52057E12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b) by amending paragraph (1) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9AB76DFE88D544048F106FE56C41F8D9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H9840E80595FC49F090BE8667DA7DFE15"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Out of amounts made available under section 48105 of title 49, United States Code, for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028—</text><subparagraph id="H03263B6E1B4842B4A0D5AA1B87F16608"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not more than $20,000,000 is authorized to be expended to provide grants under the program established under subsection (a)(1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B8653C2729A4B72A13581845DCDDBDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>$20,000,000 is authorized to provide grants under the program established under subsection (a)(2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E4CA0116846455BA5E5BB58D0B30011"><enum>(C)</enum><text>$20,000,000 to provide grants under the program established under subsection (a)(3); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23D1949556BB4969870F194B561DC528"><enum>(D)</enum><text>$20,000,000 to provide grants under the program established under subsection (a)(4).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H227C02105FC8424D9DC33729AA3FBB1F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H787868D1E2AF47D5AAB701747C749415"><paragraph id="H49750E3171BD4DBCA2E92972FBF947E5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An application for a grant under the program established under subsection (a)(3) shall be submitted, in such form as the Secretary may specify, by—</text><subparagraph id="H6FF7B37A422F4130AC1712BC59D035E0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an entity that—</text><clause id="H9E76AF011DEA4FBE95E43E02588BDF5B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>actively designs or manufactures any aircraft, aircraft engine, propeller, or appliance, or a component, part, or system thereof, covered under section 44704 of title 49, United States Code; and</text></clause><clause id="HF51339E74C3D4B6A889277C1069F0305"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>has significant operations in the United States, and a majority of its employees engaged in aviation manufacturing or development activities and services are based in the United States; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6F08702C12D494ABD908CC609240657"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an accredited institution of higher education (as defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/10001">20 U.S.C. 10001</external-xref>)), or a high school or a secondary school (as such terms are defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)) that has or is working to establish an aviation manufacturing program.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0B98F027DF94B97BEB79438BF6DD1D2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An application for a grant under the program established under subsection (a)(4) shall—</text><subparagraph id="H03B2AACBC7294C1AB542FDB5C5E34DEE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be submitted, in such form as the Secretary may specify, by a partnership that—</text><clause id="H6B98195547E94CBD85E0AEF488F0C5AE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is an industry or sector partnership (as such term is defined in section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>)), or is in the process of establishing an industry or sector partnership;</text></clause><clause id="HE4881017CC36403D96BC62811C7CE71A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes an air carrier (as defined in section 40102 of title 49, United States Code), a flight school described in paragraph (1)(C), a holder of a certificate described in paragraph (2)(A), or an aviation company described in paragraph (3)(A); </text></clause><clause id="HDE51B85DE4514A8B8E45A22BD1E79B68"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>is comprised of multiple employers from the aviation and aerospace industry;</text></clause><clause id="HC144F0CBF3FE4F0BA9CE98814444B850"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>may include not more than 1 entity that is a previous recipient of grant funding from any program established under paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a), but such entity may not serve as a fiscal agent (as described in subparagraph (B)); and</text></clause><clause id="HDEF840AB3108418CA111E2FE7EC553F7"><enum>(v)</enum><text>does not include an entity that is a current recipient of grant funding from any program established under paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a), unless the application demonstrates that any grant funding currently received by the entity would expire or otherwise cease prior to the receipt of the grant funding under paragraph (4) of subsection (a);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB30ADE220C4D415ABE6E0AE0D7FDA7E5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>designate a partner from within the partnership, or an intermediary which may be a State or local workforce board or an accredited institution of higher education (as such term is defined in paragraph (1)(B)), to serve as the fiscal agent for the grant; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H863706D5099742C1BFADD3CF441CF30C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>instruct the fiscal agent designated under subparagraph (B) to, as appropriate—</text><clause id="H00A982A2AC184176854204E8CD782549"><enum>(i)</enum><text>receive funds;</text></clause><clause id="H66C468F3BDBE4DA889EA3AC5DC1FFCA1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ensure sustained fiscal integrity and accountability for expenditures of funds in accordance with Federal Aviation Administration regulations;</text></clause><clause id="HE20B325EF2B14E76B709B2A37C450E6A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>respond to audit financial findings;</text></clause><clause id="HDB209FF614AE4011BEC8E664375630E3"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>maintain proper accounting records and documentation; and</text></clause><clause id="H4443497D8EF045A6954ACD2BAA4A6ACB"><enum>(v)</enum><text>prepare financial reports.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HCD830FE80287441A8BAF495C729396CE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="H2B3508FE93DD4E8CB415BD441B6D5861"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>pilot</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA91419AC35BF40E595FF84005162C745"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H437E3715FC134C4CA8BC92CC2A840733"><paragraph id="H660F3FDB0A144A868FAE9CDE1757C546"><enum>(3)</enum><text>For purposes of the program established under subsection (a)(3), an eligible project is a project—</text><subparagraph id="HFF84FC47658E4855B75D132285E73C07"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to establish or support educational programs that teach technical skills used in aviation manufacturing, including the production of components, parts, or systems thereof for inclusion in an aircraft, aircraft engine, propeller, or appliance;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8E9393EDADD49A898B5E927F01C642C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to establish scholarships, internships, or apprenticeships for individuals pursuing employment in the aviation manufacturing industry;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23A30F3C212F483F82F2EA38F0B17795"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to support outreach about careers in the aviation manufacturing industry to—</text><clause id="HA9B9BEC228654219B2C294889076B4C1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>primary, secondary, and post-secondary school students; </text></clause><clause id="HCF764648DF504512949973FBFF70DF00"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to communities underrepresented in the industry; or</text></clause><clause id="H6E4E40780084419F958810441BEA84DD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to students in economically disadvantaged geographic areas;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H844DC2CAB81C4F82AFBFB825DEDF4241"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to support transition to careers in aviation manufacturing, including for members of the Armed Forces; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7C0234BA8944CF2B8E69BE681BC835D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>to otherwise enhance aviation manufacturing technical education or the aviation manufacturing industry workforce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H789D179F6A5B40F1855B4CE12E8B2CEF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>For purposes of the program established under subsection (a)(4), an eligible project is a project—</text><subparagraph id="H8AFA1F03A0EB4E8BB8679FB71DA934A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to carry out planning and partner development activities, which may include—</text><clause id="HB930D4A9BBD143A7824DCE921C5D71E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>convening key stakeholders as identified in the application process to establish or expand educational programs that teach technical skills used in pilot training, aviation maintenance, or aviation manufacturing;</text></clause><clause id="H6F0E60A0DF164292AB48C5B9DD4D285E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>conducting outreach to local businesses and business associations, including activities to increase marketing and activity visibility within the community;</text></clause><clause id="HB1FC25401F554C1CA769A13C49FCD95F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>conducting an evaluation of workforce needs in the local area;</text></clause><clause id="HBCE64D56FEA04FB2850E64F30D0045F4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>conducting survey and planning activities for partnership-related infrastructure needs; or</text></clause><clause id="H8B5549B53BAC4612A51D117F98BF704E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>recruiting veterans of military service and individuals with barriers to employment;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD1BC7962366841AD85738BC1DD723D23"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to provide career services as described in section 134(c)(2)(A) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(c)(2)(A)</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H94EA271DDFD44E0F8A2F6AE55C022646"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to provide training services as described in section 134(c)(3)(D) of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3174">29 U.S.C. 3174(c)(3)(D)</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C0C916720814B2596120F57EFB17BB6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>to provide services to support the success and retention of individuals who are participating in any training program established under subsection (a)(4).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

