<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6276AC8C0C3642A48BFEAFA6311C786F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 651 IH: Cultivating Organic Matter through the Promotion Of Sustainable Techniques Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 651</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the designation of composting as a conservation practice and activity, and to provide grants and loan guarantees for composting facilities and programs, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBD21DF07F82A4E6DB4414E99082A7118" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H46B3230952A04B958BFEE5629D6EAC87" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Cultivating Organic Matter through the Promotion Of Sustainable Techniques Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>COMPOST Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H8774825969B648B39D9DD6D12877C3C5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Composting as conservation practice</header> <subsection id="HCEDE096F2D3840F9835C11E2F4DF6BDE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Conservation standards and requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1241(j) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3841">16 U.S.C. 3841(j)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1F581F0F9A6242F0BC255B17ACD0FFFE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (2) as paragraph (3); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H64EB30148838433794E6731F2BF395EC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (1) the following new paragraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC5D3B9E94868408CBAF12BE8C20BD246" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<paragraph id="HB975E58E5DAE45D7841A2CFFFE5208F4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Composting as conservation practice and activity</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE2B6456EEFB540D490EBAABF923E3D4A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall by regulation provide that composting is a conservation practice and a conservation activity for the purposes of this title.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H76DF79480C3C4B0DA747BB3541E07AB6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Composting defined</header> <clause id="H6BCDB7FA3A9B46AAB73AC6659237AA63"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>composting</term> means—</text> 
<subclause id="HEA6F0227DB8B40D38408844A0B42F4EC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>an activity (including an activity that does not require the use of a composting facility) to produce compost from organic waste that is—</text> <item id="H310B861513544672869669A55374E79F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>generated on a farm; or</text></item> 
<item id="HE3D547FB7F6A4B34901834998AF93543"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>brought to a farm from a nearby community and used to produce compost on that farm; and</text></item></subclause> <subclause id="HD6D33B36A8444C73996B86FC1481005B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the use and active management of compost on a farm, in accordance with any applicable Federal, State, or local law, to improve water retention and soil health.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H92148C147FFE458EB3AE9CA3CC1F4397"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Determination of nearby communities</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, shall issue regulations for determining whether a community is nearby for purposes of clause (i)(I), which shall ensure that bringing organic waste from the community to the farm to produce compost results in a net reduction of greenhouse gas emissions.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6B4FE85194724A04B30A1FF4553D5D60"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conservation stewardship program</header><text>Section 1240I(2)(B)(i) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3839aa-21">16 U.S.C. 3839aa–21(2)(B)(i)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>and composting practices</quote> after <quote>agriculture drainage management systems</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAE2878C294FB47369249C4B8F780C5DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Environmental quality incentives program</header><text>Section 1240A(6)(A)(ii) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3839aa-1">16 U.S.C. 3839aa–1(6)(A)(ii)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>, including composting practices</quote> before the semicolon at the end.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HDDC32A7EB99947369CC687522093D63B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Delivery of technical assistance</header><text>Section 1242(h) of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3842">16 U.S.C. 3842(h)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HD261DAB1800D4CA6BF6D848DDF7F0ABE" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="H82CBC795322D4E50BF6FAA387B2B740E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Development of composting practice standard</header><text>In addition to conducting a review under this subsection of any composting facility practice standard established before the date of enactment of this paragraph, the Secretary shall establish a composting practice standard under the process developed under paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="HE859CDF66A674A8EB1B8B02074539A09"><enum>3.</enum><header>Composting grant and loan guarantee program</header> <subsection id="H2ABA8DBF586B42D9B4CBD35552C862C4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act is amended by inserting after section 310I (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1936">7 U.S.C. 1936</external-xref>) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5F37763E27614BC5906E47603EEF8379" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="HE08749E642DE4456B891AB29E740A5CA"><enum>310J.</enum><header>Grants and loan guarantees for composting programs</header> 
<subsection id="HED2D5603B3E745A19B39D4BA292DD11F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, shall establish and carry out a program to award grants and loan guarantees, on a competitive basis, for projects that expand access to food waste composting.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H705AA1ADE3324503B93E2F59D57B6C40"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants</header> <paragraph id="H95B0A3EE102540F3843D0EC5A1BBF65A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amount</header> <subparagraph id="H2A04D7DAA5184A20926C7096A71DE77B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Cost share</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total amount of grant funds awarded for a project under this section shall not exceed 75 percent of the cost of the project for which the grant is awarded, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC0BD619309DE4883B57B24088E814922"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Maximum</header><text>The total amount of grant funds awarded for a project under this subsection shall not exceed $5,000,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H21047B52464D417F963D0371872AC919"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Allocation</header><text>Of funds made available to carry out this subsection in each fiscal year, the Secretary shall allocate not less than 25 percent to projects that do not include the use of centralized commercial composting, to the extent there are sufficient applications for such projects.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H471B6D6F3B4C48D7B2DBD54A38586C29"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Timeline</header><text>An entity receiving a grant under this subsection shall fully expend the awarded grant funds within 3 years of receiving the funds.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFFB563A3F1574EBF9BC7B1B1F6B7E57C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may award a grant under this section to any of the following entities:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H0B2FF2B1EED341BAA7A5E61A80A21A32"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A State, local, territorial, or Tribal government.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7786912AB52E4AB7A0D86ECE3C546B42"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A local educational agency (as defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE413790DBCB34D4AB3F57C08C13474BD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An institution of higher education.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD76002DE9B0F46CBA05DDA08A3768B92"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A non-profit organization.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H94FB2412A841482783CD8266591E5141"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A farmer or rancher.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H54F2374575BB4AEAB7F411AEC5C15567"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A consortium of any of the entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (E).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H52082F1EF55D42B6B01EA34CDFE4FDFD"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One or more of any of the entities described in subparagraphs (A) through (F), in coordination with a for-profit organization.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H10C8DF3A639C47AB8209728343F01923"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Loan guarantees</header> <paragraph id="HBC0845CCA83B41AFA38D7BEF93ACFE8B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amount</header> <subparagraph id="HA6213B30BE774551B59D86E43006F262"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Cost share</header><text>The Secretary may award a loan guarantee under this section in an amount that does not exceed 80 percent of the cost of a project that is eligible for assistance under this section, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HACE4B42136FD48F1A27C8321B9CE4C59" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Maximum</header><text>The Secretary may not provide a loan guarantee under this section in an amount that exceeds $5,000,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7F1682F56BDD40D598470BB173A596D6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may award a loan guarantee under this section to a for-profit organization, farmer, or rancher that demonstrates successful prior experience in developing, managing, and marketing composting facilities.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1C8BE71A67A24E4B88BB54428DE2CE85"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible Projects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may award grants and loan guarantees under this section for projects to carry out the following:</text> <paragraph id="HB5D47624A97946F586B64394EEE990BE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Composting facility or site permitting, planning, and construction.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE45E912AE2D74EE9990531B819A174A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Acquisition of machinery, equipment, and other physical necessities required to operate a composting facility, system, or program, except depackaging equipment.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61BB65B4B3434E38B41F7895780280A2" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Activities to increase the production capacity throughput of a composting facility.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD57B785F05684194886D44DE0EC60343"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Implementation of onsite composting systems and programs (such as home composting programs, community garden and urban farm composting, and other onsite composting systems at institutions, nonprofits, and businesses).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC8A68D78DC084DA1BEBED7E1A86A0406"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Projects that are based on a distributed infrastructure strategy (such as a strategy that incorporates a mix or choice of home composting, farm and ranch composting, onsite composting, community-scale composting, or centralized commercial composting).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H40298BA5FFE3455987FC5E6A5AEA189F" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Collection of organic waste intended for processing at a composting facility or system, or through a composting program, including curbside pick-up programs, community drop-off programs, and facility- or event-specific programs (such as programs at schools, restaurants, stadiums, or festivals).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4CA5BF631E6140CDAC09189E5A9C1042" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Activities for land-based compost application, including compost application on a farm or ranch.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B0C14C0E9434476AB1469FA8A7B3CA3"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Market development projects that create a demand for compost product or increase commercial and residential participation in composting.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8BDC30AAB12C4EAEA3D4589067B8F113"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An eligible entity applying for a grant or loan guarantee under this section shall demonstrate that the project for which such assistance is sought—</text> 
<paragraph id="HD11A2C3D024D418B82705B9222E98BD6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>will—</text> <subparagraph id="HBB9BAE8472F641A6809B101964759D58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>result in composting of food waste (which may include such composting in combination with non-food organic waste);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8B1D3088619740A1BC719926572006D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>result in increased total capacity to accept and process food waste into finished compost product; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1C3BC049471548179220D46FE437AEE8" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>include at least one operator of a facility or system, if applicable, who is trained on best management practices for composting (such as odor, vector, pathogen, and contaminant control practices);</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H96777632520646D9BE52CA5A21EC804C" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a market development project, is likely to create sufficient demand to increase total capacity, in the targeted market, to accept and process food waste into high-quality finished compost; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3FB740AB3E4C4E7786D4E83B41346A1E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the case of land-based compost application activities, is consistent with any applicable requirements pursuant to section 1241(j) of the Food Security Act of 1985.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9E9BF45F1F6E43DC98985A4E07F23D15"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Priority factors</header><text>In awarding grants and loan guarantees under this section, the Secretary shall prioritize projects that include the greatest number of the following factors:</text> <paragraph id="H40417791BA99435EA33A8CBFE3853A81"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The project is located in or serving a location with significant access to food waste and no or limited prior access to food waste composting.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2E3CCF2E4AC84B7FBA113ABC458EEB35"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The project demonstrates the potential to create new capacity for the volume or weight of food waste collected and processed, or make significant gains in the number of people with access to food waste composting facilities or systems.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H458C0DAD96A14171A914730402C418E3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The project includes a demonstrated plan for following best management practices and producing a high-quality compost product.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H03D83FB4D16148CFB155D8BC1B386F2F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The project incorporates the participation of small and diverse businesses (such as minority-, woman-, and veteran-owned businesses certified by the Small Business Administration or under a State program or another recognized certification program and other businesses led by Black people, Indigenous people, or other people of color).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50D37782FD3146B8BEEE2A25E2C198E5"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The project creates opportunities for hiring and leadership development practices that are inclusive and provide living wages.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H98816C4703A54D528C0E3B2340D904F7"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The project serves disadvantaged and low-income communities, engages Black farmers, Indigenous farmers, and other farmers of color, or incorporates an environmental justice plan or principles.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H30E9860D1D104050B0EE621899CEED4A"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The project is for a facility or system that accepts or plans to accept and process only source separated organics.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H21958016AEA94924857638D146CA0BF1" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Secretary may award only one grant or loan guarantee under this section for any project.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H2A02DBEBF9BF4C1AA99E04E177F4978D"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="HECEF7F6DDE384170AC03F002EFF798D0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Source separated organics</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA087C2CD0584436789E44777E608B9AE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>source separated organics</term> means organic waste that is separated from other waste by the waste generator.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEC3FF46EDF694F9F95731195CF0382DB" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Inclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>source separated organics</term> includes materials that are certified to meet ASTM standard D6400 or D6868.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HD4AD5D1AE81D466BA84F70D6C87C3751" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>source separated organics</term> excludes mixed solid waste.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2FE3E26CA4214CDB8492E93334E097BB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Centralized commercial composting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>centralized commercial composting</term> means a regional composting facility that produces at least 10,000 tons of compost annually. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H154F8C3A1D1F4F8BA6628302B8464063"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $200,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2033.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

