<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6F0B66D3677242F9B064381C8DF16680" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5805 IH: No Work, No Pay Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5805</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001129">Mr. Collins</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 to prohibit Members of Congress from making direct and personal solicitations of campaign funds or making campaign expenditures during a Government shutdown, to reduce the pay of Members of Congress if a Government shutdown takes effect, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H65C447EE509240D0893774C7E5E7FC5A" style="OLC"><section id="H674F7BE6FB264E428AEDA2490F9236D8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Work, No Pay Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA56E3886D04A4A428C21F88CED9E7A5D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibiting Members of Congress from engaging in certain campaign activities during Government shutdown</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title III of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/30101">52 U.S.C. 30101 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H9E6C6AFE41B1479B8CFD29D231651DEE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H5F3A82F2D7D64C6DB89CFFCB14E9CA90"><enum>325.</enum><header>Prohibiting Members of Congress from engaging in certain campaign activities during Government shutdown</header><subsection id="H683D9C00C0D34F1E90ACD120C2514E45"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Direct and personal solicitation of contributions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual holding the office of Senator or Representative in, or Delegate or Resident Commissioner to, the Congress may not make a direct and personal solicitation of funds in connection with an election for Federal office at any time during which a Government shutdown is in effect.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB8423F3C9E044628858FC13A7710F409"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Expenditures by authorized committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An authorized committee of a candidate who is an individual holding the office of Senator or Representative in, or Delegate or Resident Commissioner to, the Congress may not make an expenditure in connection with an election for Federal office at any time during which a Government shutdown is in effect.</text></subsection><subsection id="H877AA2DAEEB74752B361E788BBDCA7A1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Determination of Government shutdown</header><text>For purposes of this section, a Government shutdown shall be considered to be in effect if there is a lapse in appropriations for any Federal agency or department as a result of a failure to enact a regular appropriations bill or continuing resolution.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H3E567606F8FC41F79F97AAC52DF17299"><enum>3.</enum><header>Reduction of pay of Members of Congress if Government shutdown occurs</header><subsection id="H0F872D433F90479A929568891D5C79CD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reduction of pay for each day of Government shutdown</header><paragraph id="H2605B11F3AB346B4AB7A6AF7E65D7232"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Reduction</header><text>If on any day during a year a Government shutdown is in effect, the annual rate of pay applicable under section 601(a) of the Legislative Reorganization Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/4501">2 U.S.C. 4501</external-xref>) with respect to each Member of Congress for the year shall be reduced by an amount equal to the product of—</text><subparagraph id="H83FA003F5BD3418394E6C72863007A77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an amount equal to one day’s worth of pay under such annual rate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8139D108AC034A4E95CD1DAB4762C892"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of 24-hour periods during which the Government shutdown is in effect.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H627A690F94124B9B8160BC36FD38E338" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This subsection shall apply with respect to days occurring after the date of the regularly scheduled general election for Federal office held in November 2024.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCF8B0E3F13514141A6843067EB23A392" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Special rule for One Hundred Eighteenth Congress</header><paragraph id="HD8716D428FB847DCB5239E51D9B6B5E2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Holding salaries in escrow</header><text>If on any day during the One Hundred Eighteenth Congress a Government shutdown is in effect, the payroll administrator of that House of Congress shall—</text><subparagraph id="H429CDADC947342828465AFA8D578E88F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>withhold from the payments otherwise required to be made with respect to a pay period for the compensation of each Member of Congress who serves in that House of Congress an amount equal to the product of—</text><clause id="H5DE94C4A6D9744EAA3A79DE6FE495273"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an amount equal to one day’s worth of pay under the annual rate of pay applicable to the Member under section 601(a) of the Legislative Reorganization Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/4501">2 U.S.C. 4501</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="HC1498A36BAAA431289B49B9F79115348"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of 24-hour periods during which the Government shutdown is in effect which occur during the pay period; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2BD9D3F925D4C8B8D397C017F664EF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>deposit in an escrow account all amounts withheld under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA807E8F6471A4157BDF62A07EFF51A9B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Release of amounts at end of the Congress</header><text>In order to ensure that this subsection is carried out in a manner that shall not vary the compensation of Senators or Representatives in violation of the twenty-seventh article of amendment to the Constitution of the United States, the payroll administrator of a House of Congress shall release for payments to Members of that House of Congress any amounts remaining in any escrow account under this subsection on the last day of the One Hundred Eighteenth Congress.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D3B74D96911464686DF6B1945BEA7C5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Role of Secretary of the Treasury</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury shall provide the payroll administrators of the Houses of Congress with such assistance as may be necessary to enable the payroll administrators to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFF227642F0704BC98A1531153CA4B000"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Payroll administrator defined</header><text>In this subsection, the <quote>payroll administrator</quote> of a House of Congress means—</text><subparagraph id="H335A1B81BBA44CF1999543258F331AD2"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of the House of Representatives, the Chief Administrative Officer of the House of Representatives, or an employee of the Office of the Chief Administrative Officer who is designated by the Chief Administrative Officer to carry out this subsection; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42893E0D34B8431FBD3B1219BFFE9487"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in the case of the Senate, the Secretary of the Senate, or an employee of the Office of the Secretary of the Senate who is designated by the Secretary to carry out this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B413F49DB894CFE994EC8074AEC90BB" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Exception for days occurring after general election</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This subsection does not apply with respect to any day during the One Hundred Eighteenth Congress which occurs after the date of the regularly scheduled general election for Federal office held in November 2024.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HE869F066391E4FEB99037C794950B304" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibiting Member official travel during shutdown</header><subsection id="HFAF95CF76AC64695B3EAD51326D8B8CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), no appropriated funds, including official funds of the House of Representatives, official funds of the Senate, or funds available under any Federal law, rule, or regulation, may be used to pay for the costs of travel by a Member of Congress during any period in which a Government shutdown is in effect.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCC11BF5663BB461289CDE6208A21F4B3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception for travel by Member to Washington Metropolitan Area</header><text>Subsection (a) does not apply with respect to travel by a Member of Congress to the Washington Metropolitan Area.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5BC8161C3E6446C2804DEC88A4E7E4B1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Washington Metropolitan Area Defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Washington Metropolitan Area</term> means the District of Columbia, the Counties of Montgomery and Prince Georges in Maryland, and the Counties of Arlington, Fairfax, Loudon, and Prince William and the Cities of Alexandria and Falls Church in Virginia.</text></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H429967D79342438399271194E7209C3E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Determination of Government shutdown</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of this Act, a Government shutdown shall be considered to be in effect if there is a lapse in appropriations for any Federal agency or department as a result of a failure to enact a regular appropriations bill or continuing resolution.</text></section><section id="HC95E0B20CD5841E2A88463120545A3DB"><enum>6.</enum><header>Member of Congress defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>Member of Congress</term> means an individual serving in a position under subparagraph (A), (B), or (C) of section 601(a) of the Legislative Reorganization Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/2/4501">2 U.S.C. 4501</external-xref>).</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

