<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2E76D31BC0EE4CFA8320F5D5A7582B64" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2747 IH: Sustainable Aviation Fuel Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2747</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230420">April 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To support the sustainable aviation fuel market, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCD19BA6FB5C64757950B8FEDA256D43E" style="OLC"><section id="H17ABDF29D5944063B45EE06A0ECAEC6B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Sustainable Aviation Fuel Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H3618274D94C746F79B9176CF553DA3B4"><enum>2.</enum><header>National goal</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is hereby declared that it is the national goal for the United States to reach—</text><paragraph id="HA337AC3BBF1D4FBD8294BFD19BDD95AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a net 35-percent reduction in greenhouse gas emissions for United States domestic and international aviation flights by 2035, as compared to 2005; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFF491ADFFC74C889DF93A0B7871C5EB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>net zero greenhouse gas emissions for United States domestic and international aviation flights by 2050.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD5AD42FE033D4C42A533A9E5144622A6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H5ED0A1E1C375474C805131A05F4D7138"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sustainable aviation fuel</header><text>The term <quote>sustainable aviation fuel</quote> means liquid fuel consisting of synthesized hydrocarbons that—</text><subparagraph id="H3CDDBC0055EB457F9BAE509A4695C479"><enum>(A)</enum><text>meets the requirements of a Department of Defense specification for military jet fuel or an American Society of Testing and Materials specification for aviation turbine fuel;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H521CD550F012439EAB1E11564F9540E2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is derived from qualified feedstock; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H757A842F5B4A4C1FBCF2B518073BDC0E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>is certified by the Environmental Protection Agency Administrator that such fuel—</text><clause id="H2C3598A09A5A47669EAEE1B726E7A51E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>either—</text><subclause id="H93E7755D7994478E90C806D96CF37996"><enum>(I)</enum><text>conforms to the standards, recommended practices, requirements and criteria, supporting documents, implementation elements, and any other technical guidance for sustainable aviation fuels that are adopted by the International Civil Aviation Organization with the agreement of the United States; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HDC56109767A84B009A066252689143AA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>meets the definition of <quote>advanced biofuel</quote> under section 211(o)(1) of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7545">42 U.S.C. 7545(o)(1)</external-xref>), as demonstrated by compliance with Environmental Protection Agency implementing regulations under subpart M of part 80 of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HBE96E98213E54129BE684B4377FC5D73"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>achieves at least a 50-percent reduction in lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions compared to conventional jet fuel.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6700767E5F574C2AA630C81A71539FDB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified feedstock</header><text>The term <quote>qualified feedstock</quote> means sources of hydrogen and carbon not originating from unrefined or refined petrochemicals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC5F4EAA6A9E45E5899DAC0DEBAFA3B3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions</header><text>The term <quote>lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions</quote> means the combined greenhouse gas emissions from feedstock production, collection of feedstock, transportation of feedstock to fuel production facilities, conversion of feedstock to fuel, transportation and distribution of fuel, and fuel combustion in an aircraft engine, as well as from induced land-use change emissions, as calculated using appropriate modeling techniques approved by a regulating authority.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A56A614BFF0477AB16BE6A002C9C237"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Induced land-use change emissions</header><text>The term <quote>induced land-use change emissions</quote> means the greenhouse gas emissions resulting from the conversion of land to the production of feedstocks and from the conversion of other land due to the displacement of crops or animals for which the original land was previously used, as calculated using appropriate modeling techniques approved by a regulating authority.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF28A4BEEDD54D75B1F0E6B6BE39D182"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Conventional jet fuel</header><text>The term <quote>conventional jet fuel</quote> means liquid hydrocarbon fuel used for aviation that is derived or refined from petrochemicals.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HD78A4883E75548E68D8F52C508FC9190"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grant program</header><subsection id="H93F17456E90A404F9E2C5AF45F1C293D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Transportation, in consultation with the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, shall carry out a competitive grant and cost-sharing agreement program for eligible entities to carry out projects located in the United States to produce, transport, blend, or store sustainable aviation fuel.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2E44F89C912847AA94280FCE2432C5D3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>In selecting an eligible entity to receive a grant or cost-share agreement under subsection (a), the Secretary shall consider—</text><paragraph id="HC7E4A1B4AD5144F9ADF25F8067A5E328"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the anticipated public benefits of a project proposed by the eligible entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6034D1CF116F41478A7D9E27C646E58E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the potential to increase the domestic production and deployment of sustainable aviation fuel;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69090637FE0F4E04891FF9E1A566E13E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the potential greenhouse gas emissions from such project;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H664FEC6654D54667A291B50711CE1136"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the potential for creating new jobs in the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BB180FB1DB04352884456ED8273D9D1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the potential net greenhouse gas emissions impact of different feedstocks to produce sustainable aviation fuel on a lifecycle basis, which shall include potential direct and indirect greenhouse gas emissions (including resulting from changes in land use); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H346AA41CC28741128AB2E271BE4750CA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the proposed utilization of non-Federal contributions by the eligible entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA71B055A97C141FB9AC45F3C50F6A826"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $200,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE9F465F5874F4167AB0EA2703434545A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than October 1, 2029, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report describing the results of the grant program under this section. The report shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H92572E2DC3CB48C1B5BAA63553077183"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the entities and projects that received grants or other cost-sharing agreements under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A871ADC88B74DB7BFF4E6E4A2C0C284"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A detailed explanation for why each entity received the type of funding disbursement such entity did.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07E862B6AB074CBE815724FDCA6DB3E0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of whether the program is leading to an increase in the production and deployment of sustainable aviation fuels and whether that increase is enough to keep the United States on track to achieve the goals described in section 2 of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H614DD29C33544770AF2ABC3DCFC6B25B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of the economic impacts resulting from the funding to and operation of the project.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H15A0AC96BB644A3DBF2CBEB8245952D0"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Eligible entity defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H9FEEFDBFEC134E9EA599AB2B9ED425B8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a State or local government other than an airport sponsor;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACB3A34319FE491D805C3E81C09CA694"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an air carrier;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0365162F625471BBBB8C778F262DB6A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>an airport sponsor; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCD1E6A649594B41BDB610CA04982888"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a person or entity engaged in the production, transportation, blending or storage of sustainable aviation fuel in the United States or feedstocks in the United States that could be used to produce sustainable aviation fuel.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HECB5D25721B640BB94C50D7C4CC267A8"><enum>5.</enum><header>Low carbon aviation fuel standard</header><subsection id="H108AF9CF97DF4163A5DE6AFC784214A6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of low carbon aviation fuel standard</header><text>Section 211 of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7545">42 U.S.C. 7545</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HFE57407444D64A97A09973B53FF2DCCF" style="OLC"><subsection id="H88C773BC6EC041BABAB57C6B886F9B6B"><enum>(w)</enum><header>Low carbon aviation fuel standard</header><paragraph id="HEB20DAAA4A844BD2932B559FC8BC0928"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H5CFCEA7106474481BCA2F663347966CD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Aviation fuel</header><text>The term <quote>aviation fuel</quote> means fuel that is produced, sold, or dispensed in the United States, for civil or military purposes, for turbine-powered aviation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H745876FEE2644E569A3BCC4E97833769"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Carbon intensity</header><text>The term <quote>carbon intensity</quote> means the quantity of lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions per unit of fuel energy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA3E0213A99694D11867100685E3C2087"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Credit exchange</header><text>The term <quote>credit exchange</quote> means a central marketplace with established rules and regulations where buyers and sellers meet to conduct trades.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8B0DE42636D46C1A501460F0BEBA52B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Fuel standard</header><text>The term <quote>fuel standard</quote> means the low carbon fuel standard established under paragraph (2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H95A4D3A4B16A4E4386A328EAF5FF082C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator shall promulgate regulations to establish a low carbon fuel standard for aviation fuels that requires a reduction in carbon intensity for aviation fuels each calendar year such that by 2050, and thereafter, the average carbon intensity of all aviation fuel used annually in the United States is reduced by at least 50 percent, as compared to the average carbon intensity of all aviation fuel used in the United States in 2005.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA80F450195024203A8A3FC0A6B0405E7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Targets</header><text>In promulgating regulations under paragraph (2), the Administrator shall set a target of a reduction of at least 20 percent in the average carbon intensity of all aviation fuel used annually in the United States by 2030, and of at least 50 percent by 2050, as compared to the average carbon intensity of all aviation fuel used in the United States in 2005.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA65660E8AF31435C8A8465AED6F74BC9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In promulgating regulations under paragraph (2), the Administrator shall—</text><subparagraph id="H4E4CCA1CE45F4371A5632FD16F370D3A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish a benchmark for the average carbon intensity of aviation fuels for each calendar year, beginning with the first full calendar year that begins 2 years after the date of enactment of this subsection, suitable to achieving the targets specified in paragraph (3);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1639AFD15D2F4F3192E0F204C00AC96F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>apply the fuel standard to persons who produce or import aviation fuel;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H223A69FC23ED4758B6C6EFD4C5024187"><enum>(C)</enum><text>establish procedures for calculating the carbon intensity of an aviation fuel, expressed in grams of carbon dioxide equivalent per megajoule, in accordance with—</text><clause id="H8312CA27F46E4758A00A26AF9B1D2356"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the standards, recommended practices, requirements and criteria, supporting documents, implementation elements, and any other technical guidance for sustainable aviation fuels that are adopted by the International Civil Aviation Organization with the agreement of the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="H5D4490F16B9A48778681458E4117F124"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other more stringent accounting practices determined by the Administrator to be the best lifecycle greenhouse gas emission accounting practices, provided that such practices account for the aggregate quantity of greenhouse gas emissions (including direct emissions and significant indirect emissions such as significant emissions from land use changes), as determined by the Administrator, related to the full fuel lifecycle, including all stages of fuel and feedstock production and distribution, from feedstock generation or extraction through the distribution and delivery and use of the finished fuel to the ultimate consumer, where the mass values for all greenhouse gases are adjusted to account for their relative global warming potential;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3F6DA09184B449BACEE6C7B263752C9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>determine how long the calculation of the carbon intensity of an aviation fuel (pursuant to the procedures established under subparagraph (C)), will remain in effect before needing to be reevaluated;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC0A98CEF97642708993F4905C2E377E"><enum>(E)</enum><text>allow a person described in subparagraph (B), who, for a calendar year, produces or imports aviation fuel—</text><clause id="H04F94309452D49A09B239380ED4D6AD1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that has an average carbon intensity that is less than the benchmark for average carbon intensity for that calendar year to, except as provided in paragraph (8), generate credits, to be used, or transferred to another person, to demonstrate compliance with this subsection; and</text></clause><clause id="HF5ABE0F0085F42FBACB861A40226DE32"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that has an average carbon intensity that is greater than the benchmark for average carbon intensity for that calendar year to purchase credits to be used to demonstrate compliance with this subsection;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3E5E77E326942428CE8C8CBA2EC395D"><enum>(F)</enum><text>determine the—</text><clause id="HD22F83032346463BA1A4CA44C53C812B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>appropriate amount of credits generated and used to demonstrate compliance pursuant to subparagraph (E);</text></clause><clause id="H73807BBA713E465BAD447D73D737D2AF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>appropriate conditions, if any, on—</text><subclause id="H3A0384B3ACA849C1B6EAAE0C9543B825"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the duration of such credits; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H1AC013513B414307B88E6B3E1670EBEB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the transfer of such credits through a credit exchange; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84A844B13B054326B9C15BACACF0A5E5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>consult with all relevant stakeholders, including aviation industry groups, renewable fuel industry groups, researchers at institutions of higher education, labor unions, consumer advocates, and any other stakeholders the Administrator determines to be appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3E38934462C43D6A7352CA7D2544EEB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the Administrator shall consult with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, the Secretary of Energy, and the Secretary of Agriculture.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D4713B25D7B455C886DBF87F3253B17"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Coordination with states</header><text>The Administrator shall, after notice and opportunity for public hearing, waive application of the fuel standard in any State that has adopted a standard for aviation fuels that the Administrator determines is at least as stringent as the fuel standard.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCACF5573DB394C44854A5C6D1686CA50"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Revision</header><text>If Congress enacts a standard or similar law that the Administrator, in consultation with the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, determines accomplishes the purposes of the fuel standard for sectors of the economy that include the aviation sector, the Administrator may revoke the fuel standard in favor of the other standard or law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE391D0EAE5A04E9F9D6DBF3E0E896F64"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Relationship to renewable fuel program</header><text>No credit may be generated under this subsection with respect to renewable fuel for which a credit is generated under subsection (o).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H738EDCE4C98D4F0DA35FFE2F7A92FE77"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator shall submit to Congress and make publicly available a report describing—</text><subparagraph id="HC4A0B8A8069547FD925F858DD803B74B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the status of the development of the fuel standard; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H028E7D66ED1E4DD991428B7EEC7D6E84"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the considerations the Administrator is using in developing the fuel standard.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H848DC32F0A8646689EE12EABA49A9C67"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement</header><text>Section 211(d) of the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7545">42 U.S.C. 7545(d)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HA20957B95C454542BDFEFDD5E6B0BA51"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H8DEE6B43854346E6930A00D425055ACC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or (o) of this section or the regulations</quote> and inserting <quote>(o), or (w) of this section or the regulations</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64A755713C5A49A7AC44C6932BD797BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or (o) of this section or who fails</quote> and inserting <quote>(o), or (w) of this section or who fails</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB65C2C8CE8634747BEFE328E8B1DAC8C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or (o) of this section which establishes</quote> and inserting <quote>(o), or (w) of this section which establishes</quote>; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB252E86403948AC8DFDC8053DA37ED7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>and (o) of this section</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>(o), and (w) of this section</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H882589EFEF2A43CAAE6EAAE5070A2EDA"><enum>6.</enum><header>Procurement of sustainable aviation fuel by the department of defense</header><subsection id="H622C6C37491943F885E38B710C34D9DA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Effective October 1, 2025, the Secretary of Defense shall make a bulk purchase of an amount of sustainable aviation fuel that is not less than 10 percent of the total amount of aviation fuel procured for operational purposes (as defined in section 2922h of title 10, United States Code) if—</text><paragraph id="H88761165892B4C32AA86B30CD87EC790"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the cost of sustainable aviation fuel is competitive with the fully burdened cost of conventional jet fuel available for the same purpose; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BA4747854E84F309E1FB47E6BF392E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the sustainable aviation fuel is refined or produced in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA943E3D6E7D048E1850D7E88E64D6AFE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Blended fuel</header><text>If the Secretary of Defense purchases sustainable aviation fuel that is blended with conventional jet fuel, the percentage of sustainable aviation fuel in such blend will be counted towards the percentage described in subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H65D39D1943304B4D9C65B8CF51E2519A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Before making a purchase under subsection (a), the Secretary of Defense or the Secretary concerned (as defined in section 101(a)(9) of title 10, United States Code) shall certify that the sustainable aviation fuel is suitable for use in aircrafts of the Department of Defense.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7B3F5A1653214A9EA507D98C04BB81FC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Waiver</header><paragraph id="HBA7F6E420AE1460F8959C1EE0039A664"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the requirements of paragraph (2), the Secretary of Defense may waive the requirement under subsection (a) for reasons of national security, including the lack of available, qualifying sustainable aviation fuel.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H87F3680B049A499BAA103206A772AD94"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice</header><text>Not later than 30 days after issuing a waiver under this subsection, the Secretary shall submit to the congressional defense committees (as defined in section 101(a)(16) of title 10, United States Code) notice of the waiver. Any such notice shall include each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HA28EB25609A0483FB246F79269EC8AFF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The rationale of the Secretary for issuing the waiver.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3327CC29643D463DA338D790FB319A9A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A certification that the waiver is in the national security interest of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF2CA1BE03FD431C98FF356C602402CA"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>The terms <quote>fully burdened cost</quote> and <quote>operational purposes</quote> have the meanings given such terms, respectively, in section 2922h of title 10, United States Code.</text></subsection></section><section id="HD87C98828E744955A2F42FE445D1E6E1"><enum>7.</enum><header>Federal aviation administration research</header><subsection id="H3E049457D2054649BDF0CF403F1A6B7C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 911(a) of the FAA Modernization and Reform Act of 2012 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/44504">49 U.S.C. 44504</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1DF08545E7CC42F6A88AF47E0C0A9FD6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>assist in the development</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block id="HB4AC17DC7DB04B349CA01044355B1F8E" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H264A674F17DC411CAD06D83A9517856F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assist in the development</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HE130F0078C554B59AC5D4668BFAACA29"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and other</quote> and inserting <quote>, other</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58D23B03CE40499B8F8A0DAD5828B5DC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking the period and inserting <quote>, and sustainable fuel that can be used without the need to blend with any other type of aviation fuel;</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2E19F24EB6B4273B1F2E0D98B3E9643"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H7D1D92BBE6754E9EBE499D1256504832" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HEAEF0A382DBE40CDAF8470738DBA126B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promote the efforts of the aviation sector to become a net-zero greenhouse gas emitting sector;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1D9BAE90406D4ADF9CC053D697468999"><enum>(3)</enum><text>study the climate impacts of non-carbon dioxide greenhouse gas emissions, water vapor, and contrails and ways to minimize such impacts; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD71FCB75292B4E619346291ABA1DD8DA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop a methodology for quantifying the non-carbon dioxide climate impacts of aviation in a lifecycle analysis, including the benefits of sustainable aviation fuel other than the reduction in carbon dioxide emissions.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC8C3DB7BB63747D3A75BAA5DFCBB2863"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Section 911 of such Act is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H232BDB79E4D94593942A5D6A7D706E10" style="OLC"><subsection id="H29C393D9149445C19F6A7A6D4C484DDB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HEBE852BCFFCC45E7A29499A83719B1DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sustainable aviation fuel</header><text>The term <quote>sustainable aviation fuel</quote> means liquid fuel consisting of synthesized hydrocarbons that—</text><subparagraph id="HDB96A03F5D5940608764105C03B31649"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is derived from a qualified feedstock; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F2A9F9BE8094D869A2972133A38758B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>conforms to the standards, recommended practices, requirements and criteria, supporting documents, implementation elements, and any other technical guidance for sustainable aviation fuels that are adopted by the International Civil Aviation Organization with the agreement of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCA5FD4E3F70F471D89243A6818CF784B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualified feedstock</header><text>The term <quote>qualified feedstock</quote> means sources of hydrogen and carbon not originating from unrefined or refined petrochemicals.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8B8137B77FA7410A9419454E89880752"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration $35,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H9444CEF4BD964181869801888E7002AE"><enum>8.</enum><header>Department of energy research</header><subsection id="H616637E275D240688510E072264776A4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Energy shall carry out a program to research the use of cover crops or other crops grown for conservation purposes rather than for sale in the production of sustainable aviation fuel.</text></subsection><subsection id="H70D28B5480A84C79A21ECC47BD3D3F3B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text>In carrying out the program under subsection (a), the Secretary shall collaborate with the national laboratories, the Department of Agriculture, and industry partners.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5E1A9533E6B54BE7895C359C39138004"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HE3443E0D75784BED87DB2582150F2AB7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Sustainable aviation fuel</header><text>The term <quote>sustainable aviation fuel</quote> means liquid fuel consisting of synthesized hydrocarbons that—</text><subparagraph id="H6B4C61DFC7D94FA08DF94B5E94A2F37E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is derived from a qualified feedstock; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H75A600ACCDEF4F279670DF0D8F165FD1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>conforms to the standards, recommended practices, requirements and criteria, supporting documents, implementation elements, and any other technical guidance for sustainable aviation fuels that are adopted by the International Civil Aviation Organization with the agreement of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H64C6B7341EEC445CA67855E1AC34F666"><enum>(2)</enum><header>National laboratory</header><text>The term <quote>national laboratory</quote> has the meaning given the term in section 2(3) of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801(3)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFCD9EB73E32D4E1DB3BE819ACC106F79"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="H0CA33961A89648139C2D03D797A27FC9"><enum>9.</enum><header>Extension of clean fuel production credit for sustainable aviation fuel</header><subsection id="H3A05CDD75B2243E7BEBADE645F0F737F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/45Z">Section 45Z(g)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended to read as follows: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBF98A6D5FC41408EA640F5F5A0D284A6" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H99A50B573CF84BDF8AD03DF0D4F7FD0B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section shall not apply—</text><paragraph id="H9B009AF7ADD64EA7BF181E02FAC64E41"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of transportation fuel which is not sustainable aviation fuel, to fuel sold after December 31, 2027, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H244F68F4CEB04BEBB4C7952D1BA84B57"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of sustainable aviation fuel, to fuel sold after December 31, 2032. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H2261010438A2486DB19BB550D235865D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to fuel produced after December 31, 2027.</text></subsection></section><section id="H47EEE7D2AFC14D7FB21F5B13FF1B4957"><enum>10.</enum><header>Sustainable aviation fuel production property added to Energy Credit</header><subsection id="H8E2F4CC1C9DA479E92E5DEEB2F08F89D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/48">Section 48</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3EB60E781FE94794AF33512ED1003080"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H93CDC48620D448D5BC5C4F2F6E1432F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A)(i)—</text><clause id="H30865FEA7B5C468AB9412A6B137FACE9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subclause (VIII), by striking <quote>and</quote>, and</text></clause><clause id="HF52851465C1C4CAB97F890AA38102369"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subclause: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCA17A04BB89E4E70B7C19F07B0C37D5E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subclause id="H5C6440CEFA7C42F3B65D49142FEB3204"><enum>(X)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sustainable aviation fuel production property, and</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>, </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H364AD7F8B1E34E67B9726A5F49541F21"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(A), by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of clause (x), inserting <quote>or</quote> at the end of clause (xi), and by adding at the end the following new clause: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HCBF63E15648A4FD683A1F8FE2586A6C3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="HBDE213C522C34E45A3AE1524E6D1EC57"><enum>(xii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sustainable aviation fuel production property, </text></clause><after-quoted-block>, and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1AD547A8914740CDAD7BB7381EA05345"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (16) as paragraph (17) and by inserting after paragraph (15) the following new paragraph: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF3557D95D5BB48FFBB91B72730BBB396" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H00C6D19A55CC465DA7CBB3FAEA620318"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Phaseout for sustainable aviation fuel production property</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of any energy property described in paragraph (3)(A)(xii) the construction of which begins before January 1, 2037, the energy percentage determined under paragraph (2) shall be equal to—</text><subparagraph id="H87B76D9EFA3C4A43B8B1256F4E78CE8C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any property the construction of which begins after December 31, 2028, and before January 1, 2030, 24 percent,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BE85E0C1F8B45C29096622B7D1A32FE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any property the construction of which begins after December 31, 2029, and before January 1, 2031, 18 percent, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H738DBB5B51BE477E831ED0015EC6BC9A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of any property the construction of which begins after December 31, 2030, and before January 1, 2037, 12 percent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>, and </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3B72FCAF3574445BD21F5DE55BD8233"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c), by adding at the end the following new paragraph: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7AC504128BAC4E28B6062C62401A31FC" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H0B6486E64C6F41F48DC8C61D02069158" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Sustainable aviation fuel production property</header><subparagraph id="HA6A71EE484304A53B98B4E0A6DE4414D" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <quote>sustainable aviation fuel production property</quote> means—</text><clause id="HF1EC0B22F22C47B7BA4C62701BB8A97F" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">property which produces sustainable aviation fuel (as defined in section 40B(d)), or</text></clause><clause id="H5F465102B8C44CD1B09BE5DE96C09BBD" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">property directly related to enabling the production or distribution of sustainable aviation fuel.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFEB561929A0241EA930FE5A41CD26436" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Recapture of credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall, by regulations, provide for recapturing the benefit of any credit allowable under subsection (a)(3)(A)(xii) with respect to any sustainable aviation fuel production property if the sustainable aviation fuel production of such property comprises less than 80 percent of the total fuel production of such property in any of the 5 taxable years immediately following the taxable year in which such property was placed in service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB32D8EAFD92545348044566786E04732"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this section shall apply to fuel produced after December 31, 2023.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

