<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF5B642C2E76F4DE2B1CFACCC50FFD0CF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6673 IH: Strengthening the Tenth Amendment Through Entrusting States 2.0 Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6673</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000295">Mr. Joyce of Ohio</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Controlled Substances Act to provide for a new rule regarding the application of the Act to marijuana, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0D8D2EE906424615AD3C7AA5C117B059" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H41E2AACCF91D49319698D47A6B6410D7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Strengthening the Tenth Amendment Through Entrusting States 2.0 Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>STATES 2.0 Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H69915870880F45D9985190B5AD68CBBB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE2231669D7D74AB3B23BA256B17D8685"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">States have vastly different visions for the role of legal cannabis in their cities and counties. Some wish to see a complete prohibition, while others believe cannabis should be treated like alcohol. States should be empowered to determine their own destiny for the cannabis markets. They should be able to enact time, place, and manner restrictions that help to aid small and craft businesses, impose regulations for health and safety, keep cannabis businesses away from schools, and generally fit with the character and values of the community.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HECBE438D0CD546068069CB38FBCBF95B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While States have the power to determine what happens within their own borders, they cannot make laws permitting or restricting interstate commerce unilaterally. In the absence of Federal movement, the illicit interstate trade in cannabis has persisted even in the face of significant State policy changes. The Federal Government should be responsible for regulating and tracking this interstate trade to ensure cannabis does not end up where it does not belong.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB0C43AD439264A29A107A0042C4158F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Today’s illicit marijuana market represents 75 percent of the known marijuana market.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBB2AD019041F43E7A779260D5031003D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Excessive taxation in licensed markets has caused the price of legal marijuana products to exceed that of illegal products by two to three times, contributing to the growth of the illicit market.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD46C5CFC91ED4DB38AFC5993D5B8AC3B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Because of Federal restrictions on marijuana activities, marijuana is currently regulated by a punitive tax structure that harms the ability of licensed operators to sell marijuana products, discourages new business creation and growth, and perpetuates illicit markets.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC11E68B9CA674403A1911BBE6FA5209B"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A Federal regulatory program for marijuana should require a framework that supports critical components such as proper administration and oversight, consumer safety protections, and enforcement.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDCDCD01FB26941F7901A274990C7A06E"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The cost of such a program should fall on users of the program through the establishment of a Federal excise tax. Such a Federal marijuana tax should—</text> <subparagraph id="H4B2C6206F2A84FADA7A12F15DCAECAD7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>support a legal market, not illegal sales and illicit activity;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4748420F88CA47A1B9C5D81A745BC028"><enum>(B)</enum><text>be low enough to not exacerbate the level of taxation set by States, thereby avoiding the pyramid effect of adding Federal taxes on top of high State taxes;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H73B0F7B5CE3A44C2BCC622B31A80FAA6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>be administrable and allow for consistent and timely collection by the Alcohol and Tobacco Tax and Trade Bureau as primary regulator; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1254FE92B5514F8EB06ABFE90A126939"><enum>(D)</enum><text>offset the costs of executing the administrative functions of a Federal regulatory framework for marijuana, including requirements for testing, enforcement and policing, youth prevention, and substance abuse prevention and education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67B23BDDEB024396A27080FB7332C6FB"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">States that legalize cannabis utilize less public safety resources on cannabis arrests. This has allowed more police resources to be devoted to violent and property crime as well as more serious types of illicit substances.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H00A5B2D972764B029619221B2DB0971E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress regarding FDA support for Tribal self-determination and self-government with respect to marijuana regulation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that, with respect to the regulation of the manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery of marijuana, the Food and Drug Administration should support—</text> <paragraph id="H8AAEC252B5564B66B5FB6BE954D75F7C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>self-determination and self-government by Indian tribes (as defined in section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5130">25 U.S.C. 5130</external-xref>)); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA0B6CEDAB96145D9907B62AB887E7739"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the treaty rights of such Indian tribes.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H61670C77BA2A445C86C835AF8F0AA391"><enum>4.</enum><header>Rule regarding application to marijuana</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part G of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/801">21 U.S.C. 801 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A5FB75A203B498C9391D3993F3B50B8" style="traditional"> 
<section id="HA65DB2B70602458E8B0F24FE362499DB"><enum>710.</enum><header>Rule regarding application to marijuana</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H4EFDC0DDB9B14AB3939135A0AA2745D3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the provisions of this Act as applied to marijuana, except the provisions described in subsection (d) and except as provided in subsection (e), shall not apply to any marijuana manufactured, produced, possessed, distributed, dispensed, administered, or delivered in compliance with State law relating to the manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery of marijuana.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8D751628BBC248528A33714FD6979789"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Indian Tribes</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the provisions of this Act related to marijuana, except the provisions described in subsection (d) and except as provided in subsection (e), shall not apply to marijuana manufactured, produced, possessed, distributed, dispensed, administered, or delivered in compliance with the law of a federally recognized Indian Tribe relating to the manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery of marijuana within its jurisdiction in Indian country, as defined in section 1151 of title 18, United States Code, so long as such jurisdiction is located within a State that permits, as applicable, the manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery of marijuana.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA6B9E011D86C4127A4935D870D301B9E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Interstate transportation</header> 
<paragraph id="HE6D687C352984E3BAE30DE4411567A61"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State law</header> 
<subparagraph id="HB7D0FAB8E1A64926A7A72DEAE5DBC769"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No State or Indian Tribe may prohibit the transportation or shipment of marijuana through the State or the territory of the Indian Tribe, as applicable, if the originating and destination States or territories permit, as applicable, the manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery of marijuana.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA3E4025B9B8E4D0D998D4B9EB27D51B0" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (A) shall not be construed to limit the authority of an originating or destination State or territory to impose reasonable restrictions within its jurisdiction on the manufacture, production, possession, distribution dispensation, administration, or delivery of marijuana—</text> 
<clause id="H6F3FBC1DBE544A36A06C725AC5228CD9" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>through time, place, and manner restrictions; or</text></clause> <clause id="H567EA13FE1FA4767A269062B544C151C" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to protect public health and safety.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0D27C9ACBB57464E9D3A91A63B2794AE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Federal law</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the provisions of this title as applied to marijuana, except the provisions described in subsection (d) and except as provided in subsection (e), shall not apply to any person engaged in marijuana transportation or shipment between two States which States permit, as applicable, the manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery of marijuana.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4C2FE291E94D4F50878D4205A7704B67"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Provisions described</header><text>The provisions described in this subsection are—</text> 
<paragraph id="H7114AB3D9C9A4E6FBFED6C8AAE043F54"><enum>(1)</enum><text>section 401(a)(1), with respect to a violation of section 409 or 418;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H040C690AE0724C94ABECAEE40ACD3D35"><enum>(2)</enum><text>section 409;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3CFD06371CDF4AA5A3DBF21D0D43B673"><enum>(3)</enum><text>section 417; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2DF0644785A1490580F4C2CF3DBFD8E6"><enum>(4)</enum><text>section 418.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6F5A703935B74F2EAA4A4C72FCD065CD"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subsections (a) through (c) shall not apply to any person who—</text> <paragraph id="HE88057080E8E44A592C21B8BEC269587"><enum>(1)</enum><text>violates this title with respect to any controlled substance other than marijuana;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF304BF3FB25E4E1B9FB6D33A286BDEFC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>knowingly or intentionally manufactures, produces, possesses, distributes, dispenses, administers, or delivers any marijuana in violation of the laws of the State or Indian Tribe in which such manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery occurs; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8E51398FE1534B72870A4DE2EE8A371E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>employs or hires any person under 18 years of age to manufacture, produce, distribute, dispense, administer, or deliver marijuana.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H89854DBF2D4B4EB09488085F7BA41DC7"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Removal from schedule</header> 
<paragraph id="HB93EFFACA0F94632BF1993EE4432AA66"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For the purposes of this title, marijuana manufactured, produced, possessed, distributed, dispensed, administered, or delivered in compliance with State law or the law of a federally recognized Indian Tribe relating to the manufacture, production, possession, distribution, dispensation, administration, or delivery of marijuana shall be deemed to be a substance that does not meet the requirements for inclusion in any schedule.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H955D161C83C44581B843794D39213F46"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rules</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Attorney General shall finalize a rule under section 201(a)(2) executing paragraph (1) of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H30192332F4FE4B2FA002EEFD8D979B5B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given to the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5130">25 U.S.C. 5130</external-xref>).</text> </subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="HDCF560A3D3AF401296C6D513016C2B78" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>5.</enum><header>Transportation safety offenses</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 409 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/849">21 U.S.C. 849</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HAD26AABF8A244A3684A2A3DB072DBE65"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b), in the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="HCE80AE9B159C4436A98FAE83E9E37CD5"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>A person</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in subsection (d), a person</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H864AE9340D9B43A2A431802DCBB6D8A5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsection (b)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (c)</quote>;</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3BE2A5620F3544CC843EDAC53A623622"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c), in the matter preceding paragraph (1)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H7B2600ABAFB04167883CBBA13A5AB657"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>A person</quote> and inserting <quote>Except as provided in subsection (d), a person</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCC03E9D4F05C43B0B7F5B341713E6A3A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subsection (a)</quote> and inserting <quote>subsection (b)</quote>; and</text> </subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1B637B37988A426894006C1DD9A4F350"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCD2803242294AB38FC8E033DF8343F2" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H390A700A3C0C4E99AA73D1187B46A201"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subsections (b) and (c) shall not apply to any person who possesses, or possesses with intent to distribute marijuana in compliance with section 710.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </paragraph></section>
<section id="H7A86443A2EB94577B644AA562E0C9E3A"><enum>6.</enum><header>Distribution to persons under age 21</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 418 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/859">21 U.S.C. 859</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H60CEE8ACFCEA46A585445C7CA3382940"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a), in the first sentence, by inserting <quote>and subsection (c) of this section</quote> after <quote>section 419</quote>;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB4059AEC7DED4E018242874DB99D088F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b), in the first sentence, by inserting <quote>and subsection(c) of this section</quote> after <quote>section 419</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H38D4F51BE05840729211F0AE1D051E44"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8581792DBC8458B913DA628294D5BB3" style="OLC"> 
<subsection id="H2C2AC3D4B2D5450A882CA1F2B1BA66C7"><enum>(c)</enum><text>Subsections (a) and (b) shall not apply to any person at least 18 years of age who distributes medicinal marijuana to a person under 21 years of age in compliance with section 710.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="HF75D76D4F2DC4AC4AE5709CC31C2A90C" commented="no"><enum>7.</enum><header>Regulation of marijuana products by Food and Drug Administration</header> <subsection id="H0EB890E5769D4FAF9EDD687612CFCBA7" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header> <paragraph id="H0ECB6440CC764D35BBA1CE59DF161898"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Marijuana product defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>marijuana product</term> means any product made or derived from marijuana that is intended for human or animal consumption, including any component of marijuana (except for raw materials other than such marijuana used in manufacturing a component of such product).</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9A475A98C1974AAB89F4BC7E89A5A92B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <subparagraph id="HCAE432AC2E9B49AFAD0E2D9325EABF76"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>biological product</term> has the meaning given to that term in section 351(i) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(i)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7161443E843A479D866F3628DC51D9E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>marijuana</term> has the meaning given to that term in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H07D53751F26847878F7D5FE615D4BF11"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>cosmetic</term>, <term>device</term>, <term>dietary supplement</term>, <term>drug</term>, <term>food</term>, and <term>tobacco product</term> have the meanings given to such terms in section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1022A6E7342C43BE9DE6A92B3DCA05F1" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Drugs</header><text>A marijuana product meeting the definition of a drug shall be treated as a drug for purposes of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H75087C14A9DD4A60AEB2015451D15174" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Food; dietary supplements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall have the same authorities under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>) and other applicable law to regulate a marijuana product that is food or a dietary supplement as the Food and Drug Administration has with respect to food containing alcohol.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H8C9A6EC950634325BD2AF327A5B0637B" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cosmetics</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A marijuana product meeting the definition of a cosmetic shall be treated as a cosmetic for purposes of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6DD63FEBCB1E46A691C3D41AEDDAF51B" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Other products</header> <paragraph id="HE20414AF1142498BA5721A18EBB3EE1A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A marijuana product that is not covered by subsection (b), (c), or (d) may be lawfully marketed pursuant to regulations issued under paragraph (2).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB6F7B1D5008F40418BAC206910A96A98" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regulation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, shall promulgate a regulation with respect to marijuana products described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC45A7F50CC694600BB7435C06AA9FFEE" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The regulation under paragraph (2) shall include requirements for—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HB8B43814661F4ECEA82ADE49962FD70F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>contaminant testing;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H594E0322AA5048B9BA044FFEE165E2CA" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>manufacturing practices; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1B4BEA388A8948A9A8E010A97E6EBDE1" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>marketing practices and postmarket reporting, with special attention to preventing consumption by youths.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB00953FD07DC411BBD7A194F8511FBB1" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>No premarket approval required</header><text>The regulation under paragraph (2) shall not require premarket approval of marijuana products described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC1B0AAFA07BF424C9B84879DA471707A" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>No marketing in combination with certain other products</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A marijuana product marketed in combination with a drug, a biological product, a device, a tobacco product, or an alcohol product is deemed to be adulterated for purposes of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/301">21 U.S.C. 301 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> <section id="H3816C74AD32A46919CEA2D0ED4AAE735"><enum>8.</enum><header>Comptroller General study on effects of marijuana legalization on traffic safety</header> <subsection id="HA1CFFEB276E74AA384A54BFD5A404A66"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a study on the effects of marijuana legalization on traffic safety.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H5864C44639FB4FE7A6A1AE3865CFAB90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusions</header><text>The study conducted under subsection (a) shall include a detailed assessment of—</text> <paragraph id="HBD4409FD94204ADC87BB52697B17C61F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>traffic crashes, fatalities, and injuries in States that have legalized marijuana use, including whether States are able to accurately evaluate marijuana impairment in those incidents;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3B30F9802AD94927B522F0E78A6AFAB8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>actions taken by the States referred to in paragraph (1) to address marijuana-impaired driving, including any challenges faced in addressing marijuana-impaired driving;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61C668D0ACC14D3AA0FC1CFE13E0F1FF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>testing standards used by the States referred to in paragraph (1) to evaluate marijuana impairment in traffic crashes, fatalities, and injuries, including any scientific methods used to determine impairment and analyze data; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H57BEFFB0AE634A06AD19CD20E84BCBD9"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Federal initiatives aiming to assist States that have legalized marijuana with traffic safety, including recommendations for policies and programs to be carried out by the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAAF598919296484C80F4D8EED4CCA338"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report on the results of the study conducted under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HCC270910B4ED40279AE36D224E5F0EDE"><enum>9.</enum><header>Rule of construction</header> 
<subsection id="H26B9D42B95724E5C8E3957FCA9AC5D9C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conduct in compliance with this Act and the amendments made by this Act—</text> <paragraph id="HCB4FD4D239C04B5C84896A4DB534F134"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not be unlawful;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H066EB580917C41EE9D94BA184693B2CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall not constitute trafficking in a controlled substance under section 401 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/841">21 U.S.C. 841</external-xref>) or any other provision of law;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE3C5F924DE3A4E5D8488D11F837FED99"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall not constitute the basis for forfeiture of property under section 511 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/881">21 U.S.C. 881</external-xref>) or section 981 of title 18, United States Code; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H689A5958FD144040B28CD1D22EE4615B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall not be subject to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/280E">section 280E</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, relating to expenditures in connection with the illegal sale of drugs.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2658E32908184FEC992B1A4B4B93C910"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds</header><text>The proceeds from any transaction in compliance with this Act and the amendments made by this Act shall not be deemed to be the proceeds of an unlawful transaction under section 1956 or 1957 of title 18, United States Code, or any other provision of law.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

