<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE7A814F1B9854277A5AF2254BC06B731" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6228 IH: To require the Secretary of Transportation and the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection to develop an alternative platform to LOGINK, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6228</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231103">November 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Transportation and the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection to develop an alternative platform to LOGINK, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H04C8235F37B3480390136CC9C3462160" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H574E590772A749F296C5C0B12A33C256" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Alternative network required</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary of Transportation and the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection shall take such steps as may be necessary—</text> <paragraph id="H9E0A9574841845928FA637B9BA7EFC31"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to work with the International Maritime Organization, the European Commission, and appropriate international governmental organizations to develop a secure platform, with architecture that cannot be manipulated, managed, operated, or infiltrated by foreign adversaries, as an alternative to the public, open, shared logistics information network known as the National Public Information Platform for Transportation &amp; Logistics (<quote>LOGINK</quote>) maintained by the Ministry of Transport of China in support of the Chinese Communist Party and China’s State Council transportation superpower plans; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H29BA20F451014FBA93C7455E0B2DB0BD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to develop standards for United States and global logistics information networks to protect United States national and economic security interests, as well as those of allied and partner countries, from potential espionage or sabotage.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H1E2785B253394FA6B2FC88504A6587C0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reports</header> <subsection id="H418B780A070943D0A0F8FBC6B5012F12"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report describing—</text> 
<paragraph id="H744E6F1CD2624B41A8E1BB554BCDCFF4"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the possible national security threats that United States and international ports and other critical infrastructure may encounter due to the use of LOGINK;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01DA26BAAE8643EF8978A9B44EE8A8D9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the possible threats on the commercial operations of United States and international ports and other critical infrastructure due to the use of LOGINK; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7662D960DB73437FAF7A6D8C26B90B8D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>steps taken to protect United States national and economic security interests with respect to logistics information networks.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H51E0541A08A34A9D9F85CC21DB19BA78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<paragraph id="H79D9DF4B2B2844A4BD7068FDD7B1E8CF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Homeland Security, the Committee on Ways and Means, and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFB8C53A375FD460B97E2CBA0D4F18300"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, the Committee on Finance, and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

