<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCB3C3463D1EC42E092A4CE7739D61635" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 851 IH: Iron Pipeline Review Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 851</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230206">February 6, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives to report on firearms trafficking along the I–95 corridor.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H0177911974FE4213B75856910C23F9D8" style="OLC">
<section id="HAAB0C9A6FB9F46C3A407C795AEF6E42E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Iron Pipeline Review Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H7DAC7794D3DA4FAAA8943E64D6C7CAE4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives report on firearms trafficking along the I–95 corridor</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Director of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, in consultation with State and local law enforcement entities, and other agencies or stakeholders as determined appropriate by the Director, shall submit to the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate a report on firearms trafficked along Interstate 95 that contains the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H29F569E88B2D4229B0F1BC468D44C247"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An analysis of the number of firearms trafficked along Interstate 95, that contains the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H66149117C4094E08B6A08863B600D8C6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Firearms listed by the State of origin, and the make and model of the firearm.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3DCC4EB112454590B191034D311F1E7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An analysis of the effectiveness of counter firearm trafficking measures.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6197FDD7B4264755BA9DC3688A10CA76"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An analysis of specific local, State and Federal laws that affect the number of firearms trafficked.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6B7BE6706CD44D51B14D01A202E35621"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of any actions directed as a result of the analysis conducted under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEE148D0870F84D19AE74811342363E70"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Recommendations, as appropriate, for Federal, State and local law enforcement entities to improve firearm trafficking measures referred to in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDEF84958898B4CC4ACBFA2DE0D21F144"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Proposals, as appropriate, for legislative actions and funding needed to improve measures to counter firearm trafficking.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

