<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H87C777BE40964A8C8FE1BE7D34EDF020" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5259 IH: PFAS Exposure Assessment and Documentation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5259</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230822">August 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000463">Mr. Turner</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to include in periodic health assessments of members of the Armed Forces an evaluation of whether the member has been exposed to perfluoroalkyl substances and polyfluoroalkyl substances, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1A959EA407424C9CB6166FB7A7B802CC" style="OLC"><section id="H75648C441E8946A298C8C3DD2F3A895E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>PFAS Exposure Assessment and Documentation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF0094D17C853498CB2027AA8C9869507"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inclusion of exposure to perfluoroalkyl and polyfluoroalkyl substances as part of periodic health assessments</header><subsection id="H3C8D92CE332C43CE9D279138571D763A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Periodic health assessment</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall ensure that any periodic health assessment provided to a member of the Armed Forces includes an evaluation of whether the member has been—</text><paragraph id="HF50CAE477E454728A720C5A81065152B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>based or stationed at a military installation identified by the Department of Defense as a location with a known or suspected release of perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances during the period in which the member was based or stationed at the military installation; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H863EE89B10364EF09D6C1ECB977CFA74"><enum>(2)</enum><text>exposed to such substances, including by evaluating any information in the health record of the member.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2850512ADF3747C597FB0DD1C2F26E08"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Separation history and physical examinations</header><text>Section 1145(a)(5) of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B61A8DA9F2246D2BA74268953CB3A61"><subparagraph id="H7E2E591B5D314AA19E978B706115AF2D" indent="up2"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Secretary concerned shall ensure that each physical examination of a member under subparagraph (A) includes an assessment of whether the member was—</text><clause id="HD0B2EB67013041D09142BCE3D205A832"><enum>(i)</enum><text>based or stationed at a military installation identified by the Department as a location with a known or suspected release of perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances during the period in which the member was based or stationed at the military installation; or</text></clause><clause id="HA6F90F25E2A046C6AC93EA77B353B9EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>exposed to such substances, including by assessing any information in the health record of the member.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HCA4DAA898A9F41EFAE176F06A7EA7339"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Deployment assessments</header><text>Section 1074f(b)(2) of title 10, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H150AA0DD993A4AF3B90EA2D1A5002269"><subparagraph id="HB4C7546B5B5C4A76871D29E177037ACE" indent="up1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An assessment of whether the member was—</text><clause id="HEC9A9FF9752E42DCA3E74C8E5CDBAC4E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>based or stationed at a military installation identified by the Department as a location with a known or suspected release of perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances during the period in which the member was based or stationed at the military installation; or</text></clause><clause id="H1C92B946984046B2B548D952F8824838"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>exposed to such substances, including by assessing any information in the health record of the member.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H74DB7A63C6D44E508CAB81694A5F2425"><enum>3.</enum><header>Provision of blood testing for members of the Armed Forces, former members of the Armed Forces, and their families to determine exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances</header><subsection id="H86BC410C625E4329A9244DB66DFB3444"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Members of the Armed Forces</header><paragraph id="H043FFB3036B7455785DC646D3D903B77"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a covered evaluation of a member of the Armed Forces results in a positive determination of potential exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances, the Secretary of Defense shall provide to that member, during that covered evaluation, blood testing to determine and document potential exposure to such substances.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D3DE3A8E93A4794BE9F5924125D1F17"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion in health record</header><text>The results of blood testing of a member of the Armed Forces conducted under paragraph (1) shall be included in the health record of the member.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD83E3530EC4E4A5690425E32B263BC87"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Former members of the Armed Forces and family members</header><text>The Secretary shall pay for blood testing to determine and document potential exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances for any covered individual, at the election of the individual, either through the TRICARE program for individuals otherwise eligible for such program or through the use of vouchers to obtain such testing.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB2C293E5C9B24BA1B7DCAFF94E80F92D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HEFA680431F5B4F8DA8232B96C8A99AF5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>covered evaluation</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H90B0011E80E84D17B86ECAB38406AF20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a periodic health assessment conducted in accordance with section 2(a);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58ED76B980314CA7917CBB53E79F2C64"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a separation history and physical examination conducted under section 1145(a)(5) of title 10, United States Code, as amended by section 2(b); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBF58CDE14B34F44884253D5FEE7F89E" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a deployment assessment conducted under section 1074f(b)(2) of such title, as amended by section 2(c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H35B5CEB8A3D44249A8EE0C2E50B363E7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>covered individual</term> means a former member of the Armed Forces or a family member of a member or former member of the Armed Forces who lived at a location (or the surrounding area of such a location) identified by the Department of Defense as a location with a known or suspected release of perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances during the period in which the individual lived at that location (or surrounding area).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H249C138487B643EE8F3DAB1F9AE078CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <term>TRICARE program</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1072(7) of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H4996EE125E6446B2BA0AEFBE6DC8170D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Documentation of exposure to perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances</header><subsection id="H7038EEF7254C4E00B942C3C9E7F99DF4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sharing of information</header><text>The Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall enter into a memorandum of understanding providing for the sharing by the Department of Defense with the Department of Veterans Affairs of the results of covered evaluations regarding the exposure by a member of the Armed Forces to perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB30A3B882D9F48999E8E157837BF68B8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Registry</header><paragraph id="H3E9BBB19F94441188F7BF4BFEBC9B110"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall establish a registry of members of the Armed Forces who have been exposed to, or are suspected to have been exposed to, perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFE4B036A9FC4EBE93CF63BD51F53933"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion in registry</header><text>The Secretary shall include a member of the Armed Forces in the registry established under paragraph (1) if a covered evaluation of the member establishes that the member—</text><subparagraph id="H91F3AEDD18B04C589B43D1C1C2DF81BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>was based or stationed at a location identified by the Department of Defense as a location with a known or suspected release of perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances during the period in which the member was based or stationed at the location; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H719FD644EE7943C182350EE319EE283D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>was exposed to such substances.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5BDDC0FF6BA40A0B5DF1524D7C63773"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Blood testing</header><text>The results of any blood test conducted under section 3(a) shall be included in the registry established under paragraph (1) for any member of the Armed Forces included in the registry. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AAFA0C2A3F44580AE824D791586A817"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Election</header><text>A member of the Armed Forces may elect not to be included in the registry established under paragraph (1). </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC5E4A70656DC4FCCBB44345E08A338A7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Provision of information</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall provide to a member of the Armed Forces more information on perfluoroalkyl substances and polyfluoroalkyl substances and the potential impact of exposure to such substances if a covered evaluation of such member establishes that the member—</text><paragraph id="H090992DEF24B4105A0969F4CC4C676A9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>was based or stationed at a location identified by the Department of Defense as a location with a known or suspected release of perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances during the period in which the member was based or stationed at the location; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86C8C1EA56C2452C8D923020CF7DAAD9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>was exposed to such substances. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HABC116CFC61645ADA611E56EA93DEEEE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to preclude eligibility of a veteran for benefits under the laws administered by the Secretary of Veterans Affairs by reason of the exposure of the veteran to perfluoroalkyl substances or polyfluoroalkyl substances not being recorded in a covered evaluation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H96D344198AEE4882A1CBE56C2C0AAC65"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Covered evaluation defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>covered evaluation</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H81C318A109C049808ECC698BB9F0B6BB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a periodic health assessment conducted in accordance with section 2(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85E87A9CA4A0498C99E7EB372B207FE5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a separation history and physical examination conducted under section 1145(a)(5) of title 10, United States Code, as amended by section 2(b); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57F1FD06CE2148819065695CD80342B0" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a deployment assessment conducted under section 1074f(b)(2) of such title, as amended by section 2(c).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

