<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1621FE68EB3149B99710EDA4615EAFCB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3069 IH: John Lewis Equality in Medicare and Medicaid Treatment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-02</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3069</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230502">May 2, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XI of the Social Security Act to improve access to care for all Medicare and Medicaid beneficiaries through models tested under the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H422E8CA038BF42729134469D60E95066" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF78F5B6B5C46496292B4BB463DC8DB89" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>John Lewis Equality in Medicare and Medicaid Treatment Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HB94ED83843E24380A06D0C9A54D34C97"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improving access to care for Medicare and Medicaid beneficiaries</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1115A of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1315a">42 U.S.C. 1315a</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HCD77652998754425BB3B7570C7516C6A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HF183548621D1448B9AC405628FC960EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>advance health equity and</quote> before <quote>improve the coordination</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H829ED44000C7488EB92D7F4DA831D0D5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text> <clause id="H33815CB8ECA14DF8942027DEE7BF5D6F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>(including the Office of Minority Health of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, the Office of Rural Health Policy of the Health Resources and Services Administration, and the Office on Women’s Health of the Department of Health and Human Services)</quote> after <quote>relevant Federal agencies</quote>; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HD9D3B016618544359AC1F629CFB798EF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>experts with expertise in medicine</quote> and inserting <quote>experts with expertise in medicine, the causes of health disparities and the social determinants of health,</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H943C56CC92F244F2A91AE0685025EED6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD7FCDD5F349943B5AFC28101FF55A12A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text> <clause id="HF1B3633E455146939532D4CFC6029B12"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text> 
<subclause id="H14428E551D334DE79D470AB05831729D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting the following after the first sentence: <quote>Prior to selecting a model under this paragraph, the Secretary shall consult with the Office of Minority Health of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, the Office of Rural Health Policy of the Health Resources and Services Administration, and the Office on Women’s Health of the Department of Health and Human Services to ensure that models under consideration address health disparities and social determinants of health as appropriate for populations to be cared for under the model.</quote>; </text></subclause> <subclause id="H1C8EF3BEAF324D9293D86DC118F9BC5E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and, for models for which testing begins on or after January 1, 2024, address health equity as well as improving access to care received by individuals receiving benefits under such title</quote> after <quote>applicable title</quote>; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H689A40F5620543A09D57682554C69843"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: <quote>The models selected under this subparagraph shall include the social determinants of health payment model described in subsection (h), the testing of which shall begin not later than December 31, 2024.</quote>; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HB2A07332F0A14131A37CC25F3ABC3CD7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by adding at the end the following new clauses:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDF7D6CBB10824A0EA9268F5CE0BE1A2E"> 
<clause id="H6A9F46EAC97945E2AB91FC8BDE99ACA6"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>Whether the model will affect access to care from providers and suppliers caring for high risk patients or operating in underserved areas.</text></clause> <clause id="H8C1756029A0C4B229F5B4FF669D40C63"><enum>(x)</enum><text>Whether the model has the potential to reduce health disparities, including minority and rural health disparities.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H1E69244EBE03487B9497D8A75FF4216C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(B)—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H6102AD48D0FE4C8E8E27D483781F414A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), by inserting <quote>or health equity</quote> after <quote>quality of care</quote>;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H6EA1021DAF2A446F9E15769E14F7C60E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by inserting <quote>or increasing health inequities</quote> after <quote>quality of care</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H24DA03B5DCBA431190594D8E2DA1AF03"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by inserting <quote>or health equity</quote> after <quote>quality of care</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HACCE1EC16721439B9624F8C3A5A00368"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)(A)—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H8D64AF73FAF944F88D4E96B8AAB58D78"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H455C8BB1DAD94CBA957ED2088094B0BA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking the period and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H7798FA6791044787AD5D7FFE7F5A8392"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2152D8B9D3744692A1607A519D5D719B"> 
<clause id="H17D34D83F4BB4C5CB2BAD2F63FACCE9C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>for models for which testing begins on or after January 1, 2024, the extent to which the model improves health equity. </text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H81BF938FBCAB4E54A90C686E31A481BB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HA1FFFE64BDCD4EA287EEEEE76C3C3BFE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H44F18DC0AE194BA0898FDC950C2859C6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or, beginning on or after January 1, 2024, increasing health inequities</quote> before the semicolon; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H05FA43C04F0C4864BDD0695EF1CD9FB6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text> in subparagraph (B), by inserting <quote>or, beginning on or after January 1, 2024, health equity</quote> after <quote>patient care</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HB779C00B88564D2397AB3F01D2212142"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by inserting <quote>or increase health disparities experienced by beneficiaries, including low-income, minority, or rural beneficiaries, or that such expansion would improve health equity</quote> before the period; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H36A0D5998C7A491489642518F8460F82"><enum>(4)</enum><text>in subsection (g), by adding at the end the following: </text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="HAE421C756F064E0F826D0E5577CC4FA4"><text>For reports submitted after the date of enactment of the <short-title>John Lewis Equality in Medicare and Medicaid Treatment Act of 2023</short-title>, each such report shall include information on the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H6A57A053787F4129BAFC1A5A3D1411CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The interventions that address social determinants of health, health disparities, or health equity in payment models selected by the CMI for testing under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBE36E6E7434E40049D92C4099B48ACA3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Estimated Federal savings achieved through reducing disparities, including rural and minority health disparities, improving health equity, or addressing social determinants of health.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFCF2726065A7447693CD8A5DAD4A64CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The effectiveness of interventions in mitigating negative health outcomes and higher costs associated with social determinants of health within models selected by the Center for Medicare and Medicaid Innovation for testing.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAF3010C18D7C479ABD52ADF09BA11EAD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Other areas determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H96B86B5EB73745CC9CF5411E14284582"><enum>(5)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2AAD466BFDD047E28B033560CB4361AB"> <subsection id="HE8BC4EDE67E54A04BEFBF52863E49892"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Social determinants of health payment model</header> <paragraph id="H4170FDBB08D042F4BA7698D97528D832"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The social determinants of health payment model described in this subsection is a payment model that tests each of the payment and service delivery innovations described in paragraph (2) in a region determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7E88F92568154C11B39C0B10C56D6D10"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Payment and service delivery innovations described</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the payment and service delivery innovations described in this clause are the following:</text> <subparagraph id="H20AE37FF7FDA4C4AAAA680B7BA2A5681"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Payment and service delivery innovations for behavioral health services, focusing on gathering actionable data to address the higher costs associated with beneficiaries with diagnosed behavioral conditions.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H499F6A8803FF4C8F8293183DBC4D5E1A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Payment and service delivery innovations targeting conditions or comorbidities of individuals entitled or enrolled under the Medicare program under title XVIII and enrolled under a State plan under the Medicaid program under title XIX to increase capacity in underserved areas.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBD5E7FAA286E4F51ACB49BB593006BA5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Payment and service delivery innovations targeting conditions or comorbidities of applicable individuals to increase capacity in underserved areas.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8240C68016CF4A83BCFD9031556591E0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Payment and service delivery innovations targeted on Medicaid eligible pregnant and postpartum women, up to one year after delivery. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

