<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA62D3BACDA884D5581F5C7CA108E1BAA" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4371 IH: School Sports Safety Study Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4371</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230627">June 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and in consultation with the Secretary of Education and the President&#8217;s Council on Fitness, Sports, and Nutrition, to conduct a study on the causes of deaths and catastrophic injuries related to high school and collegiate sports and formulate recommendations to prevent such deaths and catastrophic injuries, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3AA4A79AF45C475C819738E0193F24A8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H83D3D33806C2487493C182B39EC78B50" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>School Sports Safety Study Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H815FF5A12AC54281A0057947E5F906F1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text> 
<paragraph id="H2CC64045B2E84BA09F7D66A33118AE15"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the National Center for Catastrophic Sports Injury Research, 2,958 high school and collegiate players from all sports combined have suffered direct traumatic injuries from 1982 to 2021. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCCDD4C6078404FFA866656C118E4BAA8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Over the past several years, the negative health effects of repeated trauma have become clearer.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31B5275792D04BD2B41CE7ADF2BDDE3C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Protecting the Nation’s children and young adults is one of the most important responsibilities of parents and elected leaders.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H3948851B9A5F41B882A8061B699828C8"><enum>3.</enum><header>Studying deaths related to high school and collegiate sports and developing recommendations to prevent future tragedies</header> <subsection id="H6E9A105C44CE43CCB11DBD044A37E695"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>), acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and in consultation with the Secretary of Education and the President’s Council on Fitness, Sports, and Nutrition, shall conduct a study—</text> 
<paragraph id="HC09B867BA7A54BF59225694CB644A0CC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to more precisely identify the causes of deaths and catastrophic injuries related to high school and collegiate sports; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H00DD5B3020474E8F887E0FA094F1CF83"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to develop recommendations to prevent such deaths and catastrophic injuries in the future.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEB545BBBE75C418983EECC3EB455F143"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Soliciting input</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Secretary shall seek input from nongovernmental entities, including organizations representing coaches, athletic trainers, parents, and health care professionals.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3ED68D1116494BAF839FD66990F1F651"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Dissemination of recommendations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall disseminate the final recommendations developed under subsection (a)(2) to high schools and institutions of higher education across the United States.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HCE56012E32F9487AADE76073F3753B15"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress and publish on the public website of the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality a report on the results of the study under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H3D9BE9E0836A43529130F29AAD2C1810"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Topics of study</header><text>The study under subsection (a) shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9738CEF1EF95473BA54154EBF20F91FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a comprehensive review of research conducted on deaths and catastrophic injuries in high school and collegiate sports;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4A8726A3AF3F49F4AF9A7F2BC1F3920D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an evaluation of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HDEB78E8EF5F6421CA0C78FA5479448F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the causes of such deaths and catastrophic injuries; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HED188241007549E6ABD050C82D63E09D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effectiveness of providing, and training on the use of, automated external defibrillators and cardiopulmonary resuscitation; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5E0D230A9EF34051B7BA68B81F053684"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the formulation of recommendations on actions that can be taken by schools, coaches, trainers, and governmental entities to prevent deaths and catastrophic injuries related to high school and collegiate sports, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HBE50F7BFCEAC4B0298B4A7957BABF2F5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>measures to prevent life-threatening injury from occurring;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC35E1DB498124276AA1427C6C71D704E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>medical treatment protocols to treat these injuries when they occur; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5ECA9446989E4C91AE1FDB98891B69EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ways in which technology and data analytics can be used to prevent serious injury and death.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

