<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7913C71434324914ABC01E481A81EDD7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4787 IH: Volunteer First Responder Housing Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4787</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000491">Mr. Lucas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To expand eligibility for certain housing programs for qualified volunteer first responders.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEEFFFF8E05F147198159BAB2757D2EB4" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H5F4CF74ECC8F43E08A510BCC1AD94ACC"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Volunteer First Responder Housing Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBCE22AD8732A41E88D0401E9BF1D4E3C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H6FE6294466C941488DD8EFFA0D784949"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Bona fide volunteer; eligible employer; qualified services</header><text>The terms <term>bona fide volunteer</term>, <term>eligible employer</term>, and <term>qualified services</term> have the meanings given those terms in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/457">section 457(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9992ED871C764FE0AD710C6D81612B30"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 501(b) of the Housing Act of 1949 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1471">42 U.S.C. 1471(b)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4DC2CA646FB40F2AE1F056CF11401FB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualified volunteer first responder</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified volunteer first responder</term> means any individual who—</text><subparagraph id="H7DADAD9C1ADA4B37B29B33F834AFF277"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a bona fide volunteer performing qualified services for an eligible employer;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H997E7E96C9B84FBABCF0B0AC924101F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>continuously served as a volunteer for the eligible employer during the 2-year period preceding the date on which the individual submits a verification letter under section 3(b) or 4(b);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9D670D8A1CCE48E6A788255E3D7CA71F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>during each of the 2 years described in subparagraph (B)—</text><clause id="HE73598EDCBCA47F28BC414B24D18DA03"><enum>(i)</enum><text>met the minimum requirements for active membership established by the eligible employer; or</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE08AAACD25054905B1F140571AE57945"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the eligible employer did not establish minimum requirements, volunteered for not less than 200 hours; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H88BB8DE7C81046D98E4760823DD6D543"><enum>(D)</enum><text>is certified as a firefighter or other first responder in the State, political subdivision of a State, or jurisdiction of an Indian Tribe in which the individual is serving as volunteer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HFFC5A85BB86B4AFD9589E85FF4C4831A"><enum>3.</enum><header>Department of Agriculture Single Family Housing Guaranteed Loan Program</header><subsection id="H138284B80B614BE4AA8964F28C96D62B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A qualified volunteer first responder who submits to the Secretary of Agriculture (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) a verification letter in accordance with subsection (b) shall be eligible for a deduction in annual income under section 3555.152(c) of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation), in the amount of $18,000.</text></subsection><subsection id="H303F4E7644E54D6F8F806755F9EB1009"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Verification letter</header><text>To be eligible for a deduction under subsection (a), a qualified volunteer first responder shall submit to the Secretary a verification letter from the head of the eligible employer for which the qualified volunteer first responder volunteers, which shall—</text><paragraph id="H3A7739BF9F104F45BA54C3E98543ECA9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include the date on which the qualified volunteer first responder joined the eligible employer as a volunteer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0977C0625E444926A5C848194537A92E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>attest to the Secretary that the qualified volunteer first responder meets the requirements under subparagraphs (B) and (C) of section 2(3); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H603938CDCB724BE1AEF6D6FD15D4D0F7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include a copy of the certification described in section 2(3)(D).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H026759A4C4BA435EBC7861169E44205F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Good Neighbor Next Door Sales Program and similar programs</header><subsection id="HCA75D505C9514A9DAA5EDF110718BCE3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A qualified volunteer first responder who submits to the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development (referred to in this section as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) a verification letter in accordance with subsection (b) shall qualify as a firefighter or emergency medical technician for purposes of any single family property disposition program carried out by the Secretary by regulation under section 204(g) of the National Housing Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1710">12 U.S.C. 1710(g)</external-xref>) that offers discounted home prices to firefighters or emergency medical technicians.</text></subsection><subsection id="H30A81288D8194DEAAB1C682ED953B58E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Verification letter</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To qualify to purchase a home under a single family property disposition program referred to in subsection (a), a qualified first responder shall submit to the Secretary a verification letter from the head of the eligible employer for which the qualified volunteer first responder volunteers, which shall—</text><paragraph id="HE30308DBDE1449C7AE292082297A9C2C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>include the date on which the qualified volunteer first responder joined the eligible employer as a volunteer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7166EF0D1A6349C08B81CCCE386A9DE7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>attest to the Secretary that the qualified volunteer first responder meets the requirements under subparagraphs (B) and (C) of section 2(3);</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H135BCF3965FE45DFB4D2E465E7B374C6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include a copy of the certification described in section 2(3)(D); and</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H5E692C357B6A41529A7D748E6EC8A2DF"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include a certification from the qualified volunteer first responder of the responder’s good faith intention to continue serving as a volunteer for the eligible employer for not less than 1 year following the date of closing.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

