<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC77C6BD5F2AD4766AF186B3EAA6862F3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 461 IH: Protecting Individuals with Down Syndrome Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 461</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000298">Mr. Estes</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="A000055">Mr. Aderholt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000388">Mr. Kelly of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001212">Mr. Stauber</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to prohibit discrimination by abortion against an unborn child on the basis of Down syndrome.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H02CE6EE82B1544968C5FACA5742BDF17" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HD336748AFBDD40F0B068E6D2E565074D"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Individuals with Down Syndrome Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H987122B678844204A8C35B17E1D23CEA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H7C27CE0A097D403CB22A1A4373014FD9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>On June 24, 2022, the United States Supreme Court issued a decision in Dobbs v. Jackson Women’s Health Organization (No. 19–1392, 2022 WL 2276808 (2022)), which overturned its prior, egregiously wrong holding in Roe v. Wade (410 U.S. 113 (1973)).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H85D1DC36ABB542DF92D948713D1A1280"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Dobbs correctly affirmed that there is no constitutional right to abort an unborn child and that the Court’s prior decision in Roe was not based in the Constitution’s text nor was it deeply rooted in the history and tradition of the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB61095DB7A644BDAA9031D6AB9F2F9E1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Federal law protects individuals with disabilities against discrimination, including in the provision of medical care.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4443764C6BC24520AAE5ECC94BE677A0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>As Congress has previously affirmed, <quote>[d]isability is a natural part of the human experience and in no way diminishes the right of individuals to live independently, enjoy self-determination, make choices, contribute to society, pursue meaningful careers, and enjoy full inclusion and integration in the economic, political, social, and educational mainstream of American society.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37D73E71189B409BA228EAE1B4B38B20"><enum>(5)</enum><text>It is the policy of the United States to respect the lives and the dignity of individuals with disabilities, including individuals with Down syndrome.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF6822C1D4C6A4F02BE6C971C197B0D40"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Federal, State, and local government all have a role to play in preventing discrimination based on disability, including discrimination against individuals with Down syndrome.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBA0A414E12B14F269663E1EAEEDDDF82"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Consistent with the overarching Federal policy of nondiscrimination, and in light of the shameful history of targeting unborn children for abortion based on race, gender, or disabilities, Congress must combat invidious discrimination by prohibiting doctors from aborting unborn children because the unborn child has been diagnosed with Down syndrome.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB906D88914F4B0D8014E02491E4F784"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Tragically, in some countries that have failed to protect unborn children diagnosed with Down syndrome, virtually every unborn child diagnosed with Down syndrome is aborted.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD17499E869C94349B27B788B579C974C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Individuals with Down syndrome are inherently valuable and worthy of dignity and respect. They enrich and strengthen our society in countless ways, including but not limited to by building meaningful relationships, participating in and creating families, learning, and working alongside other Americans. </text></paragraph></section><section id="HCDE6E350DACA44EFB4E82D8667E78BDC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Discrimination by abortion against an unborn child on the basis of Down syndrome prohibited</header><subsection id="H26A81B0B6DB94A6397A964A5D33ACFAE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/13">Chapter 13</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2337488075E04856AF3B3D339C171EEA"><section id="HDC01B4AED9E0490B98FD3B4E30208F85"><enum>250.</enum><header>Discrimination by abortion against an unborn child on the basis of Down syndrome prohibited</header><subsection id="H16FB1C59309A4A84BE7E8294FC80B9B5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H66C079B4E16C40F3972804095E151F29"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Abortion</header><text>The term <term>abortion</term> means the act of using or prescribing any instrument, medicine, drug, or any other substance, device, or means with the intent to—</text><subparagraph id="H445AB50C993145B0B5F1BD00A85B3868"><enum>(A)</enum><text>kill the unborn child of a woman known to be pregnant; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5445262FA469425998DCD0CAB9B2FC02"><enum>(B)</enum><text>terminate the pregnancy of a woman known to be pregnant, with an intention other than—</text><clause id="HD82E826F0C42489AB6D673F7FD85441F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to produce a live birth and preserve the life and health of the child born alive;</text></clause><clause id="H09A0329EFC6048709E66ECAE53F8B875"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to save the life of the pregnant woman; or</text></clause><clause id="H9CC9B23B7F484395B639281CA55DAF0C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to remove a dead unborn child.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD35B7C7A12BA44E4B656738EEEA4F283"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Down syndrome</header><text>The term <term>Down syndrome</term> means a chromosomal disorder associated with—</text><subparagraph id="H9DF435F1C5484E2BA7D070ADDE83A774"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an extra copy of the chromosome 21, in whole or in part; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46932B59E9FB4638889A3BA025B20797"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an effective trisomy for chromosome 21.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CAA8C3CCADA4868B15EC7BF4140A3EA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Qualified plaintiff</header><text>The term <term>qualified plaintiff</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HCA982EB5330B4289BF61E98A56B63333"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a woman upon whom an abortion is performed or attempted in violation of this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0D30CF76D4BD41A28C8282C2439175EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a maternal grandparent of the unborn child if the woman upon whom an abortion is performed or attempted in violation of this section is an unemancipated minor;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E685F80C6BF4B8FB577A1E2751220E6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the father of an unborn child who is the subject of an abortion performed or attempted in violation of this section unless the pregnancy or abortion resulted from the criminal conduct of the father; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A951D1391AE46B38E4E7EC38B9960EE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Attorney General.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H879C9BCFE50F47EBAB5EC658DAB58B92"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Unborn child</header><text>The term <term>unborn child</term> means an individual of the species homo sapiens from the beginning of the biological development of that individual, including fertilization, until the point of being born alive, as defined in section 8(b) of title 1.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7F8BFD5206E14937AA1954087472AC86"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Offense</header><text>It shall be unlawful to—</text><paragraph id="H389D32ABF8EF425E9171771DA13EA64F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>perform an abortion—</text><subparagraph id="H96229B2DB9B54F4F8392A6DC66511847"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with the knowledge that a pregnant woman is seeking an abortion, in whole or in part, on the basis of—</text><clause id="H1E20DA9F20514A6C95F4E47C61C8DC78"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a test result indicating that the unborn child has Down syndrome;</text></clause><clause id="H4619B45D671B4C13A253806295D8E7FE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a prenatal diagnosis that the unborn child has Down syndrome; or</text></clause><clause id="HF382E39DDFFB4007AD6342512FAA6CA0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any other reason to believe that the unborn child has or may have Down syndrome; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6D5019389EA4B1FADF0DABD7E181950"><enum>(B)</enum><text>without first—</text><clause id="H05BDA149C8F04617A7921A490435243D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>asking the pregnant woman if she is aware of any test results, prenatal diagnosis, or any other evidence that the unborn child has or may have Down syndrome; and</text></clause><clause id="HA87DC137086B4FF7B210FDEB6902E734"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>if the woman is aware that the unborn child has or may have Down syndrome, informing the pregnant woman of the prohibitions on abortion under this section;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDDC6544D5E364CB4BC5E0557AACC50BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>use force or the threat of force to intentionally injure or intimidate any person for the purpose of coercing an abortion described in paragraph (1)(A);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF08E9351DEA4C0CA0805D94B9310182"><enum>(3)</enum><text>solicit or accept funds for the performance of an abortion described in paragraph (1)(A); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE38BCD2F3B149B4B397FA30374D228E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>knowingly transport a woman into the United States or across a State line for the purpose of obtaining an abortion described in paragraph (1)(A).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H426E0BBFB4C649E5B853A27E90DA2AC2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Criminal penalty</header><text>Any person that violates, or attempts to violate, subsection (b) shall be fined under this title, imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAB76C64950C5494CBAED10362D1CF2EA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Civil remedies</header><paragraph id="H9D29812BC1D94D0398CEABA4BAABEA0F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Civil action by woman on whom abortion is performed</header><text>A woman upon whom an abortion has been performed or attempted in violation of subsection (b)(2) may bring a civil action in an appropriate court against any person who engaged in a violation of subsection (b)(2) to obtain appropriate relief.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D6D933F026A4E29937064984C58A78B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Civil action by relatives</header><subparagraph id="HBF3FB85718314DDC82757C853E84409C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (B), the father of an unborn child who is the subject of an abortion performed or attempted in violation of subsection (b), or a maternal grandparent of the unborn child if the pregnant woman is an unemancipated minor, may bring a civil action in an appropriate court against any person who engaged in the violation to obtain appropriate relief.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3EA2A91AF6EF4AA6AECE4BAA2B54F9AC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Subparagraph (A) shall not apply if—</text><clause id="H25333BBB9DBF4FF88785E766B60C835A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the pregnancy or abortion resulted from the criminal conduct of the plaintiff described in subparagraph (A); or</text></clause><clause id="H599887B5052F477DA0F34F4B045984C4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the plaintiff described in subparagraph (A) consented to the abortion.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8142F2297FC4F33870FC7088CF6F41A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appropriate relief</header><text>Appropriate relief in a civil action under this subsection includes—</text><subparagraph id="H0079446AC15B47FBA422E6812A5F6E57"><enum>(A)</enum><text>objectively verifiable money damages for all injuries, psychological and physical, including loss of companionship and support, occasioned by the violation of this section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C98AAEC8A004534B49EADB6B6A70906"><enum>(B)</enum><text>punitive damages.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC7DCC107B09498A87E0398E3B0F492D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Injunctive relief</header><text>A qualified plaintiff may bring a civil action in an appropriate court to obtain injunctive relief to prevent an abortion provider from performing or attempting further abortions in violation of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB08D62369A3A41D99A2ED7BAE265DD9D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Attorney’s fees for plaintiff</header><text>The court shall award a reasonable attorney’s fee as part of the costs to a prevailing plaintiff in a civil action under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H176FE1AE11A1499CBD3C334DFC1BC0B5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Bar to prosecution</header><text>A woman upon whom an abortion is performed may not be prosecuted or held civilly liable for any violation of this section or for a conspiracy to violate this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAD1A581884A5438ABD7322E52D95445D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Loss of Federal funding</header><text>A violation of subsection (b) shall be deemed discrimination for the purposes of section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/794">29 U.S.C. 794</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H6C653D21F9A44CE4A36214A793B240DB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header><paragraph id="H32830ACB35264AEC8A51C8BF737DD608"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A physician, physician’s assistant, nurse, counselor, or other medical or mental health professional shall report known or suspected violations of any of this section to appropriate law enforcement authorities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H719D9BD2156D4CA492DEA53CA08D8FFB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criminal penalty</header><text>Any person who violates paragraph (1) shall be fined under this title, imprisoned not more than 1 year, or both.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H29637A2592854F838444193A85CD5F3E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Expedited consideration</header><text>It shall be the duty of the district courts of the United States, the courts of appeals of the United States, and the Supreme Court of the United States to advance on the docket and to expedite to the greatest possible extent the disposition of any matter brought under this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9F51B163DAFD4AE6AC32DC020996C61D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Protection of privacy in court proceedings</header><paragraph id="H3531EE61D4804C6E932325BF292660B9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except to the extent the Constitution of the United States or other similarly compelling reason requires, in every civil or criminal action under this section, the court shall make such orders as are necessary to protect the anonymity of any woman upon whom an abortion has been performed or attempted if she does not give her written consent to such disclosure. Such orders may be made upon motion, but shall be made sua sponte if not otherwise sought by a party.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H490A1E864BDA408E9E3349A4241EEB61"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Orders to parties, witnesses, and counsel</header><text>The court shall issue appropriate orders to the parties, witnesses, and counsel and shall direct the sealing of the record and exclusion of individuals from courtrooms or hearing rooms to the extent necessary to safeguard the identity of a woman described in paragraph (1) from public disclosure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC315A1B4112847ABA39D86AA995B858F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Pseudonym required</header><text>In the absence of written consent of the woman upon whom an abortion has been performed or attempted, any party, other than a public official, who brings an action under this section shall do so under a pseudonym.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE2EE23B50A540DE955E73CEDC1A9641"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>This subsection may not be construed to conceal the identity of the plaintiff or of witnesses from the defendant or from attorneys for the defendant.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCE0AF17163D440B5A6C6A68C2432E0E7"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><paragraph id="H272E41CFB5A34DF5B7A33CA4B185E17F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Greater protection</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to pre-empt or limit any Federal, State, or local law that provides greater protections for an unborn child than those provided in this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8A8BBCE94054A2895509E20CE269E9F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Creating or recognizing right</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed as creating or recognizing a right to abortion nor shall it make lawful an abortion that is otherwise unlawful under Federal, State, or local law.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HFAC1854CDEFD492AA720AE055D59A6F6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/13">chapter 13</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB17F962E0CB4B4BB5561AC435DB7EC2"><toc><toc-entry bold="off" level="section">250. Discrimination by abortion against an unborn child on the basis of Down syndrome prohibited.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H77795D4746364AD1BB87BEEDCA7BE156"><enum>4.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any portion of this Act, or the amendments made by this Act, or the application thereof to any person or circumstance is held invalid, such invalidity shall not affect the portions or applications of this Act which can be given effect without the invalid portion or application.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

