<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H38156F551A3D43349202FB42C1DDD5CC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5414 IH: Improving Mental Health Access from the Emergency Department Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5414</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230912">September 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Director of the Center for Mental Health Services of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration, to award grants to implement innovative approaches to securing prompt access to appropriate follow-on care for individuals who experience an acute mental health episode and present for care in an emergency department, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8B18102BA4734F64869D918B14E43DA2" style="OLC"><section id="H1F494A03999A4A92A42F05690430EEB7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Improving Mental Health Access from the Emergency Department Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7E70603ED23D444AA68AFFB4CC867E1B"><enum>2.</enum><header>Securing appropriate follow-on care for acute mental health illness after an emergency department encounter</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act is amended by inserting after section 520J of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290bb-41">42 U.S.C. 290bb–41</external-xref>) the following new section:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC23833BEE6BA42D0835D85602FD801B0" style="OLC"><section id="HD7D04AF416A44665B451ADF25240C18E"><enum>520J–1.</enum><header>Securing appropriate follow-on care for acute mental health illness after an emergency department encounter</header><subsection id="H5078A94965CD479B85F8DCB3605C2CA6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may award grants on a competitive basis to qualifying health providers to implement innovative approaches to securing prompt access to appropriate follow-on care for individuals who experience an acute mental health episode and present for care in an emergency department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4038B7A522EE41B391112C603AFFBBB7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible grant recipients</header><text>In this section, the term <term>qualifying health provider</term> means a health care facility licensed under applicable law that—</text><paragraph id="HA1B2DD856C2342B196531682C1C5AC26"><enum>(1)</enum><text>has an emergency department;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF01AF4EBCBD42D69BA0626FD8CFB337"><enum>(2)</enum><text>is staffed by medical personnel (such as emergency physicians, psychiatrists, psychiatric registered nurses, mental health technicians, clinical social workers, psychologists, and therapists) capable of providing treatment focused on stabilizing acute mental health conditions and assisting patients to access resources to continue treatment in the least restrictive appropriate setting; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H835C74D7F0B6416FB447105D77226172"><enum>(3)</enum><text>has arrangements in place with other providers of care that can provide a full range of medically appropriate, evidence-based services for the treatment of acute mental health episodes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1DA7E51EA87F4518BE1805AD47E8AF9A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>A qualifying health provider receiving funds under this section shall use such funds to create, support, or expand programs or projects intended to assist individuals who are treated at the provider’s emergency department for acute mental health episodes and to expeditiously transition such individuals to an appropriate facility or setting for follow-on care. Such use of funds may support the following:</text><paragraph id="HDD929BA467FE46D39E1D5D05B014CF3E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Expediting placement in appropriate facilities through activities such as expanded coordination with regional service providers, assessment, peer navigators, bed availability tracking and management, transfer protocol development, networking infrastructure development, and transportation services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA16F009BF18D4BF98DE7E824538B78A9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Increasing the supply of inpatient psychiatric beds and alternative care settings such as regional emergency psychiatric facilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2A123671B8AC45C2BFA61E860C5AE9F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Use of alternative approaches to providing psychiatric care in the emergency department setting, including through tele-psychiatric support and other remote psychiatric consultation, implementation of peak period crisis clinics, or creation of psychiatric emergency service units.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4CE0D4A8B094B1C8DE55268E6794096"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Use of approaches that include proactive followup such as telephone check-ins, telemedicine, or other technology-based outreach to individuals during the period of transition.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5648899A9383471DA965DD59BF776F76"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Such other activities as are determined by the Secretary to be appropriate, consistent with subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF705D9772A384C58B2962F6B2A35D064"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Application</header><text>A qualifying health provider desiring a grant under this section shall prepare and submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may require. At a minimum, the application shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HE626351292CE4389BB8053C9865DCA4E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of identified need for acute mental health services in the provider’s service area.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H833760676F584CA193ED3B8BB6E96913"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of the existing efforts of the provider to meet the need for acute mental health services in the service area, and identified gaps in the provision of such services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H651EDBF3B17B4D89A324028796E97076"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A description of the proposed use of funds to meet the need and gaps identified pursuant to paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H95B810BD678944EF92D1A6F6C367FD26"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A description of how the provider will coordinate efforts with Federal, State, local, and private entities within the service area.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6E7CDB8AFCF4908B419633CE84B5735"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of program objectives, how the objectives are proposed to be met, and how the provider will evaluate outcomes relative to objectives.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8E955B5C4FB74C2AAD444DBA8414D5F5"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there is authorized to be appropriated $15,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

