<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H25A0F64BA5144D5496541E9774031A39" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3465 IH: To enhance Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation transparency.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3465</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To enhance Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation transparency.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H79059500C3FE43F084D3EDCE9273A34F" style="OLC"><section id="HDA79924B97094043BA796B41DE97F49B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation transparency</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 13(c) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1823">12 U.S.C. 1823</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HFCE5DA622D0F49619B85375E90D1A366"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (1)(C), by inserting after <quote>taken</quote> the following: <quote>after notification to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and</quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1E81EF245C342329255E714A52E525F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text><subparagraph id="H2BC07BE9634A41198473FFC89EB65E7A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)(i)(I), by striking <quote>a present-value</quote> and inserting <quote>an expected present-value</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BD57A408FEC4E729B14EB64D94EFCB0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (G)—</text><clause id="HA0B4712920034049AAB8B3EA6E6C3717"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in clause (i)—</text><subclause id="H39EB82E1AF014E82929B3B4B72865DA6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>after notification to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate and</quote> before <quote>upon the</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H6CF4C56A8EFE41FE828F1BCC84FD8D83"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by striking <quote>would</quote> and inserting <quote>that can be shown to</quote>;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H1CAEAEF56693472A821ACC41D6B9E645"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in clause (iii)(I), by inserting before the semicolon the following: <quote>, including documentation of factors, empirical analyses, and data that gave rise to the determination</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H34FFEB4DD3014F74A1C21E24F2B1E4E6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H11F209102C3A414E87960D360E76FEAA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="HC90CC6F69B274157A6BAFBF0B0804E7E"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Additional reports to Congress on emergency determinations</header><subclause id="H275DEEEE994643469C3BD0021F512650"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each determination under clause (i), the Board of Directors, the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System, and the Secretary of the Treasury shall each provide to the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate—</text><item id="H00DE84A0B8DB418EA00EC38283904789"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 3 days after such determination, all documentation related to such determination, including staff analyses and memoranda; and</text></item><item id="H448F2670C7E742E3B112F1F109CF0192"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 30 days after such determination, any analyses undertaken to justify such determination, including data, metrics used, and quantitative analyses undertaken.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HDC1DE58B1C6C432E8802E1E4D7B577EA"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Information requested by committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall provide the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate with such additional information related to a determination under clause (i) as the committees may request. The Secretary of the Treasury may submit, with such information, a written request and justification for the committees to treat the information confidentially.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H33D62E305FF14D92BF8D1E207E88D529"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in paragraph (8)(B), after <quote>in writing</quote> by inserting <quote>, shall include details of factors that led to the determination and analyses of those factors and their implications</quote>.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

