<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HAA1FCD74979145FE986347B67F4B7769" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5149 IH: To direct the Secretary of Defense to carry out a pilot program to provide stipends to certain members separating from the Armed Forces.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5149</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230804">August 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to carry out a pilot program to provide stipends to certain members separating from the Armed Forces.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8D0931DFDD3E49C18FB0123ED24482BA" style="OLC"><section id="H8D33AFA720AF4038A4AE9DCDEBF4BD93" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Pilot program to provide a monthly stipend to certain recently separated members</header><subsection id="HFD83BAE883454D2282E86ECEC112E35D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Secretary of Veterans Affairs, shall carry out a pilot program to provide a stipend to a covered individual.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2D30B8E8DD4748CAABDE3B2CF34CB4BB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amount</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A stipend paid under this section to a covered individual shall be in an amount that the Secretary determines will pay for one month of food and housing for the household of such covered individual in the location where such household resides.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF37F130F233D42D88407A6957187A0E2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Payments</header><text>A covered individual shall receive a stipend under this section once a month for the first four months following the separation of the covered individual from the Armed Forces.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD55896A7CAAC4E22A19F4C8FE9E82251" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives regarding the pilot program. Such report shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H7327BDAEE4944C9EAD5E0AD149EE84CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The number of covered individuals paid a stipend under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DD71D4D820A408C95073BB1EA8D3312"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The average amount of such a stipend.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H904381FB04C841E9900F1883CE1DD3D8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The effectiveness of the program in mitigating financial hardships of covered individuals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E4A2ECD616442F49174A21D4D1E7CD8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A plan to make the pilot program permanent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F3925E0341F4BF680A097C531CD2689"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The recommendation of the Secretary whether to make the pilot program permanent.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H402A9BD9C0CE4200A68A1A8B5F297BF6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The pilot program shall terminate after operating for four months.</text></subsection><subsection id="H988D80EF339842119AF56B5AB1285ADE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H10A0115BCFEF415C879AB54C04EBE758"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered individual</quote> means an individual—</text><subparagraph id="H1AE3652258ED4AC4B8FE75AFCE102679"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who separates from the Armed Forces under honorable conditions after at least four years of service on active duty; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H189CDB46BDB5435CAE21933644C9C02D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">whom the Secretary of Defense determines will experience financial hardship during the first 120 days following such separation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8B68E165B4F14E2D9E5E77445D7AABCB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>dependent</quote> means a dependent registered under the Defense Enrollment Eligibility Reporting System.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C62D45021A9441E8AD3D931CAD09042"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The term <quote>household</quote> means a covered individual and all dependents of such covered individual who share a residence.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

