<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC647604B032644CD8BCF087D543F17A8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5239 IH: The Gulf of Mexico Commerce Protection Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5239</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000806">Mr. Webster of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the issuance of an interim or final rule that establishes a vessel slowdown zone in the Gulf of Mexico until the Secretary of Commerce completes a study demonstrating that proposed mitigation efforts would have no negative impact on supply chains, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1C13CE9DF0664AC59DCD61E8A0632927" style="OLC"><section id="H6D068EC304524F89B026B0DBF0370BBA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>The Gulf of Mexico Commerce Protection Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE40C7242C7ED49BC87F9A5DA4795F6B2" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on issuance of rule relating to vessel slowdown zone in Gulf of Mexico</header><subsection id="H03E002AAB26D43E3BBF7D00DA379B8AF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration shall not issue an interim or final rule that establishes a vessel slowdown zone in the Gulf of Mexico until the Secretary of Commerce—</text><paragraph id="H0C0D0412D4904F4FAE29FB9FFE1BB299"><enum>(1)</enum><text>completes a study demonstrating that mitigation protocols developed under subsection (b) would have no net negative impact on supply chains or maritime commerce; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6777DFFEE9A24A9BA0496AF1FC4EE92E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 60 days after completing such study, submits to the Committees on Energy and Commerce and Natural Resources of the House of Representatives and the Committees on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and Natural Resources of the Senate a report containing the findings of such study.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H42E42308170B4FAB929729B764A12159"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mitigation protocols required</header><paragraph id="H7E8F8296826C426A9209990129587B53"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Under Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, in consultation with the Secretary of the department in which the Coast Guard is operating, the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary of Transportation, and the Secretary of the Interior, and with input from affected stakeholders, shall develop mitigation protocols that make use of any monitoring system designed under section 11303 of the Don Young Coast Guard Authorization Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1391">16 U.S.C. 1391</external-xref>) to direct sector-specific mitigation measures that reduce risk of serious injury and mortality to Rice’s whales in the Gulf of Mexico.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98F4529D9A40461EB72034769B3573FE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The mitigation protocols developed under paragraph (1) may not include any prohibitions on transit at night or implementation of a static vessel slowdown zone.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

