<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC7DBEB5E6FFF4C88AE6013BFF3BBF77D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>111 HR 6275 IH: Protecting Consumer Access to Generic Drugs Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6275</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231107">November 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit brand name drug manufacturers from compensating generic drug manufacturers to delay the entry of a generic drug into the market, and to prohibit biological product manufacturers from compensating biosimilar and interchangeable product manufacturers to delay entry of biosimilar and interchangeable products, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6874D70B8C4C42F7BC8819BD568173EA" style="OLC"><section id="H40466C315973402599A15CB39964ABA2" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Consumer Access to Generic Drugs Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD1DAB32EE54A41BFA06216729912F45A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Unlawful agreements</header><subsection id="HE60DD7913B4C41B3A34A0300AE9CFC75"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Agreements prohibited</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subsections (b) and (c), it shall be unlawful for an NDA or BLA holder and a subsequent filer (or for two subsequent filers) to enter into, or carry out, an agreement resolving or settling a covered patent infringement claim on a final or interim basis if under such agreement—</text><paragraph id="H978915715886405E8569F3FB5659D4FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a subsequent filer directly or indirectly receives from such holder (or in the case of such an agreement between two subsequent filers, the other subsequent filer) anything of value, including a license; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB14546AEE0A244FABA5EC09B46DD13B8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the subsequent filer agrees to limit or forego research on, or development, manufacturing, marketing, or sales, for any period of time, of the covered product that is the subject of the application described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (g)(8).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H95CD73BA419B413BA69819771B2412A6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exclusion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall not be unlawful under subsection (a) if a party to an agreement described in such subsection demonstrates by clear and convincing evidence that the value described in subsection (a)(1) is compensation solely for other goods or services that the subsequent filer has promised to provide.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5A0FDBF67AF5419A99BBD95F7F3CCA4F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall prohibit an agreement resolving or settling a covered patent infringement claim in which the consideration granted by the NDA or BLA holder to the subsequent filer (or from one subsequent filer to another) as part of the resolution or settlement includes only one or more of the following:</text><paragraph id="H509FBB09F45E4358B51E429E935AB8E9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The right to market the covered product that is the subject of the application described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (g)(8) in the United States before the expiration of—</text><subparagraph id="H99E8CA4A18EC4406BB2AF9FD975107D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any patent that is the basis of the covered patent infringement claim; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4340A9E58DDF4FB5B2BA24074DB8FF4E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any patent right or other statutory exclusivity that would prevent the marketing of such covered product.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFDAD58400AB94B9291F47D32DD60F5D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A payment for reasonable litigation expenses not to exceed $7,500,000 in the aggregate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78C5B30092C14BF9B91BBC1C2FFE4D04"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A covenant not to sue on any claim that such covered product infringes a patent.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCBB4F1161839457F9537AA35FF29CF20"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Enforcement by Federal Trade Commission</header><paragraph id="H9739766241234C77B1F3AC8541E05DFD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>General application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements of this section apply, according to their terms, to an NDA or BLA holder or subsequent filer that is—</text><subparagraph id="H5E0612E9370D4ABFA7816EF0783018D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a person, partnership, or corporation over which the Commission has authority pursuant to section 5(a)(2) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45(a)(2)</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9BE4CA7262943498BE6C903751BCDBD"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a person, partnership, or corporation over which the Commission would have authority pursuant to such section but for the fact that such person, partnership, or corporation is not organized to carry on business for its own profit or that of its members.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H10BCED737D284B35A63D9C7D512E811C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices enforcement authority</header><subparagraph id="H829C52D63C3746CC95887019B2EC84EC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A violation of this section shall be treated as an unfair or deceptive act or practice in violation of section 5(a)(1) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45(a)(1)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H860822DC7A81406F812E7EE087D9ABC5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Powers of Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subparagraph (C) and paragraphs (1)(B) and (3)—</text><clause id="H0A623A1B0C884E66852700781FE9B28A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Commission shall enforce this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section; and</text></clause><clause id="HACDC2B36193945ECAF20CB1E2FBC1060"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any NDA or BLA holder or subsequent filer that violates this section shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C5EEFC0FAC845A495339618E3A88214"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Judicial review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a cease and desist order issued by the Commission under section 5 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45</external-xref>) for violation of this section, a party to such order may obtain judicial review of such order as provided in such section 5, except that—</text><clause id="H5E700ACDF726480C8F6F36546A6489BE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such review may only be obtained in—</text><subclause id="H209E5C840F3C429FBBAD64E6C6EE421A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit;</text></subclause><subclause id="H7C6B53E075DB42BE8BCC0D17FA4E8F31"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States Court of Appeals for the circuit in which the ultimate parent entity, as defined in section 801.1(a)(3) of title 16, Code of Federal Regulations, or any successor thereto, of the NDA or BLA holder (if any such holder is a party to such order) is incorporated as of the date that the application described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (g)(8) or an approved application that is deemed to be a license for a biological product under section 351(k) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(k)</external-xref>) pursuant to section 7002(e)(4) of the Biologics Price Competition and Innovation Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/148">Public Law 111–148</external-xref>; 124 Stat. 817) is submitted to the Commissioner of Food and Drugs; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H1C77BC9E1D1C4079BCDAE5C9CBD022E6"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States Court of Appeals for the circuit in which the ultimate parent entity, as so defined, of any subsequent filer that is a party to such order is incorporated as of the date that the application described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (g)(8) is submitted to the Commissioner of Food and Drugs; and</text></subclause></clause><clause commented="no" id="HD740A80D07904DE69D260A169AF44E91"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the petition for review shall be filed in the court not later than 30 days after such order is served on the party seeking review.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9F302DE3A8A44699ED982CECCD27D21"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional enforcement authority</header><subparagraph id="H9DF063CE35F34CEDB74EF0002E3B3CD8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Civil penalty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may commence a civil action to recover a civil penalty in a district court of the United States against any NDA or BLA holder or subsequent filer that violates this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H90D90893139448C2A38289AD7C0AF8C5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Special rule for recovery of penalty if cease and desist order issued</header><clause id="HC9AAAFCA898A45559C231819BE2A3076"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Commission has issued a cease and desist order in a proceeding under section 5 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45</external-xref>) for violation of this section—</text><subclause id="H89217B09E5E34DA7821685AA74181789"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Commission may commence a civil action under subparagraph (A) to recover a civil penalty against any party to such order at any time before the expiration of the 1-year period beginning on the date on which such order becomes final under section 5(g) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45(g)</external-xref>); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H957F588B9E4A402F9B407DB527012C46"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in such civil action, the findings of the Commission as to the material facts in such proceeding shall be conclusive, unless—</text><item commented="no" id="H5DAEBC671BC3420E9EECCFEDB3A8C0B1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the terms of such order expressly provide that the Commission’s findings shall not be conclusive; or</text></item><item commented="no" id="H3FF388799594451CAA2A4945FE8F82DD"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>such order became final by reason of section 5(g)(1) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45(g)(1)</external-xref>), in which case such findings shall be conclusive if supported by evidence.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H1B04A0FE47CC41A6B02D6B8B8A1655CA"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Relationship to penalty for violation of an order</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The penalty provided in clause (i) for violation of this section is separate from and in addition to any penalty that may be incurred for violation of an order of the Commission under section 5(l) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45(l)</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0098CA0004814D1A8AA4FE1BAB8BB983"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Amount of penalty</header><clause commented="no" id="H40DA9211765246C9B6426C2BFDAC094F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amount of a civil penalty imposed in a civil action under subparagraph (A) on a party to an agreement described in subsection (a) shall be sufficient to deter violations of this section, but in no event greater than—</text><subclause id="H3F47FB748047446FAC2CABCE58F422C8"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such party is the NDA or BLA holder (or, in the case of an agreement between two subsequent filers, the subsequent filer who gave the value described in subsection (a)(1)), the greater of—</text><item id="H85A7A54D7ACB4630889B6E528A236921"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">3 times the value received by such NDA or BLA holder (or by such subsequent filer) that is reasonably attributable to the violation of this section; or</text></item><item id="H2F81D486A43643FBB89B8F517BD76F43"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">3 times the value given to the subsequent filer (or to the other subsequent filer) reasonably attributable to the violation of this section; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="HB3DCF40D22714476B0489DEBE2DEE6BC"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if such party is the subsequent filer (or, in the case of an agreement between two subsequent filers, the subsequent filer who received the value described in subsection (a)(1)), 3 times the value received by such subsequent filer that is reasonably attributable to the violation of this section.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H174D12D1A4FA4CB7A7B88B5BE0D611DB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Factors for consideration</header><text>In determining such amount, the court shall take into account—</text><subclause id="H1F68572F6436416D840D20C307CE0C97"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the nature, circumstances, extent, and gravity of the violation;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD436AEBD1E584BC0BA37B748E0BCD4D3"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to the violator, the degree of culpability, any history of violations, the ability to pay, any effect on the ability to continue doing business, profits earned by the NDA or BLA holder (or, in the case of an agreement between two subsequent filers, the subsequent filer who gave the value described in subsection (a)(1)), compensation received by the subsequent filer (or, in the case of an agreement between two subsequent filers, the subsequent filer who received the value described in subsection (a)(1)), and the amount of commerce affected; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE3BE091CC6BB4AEC9C672D726767EFB7"><enum>(III)</enum><text>other matters that justice requires.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE84E28E05C3A4072AE25F4275F19A945"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Injunctions and other equitable relief</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a civil action under subparagraph (A), the United States district courts are empowered to grant mandatory injunctions and such other and further equitable relief as they deem appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H55C66C8CB34E4FDF9559A4FCA4D6E322"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Remedies in addition</header><text>Remedies provided in this subsection are in addition to, and not in lieu of, any other remedy provided by Federal law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B5D1C7E10DD4D1EBBA9E309912CB6EC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Preservation of authority of Commission</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to affect any authority of the Commission under any other provision of law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE0AA3F2132B24621B18B508120098EA9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Federal Trade Commission rulemaking</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may, in its discretion, by rule promulgated under section 553 of title 5, United States Code, exempt from this section certain agreements described in subsection (a) if the Commission finds such agreements to be in furtherance of market competition and for the benefit of consumers. </text></subsection><subsection display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEB3E4CF65D154C3C9F5AA5EB06E2F4A1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Antitrust laws</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall modify, impair, limit, or supersede the applicability of the antitrust laws as defined in subsection (a) of the first section of the Clayton Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/12">15 U.S.C. 12(a)</external-xref>), and of section 5 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45</external-xref>) to the extent that such section 5 applies to unfair methods of competition. Nothing in this section shall modify, impair, limit, or supersede the right of a subsequent filer to assert claims or counterclaims against any person, under the antitrust laws or other laws relating to unfair competition.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC62024DD901D4EEDB1402EA3EC5B0CB0"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H2839BBE61A6244F2BE13F8692489E653"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agreement resolving or settling a covered patent infringement claim</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agreement resolving or settling a covered patent infringement claim</term> means any agreement that—</text><subparagraph id="HAE3E120702484755A18E4D08E80041AF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>resolves or settles a covered patent infringement claim; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE544F7DC1CB48D2BFFE1C460CD600A7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is contingent upon, provides for a contingent condition for, or is otherwise related to the resolution or settlement of a covered patent infringement claim.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF42121FB1C444339998FCDABFF83DFE8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Commission</header><text>The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Trade Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H5EA511B9FA3E41D7A4FE4A67B5199070"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered patent infringement claim</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered patent infringement claim</term> means an allegation made by the NDA or BLA holder to a subsequent filer (or, in the case of an agreement between two subsequent filers, by one subsequent filer to another), whether or not included in a complaint filed with a court of law, that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1A039BCF804B42F09D4CC1CFBEFA3BBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the submission of the application described in subparagraph (A) or (B) of paragraph (8), or the manufacture, use, offering for sale, sale, or importation into the United States of a covered product that is the subject of such an application—</text><clause id="H49DC25A95E9F48ECA0ABA99FA64E99D3"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an agreement between an NDA or BLA holder and a subsequent filer, infringes any patent owned by, or exclusively licensed to, the NDA or BLA holder of the covered product; or</text></clause><clause id="HD249EDBB1623455398B55AF4D83F9189"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of an agreement between two subsequent filers, infringes any patent owned by the subsequent filer; or </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H5A793823F9C848C785D0B91C6A1D51A8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of an agreement between an NDA or BLA holder and a subsequent filer, the covered product to be manufactured under such application uses a covered product as claimed in a published patent application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HCBECAE87D6AE4BD8A42BB569EC0CF3EB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered product</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered product</term> means a drug (as defined in section 201(g) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321(g)</external-xref>)), including a biological product (as defined in section 351(i) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(i)</external-xref>)).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H652F8BB5A2714EAC824C857415819675"><enum>(5)</enum><header>NDA or BLA holder</header><text>The term <term>NDA or BLA holder</term> means—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC32ADD59DE8E4851AC5414A7DFA8C9E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the holder of—</text><clause id="H3315C9F911C84563BB34208AB73BB84F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an approved new drug application filed under section 505(b)(1) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(b)(1)</external-xref>) for a covered product; or</text></clause><clause id="HBD0330ECA4584E30B897136A03DCB2D0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a biologics license application filed under section 351(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(a)</external-xref>) for a covered product;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HCCFB00997FE14BAFA9682ED0450799E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a person owning or controlling enforcement of the patent on—</text><clause id="H24E50C1C340B46EE9E4870612A340AD0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the list published under section 505(j)(7) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(j)(7)</external-xref>) in connection with the application described in subparagraph (A)(i); or</text></clause><clause id="HB233C00009C147BBB1E73A5A2824BD0F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any list published under section 351 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262</external-xref>) comprised of patents associated with biologics license applications filed under section 351(a) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(a)</external-xref>); or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HACBBC4C4C88B4A8DA6E531E51C652DBC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the predecessors, subsidiaries, divisions, groups, and affiliates controlled by, controlling, or under common control with any entity described in subparagraph (A) or (B) (such control to be presumed by direct or indirect share ownership of 50 percent or greater), as well as the licensees, licensors, successors, and assigns of each of the entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC84FA368090E49D98D43DB844CDB8C17"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Patent</header><text>The term <term>patent</term> means a patent issued by the United States Patent and Trademark Office.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3DAEC26B385A4C44BF7453C8543EBABD"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Statutory exclusivity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>statutory exclusivity</term> means those prohibitions on the submission or approval of drug applications under clauses (ii) through (iv) of section 505(c)(3)(E) (5- and 3-year exclusivity), clauses (ii) through (iv) of section 505(j)(5)(F) (5-year and 3-year exclusivity), section 505(j)(5)(B)(iv) (180-day exclusivity), section 527 (orphan drug exclusivity), section 505A (pediatric exclusivity), or section 505E (qualified infectious disease product exclusivity) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(c)(3)(E)</external-xref>, 355(j)(5)(B)(iv), 355(j)(5)(F), 360cc, 355a, 355f), or prohibitions on the submission or licensing of biologics license applications under section 351(k)(6) (interchangeable biological product exclusivity) or section 351(k)(7) (biological product reference product exclusivity) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(k)(6)</external-xref>, (7)).</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H88BF0D4564AA4CEEBA4B8142274784E5"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Subsequent filer</header><text>The term <term>subsequent filer</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H82FA946C135045559412734B019C1F63"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a drug, a party that owns or controls an abbreviated new drug application submitted pursuant to section 505(j) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(j)</external-xref>) or a new drug application submitted pursuant to section 505(b)(2) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(b)(2)</external-xref>) and filed under section 505(b)(1) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(b)(1)</external-xref>) or has the exclusive rights to distribute the covered product that is the subject of such application; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42F2841440D64338A1D42B880C1CFA2F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a biological product, a party that owns or controls an application filed with the Food and Drug Administration under section 351(k) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/262">42 U.S.C. 262(k)</external-xref>) or has the exclusive rights to distribute the biological product that is the subject of such application.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF0310A1FCE7E44078454ECD13032B27F"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section applies with respect to agreements described in subsection (a) entered into on or after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9A99350747024598942B1833573ECE00"><enum>3.</enum><header>Notice and certification of agreements</header><subsection id="H40EE56318DC94C17BCB6FCA15B605992"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notice of all agreements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1111(7) of the Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref> note) is amended by inserting <quote>or the owner of a patent for which a claim of infringement could reasonably be asserted against any person for making, using, offering to sell, selling, or importing into the United States a biological product that is the subject of a biosimilar biological product application</quote> before the period at the end.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAABBE10710BE464D8BAB419398BC7AE5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification of agreements</header><text>Section 1112 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref> note) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBE7AC6CF9D9F4146ADFBAB67707E6C09" style="OLC"><subsection id="H2679DBCE4CC6447D9033172088865E4E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>The Chief Executive Officer or the company official responsible for negotiating any agreement under subsection (a) or (b) that is required to be filed under subsection (c) shall, within 30 days of such filing, execute and file with the Assistant Attorney General and the Commission a certification as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H9B790AFDF966485088464BFE3F7F27A1" style="OLC"><text>I declare that the following is true, correct, and complete to the best of my knowledge: The materials filed with the Federal Trade Commission and the Department of Justice under section 1112 of the Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act of 2003, with respect to the agreement referenced in this certification—</text><paragraph id="H9A5ACF08668A451E8D48555950D4B075"><enum>(1)</enum><text>represent the complete, final, and exclusive agreement between the parties;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA9401C8C47B2482C8648287222B46A23"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include any ancillary agreements that are contingent upon, provide a contingent condition for, were entered into within 30 days of, or are otherwise related to, the referenced agreement; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68A200B814114AADB3507EA908EAC5CE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>include written descriptions of any oral agreements, representations, commitments, or promises between the parties that are responsive to subsection (a) or (b) of such section 1112 and have not been reduced to writing.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H6B45C4D269C34EE6AB5F76E98AC91C28"><enum>4.</enum><header>Forfeiture of 180-day exclusivity period</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 505(j)(5)(D)(i)(V) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355(j)(5)(D)(i)(V)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>section 2 of the <short-title>Protecting Consumer Access to Generic Drugs Act of 2023</short-title> or</quote> after <quote>that the agreement has violated</quote>.</text></section><section id="HDC02B3A7360E4B0397E53F56F29DED08"><enum>5.</enum><header>Commission litigation authority</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 16(a)(2) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/56">15 U.S.C. 56(a)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H2924FFA97A8F42A4907A4A4D6D89B5B6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>or</quote> after the semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2C576DDC55541DEAF0E6D42C6ADF20E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E), by inserting <quote>or</quote> after the semicolon; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4BC3C6BCAEAB464D85416A27CCFA23F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (E) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBDC988D0C8514DABB82AD283931D6F3A" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H7690E67C9D7A41238B061C7E776D7C61"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">under section 2(d)(3)(A) of the <short-title>Protecting Consumer Access to Generic Drugs Act of 2023</short-title>;</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H19FD5D0E421B4E639EA0210A8C5F5E10"><enum>6.</enum><header>Statute of limitations</header><subsection id="HD12CE1CD8CF7494182BBC5DEB2E0FD37"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in subsection (b), the Commission shall commence any administrative proceeding or civil action to enforce section 2 of this Act not later than 6 years after the date on which the parties to the agreement file the Notice of Agreement as provided by section 1112(c)(2) and (d) of the Medicare Prescription Drug, Improvement, and Modernization Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/355">21 U.S.C. 355</external-xref> note).</text></subsection><subsection id="H3CA2D77DDBE647C5B02E37EC6AF2413C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Civil action after issuance of cease and desist order</header><text>If the Commission has issued a cease and desist order under section 5 of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45">15 U.S.C. 45</external-xref>) for violation of section 2 of this Act and the proceeding for the issuance of such order was commenced within the period required by subsection (a) of this section, such subsection does not prohibit the commencement, after such period, of a civil action under section 2(d)(3)(A) against a party to such order or a civil action under subsection (l) of such section 5 for violation of such order.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

