<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFC8A05D994994F698890FE9ACC0EFA7D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3241 IH: Amateur Radio Communications Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3241</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Federal Communications Commission to revise section 97.307(f) of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations, to allow greater flexibility in the amateur radio service, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2507634A251541E68AD2AD6193F5CC32" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H00BD98F53C1A4D20B164CDC7F6D640AF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Amateur Radio Communications Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HFCC455E6588045969ED1546ECC7E807E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H390BEF5D2C1E4870A6C2B98217DC42FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">More than 778,000 amateur operators in the United States are licensed by the Federal Communications Commission in the amateur radio services, and, by treaty, additional amateur operators licensed by other sovereign entities and jurisdictions are authorized to operate within the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2041628D7B5D435D80372106E40AA9DD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amateur radio, in addition to providing life-saving emergency communications at no cost to taxpayers, provides a fertile ground for technical self-training in modern telecommunications, electronics technology, and emergency communications techniques and protocols.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF97C36866FC64FFC9225FA9270631504"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2016, the Commission issued a Notice of Proposed Rulemaking agreeing with the petition of the American Radio Relay League to remove an outmoded limit on digital data rate transmissions (contained in part 97.307(f) of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations) that constrains the use of the amateur spectrum, particularly during emergencies and declared disasters.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF04FB1C6302C49DAA5F50A362D88F993"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Adopted in 1980, the present data rate limit is a relic of an era long since relegated to obsolescence by the remarkable advancements in digital data communications.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H729C0070B4624ACD8FD277C270E9F2D4"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The present data rate limit has no place in the modern digital communications world. Slower speeds needlessly occupy busy amateur frequencies for longer than necessary to transmit messages, leading to unnecessary crowding without benefit to anyone, and a delay in the transmission of mission critical information during emergencies and declared disasters.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H039E7686B6474622922A5DFDB9A78788"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">United States amateurs developed the first amateur digital protocols, but now are consigned to watching as amateurs in other countries take the lead in squeezing more data within each bandwidth. Amateurs in other countries universally are permitted to use modern digital data speeds denied amateurs in the United States. United States amateurs can hear and decode higher speed signals every day, but are not permitted to respond with the same protocol.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE556080B6BEB47D891C23EB9DC182A04"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This situation is not because of any affirmative decision, but simply because there has been an 8-year unexplained lack of action to update the rules.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5737FA6EB4D4D5195C6DB2EC1BC506B"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is embarrassing that in recent years, including this year, radio amateurs have had to apply to the Commission for temporary waivers, which are always granted, of the limit on data communications to efficiently manage emergency, health, and welfare messages from hurricane-prone Caribbean islands, and even from within the United States. Amateurs in the Caribbean, as in other areas of the world, generally are using equipment and software developed by the amateur community and promoted by the International Telecommunication Union specifically to ensure communications capabilities during times of severe weather.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE00E8CFA8D2B436BA6134C20A513278F"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Amateur radio has led many young people into scientific and engineering professions, including many related to the digital services and technologies that are at the heart of the wireless communications marketplace of today. The incentive to work on improving data communications technologies is the ability to experiment on the airwaves and to employ improved capabilities both casually and in times of need.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1C6F51DBAD384330903971B9F50044D7"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This capability should be restored to radio amateurs in the United States.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H42C68E2886384F80BB40D19C746D8DDE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Repeal of symbol (baud) rate limits and adoption of 2.8 kHz bandwidth limit</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Communications Commission shall revise section 97.307(f) of title 47, Code of Federal Regulations, to—</text> <paragraph id="H92E294D7398440C2B0982CC555520DA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>repeal the symbol (baud) rate limits described in paragraphs (3) and (4) of such section; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H96017E6A4BBE495888947DEF17E4E932"><enum>(2)</enum><text>replace such limits with a 2.8 kilohertz bandwidth limit for radioteletype and data emissions in the relevant frequency bands.</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

