<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H32BD92E9852E4DBE8EE8BFDD0D308188" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1583 IH: Alice Paul Voter Protection Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1583</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230314">March 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to prohibit interfering with voter registration, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD363F72D18314DB4B3C8776780E95F8A" style="OLC"><section id="HD20F24B3813F486C91C2F18AD7F46119" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Alice Paul Voter Protection Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6AD58DB46A3B4463BC8EFC42C7AE2E08" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibiting hindering, interfering with, or preventing voter registration</header><subsection id="HB0DE842E8A6845AA8992A64C020A7AA9"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/29">Chapter 29</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H57FB2E8871A44FA6A314C406E700E435" style="USC"><section id="H37FB0187E61B4C99B105DEC13F80D863"><enum>612.</enum><header>Hindering, interfering with, or preventing registering to vote</header><subsection id="H149C7A9235784BFCABA0891A7B32DF46"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It shall be unlawful for any person, whether acting under color of law or otherwise, to corruptly hinder, interfere with, or prevent another person from registering to vote or to corruptly hinder, interfere with, or prevent another person from aiding another person in registering to vote.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1366A10FFA5B469EB5637D57F747F57E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Attempt</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who attempts to commit any offense described in subsection (a) shall be subject to the same penalties as those prescribed for the offense that the person attempted to commit.</text></subsection><subsection id="H00A0799E7DBD40CA95F6454D8BCB6E7D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>Any person who violates subsection (a) shall be fined under this title, imprisoned not more than 5 years, or both.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HC5B1ACB41BDE4FB49E593210BFAC71BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/29">chapter 29</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H735CA1EADA6F4FE0A210ACBECE50F94E" style="USC"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">612. Hindering, interfering with, or preventing registering to vote.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H88ED50F39F124EABB50F2A77AE14EECE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective Date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply with respect to elections held on or after the date of the enactment of this Act, except that no person may be found to have violated section 612 of title 18, United States Code (as added by subsection (a)), on the basis of any act occurring prior to the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H53C78DED768A46E6A4EEEA768CF89CFD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Establishment of best practices</header><subsection id="HE10E9CA319F14BC7855ECFAD10E4EB00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Best practices</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Election Assistance Commission shall develop and publish recommendations for best practices for States to use to deter and prevent violations of section 612 of title 18, United States Code (as added by section 2), and section 12 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20511">52 U.S.C. 20511</external-xref>) (relating to the unlawful interference with registering to vote, or voting, or attempting to register to vote or vote), including practices to provide for the posting of relevant information at polling places and voter registration agencies under such Act, the training of poll workers and election officials, and relevant educational materials. For purposes of this subsection, the term <term>State</term> includes the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, Guam, American Samoa, the United States Virgin Islands, and the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDCF5D385BF5E4643AA8CAA7D81A99014"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusion in voter information requirements</header><text>Section 302(b)(2) of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21082">52 U.S.C. 21082(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H7861C26F1243498F84DB95C952B399F5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (E);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8437BA66CB4844F4815C5E40C04B5844"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (F) and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1CBBF38F0F84229B105A6AEB846853D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H999CF291C44E42E1B9C9EEB081A8CFCD" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H98DF3D7C1770443C9486E040FFD046F3"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">information relating to the prohibitions of section 612 of title 18, United States Code, and section 12 of the National Voter Registration Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20511">52 U.S.C. 20511</external-xref>) (relating to the unlawful interference with registering to vote, or voting, or attempting to register to vote or vote), including information on how individuals may report allegations of violations of such prohibitions.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

