<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Enrolled-Bill" dms-id="H650C0D058BD64D67B18D4332777C956D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title> HR 346 ENR: NOTAM Improvement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date></dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="no">I</distribution-code> 
<congress>One Hundred Eighteenth Congress of the United States of America</congress> <session>At the First Session</session><enrolled-dateline>Begun and held at the City of Washington on Tuesday, the third day of January, two thousand and twenty-three</enrolled-dateline> 
<legis-num>H. R. 346</legis-num> 
<current-chamber display="no"></current-chamber> 
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To establish a task force on improvements for notices to air missions, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H047EB33FA8DA4D53B77D6FA8C13BF0F4" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H62412E27B1B2445EAAE40DC639E13719" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <short-title><quote><short-title>NOTAM Improvement Act of 2023</short-title></quote></short-title>.</text></section> <section id="H86529FCC53534CC995AF8AFD4FE99153" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>2.</enum><header>FAA Task Force on NOTAM Improvement</header> <subsection id="H6C65F0D200744F0C89E8CBF26D90FA71" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall establish a task force to be known as the FAA Task Force on NOTAM Improvement (in this section referred to as the <quote>Task Force</quote>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H6B09CD89F8064E93B56DF8C01379F0D7" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The Task Force shall consist of members appointed by the Administrator, including at least one member of each of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H0212A91F57AE442FA211618C256FC359" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Air carrier representatives.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE863C1425ABF488199590A41F8CADA0B" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Airport representatives. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H64502F8E217244FE8766EDC80BE73B15" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Labor union representatives of airline pilots.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA5154E83194249459BCB9BC93C96F2CC" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Labor union representatives of aircraft dispatchers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H980F1A6226A749B7BF3BF0926A9192D6" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The labor union certified under section 7111 of title 5, United States Code, to represent FAA air traffic control specialists assigned to the United States NOTAMs Office.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD656C77F3EE9424B9352E67655C4B363" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The labor union certified under section 7111 of title 5, United States Code, to represent FAA aeronautical information specialists.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD134DC0A6C6B4F6FA54762A426F8D91E" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(7)</enum><text>General and business aviation representatives.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HABDBBD1F97F94A009482120F4796662C" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Aviation safety experts with knowledge of NOTAMs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1515BD3B4DAF44DB8A19A446146A9715" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Human factors experts.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAA47EA7A34D14F94867074EA4310AB9A" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Computer system architecture and cybersecurity experts. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD3F59533A0DA4AB5A96FBE9307991C5F" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The duties of the Task Force shall include—</text>
<paragraph id="H3C65CCC99D94410185D70CA5E4055E4E" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>reviewing existing methods for publishing NOTAMs and flight operations information to pilots;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H852171E6B59A49858661FC827C92B9E2" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reviewing regulations, policies, systems, and international standards relating to NOTAMs, including their content and presentation to pilots;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2486F53C4D1D4596A66E55D99BCD94B9" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>evaluating and determining best practices to organize, prioritize, and present flight operations information in a manner that optimizes pilot review and retention of relevant information; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H85E3795A360C4069863FDDB22129B516" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(4)</enum><text>providing recommendations for—</text>
<subparagraph id="HD55380471F3E4E6D8486D1616735BBB9" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improving the publication and delivery of NOTAM information in a manner that prioritizes or highlights the most important information, and optimizes pilot review and retention of relevant information;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCE839220DD924E4E9FFE93F417F919E3" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ways to ensure that NOTAMs are complete, accurate, timely, relevant to safe flight operations, and contain pertinent information;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0E984017FA1146E3BDB709A8F09DA6E0" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any best practices that the FAA should consider to improve the accuracy and understandability of NOTAMs and the display of flight operations information; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB608B5177B744683B3F95B51EA46A7D6" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(D)</enum><text>ways to work with air carriers, other airspace users, and aviation service providers to implement solutions that are aligned with the recommendations under this paragraph; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H62B9C29EBC324D9EAEF5752032A5F470" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(E)</enum><text>ways to ensure the stability, resiliency, and cybersecurity of the NOTAM computer system. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4D8BF0A54DC84C55BAFDF5BDC0B35C17" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the establishment of the Task Force, the Task Force shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate a report detailing—</text>
<paragraph id="H5BF1ADE349DE45B590642F3827C0A65E" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the results of the reviews and evaluations of the Task Force under paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (c);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFA768F928EC8408C83C7D11A4BFBB389" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the best practices identified and recommendations provided by the Task Force under subsection (c)(4);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA0FA771EDF6F4FA5BF5687B17614EFB0" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any recommendations of the Task Force for additional regulatory or policy actions to improve the publication of NOTAMs; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H55044B8C3E414090879D5294DE20A091" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the degree to which implementing the recommendations of the Task Force described under paragraph (2) will address National Transportation Safety Board Safety Recommendation A–18–024.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE12E9A2764BF446E8CAA9D92C802FF46" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Applicable law</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">Chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the Task Force. </text></subsection> <subsection id="HC093B4FF374D4A2E8C8366AC4606ECCE" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The Task Force shall terminate on the later of—</text>
<paragraph id="HF109FB53C7F3458782F5F119E91B9470" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the date on which the Task Force submits the report required under subsection (d); or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB91C1CE938F041AA94C047CB2D5FAEAB" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the date that is 18 months after the date on which the Task Force is established under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2F29B2B77CBD4DBCA8C7DFEA1FD77237" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The Administrator shall have the authority to carry out the recommendations of the Task Force detailed in the report required under subsection (d).</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H53AB2A4A4AE94382AD76A28F252ADE04" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to require the FAA to duplicate any prior, ongoing, or planned efforts related to the improvement of NOTAMs, including any efforts related to implementing any previously enacted requirements.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H953872CE2A8E48F1B731615222201C96" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H6663F7EA47D74B7BB3B563C939D1DDB9" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(1)</enum><header>FAA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>FAA</term> means the Federal Aviation Administration.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H14189450CC4D4F269AE11174B5B5C058" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(2)</enum><header>NOTAM</header><text>The term <term>NOTAM</term> means a notice containing information (which is not known sufficiently in advance to publicize by other means) concerning the establishment, condition, or change in any component (including a facility, service, or procedure thereof) or hazard in the National Airspace System, the timely knowledge of which is essential to personnel concerned with flight operations. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H24521B37E27D4560B9290D782C120BE5" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>3.</enum><header>Additional requirements</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than September 30, 2024, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall make the following improvements:</text>
<paragraph id="H5EC7F5247FB8462CB313ED53730447A3" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Complete implementation of a Federal NOTAM System (in this section referred to as a <quote>FNS</quote>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4642AA2E5BA24F5AB2231645B5A5A191" committee-id="SSCM00"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Implement a back-up system to the FNS.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H01255A2DA60F4F21B6483500342CC6C8" committee-id="SSCM00" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Brief the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate on a plan to enhance the capability to deliver information through the FNS that is machine-readable, filterable, and in the format used by the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) to promote further global harmonization among neighboring Air Navigation Service Providers (ANSPs) and provide users of the National Airspace System with one consistent format for domestic and international operations. </text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> <attestation><attestation-group><role>Speaker of the House of Representatives.</role></attestation-group><attestation-group><role>Vice President of the United States and President of the Senate.</role></attestation-group></attestation> </bill> 

