<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB04655316D9D4EDCB7DE7F1B81BBB928" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2445 IH: Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2445</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Office of the Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3E28D217493A4A059121E00C5E2AD15F" style="OLC"><section id="H0C96F91E33FF45958FF7F122FEB703D4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0E6426829C4843DA9610B8A9516335B3" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA9BBC3DA6A647DAB28F788BF26394E0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The purposes of this section are as follows:</text><paragraph id="H4492BD0893F347488EBAE84529BEFD96"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To provide for the independent and objective conduct and supervision of audits and investigations, including within the territory of Ukraine, relating to the programs and operations funded with amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D854B09D9C7433BB16E01ED64B0C87B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To provide for the independent and objective leadership and coordination of, and recommendations on, policies designed to prevent and detect waste, fraud, and abuse in such programs and operations described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4F02F0BC96C43E5846EADE032EF6C17"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To provide for an independent and objective means of keeping the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Defense, and Congress fully and currently informed about problems and deficiencies relating to the administration of such programs and operations and the necessity for and progress on corrective action.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB59C03E5EA1A4A3490EF99BF37B096E1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Office of Inspector General</header><text>There is hereby established the Office of the Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance to carry out the purposes set forth in subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7FC303F25DD74E0EB15BF5BCF88B1E40"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appointment of Inspector General; removal</header><paragraph id="H7391ACA0554143959F5AF2931318E4AC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text>The head of the Office of the Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance is the Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance (in this section referred to as the <quote>Inspector General</quote>), who shall be appointed by the President with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE686673A502748459CC89C5C4AFDB7AC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Qualifications</header><text>The appointment of the Inspector General shall be made solely on the basis of integrity and demonstrated ability in accounting, auditing, financial analysis, law, management analysis, public administration, or investigations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91EB6C6C122E42A6BC96E342555449D5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deadline for appointment</header><text>The appointment of an individual as Inspector General shall be made not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18667C1F2E7143F1900625931B586D73"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Compensation</header><text>The annual rate of basic pay of the Inspector General shall be the annual rate of basic pay provided for positions at level IV of the Executive Schedule under section 5315 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C7D1F61A8F84B4B8F8FC6BFCE203EAE"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Prohibition on political activities</header><text>For purposes of section 7324 of title 5, United States Code, the Inspector General shall not be considered an employee who determines policies to be pursued by the United States in the nationwide administration of Federal law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EA2CA5518EA4842B68778D3159596F6"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Removal</header><text>The Inspector General shall be removable from office in accordance with the provisions of section 403(b) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC6375BCEEFC74051A6467BBBC4A5E176"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Assistant inspectors general</header><text>The Inspector General shall, in accordance with applicable laws and regulations governing the civil service—</text><paragraph id="HD3939877211E4C64AD8FC0A99C8CF494"><enum>(1)</enum><text>appoint an Assistant Inspector General for Auditing who shall have the responsibility for supervising the performance of auditing activities relating to programs and operations supported by amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BAC0119D7DB42DC999061CE060E9DF5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>appoint an Assistant Inspector General for Investigations who shall have the responsibility for supervising the performance of investigative activities relating to such programs and operations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H358D46C559C744B79460327763C4B2E7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Supervision</header><paragraph id="HA7A34ED5FABB4EC58C96C52CFFFE4A84"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Inspector General shall report directly to, and be under the general supervision of, the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Defense.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE936D4369C97402D9105EFB64D91E99A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Independence to conduct investigations and audits</header><text>No officer of the Department of Defense, the Department of State, or the United States Agency for International Development shall prevent or prohibit the Inspector General from initiating, carrying out, or completing any audit or investigation related to amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine or from issuing any subpoena during the course of any such audit or investigation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5B9C59BA418C4380A62D61430C43116B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Duties</header><paragraph id="HFE9C03A64F7545998909F4413E5EEEBD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Oversight of military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine</header><text>It shall be the duty of the Inspector General to conduct, supervise, and coordinate audits and investigations of the treatment, handling, and expenditure of amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine, and of the programs, operations, and contracts carried out utilizing such funds, including—</text><subparagraph id="HCC6910F8C3A44D4DA2A723FD3AD1E429"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the oversight and accounting of the obligation and expenditure of such funds;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H075FD5C31DC14EFE866207A356B3D424"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the monitoring and review of contracts funded by such funds;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA24D7AD2C2FA47E5947635F2E3BBF5E4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the monitoring and review of the transfer of such funds and associated information between and among departments, agencies, and entities of the United States and private and nongovernmental entities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H324155C993924032BA35C05D69EAC0F3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the maintenance of records on the use of such funds to facilitate future audits and investigations of the use of such funds;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB616006E93E9457E9EA0F31A4F9AB53F"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the investigation of overpayments such as duplicate payments or duplicate billing and any potential unethical or illegal actions of Federal employees, contractors, or affiliated entities and the referral of such reports, as necessary, to the Department of Justice to ensure further investigations, prosecutions, recovery of further funds, or other remedies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2BFFFA7BDBF745AF92BF87EADA44D3EE"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the monitoring and review of all military and nonmilitary activities funded by such funds; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5CD316E4C6944CC5A5ABFE06E688F5E5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>the tracking and monitoring of all lethal and nonlethal security assistance provided by the United States, including a review of compliance with all applicable end-use certification requirements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE738916BE00B427BB8EAC6FCF149B260"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Other duties related to oversight</header><text>The Inspector General shall establish, maintain, and oversee such systems, procedures, and controls as the Inspector General considers appropriate to discharge the duties under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31EB46E1547B447DAE4DDBA2B7899101"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Duties and responsibilities under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/4">chapter 4</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code</header><text>In addition to the duties specified in paragraphs (1) and (2), the Inspector General shall also have the duties and responsibilities of inspectors general under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/4">chapter 4</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C0C72B386134F18A94C391D27A087A7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Coordination of efforts</header><text>In carrying out the duties, responsibilities, and authorities of the Inspector General under this section, the Inspector General shall coordinate with, and receive the cooperation of each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HCAD469A16CF04F7FB66DDD8E9047F3DE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Inspector General of the Department of Defense.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC12C8D7E9974332AEE11B4C32FC6DFD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Inspector General of the Department of State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B902F2413C445F9919ABF00CBB61CBE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Inspector General of the United States Agency for International Development.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5D60595A250243A280D988BA0058C600"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Powers and authorities</header><paragraph id="HABE425C5DDB949AD83ABF51C9717EA0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorities under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/4">chapter 4</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code</header><text>In carrying out the duties specified in subsection (f), the Inspector General shall have the authorities provided in section 406 of title 5, United States Code, including the authorities under subsection (e) of such section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F7648A2649642ACB7D56C919C9CCA2D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Audit standards</header><text>The Inspector General shall carry out the duties specified in subsection (f)(1) in accordance with section 404(b)(1) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H696145787A264419B6E276C1CBB9F438"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Personnel, facilities, and other resources</header><paragraph id="H3A04B8C2CDD74E368E8AD2AF68A32629"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Personnel</header><subparagraph id="H52F9081F3F1A4A4DAEE65B9415883529"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Inspector General may select, appoint, and employ such officers and employees as may be necessary for carrying out the duties of the Inspector General, subject to the provisions of title 5, United States Code, governing appointments in the competitive service, and the provisions of chapter 51 and subchapter III of chapter 53 of such title, relating to classification and General Schedule pay rates.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1996726A0CC34713AA57F2E220FF5E3B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Additional authorities</header><clause id="H6C5FCAD20E784B1C9F1E52030F1E3E79"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to clause (ii), the Inspector General may exercise the authorities of subsections (b) through (i) of section 3161 of title 5, United States Code (without regard to subsection (a) of that section).</text></clause><clause id="H2282EA06BB0544249B27CCB28BDF8149"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Periods of appointments</header><text>In exercising the employment authorities under subsection (b) of section 3161 of title 5, United States Code, as provided under clause (i) of this subparagraph—</text><subclause id="HAA04BBB1680947D2A1B9770EA49B8FB0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>paragraph (2) of that subsection (relating to periods of appointments) shall not apply; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7A5844F7E90942F0A9FACA23B5C69F12"><enum>(II)</enum><text>no period of appointment may exceed the date on which the Office of the Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance terminates under subsection (o).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3001B6DC6F74628A4BC82B6F05F7138"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Employment of experts and consultants</header><text>The Inspector General may obtain services as authorized by section 3109 of title 5, United States Code, at daily rates not to exceed the equivalent rate prescribed for grade GS–15 of the General Schedule by section 5332 of such title.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C6BCDA6E3F948BE80019EA5AE6EA70E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Contracting authority</header><text>To the extent and in such amounts as may be provided in advance by appropriations Acts, the Inspector General may enter into contracts and other arrangements for audits, studies, analyses, and other services with public agencies and with private persons, and make such payments as may be necessary to carry out the duties of the Inspector General.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FA3CB6AB93B4A0A97DDA0F4FA86E3E6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Resources</header><text>The Secretary of State or the Secretary of Defense, as appropriate, shall provide the Inspector General with—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F64BAF7ED1D4D6FB5CB1D5AF3D8B79B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">appropriate and adequate office space at appropriate locations of the Department of State or the Department of Defense, as the case may be, in Ukraine or at an appropriate United States military installation in the European theater, together with such equipment, office supplies, and communications facilities and services as may be necessary for the operation of such offices, and shall provide necessary maintenance services for such offices and the equipment and facilities located therein; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAA4C8C2907DB4307A3138B7074347FEB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>appropriate and adequate support for audits, investigations, and related activities by the Inspector General or assigned personnel within the territory of Ukraine.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDEA3E0F651174362B74CFA04F10156A4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Assistance from Federal agencies</header><subparagraph id="H1A33D0D38601436F801636A7322C7828"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Upon request of the Inspector General for information or assistance from any department, agency, or other entity of the Federal Government, the head of such entity shall, insofar as is practicable and not in contravention of any existing law, furnish such information or assistance to the Inspector General, or an authorized designee.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24E5CCDBC2F641F89A216A353898D58B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reporting of refused assistance</header><text>Whenever information or assistance requested by the Inspector General is, in the judgment of the Inspector General, unreasonably refused or not provided, the Inspector General shall report the circumstances to the Secretary of State or the Secretary of Defense, as appropriate, and to the appropriate congressional committees without delay. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H07860AA959954154B9DFE4EF6810D774"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H873101152FDB4B3CA14356141A1C41A5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Quarterly reports</header><text>Not later than 30 days after the end of each fiscal-year quarter, the Inspector General shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report summarizing, for the period of that quarter and, to the extent possible, the period from the end of such quarter to the time of the submission of the report, the activities during such period of the Inspector General and the activities under programs and operations funded with amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine. Each report shall include, for the period covered by such report, a detailed statement of all obligations, expenditures, and revenues associated with military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="H9202D9DBF05A41CCA6BA770020231C86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Obligations and expenditures of appropriated funds.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDEC3DF05B3784EFB81B08BA2601A3C7B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Operating expenses of agencies or entities receiving amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B29768B50DA45299D838372287EDE92"><enum>(C)</enum><text>In the case of any contract, grant, agreement, or other funding mechanism described in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H331338AE0F74439BA9E6C44AD647A2EE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the amount of the contract, grant, agreement, or other funding mechanism;</text></clause><clause id="H2BF7833EB6C34CC4A021E0ACD2B036B1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a brief discussion of the scope of the contract, grant, agreement, or other funding mechanism;</text></clause><clause id="HCFF5278B0CFF495EA4672194A8895AD9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a discussion of how the department or agency of the United States Government involved in the contract, grant, agreement, or other funding mechanism identified, and solicited offers from, potential individuals or entities to perform the contract, grant, agreement, or other funding mechanism, together with a list of the potential individuals or entities that were issued solicitations for the offers; and</text></clause><clause id="HB16E77DFCE704B40A2E3AEEE0282B15C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the justification and approval documents on which was based the determination to use procedures other than procedures that provide for full and open competition.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF19C68F22FD44FAF9E44198E93D98520"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An accounting comparison of—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H36F847588FDA441AB32F8DC43E58D47B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the military and nonmilitary support provided to Ukraine by the United States; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4F559564C5484F13AC8E978A477B6A9B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the military and nonmilitary support provided to Ukraine by other North Atlantic Treaty Organization member countries, including allied contributions to Ukraine that are subsequently backfilled or subsidized using United States funds.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDDC8B1C236814A839575F4419CDD0072"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An evaluation of the compliance of the Government of Ukraine with all requirements for receiving United States funds, including a description of any area of concern with respect to the ability of the Government of Ukraine to achieve such compliance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DC22ADAFE3D4A31A3CEBC92C1099C20"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered contracts, grants, agreements, and funding mechanisms</header><text>A contract, grant, agreement, or other funding mechanism described in this paragraph is any major contract, grant, agreement, or other funding mechanism that is entered into by any department or agency of the United States Government that involves the use of amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine with any public or private sector entity for any of the following purposes:</text><subparagraph id="H551BB4D86D0A4EE98CA008C9AADF2A6F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>To build or rebuild physical infrastructure of Ukraine.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0A836FA278C54B5584E15BB3520F5379"><enum>(B)</enum><text>To establish or reestablish a political or societal institution of Ukraine.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95DD73A27DA24153878C4CFC23BB7879"><enum>(C)</enum><text>To provide products or services to the people of Ukraine.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6A248BE7A754771BF6F4819AC736E20"><enum>(D)</enum><text>To provide lethal or nonlethal weaponry to Ukraine.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C4A73C0E96441E69B9CF7BAAE0063B4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>To otherwise provide military or nonmilitary support to Ukraine.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9D83BBB539E4D5EA9EA7D6050CEB566"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Inspector General shall publish on a publicly available internet website each report under paragraph (1) of this subsection in English and other languages that the Inspector General determines are widely used and understood in Ukraine.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H136ED0FBD9F740EE954E5F78D2A1FE0D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Form</header><text>Each report required under this subsection shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex if the Inspector General considers it necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD65D0CC5DAE7422C869E65F5EE843B4B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to authorize the public disclosure of information that is—</text><subparagraph id="H775F87C940684E31907BF04DAEE080D7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>specifically prohibited from disclosure by any other provision of law;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H914612D7B1AF4EABA8EA749DEABF83E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>specifically required by Executive order to be protected from disclosure in the interest of national defense or national security or in the conduct of foreign affairs; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13C60E54C2EA4014A43101EA26643860"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a part of an ongoing criminal investigation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H47D2D63EA6D546B0B7FCCBC455A24BFE"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Report coordination</header><paragraph id="H8D8704AF821D4110BB01A4454B5E7DC6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Submission to secretaries of State and defense</header><text>The Inspector General shall also submit each report required under subsection (i) to the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Defense.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4CABD102423E4283A2295200827451C3"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Submission to Congress</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H896A9EF7677C4C2BB46432E8003415C5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after receipt of a report under paragraph (1), the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees any comments on the matters covered by the report. Such comments shall be submitted in unclassified form, but may include a classified annex if the Secretary of State or the Secretary of Defense, as the case may be, considers it necessary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9172333FCCB6453DAE985A5939B276C7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Access</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On request, any Member of Congress may view comments submitted under subparagraph (A), including the classified annex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4D10353FF6D04360B0274319AFA46CE5"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Transparency</header><paragraph id="H54F3D664F5E546BD853A33ED0875AD6F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 60 days after submission to the appropriate congressional committees of a report under subsection (i), the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Defense shall jointly make copies of the report available to the public upon request, and at a reasonable cost.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H206F299DCB8F47DE8AD9B15F91C50111"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Comments on matters covered by report</header><text>Not later than 60 days after submission to the appropriate congressional committees under subsection (j)(2)(A) of comments on a report under subsection (i), the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Defense shall jointly make copies of the comments available to the public upon request, and at a reasonable cost.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5304CBC5790E4C3DA1E91475362F8768"><enum>(l)</enum><header>Waiver</header><paragraph id="HCC4ED85282FC42ADA8C8D904D0B264AB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The President may waive the requirement under paragraph (1) or (2) of subsection (k) with respect to availability to the public of any element in a report under subsection (i), or any comment under subsection (j)(2)(A), if the President determines that the waiver is justified for national security reasons.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E8C24EB5E6947E8BA755156190877CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice of waiver</header><text>The President shall publish a notice of each waiver made under this subsection in the Federal Register no later than the date on which a report required under subsection (i), or any comment under subsection (j)(2)(A), is submitted to the appropriate congressional committees. The report and comments shall specify whether waivers under this subsection were made and with respect to which elements in the report or which comments, as appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFDBA053A90344882978BE636BCE394D4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Submission of comments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may not waive under this subsection subparagraph (A) or (B) of subsection (j).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H995C24474A75461F9FB94E979E956ED5"><enum>(m)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H74B97CE646664283A2CE8EC8A1CA1817"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine</header><text>The term <term>amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H901D51EE362142D6903F8BB815E5BE8B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>amounts appropriated or otherwise made available on or after January 1, 2022, for—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H510EE39931DE483BB56AF6272E0DFA81"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Ukraine Security Assistance Initiative under section 1250 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2016 (Public Law 11492; 129 Stat. 1608);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD11A1CD335744F51BAEDA004C225F112"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any foreign military financing accessed by the Government of Ukraine;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9618EB9F301348978A3BCC9AA53EB16F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Presidential drawdown authority under section 506(a) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2318">22 U.S.C. 2318(a)</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE2D72431C9C444249026A02F9611D6B2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the defense institution building program under section 332 of title 10, United States Code;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA4B48020B75D421BAAD6046E79FE0661"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the building partner capacity program under section 333 of title 10, United States Code;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F89EAED111949229CED4F4FFCC558BD"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the International Military Education and Training program of the Department of State; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4479E9B2D2454D1AAFCCE03995B76D42"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the United States European Command; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H928098A6C4354D83857F9FEF646D2A37"><enum>(B)</enum><text>amounts appropriated or otherwise made available on or after January 1, 2022, for the military, economic, reconstruction, or humanitarian support of Ukraine under any account or for any purpose not described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEAAF46F39A74421B41177FA55590622"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H4B2996453D8C4098AA7B0FB31B914F72"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committees on Appropriations, the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Relations, and Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3DB89C56575747D388F14AC890231050"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committees on Appropriations, the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, and the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3681609FE78949789DB07F99CDF4B6EE"><enum>(n)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><paragraph id="H5EDE32060A2A41E9895C07E9AE348F55"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $70,000,000 for fiscal year 2023 to carry out this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H52BC50C69A6048EE8E83F4C3D9A1234A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Offset</header><text>The amount authorized to be appropriated for fiscal year 2023 for the Ukraine Security Assistance Initiative is hereby reduced by $70,000,000.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H322D6A9CC2F545C5B5A97EB5ACAADB58"><enum>(o)</enum><header>Termination</header><paragraph id="H9DA8F3187B30474D84C475D290E1C0AA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Office of the Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance shall terminate 180 days after the date on which amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine that are unexpended are less than $250,000,000.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H045FABB6251F488EBDC4650E0C919AC0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>The Inspector General shall, prior to the termination of the Office of the Special Inspector General for Ukraine Assistance under paragraph (1), prepare and submit to the appropriate congressional committees a final forensic audit report on programs and operations funded with amounts appropriated or otherwise made available for the military and nonmilitary support of Ukraine.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

