<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H01E6876B1C624FE4AFC6130C3911B08A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1089 IH: VA Medical Center Facility Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1089</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230217">February 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Mrs. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require directors of medical centers of the Department of Veterans Affairs to submit annual fact sheets to the Secretary of Veterans Affairs on the status of such facilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H35D5FF1E0C494EA291131A0777BA57CA" style="OLC"><section id="HD2360297606E4B51B6906B0FA11BE3CD" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>VA Medical Center Facility Transparency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H433A57D08F9749DCA0927310A4DFFA41" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Information on medical facilities of the Department of Veterans Affairs</header><subsection id="HDD85B0B84B9145BB9832FEA6953DD4BF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Fact sheets</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall ensure that each director of a medical center of the Department of Veterans Affairs submits to the Secretary, the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Senate, and the appropriate Members of Congress the following:</text><paragraph id="HFA02B860FFBC436BB2823FA7CC9F5183"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An annual concise, easy-to-read fact sheet containing, with respect to the year covered by the fact sheet each of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HFAF53EAE91124F9B9D25AA2AE424E7D4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Statistics regarding—</text><clause id="H15926023595745769867E10723A1FABD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number of veterans who were treated at a medical facility of the Department under the jurisdiction of the director;</text></clause><clause id="HF07E67EFF2314AC5B8B6DD85EA355141"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the number of appointments conducted by each such facility;</text></clause><clause id="H6575AE58F0F440CB92E00F556D06DE99"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the most common illnesses or conditions for which treatment was furnished;</text></clause><clause id="H3AE804EB895D49A9A1B3A8E28797A4CD"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the satisfaction of veterans who were treated at each such facility;</text></clause><clause id="HC97E23CAE4A04B46A96C81D5A72669F9"><enum>(v)</enum><text>how each such facility compares with other facilities with respect to the satisfaction of veterans who were treated at the facilities; and</text></clause><clause id="HA37581B0D6C844FC83AEE9C433F16B3C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>other matters the director determines appropriate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4BAD2EDAD92D4A36AE35F50C11C5744A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of any successes or achievements experienced by such facilities, including—</text><clause id="H14BE23422D3D4BA9B98417320CCD41C6" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>actions taken to improve such facilities;</text></clause><clause id="HA4C7E3AD7371428DA0E5467C29ACC3EB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>actions taken to improve the access to and quality of the care provided at such facilities; and</text></clause><clause id="H705B1096CB734B68B2364EA9A895B2F9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any other accomplishments determined appropriate by the director.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A55CF955B07462FB646DB095B564F43"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of special areas of emphasis or specialization by such facilities, such as efforts aimed at meeting the needs of women veterans, suicide prevention and other mental health initiatives, opioid abuse prevention and pain management, or special efforts on veteran homelessness, or other matters as the director determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC5DC88716CD644FFB0EA394057D5740D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A description of matters concerning such facilities that have previously been identified as deficient and needing remediation that are still in need of such remediation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD0B44D16671A4A7DB323DC71F00CA42D"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A quarterly fact sheet containing, with respect to the quarter covered by the fact sheet, the average wait time for veterans to receive treatment at the medical facility of the Department under the jurisdiction of the director.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10DA27DE6F4444BF978CC13A3853CC62"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Availability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each fact sheet under subsection (a) shall be made publicly available—</text><paragraph id="H1F7965A70EFE4ACBB9EAEC6B55404739"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in a physical form at the relevant medical facility of the Department in a conspicuous location; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H865E40853E5447728F4DAE1AC31C751B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in an electronic form on the internet website of the facility.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAF68F2BA815A44EDA4DC94F4DA76F786"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Timing of fact sheets</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The fact sheets under subsection (a) shall be submitted during the first fiscal year beginning after the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and not less frequently than—</text><paragraph id="H259B5036E882498ABE1BA1FF0CF31E81"><enum>(1)</enum><text>once each fiscal year thereafter with respect to the annual fact sheet under paragraph (1) of such subsection; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1060A293805A410684826D9B12A14FA1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">once each fiscal quarter thereafter with respect to the quarterly fact sheet under paragraph (2) of such subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3A1C84AEF2E249579BBAB5926CE64925"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Standardized format</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a standard format for the fact sheets under subsection (a) to ensure that each director of a medical center of the Department carries out such subsection in a consistent manner.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEC29CD4770B845D1B995DE0786090522"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H7B07C8F5FB914068873BA8DFD0BFE4FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>appropriate Members of Congress</term> means, with respect to a medical facility of the Department of Veterans Affairs about which a fact sheet is submitted under subsection (a), the Senators representing the State, and the Member, Delegate, or Resident Commissioner of the House of Representatives representing the district, that includes the facility.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H975D6586EA8B4868A5BF6392178278CA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and any territory or possession of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

