<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1DDDDB42CABC41BFB8096811FC840CE6" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5629 IH: Child Poverty Reduction Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5629</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reduce child poverty in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H361EC494E7F14D1999F96887744DA828" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H817C653AC6B647969B9ACAF9604170D8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Child Poverty Reduction Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H12D23BC374D34C8DAC2D144061B05278"><enum>2.</enum><header>Child poverty goal and accountability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title IV of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/601">42 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after part B the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD7C63AF16BE44373AFEFE609F5332A50" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<part id="H21D6DABFFCEA49F28E9889F7D8779833"><enum>C</enum><header>Child poverty accountability measure</header> 
<section id="H233742AE96BE4DEEA7E842EAE64B2494"><enum>441.</enum><header>National goal to cut child poverty by half</header> 
<subsection id="H1F0E2D3FC83243E28DA90EFD4ED450FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to reduce the number of children living in poverty in the United States by half in 5 years.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H998C3144D40D45C8B428F657B16DCC90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of the Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that an effort to reach the goal described in subsection (a) shall include reducing the number of children in deep poverty as well as reducing child poverty among racial or ethnic groups with disparate poverty rates.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H2C184691E5BC48E0BF494EF76F0FC0CE"><enum>442.</enum><header>Establishment of annual reporting</header> 
<subsection id="H5FFC563716C2465E8E182C4D4C9578A2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Anchored supplemental poverty measure</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the Bureau of the Census to report an anchored Supplemental Poverty Measure for individuals who have not attained 18 years of age, annually beginning with calendar year 2023. Beginning with the report for calendar year 2024, the report shall be based on poverty thresholds which are adjusted for inflation using the Consumer Price Index for all-urban consumers (as published by the Department of Labor). This subsection shall not be interpreted to require or authorize the replacement of any other calculation or measure reported by the Bureau of the Census.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB3B952A5E687491AB428DD2A29A72ADD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timing of release of Current Population Survey Annual Social and Economic Supplement microdata</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Bureau of the Census shall release the Current Population Survey Annual Social and Economic Supplement microdata for each year as a single file containing the anchored Supplemental Poverty Measure and any other poverty rates the Bureau of the Census reports. The file shall be released at the same time as the Bureau of the Census report on Income, Poverty, and Health Insurance Coverage in the United States. That report, or companion reports, should include poverty statistics and thresholds for the anchored Supplemental Poverty Measure and any other measures the Bureau of the Census reports.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HED5F35D2E8544BDD876971F41D569DB7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Reporting in relation to the territories</header> 
<paragraph id="HB2E4A9363BDF46569E00D6827B5A69FB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the Bureau of the Census to develop data to report an anchored Supplemental Poverty Measure for Puerto Rico, Guam, the United States Virgin Islands, the Northern Mariana Islands, and American Samoa, as part of the annual report required by subsection (a), not later than the close of fiscal year 2025.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H043A03AE820546A8A07ABBDB4BBBF9EE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report required if compliance is not feasible</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary determines that it will not be feasible to comply with all or part of paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit to the Congress, not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this section, a report that explains what is not feasible, why it is not feasible, and includes details on what, if anything, would be needed to enable such compliance and by what date compliance could be achieved.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H432208C4E6CD4D33A48ABA4CF70916DF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitations on authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this subsection, there are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary a total of not more than $2,000,000 for fiscal years 2024 through 2026.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8BC8F3FBE84145FCBBEFBF0E30A84B9B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Improving income data for use in annual reporting</header> <paragraph id="HB9BD0650A9954144B847E02B04ED7DAD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the Bureau of the Census to develop income data with corrections for under-reporting of income data for calculating an anchored Supplemental Poverty Measure as part of the annual report required by subsection (a), not later than the close of fiscal year 2025.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8AB6A29F2BE42DEACCB455E533BDD51"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report required if compliance is not feasible</header><text>If the Secretary determines that it will not be feasible to comply with all or part of paragraph (1), the Secretary shall submit to the Congress, not later than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this section, a report that explains what is not feasible, why it is not feasible, and includes details on what, if anything, would be needed to enable such compliance and by what date compliance could be achieved.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H568740C274404D4FA2D2B3401C0E5F4C"><enum>443.</enum><header>Child poverty reports</header> <subsection id="HE2A55363A1804DEF81814BCF60B1807E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual reports on the effect of Federal policies on child poverty in the United States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 6 months after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary shall enter into an agreement with the National Academy of Sciences to submit to the Congress annual reports providing an evidence-based, non-partisan analysis of how Federal policies or programs have contributed to meeting the goal set forth in section 441(a), based on their effect on the anchored Supplemental Poverty Measure for children as reported by the Bureau of the Census pursuant to section 442.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF24222721828423099E1B0AE17489CCB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of reports</header> 
<paragraph id="HF8761FE604D845888666709567D14A87"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each such report—</text> <subparagraph id="H7B13AE6E972D4D55857486BAB6403735"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall analyze how, and the extent to which, Federal policies and programs contribute to meeting the goal referred to in subsection (a) of this section;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC4AFFDA75E5144AD9A12BC88F9BD4071"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall take into account the number of children in deep poverty and child poverty among racial or ethnic groups with disparate poverty rates;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3EDEE5A4A9184AC89150F4B023ACC54C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall attempt to ascertain whether each studied policy or program reduces or increases the number of children living in poverty, why the policy or program does so, and the extent to which the policy or program does so; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA66A259B6CBD4C63B30E892A97B08088"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall include, to the extent feasible, projections on how such policies or programs would affect the number of children living in poverty in future years, which shall be made on the basis of previously released Current Population Survey Annual Social and Economic Supplement data, and adjusted periodically as new estimates from the Bureau of the Census become available.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0D2E148CCDB649E0B843D68520C3F042"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Data corrections</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Where feasible, each such report shall correct the underlying Current Population Survey Annual Social and Economic Supplement data, for under-reporting of income and in-kind benefits and shall include estimates using both uncorrected and corrected income data. Because available information with which to produce corrected income data is currently limited and not timely, each such report shall indicate the year to which the corrected income data pertain and other limitations of the data. As soon as corrected income data from the Census Bureau become available under section 442(d), each such report shall use those data.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF0F06740DCF64EACAB40C08AF12E69D3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Feasibility review of State and local evidence-Based policies</header><text>The 1st report under subsection (a) shall include a review of the feasibility of including consideration of State and local evidence-based policies or programs in subsequent such reports, and if the review determines that including the consideration is feasible, then each such report shall include an analysis of the additional policies.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC880D84936E74D2A8EFCE0B3F16F969E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Timing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report for a year under subsection (a) shall be made after the report of the United States Census Bureau on Income, Poverty, and Health Insurance Coverage in the United States for the year is released, and—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6FFBE39CBABC4643A37A53904344F4B7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the case of the 1st such report, before the beginning of the 1st calendar year that begins more than 6 months after the date of the enactment of this section; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H589E573C5C19456A86222CB903B13AFB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in the case of each subsequent such report, before the end of the year.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE941A87316714D6F98D10BAA85AC5FE4"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Limitations on authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out this section, there are authorized to be appropriated not more than—</text> <paragraph id="H9D812B03B78F47E387DC7B8109AE8427"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$1,200,000 for fiscal year 2024; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFF9809B17B91441787780B7ECE72952C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$1,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2025 through 2033.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HDBA401F0C9A7454B875D4A19BBD65576"><enum>444.</enum><header>Child poverty reduction strategy clearinghouse</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish, and annually update, on a website of the Department of Health and Human Services, an online collection of resources related to the national child poverty reduction goal established in section 441 of this Act, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H46A5A6FC40624583848657318D1A9E31"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the anchored Supplemental Poverty Measure published under section 442 of this Act;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9126BDC45BB14B8994170F0F3182031D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the reports required by section 443 of this Act;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2326207D80D74EFEA71ACFF3851EA217"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the report required by section 3 of the <short-title>Child Poverty Reduction Act of 2023</short-title>;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H82D723BB5D824844B25DF8C1F9BABE44" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the report required by section 4 of the <short-title>Child Poverty Reduction Act of 2023</short-title>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3689A60349E24274BB1AF228F60D895B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>links to other relevant Federal reports, analyses, evaluations, and resources related to child poverty as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HB34B650415784DEF973A9DEBD1CF4D0C"><enum>445.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this part:</text> 
<paragraph id="HE4AF725C0DF8454391CCC8662554158D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Anchored</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>anchored</term> means fixed at a given point in time, and annually adjusted by a measure reflecting only changes in prices.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCED5F61CD4AC4F879984CE4F86932F60"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Poverty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>poverty</term> means, with respect to an individual or family, that the individual or family has a total annual income that is less than the anchored Supplemental Poverty threshold for the individual or family, as provided in the Bureau of the Census report under section 442.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6D6F48DF137B4DA797B846866F8B8574"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deep poverty</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>deep poverty</term> means, with respect to an individual or family, that the individual or family has a total annual income that is less than 50 percent of the anchored Supplemental Poverty threshold for the individual or family, as provided in the Bureau of the Census report under section 442.</text></paragraph></section></part><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H834336E7B365421584E66F4D877D6307"><enum>3.</enum><header>Update of <quote>A Roadmap to Reduce Child Poverty</quote></header> <subsection id="HA9D999BE38EC4612A41B631822D3F211"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 12 months after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall enter into an agreement with the National Academy of Sciences to revise and update the National Academies report entitled <quote>A Roadmap to Reduce Child Poverty</quote> within 24 months after the date of entry into the agreement.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H20C059415E964E01A3BC055EEA597C15"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitations on authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out subsection (a), there are authorized to be appropriated not more than $2,200,000.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H90BE1FA2B8684289A6311F205AD84FC3" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header>Report on reducing long-term, intergenerational child poverty</header> <subsection id="HC9E53BB7EBDF4DD29A83C6354FE4C8AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 6 months after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall enter into an agreement with the National Academy of Sciences to publish, within 36 months after the date of entry into the agreement, a report on evidence-based policies to reduce long-term, intergenerational child poverty, which report shall build on the National Academies report entitled <quote>A Roadmap to Reduce Child Poverty</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE867098AD10E456B929016CD1BA46BDC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitations on authorization of appropriations</header><text>To carry out subsection (a), there are authorized to be appropriated not more than $2,200,000.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

