<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA03977BCDCBD4E568F4372651C3EA6E4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5471 IH: Honor Our Commitment Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5471</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To halt removal of certain nationals of Vietnam, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H502130A9FE91497B8E47167CEACBB468" style="OLC"><section id="H2C72334B443C4865A61CE279734E32A3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Honor Our Commitment Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HD0151DA304B24588AB81D47F6A0C9D64"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds as follows:</text><paragraph id="H59322ECA94484DF09E65BAAF03133C18"><enum>(1)</enum><text>From April to September 1975, the United States conducted Operation New Arrival to relocate 130,000 Vietnamese refugees to the United States following the end of the Vietnam War. During this time, more than 50,000 Vietnamese refugees were processed through Camp Pendleton for resettlement in southern California.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC24B2BCDEA1A42F28E630BD990AD3F60"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In the 4 decades since they fled Vietnam as refugees, Vietnamese Americans have woven their stories into the American fabric.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H977F4BD8CD864432B10369D88E5BC43D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The largest concentrations of Vietnamese Americans can be found in Orange County, California, followed by San Jose (California), Houston (Texas), Seattle (Washington), Northern Virginia, and New Orleans (Louisiana).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AE4CC57AA1B466B9796CCF557DF88BF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the American Community Survey, 1.4 million Americans speak Vietnamese at home, the fourth-most-common language other than English.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77DED3BAEC2C4F3596DBB74620F93C72"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Immigrants may find it difficult to assimilate into their new communities as a result of the trauma of war. A 2018 study published by Rashmi Gangamma and Daran Shipman in the Journal of Marital and Family Therapy noted that <quote>the traumatic nature of (an immigrant’s) forced displacement flight, and resettlement can increase vulnerability to mental distress.</quote> First generation immigrant children are especially vulnerable to gang violence when their parents find it difficult to navigate their new communities culturally and politically.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF263723AB62847DA95C6B88BC95152AA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 2008, the United States and Vietnam signed a bilateral repatriation agreement, hereinafter known as the 2008 Vietnam-U.S. Memorandum of Understanding (MOU).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE1385A235B94A5180FE18CFF30BD83C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>According to section 2, article 2 of the 2008 Vietnam-U.S. MOU, <quote>Vietnamese citizens are not subject to return to Vietnam under this Agreement if they arrived in the United States before July 12, 1995, the date on which diplomatic relations were re-established between the U.S. Government and the Vietnamese Government. The U.S. Government and the Vietnamese Government maintain their respective legal positions relative to Vietnamese citizens who departed Vietnam for the United States prior to that date.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4990DC6810D479DBFABB7F33B05E7AC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Under President George Bush and President Barack Obama, the United States recognized the 2008 Vietnam-U.S. MOU’s protections and refrained from deporting pre-1995 Vietnamese refugees.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H47156C9266A9439E82AF30D9418D9101"><enum>(9)</enum><text>In November 2020, President Donald Trump’s Administration signed a new agreement with Vietnam which allows for the deportation of Vietnamese refugees who arrived in the United States prior to July 12, 1995. This includes lawful permanent residents who have committed certain minor crimes and others who came to the United States as children after the Vietnam War.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF7A8BFF908E54048B710AC617B51378F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Limitation on the detention and removal of nationals of Vietnam</header><subsection id="H0DCC3BBE68F64377874DCDA6A0C764CD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation on detention and removal</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (b), an alien may not be detained or removed from the United States on or after the date of enactment of this Act if the alien—</text><paragraph id="H1EE358936326453CB09DBB3E6CEB97CA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>is a national of Vietnam;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAD12BF81F974868BFD32B91051C7F30"><enum>(2)</enum><text>entered the United States on or before July 12, 1995 and has continuously resided in the United States since such entry; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3724951731C24BBABA920B78763FD5A8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>is subject to a final order of removal.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCBB84A3ED5C94C04BA09556058B40945"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subsection (a) shall not apply to an alien if—</text><paragraph id="HD501952801A34F288ABF36096B0C1729"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of Homeland Security determines, based on credible facts, that the alien is directly responsible for harming the security of the United States; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA681D0D88F5947B492B860E1C22FCBDC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the alien is subject to extradition.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCB17B23D64C44EFEAB4A81233F5C1FA0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Employment authorization</header><text>The Secretary of Homeland Security shall authorize an alien described in subsection (a) to engage in employment in the United States and provide such alien with an <quote>employment authorized</quote> endorsement or other appropriate work permit.</text></subsection></section><section id="H593B3DF0FE724EC8A7CE24C6665E613E"><enum>4.</enum><header>Notice for certain Vietnamese nationals with removal orders</header><subsection id="H65B8776F759C48038524B6AADDA92EBC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall provide notice of the provisions of this Act to each alien described in section 3(a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H087C6D5534BF487B87A8805F728B2F84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents of notice</header><text>The notice described in subsection (a) shall include information explaining the requirements and instructions for filing a motion to reopen removal proceedings under section 240(c)(7) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1229a">8 U.S.C. 1229a(c)(7)</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="H6BA71BFDE1CD4DD399C12ABE123E77C7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Judicial review</header><subsection id="H96DD3209B1ED408BA1DBA9851E16A5DC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, an individual or entity who has been harmed by a violation of this Act may file an action in an appropriate district court of the United States to seek declaratory or injunctive relief.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0ECD1A5B2B5645D8A10841402A537B84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act may be construed to preclude an action filed pursuant to subsection (a) from proceeding as a class action (as such term is defined in section 1711 of title 28, United States Code).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

