<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H078BA8C2ACBA43D5A92002F8794EEC0E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 922 IH: Reprioritizing Unserved Rural Areas and Locations for Broadband Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 922</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 to provide requirements on the use of assistance for broadband deployment, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEB2BE6E98DEC4332BF1885E29D12895C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD7C5668E786A45D18706728D1976745C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reprioritizing Unserved Rural Areas and Locations for Broadband Act of 2023</short-title></quote> and the <quote><short-title>RURAL Broadband Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7507EC343AB64331A0F10EE858143556"><enum>2.</enum><header>Use of assistance for deployment of broadband infrastructure</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title VI of the Rural Electrification Act of 1936 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/950bb">7 U.S.C. 950bb et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HB85743CC76174A4F9FB05A2AE32B5EE2" style="OLC">
<section id="HCE0EBFA4DE9E41C68A9D1D8717140EF9"><enum>607.</enum><header>Use of assistance for deployment of broadband infrastructure</header>
<subsection id="H2EB015640ED84499871B5F45384726AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of qualifying broadband-Capable infrastructure</header><text>In this section, the term <term>qualifying broadband-capable infrastructure</term> means fixed terrestrial broadband-capable infrastructure—</text> <paragraph id="HBCB814CAF13547BEB39A4FB078294C55"><enum>(1)</enum><text>used by a service provider to provide fixed terrestrial broadband service for which the service provider receives universal service support under section 254 of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/254">47 U.S.C. 254</external-xref>), if—</text>
<subparagraph id="HB6538E7FD89D4E29A376ADB5584D457C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the broadband service satisfies the current speed benchmark for fixed services established by the Federal Communications Commission under section 706 of the Telecommunications Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/1302">47 U.S.C. 1302</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H90B5199E8CE94E62A3FB910494D60295"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the service provider is in compliance with buildout obligations in the relevant area to provide retail fixed terrestrial broadband service that will comply with the applicable broadband speed standard described in subparagraph (A); or</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3A4EA98D8AAA4361A2352FB7AB4DF144"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that—</text> <subparagraph id="H55964D2F21F94CB5929C4D349BD4E866"><enum>(A)</enum><text>was financed with funds provided by the Secretary under this Act or any other program carried out by the Secretary for the costs of the construction, improvement, or acquisition of facilities or equipment for the purpose of providing fixed terrestrial telecommunications or broadband service; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H97B4E528A50E4D0780BB2146F18B1DBA"><enum>(B)</enum>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H52F3C074B7DA4EE1B3DB5E39BA77D44D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is used to provide fixed terrestrial broadband service, if—</text> <subclause id="H3D64AA80D51841D2AD891A2DA4C6AC1F" indent="up1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the broadband service satisfies any applicable broadband speed standards established by the Secretary; or</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H7F73226B16474CC0B153883B120CDA3C" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the service provider is in compliance with buildout obligations in the relevant area to provide retail fixed terrestrial broadband service that will comply with the applicable broadband speed standards described in subclause (I); or</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H0BDD7923F7A54BA1B8469E08AD8E0C61" indent="up1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>was financed with a loan under this Act or any other program carried out by the Secretary that remains outstanding for the purpose of providing fixed terrestrial telecommunications or broadband service.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H8CD2DBB936BF46DEAF2D51D49C1A215E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Restriction on use of assistance</header><text>A loan, grant, or other assistance awarded under this Act, or by the rural development mission area under the Consolidated Farm and Rural Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1921">7 U.S.C. 1921 et seq.</external-xref>), may not be used to coordinate, approve, or finance the deployment of broadband-capable infrastructure by a service provider to provide retail fixed broadband service that would overbuild or otherwise duplicate qualifying broadband-capable infrastructure that another service provider is using to provide retail fixed terrestrial broadband service in the same geographic area.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9E1C5F5702404F45A6BCFA9A922C6B2D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of assistance in unserved areas</header><text>A loan, grant, or other assistance provided by the Secretary hereunder, acting through the Administrator of the Rural Utilities Service, to coordinate, approve, or finance the deployment of broadband-capable infrastructure by a service provider may be used to provide retail fixed broadband service only in a geographic area in which there is no qualifying broadband-capable infrastructure owned or operated by another service provider.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


