<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Engrossed-in-House" dms-id="H63EA42386CB6410EBE795F3E52BDE813" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1715 EH: Advanced Weather Model Computing Development Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date></dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="no">IB</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1715</legis-num>
<current-chamber display="no">IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To direct the Department of Energy and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration to conduct collaborative research in order to advance numerical weather and climate prediction in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H8AEB6EA54FED4B5D90D68964FFB8EC0C" style="OLC">
<section id="HBF60DBD439E649708E31CBEE9ED6068B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Advanced Weather Model Computing Development Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H50C1503820F54B70AC379E83328DEE2C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text>
<paragraph id="HDC6BC7C16C05472FBBD151EF6A2546E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <quote>Department</quote> means the Department of Energy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7CD7B60804E74B1A9806F5D96BDEC186"><enum>(2)</enum><header>National Laboratory</header><text>The term <quote>National Laboratory</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFED69997182E4B17B1914AC9DF54932A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Energy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H16834DF0403C467CB1A526F08F171BAC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H884AC91761654E37A436BCEE153AE5F1"><enum>3.</enum><header>Department of Energy and National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration research and development coordination</header>
<subsection id="H0EFBAF913CB7461A86883951C996F01D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary and Administrator shall carry out collaborative research and development activities in artificial intelligence and high performance computing focused on the advancement of climate models and operational numerical weather prediction relevant to agency missions.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H25F77C86765D40DF92BB765319CF3521" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary and Administrator shall carry out the activities under subsection (a) through the establishment of a memorandum of understanding, or other appropriate interagency agreement. Such memorandum or agreement, as the case may be, shall require the use of a competitive, merit-reviewed process, which considers applications from Federal agencies, National Laboratories, institutions of higher education, nonprofit institutions, and other appropriate entities.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HB018A11A43F9452A9A39542DB9A30BA7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Secretary and Administrator may—</text> <paragraph id="HC1F6EF7FC4024E41A74E4D595F77438C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct collaborative research to develop new methods and optimization of modeling and simulation, machine learning, data assimilation, large scale data analytics, and predictive analysis techniques;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H57836270FD764A50BE738A7EA99DFF12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>explore options for performance portability of the optimized weather model codes between the operational computing systems of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and the Department’s high performance computers;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H531807AFD2034DA2863C4BF0AF7B9FAC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop methods to accommodate large data sets of weather and climate information;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5913B700891449D78E2D054E36786903"><enum>(4)</enum><text>to the maximum extent practicable, and in compliance with national security policies, promote collaboration, open community-based development, and data sharing between Federal agencies, National Laboratories, institutions of higher education, nonprofit institutions, and other appropriate entities by providing the necessary access and secure data transfer capabilities; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C70CB9EE22A44708615320FC9D504CA"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support maintenance of and improvements to scientific computing infrastructure that the Secretary and Administrator determine appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HA38DBEECC2FC4126A78D2812C972A0D0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>In carrying out the activities under subsection (a), the Secretary and Administrator are authorized to—</text> <paragraph id="H2AB43AF11DD04F93A63434FEF810C6DC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>carry out reimbursable agreements between the Department, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and other entities in order to maximize the effectiveness of research and development; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5355736B8FB84FED90DDEAD6FD0EB87B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collaborate with other Federal agencies as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H6FEA5D364CFC4C2BA1670F63D5BA49C6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary and Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate, a report detailing the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HFC6833A303324FE89093B6AF66B4A8B4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Interagency coordination between each Federal agency involved in the research and development activities carried out under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD79AB877ACEE4AA994B37A6854CE4097"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Potential opportunities to expand the technical capabilities of the Department and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEDF7944FAC9B42409B201C35B47163FC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Collaborative research achievements.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAE19958B67884DE5942EDD9BE92F5BAE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Areas of future mutually beneficial gains as a result of the activities described in subsection (c).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H05D97174C2DD41608E657571531250C2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Continuation of coordination between the Department and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration on activities described in subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H4866C051E9DA4DD3846DEBEF29C93FE4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Climate and weather prediction on high performance computers initiative</header> <subsection id="HC0FBFF96F5434B0EA6FD14B9A0B0BA66" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, in collaboration with the Secretary, shall carry out an initiative, which may leverage Department high performance computers or expertise, to run advanced models in order to conduct proof of concept scenarios in comparison with current issued forecasts and models. The Secretary and Administrator shall carry out the initiative through a competitive, merit-reviewed process, and consider applications from Federal agencies, National Laboratories, institutions of higher education, nonprofit institutions, and other appropriate entities.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H8A0E41AAF4CB4D4A95F9F8BF5822B5E1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Components</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the initiative under subsection (a), the Administrator shall prevent duplication and coordinate research efforts in artificial intelligence, high performance computing, modeling and simulation, machine learning, data assimilation, large scale data analytics, and predictive analysis across the Department, and may—</text> <paragraph id="HB5CAD814B0C648B7A21B9E0412E098D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>run real-time weather forecast scenarios to conduct comparative research between National Weather Service issued forecasts to forecasts developed through the use of operational models run on high performance computers;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H960AADA68EF74D6588B4F494A43B2A11"><enum>(2)</enum><text>share relevant modeling system and applications innovations developed through the initiative, including Unified Forecast System-based applications, through community-based activities; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3CF4DD46167B4754B748BFEDF7C00D6A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">leverage related weather and climate efforts and data from the National Science and Technology Council, the Interagency Council for Advancing Meteorological Services, and other relevant interagency entities.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HFB0608ACFDCD4F47A393E081DFE28A6A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate a report evaluating the following:</text> <paragraph id="H2A475B57EF6E471EB9BC7B5CD0F5C1CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The effectiveness of the initiative under subsection (a), including applied research discoveries, and advanced modeling improvements achieved.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC9316D3133134E38957DE20218D1DD48"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Potential opportunities to expand the high performance computing capabilities of the Department and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HB0AA1B61F1AF472C9E1B3895223DDC32"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The authority under this section shall terminate five years after the date of the enactment of this section.</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H9F4F5E3CB68C44C8B9BF7923A18F170C"><enum>5.</enum><header>Research security</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The activities authorized under this Act shall be applied in a manner consistent with subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (enacted as division B of the CHIPS Act of 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>)).</text></section> </legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230509" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives May 9, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="no">Cheryl L. Johnson,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation> <endorsement display="yes"></endorsement> </bill> 

