<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4A39A5BF897F4EA8A391DAED447026D4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5442 IH: Drone Reform Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5442</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230913">September 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Permanent Select Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To consolidate within the Department of Defense all executive authority regarding the use of armed unmanned aerial vehicles, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H84EDEE7F9E8C489F9521B9DD41DC20BA" style="OLC"><section id="H6EFAC5185A3A4CCBA51104D50C0F307A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Drone Reform Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HAFA35FB2928C4A4AB5903016C52CC751"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Defense executive authority over use of armed unmanned aerial vehicles</header><subsection id="H665AC66CD4B64056B8718A63039D17DE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>DOD executive authority</header><paragraph id="HBB25EA2E719C4CE8B8B2D50B6D2A05FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No operation involving the use of an armed unmanned aerial vehicle shall be carried out under the authority of a department or agency of the Federal Government other than the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B1A9D7D46E5470D9032EC13F94251A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use by military personnel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Only uniformed members of the United States Armed Forces may—</text><subparagraph id="H72EE45F310534CA9822CE69E80CD2E9D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>operate, or order the operation of, an armed unmanned aerial vehicle; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3290A1D4A6994E83865FADECC6ACD4C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>operate or fire, or order the operation or firing of, any weapon or other munition carried on an armed unmanned aerial vehicle.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E2C0F4839F34EDE88A59DE23193F295"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicable law</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The operation and use of an armed unmanned aerial vehicle shall be subject to the requirements of title 10 of the United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCD59341395E74823A2C8D712D9B87CE4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rules of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this section shall be construed—</text><paragraph id="HE972E1B241BC412DA8CF8BA14B96FC6A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to limit or expand any authority of any component of the Federal Government to provide advice, including intelligence, to the Department of Defense in support of actions described in paragraphs (1) and (2) of subsection (a); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE01646CA92954FAF879FF64C873DC1E7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to create any authority, or expand any existing authority, for the Federal Government to kill any person.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H71B162CC557342A1A5458EEE6C3B3D32"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Unmanned aerial vehicle</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>unmanned aerial vehicle</term> means an aircraft that is operated without the possibility of direct human intervention from within or on the aircraft. The term includes aircraft referred to as a drone, UAV, unmanned aircraft (UA), unmanned aerial system (UAS), remotely piloted aircraft (RPA), remotely piloted vehicle (RPV), remotely operated aircraft (ROA), and unmanned aerial vehicle system (UAVS).</text></subsection><subsection id="H146E1BB5A6A842E9B5C1266C4F06DE85"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall take effect 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

