<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2A88D0EA9EF84458BAB51E661FE1B6CE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3202 IH: Assad Regime Anti-Normalization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3202</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000600">Mrs. Radewagen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit any official action to recognize or normalize relations with any Government of Syria that is led by Bashar al-Assad, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB67E888F94234519BD65F045C5215265" style="OLC"><section id="H14C51DE6EEA94906997303808E9E7DD3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Assad Regime Anti-Normalization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H21ABB0AB9C644A3D96E700ECD30769E8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modifications to the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act</header><subsection id="HC1B35BB1800B4A96A3B7AD0FE696D3C6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 7412 of the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019 (title LXXIV of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8791">22 U.S.C. 8791</external-xref> note) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC1C5558018FE4528B2AFFC9A9830CC92"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="HECBE9A1B398F4C0295C953824861EB88"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>with respect to a foreign person if the President determines that the foreign person, on or after such date of enactment, knowingly engages in an activity described in paragraph (2).</quote> and inserting </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFE2D0BE5DD3E4E6AA93A9DCBE94A4C2C" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text>with respect to a foreign person that the President determines—</text><subparagraph id="H41008080AA954D99A77115A33F6E6190"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly engages, on or after such date of enactment, in an activity described in paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2AF43E5F6B064B9EAFCCFE9C5DFA5252"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is an adult family member of a foreign person described in subparagraph (A); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB84676BAA387491FAAB3D4F33D7137A0"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is owned or controlled by a foreign person described in subparagraph (A) or (B).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCD4B9E06CFE40B59D41A343F54B4FF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H2779823A176542C98648C5D8E61D611A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="HCDFAD5E5D20D427A9E5A85559023C4BA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by amending clause (i) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H66BEEAE6394C44BE9E879A4399993169" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H5654187372FA42DF9E2AE8EE891A656F"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Government of Syria (including any entity owned or controlled by the Government of Syria), a senior political figure of the Government of Syria, a member of the People’s Assembly of Syria, or a senior foreign political figure (as such term is defined in section 101.605 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations) of the Arab Socialist Ba’ath Party of Syria, including any such senior foreign political figure who is—</text><subclause id="H01BB76B514194F688C10D3608402F375"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a member of the Central Command, Central Committee, or Auditing and Inspection Committee of such Party; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H90005E4178C940F8BD0495958E1B99EF"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a leader of a local branch of such Party;</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause><subclause id="HD32CCD64D45442A2B561A0AC35BB02C6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subclause><subclause id="HB0E96CA8ED3744098466ED45BF53B916"><enum>(III)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking the semicolon and inserting <quote>; or</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H69B233F07CAC4A9DAAAB9C85E45763DC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following new clause:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC133F8360BBB4DD8903D7BB4016F1871" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H08BE54B1BB4B45E68E299AF80D459112"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Syria Arab Airlines, Cham Wings, or any foreign person owned or controlled by Syria Arab Airlines or Cham Wings;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="HBF7049B31CCC49F4BC4D08E98F4D9F4D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by amending subparagraph (C) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H67211086F2AF42A88E213FE862BAF6C5" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H0627131BDF2647B7A763D5106FF2C5F7"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> knowingly sells or provides aircraft or spare aircraft parts—</text><clause id="HF3B46DA3F7714323B7C94DE48E674BE5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to the Government of Syria; or</text></clause><clause id="H1CB6E418BBC346629BF7ABD3AE3698C5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for or on behalf of the Government of Syria to any foreign person operating in an area directly or indirectly controlled by the Government of Syria or foreign forces associated with the Government of Syria;</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause id="H987AC8031CD64B59B359FB50CC05535A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (D), by striking <quote>; or</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></clause><clause id="H1ABECA61DEE649DBA945218AD9CF4BB6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (E)—</text><subclause id="H51AA67FDD2EC4949A32D5BC1972A21CF"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>construction or engineering services</quote> and inserting <quote>financial, construction, or engineering services</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HE2944C51D13146C7A572B7DC861040E0"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking the closing period and inserting a semicolon; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HF0EE3DE683EB48B8BB237058F7F0DDE0"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraphs:</text><quoted-block id="H1FED9668C9EB4FFABA5C69CE78168B9C" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H8CECF0085528483A96281C4D98CBDC67" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly engages in or directs— </text><clause id="HA9374A4BF74440A3933B0D4F43E09D9A" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the diversion of goods (including agricultural commodities, food, medicine, and medical devices), or any international humanitarian assistance, intended for the people of Syria; or</text></clause><clause id="H62FA0DADAC2A4D619F88B1B91178FDCB" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the dealing in proceeds from the sale or resale of such diverted goods or international humanitarian assistance, as the case may be;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD3C3FA4A81C847D8B84DEBEDBD19D3DF"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly, directly or indirectly, engages in or attempts to engage in, the seizure, confiscation, theft, or expropriation for personal gain or political purposes of property, including real property, in Syria or owned by a citizen of Syria;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE2E028E7AFD4AA9839CE74D0E4E6F87"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly, directly or indirectly, engages in or attempts to engage in a transaction or transactions for or with such seized, confiscated, stolen, or expropriated property described in subparagraph (G); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H556CAFF1C5F64BD08F9CA60E3395D1A3"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly provides significant financial, material, or technological support to a foreign person engaging in an activity described in any of subparagraphs (A) through (H).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC9F6A61FFE7C4E70B281A14BCDBB3BBC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block id="H36113069F9944FA0B456A295E1687CE3" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H4E681235BB4644E0A558A62B82879E3C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Transaction defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of the determination required by subparagraph (a)(2)(A), the term <quote>transaction</quote> includes in-kind transactions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA851EB0DE826424D9550991DB3412BD5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Significant transaction clarified</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term ‘significant transaction’ includes any natural gas, electricity, or other energy-related transaction, without regard to whether such transaction was authorized by a license or regulation issued prior the date of the enactment of this paragraph pursuant to section 203 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1702">50 U.S.C. 1702</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBE7E1A0A3B4432FB8BA5B1F61CBD423"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block id="H0321B74415134F8C83B1558F07D93DFC" style="OLC"><subsection id="HFA5F0568C2F5401B823BFED3998B9979"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Congressional requests</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after receiving a request from the chairman and ranking member of one of the appropriate congressional committees with respect to whether a foreign person knowingly engages in an activity described in subsection (a)(2) the President shall—</text><paragraph id="H1B63FF624A0446BD83267F0180254FC4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make the determination specified in subsection (a)(1) with respect to that foreign person; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C7C61A53DC549F8B5AF9C780763320E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to such chairman and ranking member that submitted the request a report with respect to such determination that includes a statement of whether the President has imposed or intends to impose the sanctions described in subsection (b) with respect to that foreign person.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8EE20EC626F5460EB25774646E76226D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Removal of exception relating to importation of goods</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019, as amended by subsection (a), is further amended—</text><paragraph id="H9A5B6718F1AB447AB7FA7380BB1B554F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking section 7434; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H07457C6FC98248FCA0F07AB713916BDD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 7435 through 7438 as sections 7434 through 7437, respectively.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA51C5A7A89DF4412BCA0C3CFC25ABFB0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Determination with respect to Syria Trust for Development</header><paragraph id="HEB9385B47E314E01A0A032762BAFC5EB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 120 days after the enactment of this Act, the President shall—</text><subparagraph id="H78EABA482DEA478BBACCEC546076678E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determine whether the nonprofit organization chaired by Asma Al-Assad, the First Lady of Syria, known as the <quote>Syria Trust for Development</quote> meets the criteria for the imposition of sanctions under section 7412(a) of the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019, as amended by subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07AC49666F8345E6B08E5D5A5878860E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate congressional committees such determination, including a justification for the determination. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A4C3C6BE0FB4A3F9629D0D2664E0A8B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The determination under paragraph (1)(B) shall be submitted in unclassified form, but the justification specified in such paragraph may be included in a classified annex. The unclassified determination shall be made available on a publicly available website of the Federal government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H54B8D133EA5B4655BD7FE324A3876597"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H37DD1BEDBB6F4F8BA495A9E571EC5446"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, and the Committee on Financial Services of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20C509EC9B1640EFAC960CB0EE72ABDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services, the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H68C3725D8690478CA35B91AC5871D489"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Findings on applicability with respect to Syrian Arab Airlines, Cham Wings Airlines, and related entities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H1A6BB8F603554759A249F27C4239F111"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2013, the President identified Syrian Arab Airlines as a blocked instrumentality or controlled entity of the Government of Syria and concurrently sanctioned Syrian Arab Airlines pursuant to Executive Order 13224 for acting for or on behalf of the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps-Qods Force of Iran.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H972BAD09BE594B9C8C1C00A7C28E632E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2016, the President sanctioned Syria-based Cham Wings Airlines pursuant to Executive Order 13582 for having materially assisted, sponsored, or provided financial, material, or technological support for, or goods or services in support of, the Government of Syria and Syrian Arab Airlines.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4C78B1185B641DD8DC44E2C376D991A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 7412(a)(2)(A)(iii) of the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8791">22 U.S.C. 8791</external-xref> note) mandates the application of sanctions against any foreign person that <quote>knowingly provides significant financial, material, or technological support to, or knowingly engages in a significant transaction with … a foreign person subject to sanctions pursuant to the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) with respect to Syria or any other provision of law that imposes sanctions with respect to Syria,</quote>, which applies to airport service providers outside of Syria.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H04E380C58034440884BA98A4741C9463" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, or the application of such provision to any person or circumstance, is found to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, or the application of that provision to other persons or circumstances, shall not be affected. </text></subsection></section><section id="H0A82106AFED24853AE01B2BD7D63673E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition of recognition of Assad regime</header><subsection id="HF74E05ED356F4FC98CE1F866E0C357B8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States—</text><paragraph id="H9DA4E8EC87974BF98F6B6F1D86044165"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not to recognize or normalize relations with any Government of Syria that is led by Bashar al-Assad due to the Assad regime’s ongoing crimes against the Syrian people, including failure to meet the criteria outlined in section 7431(a) of the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0A817D2736A446FB2434389DE534AE7"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to actively oppose recognition or normalization of relations by other governments with any Government of Syria that is led by Bashar Al-Assad, including by fully implementing the mandatory primary and secondary sanctions in the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019 and Executive Order 13894; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H684F023470D8407BA6A707ACFDF9B7FD"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to use the full range of authorities, including those provided under the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019 and Executive Order 13894, to deter reconstruction activities in areas under the control of Bashar al-Assad.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0110F16DD1C5441EABE743D2A4CFD8E9"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In accordance with subsection (a), no Federal official or employee may take any action, and no Federal funds may be made available, to recognize or otherwise imply, in any manner, United States recognition of Bashar al-Assad or any Government in Syria that is led by Bashar al-Assad.</text></subsection></section><section id="H68665D3C77C74BAD9D24DA020CF5E7B2"><enum>4.</enum><header>Interagency strategy to counter normalization with Assad regime</header><subsection id="H27D991DB68B14160A72E21535C3047A4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report and strategy required</header><paragraph id="H1AD0D3A199E341D18CC2D5488E55F0F3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for a period not to exceed 5 years, the Secretary of State (in consultation with the Secretary of the Treasury, the Administrator of the Drug Enforcement Administration, and the heads of other appropriate Federal departments and agencies) shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report and strategy to describe and counter actions taken or planned by foreign governments to normalize, engage with, or upgrade political, diplomatic, or economic ties with the regime led by Bashar al-Assad in Syria (in this section referred to as the <quote>Assad regime</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55D45622A8CA4481A7CBFFE01D72F6D1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>The elements of the report under paragraph (1) shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H7F00449CD72E4F5080596A1C92717F1F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of violations of international law and human rights abuses committed by Bashar al-Assad, the Government of the Russian Federation, or the Government of Iran and progress towards justice and accountability for the Syrian people;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H007758C78D6A4454B61ACE6C9BB2B3BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full list of diplomatic meetings at the Ambassador level or above, between the Syrian regime and any representative of the Governments of Turkey, the United Arab Emirates, Egypt, Jordan, Iraq, Oman, Bahrain, Kuwait, the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, Tunisia, Algeria, Morocco, Libya, or Lebanon, respectively;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA2C337E426B94D17BDED876A97596E28"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full list of transactions, including investments, grants, contracts, or donations (including loans or other extension of credit), exceeding $50,000 in areas of Syria held by the Assad regime by any persons from Turkey, the United Arab Emirates, Egypt, Jordan, Iraq, Oman, Bahrain, Kuwait, the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, Tunisia, Algeria, Morocco, Libya, or Lebanon;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21BF90B1037149DA87B1BFC8E1AAAF03"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for each item on the list identified in subparagraph (C), a determination of whether such transaction subjects any of the parties to the transaction to sanctions under the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019, as amended by section 2; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H87CEF6EA1EA249D8A9971AE01BD6F1F1"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the steps the United States is taking to actively deter recognition or normalization of relations by other governments with the Assad regime, including specific diplomatic engagements and use of economic sanctions authorized by statutes or implemented through Executive Orders, including—</text><clause id="HE85AA42D9CB74F86B8C0770649B34275"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Caesar Syria Civilian Protection Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8791">22 U.S.C. 8791</external-xref> note);</text></clause><clause id="H76D2D1713BA548D2A3CF1EC077243A7F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Syria Accountability and Lebanese Sovereignty Restoration Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151">22 U.S.C. 2151</external-xref> note);</text></clause><clause id="HA5554D44899444C8B910FFD993D3B59A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8501">22 U.S.C. 8501 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H937783BDB0B246CA9914BDA0D5982DCA"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Executive Order 13894 (84 Fed. Reg. 55851; relating to blocking property and suspending entry of certain persons contributing to the situation in Syria);</text></clause><clause id="HDF066884E9D342D389DA9C2E3EB0F078"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the Global Magnitsky Human Rights Accountability Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/10101">22 U.S.C. 10101 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></clause><clause id="H7BA42854ECBF42BFA04277A010D0CC9D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the Countering American Adversaries through Sanctions Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/9401">22 U.S.C. 9401 et seq.</external-xref>); and</text></clause><clause id="H8D8272B6F5A34FC5A3BC7D29810BFEDD"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the Foreign Narcotics Kingpin Designation Act; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H919F96F2439D48F4A87C19274D8940F0"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of how recognition or normalization of relations by other governments with the Assad regime impacts the national security of the United States, prospects for implementation of the United Nations Security Council Resolution 2254, prospects for justice and accountability for war crimes in Syria, and the benefits derived by the Government of the Russian Federation or the Government of Iran.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6FC6FBFF90C549EC87C5ACD89F6CB700"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Scope</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The initial report required by subsection (a) shall address the period beginning on January 1, 2021, and ending on the date of the enactment of this Act, and each subsequent report shall address the one-year period following the conclusion of the scope of the prior report.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7ED47A1085EF4245995A0ACB9CC9EA46"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report under subsection (a) shall be submitted in an unclassified form, but may contain a classified annex. The unclassified section of such a report shall be made publicly available on a website of the United States Federal Government.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCDBC7BD6F3BB4AA4B30B80415ECDBA6A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="H54BD768BD48D44E1B3334A7AA4A60195"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCE308557092B4F029EE84A316A4366D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on the Judiciary, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Appropriations, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HA4C11FA008534BFCBD0D376E4D685B31"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reports on manipulation of United Nations by Assad regime in Syria</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for a period not to exceed 5 years, the Secretary of State, shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report on the manipulation of the United Nations by the regime led by Bashar al-Assad in Syria (in this section referred to as the <quote>Assad regime</quote>), including—</text><paragraph id="H010EAB67E5064096A363DF3AC092597F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of conditions, both explicit and implicit, set by the Assad regime with respect to United Nations operations in Syria including with respect to implementing partners, hiring practices, allocation of grants and contracts, and procurement of goods and services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0DD64C409A34DE893434A3688B851F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the extent to which the United Nations has rejected or otherwise opposed any of the conditions described in paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1929FE28D69F4E7FA99BE7CED4420105"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an identification of officials or employees of the United Nations (including funds, programs and specialized agencies of the United Nations) with ties to the Assad regime, including family ties, or persons designated for sanctions by United Nations donor countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3665CA3D39654BB69694419AE0059D5E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a full account of access restrictions imposed by the Assad regime and the overall impact on the ability of the United Nations to deliver international assistance to target beneficiaries in areas outside regime control;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84B1F7F2F66A49B994F1776E54492169"><enum>(5)</enum><text>a description of ways in which United Nations aid improperly benefits the Assad regime and its associates in defiance of basic humanitarian principles;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4685AC60F874F82ACF66970843BC9D9"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of the due diligence mechanisms and vetting procedures in place to ensure entities contracted by the United Nations to ensure goods, supplies, or services provided Syria do not have links to the Assad regime, known human rights abusers, or persons designated for sanctions by United Nations donor countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E8383DA16C743D59A2FE47E55ADC3BA"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an identification of entities affiliated with the Assad regime, including the Syria Trust for Development and the Syrian Arab Red Crescent, foreign government ministries, and private corporations owned or controlled directly or indirectly by the Assad regime, that have received United Nations funding, contracts, or grants or have otherwise entered into a formalized partnership with the United Nations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41558CC3A44E46BEAF8AA5F5D72BD17E"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of how the Assad regime sets arbitrary or punitive exchange rates to extract funding from the United Nations, as well as the total amount extracted by such means;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H06080EC0FA3A46D494D3658F887F4C8B"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an assessment of the degree to which the various forms of manipulation described in this section has resulted in compromises of the humanitarian principles of humanity, neutrality, impartiality, and independence of the United Nations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28491DEFE9174A809CF080240812C61B"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a strategy to reduce the ability of the Assad regime to manipulate or otherwise influence the United Nations and other aid operations in Syria and ensure United States and international aid is delivered in a neutral and impartial manner consistent with basic humanitarian principles. </text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

