<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4B4FAEC8F4514B8FAA7DCE1132F3902B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2920 IH: Statutes of Limitation for Child Sexual Abuse Reform Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2920</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230426">April 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Child Abuse Protection and Treatment Act to incentivize States to eliminate civil and criminal statutes of limitations and revive time-barred civil claims for child abuse cases, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFCCA8042F60A4919AF879A28F7CCD79A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HB8EF987300EC45D8B5DD3518FE528A41" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Statutes of Limitation for Child Sexual Abuse Reform Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H82E17231C859480EA569E948A60FBD05"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H1C72F12B44634941B19BB739D5D143E5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Child sexual abuse is a pernicious crime perpetrated through threats of violence, intimidation, manipulation, and abuse of power.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDE3918A2A5884BE79CD929A1ADC81C8C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The prevalence of child sexual abuse is difficult to determine because it is often not reported; however, data suggests that child sexual abuse is a public health epidemic that affects 1 in 5 girls, and 1 in 13 boys in the Nation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H64D318FB009B426797A81FE0B9C853D3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The prevalence of child sex trafficking is difficult to estimate, but the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children (NCMEC) reports receiving more than 19,000 reports of child sex trafficking in 2022.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA3F301D5C2F492DBE713DDC43AED1C8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>It is estimated that there are approximately 7 million cases of child abuse and maltreatment reported every year in the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB60B248C64D046A1BD2F836EA55F7D4A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Historically, nearly 90 percent of child victims never go to the authorities and the vast majority of claims have expired before the victims were capable of getting to court.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAA44622376964E87A00C85461EFB4D43"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Due to the subversive nature of this crime, the average age of disclosure of child sexual abuse does not occur until a victim is over 52 years old.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3EFFBB081CA843D398318E4B16897F00"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Because many State statutes of limitations applicable to laws involving child sexual abuse fail to give victims adequate time to come forward and report their abuse, numerous victims are unable to seek fair and just remediation against their abusers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8A9DB3CFA59B457797356770E6F4978A"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Due to the especially heinous nature of child sexual abuse, it is imperative that perpetrators of this crime are punished, prevented from reoffending, and victims have the opportunity to see their abusers brought to justice.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8751905600244D45BC59C306D8848416"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The negative effects over a survivor’s lifetime generate many costs that impact the Nation’s health care, education, criminal justice, and welfare systems, with the economic burden of child sexual abuse estimated at nearly $2 trillion annually.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HE41886E3C92F4ADBAE2FE41D05B8D79D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Elimination of State statutes of limitations for child abuse cases</header> <subsection id="H78C1824229D842008F1177060C3C6D98"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 107(e)(1) of the Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5106c">42 U.S.C. 5106c(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H294C7EA330F944A597D5DDB7DCBC244C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE0D6633147644F71AD78FFD5E69A8772"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBCD39056C8B24039AA33551BF83D2AFD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC2ADD45CACAB4EB3983935009816543F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <subparagraph id="H48F0C7AE99B74B86A75547EBE9BC29F5"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">elimination of State civil and criminal statutes of limitations laws for child sexual abuse, exploitation, and sex trafficking, and adoption of laws reviving previously time-barred civil claims for child sexual abuse, exploitation, and sex trafficking. </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HDF40E6F4AFD941F0856AA50BD88FC51A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 111(b) of the Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5106g">42 U.S.C. 5106g(b)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE3855220709D4D6EA090C1373610B694" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="HAE859B3BC202465CAB14AEB1155F795E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Child sexual abuse and exploitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of section 107(e)(1)(D), the term <term>child sexual abuse and exploitation</term> shall include an act or a failure to act on the part of a parent, caretaker, or any other person.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H904C16158E174562A12032B225D91091"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grants for eliminating certain statutes of limitation</header> 
<subsection id="H5ADFEFEE1F9C426E9D6FF237B92B63B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Health and Human Services may make grants to States that are eligible to receive an award under section 107 of the Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5106c">42 U.S.C. 5106c</external-xref>) achieve one or more of the following reforms:</text> <paragraph id="H8BDF99D01B574B4F83CB6B3F3DDA1CC8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The elimination of all State civil statutes of limitations for claims of, related to, or arising from, child sexual abuse, exploitation, and sex trafficking, against perpetrators, other individuals, and public and private entities. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H58BD61B447FF45AFAB63DBAC6314F941"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The elimination of all State criminal statutes of limitations for all felony and misdemeanor sex crimes against children, including sexual abuse, exploitation, and trafficking, and for inchoate offenses related to such sex crimes, including attempt, conspiracy, solicitation, and aiding and abetting.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF6C977686FF943C294D15D7FF53BA29D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The revival of previously time-barred civil claims for child sexual abuse, exploitation, and sex trafficking against perpetrators, other individuals, and public and private entities, which, at a minimum, permits previously time-barred claims a 2-year period or until a victim reaches age 55, whichever is longer.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7B592D1082D0486880D1887DDB8336A8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Allocation</header><text>Of the funds made available to carry out this section—</text> <paragraph id="H0F1DBAD318554046B0F9CD09587F219A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">25 percent shall be for States that achieve one of the reforms described in paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (a);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD7A051AFEDFC461F8C7DE43ED8CB608B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">35 percent shall be for States that achieve two of such reforms; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF77C0BDDFEF436DB999B6EDF65F54E4"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">40 percent shall be for States that achieve three of such reforms. </text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">An award under this section shall be in addition to any funds for which the State is otherwise eligible to receive under section 107 of the Child Abuse Prevention and Treatment Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5106c">42 U.S.C. 5106c</external-xref>). </continuation-text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAEFC95E634994EA68F29A8117672AB86"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $20,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2031.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H109A389DEB894453A92FBC3A172BDCA7"><enum>5.</enum><header>Technical correction</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1404A of the Victims of Crime Act of 1984 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/34/20103">34 U.S.C. 20103</external-xref>), by striking <quote>section 109</quote> and insert <quote>section 107</quote>.</text></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

