<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H51D4A42E1DE94B8EB1F72FF082B612BD" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3666 IH: Stop Our Scourge Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3666</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000597">Mr. Garbarino</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001052">Mr. Harris</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000302">Mr. Joyce of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Homeland Security to designate illicit fentanyl as a weapon of mass destruction, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H888B1E4EBFB54747A0BFCEF1F41440D3" style="OLC"><section id="H78ADD6B4C35E442C85FBD7A07E756A0C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stop Our Scourge Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SOS Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC3AAF545EB694441A8D32EFA92AA0BF8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Designation of fentanyl as a weapon of mass destruction</header><subsection id="H3588D66854D9405A9FEEC54026EA77A0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall designate illicit fentanyl as a weapon of mass destruction for purposes of title XIX of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/590">6 U.S.C. 590 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H9B91E56657CA40F5A77E7B41D7291EF8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>illicit fentanyl</term> means fentanyl and any analogue thereof that is manufactured, distributed, or dispensed, or possessed with intent to manufacture, distribute, or dispense, in violation of section 401, 406, or 416 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/841">21 U.S.C. 841</external-xref>, 846, 856).</text></subsection></section><section id="HE5A902152C184489880D3A3DEA659963"><enum>3.</enum><header>Assessment regarding illicit fentanyl</header><subsection id="H04BC299D611D4D74981BA293B8C29689"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The head of the Office of National Drug Control Policy, in consultation with the heads of such other Federal agencies as the head of the Office of National Drug Control Policy deems appropriate, shall conduct an assessment of the following:</text><paragraph id="HE863469D2C36445098731F09366A84E1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Foreign manufacturing of illicit fentanyl.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBAFBA89B326A471E87EB9C895B370CFC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The tools and capabilities across Federal agencies to address trafficking of illicit fentanyl.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECD0C9F06A81480FACC5868F8F633438"><enum>(3)</enum><text>How coordination of Federal efforts to address such trafficking can be improved, including identification of duplicative Federal efforts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A523FD1B31D4D86902431442BD62C8D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The capacities of the Mexican military to conduct counterdrug missions with respect to illicit fentanyl.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59AF16A3736B49A2994AB885CE8D289C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The capacities and willingness of the People’s Republic of China to curtail the flow of illicit fentanyl, conduct inspections and investigations with respect to illicit fentanyl, screen for illicit fentanyl at ports of exit, implement <quote>know-your-customer</quote> standards, and hold traffickers of illicit fentanyl accountable.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7234628E0B82432486D783DE1C76CE33"><enum>(6)</enum><text><italic></italic>Illicit fentanyl being trafficked into the United States from Mexico, including the purity, formulation, and weight of the illicit fentanyl.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB33CEFFFEC9A45BCA373C9D7B6C264FB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Timing; report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the head of the Office of National Drug Control Policy shall—</text><paragraph id="H72BDD889A21F4427A1723EFA8A833CB8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>complete the assessment required by subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D5688C36CE54E4B9CEE6AEFB8808A69"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit a report to the Congress on the results of such assessment.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB5F17D29FAB04C20B82F8F9332FB1241"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>illicit fentanyl</term> means fentanyl and any analogue or precursor thereof that is manufactured, distributed, or dispensed, or possessed with intent to manufacture, distribute, or dispense, in violation of section 401, 406, or 416 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/841">21 U.S.C. 841</external-xref>, 846, 856).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

