<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0C483E8BA9264E668D6F0B6983F11663" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 846 IH: Debt Explanation Before Taxwriters Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 846</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230206">February 6, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001199">Mr. Smucker</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 31, United States Code, to require the Secretary of the Treasury to appear before Congress before the debt limit is reached or extraordinary measures are taken to prevent default.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H7DEFFAB69DF54E039C83B433B0636213" style="OLC">
<section id="H5484A7FF19694EC3A3DBDDB87D480F20" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Debt Explanation Before Taxwriters Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>DEBT Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H5EDF97AB1D26441FAF30E5916F2679D5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Secretary of Treasury appearance before Congress before reaching debt limit or extraordinary measures taken</header> <subsection id="H2EE9A47366484E88995F452305847B0A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HAC981D43EC7B4C2BA2E0BEFCC9FD92C1" style="USC">
<section id="H40C805003BDB4A76A85725A9467AC98B"><enum>3131.</enum><header>Secretary of Treasury appearance before Congress before reaching debt limit or extraordinary measures taken</header>
<subsection id="H0927D32F428B401EA463F6D96034C098"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not more than sixty days and not less than twenty-one days prior to any date on which the Secretary of the Treasury anticipates either that the public debt will reach the limit specified under section 3101, as modified by section 3101A, or that extraordinary measures will be taken to prevent the United States from defaulting on its obligations, the Secretary shall appear before the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Finance of the Senate, to submit a detailed explanation of—</text> <paragraph id="HE42C232EF7F74F108F1CF3F29B7F2160"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any extraordinary measures the Secretary will take to fund Federal government obligations prior to such increase and an estimate of the administrative cost of taking such extraordinary measures; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1B096C3FE7C24C41A2EDA885A1604F30"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any reversal of such measures, and any other changes taken in the funding of Federal government obligations, as a result of such increase.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCC19D0A4A2A84F6795CC1FFD0F6A8AF4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Extraordinary measures defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this section, the term <quote>extraordinary measures</quote> means each of the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HAD92CC46EF09437AA65FAB1EB1676B96"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Suspending sales of State and Local Government Series Treasury securities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B5EA749013F416AA36599A29C1348DF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Redeeming existing, and suspending new, investments of the Civil Service Retirement and Disability Fund and the Postal Service Retiree Health Benefits Fund.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H22086E4EAB304F7D8090B382572CCAEF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Suspending reinvestment of the Government Securities Investment Fund.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5D3C5AEEEA004259BA1D019A317CE6AD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Suspending reinvestment of the Exchange Stabilization Fund.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H056F771290C64B89872CD4D74FF9A25C" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Directing or approving the issuance of debt by the Federal Financing Bank for the purpose of entering into an exchange transaction for debt that is subject to the limit under this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1BA94FDD1CB6444EBD87087C5C28B932" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Suspending investments in the Government Securities Investment Fund of the Thrift Savings Fund.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H05B4A3D32DFE451F891664205225D0D1" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Suspending investments in the stabilization fund established under section 5302 of title 31, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2588AE05C0E0433F95D14C3D412E448B" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Suspending new investments in the Civil Service Retirement and Disability Fund or the Postal Service Retiree Health Benefits Fund.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H44679F0AB0D84FD9866FA242EC20DF7E" commented="no"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Selling or redeeming securities, obligations, or other invested assets of the Civil Service Retirement and Disability Fund or the Postal Service Retiree Health Benefits Fund before maturity.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H261625320814424FA67EAD043881C445"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/31">chapter 31</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/3130">section 3130</external-xref> the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H152D01A8020248AA86499E137B148E04" style="USC">
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration">
<toc-entry level="section">3131. Secretary of Treasury appearance before Congress before reaching debt limit or extraordinary measures taken.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


