<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD2303D8244254530A0485D4CB6238845" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5383 IH: Giving Increased Variety to Ensure Milk Into the Lives of Kids Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5383</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 to allow certain participants in the special supplemental nutrition program for women, infants, and children to elect to be issued a variety of types of milk, including whole milk, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H474E94A959B24B5091C3EA759F8EC67E" style="OLC">
<section id="HF570D34F5E704C92B776256CC7D63D33" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Giving Increased Variety to Ensure Milk Into the Lives of Kids Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>GIVE MILK Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H8B90A2754DDE486F926F05A60C2C9C4F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="H05578A41769C46889882E67DBE3835EE"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Most Americans, including most children and adolescents, do not consume adequate levels of dairy, on average consuming only about half of the recommended amounts of dairy foods daily.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H39EBE8958DA944D1AD1930063DDE202F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Milk is a source of many nutrients essential to health, and is the leading source of calcium, vitamin D, potassium, and phosphorus for children ages 2–18 and is a source of thirteen essential nutrients (calcium, phosphorus, vitamin A, vitamin D (in fortified products), riboflavin, niacin, vitamin B12, protein, potassium, zinc, choline, magnesium, and selenium) in the diets of children and adolescents, including three nutrients of public health concern: vitamin D, calcium, and potassium.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD0B190079F704AF2817ED9C67D6126D8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Dairy foods are associated with improved bone health, a lower risk of type 2 diabetes, a beneficial or neutral effect on blood pressure, and may help reduce the risk of cardiovascular disease, coronary heart disease, and stroke.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCE71948A3CD34B09AE8B0A926D6AC126"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a September 2019 report on beverage recommendations for early childhood, the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics, American Academy of Pediatric Dentists, American Academy of Pediatrics, and the American Heart Association found that—</text>
<subparagraph id="H95FC5BF640334295AB61D9A4A24129E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">medical professionals are in agreement that whole milk is good for childhood development between ages one and two;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HADBB8B2B6CDB4BCC93CB92797AC8D9C1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>skim and low-fat milk are recommended for young children;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9E7EC6CD9E6F4171A2D8FC0156514537"><enum>(C)</enum><text>plant-based, non-dairy milks are not recommended for young children; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H55A6D97515174D9B9A0758947C1C40A8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an expert panel under the study recognized that there has been recent research and discussion regarding the role of dairy fat in healthy dietary patterns but in the absence of clear evidence justifying a departure from current recommendations, such expert panel chose to remain consistent with current guidance recommending whole milk for most children ages 12–24 months and fat-free (skim) or low-fat (1 percent) milk for children ages 2 years and older.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HAC7827B417F04DCFB22CC9502AA2CD04" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The 2020 through 2025 Dietary Guidelines for Americans recommendation of the number of dairy servings for young children is—</text> <subparagraph id="HF45B997726C945679DD46208D1832EE2" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>1.5 to 2 servings for 12 to 23 months; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H686C241D78664A5CB1F19A41B5D2096A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>2 to 2.5 servings for 2 to 4 years.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> <section id="HF6E3306AA84546C3B5411C49429944CE"><enum>3.</enum><header>WIC election for type of milk</header> <subsection id="HDD870658663E4CFC97553243B6D137AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Election for type of milk</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 17(f) of the Child Nutrition Act of 1966 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1786">42 U.S.C. 1786(f)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H63FEFF379766480CB285882E7E62E4BE" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<paragraph id="H20E06516D2FE465CBAA76D18AFE5A88B"><enum>(27)</enum><header>Election for type of milk</header>
<subparagraph id="HFB2EA17DB2E346FE8205B5205A0E6016"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, in the case of an individual participating in the program authorized by this section who is issued milk by the Secretary, such individual (or the parent or guardian of such individual) may elect to be issued nonfat milk, low-fat milk, reduced fat milk, or whole milk.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H526D241724874845A520B05F4BCE7178"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Election</header><text>The Secretary shall issue the type of milk elected by an individual under subparagraph (A) to such individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="HC9E050C954F445379FAEE40381219DF3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Revision of regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture shall revise regulations in accordance with the amendments made by this section, including revision of section 246.10 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations. </text></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

