<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB1766AAE21CE4254A36DE33230F16358" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 2894 IH: Block Nuclear Launch by Autonomous Artificial Intelligence Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2894</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230426">April 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the use of Federal funds to launch a nuclear weapon using an autonomous weapons system that is not subject to meaningful human control, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB36F5B1F3F2540D5829DB2A2EB91C4DB" style="OLC"><section id="H37728FFECA5C4552AEAE489DBBC1264B" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Block Nuclear Launch by Autonomous Artificial Intelligence Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA2F8C8708CFA4077AD05AFB6CC028259"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H3163A825E35A457AA85F561CC059A900"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Department of Defense Directive 3000.09 defines <quote>autonomous weapons system</quote> as a weapons system that, once activated, can select and engage targets without further intervention by an operator.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H16F1AC2BABC14DEFB13A4784C300CF4A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Article 3, clause 8 of the United Nations Convention on Certain Conventional Weapons prohibits the indiscriminate use of weapons, which is defined as <quote>any placement of such weapons … which may be expected to cause incidental loss of civilian life, injury to civilians, damage to civilian objects, or a combination thereof, which would be excessive in relation to the concrete and direct military advantage anticipated</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCD819A9FEDC4C7897FA1C86F8733790"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 5.10 of the Department of Defense Law of War Manual states <quote>[c]ommanders, at all levels, have a great responsibility to exercise the leadership necessary to reduce the risk of harm to civilians and civilian objects</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H60721DE7AF2A4581BC99389ACF9FFCEC"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In a report on autonomous weapons systems published on December 1, 2021, Human Rights Watch and the International Human Rights Clinic of Harvard Law School argue that <quote>[r]obots lack the compassion, empathy, mercy, and judgment necessary to treat humans humanely, and they cannot understand the inherent worth of human life</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1857893DE18F495DB8F88454730C1E8D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The 2022 Nuclear Posture Review states <quote>[i]n all cases, the United States will maintain a human <quote>in the loop</quote> for all actions critical to informing and executing decisions by the President to initiate and terminate nuclear weapon employment</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1E89D48436574C07A007010F20527676"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The National Security Commission on Artificial Intelligence, established by Congress pursuant to section 1051 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/232">Public Law 115–232</external-xref>), recommends that the United States <quote>clearly and publicly affirm existing U.S. policy that only human beings can authorize employment of nuclear weapons and seek similar commitments from Russia and China</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H273FB0DD036146849A96CED49679CD5C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>On February 16, 2023, the Department of State issued a Political Declaration on Responsible Military Use of Artificial Intelligence and Autonomy, which includes the following statement: <quote>States should maintain human control and involvement for all actions critical to informing and executing sovereign decisions concerning nuclear weapons</quote>. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31023CBDBC0B40D4BA9F5FD7663FC03B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Large-scale nuclear war would lead to the deaths of millions of people, firestorms, radioactive fallout contamination, agricultural failure, and catastrophic climate results.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADB6E64C943A4D57B39D98204C2B1818"><enum>(9)</enum><text>To comply with international humanitarian law, human control and human legal judgment are essential in the nuclear command and control process.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE8B9D0CF120A448C8B857445242F1A38"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H4F6907C3239C429B8FEA1BF2D22398C4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the use of lethal, autonomous nuclear weapons systems that are not subject to meaningful human control cannot properly adhere to international humanitarian law; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2105B0601C44476A1358224222DD12A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any decision to launch any nuclear weapon should not be made by artificial intelligence.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB9BA93BE52FC4F88A4A93DDE09B2DA65"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibition on use of Federal funds to deploy nuclear weapons with autonomous weapons systems not subject to meaningful human control</header><subsection id="HDC0D25DA0C074AC996E27C79CDA65637"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">None of the funds authorized to be appropriated or otherwise made available for any fiscal year may be obligated or expended to use an autonomous weapons system that is not subject to meaningful human control to—</text><paragraph id="H2E71D7983E604BBC89C1A32F2BCD9057"><enum>(1)</enum><text>launch a nuclear weapon; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB66C37626D7C4B56948FEE7005B4015B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>select or engage targets for the purposes of launching a nuclear weapon. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0B640EEF2CEE4328822B614A7BD2B7E4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HB24AD39CD45C401298A1397EB8798328"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>autonomous weapons system</quote> has the meaning given such term in Department of Defense Directive 3000.09, titled <quote>Autonomy in Weapons Systems</quote> as in effect on the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD781345C72F746869821729D53510D12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>meaningful human control</quote> means, with respect to an autonomous weapons system, human control of—</text><subparagraph id="H870E8C1C66774835B217FC3A09AB6C2C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the selection and engagement of targets; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB81F38DE3E541FF9D85F0CDF0C86827"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the time, location, and manner of use.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

