<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5E8C6A69954C47F6B1B3BBFE9E422DDC" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5816 IH: Eviction Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5816</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230928">September 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an Office of Eviction Prevention in the Department of Housing and Urban Development and to authorize funding for the Eviction Protection Grant Program of such Department, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD5FDFB02852E41C59A30565FE31E28A7" style="OLC"><section id="HD625AE47AB084339A1182B0E16DF3B21" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Eviction Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H43EB7CBEED634C14B857DFB4EFD91EAF"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of Office of Eviction Prevention</header><subsection id="HB2462489365E44EDB0D4A3ADCB3520E5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 4 of the Department of Housing and Urban Development Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3533">42 U.S.C. 3533</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0E9122F027EE4AA085E916EEA47D4C9D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H0C5AC6AB1C2C484F91164BF3B7FEF510"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Office of Eviction Prevention</header><paragraph id="H5A4B71BAB0FB43039790107D8A1B8341"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established in the Department, in the Office of the Secretary, the Office of Eviction Prevention.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D6F5A2ADCFB42BDB13C349C7779D83B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director</header><text>There is established the position of Director of the Office of Eviction Prevention. The Director shall be the head of the Office of Eviction Prevention and shall be appointed by, and shall report to, the Secretary. Such position shall be a career-reserved position in the Senior Executive Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0213E2C5E044478966B50BBE74FFB7C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Mission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The mission of the Office of Eviction Prevention shall be to prevent evictions from rental housing and to protect tenants of such housing from the harm of evictions and eviction filings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H55249FF78DE2451EAC09FFF6ABB91F2B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Functions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall have primary responsibility within the Department for all activities and matters relating to eviction prevention, including the following:</text><subparagraph id="HE80E6D3D64584F5C845D62FBBD12F3EF"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Administering the Eviction Protection Grant Program of the Department, including—</text><clause id="H6B3C6553B6114588AC7EB3DCBF7BC5AF"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conducting a robust evaluation of grantees under the program and the activities undertaken under the program by grantees, and assessing whether such activities improved outcomes for tenants served by a grant, taking into consideration the differing tenant protections in States and localities;</text></clause><clause id="H3F5D85A7462B43F08C39EA5FA9A10892"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identifying, and reporting to the Congress on, best practices and activities for eviction protection, including identifying resources and funding needed to continue and replicate best practices and activities; and</text></clause><clause id="HC4D49F616AB3413E9566AB917DC367F6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing technical assistance and support to grantees under the program to provide them with training, expertise, best practices, and problem-solving strategies.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B2856D60A0A4CDE91793E165C3E4110"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Analyzing and reporting on information gathered through the Eviction Protection Grant Program and other programs administered by the Office.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC36C591B313A481AA89B50A1C612B685"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinating with the Office of Policy Development and Research of the Department in establishing a database on evictions, which shall be administered by such Office and shall include such measures as may be necessary to protect against the release of personally identifiable information regarding tenants, analyzing information collected by such database, and reporting to the Congress regarding such analyses.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H98D30380400A4450BB50696C29B95120"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordinating strategies to prevent evictions and early lease terminations in housing programs administered by the Department, including through—</text><clause id="HAA9D93D6FF784B19AD863D3E2ECE5C1B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>training offices and personnel of the Department on eviction prevention policies and programs and tenants rights; and</text></clause><clause id="H51916245599D4B3AA6F8BD13CA0FE905"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinating with other offices of the Department, including the Office of Fair Housing and Equal Opportunity and the Office of Gender-Based Violence.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H012585AD857E4229A555661F24A77028"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Collaborating with other Federal agencies, including the Office of Access to Justice of the Department of Justice, the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, the Department of Agriculture, the Department of the Treasury, the Department of Veterans Affairs, and the Department of Defense, to develop best practices for eviction prevention strategies within Federal programs and the private rental market. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BB87B426B6E4EFC99F3C0EE485D2E2C"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Identifying strategies to prevent and reduce evictions across the United States, including—</text><clause id="H4716528A67844755B093EBF7010901C0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>collaborating with Federal agencies whose activities impact tenants in federally subsidized housing and housing in the private rental market, including the Federal Housing Finance Agency, the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection, the Department of Justice, the Federal Trade Commission, the Department of Health and Human Services, the Department of Transportation, the United States Domestic Policy Council, and the National Economic Council;</text></clause><clause id="HE30C2296B1A04532809AC4349340D813"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing a working group on eviction prevention to study and develop solutions to the national eviction crisis, which working group shall include representatives of agencies referred to in clause (i), tenant representatives, representatives of legal services providers, and grantees under the Eviction Protection Grant Program;</text></clause><clause id="HDB7ED48ABC3940FBBCEC669BD06EF6B4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>providing technical assistance to housing providers, State and local governments, and other agencies on issues related to evictions and tenant protections; and</text></clause><clause id="H6BAFDFA0B47F43D1B34F49AAB94508AF"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>coordinating with State and local governments and agencies, including State housing finance agencies, on such issues.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC394794B7CF4D9A937712CBB5B6994F"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Conducting outreach to and engagement with tenants to—</text><clause id="H7CF4A4173EC947818224A627FB1F94C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>provide education and information about tenant protections and available eviction prevention programs, including by developing resources and materials for tenants;</text></clause><clause id="H31458E0F17C84BE6A02B5629D53C5C22"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>collect complaints and feedback from tenants and community members on evictions and eviction-prevention programs; and</text></clause><clause id="H67B3D0F133F844EAA42221DD0DE9180D"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>refer complaints regarding evictions to appropriate Federal, State, and local agencies or organizations, including legal and other advocacy organizations, appropriate to address housing-related issues.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H17E01E22B4AF4A1EA5161F5E38F4079B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Covered evictions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection the term <quote>eviction</quote> includes the variety of processes and means by which landlords remove tenants from rental properties, including—</text><subparagraph id="H871FF1578A4B4847B477AF6B3B2DCCFC"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">court-ordered evictions, including eviction filings, court-ordered eviction rulings, and any eviction actions that take place through the judicial system;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCEEACDC89CA14157B2BEFA63ACC0FAA4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">extra-legal evictions that do not involve the judicial system, commonly known as illegal, unlawful, informal, or self-help evictions, including threatening tenants, changing the locks on rental units, shutting off the utilities to such units, and paying tenants to surrender occupancy of a unit;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H017AA752B2894876ADD2B6C8D7E65241"><enum>(C)</enum><text>administrative actions by public housing agencies to evict residents of public housing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBAB957F4BCF1462DABA4B417C5069AFE"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">early lease terminations by housing providers receiving assistance from the Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HEC20B7D03FBD4992AC15E168F5A83398"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Transfer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Housing and Urban Development shall provide for the transfer of the administration of the Eviction Protection Grant Program of the Department, which as of the date of the enactment of this Act is the responsibility of the Office of Policy Development and Research, to the Director of the Office of Eviction Prevention established under section 4(i) of the Department of Housing and Urban Development Act, as added by the amendment made by subsection (a) of this section.</text></subsection></section><section id="HFF10430DFB014AD5B44469D618471F52"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated—</text><paragraph id="H50C2394E74B14EB388A9DBFFFA2F4BD1"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 for grants under the Eviction Protection Grant Program of the Department of Housing and Urban Development; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H002D6074120B4571BD5D73988E9AFC9A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$100,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 for costs of personnel for and activities of the Office of Eviction Prevention.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

