<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H466BAECCC0BF4E14B0A77DCAC86608C3" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1766 IH: Streamlining Interstate Transmission of Electricity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-23</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1766</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230323">March 23, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Power Act to establish a procedure for the siting of certain interstate electric transmission facilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0332276A5A33429EB48C51D39FAC8A44" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H7DC2E741D71642BCA3251E5676ED8D9D"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Streamlining Interstate Transmission of Electricity Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SITE Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF1018CF3EB6249B89A4BCF03793328AD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Siting of certain interstate electric transmission facilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part II of the Federal Power Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/824">16 U.S.C. 824 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEDECDD7D48B64BD2BEFAAB8A22140451"><section id="H89A45716C312446897CEDEBB3F00B674"><enum>224.</enum><header>Siting of certain interstate electric transmission facilities</header><subsection id="HDE01CADAB39C43C3B8889D206B6E7B03"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H1C1A5CAA6C884F3A9DD544684DC6B8DE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Affected landowner</header><subparagraph id="H76DF8C9C81FA4C8CB52BCD201C946E64"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>affected landowner</term> includes each owner of a property interest in land or other property described in subparagraph (B), including—</text><clause id="H5B642CCD2C9D4A4A81890C33B2F46036"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Federal Government;</text></clause><clause id="HFF0D3211EAFA4200A199079AB1810DEF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a State or local government; and</text></clause><clause id="H7DA674AC85D9442E992B3C02A429685E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>each owner noted in the most recent county or city tax record as receiving the relevant tax notice with respect to that interest.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7D24A4AAA65486DA1941A40105DAA00"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Land and other property described</header><text>The land or other property referred to in subparagraph (A) is any land or other property—</text><clause id="HA68F5B8C7A494D70A131A1362C529B2E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is or will be crossed by the energy transmission facility proposed to be constructed or modified under the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity;</text></clause><clause id="H20E34792A3494FB893A52723AB69398A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that is or will be used as a facility site with respect to the energy transmission facility proposed to be constructed or modified under the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity;</text></clause><clause id="HDB84E88079C846A3854F2428DFA3351F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>that abuts any boundary of an existing right-of-way or other facility site that—</text><subclause id="HC549ABACAC0C488E869731BADFB24687"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is owned by an electric utility; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA184D8104C944DEA8EA55EA9B2E230D9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is located not more than 500 feet from the energy transmission facility to be constructed or modified under the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H68538B8118F048EA8D9EE5892D678101"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>that abuts the boundary of a proposed facility site for the energy transmission facility to be constructed or modified under the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity;</text></clause><clause id="H154C8B8A7E53462EB06CA54EE839B6A1"><enum>(v)</enum><text>that is crossed by, or abuts any boundary of, an existing or proposed right-of-way that—</text><subclause id="H68508D6219754DD39A2100000AD394AC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>will be used for the energy transmission facility to be constructed or modified under the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H472D5F12931246B7AAEF6ADA1F75AE82"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is located not more than 500 feet from the proposed location of that energy transmission facility; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H70256FE176B9465AB61499C01267C709"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>on which a residence is located not more than 500 feet from the boundary of any right-of-way for that energy transmission facility.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6EFFA74CAEFE4686BAF11BBBDA207742"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Alternating current transmission facility</header><text>The term <term>alternating current transmission facility</term> means a transmission facility that uses alternating current for the bulk transmission of electric energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H893D88EAEEB949B7942BA9F584E92DE3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Energy transmission facility</header><text>The term <term>energy transmission facility</term> means, as applicable—</text><subparagraph id="H40794D01AA68446986D5694ED7CA301F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an alternating current transmission facility; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE90E85B5D3B84A84963341B19B010A02"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a high-voltage, direct current transmission facility. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3489DB7FBB0F40E2961A5335C4D12544"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Facility site</header><text>The term <term>facility site</term> includes—</text><subparagraph id="HBBAAB1D6362D4A208497CA25326EDFFA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a right-of-way;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE3C3F2C9C77143058AB5AD863C746953"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an access road;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H167D44FA79E14728964B19C23C82DF85"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a contractor yard; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF4CE9206FCA141208BBED5FA12701926"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any temporary workspace.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8C4D8B7FF574BC6B882992378102B28"><enum>(5)</enum><header>High-voltage, direct current transmission facility</header><text>The term <term>high-voltage, direct current transmission facility</term> means a transmission facility that uses direct current for the bulk transmission of electric energy.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4EDB4E2B1DFB448CA09A85EE5C449E7D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Tribal land</header><text>The term <term>Tribal land</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian land</term> in section 2601 of the Energy Policy Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/3501">25 U.S.C. 3501</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5373181FF3E44D8F9CE9BCF5801125CA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certificate of public convenience and necessity</header><paragraph id="H4B776530C891429F870DDB452C835ACE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>On receipt of an application under subsection (c)(1) relating to an energy transmission facility described in paragraph (2), the Commission, after making the finding described in paragraph (3) with respect to that energy transmission facility, shall issue to any person, by publication in the Federal Register, a certificate of public convenience and necessity for the construction, modification, operation, or abandonment of that energy transmission facility, subject to such reasonable terms and conditions as the Commission determines to be appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2D7EB877C864470A23B700D2783FBFC"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Energy transmission facility described</header><text>An energy transmission facility referred to in paragraph (1) is an energy transmission facility that—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H8169EF81FC954DF7865B61F280232DD5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>traverses or, on construction or modification in accordance with a certificate of public convenience and necessity issued under that paragraph, will traverse not fewer than 2 States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5C82B8ABD09C4D89A1E384F03FA33557"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is not less than 1,000 megawatts or 1,000 megavolt-amperes in power capacity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H343F5DA38D31464EBE0D1AF13E4D06AC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Finding described</header><text>The finding referred to in paragraph (1) is a finding that—</text><subparagraph id="H629BD2EE261441119EAF70F78B11A70C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the applicant for a certificate of public convenience and necessity is able and willing—</text><clause id="H62F4A679B3624DC08E44882864AAA469"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to carry out the activities and perform the services proposed in the application in a manner determined to be appropriate by the Commission; and</text></clause><clause id="HCFC2AC35AE94458394C6BC651685A104"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to achieve compliance with the applicable requirements of—</text><subclause id="H2BCC611500F74FBD9F18359A06115DFA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>this part; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H0A3DCD2A80D64951B9C0F42CA2313F69"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any rules and regulations promulgated by the Commission pursuant to this part;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5B3386839EE4239AFB39F0FDBF3CA00"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the energy transmission facility to be constructed, modified, or operated under the certificate of public convenience and necessity will—</text><clause commented="no" id="HABD1BD5B067844B3A6F9E8A7C94B7176"><enum>(i)</enum><text>traverse not fewer than 2 States;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HAFBCA9BA0D3F49A68E82BD7DBED46909"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>be used for the transmission of electric energy in interstate commerce; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H9A595EADC14F467DA03DDB6289444E34"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>have a power capacity of not less than 1,000 megawatts or 1,000 megavolt-amperes; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5CF8144AC1348369EAE7AB5E34E5E59"><enum>(C)</enum><text>operation of the energy transmission facility as proposed in the application—</text><clause id="H01BA1E96736C4E7288581F7F4AE8C286"><enum>(i)</enum><text>will—</text><subclause id="H013228FF82724D5C81CFA97CEB7B211C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>enable the use of renewable energy; </text></subclause><subclause id="H751FF8F094224B92805CE0B108FEB18A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>reduce congestion; or </text></subclause><subclause id="H6829CA7FD5C6472F8EB0CACE6CDCE72E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>improve the reliability of the transmission system;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HE2841A5B39A74011AAF62FF8565EA1CE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>will maximize, to the extent reasonable and economical, the use of—</text><subclause id="HBF790593B447453CA84806070264D672"><enum>(I)</enum><text>existing facility sites; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H402D98C439E74A90AF51FE55AD2B428C"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the transmission capabilities of existing energy transmission facilities; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H6B3D2CD32FAF460D99A97EE753BE713E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>will, to the extent practicable, minimize the use of eminent domain.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H816EC1CF2F0242DC9C9CE25274FA45EB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Commission shall issue rules specifying—</text><subparagraph id="H1A670D7F091847A8B06C54D723B40CC2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a pre-filing process during which a person described in subsection (c)(1) and the Commission shall consult with—</text><clause id="HCE698E768468456BB6153D07E6D2545A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the appropriate State agencies, State public utility commissions, and State energy offices in each State the proposed project traverses; </text></clause><clause id="HD41EA1BCCBFB4FC0ACAA1D9B974692B5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>appropriate Federal agencies; and</text></clause><clause id="H878C15B5E1D54BC2B9C40DBE68B167B9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>each Indian Tribe that may be affected by the proposed project;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71859A86764742319E235602D291B5EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the form of, and information to be contained in, an application submitted under subsection (c)(1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HC2BB84ECBB2344099F8C668EFFC502DF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>requirements for determining whether the applicable energy transmission facility will be constructed or modified—</text><clause commented="no" id="H06DB9B868FCB4C7E935D2E36E5F35685"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to traverse not fewer than 2 States;</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HD90350D0AD904CD69A077DEE4DF991DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to be used for the transmission of electric energy in interstate commerce; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H25758ED9CE1B417D9E64C22FDFF35F60"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>to have a power capacity of not less than 1,000 megawatts or 1,000 megavolt-amperes;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF59DFF45940044E9961E2DC0165E0574"><enum>(D)</enum><text>criteria for determining the reasonable and economical use of—</text><clause id="H9A3DED37C0644777A5A71C12D52FF6CC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>existing rights-of-way; and</text></clause><clause id="H65E48C65BA1547718A97B658E9C7A356"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the transmission capabilities of existing towers or structures;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9726CDC7704D41A39D3EE02C22B0FA4A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>the manner in which an application submitted under subsection (c)(1) and any proposal for the construction or modification of an energy transmission facility shall be considered, which, to the extent practicable, shall be consistent with State statutory and regulatory policies concerning generation and retail sales of electricity in the States in which the electric energy transmitted by the energy transmission facility will be generated or sold; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E93C50B4962409FBF697B4C4776D7A0"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the manner in which the Commission will consider the needs of communities that will be impacted directly by the proposed energy transmission facility, including how any impacts of the proposed energy transmission facility could be mitigated or offset.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H1729A6DEAD6142A899480FB9DB415C53"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Public notice, comment, and opportunity for a hearing on certain draft documents</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H8F4AB0BFAEC84CAC8A28CB9507F93CD2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall provide not less than 90 days for public comment on any initial scoping document or draft environmental impact statement prepared for an energy transmission facility with respect to which an application for a certificate of public convenience and necessity has been submitted under subsection (c)(1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H47F455BE4C4A4F72A9AE2B5BD84E91C9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity for hearing</header><text>The Commission shall—</text><clause commented="no" id="HD8A02501F9974FBAA17F4221576F1E09"><enum>(i)</enum><text>publish in the Federal Register a notice of the filing of each draft scoping document or draft environmental impact statement described in clause (i); and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H12151268DDD74F809559E35D25B4FD66"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide to the individuals and entities described in paragraph (6)(B) notice and reasonable opportunity for the presentation of any views and recommendations with respect to the initial scoping document or draft environmental impact statement.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H449623EDA5E74A358D5107311E3C4F03"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Tribal consent</header><text>With respect to an Indian Tribe that may be affected by a potential project, the Commission—</text><clause commented="no" id="H0501826C0ABA46B2ADCA08C80DDD9466"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall provide notice to the appropriate Tribal officials and an opportunity of public comment in accordance with subparagraph (A); and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H0D383436E72744D4B8C2D2B0730DF236"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall not approve a scoping document or draft environmental impact statement unless consent has been obtained from the proper Tribal officials in a manner consistent with the requirements of section 2 of the Act of February 5, 1948 (62 Stat. 18, chapter 45; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/324">25 U.S.C. 324</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA48889A8E66A42AC8C148E3F5C43C23C"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Notice and opportunity for a hearing on applications</header><subparagraph id="HC86C51DC739C438887A43AB2796EA209"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In any proceeding before the Commission to consider an application for a certificate of public convenience and necessity under this section, the Commission shall—</text><clause id="HF0FD2895AD1D4A5387E70F9B92F0F79D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>publish a notice of the application in the Federal Register; and</text></clause><clause id="H8C621FF1CA3141AD8CB7DC59914680DD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provide to the individuals and entities described in subparagraph (B) a notice and reasonable opportunity for the presentation of any views and recommendations with respect to the need for, and impact of, the construction or modification of the energy transmission facility proposed to be constructed or modified under the certificate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7DFB46CC3C5C46539B01EE3904CAD316"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Individuals and entities described</header><text>The individuals and entities referred to in subparagraph (A) are—</text><clause id="HB3EF2588924E4285A21D9B5624630BE5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>an agency, selected by the Governor (or equivalent official) of the applicable State, of each State in which the energy transmission facility proposed to be constructed or modified under the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity is or will be located;</text></clause><clause id="H9287BB7C684A482DAB2153CDC84CFE70"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each affected landowner; and</text></clause><clause id="H51DF183C86E84846B5BBDDBF496555F1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>as determined by the Commission—</text><subclause id="H9D11F98852334C4384FFAD05AFB08166"><enum>(I)</enum><text>each affected Federal agency; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7CFBA9E994DE4AC8BDB0B4C72CB82289"><enum>(II)</enum><text>each Indian Tribe that may be affected by the proposed construction or modification.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7AB518C891A14BC59146FD114DBF4D69"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>The Commission may not—</text><clause id="HBFAFC6BEEB54467BB789F19D0C993B93"><enum>(i)</enum><text>require an applicant for a certificate of public convenience and necessity under this section to provide any notice required under this section; or</text></clause><clause id="H6FC6AF0EA0CC4E96A972CC617484ECBD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>enter into a contract to provide any notice required under this section with—</text><subclause id="H7F5A579815AD40D98D55D82407C900C3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the applicant for the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H19D996EE6AAB4BC98D0F5F127FE94DF8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any other person that has a financial interest in the project proposed in the application for that certificate.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2682287B3F48421CA00445CEA4664AD3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applications</header><paragraph id="HAF0E3FC4E3D845FC94813BBE09CF24AB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A person desiring a certificate of public convenience and necessity under this section shall submit to the Commission an application at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Commission may require.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEAB46AEDD25044109B69450CB5F11D34"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>An application submitted to the Commission under paragraph (1) shall include all information necessary for the Commission to make the finding described in subsection (b)(3).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H960B2BDFC98C48DD89AD67B80838DD83"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Notice to affected landowners</header><paragraph id="H90F6A7CE7F0C4EAABDC6993EB974E983"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall provide written notice of an application submitted under subsection (c)(1) to all affected landowners in accordance with this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2B4D64FB17443FB80DD46109689F19E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Any notice provided to an affected landowner under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="H74E1D92A637647599EA337D02391E426"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The following statement in 14-point bold typeface:</text><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">“‘The [name of applicant] has proposed building power lines that will cross your property, and may also require building transmission towers on your property. If the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission approves [applicant]’s proposed project, then [applicant] may have the right to build transmission towers on, and power lines over, your property, or use your property to construct the proposed project, subject to paying you just compensation for the loss of your property.</continuation-text><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">“‘If you want to raise objections to this, or otherwise comment on this project, you can do so by submitting written comments to the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission Docket No. [___]. You can do this electronically or by mail. To do so electronically [to be inserted by the Commission]. To do so by mail [to be inserted by the Commission].’.</continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF93EF6970226456B81748D9327E500B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A description of the proposed project, including—</text><clause id="H5BC4F9846F0346EDB468C105B4636B6F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the location of the proposed project (including a general location map); </text></clause><clause id="H9159206DE52A4C09B26B56FA64DA8CA7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the purpose of the proposed project; and</text></clause><clause id="H315900D5F77C4AC08C3BE00450CB2DE2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the timing of the proposed project.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF7E577EF52BA48C3B8F1D572BA4DCFF1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The name of, and the location in the docket of the Commission at which may be found, each submission by the applicant to the Commission relating to the proposed project. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2080560152904A90863FB2BAFD4C47DF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A general description of what the applicant will need from the landowner if the proposed project is approved, including the activities the applicant may undertake and the facilities that the applicant may seek to construct on the property of the landowner. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H77CD1F2FC2DD4A69BF2D6453AD04944C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A description of how the landowner may contact the applicant, including—</text><clause id="H0797E1132B88477986B8242C9628DB51"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a website; and </text></clause><clause id="H07724F14B1CA4EF9BA3FF51A3EF83CFD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a local or toll-free telephone number and the name of a specific person to contact who is knowledgeable about the proposed project.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4BE5D68FAFA64AFBBBE5A4D10505FE46"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A description of how the landowner may contact the Commission, including—</text><clause id="H92890AACAC39415BB7A744A453D29A68"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a website; and </text></clause><clause id="HE3776E08D6E8443E9AA105A1BFF6A8C9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a local or toll-free telephone number and the name of a specific person to contact who is knowledgeable about the proposed project.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H988596127A1A4573B6130970B7C09E02"><enum>(G)</enum><text>A summary of the rights that the landowner has—</text><clause id="H96CF9304CB85450B8AC0AA8ABC4F7FE9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>before the Commission; and </text></clause><clause id="HBC8D5E31C64C49BEB1652AE44607DCA1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in other proceedings under—</text><subclause id="H09F29378BE6F45B398409FAF8FCEB785"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure; and </text></subclause><subclause id="H326DD7B9A74A49B1AB3EB08BEBCA6738"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the eminent domain rules of the relevant State.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H887742A5202940C3A2088740CBD673DA"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Any other information that the Commission determines to be appropriate. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6762F77B84D64B099411837EF1AFE1EB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Obligation of applicant</header><text>An applicant for a certificate of public convenience and necessity under this section shall submit to the Commission, together with the application for the certificate, the name and address of each affected landowner.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H029D6ED601974794930FC20F030A9495"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Regulatory jurisdiction</header><paragraph id="H0FD1CC44FF8F4991B10C367A56D9FBD4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Commission shall have exclusive jurisdiction over, and no State shall regulate any aspect of, the siting or permitting of an energy transmission facility constructed, modified, or operated under a certificate of public convenience and necessity issued under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEED00A7B626474BB201017E16F2AD2D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text>Nothing in this section affects the rights of States under—</text><subparagraph id="H1ED8DCD004BA4BBF834FF8EFAA0E6B8F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the <act-name parsable-cite="CAMA72">Coastal Zone Management Act of 1972</act-name> (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1451">16 U.S.C. 1451 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5BBEF3B42BF49059D82A02B6B27E6E5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1251">33 U.S.C. 1251 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H500EB4C6C4AC4BFDB9805580C2FEE321"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Clean Air Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/7401">42 U.S.C. 7401 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H442BC1877B3142068E1B52E476880BA4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>division A of subtitle III of title 54, United States Code (formerly known as the <quote>National Historic Preservation Act</quote>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7CF9033A591843078EF30F2CD9FDE2C1"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Judicial review</header><paragraph id="H940A6BA03C19442C8F200E06553D8CE6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any person aggrieved by an order issued by the Commission under this section may obtain review of the order in—</text><subparagraph id="H6631701C7C774A089FF9A9D52669758B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the court of appeals of the United States for any judicial circuit in which the energy transmission facility to be constructed or modified under the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity is or will be located; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H428B44CF555F4F7E9DABD2ECAE0A1A96"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C2CCAD0EB764C8BA3E7EBA4632BBE79"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Petition for review</header><subparagraph id="H76A2A008FF794EFEAEBD30FF51204CC1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A person may obtain review under paragraph (1) by filing in the applicable court a written petition praying that the order of the Commission be modified or set aside in whole or in part.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H461132DE728D4DD5989B711542AED090"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>A petition under subparagraph (A) shall be filed by not later than 60 days after the date on which the applicable order of the Commission is published in the Federal Register.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C342D6D79064A5089102701D6B69B01"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Person aggrieved</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Act, a person aggrieved by an order of the Commission issued under this section need not—</text><subparagraph id="HA514EE6FD56E4564956C1D1B4A6626CF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>have been a party to the proceedings before the Commission in which that order was issued in order to obtain judicial review of the order under this subsection; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H998520795F2D457FA533D0798850212E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have requested rehearing before the Commission prior to seeking judicial review.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H685282EFEF0E44CA96B957E8E6B723D6"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Right of eminent domain for energy transmission facilities</header><paragraph id="H92C5D487DDEA42BB93D552D8106ECC97"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The holder of a certificate of public convenience and necessity may acquire through the exercise of the right of eminent domain in a court described in paragraph (2) any right-of-way, land, or other property that is necessary to construct, modify, operate, or maintain an energy transmission facility in accordance with that certificate if the holder—</text><subparagraph id="HD538A68995FC4B3B8767C9A007DE587D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>cannot acquire the necessary right-of-way, land, or other property by contract;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H57B8410B11E545D7B132659D09A570E4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is unable to agree with the owner of the right-of-way, land, or other property with respect to the compensation to be paid for that right-of-way, land, or other property; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53E058E1222349C186CAC895655A5FAD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>cannot clear defective title with respect to the right-of-way, land, or other property.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD81A6229061B41D0A982A497C9CDBBC0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Court described</header><text>A court referred to in paragraph (1) is—</text><subparagraph id="H786A053229C641C7AC4EF9583F537DFA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the district court of the United States for the district in which the applicable land or other property is located; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H426B67C986A14C779F4DA4A07275E2C7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the appropriate State court.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8A84520942043A4A0A21B9A0FFFBFFB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notice of decision to issue certificate</header><text>The holder of a certificate of public convenience and necessity may not exercise the right of eminent domain under this subsection with respect to any property covered by the certificate unless the Commission has first, in addition to publishing the notice of certificate of public convenience and necessity in the Federal Register, provided all affected landowners with notice of—</text><subparagraph id="H15810DFAB02B45EB8419E9D2670426A0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the decision of the Commission to grant the certificate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F378C12275A4FC481AD9C6B9FE53EC5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the procedures for obtaining judicial review of that decision under subsection (f), including a description of the time period for seeking judicial review under that subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H323D2252ED2B4127A8FB0493A6E8153C"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Condemnation procedures</header><paragraph id="H570FAA5B42CF4BDFB3436A6E758F1B34"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appraisals</header><subparagraph id="HACE1CC95D8F448BFBA29F6BA725207A6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A holder of, or applicant for, a certificate of public convenience and necessity shall have any property that the holder or applicant seeks to acquire through the exercise of the right of eminent domain under subsection (g) appraised in accordance with generally accepted appraisal standards by an appraiser selected by the owner of the property, subject to subparagraph (D).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H53080F9813CB4FABB17EB4437B26FD80"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><clause id="H9F55D590DE794330803162DC47696759"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Costs</header><text>The applicable holder of, or applicant for, a certificate of public convenience and necessity shall pay for each appraisal carried out under subparagraph (A).</text></clause><clause id="H5FBC6EA01F0345CBA579D56805834032"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Inspections</header><text>The owner of the applicable property (or a designated representative of the owner) shall be given the opportunity to accompany the appraiser during any inspection of the property that is part of an appraisal under subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4260B27FC57648AC9242E8BFCB3359E7"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>An appraisal under subparagraph (A) shall be carried out before the holder of, or applicant for, the certificate of public convenience and necessity—</text><clause id="H80CD4C059F7C4D6AB7DEF90E2F1BBB4A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>makes an offer of just compensation under paragraph (2); or</text></clause><clause id="HAAF956A382B44B71BDF5836214BB1372"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>commences an action or proceeding to exercise the right of eminent domain under subsection (g).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4548655DF692450087C32496B6597D49"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Selection of appraiser</header><text>If the owner of the applicable property does not select an appraiser under subparagraph (A) by the date that is 60 days after the date on which the holder of, or applicant for, the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity requests that the owner do so, the holder or applicant shall have the right to select the appraiser.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAEBBB9679EF4E8BBF0AEA55EA8F7763"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Offers of just compensation</header><subparagraph id="H5DD1AC4E420E4DF5BCC30C8FC37AB28C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any offer of just compensation made to an affected landowner of property that is covered by a certificate of public convenience and necessity—</text><clause id="HF6D61EA6300448459C06DA52181EAD22"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be made in writing;</text></clause><clause id="H8A383E766F1B4D368B866F808589F48E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may not be for an amount less than the fair market value of the property, as determined by an appraisal carried out under paragraph (1); and</text></clause><clause id="HF6766A6213604D86951212776EE2D587"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>shall include compensation for—</text><subclause id="H3978752A0E774961BA45866EE2BCDED5"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any lost income from the property; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H6138C8A6F29C43BF97B3FA9D6CC8EE46"><enum>(II)</enum><text>any damages to any other property of the owner.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H99FA0321C4BF4935B72FD1BD9DADD964"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Timing</header><text>The holder of, or applicant for, a certificate of public convenience and necessity may not make an offer of just compensation to an affected landowner until the date that is 30 days after the date on which the Commission provides a notice to the affected landowner under subsection (g)(3).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC25304E00C6C4034A8044F29073CF9BE"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Jurisdictional limitations</header><subparagraph id="H3241085D75114A169E98BA301EE4D0C4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Minimum jurisdictional amount</header><text>A district court of the United States shall only have jurisdiction of an action or proceeding to exercise the right of eminent domain under subsection (g) if the amount claimed by the owner of the property to be condemned exceeds $3,000.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDAB969E49C8F4515B32A1A6474BCCF30"><enum>(B)</enum><header>State ownership interests</header><clause id="HD607DF06F56242A597242B9D477F08DD"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), a district court of the United States shall have no jurisdiction to condemn any interest owned by a State.</text></clause><clause id="H6EA4F4CC753841C3BD319A5ABE9F4D8E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Notwithstanding clause (i), a district court of the United States shall have jurisdiction—</text><subclause id="H97A8A502199D490CAEADFFF9810BE0D1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to condemn any existing utility or transportation easement or right-of-way that—</text><item id="H7B1D038106564127AC299218F91B2603"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is on State property; or</text></item><item id="H8DD9144916C24CE1A7707F6C2DE27526"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is on private property and is owned by a State; and</text></item></subclause><subclause commented="no" id="HD51C6385205E4FA184F4511694F62720"><enum>(II)</enum><text>to condemn any real property conveyed to a State for the purpose of obstructing the construction, modification, or operation of an energy transmission facility in accordance with a certificate of public convenience and necessity issued under this section.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9FFA7CBE40C74C8D8FB776ABFBA21F8B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Tribal land</header><text>A district court of the United States shall have no jurisdiction to condemn any interest in Tribal land.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H15FE43EABC2045F8A9250AFBC1BDADF8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Limitation on condemnation</header><text>In any action or proceeding to exercise the right of eminent domain under subsection (g), a court—</text><subparagraph id="H50F21C371F0C423FBC9BED75F6A9589C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may condemn an interest in property only to the extent necessary for the specific facilities described in the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6FFABF1DB9934843B062CCE490BCB850"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may not—</text><clause id="H39F9D7DD7CF0449B8863F48D1C4987D5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>condemn any other interest; or</text></clause><clause id="H23F31D28394E405DB1954EC62B9FFF1B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>condemn an interest for any purpose not described in that certificate.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAA4F9123E064F5AAECE373A6993959E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Right of possession</header><text>With respect to any action or proceeding to exercise the right of eminent domain under subsection (g), an owner of property covered by the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity shall not be required to surrender possession of that property unless the holder of the certificate—</text><subparagraph id="H540E0DCEA5684B7C9A569EFB39D9B9D5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has paid to the owner the award of compensation in the action or proceeding; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC093D42D72D43E78E557FB0959591F1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has deposited the amount of that award with the court.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB80FA6F371C44E56B36D0953A711AB68"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Litigation costs</header><subparagraph id="H2CE9BABD02E24EF98987F57267C36C38"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A holder of a certificate of public convenience and necessity that commences an action or proceeding to exercise the right of eminent domain under subsection (g) shall be liable to the owner of any property condemned in that proceeding for the costs described in subparagraph (B) if the amount awarded to that owner for the property condemned is more than 125 percent of the amount offered to the owner by the holder before the commencement of that action or proceeding.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CDD3ED2A44648D983F61AB0052BF669"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Costs described</header><text>The costs referred to in subparagraph (A) are litigation costs incurred for the action or proceeding described in that subparagraph by the owner of the property condemned, including—</text><clause id="HB08560CA54F64365B804E31F15644B77"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reasonable attorney fees; and</text></clause><clause id="H5478ECED18274AB58EDF6244F96F78A5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>expert witness fees and costs.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF4E9F4E4E3FA46FAAB098F5D9901D71E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Enforcement of conditions</header><paragraph id="H7B14518DDE5D4910B09CE177218CC6E6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An affected landowner the property of which has been acquired by eminent domain under subsection (g) shall have the right—</text><subparagraph id="H71B8712CDA0F41BAA8971327BB17EE03"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to enforce any condition in the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6AE54E55885E4D598B4DE0D7B9A39F9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to seek damages for a violation of any condition described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4F62D843F6014ED4982EDC90D7A32CDD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>The district courts of the United States shall have jurisdiction over any action arising under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCB185C296BF7412C9F5307C819D95A22"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Other landowner rights and protections</header><paragraph id="H30C2A5B8F8E44B7FACBCE2FF2118B365"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Failure to timely complete projects</header><subparagraph id="HE751DDD4FA654A2191FA994110D892AF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Surrender of condemned property</header><clause id="HAC77E3BBDA2F43119B84A9A3DC1C18FF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An individual or entity from which an interest in property is acquired through the exercise of the right of eminent domain under subsection (g) by the holder of a certificate of public convenience and necessity that is issued for the construction, modification, or operation of an energy transmission facility may demand that the holder of the certificate surrender that interest to that individual or entity if—</text><subclause id="HB3FA59F7CE29406D80BC90BE1D2341D5"><enum>(I)</enum><item commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H580F8319271E44B1AF4E6B7717AFE899"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the energy transmission facility is not in operation (as modified, in the case of a modification of an energy transmission facility) by the date specified in the certificate (including any modification of the certificate by the Commission); and</text></item><item id="H942429DF66F34BFBAD9D65F1B87F7089" indent="up1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>there is no request for the extension of that date pending before the Commission; or</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H977DEB6B84D64233AF6A2EDA0BA602DC"><enum>(II)</enum><text>subject to clause (ii), the holder of the certificate, with the approval of the Commission, abandons the portion of the energy transmission facility that is located on the applicable property relating to that interest.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HBD0761013F0A4FC08C27DFE03F0CE95D"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>The Commission may not approve in a certificate of public convenience and necessity issued under this section or in any subsequent proceeding the abandonment of all or any part of an energy transmission facility unless the Commission requires the holder of the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity to offer to each individual or entity described in clause (i) the option of having the property acquired from that individual or entity as described in that clause restored to the condition that the property was in prior to the issuance of the certificate.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD9E34DC2E7E444B2B201D1E9DE53F12A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Repayment of condemnation award</header><text>If an individual or entity described in subparagraph (A)(i) demands the surrender of an interest under that subparagraph, the holder of the applicable certificate of public convenience and necessity shall be entitled to repayment of an amount equal to not more than 50 percent of the condemnation award relating to the interest.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H84F95F1E8C6F4F8C88E4657D7BD92DAB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>The district courts of the United States shall have jurisdiction over any action arising under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D0CE259B85E4EF294016DA339DD5030"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Material misrepresentations</header><subparagraph id="H69698AA411CC46C2AD80AF4429959A98"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Rescission of transaction</header><clause id="HFC76BD8950E742F08238FB56D7E98B01"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>An affected landowner that proves, by a preponderance of the evidence, that the affected landowner has granted a right-of-way or any other interest based on a material misrepresentation made by or on behalf of an applicant for, or holder of, a certificate of public convenience and necessity under this section shall have the right to rescind the transaction.</text></clause><clause id="H198ACAE6E9BC447BB76CBB37E64E50B1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Jurisdiction</header><text>The district courts of the United States shall have jurisdiction over any action arising under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63476407503A4C6C99B68869B2E68B73"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Civil penalties</header><clause id="HB908F9CEE5E9429E82DD52A8E7419A5C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If an applicant for, or holder of, a certificate of public convenience and necessity makes a material misrepresentation, or if a material misrepresentation is made on behalf of such an applicant or holder, to an affected landowner concerning the energy transmission facility to be constructed or modified under the certificate, the applicant or holder shall be subject to a civil penalty, to be assessed by the Commission, in an amount not to exceed $10,000 per affected landowner to which the misrepresentation was made.</text></clause><clause id="H4B45D68041A8442BB75AA9C3951A3C1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>The penalty described in clause (i) shall be assessed by the Commission after providing notice and an opportunity for a public hearing.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H725F3EAE73BC4F739A0D00F4126DCBEF"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In determining the amount of a penalty under clause (i), the Commission shall take into consideration the nature and seriousness of the violation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

