<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9FC78B25620943B0B5CBB8270781E8A0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>115 HR 5761 IH: Opportunity Zones Transparency, Extension, and Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5761</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230927">September 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to modify the rules relating to qualified opportunity zones, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H679C2B66E0584554BB8AE92E7750AA28" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H24B074D1177A47E1ABB4CE80371214B2"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Opportunity Zones Transparency, Extension, and Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H29D3D7BCE59845FBAF2BA1DB8420246E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress makes the following findings:</text><paragraph id="H2E3E0C089DE04B729513E8FAFFCFAF78"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The 8,764 population census tracts designated as qualified opportunity zones under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1400Z">section 1400Z–1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 span across all 50 States, the District of Columbia, and 5 Territories and overwhelmingly represent communities that have been economically left behind as the American economy has surged forward.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4FF96605B634F2994E1A4B4C861E202"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The average poverty rate of residents in qualified opportunity zones is 26.4 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H004BEE3C04184B509288345C8432063D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Forty-four percent of qualified opportunity zones are persistently poor, meaning they are census tracts in which the poverty rate has exceeded 20 percent since at least 1990.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC83FBA0DEE640D2BA15EED845341BCB"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the latest available data from the Department of the Treasury through 2020, opportunity zone investment reached at least 3,800 communities, or 48 percent of all designated census tracts. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11B73A88717441BB802639D01DFFCB75"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The communities that received opportunity zone investment are economically distressed places. On average, they rank in the 87th percentile for poverty, 81st for median household income, and 80th for unemployment.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEDFD01D33B764080B153BF518BD682E9"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The total amount of opportunity zone equity invested was at least $48 billion through the end of 2020, raised from an estimated 21,000 individuals and 4,000 corporate investors deployed into 7,800 Qualified Opportunity Funds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8103EE0ECB9841C1ABF8C0A91CFDF6EA"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The Investing in Opportunity Act, which first proposed opportunity zones, originally incorporated reporting requirements to evaluate the impact the incentive will have on designated communities and it is critical that Congress act to reinstate reporting requirements as soon as possible.</text></paragraph></section><title id="H1A6DB2FACBCC4D5A90074B0EA28CCDCF" style="OLC"><enum>I</enum><header>Modification of population census tracts designated as qualified opportunity zones</header><section commented="no" id="H72042F0316434356B7C68D5D62EA0E61"><enum>101.</enum><header>Modification of population census tracts designated as qualified opportunity zones</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1400Z">Section 1400Z–1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE94ED59BFA424C8C9264634852651A93"><subsection id="HD136852BB03E4702A032266D99570919"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Disqualification of certain population census tracts</header><paragraph id="H814790102A494E139194CDAAC2E06FE8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (5), any disqualified census tract shall not be treated as a qualified opportunity zone for any period after the date that is 30 days after the date on which the Secretary publishes the final list of disqualified census tracts under paragraph (4)(B).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H681A5402B46349B6B5C00B6611572AE2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Replacement zones</header><subparagraph id="H9B1896BE48B342E686B13CCB8AA175FB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The chief executive officer of a State shall nominate additional population census tracts to replace any population census tract the designation of which as a qualified opportunity zone was terminated by reason of paragraph (1). Except as otherwise provided in this paragraph, the rules of subsections (b), (c), (d), and (f) shall apply to any population census tract nominated under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04C73BC3B98B4D7EA7061D0B6FAAA70D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>No population census tract nominated under subparagraph (A) may be designated as a qualified opportunity zone unless the chief executive officer of the State certifies in writing to the Secretary that the chief executive officer has consulted with the chief executive officer (or the equivalent) of each local jurisdiction in which the population census tract is located. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DC2B51C1C614B34AB674A2F5F4A9AD5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Special rules</header><text>For purposes of this subchapter—</text><clause id="H48561D70ACD944199CBA44D327A5AFE1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any population census tract which is a disqualified census tract (as defined in paragraph (3) without regard to subparagraph (A)(i) thereof) may not be nominated as a qualified opportunity zone under this paragraph,</text></clause><clause id="H85CB4BD5C76D4555BFFC147060A26A4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the determination period with respect to a nomination under subparagraph (A) shall be the 45-day period beginning on the date on which the Secretary publishes the final list of disqualified census tracts under paragraph (4)(B), as extended under subsection (b)(2), and</text></clause><clause id="H3391DAA64D69458E8B75AE5A1C410B02"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the period for which any such designation is in effect shall be the period beginning on the date such designation takes effect and ending on the last day of the 10th calendar year beginning on or after the designation date as a qualified opportunity zone for the population census tract which it is replacing as such a zone by reason of the termination under paragraph (1).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD41A5D457E3C4970B81255D4112CC0B1"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>The Secretary shall prescribe such regulations or other guidance as may be necessary or appropriate to carry out the purposes of this paragraph. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEE08298AE48B453DB1B1BC0F8EBC5EFC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Disqualified census tract</header><text>For purposes of this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="HBE451F2592AC4ED3B4C2F905649337C1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>disqualified census tract</term> means any population census tract which—</text><clause id="HF163F23F2DC5441C84A5BC06BCE3E7B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>was designated as a qualified opportunity zone before the date of the enactment of this subsection, and</text></clause><clause id="H94B30226DF184800A01CF597B612527D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is described in subparagraph (B) or (C).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7FA86E5DA8D4C708374C2C875394E43"><enum>(B)</enum><header>High median family income tracts</header><clause id="H6DB2C10E43B946DB9BC59FACFDAB1426"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in clauses (ii) and (iii), a population census tract is described in this subparagraph if the median family income for such tract exceeds 130 percent of the national median family income as published by Department of Housing and Urban Development or the CDFI Fund.</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H88B2F02D80D246E8AA5243F413EBFBBD"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply if the poverty rate of such population census tract (excluding students enrolled in an institution of higher education (as defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965)) is equal to or greater than 30 percent. </text></clause><clause id="HCD1DE99E621A4A3F90D13231145A1537"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Request to retain designation for certain population census tracts</header><text>Clause (i) shall not apply if the Secretary, upon a request of the chief executive officer of the State made not later than 60 days after the date the Secretary publishes the list described in paragraph (4)(A), determines that—</text><subclause id="H568743317F5442EB8E92C1CF55BF6EA3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the designation of such population census tract was consistent with the purposes of this subchapter, or </text></subclause><subclause id="HB9E0C2675FB44110B9E7C2E5C4189C1F"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the median family income for the population census tract does not exceed 130 percent of the national median family income as published by Department of Housing and Urban Development or the CDFI Fund. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H4D8C059F042B44BFB6E9026FD95F9342"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Election to include additional population census tracts</header><clause commented="no" id="HB796C39256F7452796EF07E86675AD19"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A population census tract is described in this subparagraph if the Secretary, upon the request of the chief executive officer of the State submitted not later than 60 days after the date the Secretary publishes the list described in paragraph (4)(A), determines that the continued designation of such population census tract as a qualified opportunity zone is not consistent with the purposes of this subchapter.</text></clause><clause id="H5E645C22F2B543D196FDF6B31304F321"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No population census tract nominated under clause (i) may be designated as a qualified opportunity zone unless the chief executive officer of the State certifies in writing to the Secretary that the chief executive officer has consulted with the chief executive officer (or the equivalent) of each local jurisdiction in which the population census tract is located.</text></clause><clause id="H5DEB21A42A564B7C80C16467613C72C3"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the date on which the Secretary publishes the final list of disqualified census tracts under paragraph (4)(B), the Secretary shall issue regulations or guidance with respect to the criteria to be used for making a determination by the Secretary under clause (i). </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HE1E9320ED2464985991E9D0CFFDB67E4"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Identification and publication of disqualified census tracts</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF88AB8D1585F44B7ADEB035D6842F545"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial identification</header><text>As soon as practical, but not later than 12 months after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the Secretary shall make public—</text><clause commented="no" id="HF16D13130C8149BDB23D951C34D246CB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a list of population census tracts described in paragraph (3)(B) (determined without regard to clause (iii) thereof), and</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="H08A36FB3EE7C496FA9F5EAC86C4414CD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a list of population census tracts which are low-income communities and were not designated as a qualified opportunity zone before the date of enactment of this subsection. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H039D6AEC1DA649D7BA4D216DDFE6ABEE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Final list of disqualified census tracts</header><text>Not later than 105 days after the date the Secretary publishes the list described in subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall make public a final list of disqualified census tracts. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H0E2150E4CF69416BA44E2F99D694B6DD"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rules for qualified preexisting investments</header><subparagraph commented="no" id="H300273D9154640F19BD000DC2349D6DC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of this subchapter, section 1400Z–2 shall be applied without regard to paragraph (1) with respect to any qualified preexisting trade or business.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H934A32128972493FA2FE96596C2E6B6B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Qualified preexisting trade or business</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph—</text><clause commented="no" id="H7ACF7D75F35E493DB4B1ADBDEE661149"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified preexisting trade or business</term> means any trade or business of a qualified opportunity fund or qualified opportunity zone business which meets the requirements of clauses (ii) and (iii) of section 1400Z–2(d)(3)(A) and with respect to which—</text><subclause id="H7DA400BDE6FF4142BDC5E562A29A0222" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>before the date of the enactment of this subsection, a registration statement under the Securities Act of 1933 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/77a">15 U.S.C. 77a et seq.</external-xref>) is filed or any comparable offering memorandum or similar disclosure document is provided in reliance on section 230.506 of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations), promulgated under the Securities Act of 1933, that discloses the intent of such trade or business to invest in the disqualified census tract,</text></subclause><subclause id="H138FBAC60C9D4DD2A307FA2E20742F1A" commented="no"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">before the first date on which the disqualified census tract appears on any list published under paragraph (4), investments in the disqualified census tract are made or agreed pursuant to a binding agreement to be made which—</text><item commented="no" id="HAA359B129FD245F8887EFF6AA70952D3"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>aggregate more than $250,000, and</text></item><item commented="no" id="H6FB1686CA5284B56ABA4CB41CFC424E5"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>have been designated in writing for the use in, or the development of, such trade or business, or</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H4157C11587274219A6CEBFDC4E7ED066" commented="no"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the qualified opportunity fund or qualified opportunity zone business is determined by the Secretary to have relied on the designation of the disqualified census tract as a qualified opportunity zone and to have suffered or is expected to suffer a loss as a result of the application of paragraph (1).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HEC14827CD3044D28ADAC557FCE7906DF" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Trade or business</header><text>The term <term>trade or business</term> includes any activity intended to qualify as a trade or business within the meaning of section 162. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD132F1FA94D40FE9BD4C2DF63AB798A"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>The Secretary shall prescribe such regulations or guidance as may be necessary or appropriate to carry out the purposes of this paragraph, including guidance to prevent speculative investment solely for the purpose of falling within the definition of a qualified preexisting trade or business. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2DFA4041BAD54F4390AC323C277AF081"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Determination of population census tract data</header><text>For purposes of applying this subsection, in determining whether a population census tract meets any qualification with respect to poverty rate or any aspect of median income, such determination shall be made using the most recent census data that has been published by the Bureau of the Census as of the date of enactment of this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H5FB37933FF444C2EAFF7A397F5FEC72E"><enum>102.</enum><header>Certain former industrial tracts permitted to be designated as opportunity zones</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1400Z">Section 1400Z-1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended by section 101, is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H11114B4D01064E629AB135DF77274AF9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HC0BB682DF14D468497A7EFC77787345E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Special rule for former industrial tracts contiguous to designated opportunity zones</header><paragraph id="HA920634C51BB4179B265867F2BE9BAB5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this chapter, the term <term>qualified opportunity zone</term> means an population census tract which is described in paragraph (2) and designated as a qualified opportunity zone under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8FF8C1713E44556958563615F13FABF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Population census tract described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A population census tract is described in this subparagraph if—</text><subparagraph id="H80183B43289D451199A3CC735F23FF90"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the tract—</text><clause id="HC4E4DC2E506642439AD6D0E973818EDE"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has a population of zero, </text></clause><clause id="H86A386CE9EFC46FE8054CAA0A7DF054F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>was previously used for industrial purposes and is a brownfield industrial site, and </text></clause><clause id="H49189DDBBD054D1B8C8ACA213513C31A" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is contiguous, including by water, to a population census tract on at least 1 side that has been designated as a qualified opportunity zone under this section, or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45B139D657AA4763B89DD4B831C8E33B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the tract was merged, as a result of the 2020 decennial census, into a census tract described in subparagraph (A)(iii) and met all requirements described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BCFEEAE3A18453F85A455CB9083AE46"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), a population census tract that is described in paragraph (2) is designated as a qualified opportunity zone if—</text><subparagraph id="H04FC737B86FA4920B979F8957B9D9287"><enum>(A)</enum><text>not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection, the chief executive officer of the State in which the tract is located—</text><clause id="H7A0852B3C55A40028E9ADE4BDC7EDC3C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>nominates the tract for designation as a qualified opportunity zone, and</text></clause><clause id="HBE3A6AD6C72A43CB995CE85791EB11DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>notifies the Secretary in writing of such nomination, and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H186D384AEBD34DA0ABA843A77C4F4063"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not later than 30 days after receiving the notification under subparagraph (A)(ii), the Secretary certifies such nomination and designates such tract as a qualified opportunity zone. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF282675CABA84F988C7274677835FFAB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Determination of census tract information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, the boundaries and population of a census tract shall be determined based on United States Census Bureau data for the 2010 decennial census. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D8D6EC847324DA7872A5AD4E9D010F9"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Number of designations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Population census tracts designated as a qualified opportunity zone under this subsection shall not be taken into account for purposes of subsection (d).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H887E4CCF6FAC4106BB04C684E8B47BE7"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this subsection—</text><subparagraph id="H88F1FE5DB6804A2490D29F34D96E8612"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Brownfield industrial site</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>brownfield industrial site</term> means a population census tract that includes real property the expansion, redevelopment, or reuse of which may be complicated by the presence or potential presence of a hazardous substance or pollutant or contaminant, including real property covered by a prospective purchaser agreement or similar agreement entered into by the Environmental Protection Agency or the appropriate State authority. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2C1BCE77A4A49FB9B784912AEAFA7A0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Hazardous substance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>hazardous substance</term> means—</text><clause id="HEAA098E2D39749E48E05BD4FB3342CF5"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a hazardous substance as defined in section 101(14) of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9601">42 U.S.C. 9601(14)</external-xref>), or</text></clause><clause id="H936256882A8B4EB8BDD1BD5158170486"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>petroleum or a petroleum product. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0642989C32104D8096AF95B31064E96B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Pollutant or contaminant</header><text>The term <quote>pollutant or contaminant</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 101(33) of such Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></title><title style="OLC" id="H3F548BDDBF1B445AAECE60F1EF02B689"><enum>II</enum><header>Information reporting requirements</header><section id="H0E02442DB0494BBD81B14AC06CAC8EAA"><enum>201.</enum><header>Information reporting on qualified opportunity funds</header><subsection id="HA8C0535539C848E8A3EC91C6A280BC4D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="HDD994666A1B34B259DF84990788409F0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Filing requirements for funds and investors</header><text>Subpart A of part III of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/61">chapter 61</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after section 6039J the following new sections:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5228CE466D224AD78EC65D06028F6E1B"><section id="H272D02CA29CA4E51A352EDE484027FD2"><enum>6039K.</enum><header>Returns with respect to qualified opportunity funds</header><subsection id="HAF96E555783E4E7BA2C54C53809DAF18"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Every qualified opportunity fund shall file an annual return (at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may prescribe) containing the information described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H4DD2D80FD5A94FBFB5321E7B9D0D7879"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information from qualified opportunity funds</header><text>The information described in this subsection is—</text><paragraph id="HDF4391212A524E6EA7F67E1F73AECBBB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name, address, and taxpayer identification number of the qualified opportunity fund,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE266DA9090C24BD499C2435AE253D7B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>whether the qualified opportunity fund is organized as a corporation or a partnership,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3E928DF64FC1451EB4E4414B072BDDA6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the value of the total assets held by the qualified opportunity fund as of each date described in section 1400Z–2(d)(1),</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HF0425990CF734980ABC1AB55DABAA8B4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the value of all qualified opportunity zone property held by the qualified opportunity fund on each such date,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H9ABBEEDA5F834E03A3DA5D6EBFE02B4E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>with respect to each investment held by the qualified opportunity fund in qualified opportunity zone stock or a qualified opportunity zone partnership interest—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA5C0C40F34544AED8B2F2C553D283C00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the name, address, and taxpayer identification number of the corporation in which such stock is held or the partnership in which such interest is held, as the case may be,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HA9F69E702291465FA251FD8122BF794B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each North American Industry Classification Code that applies to the trades or businesses conducted by such corporation or partnership,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF7D36417E1044BB3B6B42E09E0BA66F3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the population census tracts in which the qualified opportunity zone business property of such corporation or partnership is located,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HF6FDEDD8BBEF4C4EB0738BF99D2CAD7E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the amount of the investment in such stock or partnership interest as of each date described in section 1400Z–2(d)(1),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H7139C710BF914F679BB958F1DF9EC7D1"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the value, as determined under regulations issued by the Secretary, of tangible property held by such corporation or partnership on each such date which is owned by such corporation or partnership,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2E100E3D5A6A4BF6BD4ECA69EB25A38D"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the value, as determined under regulations issued by the Secretary, of tangible property held by such corporation or partnership on each such date which is leased by such corporation or partnership,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HCA1700EC86254994B1604C8C01B80C0A"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the information described in paragraph (6)(E) with respect to buildings with 1 or more residential rental units which are held by such corporation or partnership, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HFF27E73E8CA3484A96EB3D1DC78BDE19"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the approximate average monthly number of full-time equivalent employees of such corporation or partnership for the year (within numerical ranges identified by the Secretary) or such other indication of the employment impact of such corporation or partnership as determined appropriate by the Secretary, which shall account for direct and indirect, temporary and permanent jobs,</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HC83DB173FC82411CBA3AEE7551A45CCB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>with respect to the items of qualified opportunity zone business property held by the qualified opportunity fund—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H03B06F3C455F47D6AD13CE94203DCF2A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the North American Industry Classification Code that applies to the trades or businesses in which such property is held,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H9BAA97E6BCAB4D5F96DB29725317035A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the population census tract in which the property is located,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H926DDBAB87B24CB780800E1AF91FC71B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>whether the property is owned or leased,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HCD641DC4FB79429880F3208FE866927D"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the aggregate value, as determined under regulations issued by the Secretary, of the items of qualified opportunity zone property held by the qualified opportunity fund as of each date described in section 1400Z–2(d)(1), and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB2A4335A80564DEFAB43491CDA7B9509"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of each building with 1 or more residential rental units—</text><clause id="HC5DC5D848AF949DBBB0DB5D2393991B1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total number of such residential rental units,</text></clause><clause id="H520F0A1E64F84D23B4A0C3EE63032B31"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the number of such units occupied by tenants with an income of 50 percent or less of area median income adjusted for family size,</text></clause><clause id="H57B5B97E590741A28E84E7E9BBB11DCB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the number of such units occupied by tenants with an income in excess of 50 percent, but not exceeding 60 percent of area median income adjusted for family size, and</text></clause><clause id="H52ADA9BD25AC429297C069D55A4B2A89"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>whether—</text><subclause id="HFE31EC0E19B04E87B27ECA2B604F3229"><enum>(I)</enum><text>at least 20 percent of such units are occupied by tenants described in clause (ii), or</text></subclause><subclause id="H5E30F1E58D1441C4A4261BDCBEE8E92C"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least 40 percent of such units are occupied by tenants with income averaging not more than 60 percent of area median income adjusted for family size,</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H3956DE4E9FBB4653B915CEA3688498D1"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the approximate average monthly number of full-time equivalent employees for the year of the trades or businesses of the qualified opportunity fund in which qualified opportunity zone business property is held (within numerical ranges identified by the Secretary) or such other indication of the employment impact of such trades or businesses as determined appropriate by the Secretary, which shall account for direct and indirect, temporary and permanent jobs,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H365966D2DB0C46E2AF88007FF93019EE"><enum>(8)</enum><text>with respect to each person who disposed of an investment in the qualified opportunity fund during the year—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H6CB592D3FC824174A6E7EB1680B9B616"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the name and taxpayer identification number of such person,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB0B20515C5FB4824B53EB892102B16ED"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date or dates on which the investment disposed was acquired, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HDADE3908F86A4A37A2C1FB93D6A9CCA1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the date or dates on which any such investment was disposed and the amount of the investment disposed, and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H68F904C2C23C410E86BD18C906BD99EB"><enum>(9)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H2CB7FA9024004D6EB3A57CEC175AAF0B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Statement required To be furnished to investors</header><text>Every person required to make a return under subsection (a) shall furnish to each person whose name is required to be set forth in such return by reason of subsection (b)(8) a written statement showing—</text><paragraph id="H1603F9167BB641D8BF2426D1614D5E53"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name, address and phone number of the information contact of the person required to make such return, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H02A4D00C8DA648D4AADD178F52BB8BF9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the information required to be shown on such return by reason of subsection (b)(8) with respect to such person.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HE5CF56BC6A84490194414920B5549638"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For purposes of this section—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HC603EB355C034616B9260C06585A1C29"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any term used in this section which is also used in subchapter Z of chapter 1 shall have the meaning given such term under such subchapter.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HC4221946DDDE408ABF140A1CDA98948A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Full-time equivalent employees</header><text>The term <term>full-time equivalent employees</term> means, with respect to any month, the sum of—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H856006F112254BD2816B02ACB8DE82D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of full-time employees (as defined in section 4980H(c)(4)) for the month, plus</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H631E85D397894C7EB821A79F983B5CE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of employees determined (under rules similar to the rules of section 4980H(c)(2)(E)) by dividing the aggregate number of hours of service of employees who are not full-time employees for the month by 120.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H2C1B140F222141A5B1885DBD312A4D69"><enum>6039L.</enum><header>Information on persons investing in qualified opportunity funds</header><subsection commented="no" id="HD005D4B320F14EB6B245BC83BA6EB8A5"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every taxpayer who makes an investment in a qualified opportunity fund shall provide an annual statement (at such time and in such manner as the Secretary may prescribe) containing the information described in subsection (b) with respect to each such investment.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="HB05563FB874E4F8DB36A5EFED39B5934"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Information from investors</header><text>The information described in this subsection is—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="HB7CA93C719D54C5887DE981D1D20CE7B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the name, address, and taxpayer identification number of the taxpayer,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HEFCF611E1E3F48D68C65AF6DECAC3E2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the name and taxpayer identification number of the qualified opportunity fund in which the investment was made,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H357DA8DAC3EA486AADA4D58C350463A0"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of such investment,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HA735DBDA9CC14867BE7A1E9CF5BB8B16"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the date such investment was made,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H49B67AC9F31A40658C27447B5B426A10"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the amount of short-term and long-term capital gains for which an election was made under section 1400Z–2(a)(1) for such investment,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H648864C74BED4521985882627BD7FDAE"><enum>(6)</enum><text>in the case of any disposition of any investment in a qualified opportunity fund during the taxable year—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H626D491444CD4F0793E2D4693C778BC1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the investment disposed,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H8B25E90ECA814D7096232DD36CE41065"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the date of the disposition, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HE875AA808C0B4879B0D55D18E9C82A65"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the amount of any previously deferred short-term and long-term capital gain included in income as a result of such disposition, and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="HEB1F0A0AE5D648A8835A9EB162D4EE9D"><enum>(7)</enum><text>such other information as the Secretary may require.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H4D5FAACA69974E73AFC72008502468B0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>Any term used in this section which is also used in subchapter Z of chapter 1 shall have the meaning given such term under such subchapter.</text></subsection></section><section commented="no" id="H3D995BECF2844021977CD2E1AA443F19"><enum>6039M.</enum><header>Information required from certain qualified opportunity zone businesses</header><subsection commented="no" id="H2BFE2B88DDFF43ADB349CF8C573D45D6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every applicable qualified opportunity zone business shall furnish to the qualified opportunity fund described in subsection (b) a written statement in such manner and setting forth such information as the Secretary may by regulations prescribe for purposes of enabling such qualified opportunity fund to meet the requirements of section 6039(b)(5).</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H05D7BA22040B4113A26E9917D9C17C5D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicable qualified opportunity zone business</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsection (a), the term <term>applicable qualified opportunity zone business</term> means any qualified opportunity zone business (as defined in section 1400Z–2(d)(3))—</text><paragraph commented="no" id="H79FECA2BDDA44DF0AEC9F3012B516F6D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">which is a trade or business of a qualified opportunity fund,</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H29635CC8C1B649DB9C5CCB429C362B42"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in which a qualified opportunity fund holds qualified opportunity zone stock, or</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H158347A488A24B61B599E754E56EE813"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in which a qualified opportunity fund holds a qualified opportunity zone partnership interest.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection commented="no" id="H5D03CF76B52843F9BDD342F96958A72B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Other terms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any term used in this section which is also used in subchapter Z of chapter 1 shall have the meaning given such term under such subchapter.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD0EC9276E3043DDAB5EAA4D975EBBC3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><subparagraph id="H503B5C1964A241EBA991B80144DE286C" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Part II of subchapter B of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/68">chapter 68</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after section 6725 the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H134F2D5EE5FD45919897BA64C5317778"><section id="H792BC65351674DD28C69CB44B2D41677" commented="no"><enum>6726.</enum><header>Failure to comply with information reporting requirements relating to qualified opportunity funds</header><subsection id="HEFDEA001D6204ED6B14294071CB65208" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Information returns by qualified opportunity funds</header><paragraph id="H33FB98B3EC854FF89E460F642A9798E7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any person required to file a return under section 6039K fails to file a complete and correct return under such section in the time and in the manner prescribed therefor, such person shall pay a penalty of $500 for each day during which such failure continues.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBA039A63E51408FAA680D0505CDCDED" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><subparagraph id="H1D5E659F3D3144ACA2CEE9DD9030234F" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The maximum penalty under this subsection on failures with respect to any 1 return shall not exceed $10,000.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCAF0D035C33A466AB732FD8A81137195" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Large qualified opportunity funds</header><text>In the case of any failure described in paragraph (1) with respect to a fund the gross assets of which (determined on the last day of the taxable year) are in excess of $10,000,000, subparagraph (A) shall be applied by substituting <quote>$50,000</quote> for <quote>$10,000</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9789F6954ECF4BF4A14196BE7CB2EEA0"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reduction where correction in specified period</header><text>If any failure described in paragraph (1) is corrected on or before the day 60 days after the due date (including extensions) for filing the return, the penalty imposed by paragraph (1) shall be $500 in lieu of the amount determined under such paragraph.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB912280B5A33446DA991D3AD8BC757B6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>De minimis errors</header><text>If—</text><subparagraph id="HC5E37CD6A8C94A3F8316447799CA7659"><enum>(A)</enum><text>there are one or more such failures described in paragraph (1) relating to an incorrect dollar amount, and no single amount in error differs from the correct amount by more than $100, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA99CE185BF5140EE8690ACA6704480F8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>there are one or more such failures described in paragraph (1) relating to a non-numerical amount and such error is inconsequential, then no correction shall be required, and, for purposes of this section, such statement shall be treated as having been filed with all correct required information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DB4C166A7BA42CEA247E31D4A07818D" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Penalty in cases of intentional disregard</header><text>If a failure described in paragraph (1) is due to intentional disregard, then—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H2675F005588948F5A5B441AE53B960E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paragraph (1) shall be applied by substituting <quote>$2,500</quote> for <quote>$500</quote>,</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H3611C8CC85A74395B4687E6584373D9D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>paragraph (2)(A) shall be applied by substituting <quote>$50,000</quote> for <quote>$10,000</quote>, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H909692DA55EB492D8BF778CF376A8728"><enum>(C)</enum><text>paragraph (2)(B) shall be applied by substituting <quote>$250,000</quote> for <quote>$50,000</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC9EF2949A7E4A29BBA89264195BDA7A" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header><subparagraph id="HE425247662F54B5FBD955886540FB5B7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any failure relating to a return required to be filed in a calendar year beginning after 2023, each of the dollar amounts in paragraphs (1), (2), (3), and (5) shall be increased by an amount equal to such dollar amount multiplied by the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year determined by substituting <quote>calendar year 2022</quote> for <quote>calendar year 2016</quote> in subparagraph (A)(ii) thereof.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C491D8E7AB449C996C496B599BB0E2F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rounding</header><clause id="H9FDA1712B0FD490183BE56B7C6DAACDB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the $500 dollar amount in paragraph (1), (3), or (5)(A) or the $2,500 amount in paragraph (5)(A), after being increased under subparagraph (A), is not a multiple of $10, such dollar amount shall be rounded to the next lowest multiple of $10.</text></clause><clause id="H5D52F79C556A4497BDF147DFA05F7C55" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Asset threshold</header><text>If the $10,000,000 dollar amount in paragraph (2)(B), after being increased under subparagraph (A), is not a multiple of $10,000, such dollar amount shall be rounded to the next lowest multiple of $10,000.</text></clause><clause id="H55550C577C034A2B8A54121ADCDEEB65" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Other dollar amounts</header><text>If any dollar amount in paragraph (2), (3), or (5) (other than any amount to which clause (i) or (ii) applies), after being increased under subparagraph (A), is not a multiple of $1,000, such dollar amount shall be rounded to the next lowest multiple of $1,000.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H40E34F0F10BE4B70884D59DEA43F845F" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Statements by investors</header><paragraph commented="no" id="HACD25E87E6F14C2DAF78C7B84074282E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If—</text><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1A76CD6A6A5048BFAE4C49D37EA0D423"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any person is required to file a statement under section 6039L for any period, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="H1CA1A734114E487D84298E14ECB4BB17"><enum>(B)</enum><text>fails—</text><clause commented="no" id="HEC818D86C3E842B5834EFFA91D19A659"><enum>(i)</enum><text>to file such statement on or before the required filing date, or</text></clause><clause commented="no" id="HDC316B8EA2DD421CAF82D6A9A0A663E1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>fails to include all of the information required to be shown on the statement or includes incorrect information,</text></clause></subparagraph><continuation-text commented="no" continuation-text-level="paragraph">such person shall pay a penalty of $5,000.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DDE2BD2AD5146C6A54229C8EE531079" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reduction where correction in specified period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any failure described in paragraph (1)(B) is corrected on or before the day 60 days after the due date (including extensions) for filing the return, the penalty imposed by paragraph (1) shall be $500 in lieu of the amount determined under such paragraph.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FB90157E1A44A6186406D6416C79B57" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>De minimis errors</header><text>If—</text><subparagraph id="H68749C403A0E40F68577347E50C4C168" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">there are one or more such failures described in paragraph (1)(B)(ii) relating to an incorrect dollar amount, and no single amount in error differs from the correct amount by more than $100, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H74238AA50F0143C8A99C706DC170E35C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">there are one or more such failures described in paragraph (1)(B)(ii) relating to a non-numerical amount and such error is inconsequential,</text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph" commented="no">then no correction shall be required, and, for purposes of this section, such statement shall be treated as having been filed with all correct required information.</continuation-text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34DC9E00A3BE42A0A5342B6DF9354116" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Penalty in cases of intentional disregard</header><text>If one or more failures described in paragraph (1)(B) are due to intentional disregard of the filing requirement (or the correct information reporting requirement), then, with respect to each such failure—</text><subparagraph id="HBFACF12D4302431EA6116FA8F633379E" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>paragraphs (2) and (3) shall not apply, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC89D7C58E1A64561ABABA3246B80AB63" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the amount of the penalty determined under paragraph (1) shall be $25,000.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7BBCC31522E34D07B97EB3661DF74164" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Inflation adjustment</header><subparagraph id="HF2F3E18B66A8454988961A737B9FB232" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any failure relating to a statement required to be filed in a calendar year beginning after 2023, each of the dollar amounts in paragraphs (1), (2), and (4) shall be increased by an amount equal to such dollar amount multiplied by the cost-of-living adjustment determined under section 1(f)(3) for the calendar year determined by substituting <quote>calendar year 2022</quote> for <quote>calendar year 2016</quote> in subparagraph (A)(ii) thereof.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD448BA7FFF049E8917747C8B1204EA2" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Rounding</header><text>The amount of any increase under subparagraph (A) shall be rounded to the nearest multiple of $100 ($10 in the case of any increase in the amount under paragraph (2)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA692E3F65C134EBC8B9B5CFF9D8F3EEF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information required to be sent to other taxpayers</header><text>Section 6724(d)(2) of such Code is amended—</text><clause id="HDBFA4E7C236F4FDDB80F465F297E23F3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or</quote> at the end of subparagraph (II),</text></clause><clause id="H695FAFA2C148401B864A727C89807E19"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of the first subparagraph (JJ) (relating to section 6226) and inserting a comma,</text></clause><clause id="H76C6809FB1634811B2C675E80BDDC054"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by redesignating the second subparagraph (JJ) (relating to section 6050Y) as subparagraph (KK),</text></clause><clause id="H860BEBAB9D3148958D6ED2E2175F186C"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end of subparagraph (KK) (as redesignated by clause (iii)) and inserting a comma, and</text></clause><clause id="H14F0CB92442A4D649FA53F7B28AAFCBA"><enum>(v)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (KK) (as so redesignated) the following new subparagraphs: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD685915CD21048D886E9969B088ABAE0"><subparagraph id="HCD36850B954842A9BD80C8FA6BF58E2D"><enum>(LL)</enum><text>section 6039K(c) (relating to disposition of qualified opportunity fund investments), or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC747332F04A4EF187478F71F6EC5028"><enum>(MM)</enum><text>section 6039M (relating to information required from certain qualified opportunity zone businesses).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8DA5DDC9FF954A75A001C771E17282C2" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Electronic filing</header><text>Section 6011(e) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H57AFCA5548034B5480A1C0BEA78DB304"><paragraph id="H60068E2B8A3440F7AAF35EDFFDD04445" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Qualified opportunity funds</header><text>Notwithstanding paragraphs (1) and (2), any return filed by a qualified opportunity fund shall be filed on magnetic media or other machine-readable form.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H71F1222A81C24C188BCE04C1B7730FAF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Clerical amendments</header><subparagraph id="HB168FDE5C7D9410EBEDDF2C3DDE9D59D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The table of sections for subpart A of part III of subchapter A of chapter 61 of such Code is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 6039J the following new items:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H46AA265360AB4AF9B45083AC17013CC6"><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="H272D02CA29CA4E51A352EDE484027FD2">Sec. 6039K. Returns with respect to qualified opportunity funds. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H2C1B140F222141A5B1885DBD312A4D69">Sec. 6039L. Information on persons investing in qualified opportunity funds. </toc-entry><toc-entry level="section" idref="H3D995BECF2844021977CD2E1AA443F19">Sec. 6039M. Information required from certain qualified opportunity zone businesses.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H014C4FC9851847F194726B4379953B89"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The table of sections for part II of subchapter B of chapter 68 of such Code is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 6725 the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H11D9C71C80CF4860902D29867D35C875"><toc><toc-entry idref="H792BC65351674DD28C69CB44B2D41677" level="section">Sec. 6726. Failure to comply with information reporting requirements relating to qualified opportunity funds.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H82D902D463E749CAA1D419BD8419F5D3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to taxable years beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA3371E4D6ED5490FB9599F556CC248EF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting of data on opportunity zone tax incentives</header><paragraph id="HACC4CC191FFE4739A693E46E1AFEDD47"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As soon as practical after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary of the Treasury, or the Secretary’s delegate (referred to in this section as the <term>Secretary</term>), in consultation with the Director of the Bureau of the Census and such other agencies as the Secretary determines appropriate, shall make publicly available a report on qualified opportunity funds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E09D5F186414ED1B9532453288AF0F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Information included</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under paragraph (1) shall include, to the extent available, the following information:</text><subparagraph id="H18BA38C9BFD44BE3883741241839B4CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of qualified opportunity funds.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71E551798DDD4947A94739363213949C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The aggregate dollar amount of assets held in qualified opportunity funds.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H286EF2BDF2AD4A30AC174811082B9650"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The aggregate dollar amount of investments made by qualified opportunity funds in qualified opportunity fund property across each industry class under the North American Industry Classification Code.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7694531CD195422C9900DE073BD1365D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The percentage of population census tracts designated as qualified opportunity zones that have received qualified opportunity fund investments.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A4F032893E8422D97B78D8F55848E5C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>For each population census tract designated as a qualified opportunity zone, the approximate average monthly number of full-time equivalent employees of the qualified opportunity zone businesses in such qualified opportunity zone for the preceding 12-month period (within numerical ranges identified by the Secretary) or such other indication of the employment impact of such qualified opportunity fund businesses as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB6958CD7505141E3A9D4BE6646794C2D"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The percentage of the total amount of investments made directly or indirectly by qualified opportunity funds in—</text><clause id="HED796AB1FF8C4C59942DEA656260DAB4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">qualified opportunity zone business property which is real property; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8C8963B8557C41FAB13747EEDF0064AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other qualified opportunity zone business property.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86347A0031084640909955FBB53BFD6F"><enum>(G)</enum><text>For each population census tract, the aggregate approximate number of residential units resulting from investments made by qualified opportunity funds in real property.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6F21BA7F7C1A43A59D428A5AD15F6FE4"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The aggregate dollar amount of investments made by qualified opportunity funds in each population census tract.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA2FE4822D4854D79876105FD56CF6030"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional information</header><subparagraph id="HD5FCA6DBEF684D7BABFF4116CE61CC96"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning with the report submitted under paragraph (1) for the 6th year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall include in such report the impacts and outcomes of a designation of a population census tract as a qualified opportunity zone as measured by economic indicators, such as job creation, poverty reduction, new business starts, and other metrics as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB9CB9E4D79C47B9A52B85250AC4621C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Semi-decennial information</header><clause id="H4AE635DBAAF4400CBDFE67F2E74FCDCA"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of any report submitted under paragraph (1) in the 6th year or the 11th year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall include the following information:</text><subclause id="H271773C050384B5DA99EFD5E67D59232"><enum>(I)</enum><text>For population census tracts designated as a qualified opportunity zone, a comparison (based on aggregate information) of the factors listed in clause (iii) between the 5-year period ending on the date of the enactment of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/115/97">Public Law 115–97</external-xref> and the most recent 5-year period for which data is available.</text></subclause><subclause id="H928552EEDA7D40D1BDB4234A7420DC46"><enum>(II)</enum><text>For population census tracts designated as a qualified opportunity zone, a comparison (based on aggregate information) of the factors listed in clause (iii) for the most recent 5-year period for which data is available between such population census tracts and a similar population census tracts that were not designated as a qualified opportunity zone.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H81C5ACEBC0FC45D7A15BDD1C3E73D330"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Control groups</header><text>For purposes of clause (i), the Secretary may combine population census tracts into such groups as the Secretary determines appropriate for purposes of making comparisons.</text></clause><clause id="H57AC61D956A6425E9F7CE1A4777950AA"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Factors listed</header><text>The factors listed in this paragraph are the following:</text><subclause id="H40C0F80345A140BF9F8597A4D04ED977"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The unemployment rate.</text></subclause><subclause id="H92B46BE4FACB48249B620946BA48C7E4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The number of persons working in the population census tract, including the percentage of such persons who were not residents in the population census tract in the preceding year.</text></subclause><subclause id="HA23B1D6D2CB9440CAAE59DA4D119B73B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Individual, family, and household poverty rates.</text></subclause><subclause id="H3C9C4598988149F39B95CDBD4D521398"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Median family income of residents of the population census tract.</text></subclause><subclause id="HC6C001B677F942778EA371DCF9240C17"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Demographic information on residents of the population census tract, including age, income, education, race, and employment.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6B474678BB804DBFBC8964E3DA772DA0"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>The average percentage of income of residents of the population census tract spent on rent annually.</text></subclause><subclause id="H6F20E0568040423BB9BC367CC2195643"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>The number of residences in the population census tract.</text></subclause><subclause id="H02F842C8CEB94A0C86B86C19773E07AD"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>The rate of home ownership in the population census tract. </text></subclause><subclause id="HC63F5E13A09844F097331B2BF3F94F47"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>The average value of residential property in the population census tract.</text></subclause><subclause id="H16BC0CF0C78949718C17F29C1A438D87"><enum>(X)</enum><text>The number of affordable housing units in the population census tract.</text></subclause><subclause id="H29BD510F3C3D4B098FA3A23AAC3A25BD"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>The number and percentage of residents in the population census tract that were not employed for the preceding year.</text></subclause><subclause id="H826C1F31B51C4A1C91F5066FEB50457C"><enum>(XII)</enum><text>The number of new business starts in the population census tract.</text></subclause><subclause id="H9D03901EC208433D861CA13C2720ABC4"><enum>(XIII)</enum><text>The distribution of employees in the population census tract by North American Industry Classification Code.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H966E46B2EC934E74939CEE991CBF3A22"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Protection of identifiable return information</header><text>In making reports required under this subsection, the Secretary—</text><subparagraph id="H38228316F7A147DE9C717317FE4B4A3F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall establish appropriate procedures to ensure that any amounts reported do not disclose taxpayer return information that can be associated with any particular taxpayer or competitive or proprietary information, </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD980249504024F909EC19EC2DEDB1973"><enum>(B)</enum><text>if necessary to protect taxpayer return information, may combine information required with respect to individual population census tracts into larger geographic areas, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72EA4AC03552472E9FBFE7015371955A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall treat any violation of this paragraph as a violation of section 6103.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H73F304E0A205484C950A6B23EE821AB6"><enum>(5)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any term used in this subsection which is also used in subchapter Z of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 shall have the meaning given such term under such subchapter.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><title style="OLC" id="HD87C5F72252D4960A6C79633DA426401"><enum>III</enum><header>Modification of rules for investments in qualified opportunity funds</header><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H5E1014599950439695ECA1FC1585EF97"><enum>301.</enum><header>Extension of deferral and investment period</header><subsection id="H60B4124C72344E6EB20BE3370A20C105"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subparagraph (B) of sections 1400Z–2(a)(2) and 1400Z–2(b)(1) of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by striking <quote>December 31, 2026</quote> and inserting <quote>December 31, 2028</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="H86867B0A5D824966ABB6F760D7A4F028" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to amounts invested after December 22, 2017.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF44D0EE366564D2BB6C9A863FEF5554F"><enum>302.</enum><header>Modification of definition of qualified opportunity fund</header><subsection id="H7938576704D84C0ABA08BB67B94A1F28"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1400Z">Section 1400Z–2(d)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA650F8EF894C488EA8C925D4BC70B415"><paragraph id="HC920CC79484741ACA7A8C6833EFB2EEB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>qualified opportunity fund</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HA27DD7F3D70C46329E2745C4948E5F04"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any qualified feeder fund, or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24BB68E6CE5E49CABC3154026824BC23"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any other investment vehicle if—</text><clause id="H0D1FC56C09BC41C98B173D2A9030B348"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such investment vehicle is organized as a corporation or a partnership for the purpose of investing in qualified opportunity zone property (other than another qualified opportunity fund), and</text></clause><clause id="H5A696A75937B47C2B7B8A6E3C80716B0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>such investment vehicle holds at least 90 percent of its assets in qualified opportunity zone property, determined by the average of the percentage of qualified opportunity zone property held in the fund as measured—</text><subclause id="HB7D3BB68B1E7478C9F4D957A83298A5F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>on the last day of the first 6-month period of the taxable year of the fund, and</text></subclause><subclause id="H63E6163CE2884D6CBA4A7FE1EA2CC60D"><enum>(II)</enum><text>on the last day of the taxable year of the fund.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HDBBAA51199C942D78468393E637E4759"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualified feeder fund</header><text>Section 1400Z–2(d) of such Code is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA3E53BFC4254FDA8EF10458BF66C8F0"><paragraph id="HF2D9CCBC9649490686ECD4475C15A8FE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Qualified feeder fund</header><text>The term <term>qualified feeder fund</term> means any investment vehicle that invests in a qualified opportunity fund if—</text><subparagraph id="H02A19EB3E6C045D8BAEA848CE8D502E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such investment vehicle is organized as a domestic partnership for the purpose of investing in one more corporations or partnerships described in paragraph (1)(B),</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A6103B529D141F88E12F9E0F680C9EE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>all investments made in the investment vehicle are made in cash, and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80DDA205F69149DA90B59E8BAF980F17"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not less than 95 percent of the assets of which are equity investments in corporations or partnerships described in paragraph (1)(B) as measured—</text><clause id="HD794CA4019C44A89965B47E79823AED3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>on the last day of the first 6-month period of the taxable year of the feeder fund, and</text></clause><clause id="HEE4D4E64F0A24704844887801F3FCF4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>on the last day of the tax- able year of the feeder fund.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H0E1BE5642E744C68A1FA892338B94792"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="H5D722B5077B046B9B401D20143BEFFC0"><enum>IV</enum><header>State and community dynamism fund</header><section id="H56DB89BAB66F4701A21472E0023E2F94"><enum>401.</enum><header>State and community dynamism fund</header><subsection id="H32F5C6E5A37A4DC78BDC95ED51297837"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established a State and Community Dynamism Fund to support public and private investment, including capital for qualified opportunity zones designated under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1400Z">section 1400Z–1(a)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, and existing small business and community economic development programs and incentives, to underserved businesses and communities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3B0A8428B59C48C7BFA241E2974EDECF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Allocation</header><paragraph id="H0F117FB9B48D4081BEBE3B41B36C3B51"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Funds appropriated to the State and Community Dynamism Fund shall be allocated to States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96ACB75F494A4FAB96475B8C98774F9E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Formula</header><subparagraph id="H6AB35A9E26144B0299C4CBF9DFF0F5F7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury shall determine the allocation by allocating Federal funds among the States based on the proportion of prime working age adults not employed in each State bears to the total of prime working age adults not employed for all the States. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBF4D8EF6F96435EB5C071022241EFB9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Minimum allocation</header><text>The Secretary shall adjust the allocations under subparagraph (A) for each State to the extent necessary to ensure that no State receives less than 0.9 percent of the Federal funds.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0A97C990ECD4934B7F5D40F8C0070D7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>To receive an allocation under paragraph (2), a State shall certify that the State will use funds to—</text><subparagraph id="H34352E2B3403414F9729A2AFA3DDF455"><enum>(A)</enum><text>build capacity in high-poverty, underbanked, rural, and otherwise underserved communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC8672C8F570643FE87BE0EE8BE899D2E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>advance investment in minority-, women, and veteran-owned businesses;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBA18BC978A84A579B8D4B3D105E2235"><enum>(C)</enum><text>address workforce development in strategic sectors of the State’s economy; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF47E6AC8C83F4822A778859ACF5489F1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>align priorities to support affordably priced housing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50ADA2B97BC04DA2993C800CDABE43F0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Suballocation</header><text>A State may spend funds allocated under this subsection directly or suballocate the funds to other entities, including units of general local government and nonprofits.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C14E53486184647A0BD393EFF8B6B4E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible uses</header><text>Funds allocated under this subsection shall be used for any eligible use in a low-income community, as defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/45D">section 45D(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, including for—</text><subparagraph id="H40D5A523973C48269872FAAD6B2C2848"><enum>(A)</enum><text>operating support and community capacity building, with priority to given to operating support and community capacity building in qualified opportunity zones, including—</text><clause id="HD75AA31F9ED74E74AD2A30962677EBB0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>personnel to support activities, including coordination, education, and investment;</text></clause><clause id="HF2B88474EBCB41319FCDDA46E48E53B8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>community-level capacity building, training, and strategic planning;</text></clause><clause id="H6F62169C2EBA4EF192192F5888B439B5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>outreach, technical assistance, and professional services to underserved businesses and underserved opportunity zone fund managers;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5164FBEAF2844319A281E50E433FCDAC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>high-impact projects, including—</text><clause id="H90D62D6568754D4B902FEDF903A8C0EF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>predevelopment costs associated with individual Qualified Opportunity Zone projects; and</text></clause><clause id="H81533B3029F44398A044857BC1CED4EA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>risk mitigation for qualified opportunity zone funds; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3312CE763D5D46D2A45563B8CD0BC771"><enum>(C)</enum><text>administrative costs, not to exceed 3 percent of the funds allocated.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8449B2B8C3074601B7ED27D52D9E8BCE"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Eligible projects</header><text>Funds used for high-impact project activities, as described in paragraph (5)(B), shall only be used for—</text><subparagraph id="H28A357CCAF734D9EB52FB7EB0FA0BC41"><enum>(A)</enum><text>business with less than 200 employees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2293B77F9767443D982C2E1EA212E8D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>projects that provide community goods or services, including health care, social services, healthy food access, education, broadband, and culture; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC357269AD144B3187C40A23137F6C8B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>affordable housing with at least 50 percent of the units that are affordable to families making less than 80 percent of area median family income.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5F4AD2607704FA8BE6957FD08D28AE1"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text>A State that receives funds under this section must prioritize activities that—</text><subparagraph id="HB575B68881684C829012B322862F3DE5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote investment in projects that substantially support minorities, as defined in section 1204(c) of the Financial Institutions Reform, Recovery, and Enforcement Act of 1989 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1811">12 U.S.C. 1811</external-xref> note), or other targeted populations, as defined in section 103 of the Riegle Community Development and Regulatory Improvement Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/4702">12 U.S.C. 4702</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51C1958509644F8299FD2FE106352F78"><enum>(B)</enum><text>have demonstrated meaningful engagement with community stakeholders.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C31D20CD88A4F8DA7D30CD731570D0F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated $1,000,000,000 to carry out this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF9BB613AB8FC418FB0D3CE9B44DE5543"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Gao audit</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall perform an annual audit of the Fund and submit to the appropriate committees of Congress a report containing the results of the audit.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4638922A70F0424B8AA85D2253E45CCB"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text>Not later than March 31 of each year, each State receiving funds under this title shall submit to the Secretary a report on the performance of the State and participating entities in the State that includes—</text><paragraph id="H27252F7E4A2E4651AFEE00C05CE33D3B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an accounting of the expenditure of funds received by the State, including on administrative or indirect costs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDCC9D6D719734B2D81A3BEC97508C4C4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>information on the number and characteristics of participants served under this title; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25C86C6A1CA243CD99AE6445BAB2CD6A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a summary describing the training, capacity-building, and technical assistance offered by the State and participating entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE9B99AD99DEE4F72921358438DD8F0AD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HDC4866775ED749C58862B7C2E2317740"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prime working age adults not employed</header><text>The term <term>prime working age adults not employed</term> means, with respect to a State, the share of the adult population aged 25 to 54 that was not employed for the most recent year for which data is available. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B4006CC78DB4CFC94C5659E7B4EAB03"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> includes the District of Columbia, any territory or possession of the United States, and any Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

