<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDF82F5B71ED043B4B7748673D071B0A0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5113 IH: REACH Our Tribes Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5113</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230801">August 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000600">Mr. Langworthy</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Crop Insurance Reform and Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 to establish a budgetary Tribal Government consultation process at the Department of Agriculture, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB23F893F2AC84E438AE349A9E2C496FB" style="OLC"><section id="H01A65DD3CA7F4C7BA741D4EBB74A4126" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Economic-development Assistance and Consultation to Help Our Tribes Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote>REACH Our Tribes Act</quote>.</text></section><section id="HE0E4C8DBF5F94979B40AC18F31BFD60D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishing a budgetary Tribal Government consultation process at the Department of Agriculture</header><subsection id="H28A8571F9A9A40AD8E82F72ACD4D542F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 309 of the Federal Crop Insurance Reform and Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/6921">7 U.S.C. 6921</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAE9C38AFBFD849AE82B5819BDC75830F" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H5852908F35ED46D288EC99B35D7027E4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Budgetary Tribal Government consultation process</header><paragraph id="H52BBD8C747294507BF8F478C1B7C8209"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of the <short-title>Rural Economic-development Assistance and Consultation to Help Our Tribes Act</short-title>, the Secretary, in consultation with the Office of Tribal Relations and the Office of Budget and Program Analysis of the Department of Agriculture, shall establish, finalize, and implement a formal process for consultation with Tribal Governments on at least an annual basis, on—</text><subparagraph id="HD077148B9BA14971A73B88FA619A401E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>annual budget requests; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCEB06CE108064BE7839D81CA15C4F99F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>bills proposing the reauthorization of certain Department of Agriculture programs over a period of multiple years with budgetary impacts, including bills providing for the reauthorization of Department of Agriculture programs (commonly known as farm bills).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H784933C596CE4D338B4C5254BEF8A126"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The consultation process under paragraph (1) shall require the Secretary to provide notice to Tribal Governments of a consultation not later than 30 days before the date on which such consultation is to occur.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H678BDD96E008462D895155AAAFC9CEEF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in consultation with Tribal Governments, shall develop and implement a mechanism for reporting on any consultation that occurs pursuant to paragraph (1). Such a report shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H733276A52FDF49E9A6AD4CBF65A9014B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a summary of issues consulted on;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE8038F45A8534E62AF81DD10AF1785B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>comments received during that consultation from Tribal Governments; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0ADFA10E941449C2A000BA9D1F66710E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>if applicable, steps taken, or to be taken, by the Secretary in response to such consultation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BC03161D4EE4CA28E1AE3210F2B940C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Scope</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The consultation process under paragraph (1) shall not be limited only to programs that are specific to Indian Tribes, but may include programs that may impact Indian Tribes and Tribal entities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5C4B547E4364A98A7015E3AF7CA7191"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed as limiting the Secretary from—</text><subparagraph id="H5CAFCD119F7C4CD8950CC0059AFE4DA1"><enum>(A)</enum><text>conducting other consultations with Tribal Governments or other entities, as specified under another provision of Federal law; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1C05B3529DC54DBDAD921048A2DEB928"><enum>(B)</enum><text>advancing other practices to conduct such consultations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H8B20FD688DEC426B9E82357A028039D7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Agriculture shall submit to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate a report on—</text><paragraph id="H1A10816CC8FD4D30868531160152AC7A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>how the Secretary developed the Tribal Government consultation process under subsection (c) of section 309 of the Federal Crop Insurance Reform and Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/6921">7 U.S.C. 6921</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a) of this section; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5821977EE66B4419BED466C223D696AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a detailed description of the consultation process so developed. </text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0F84739ED62D4E6A951DB8C87CB2D323"><enum>3.</enum><header>Requiring Department of Agriculture to report program funding to Tribal entities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 309 of the Federal Crop Insurance Reform and Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/6921">7 U.S.C. 6921</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H919327B771AD4FBFB0CEDF6D927B2EF0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H578A04F7477443FD9561198EB460F586"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Program funding reporting</header><text>The Secretary and the Office of Tribal Relations shall, in consultation with Tribal Governments, establish a plan for analyzing and publicly reporting to Tribal entities on funding provided through programs administered by the Secretary for which such entities are eligible to apply. In conducting such analysis, the Secretary shall identify ways to improve assistance provided through such programs to Tribal entities, including through conducting additional outreach to provide technical assistance for such programs that are underutilized by Tribal entities.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H2C220EFAE1234490A6CD132520FBAB91"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions relating to Tribes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 309 of the Federal Crop Insurance Reform and Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/6921">7 U.S.C. 6921</external-xref>), as amended by section 2, is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HE4D139C5FB03444B9B8F4681DE74D324" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HDF527D66E3AC41DEA84AAF3FC8430D89"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><paragraph id="H396A6473107C430FBA1FA6A60A04698B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In this section:</text><subparagraph id="H8147829D1300438DB61EE58835A3E9BB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The term <quote>1994 Institution</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 532 of the Equity in Educational Land-Grant Status Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/301">7 U.S.C. 301</external-xref> note). </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF025D2B3BF7045148E6EFCA92D7F504B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The term <term>Tribal entity</term> means an Indian Tribe, Tribal organization, Tribal Government, 1994 Institution, Urban Indian organization, tribally-owned or tribally-controlled business or non-profit organization, an arm or instrumentality of one or more Indian Tribes, or a business or nonprofit organization owned or controlled by one or more members of an Indian Tribe.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80BA92579ABC46AB89539C5B1981401A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <term>Urban Indian organization</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Health Care Improvement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/1603">25 U.S.C. 1603</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE598344A9F240C29CF640A85177A924"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Tribal Government</term> means the governing body of any Indian or Alaska Native Tribe, band, nation, pueblo, village, community, component band or component reservation, individually identified (including parenthetically) in the list published most recently as of the date of enactment of this Act pursuant to section 104 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5131">25 U.S.C. 5131</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF0F05B982A6641FE9A2A52B90A658F57"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The term <term>Tribal organization</term> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Educational Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC0E75C961C4B46A89F97DF1E307216FF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsections (c) and (d), the term <quote>Indian Tribe</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 102 of the Federally Recognized Indian Tribe List Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5130">25 U.S.C. 5130</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H9452D6492ED5409F9D0CF6D26B52972F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Interagency task force on economic development programs</header><subsection id="H525E886177AB493C80F0F277A36BE7DC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Agriculture, in consultation with the Secretary for Housing and Urban Development and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development, shall establish an interagency task force—</text><paragraph id="HA4048DDA021547A68F845EF33E476B45"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to review guidance and application requirements for economic development programs administered by the Secretary of Agriculture; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C6339CC89F34FBDAA3796E2740B27A5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to develop interagency agreements to reduce administrative and planning burdens for applicants to such programs and the Federal agencies administering such programs.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF161345A9FD14B02BFE4573B6E4DE521"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Composition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The interagency task force established under subsection (a) shall be composed of the following:</text><paragraph id="H508C007774954E0D818AC129B4EF3B4E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Deputy Under Secretary for Rural Development of the Department of Agriculture (or their designee).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77845731E493431DAB7640C5F1BAF690"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development (or their designee). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB000634D8B3474DBF83CBF4F9EE6437"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Principal Deputy Assistant Secretary for Community Planning and Development of the Department of Housing and Urban Development (or their designee).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CACD1133B974DCEA6E2A0F846421604"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other individuals or officials as determined appropriate by the Secretary of Agriculture, in consultation with the Secretary for Housing and Urban Development and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE32195FE084748E3A41F6CD9FC94E257"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The task force established under subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="H2B5953ED205A4D599BC47A70135F88FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in developing the agreements under subsection (a), identify opportunities for the Secretary of Agriculture, the Secretary for Housing and Urban Development, and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development—</text><subparagraph id="H2128E092701248ECA214231024E556F3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to align strategic planning requirements, stakeholder engagement requirements, and other application requirements; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEBC3CA5DD40E411B93BACCCA61488D11"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to issue joint guidance across programs of each such agency; and </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H84124DCC49714B08976597D71331596C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish a plan for regularly reviewing and updating interagency agreements entered into pursuant to subsection (a) to ensure that such agreements—</text><subparagraph id="HA1105A92A4CA44B6BB71A88286A2ACEE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">advance shared economic development objectives;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EE37AA0C8CA41D88C3F0623FA94954B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce applicant administrative and planning burdens;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H734B3CE979C54812A46EFACC34EE1360"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce technical assistance needs;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6B7FB423B7F410592C5D2F3CDFFEA44"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce duplication in agency efforts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H594C34B6A8714E9A82EF4D236C276C79"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve collaboration across Federal, State, and local agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3AB3CAF013A84E6C9E2F990A1791B2BC"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encourage and improve stakeholder and community engagement.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H93F18B35D7E940ECBCFD507D395F1454"><enum>6.</enum><header>Establishing a comprehensive repository of Federal Tribal economic development programs</header><subsection id="H91AD0ECC3258471AA444E671C6D92C31"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Commerce, in consultation with the Office of Native American Business Development, shall establish and implement a working group to develop, and regularly update, a comprehensive and public repository of Federal economic development programs available to Tribal entities <italic></italic>(as defined in subsection (e) of section 309 of the Federal Crop Insurance Reform and Department of Agriculture Reorganization Act of 1994 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/6921">7 U.S.C. 6921</external-xref>), as added by section 4) to—</text><paragraph id="H5DC6CAFB2D584C47804E895FC3B1D0AD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reduce agency and applicant administrative burden in identifying Tribal economic development programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A5F21E0584C437AB92AD347279268A7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>improve awareness and utilization of Tribal economic development programs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2427A975E58F46B1A6A57808C30EBF35"><enum>(3)</enum><text>improve the ability of the Office of Native American Business Development to assist Tribal entities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H519C9BEAE05E488FABE6A28DCAE57027"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The working group established under subsection (a) shall be composed of representatives of—</text><paragraph id="H8832F54C1E214E388CFB6A07419C2DFB"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Office of Native American Business Development;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71C41B76FA2F4C1BBBFF49B932826C7E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Economic Development Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B7CE546B0E848AB901B4D13B7AE09C8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Small Business Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC0BC106CCAF4900A6A8750F5815753A"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Department of Agriculture;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE86B6127EFBF4324A2D8BB928E1A28AD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Department of Education;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H160B82B02B8349398CB46A1104F79834"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Department of Health and Human Services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC56D001881114E81982BD5CD68A059B4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Department for Housing and Rural Development;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2402711CE450445FAD636B3B97FE1B97"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Department of the Interior; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7CC241E141D14344B5866074E2382240"><enum>(9)</enum><text>such other Federal offices or agencies, as determined appropriate by the Secretary of Commerce.<italic></italic></text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0289241A7B68412283A2FC6699310199"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><italic></italic>The working group established under subsection (a) shall—</text><paragraph id="H2BA4C85CE3AC430DB02F78543D1277E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify economic development programs across Federal agencies for which Tribal entities are eligible to participate or receive assistance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H357A199890594DDD8A619B27A722157F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish a comprehensive publicly accessible repository of information on such programs;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5CFBA199CFE42DA8219A3EC3EBDA2F6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop and execute a plan for sharing such repository with Federal, State, and local agencies and Tribal entities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5F2D042A2AA4A18B42CD627D9A82FE4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop and execute a plan for regularly reviewing and updating such repository once at least every 2 years.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

