<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF2DF0DE2BEF84B1DBB5C936E4B5A823F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1111 IH: Department of Peacebuilding Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1111</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230221">February 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a Department of Peacebuilding, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1F491060658F46B6BC2B938BCE02CABF" style="OLC"><section id="H62D16E667E3348F4BFC2A9230A44A237" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="HDDA1985B2F3B4FA48F23F0E25BF44081"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text>This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Department of Peacebuilding Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF1931BF49FCC4125A8C613AC456DECD2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration"><toc-entry idref="H62D16E667E3348F4BFC2A9230A44A237" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HAA93AD3B8456401EA04ABA016A606EF4" level="section">Sec. 2. Findings.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBB929306C3E348E4B9847FB685298273" level="title">Title I—Establishment of Department of Peacebuilding</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H194EBAB88A5940F59BC5CECE74A900B0" level="section">Sec. 101. Establishment of Department of Peacebuilding.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HC816D7AA4A3944E9A94820308C408EFF" level="section">Sec. 102. Responsibilities and powers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8D19279AD33840B7A90279EDD57D5080" level="section">Sec. 103. Principal officers.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB751F7F2086448ADBB7AFB80631D4C89" level="section">Sec. 104. Office of Peace Education and Training.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9EE97C43DC924A628146B2B361E58893" level="section">Sec. 105. Office of Domestic Peacebuilding Activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H3FF80440FDE04CA4848D2671CE22F86C" level="section">Sec. 106. Office of International Peacebuilding Activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HAAEF828A12FE46748B0D634D216088D7" level="section">Sec. 107. Office of Technology for Peace.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDCCF1ACE4A4E4C3D9D507448BDC48758" level="section">Sec. 108. Office of Arms Control and Disarmament.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB752E6C4095B435181257CB0C89A4832" level="section">Sec. 109. Office of Peacebuilding Information and Research.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB5631C43D57D4A2F9EE5BBB8DC03A842" level="section">Sec. 110. Office of Human Rights and Economic Rights.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF1387FE4BCAB40A7B433E4D19AB278E4" level="section">Sec. 111. Intergovernmental Advisory Council on Peace.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF9B554431D05495AA0DCD9DC36B155AB" level="section">Sec. 112. Federal Interagency Committee on Peace.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF1267A3B424D491D8395FEC942C1E474" level="section">Sec. 113. Staff.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7659753D27294ABF894DDF3C92429D7B" level="section">Sec. 114. Consultation required.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HE02B4C5776B3424D893158DF908A3D96" level="section">Sec. 115. Collaboration.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0F8ACB603D8A491FB17C011204328923" level="title">Title II—Other Matters</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HFB251080009448C4860B7D8D5D902DA3" level="section">Sec. 201. Legislative recommendations of the Secretary.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF9955CB977A349C19CBFCDB17280A4CA" level="section">Sec. 202. Peace Days.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBF5C82657FFB478181F7C88A49FEEE2F" level="section">Sec. 203. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA889302A0E674CA1B623E0A99AA2E4D5" level="section">Sec. 204. Authorization of appropriations.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="HAA93AD3B8456401EA04ABA016A606EF4"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H03F192C9C4904013BC2314AF96D70F55"><enum>(1)</enum><text>On July 4, 1776, the Second Continental Congress unanimously declared the independence of the 13 colonies, and the achievement of peace was recognized as one of the highest duties of the new organization of free and independent States by declaring, <quote>We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H418BDD19ADDE466B8C15D3DFAA7AAE40"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Constitution of the United States, in its preamble, further sets forth the insurance of the cause of peace in stating, <quote>We the People of the United States, in Order to form a more perfect Union, establish Justice, insure domestic Tranquility, provide for the common defense, promote the general Welfare, and secure the Blessings of Liberty to ourselves and our Posterity</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD240FA41843A4BD593646E713CF1F07F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The United States has been at peace for only 21 entire years since its birth during the Revolutionary War. During the course of the 20th century, more than 100,000,000 people perished in wars. Thus far in the 21st century, nearly 1,000,000 people have died in conflict and war. Many of our citizens today have never known a peaceful year in their lifetimes. In 2022, over 88 million people were forcibly displaced due to violence in its many forms.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E0EC02CA27F44EDBA6F6144959B2389" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Since late 2001, the United States appropriated and was obligated to spend an estimated $6.4 trillion through Fiscal Year 2020 in budgetary costs related to and caused by post 9/11 wars and an additional minimum of $1 trillion to care for veterans of these wars for several decades.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H03AE462950F842A3BADAFB8321A620A8"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The physical, emotional, monetary, and other costs of violence are enormous, cut across all sectors of society in the United States, disproportionately impact people of color, and are interrelated. A World Health Organization report estimates that interpersonal violence within the United States costs approximately $300 billion annually, not including war-related costs. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention reports one in four children experience some form of child abuse or neglect in their lifetimes; nearly one in four women report having experienced severe physical violence from an intimate partner; Native American women are sexually assaulted, murdered and disappeared at higher rates than other American women. There are 3.3 million reports of violence against children that result in foster care placements every year; 25 percent of kids in foster care experience PTSD, fewer than 3 percent earn a college degree; 20 percent become homeless after the age of 18; and only 50 percent will be employed by the age of 24. One in five high school students reported being bullied at school during 2017 and cyberbullying impacts many young people. Criminalization disproportionately impacts African Americans and other people of color, including high rates of school suspensions and expulsions and incarceration. African Americans are incarcerated at more than five times the rate of Whites. Suicide impacts young people in both affluent and non-affluent communities. In 2015, 17 percent of students considered attempting suicide. Suicide is the second leading cause of death among American Indian and Alaska Natives aged 10 to 34. Approximately 20 veterans a day commit suicide nationwide. About 14 young people die from homicides each day. Research shows victims of one form of violence are more likely to experience other forms of violence. A past history of violence, including domestic violence; use of alcohol or illegal drugs; being young and male; or a personal history of physical or sexual abuse or trauma, increases the risk of more violence, obesity, high-risk sexual behavior, depression, academic difficulties, school dropout and suicide. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE6ACF8744BEB4CEC958A01757ED8B07E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>More people have died from guns in the United States since 1968 than on battlefields of all the wars in United States history. Every year 250,000 people are killed by gun violence around the world, a third of those in Brazil and the United States. Firearms are the second leading cause of death for American children and teens and the first leading cause of death for Black children and teens. Every day 47 children and teens in the United States are shot and 96 Americans are killed by gun violence. During 2017 and 2018, there was one mass shooting almost every day in the United States. Young people go to school wondering where to hide when a shooter enters their classroom. Each gun injury and fatality results in trauma to family members and loved ones. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11464CC0F03F4687BC083FB722AF0A33"><enum>(7)</enum><text>According to reports by the Institute of Economics and Peace (in this Act referred to as <quote>IEP</quote>), which measures the economic impact of violence and conflict to the global economy, the economic impact of violence to the global economy was $16.5 trillion in 2021. One IEP report found that the regional impact of violence in North America, 99 percent of which can be attributed to the United States, amounted to $2.73 trillion in 2017. If violence containment spending was reduced by 15 percent, the world would save $1.4 trillion, which would be the funding required to achieve the United Nations Millennium Development Goals of halving extreme poverty rates, ensuring healthy lives for all, halting the spread of HIV and AIDS, providing universal primary education, decent jobs, gender equality, promoting peaceful, inclusive and just societies, and more. Three percent of United States military spending could end starvation on earth. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7E42D3BC730D45EF8E0A1C736CB85230"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Peace is a human right and a security issue. Peace is the essential prerequisite for the survival of humanity as we know it in the 21st century. The United Nations defines human rights as those rights which are inherent to our nature, and without which we cannot live as human beings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6AE0C5D1276748E8BEB3BB8D38B379B9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Violence prevention is cost effective. For every dollar spent on violence prevention and peacebuilding, thousands of lives and dollars are saved. Research indicates that investing early to prevent conflicts from escalating into violent crises is, on average, 60 times more cost effective than intervening after violence erupts. The philosophy and techniques of nonviolence and the science of peacebuilding provide tools and techniques that can be applied not only at the levels of individual and community growth, but also within the Federal Government and at national and international levels.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFCBBC9556B2943279F6DF5332BAB29EB"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United Nations recognizes that promotion of peace is vital for the full enjoyment of all human rights and the United Nations Declaration on the Right of Peoples to Peace mandates that preservation of the right to peace is a fundamental obligation of each country. In 1999, the United Nations adopted a Programme of Action on a Culture of Peace, stating that a culture of peace is an integral approach to preventing violence and violent conflicts, an alternative to the culture of war and violence, and is based on education for peace, the promotion of sustainable economic and social development, respect for human rights, equality between women and men, democratic participation, tolerance, the free flow of information, and disarmament. The United Nations declared the years 2001 through 2010 an International Decade for a Culture of Peace and Non-Violence for the Children of the World, and the United Nations supports a culture of peace. In 2015, the United Nations adopted 17 sustainable development goals, including promotion of peaceful and inclusive societies which recognize the link between justice, human rights, and government based on the rule of law and peace.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H125A315E4E4D49BABD436748B48FF4A6"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Peacebuilding is defined by the United Nations as a range of measures targeted to reduce the risk of lapsing or relapsing into conflict by strengthening national capacities at all levels for conflict management and to lay the foundations for sustainable peace and development. Peacebuilding is built upon research into the root causes of violence in the United States and the world, through promotion and promulgation of effective policies and programs that ameliorate those root causes of violence, and through providing all citizens, organizations, and governmental bodies with opportunities to learn about and practice the essential tools of nonviolent conflict resolution and peacebuilding.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A6B9A77D131485C8FE630C489B6EF35"><enum>(12)</enum><text>In 2000, the Earth Charter Commission released the Earth Charter, an international declaration of fundamental values and principles created to build a just, sustainable, and peaceful global society. The preamble of the Earth Charter provides, <quote>To move forward we must recognize that in the midst of a magnificent diversity of cultures and life forms we are one human family and one Earth community with a common destiny. We must join together to bring forth a sustainable global society founded on respect for nature, universal human rights, economic justice, and a culture of peace.</quote>. Peacebuilding is working together with all nations to protect both life and land and hold the Earth in balance.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6602B9F6AF024A69ADD2F1D02FF4AF77" commented="no"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Anthropomorphic climate change threatens not only the earth and all beings, but also impacts the present lives of our children and robs them of hope for a safe future. A 2021 Lancet global health study of 10,000 youth found 59 percent are <quote>very</quote> or <quote>extremely concerned</quote> about climate change and its impact on their mental health.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H395AA2517AE54FE4AF34CA63A4128E12" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><text>Nuclear weapons expose the world to harm on a vast scale. It has long been held that a nuclear war cannot be won and must never be fought. Yet, over the next 30 years, the United States plans to spend some $1.7 trillion to replace its entire nuclear weapons infrastructure and upgrade replacement of its nuclear bombs and warheads and the bombers, missiles and submarines that deliver them.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E4260060260414DA4977FDF3A068CAF"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Systemic racism is a significant driver of violence and key obstacle to peace in the United States. Confronting and uprooting systemic racism in America will require efforts by the Federal Government both to properly acknowledge, memorialize, and be a catalyst for progress toward permanently eliminating persistent racial inequities, including through a United States Commission on Truth, Racial Healing, and Transformation, and to develop material remedies for the institution of slavery, including through a United States Commission to Study and Develop Reparation Proposals for African-Americans.</text></paragraph></section><title id="HBB929306C3E348E4B9847FB685298273"><enum>I</enum><header>Establishment of Department of Peacebuilding</header><section id="H194EBAB88A5940F59BC5CECE74A900B0"><enum>101.</enum><header>Establishment of Department of Peacebuilding</header><subsection id="HB11B6818C515457E9E2F3311EBCCA090"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is hereby established a Department of Peacebuilding, which shall—</text><paragraph id="HA73EACC0026041079BDAE0AC8301BD32"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be within the executive branch of the Federal Government; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HECF3BACCD323496EB8E3B9BA50528678"><enum>(2)</enum><text>be dedicated to peacebuilding, peacemaking, and the study and promotion of conditions conducive to both domestic and international peace and a culture of peace.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD2E26338641428B94FDACBEFF4B4C76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Secretary of peacebuilding</header><text>There shall be at the head of the Department a Secretary of Peacebuilding, who shall be appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H18202D17CFD74A308D1707A2899CDBC3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Mission</header><text>The Department shall—</text><paragraph id="H3C1907FD4DAF40F69A01FF65612F4D91"><enum>(1)</enum><text>cultivate peace and peacebuilding as a strategic national policy objective;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD213731272F44CA8BCA8C59F90483690"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reduce and prevent violence in the United States and internationally through peacebuilding and effective nonviolent conflict resolution;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01632C6CE8C1426487C5038641D8344F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>strengthen nonmilitary means of peacemaking;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0354AACAC4DF4EEAB786B95D2620C007"><enum>(4)</enum><text>take a proactive, strategic approach in the development of field-tested best practices and policies that promote national and international conflict prevention, nonviolent intervention, mediation, peaceful resolution of conflict, and structured mediation of conflict;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8488066A941240DC834084E6810FA98E"><enum>(5)</enum><text>address matters both domestic and international in scope;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE33926FE16FD44AAB529CD9F3D2A596E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address the interconnection of all life and the intersectionality of peace and justice, equality, health, healing, national security, education, the economy, rule of law, democracy, planetary survival, and other aspects of civil rights, civil liberties, and human rights;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CB3B269FC044C89B04931277FCA384A"><enum>(7)</enum><text>provide an institutional platform for the growing wealth of expertise in peacebuilding to dramatically reduce the national and global epidemic of violence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H950FC52B0F2448019B6BF93AA65B266A"><enum>(8)</enum><text>support local communities in finding, funding, replicating, and expanding programs to reduce and prevent violence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3D7D868DB2341CFA9B24180AA4CA6E9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>invest in nongovernmental organizations that have implemented successful initiatives to reduce and prevent violence, both internationally and domestically; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE4F04F6EA96244A5B92597B6DA10A633"><enum>(10)</enum><text>consult with other Federal agencies to apply and practice the science of peacebuilding in their respective fields of responsibility.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC816D7AA4A3944E9A94820308C408EFF"><enum>102.</enum><header>Responsibilities and powers</header><subsection id="H440028B448BE47CDAAC1E8D50AF214CF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall, on an ongoing basis—</text><paragraph id="H54AE87E8627A40F9A92BB27828BC3663"><enum>(1)</enum><text>work proactively and interactively with each branch of the Federal Government on all policy matters relating to conditions of peace;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6A3B838F54074BC8A9A6870F02D02807"><enum>(2)</enum><text>call on the experience and expertise of individuals and seek participation in the development of policy from private, public, and nongovernmental organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0E24286E2904752A933D18198A5B985"><enum>(3)</enum><text>monitor and analyze causative principles of conflict and make policy recommendations for developing conditions of peace and maintaining peaceful conduct;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H494CB3291EFC469486D028B18EBB8035"><enum>(4)</enum><text>research effective violence reduction programs and promote and promulgate such programs within the Federal Government and society; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C02AA04FE4246F79260526516A67F0E"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult with private, public, and nongovernmental organizations to develop a metric model that provides the means to measure and report progress toward peace in the United States to the President, Congress, and the public, and issue reports on such progress annually with those reports to be available to the public on the website of the Department.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF568665CB94E47FC8D874653F7592692"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Domestic responsibilities</header><text>The Secretary shall collaborate with governmental and nongovernmental organizations and individuals to promote personal and community security and peace by—</text><paragraph id="HC87022C2F1EA49479413A4C222E1D0D1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>developing new policies and supporting existing policies that effectively address personal and family violence, including suicide, domestic violence, spousal abuse, child abuse, and mistreatment of the elderly and others;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFAC1BE8873D041C5B70FD6B017AD23DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>creating new policies and programs and expanding existing policies and programs that effectively reduce drug and alcohol abuse;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3687079646144F5AEFA5E36D98B7815"><enum>(3)</enum><text>analyzing existing policies, employing successful, field-tested programs, and developing new approaches for dealing with the tools of violence, including handguns and assault weapons, especially among youth;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96D268AD53294692B8DA58FF6140883C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>developing new and expanding effective programs that address and ameliorate societal challenges such as school violence, gangs, police violence, hate crimes, economic injustice, human trafficking, racial or ethnic violence, violence against LGBTQ+ individuals, and police-community relations disputes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD275118BEB5F4439AB522F26DDAB1169"><enum>(5)</enum><text>making policy recommendations to the Attorney General of the United States regarding civil rights and labor law;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D9E09B235CC41C09979B9F40FE258DA"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assisting in the establishment and funding of community-based violence prevention programs, including virtual violence prevention programs for at-home participation, violence prevention counseling and peer mediation in schools and via video conferences, and unarmed civilian peacekeeping and crisis mitigation at a local level;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D0DFA80976C431586FEBF41BC1C31B3"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing counseling and advocacy on behalf of individuals victimized by violence, including those with mental health challenges;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DB148502C0D4DFD8D5F01C18D76D26F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>providing for public education programs and counseling strategies that promote acceptance and respect for the diversity of all individuals in the United States without regard to race, religion, creed, gender and gender identification, sexual orientation, age, ethnicity, national origin, class and economic status, and other perceived differences; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19F3FB3BE1A44251AFEA1B64553C3ACE"><enum>(9)</enum><text>supporting local community initiatives that draw on neighborhood resources to create peace projects that facilitate the development of conflict resolution and healing of societal wounds such as patriarchy, racism, war, manifest destiny, and economic injustice to thereby inform and inspire national policy.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H66AA52AC09314347B1FCD70116B359E4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>International responsibilities</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="HCAF3E15277C7493A96DB1A14AB9D47AC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>advise the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of State on matters relating to national security, including the protection of human rights and the prevention of, amelioration of, and de-escalation of unarmed and armed international conflict;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB8CCE25ADCE144FEA9A2751B49D7BD18"><enum>(2)</enum><text>contribute to and participate in the development of training of all United States personnel who administer post-conflict reconstruction and demobilization in war-torn societies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE664F1094604483827C7C287E4FCA70"><enum>(3)</enum><text>sponsor national and regional conflict-prevention and dispute-resolution initiatives, create special task forces, and draw on local, regional, and national expertise to develop plans and programs for addressing the root sources and issues of conflict in troubled areas;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8B1848319644695846FF8E193A770F4"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop violence prevention, amelioration and violence de-escalation training for the general public to provide tools and educate about peacebuilding skills and to promote sustainable peace, peacebuilding buy-in and peacebuilding awareness; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H042E709861BB492496EE4E605143FE26"><enum>(5)</enum><text>counsel and advocate on behalf of women victimized by violence, including rape, situations leading up to conflict, conflicts, and post-conflict situations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C67EF34140D439EA90345F942F779CB"><enum>(6)</enum><text>counsel and advocate on behalf of victims of human trafficking both domestically and internationally and work to end the trafficking of human beings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H356C86CDC82D428F9173941200AF7DBF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>provide for exchanges between the United States and other nations that endeavor to develop domestic and international peace-based initiatives;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H444543C174DA498190E0DB60A7AAD50B"><enum>(8)</enum><text>encourage the development of international sister city programs, pairing United States cities with cities around the world for artistic, cultural, economic, educational, and faith-based exchanges;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H76BCC388A8ED49768F405BC066810A57"><enum>(9)</enum><text>establish and administer a budget designated for the training and deployment of unarmed civilian peacekeepers to participate in multinational nonviolent peacekeeping forces that may be conducted by civilian, governmental, or multilateral organizations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE9D216F414B4453AD4C9D5B099E7777"><enum>(10)</enum><text>jointly with the Secretary of the Treasury, strengthen peace enforcement through hiring and training monitors and investigators to help with the enforcement of international arms embargoes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D54241E2DD6428F8EFB2188A9FC6EEA"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in consultation with the Secretary of State, bring together all stakeholders who are impacted by a conflict by facilitating peace summits where such stakeholders may gather under carefully prepared conditions to promote nonviolent communication and mutually beneficial solutions and to prevent future violence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H78F60AE0244E4BDE8A59526C2493DB68"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the President recommendations for reductions and elimination of weapons of mass destruction, and make annual reports to the President on the sale of arms from the United States to other nations, with an analysis of the impact of such sales on the defense of the United States, how such sales affect peace and security, and how reduction or cessation of such sales affect peace and security;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4256E206F45C43CF9A4EAB9D0BFC34AA"><enum>(13)</enum><text>in consultation with the Secretary of State, develop strategies for sustainability and management of the distribution of international funds;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H695D4C04D9014D03AAC20109F53A5A3C"><enum>(14)</enum><text>advise the Permanent Representative of the United States to the United Nations on matters pertaining to the United Nations Security Council;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA5850F6A21BF4377816C91BA34F8417C"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support the implementation of international peacebuilding strategies through a balanced use of peacebuilding, reconciliation, diplomacy, development, and defense with the goal of preventing and ending war and violence; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA98987F21F6B41A2A22F67E5DAEC905D"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encourage all nations to create infrastructures for peace within their nations and among nations.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H022EDA4E2F564DCF8EAC93BFA478CB50" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Membership of the Secretary of Peacebuilding on the national security council</header><text>Section 101(c) of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3021">50 U.S.C. 3021(c)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>the Secretary of Peacebuilding</quote> after <quote>Treasury</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H61A99272C16B4279B3C30187EA675478"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Human security responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall address and offer nonviolent conflict resolution strategies and suggest resources for unarmed civilian peacekeepers to the appropriate relevant parties on issues of human security if such security is threatened by conflict or crisis, whether such conflict or crisis is geographic, religious, ethnic, gender-based, racial, or class-based in its origin, derives from economic concerns, health concerns or is initiated through disputes concerning scarcity of natural resources (such as water and energy resources), food, health resources (such as life-saving medicine, medical and protective equipment and supplies, including viral and bacterial infection testing supplies and vaccines), trade, or climate and environmental concerns.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF6DB957B9DEE46DEB8BD91284EB4DBA0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Media-Related responsibilities</header><text>Respecting the First Amendment to the Constitution of the United States of America and the requirement for free and independent media, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="HB8FC33AE482D47D08F729C08ED14C022"><enum>(1)</enum><text>seek assistance in the design and implementation of nonviolent policies from media professionals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7DC9A545A34E4C9DBC092591071304B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>study the role of the media in the escalation and de-escalation of conflict at domestic and international levels, including the role of fear-inducing and hate-inducing speech and actions, and making the findings of such study public; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H88D5064115614160B0E9901AEE7B842E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>make recommendations to professional media organizations in order to provide opportunities to increase media awareness of peacebuilding initiatives.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A1BED39949D480DBC8385C7A7FBB610"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Educational responsibilities</header><text>The Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H2893B17BEA444AF5AA19C3062F500B46"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult with the United States Institute of Peace, the Department of Education, Indigenous communities, and other concerned individuals and organizations and develop a peace education curriculum that includes studies of—</text><subparagraph id="HCC27C402F97A4F00943D3BAB93FBE478"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the civil rights movement in the United States and throughout the world and human rights and liberties movements, with special emphasis on the role of nonviolence and how individual endeavor and involvement have contributed to advancements in peace and justice;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBD4C49D7FAF4A1188CCD0E8FF3199F4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>underlying causes of violence and conditions of peace;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46F8F0FB8E684FC792642776FC1E7E58"><enum>(C)</enum><text>practices that enhance peace and peacebuilding;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBE69E6CD93734D3C897D3DCFA589897A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the contributions to the United States of its diverse ethnicities, races, and religious communities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD8BC2416BE84DC4926A8D76DE4A7129"><enum>(E)</enum><text>peace agreements and circumstances in which peaceful intervention has worked to stop conflict; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HED5757FD8BB440ADBF824E026B2222FC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>the patriarchal structure of society and the inherent violence of such structure in the shaping of relationships and institutions;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF32206561A649298328A740D653AA0C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in consultation with the Secretary of Education—</text><subparagraph id="HD980A7704D9B44D38351C0354BEB0B08"><enum>(A)</enum><text>commission and participate in the development of such curriculum and make such curriculum available to local school districts to enable the use of peace education objectives at pre-kindergarten schools, elementary schools, and secondary schools in the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4845C9CFF16F4EEB993D21E642F82706"><enum>(B)</enum><text>support in early childhood, pre-kindergarten schools, elementary schools, secondary schools, and institutions of higher education a well-resourced, balanced education that includes math, environmental stewardship, science, English, history, ethnic studies, economics, justice, critical thinking, social studies, health, physical education, foreign languages, the arts, and music that will prepare students for success in a globally interconnected world; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B89B360E7BD4A7A87764C3A0E998D26"><enum>(C)</enum><text>offer incentives in the form of grants and training to encourage the development of State peace curricula and assist schools in applying for such grants and training;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1558931E923245B488AF1221F5A34F3D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>work with educators to equip students to become skilled in achieving peace through reflection, and facilitate instruction in the ways of peaceful conflict resolution;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FD6C5A20F7F430FB5F868B13A7ED7F0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>ensure that schools are nonviolence zones that provide a peaceful educational environment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1A941F7A1C7C4D2AA854DCE51BDADE52"><enum>(5)</enum><text>create school and community cultures where students and staff do not feel threatened and are free from bullying and harassment by developing and implementing curricula in nonviolent conflict resolution education, mindfulness, and restorative practices for teachers, students, parents, the school community, and the community at large;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H65AD133D0D1D44EE9CD8D23DFBE9C114"><enum>(6)</enum><text>maintain a public website to solicit and receive ideas for the development of peace from the wealth of the politically, socially, and culturally diverse public;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H541EC08E0C62414EBEFA84DC964F1FE3"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">proactively engage the critical thinking capabilities, including civic education on citizen duties to foster democratic principles, of students and teachers of pre-kindergarten schools, elementary schools, secondary schools, and institutions of higher education through the internet and other media and issue periodic reports concerning any submissions from such students and teachers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1C032BCD18C4B64AEB788123EE82DA8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>establish a Peace Academy that shall—</text><subparagraph id="HCBFABD40C25A459DBDF276933B4FA187"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be modeled after the military service academies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC831755B6334CA291F21B545DC4F11C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide a 4-year course of instruction in peace education, after which graduates will be required to serve 5 years in public service in programs dedicated to domestic or international nonviolent conflict resolution; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H61BDC642CEC24E9A9BC4AE45D2F749E9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>provide grants for peace studies departments in institutions of higher education throughout the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8D19279AD33840B7A90279EDD57D5080"><enum>103.</enum><header>Principal officers</header><subsection id="HD6026FACF0CD4FF38EF3C91A3A28171F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Under secretary of peacebuilding</header><text>The President shall appoint an Under Secretary of Peacebuilding in the Department, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate. During the absence or disability of the Secretary, or in the event of a vacancy in the office of the Secretary, the Under Secretary shall act as Secretary. The Secretary shall designate the order in which other officials of the Department shall act and perform the functions of the Secretary during the absence or disability of both the Secretary and Under Secretary or in the event of vacancies in both offices.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE5DA7789808C4C5BA5C6DE216AA2367C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional positions</header><paragraph id="HFE2778EB70664769BA6A8A49D9D89DD9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall appoint in the Department, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate—</text><subparagraph id="H67D570A2057E4DF0AF07602EB279A098"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an Assistant Secretary for Peace Education and Training;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7DAA59F9C8534A59886DE3ADFB8B54A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an Assistant Secretary for Domestic Peacebuilding Activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04C5582CF0AC4E608A0B7BF2E7F0A7AC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an Assistant Secretary for International Peacebuilding Activities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC705C7DAA3084B12A02E1A887E5A4911"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an Assistant Secretary for Technology for Peace;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C8A7818B4BB41CB83AD09DBD7E9B03B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an Assistant Secretary for Arms Control and Disarmament;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CB7C23E3CA9405FA3344BC8F7213910"><enum>(F)</enum><text>an Assistant Secretary for Peacebuilding Information and Research;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09214F8321C84DCCA2AD7089A2412641"><enum>(G)</enum><text>an Assistant Secretary for Human and Economic Rights; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9DB42B0043274A0BB7CFE5746166B27B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a General Counsel.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB667816B793449F8A6EE86EF1E93B74"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Establishment of inspector general of the department of peacebuilding</header><text>Section 12 of the Inspector General Act of 1978 (5 U.S.C. App.) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H80F85DF7AA424C1AA3EFB60F5DE9FB35"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by inserting <quote>Peacebuilding,</quote> after <quote>Homeland Security,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H397D0D69D2704BECAED45763025D31B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by inserting <quote>Peacebuilding,</quote> after <quote>Homeland Security,</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0B74CAD4C446461E9760F1992426DF1F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional officers</header><text>The President shall appoint 4 additional officers in the Department, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate. The officers appointed under this paragraph shall perform such functions as the Secretary shall prescribe, including—</text><subparagraph id="H19D459BBE2F5482C864E24D6B0A4D9A9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>congressional relations functions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H541A4BCF7B2C49CB9737BFAB88B68C8B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>public information functions, including providing, through the use of the latest technologies, useful information about peace and the work of the Department;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86C0A2F747284506AA4A765364A79DED"><enum>(C)</enum><text>management and budget functions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27D1308380F5460A9ACD0A4A10A06E81"><enum>(D)</enum><text>planning, evaluation, and policy development functions, including development of policies to promote the efficient and coordinated administration of the Department and its programs and encourage improvements in conflict resolution and violence prevention.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9476E75D6D5D49A7AB87FEB12B084AEF"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Description of functions</header><text>In any case in which the President submits the name of an individual to the Senate for confirmation as an officer of the Department under this subsection, the President shall state the particular functions such individual will exercise upon taking office.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H55FDEADE7F6A4B44A6AF0599C5FFD518"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority of secretary</header><text>Each officer described in this section shall report directly to the Secretary and shall, in addition to any functions vested in or required to be delegated to such officer, perform such additional functions as the Secretary may prescribe.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB751F7F2086448ADBB7AFB80631D4C89"><enum>104.</enum><header>Office of Peace Education and Training</header><subsection id="H5856DFEC5A16496B8036F7A984F78EA4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be in the Department an Office of Peace Education and Training, the head of which shall be the Assistant Secretary for Peace Education and Training. The Assistant Secretary for Peace Education and Training shall carry out those functions of the Department relating to the creation, encouragement, and impact of peace education and training at the pre-kindergarten, elementary, secondary, university, and postgraduate levels, and disseminate applicable policies and research in consultation with entities of the Department of Health and Human Services, including—</text><paragraph id="HCADF664F6FB445889B36C6C4C46FF62B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Administration for Children and Families;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32955E116E0E4D61A7A2A6B7794CDB0C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Administration on Aging;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7926BB96C8724D849F226098C4B513EA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D8A929651FB48B5939D197D6DC67ED0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the National Institutes of Health. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAF8EDF61B69244F781F0FF305D9969D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Peace curriculum</header><text>The Assistant Secretary of Peace Education and Training, in consultation with the Secretary of Education, Indigenous communities, the United States Institute of Peace, nongovernmental organizations, public institutions, peace and conflict studies programs of institutions of higher education, and Federal agencies that provide effective peace training materials and curricula, shall create and support the development and dissemination of effective peace curricula and supporting materials for distribution to the State educational agency in each State and territory of the United States and any other interested institutions. Each peace curriculum shall include—</text><paragraph id="HFD69DB9DBCAD419FA4B87976E77FE1AA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>building communicative peace skills and nonviolent conflict resolution skills;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H482A7A4722EC412987DDB150AD2E9236"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">teaching and fostering compassion, empathy, mindfulness, kindness, acceptance, understanding, respect, inclusion, and forgiveness;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H745F3A71CA8844CE8EB13356A5040505"><enum>(3)</enum><text>teaching about historical and contemporary events utilizing nonviolent and peacebuilding principles to promote a culture of peace and about individuals and organizations employing nonviolent and peacebuilding principles to improve society;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DFBAFEA99EC4B66A89FFCCF436E54E1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>teaching about the benefits of a peaceful society, including economic, health, social, and scientific implications of peace; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H630CF70007F644DB941877A74DDC3BED"><enum>(5)</enum><text>promoting other objectives to increase the knowledge of peace processes.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H878512D2715C4EE5BE09E23B0D502E46"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Assistant Secretary of Peace Education and Training shall—</text><paragraph id="H2D8EB4A4F3E24BF0A20185D47A946FA3"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide peace education grants to institutions of higher education for the creation and expansion of peace studies departments and the education and training of teachers in peace studies, violence prevention, peacebuilding, community building, and nonviolent conflict resolution skills; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23842081BC2848EC94AB945E4ACED2B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish a grant program to be known as the Community Peace Block Grant program under which the Secretary shall make grants to nonprofit organizations and nongovernmental organizations for the purposes of developing innovative school and neighborhood programs for nonviolent conflict resolution and creating local peacebuilding initiatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H9EE97C43DC924A628146B2B361E58893"><enum>105.</enum><header>Office of Domestic Peacebuilding Activities</header><subsection id="HAE61C089B25E4C0FBBEEE948CF551FF4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be in the Department an Office of Domestic Peacebuilding Activities, the head of which shall be the Assistant Secretary for Domestic Peacebuilding Activities. The Assistant Secretary for Domestic Peacebuilding Activities shall carry out those functions in the Department affecting domestic peace activities, including the development of policies that prevent domestic violence and that increase awareness about intervention and counseling on domestic violence and conflict.</text></subsection><subsection id="H28D287D460E3416ABE09A17FC18CCA07"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for Domestic Peacebuilding Activities shall—</text><paragraph id="H2448E10497774D8CBE4E6FB12BD399FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop policy and disseminate best practices from the field for the treatment of drug and alcohol abuse;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4EF4DA1D36DD4C55ABEDC943E83AFEB2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop community-based strategies for celebrating diversity and promoting acceptance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F35B03020684BCFB39344467BDFF9CA"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop new policies and build upon existing proven programs to prevent the school-to-prison pipeline by promoting restorative and conflict resolution practices at pre-kindergarten, elementary, secondary, university, and post graduate levels and in police academies, with funding for teacher, staff, student, and community training in nonviolence, restorative practices, conflict resolution, and diversity understanding and appreciation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H317E14EED9E0424A9910800A50A3D3DA"><enum>(4)</enum><text>develop new policies and build on existing proven programs—</text><subparagraph id="H8B1D2A30B9F548ECB575D669D677AFEE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to assist in the prevention of hate, a culture of violence and domination, violence and crime, including the development of non-threatening, non-harassing community policing strategies, mindfulness, and conflict de-escalation training, and other peaceful settlement skills among police and other public safety officers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC864AFC1E20A4FE69A26BEBE5777B3E3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to assist in the re-entry into the community by individuals who have been incarcerated by providing trauma healing, including training in anger management, conflict resolution, peacebuilding skills, life skills, and educational and job skills;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB78EC03424746E499289A7B6BA3A3DA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to assist in creating strong, happy, and healthy families, including supporting mental health services, domestic violence prevention, gang prevention, anti-bullying programs, animal cruelty prevention, substance abuse prevention, and the development of peaceful parenting skills;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60C9ACB2366F498C83A4C1A3A6AD97EA"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to promote peacebuilding and community-building and to provide restorative justice and restorative practice programs at all levels of the criminal justice system that bring together offenders, victims, and community members in an effort to repair the damage caused by criminal activity through accountability and rehabilitation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30462A39445E41E38DAB5B5A087140C2"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to develop violence prevention and violence de-escalation training for the general public to provide peacebuilding tools for all and to promote sustainable peace, peacebuilding buy-in, and peacebuilding awareness; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D111FC4705B49D8BD08F3F45ED906D5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>to provide for training and deployment into neighborhoods of nonmilitary domestic conflict prevention and peacemaking personnel, including violence interrupters, community safety task force, and civilian community peacekeepers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BFA95F5D2AD479586A7884DB1400185"><enum>(G)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to implement respectful, non-targeting, and non-harassing community-based policing to break down barriers between law enforcement officers and the people such officers serve; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H489D05424F7F4DEA9D691D6F7B2A759A"><enum>(H)</enum><text>to encourage and facilitate formation of locally and State-run and administered citizen’s boards to recommend any appropriate training as needed for working compassionately and effectively with local, regional, and State populations and to review and hold accountable actions of all local, regional, and State police and law enforcement departments in the United States;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AE607838F83475CA2CDEF5CD7903DF5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>promote informal and cultural exchanges between individuals and groups of proximate neighborhoods and regions to encourage understanding and acceptance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD328C00646494AA68104AA843C91CC92"><enum>(6)</enum><text>disseminate applicable policies and research in consultation with—</text><subparagraph id="H8E61F1CD89C040CD81FB8C1D3EF10F40"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Department of Justice;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5B68DA9124BB445B93CD8793FCD84ABA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Department of Health and Human Services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDA6FF6FED05447C9A9D0325A67F1DD9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Department of State; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF2F48CF281D9460F9C3F144BD7D114D4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Department of Education.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7288517331E2459E9CE5BDDBB4E514A9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for Domestic Peacebuilding Activities shall establish a grant program to be known as the Cultural Diplomacy for Peace grant program under which the Secretary shall make grants to pre-kindergarten schools, elementary schools, secondary schools, institutions of higher education, nonprofit organizations, and nongovernmental organizations for the purpose of developing domestic cultural exchanges, including exchanges relating to the arts, sports, science, and other academic disciplines, that promote diplomacy and cultural understanding between neighborhoods and members of such neighborhoods.</text></subsection></section><section id="H3FF80440FDE04CA4848D2671CE22F86C"><enum>106.</enum><header>Office of International Peacebuilding Activities</header><subsection id="HCB068FB41FF7402C8AB7DB61BF442249"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be in the Department an Office of International Peacebuilding Activities, the head of which shall be the Assistant Secretary for International Peacebuilding Activities. The Assistant Secretary for International Peacebuilding Activities shall carry out those functions in the Department affecting international peace activities.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAC6D6CB0C49D4277BC7E5F0BB0B83531"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for International Peacebuilding Activities shall—</text><paragraph id="H94954087C19649EF934F668E05677D47"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop new programs and promote existing proven programs to—</text><subparagraph id="HB572053146444F318AA2B10AA08322B2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide for the training and deployment of graduates of the Peace Academy established under section 102(g) and other nonmilitary conflict prevention and peacemaking personnel;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA200B2AB3AA849A480B6B0B5DFE90E85"><enum>(B)</enum><text>support national and regional conflict-prevention, de-escalation, and peaceful dispute-resolution initiatives in nations experiencing social, political, medical, or economic strife and among all nations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7CBABC73A694994BBB54EB21F683C6B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop community building, violence prevention, amelioration and de-escalation training for the general public to educate about peacebuilding skills and to promote sustainable peace, peacebuilding buy-in and peacebuilding awareness;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F7DE3A1F1FE4BAF9C70C3408CCD087F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide training for the administration of post-conflict reconstruction and demobilization in war-torn societies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2325A4A5ACB4453881EB09BF6040D6A5"><enum>(E)</enum><text>address root causes of violence;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDADC247CECB74B9CB8F5420DE12E50A5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>eradicate extreme hunger, infectious and other diseases, and poverty;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA47542CB0B6D4BA380FD4035F9266C69"><enum>(G)</enum><text>eradicate genocide;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE93A463B5BA4ECBBB50A972F28DCB30"><enum>(H)</enum><text>achieve universal primary education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H962436D00AE149C4B887EDAADE815B6A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>empower women and girls;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C7EB9C422EC4AA0BDF9FF049F85839C"><enum>(J)</enum><text>eradicate human trafficking; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H246C5E894D0E4934B9596D35BBFEEE38"><enum>(K)</enum><text>eradicate dehumanization and mistreatment of individuals;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB65FD97581134945BE752DAD2CF2A1F4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>support the creation of a multinational nonviolent peace force;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA914D3CCCADB49D991E07FBD86B5F7A7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide for exchanges between individuals of the United States and other nations that are endeavoring to develop domestic and international peace-based initiatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E4406E1682F4B3BBAD466A270B74328"><enum>(4)</enum><text>disseminate applicable policies and research in consultation with—</text><subparagraph id="HFBB12CD35D7B4663BC71EA5BE2960854"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Department of State;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H098B6C7DF7024D5C9EF5B4C7F7C06796"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Department of Labor;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7152E4B580B44A299EBC85BD1134074F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Peace Corps;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H404A2789556A4E84BE80468ED2DDDBE3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the United States Institute of Peace; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB697FB987D1D4FA5A32744796661D9F0" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any other applicable entities.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB992FE61BFDE417B87900141A0B04F4E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for International Peacebuilding Activities shall establish a grant program to be known as the International Cultural Diplomacy for Peace grant program under which the Secretary shall make grants to pre-kindergarten schools, elementary schools, secondary schools, institutions of higher education, nonprofit organizations, and nongovernmental organizations for the purpose of developing international cultural exchanges, including exchanges related to the arts, sports, science, and other academic disciplines, that promote diplomacy and cultural understanding between the United States and other nations.</text></subsection></section><section id="HAAEF828A12FE46748B0D634D216088D7"><enum>107.</enum><header>Office of Technology for Peace</header><subsection id="HAD2D00D75B0E43F29456CA8009B82A7D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be in the Department an Office of Technology for Peace, the head of which shall be the Assistant Secretary for Technology for Peace. The Assistant Secretary for Technology for Peace shall carry out those functions in the Department affecting the awareness, study, ethical implications and impact of evolving existing technologies and developing new technologies, including artificial intelligence, mobile technologies, social media, drones, and data science and information, on the creation and maintenance of domestic and international peace, and disseminate applicable policies and research in consultation with appropriate entities of the Department of State.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4E8E8A7C3813436280AC75C4E8A25ECA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Grants</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for Technology for Peace shall make grants for the research and development of technologies in transportation, communications, agriculture, medicine, and energy that—</text><paragraph id="H1861ED4466C545F2AE449D8D095911AB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>are nonviolent in application;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H00E81B3A4EC74B959617E1C74A899BFD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encourage the conservation and sustainability of natural resources, including air, water, land, in order to prevent future conflicts regarding scarce resources due to overuse or natural or human-caused disasters, including climate change and pandemics; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H81A1C953A84146E99749D94719A83D10"><enum>(3)</enum><text>promote a green, peaceful economy.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDCCF1ACE4A4E4C3D9D507448BDC48758"><enum>108.</enum><header>Office of Arms Control and Disarmament</header><subsection id="HAD991EE77DF04EEC8DE15F2008D1B049"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be in the Department an Office of Arms Control and Disarmament, the head of which shall be the Assistant Secretary for Arms Control and Disarmament. The Assistant Secretary for Arms Control and Disarmament shall carry out those functions in the Department affecting arms control programs and arms limitation agreements.</text></subsection><subsection id="H590DAB8EAA5043828E15AE87C12527FF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for Arms Control and Disarmament shall—</text><paragraph id="HE55046B7BFB442708A8583FE5201E741"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">advise the Secretary on interagency discussions and international negotiations, including discussions involving the United Nations, the Secretary of State, the Atomic Energy Commission, and the Secretary of Defense, regarding the increase or reduction and elimination of weapons of mass destruction throughout the world, including the dismantling of such weapons and the safe and secure storage of materials related thereto and efforts to limit or cease development, testing, manufacture or possession of nuclear weapons or threats to use them or to allow any nuclear arms to be stationed in the territory of any nation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68CD4A54231244BE9DF686015EEAD7DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assist nations, international agencies, and nongovernmental organizations in assessing the locations of the buildup of nuclear arms and other weapons of mass destruction;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26D6FC0661F44EF9B7957BA1B3253C6A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>develop nonviolent strategies to prevent and deter testing or use of offensive or defensive nuclear weapons, weaponized drones, assault weapons, and other weapons of mass destruction, whether based on land, underground, air, sea, or in space;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A7ABB75174B46EAA1B26ABBEEE11622"><enum>(4)</enum><text>serve as a depository for copies of all contracts, agreements, and treaties that address the reduction and elimination of nuclear weapons and other weapons of mass destruction, and the protection of space from militarization;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H998D8C3650504D98BD9E983B49B8AACB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>provide technical support and legal assistance for the implementation of such contracts, agreements, and treaties;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19A564955AAD437EBB1B1615D19591FD"><enum>(6)</enum><text>disseminate applicable policies and research in consultation with the Department of State and the Department of Commerce; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0DC1FC114FAE4D838AB5D6C5BD35157C"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">address and support nuclear waste cleanup at nuclear test sites, nuclear research facilities and laboratories, Superfund Sites of former and present military bases in the United States and abroad and at lands, in waters, and in the air adjacent to old and new nuclear reactors and nuclear-contaminated sites.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB752E6C4095B435181257CB0C89A4832"><enum>109.</enum><header>Office of Peacebuilding Information and Research</header><subsection id="H75BE7F65B4FE45E696390F21F133B630"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be in the Department an Office of Peacebuilding Information and Research, the head of which shall be the Assistant Secretary for Peacebuilding Information and Research. The Assistant Secretary for Peacebuilding Information and Research shall carry out those functions in the Department affecting research and analysis relating to creating, initiating, and modeling approaches to peaceful coexistence and nonviolent conflict resolution and shall make this information available to Congress, the public, and other interested entities on an ongoing basis.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1151623A4A7148C69DFD2E193528BACD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for Peacebuilding Information and Research shall—</text><paragraph id="HB92D687033A74038974FC8F524159949"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">commission or compile studies on the impact of war, mass shootings, police violence and other types of violence, especially on the physical and mental condition of children (using the 10-point anti-war agenda in the United Nations Children’s Fund report, State of the World’s Children 1996, as a guide) that shall include the study of the effect of war on the environment and public health;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF07C10472A0B4D2E84378366E02303B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>commission or compile studies on the impact of war and other types of violence on soldiers, veterans and civilians;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA1CB87AF45D45A0868DA8A9D40D7AC4"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">commission or compile studies on the effect of war and other types of violence on the environment, public health, the economy, and national security;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H671210C9D5FE48BCB64BFF31DED65922"><enum>(4)</enum><text>commission or compile studies on the impact of violence, racism and inequality on such conditions of peace as health care, employment, education, economic equity, food security, voting rights, housing, justice, and rule of law;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D54EBDE02394B5580EEBC515FF1F14B"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compile information on effective community peacebuilding activities and disseminate such information to local governments and nongovernmental organizations in the United States and abroad;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5BBEA69A3514431B01A0BBDF5BC63C2"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">commission or compile research on the effect of violence in the media, including the use of untruths, misinformation and false information and make such reports available to Congress and the public annually;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35C0B6EB30F242208E68167970F5B79C"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">commission or compile research on the number and circumstances of deaths caused by law enforcement using guns or other weapons, devices or methods, the number and circumstances of deaths to law enforcement officials caused by guns or other weapons, devices or methods, the effects of gun violence in the United States, and make such reports available to Congress and the public annually;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6AEBE07F0184EFCAEE2755035CCE6D6"><enum>(8)</enum><text>commission or compile research on the effect of teaching nonviolent conflict resolution skills and practices and social emotional education in schools and disseminate such information to educational institutions, Congress and the public annually;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAA3ED2667272472DA9BD3F769C2E97A9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>commission or compile any other such research that will foster understanding of the root causes of violence, the root conditions of peace, and policies and practices to promote a culture of peace;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B7CA27677F64E6FA939F0E4675523FF"><enum>(10)</enum><text>publish a monthly journal of the activities of the Department and encourage scholarly participation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H532C421DDA5C4B47BFE7AB7B4E38DD9A"><enum>(11)</enum><text>sponsor conferences throughout the United States to create awareness of the work of the Department;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90F86892080E44AA8DC68459D30BF248" commented="no"><enum>(12)</enum><text>make available to the public reports, studies, and compiled research described in this Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A0C092BCD354355B457FAF91451DB31"><enum>(13)</enum><text>where applicable, work to carry out the responsibilities under this subsection in consultation with the United States Institute of Peace and other governmental and nongovernmental organizations, including—</text><subparagraph id="HE980FF94D23A4283B31E44A6F60AA01E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Department of Health and Human Services;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD7EB159BDBA422795632CEC59FCA859"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Department of Justice; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE9AC021FFDBE42229DEE10C125476876"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Department of State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HB5631C43D57D4A2F9EE5BBB8DC03A842"><enum>110.</enum><header>Office of Human Rights and Economic Rights</header><subsection id="H0C407C316D7C42D184ABF4884D9B1D12"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be in the Department an Office of Human Rights and Economic Rights, the head of which shall be the Assistant Secretary for Human Rights and Economic Rights. The Assistant Secretary for Human Rights and Economic Rights shall carry out those functions in the Department that support the principles of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, adopted by the General Assembly of the United Nations on December 10, 1948.</text></subsection><subsection id="H74703CDC99DE44039920E3196A7E516B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Assistant Secretary for Human Rights and Economic Rights shall—</text><paragraph id="H3EAC9BA686A24C4598A11C8266444FB4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assist the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of State, in furthering the incorporation of the principles of human rights, as enunciated in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, into all agreements between the United States and other nations to help prevent and reduce the causes of violence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D941B8467224A25830493E6DE160D87"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult with the Secretary of State, the United Nations, the Atrocities Prevention Board of the White House, the Department of Justice, and other similarly concerned governmental and nongovernmental organizations to gather information on and document domestic and international human rights abuses, including genocide, torture, State executions, police brutality, detention for profit, caging of children and other individuals, murder of unarmed civilians, solitary confinement (especially among children), human trafficking, child soldiers, child labor, and slave labor and recommend to the Secretary nonviolent responses to promote awareness, understanding, and correction of abuses;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E8FE04791D54584857B24D3F56C1483"><enum>(3)</enum><text>make such information available to other governmental and nongovernmental organizations in order to facilitate nonviolent conflict resolution;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEE5E80CEC5140CEB77E31D282F87D47"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide trained observers to work with nongovernmental organizations for purposes of creating a climate conducive to the respect for human rights;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF54EABDF22C34B9A97E7F24884205FF3"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conduct economic analyses of the scarcity of human and natural resources as a source of conflict and make recommendations to the Secretary for nonviolent prevention of such scarcity, nonviolent intervention in case of such scarcity, and the development of programs to assist people facing such scarcity, whether due to armed conflict, greed, misdistribution of resources, overuse or other human causes, including climate disruption, or natural causes;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC8D1EBAA6B0450088FD1949D6057D96"><enum>(6)</enum><text>conduct economic analyses of the impact of violence within and among nations as a source of human displacement and criminalization, vilification, victimization and mistreatment of those fleeing their homes to seek better and safer lives and make recommendations to the Secretary for nonviolent solutions and development of programs to assist people facing such conditions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34B0028D9D1E4497A02A676ED0473E73"><enum>(7)</enum><text>assist the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of State and the Secretary of the Treasury, in developing strategies regarding the sustainability and the management of the distribution of funds from international agencies, the conditions regarding the receipt of such funds, and the impact of those conditions on the peace and stability of the recipient nations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7BAA2F6C2E046C4AA632BFAE31C0310"><enum>(8)</enum><text>assist the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of State and the Secretary of Labor, in developing strategies to promote full compliance with domestic and international labor rights law;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA392205D26954782999848E7EDC74698"><enum>(9)</enum><text>conduct policy analysis to ensure that the international development investments of the United States positively impact the peace and stability of the recipient country; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H935FCC93CD9D4327ADA2ACF0E2E484B9"><enum>(10)</enum><text>disseminate policies and research in consultation with appropriate entities of the Department of State.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF1387FE4BCAB40A7B433E4D19AB278E4"><enum>111.</enum><header>Intergovernmental Advisory Council on Peace</header><subsection id="H64B1D00B11BF48509356CA1F2C529E4A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There shall be in the Department an advisory committee known as the Intergovernmental Advisory Council on Peace (in this section referred to as the <quote>Council</quote>). The Council shall provide assistance and make recommendations to the President and the Secretary concerning intergovernmental policies relating to peace and nonviolent conflict resolution.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD9A8E48FE78F418880283E8BCA68F0DF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text>The Council shall—</text><paragraph id="HE0655672769748B79E145AE6D7BC0E7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide a forum for representatives of international bodies, the Federal Government, Tribal governments, and State and local governments to discuss peace issues, including practices, traditions and policies that promote peacebuilding and crises and wellness issues;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAA0C1945C324389B77A2E0A4724AE57"><enum>(2)</enum><text>promote better intergovernmental relations and offer professional mediation services to ameliorate and resolve intergovernmental and intragovernmental conflict as needed, including elimination of inflammatory rhetoric; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB23D142A700D434E87ED72916A252D12"><enum>(3)</enum><text>submit biennially, or more frequently if determined necessary by the Council, a report to the President, the Secretary, and Congress reviewing the impact of Federal peace activities on the Federal Government and on State and local governments.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB3CE4DF2FCED43C8B837919F98E045BD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Secretary shall appoint the members of the Council.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF9B554431D05495AA0DCD9DC36B155AB"><enum>112.</enum><header>Federal Interagency Committee on Peace</header><subsection id="H9134792904204A72996F77563B1262EC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>There is established a Federal Interagency Committee on Peace (in this section referred to as the <quote>Committee</quote>). The Committee shall—</text><paragraph id="H2A450602E4914357802A30BEEAE6E785"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assist the Secretary in providing a mechanism to assure that the procedures and actions of the Department and other Federal agencies are fully coordinated; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H740539CA79094416BCBC0958D18694BF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>study and make recommendations for assuring effective coordination of Federal programs, policies, and administrative practices affecting peace, peacebuilding and violence prevention, and wellness.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9C36D498C12E451CB7387EF9A6882FC8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Secretary shall appoint the members of the Committee.</text></subsection></section><section id="HF1267A3B424D491D8395FEC942C1E474"><enum>113.</enum><header>Staff</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may appoint and fix the compensation of such employees as may be necessary to carry out the functions of the Secretary and the Department. Except as otherwise provided by law, such employees shall be appointed in accordance with applicable laws and the compensation of such employees fixed in accordance with title 5, United States Code.</text></section><section id="H7659753D27294ABF894DDF3C92429D7B"><enum>114.</enum><header>Consultation required</header><subsection id="H2D97C8FCBF484A5EB254343CC0D397AA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Consultation in cases of conflict and violence prevention</header><paragraph id="H4F9A3105A80F4206B1C94530EDB6771F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In any case in which a conflict between the United States and any other government or entity is foreseeable, imminent, or occurring, the Secretary of Defense and the Secretary of State shall consult with the Secretary of Peacebuilding concerning violence prevention, nonviolent means of conflict resolution, and peacebuilding.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B5333C115A941889375136EC971A559"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Diplomatic initiatives</header><text>In any case in which a conflict described in paragraph (1) is ongoing or recently concluded, the Secretary shall conduct an independent study of diplomatic initiatives undertaken by the United States and other parties to such conflict.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0EAF227C2694077B1C208B94DD14422"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Initiative assessment</header><text>In any case in which a conflict described in paragraph (1) has recently concluded, the Secretary shall assess the effectiveness of any initiatives in ending such conflict.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24279219D81F4262957E159B1D512081"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consultation process</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a formal process of consultation in a timely manner with the Secretary of State, the Secretary of Defense, and the National Security Council—</text><subparagraph id="HBA671CE31F8A451D966599582E0E41A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prior to the initiation of policies or withdrawal of resources that may lead to violence and of any armed conflict between the United States and any other country; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H25C9D93311DE4158A59E082EC0F8B301" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">for any matter involving—</text><clause id="H3FACC01AD7D0492A99BE9E2AE9BF4CDB" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the use of Department of Defense personnel within the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="H0DC829510BF249A38A07762C770DF896"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the proposed or actual distribution of equipment of the Department of Defense to local or State law enforcement entities or to other individuals or entities.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3EE60E6320364172A4A072268C91D56B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation in drafting treaties and agreements</header><text>The head of each appropriate Federal agency shall consult with the Secretary in drafting treaties and peace agreements.</text></subsection></section><section id="HE02B4C5776B3424D893158DF908A3D96" commented="no"><enum>115.</enum><header>Collaboration</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall, for the greatest effectiveness in promoting peace and peacebuilding, collaborate with other Federal agencies, applicable experts, nongovernmental organization stakeholders, appropriate non-profit organization stakeholders and State, Tribal, and local leaders and stakeholders regarding all related programs in all Federal agencies. The collaboration shall include and prioritize those who are most impacted by the programs for the purpose implementing or updating such programs and for the purpose of evaluating the effectiveness and impacts of such programs. </text></section></title><title id="H0F8ACB603D8A491FB17C011204328923"><enum>II</enum><header>Other Matters</header><section id="HFB251080009448C4860B7D8D5D902DA3"><enum>201.</enum><header>Legislative recommendations of the Secretary</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the appointment of the first Secretary, the Secretary shall prepare and submit to Congress proposed legislation containing any necessary and appropriate amendments to the laws of the United States to carry out the purposes of this Act.</text></section><section id="HF9955CB977A349C19CBFCDB17280A4CA"><enum>202.</enum><header>Peace Days</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall encourage citizens to observe and celebrate the blessings of peace and endeavor to create peace on Peace Days. Such days shall include discussions of the professional activities and the achievements in the lives of peacemakers.</text></section><section id="HBF5C82657FFB478181F7C88A49FEEE2F"><enum>203.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HFA1E1DA8F54A4BEEBC24BB8595A9D88E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Department</header><text>The term <term>Department</term> means the Department of Peacebuilding established under section 101(a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H584E6393426E4216ADDF497C2D610E93"><enum>(2)</enum><header>ESEA terms</header><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meaning given those terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F379EBFFC8942C584617981DF0A947A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> has the meaning given the term <term>agency</term> in section 551(1) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H749E9A5A6B454777A9D72D37362000BA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given that term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39FEA91941D743AB8B12207C3B76978B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Nonprofit organization</header><text>The term <term>nonprofit organization</term> means an entity that—</text><subparagraph id="HF3DFC309AF23487DA58CE65B492ACE61"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">26 U.S.C. 501(c)(3)</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5FEE79606AE4580A7CDA7403111E6B2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is exempt from tax under section 501(a) of such Code.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BDDBC8F831D4202855D72566B6B9EC8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Peacebuilding appointed under section 101(b).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HA889302A0E674CA1B623E0A99AA2E4D5"><enum>204.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><subsection id="HAD340E7A03BB4BB3B83FC32C7A12CF2C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act such sums as may be necessary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4F9F51A7F4224FEBA02D7C50729EACDE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Limitation on use of funds</header><text>Of the amounts appropriated pursuant to subsection (a), at least 85 percent shall be used for domestic peace programs, including administrative costs associated with such programs.</text></subsection></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

