<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE80C321691E641BBB698E7D47392A10A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1401 IH: Eradicating Narcotic Drugs and Formulating Effective New Tools to Address National Yearly Losses of life Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1401</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230307">March 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000235">Mr. Ezell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001135">Mrs. Chavez-DeRemer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Mrs. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000594">Mr. Tony Gonzales of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection to regularly review and update policies and manuals related to inspections at ports of entry.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA1E12D07F25B40788B99F3ADAB13959C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H96FA890DCB414FA3B125C396CD649C91" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short titles</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Eradicating Narcotic Drugs and Formulating Effective New Tools to Address National Yearly Losses of life Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>END FENTANYL Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HA9D00221E56D43689C6FBA3807E85C71"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring timely updates to U.S. Customs and Border Protection field manuals</header> <subsection id="H8BDF8EB5867C489AA6478ABBCC9D5218"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not less frequently than triennially, the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection shall review and update, as necessary, the current policies and manuals of the Office of Field Operations related to inspections at ports of entry to ensure the uniform implementation of inspection practices that will effectively respond to technological and methodological changes designed to disguise illegal activity, such as the smuggling of drugs and humans, along the border.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6D6B8E26BEED40CA8D83CC8D18A085F8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header><text>Shortly after each update required under subsection (a), the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection shall submit a report to the <committee-name committee-id="SSGA00">Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate</committee-name> and the <committee-name committee-id="">Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives</committee-name> that summarizes the policy and manual changes implemented by such update.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

