<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H65EB26D1098E47E6A1D94D5BB0A8EA97" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5368 IH: Freedom to Breathe Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5368</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230908">September 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000596">Ms. Greene of Georgia</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001129">Mr. Collins</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000175">Mr. Ogles</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000190">Mr. Norman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit through December 31, 2024, the imposition of a mask mandate on passengers of air carriers or public transit and in educational settings within the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H73A86678AE58420497F34087C89EA9E3" style="OLC"><section id="HC2D6343724944766865E281D7868DAAE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Freedom to Breathe Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA576948487EA4891B5E532AEE99646F5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HF862AB83B93747149BDD53EA96E5205A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Air carrier</header><text>The term <term>air carrier</term> means an air carrier conducting passenger operations under part 121 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC05D1A921DC94CAA9ED2C4E75F12C288"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicable period</header><text>The term <term>applicable period</term> means the period that begins on the date of enactment of this Act and ends on December 31, 2024.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3719E402D9F34DF286505C6459F696C6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Commuter rail passenger transportation</header><text>The term <term>commuter rail passenger transportation</term> has the meaning given the term in section 24102 of title 49, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3FC22898B8954C24B704BF17AD6065EC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>ESEA definitions</header><text>The terms <term>elementary school</term> and <term>secondary school</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DA93291BB47489FA67F9E1CC19CA788"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Covered educational institution</header><text>The term <term>covered educational institution</term> means an elementary school, secondary school, or institution of higher education, that receives Federal funds.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0284372D3FCA4F00BE70A6AC4961C4E1" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H991E9A4A49854055AF43B1C43DBBADA8"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Mask</header><text>The term <term>mask</term> means a material covering the nose and mouth of the wearer, excluding face shields.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD7C83A701F53479E989107365BC423C6"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Mask mandate</header><text>The term <term>mask mandate</term> means an order, directive, or ordinance which requires an individual to wear a mask to travel on any conveyance, or to enter or remain in any place within the United States, in response to a public health emergency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE476CA8F03C49F081485313055836F0"><enum>(9)</enum><header>National airspace system</header><text>The term <term>national airspace system</term> has the meaning given such term in section 245.5 of title 32, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE97CAAA36E149A99826DA3BAE2A38BC"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Public transit</header><text>The term <term>public transit</term>—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H956604A5CBBD4D9E8F269659DBC7E3FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means a regular, continuing shared-ride surface transportation service that is open to the general public or open to a segment of the general public defined by age, disability, or low income; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA6307BFBC0824DFCABE71394A282E4A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA41FADBAEF694B4789C4A79D7F59107E"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">intercity passenger rail transportation provided by the entity described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/243">chapter 243</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code (or a successor to such entity);</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H457A281A37BB4643B6E3BC32F6C19D7D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">intercity bus service;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H239861290584463AA1B89924EA3791EA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">charter bus service;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB905F5DE71D6461EA65B82825314EEBE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">school bus service;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H560E8387CCB9457E8FCFF05E468B7E1F"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sightseeing service;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H33EDAD8C921F4A328759CF5465666024"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">courtesy shuttle service for patrons of 1 or more specific establishments;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A9E097BAFA64ECE9F0CDE27341A442A"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">intra-terminal or intra-facility shuttle services; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6E0C7CF10EC34BEC8959A3EDA148B975"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>commuter rail passenger transportation. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HA101083359A04EDD83727C41B6A90D6C" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>3.</enum><header>Restrictions on the use of Federal funds</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">During the applicable period, notwithstanding any other provision of law, no Federal funds may be obligated or expended to propose, establish, implement, or enforce, directly or indirectly through the imposition of a condition on receipt of Federal funds, any requirement that an individual wear a mask or comply with a mask mandate while traveling as a passenger of an air carrier in the national airspace system, using public transit, or while in any elementary school, secondary school, or institution of higher education.</text></section><section id="H0A89482F25714D2D97F449AAB5F4E3CA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Prohibitions on imposing a mask mandate on passengers of air carriers in the national airspace system</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23DE597C8BD84F6BB37265004B9D6848"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">No mask requirements on passengers of air carriers in the national airspace system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, during the applicable period, neither the President nor any other Federal officer, employee, agency, or office shall issue or enforce an order requiring an air carrier to impose a mask mandate on individuals who are passengers of the air carrier in the national airspace system. </text></subsection><subsection id="HF2C2680CD3784B75BA38720C795AAEC7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No authority To refuse air transportation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the applicable period, no certificate holder under part 119 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, which conducts scheduled operations under part 121 of that title, nor any other air carrier who provides passenger air transportation in the national airspace system, shall refuse transportation to a passenger on the basis that the passenger refuses to wear a mask or comply with a mask mandate while traveling in the national airspace system.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0A243DE35D5F46B59975B801D3C4E068"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No authority To issue or enforce mask mandates on passenger air carrier operations in response to a public health emergency</header><text>Section 361 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/264">42 U.S.C. 264</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H576EE21F83B044F1AA392F72DE276E5A"><subsection id="H8FF0B05C27074D468600155A9CCAC3AC"><enum>(f)</enum><text>Nothing in this section authorizes the Secretary to require individuals to comply with a mask mandate (as defined in section 2 of the <short-title>Freedom to Breathe Act</short-title>) while traveling as a passenger of an air carrier (as defined in such section) in the national airspace system (as defined in such section) in response to a public health emergency declared under section 319 during the applicable period (as defined in such section).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB61845C0814C49E6B278A655E0B9D475"><enum>5.</enum><header>Prohibitions on imposing a mask mandate on passengers using public transit</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDCCCBC4945C04B7EA3216292969854CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">No mask requirements on passengers using public transit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, during the applicable period, neither the President nor any other Federal officer, employee, agency, or office shall issue or enforce an order requiring a Federal, State, or local public transit agency or authority to impose a mask mandate on passengers using public transit. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6D3B473AED374585838305C25F32D824"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No authority To refuse public transit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the applicable period, no public transit operator shall refuse transportation to a passenger on the basis that the passenger refuses to wear a mask or comply with a mask mandate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9FD1F563453241ED94732CF9F1C9BEB7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No authority To issue or enforce mask mandates on passenger air carrier operations in response to a public health emergency</header><text>Section 361 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/264">42 U.S.C. 264</external-xref>), as amended by section 4(c), is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF68DF77BF3C6438F877143E0451FA0A6"><subsection id="H7EA3B1FD81B64239AF86402F8093E109"><enum>(g)</enum><text>Nothing in this section authorizes the Secretary to require individuals to comply with a mask mandate (as defined in section 2 of the <short-title>Freedom to Breathe Act</short-title>) while using public transit (as defined in such section) in response to a public health emergency declared under section 319 during the applicable period (as defined in such section).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H5103A38CDF544299A36773252A3B6B5A"><enum>6.</enum><header>Prohibitions on imposing a mask mandate in education settings</header><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43D94352D7AC4796BDA5412E32152229"><enum>(a)</enum><header>No mask requirements in schools or institutions of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, during the applicable period, neither the President nor any other Federal officer, employee, agency, or office, shall issue or enforce a mask mandate requiring individuals to wear a mask in any elementary school, secondary school, or institution of higher education. </text></subsection><subsection id="H44BFD91DCC194DE1A173F16145CB84AB" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No authority To refuse access to education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the applicable period, a covered educational institution shall not refuse entry to or participation in any educational service or activity to a student, teacher, parent, or other individual on the basis that the student, teacher, parent, or other individual refuses to wear a mask or comply with a mask mandate during the educational service or activity.</text></subsection><subsection id="H02922EE375DC458EB43CE75333B816A1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>No authority To issue or enforce mask mandates in educational settings in response to a public health emergency</header><text>Section 361 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/264">42 U.S.C. 264</external-xref>), as amended by section 5(c), is further amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F526839B3BC4EEDB3EA32A1A7230EB4"><subsection id="HA41D478F940F4A188D651831091F2B9E"><enum>(h)</enum><text>Nothing in this section authorizes the Secretary to require individuals to comply with a mask mandate (as defined in section 2 of the <short-title>Freedom to Breathe Act</short-title>) in any elementary school or secondary school (as such terms are defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965) or institution of higher education (as defined in section 102 of the Higher Education Act of 1965) in response to a public health emergency declared under section 319 9 during the applicable period (as defined in such section).</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H71E5127ED5B3413CBA7E292F65C6294B"><enum>7.</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the head of each Federal agency or office to which this Act applies shall issue such new or revised regulations as are necessary to carry out this Act.</text></section><section id="H0F8D461B1BB34017887C26E2E5049D05"><enum>8.</enum><header>Preemption</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The provisions of this Act shall supersede any provision of Federal, State, Tribal, territorial, or local law, declaration, guidance, or directive to the extent that such laws, declarations, guidance, or directives are inconsistent with this Act. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

