<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDA3F270690794787AA4AE6DDDEB0CB80" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6856 IH: Prescription Drug Rebate Reform Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6856</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reform prescription drug pricing and reduce out-of-pocket costs by ensuring consumers benefit from negotiated rebates.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFEB6ECE395984F9DB2AD6591578CB593" style="OLC"><section id="H5B2214FB48F843C8883218320B27F7B7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Prescription Drug Rebate Reform Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HAE867DE837D14BFC8FD2F64728C1B638"><enum>2.</enum><header>Cost-sharing with respect to prescription drugs</header><subsection id="HB83CB7F1E3EF464F8CD8FBFB4FEC2E26"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart II of part A of title XXVII of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-11">42 U.S.C. 300gg–11 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCC14589127F541938B6FDEA3AE100901" style="OLC"><section id="HD6232003A759484D9AF7030D25BFBF7C"><enum>2729A.</enum><header>Cost-sharing with respect to prescription drugs</header><subsection id="HB0052E8CCD2F4AE68352E3B1750313EA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A group health plan or health insurance issuer offering group or individual health insurance coverage shall set any coinsurance obligation an enrollee has with respect to a prescription drug covered by the plan or coverage based on the net price of the drug, such that no payment by the enrollee with respect to the drug is based on a percentage of the list price of a drug.</text></subsection><subsection id="H6E83321C22EF4EF8BC741337230D815B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>Subsection (a)—</text><paragraph id="H9C370A713FB64776BF2032195E03C94E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall apply with respect to a prescription drug benefit when the enrollee is required to pay a deductible with respect to such benefits and—</text><subparagraph id="HA7EAF8FE82A541498262B9697A5A4601"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has not yet satisfied the deductible under the plan or coverage; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H301C2BF84FB64CD78E7549AF94203F99"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has another coinsurance obligation with respect to such benefits under the plan or coverage; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H21DBCDAA0C06425BA8244AFFEF873240"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall not apply if, with respect to the dispensed quantity of a prescription drug, the net price and list price are the same, or are different by not more than 1 cent.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H153FE8AE69D549ABBE081E312AFD3E79"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Copayments</header><text>Nothing in this section prevents a group health plan or health insurance issuer from requiring a copayment for any prescription drug if such copayment is not tied to a percent of the specified cost of the drug.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFA6ED0B214964CF5A5ED73F917C2D098"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text><paragraph id="HC39648DDD6E1458AAC04635CFCF97E76"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>coinsurance</term> means, with respect to prescription drug coverage under a group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage, a payment obligation of an enrollee in such health plan or health insurance coverage that is based on a portion or percentage of the specified cost of a prescription drug, which may be up to 100 percent of that cost;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAFCE378D58E41F6AE37B3CA536DC7ED"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>deductible</term> means the payment obligation of an enrollee in a group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage before the group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage will pay any portion of the cost of prescription drug coverage;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FA4A44243494A4C8DA995F2E36A2558"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>list price</term> has the meaning given the term <term>wholesale acquisition cost</term> in section 1847A(c)(6)(B) of the Social Security Act;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29DDE244C2AD4346BBBFFFC9906B01E4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the term <term>net price</term> means, with respect to prescription drug coverage under a group health plan or group or individual health insurance coverage, the list price of the drug net all rebates, discounts, concessions, and other adjustments applied to the cost paid by the group health plan or health insurance issuer, or by any other entity that provides pharmacy benefit management services under a contract with any such group health plan or health insurance issuer, regardless of whether such adjustments are prospective or retrospective; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0D4E7EFC15A4DC48AE1459ADA9DF87B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the term <term>prescription drug</term> means a drug, as defined in section 201(g) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, that is subject to section 503(b)(1) of such Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H3DCEEC0FB3FA467097E91C2ACA8F18A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>Section 2729A of the Public Health Service Act, as added by subsection (a), shall apply with respect to plan years beginning on or after January 1, 2025.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

