<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C1AFAFDB4204226AB2BF4354D5F9A51" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6394 IH: Semiquincentennial Congressional Time Capsule Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6394</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231113">November 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000055">Mr. Aderholt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for the creation of a Congressional time capsule in commemoration of the semiquincentennial of the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3864EEC2995748FDA2BD66D1061C90C2" style="OLC"><section id="HAE0A2F4BA69D49DC86704DF8BD51C5EC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short Title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Semiquincentennial Congressional Time Capsule Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H9C57D07159134DD79F18AD2DF1A0FE91"><enum>2.</enum><header>Semiquincentennial Congressional Time Capsule</header><subsection id="H75C1B956B11D41848079AB6DD811226D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Creation by Architect of the Capitol</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Architect of the Capitol shall create a Congressional time capsule, to be known as the <quote>Semiquincentennial Congressional Time Capsule</quote> (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Time Capsule</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDFFA37A6DA5744128F6F50B5453BB8F4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><paragraph id="H92BB6DB6BAB140E597E4F9A48CA15C25"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination by congressional leadership</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office of the Speaker of the House of Representatives, Office of the Minority Leader of the House of Representatives, Office of the Majority Leader of the Senate, and Office of the Minority Leader of the Senate shall jointly determine the contents of the Time Capsule, taking into account the requirements of paragraph (2).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0A6FE8B582B4A01ACB04E6042383342"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Specifications</header><text>The contents of the Time Capsule shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HEA88662BCCAF41E09A53C90F0E9E820B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a representative portion of all books, manuscripts, miscellaneous printed matter, memorabilia, relics, and other materials relating to the United States Semiquincentennial;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1C79D3BA0D342C9B0378750F687AAD0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">copies or representations of important legislative and institutional milestones of Congress during the time before the Time Capsule is buried;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EA9B03BFB3F41F0BE3B0AB2FB52AEFA" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a message from Congress to the future Congress when the Time Capsule will be opened; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A28BB64D53C4B41841ABA4951F0101A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such other content as the offices described in paragraph (1) consider appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H870C46F1A8D04A938285ED44FF91C3C4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In carrying out this subsection, the offices described in paragraph (1) may consult with the Architect of the Capitol, the Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution, and such other entities of the Federal Government as the offices consider appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2EA89C54413D44A29923FDBD0A7A6A10"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties of Architect</header><text>The Architect of the Capitol shall—</text><paragraph id="H37E597F1EA2440BB98AF8F5A2B8A09E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prepare the Time Capsule to be sealed and buried on the West Lawn of the Capitol, at a location specified by the Architect, on or before July 4th, 2026, at a time which would permit individuals attending this event to also attend the burial of a time capsule in Independence Mall in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, under section 7(f)(1) of the United States Semiquincentennial Commission Act of 2016 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/36/101">36 U.S.C. 101</external-xref> note prec.); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1F2F3BBEFE844621938EDD9396C9F8DF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">install a plaque to provide such information about the Time Capsule as the Architect considers appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H505F57D371254DD180688DD7801E763E"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Unsealing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Time Capsule shall be sealed until July 4th, 2276, on which date the Speaker of the House of Representatives shall present the Time Capsule to the 244th Congress, and such Congress shall determine how the contents within should be preserved or used.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF6FB300F06634B7FB7E702050BAF1349" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act, and any amounts so appropriated shall remain available until expended.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

