<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H24A3E04F42774D0EAA6530B9A0CF559D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1331 IH: To treat Hurricane Ian as a qualified disaster for purposes of determining the tax treatment of certain disaster-related personal casualty losses.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1331</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230301">March 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To treat Hurricane Ian as a qualified disaster for purposes of determining the tax treatment of certain disaster-related personal casualty losses.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1B38735A9D3C456FAF72B798F38550EB" style="OLC"><section id="H6A6A9804A91D41458436EDF0DABF8408" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Hurricane Ian treated as qualified disaster for purposes of tax treatment of certain disaster-related personal casualty losses</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In the case of any taxable year ending after August 31, 2022, for purposes of section 304(b) of the Taxpayer Certainty and Disaster Tax Relief Act of 2020, the term <quote>qualified disaster area</quote> shall include any area with respect to which a major disaster was declared, during the period beginning on September 22, 2022, and ending on the date of the enactment of this Act, by the President under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act by reason of Hurricane Ian.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

