<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H61ABA5DBD7C642B28F1DD31D10E0A354" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3667 IH: Social Security Child Protection Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3667</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000815">Mr. Wenstrup</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title II of the Social Security Act to provide for the reissuance of social security account numbers to young children in cases where confidentiality has been compromised.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H91AEF26D6D6B49D39533B82D8884275C" style="OLC"><section id="H82697F9951EE4BA9912EE13EF9652095" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Social Security Child Protection Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCFEFA61BFB6945CDA2119962F7A3B9AA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reissuance of Social Security account numbers to young children in cases where confidentiality has been compromised</header><subsection id="HD4B000F2C1F841DB9B3859C6338881EB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 205(c)(2)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/405">42 U.S.C. 405(c)(2)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4140242F73214F7EAEFDEE41EB3D1F98"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating clause (iii) as clause (iv); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEB24F474AA9242B29AF29FF464396962"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after clause (ii) the following new clause:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2680E897CF764AC7A6D8F68884072857" style="traditional"><clause id="HCCA9BA6A1B414297BF702CEFF27ADE2C" indent="up3"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In any case in which a social security account number has been issued to a child who has not attained the age of 14 pursuant to subclause (IV) or (V) of clause (i) and it is demonstrated by evidence, as determined by the Commissioner of Social Security, and submitted under penalty of perjury to the Commissioner by a parent or guardian of the child that in the course of transmission of the social security card to the child, the confidentiality of such number has been compromised by reason of theft of such social security card, the Commissioner shall issue a new social security account number to such child and make note in the records maintained with respect to such child of the pertinent information received by the Commissioner regarding the theft of the social security card.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H74A19E60F1E3435491CA17239376C311"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

