<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC9350752ACB645AA881EA4CD84AAE5E7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3873 IH: Ocean Regional Opportunity and Innovation Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3873</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230606">June 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barrag&#225;n</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish Ocean Innovation Clusters to strengthen the coastal communities and ocean economy of the United States through technological research and development, job training, and cross-sector partnerships, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF139847B4D9D411C81C3DA50219892AD" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H82A6F4D29D9C4F13882ABB41CB06D41A"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ocean Regional Opportunity and Innovation Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H252100949F944471AA581F89A59D30A8"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act: </text> 
<paragraph id="H3F2720DE737542D3AB31CF05DBAD3E33"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blue Economy</header><text>The term <term>Blue Economy</term> means the value and impact of sustainable industries related to the Great Lakes, oceans, bays, estuaries, and coasts on the economy of the United States, including living resources, marine construction, marine transportation, offshore energy development and siting including for renewable energy, offshore mineral production, ship and boat building, tourism, recreation, subsistence, commercial, recreational, and charter fishing, seafood processing, and other fishery-related businesses, kelp and shellfish aquaculture, coastal resilience, and other industries the Secretary of Commerce considers appropriate. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB498F6CC0E6442BB16C5366999213F2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Director of Sea Grant</header><text>The term <term>Director of Sea Grant</term> means the Director of the National Sea Grant College Program appointed under section 204(d)(1) of the National Sea Grant College Program Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1123">33 U.S.C. 1123(d)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H967DE2D7F5054D6FBE4B4CB4CAF7687E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Indian Tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H26C8E973D554489EBA61F1564173877F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Native Hawaiian organization</header><text>The term <term>Native Hawaiian organization</term> has the meaning given the term in section 6207 of the Native Hawaiian Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7517">20 U.S.C. 7517</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H845A3F8F239443B3B14FBB9E7184DE44"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Ocean Innovation Center for Cross-Sector Collaboration</header><text>The term <term>Ocean Innovation Center for Cross-Sector Collaboration</term> means a physical space for collaboration developed and managed in accordance with section 3(i). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF25149B542AE459CBDA6982089A57141"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Ocean Innovation Cluster</header><text>The term <term>Ocean Innovation Cluster</term> means an eligible entity designated by the Secretary of Commerce under section 3.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HCF94852E09F34AEFAA2670CC842B46CE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Ocean Innovation Clusters</header> 
<subsection id="H214ACC91692541FCB92A643604376997"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Commerce, in consultation with the Director of Sea Grant, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development, shall designate not fewer than 7 eligible entities as Ocean Innovation Clusters.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA32461BC32874DB6A15E2D2FFEA4AE34"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible entities</header><text>For purposes of this section, an eligible entity is an entity—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5DA10F9D865149DBA67BA4252DD3A4A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that is composed, in a concentrated geographic region, of 1 or more—</text> <subparagraph id="H235BF2043CEC4A93B334D083FC0FA3AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>business organizations;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3525879C0F5C486BB9D127DA445FDD22"><enum>(B)</enum><text>academic institutions, including minority- and Tribal-serving institutions;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF10A524669814FFCAA625C26BE7C8F6B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>not-for-profit organizations;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H98D2429EC85F4628A4A009CBE6EE343C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Federal, State, or local governmental entities, agencies, or instrumentalities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H23847732B31F430E9697AE1D97E8F759"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Indian Tribes; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF3BEE100445E48CBB75886C2A03F61CF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Native Hawaiian organizations; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB1F455D366CF4A66BB0D92233C19F307"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that is led by a not-for-profit organization; and </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H711651BEA6E5467BAC5086F0E286D909"><enum>(3)</enum><text>that works to deliver services in the concentrated geographic region where the entity is located, enhance collaboration, promote innovation, and contribute to the equitable and sustainable growth of the Blue Economy across all sectors.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H4E332E6584E544EEB80CFFB44ACE6617"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In designating entities as Ocean Innovation Clusters under subsection (a), the Secretary of Commerce shall prioritize entities with a history of supporting cross-sector growth and development of the Blue Economy.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H1409CD8A22E84BAEA88A3218FF2F01CF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Geographic diversity</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce shall designate not fewer than 1 Ocean Innovation Cluster under subsection (a) in—</text> <paragraph id="H7B966EF15CC343538FB8AC1F26FFA52C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>each of the regions covered by the 5 regional offices of the National Marine Fisheries Service; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H08C92695CE3C444A89E6D27934504D09"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Great Lakes region; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC77DEAD8033744D09F4A6EFEF4ACBC03"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Gulf of Mexico region. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H706D74851360464488B7D4A2C3208E30"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In designating an eligible entity as an Ocean Innovation Cluster under subsection (a), the Secretary of Commerce shall consider the following:</text> <paragraph id="H17A819CAAAEC4BCDBC99D2D8B9B7D764"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The economic development potential of the coastal community or region in which the entity is located.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H953BA2DAC6364CF483AE891B1124652D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The ability of the entity to incorporate and bring growth and opportunity to broad geographic areas, including urban, rural, and underserved areas.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDBBB99836760407B86BFE038BE9406AF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Whether the entity serves a diverse, multigenerational, ocean-dependent population consisting of groups with different socioeconomic and educational attainment levels, industries, and Indian Tribes.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC16EEC8FA216446B817AF1D2BBD884DC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The ability of the entity to cultivate and leverage partnerships with private industry, academia, nongovernmental organizations, Federal, State, and local governments, and Indian Tribes to collaborate on shared outcomes. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCB39F4FBAA0F41A39F36F1BCCEE07031"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The relative potential for the designation of the entity as an Ocean Innovation Cluster to reverse a decline, or accelerate growth, in ocean sector jobs.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF2CD26CBD4F842E09CE1626795C7E2A0"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The ability of the entity to carry out projects that support economic and climate resilience through economic diversification and long-term recovery from natural disasters.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6BD75004435D45AC8C8DA2E051F81315"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The extent, rural and underserved nature, and economic underutilization of the coastline and ocean area that projects carried out by the entity could affect.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H750686D7143245B4AEFF5C7C7641F1DC"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Partnership management</header> 
<paragraph id="H4CDBE8BAD3094B61BC1A2D57A3D81923"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Partnership liaisons</header> 
<subparagraph id="H93898D12DFC449AA84CD28B55D553F9F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>The Director of Sea Grant, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development shall each designate 1 partnership manager from within their respective agencies to serve as a partnership liaison between each Ocean Innovation Cluster and Sea Grant, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and the Economic Development Administration, respectively.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0AF9FC0A29944274BD2FB1E914525BAE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Function</header><text>Each partnership liaison designated under subparagraph (A) shall ensure that Ocean Innovation Clusters—</text> 
<clause id="HCB5C2E32BAEC4BF38730E90B065EC1FC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>have direct communication with the agency of the liaison; and </text></clause> <clause id="HA277F0A8DDD5471C9164C7F663DADBEF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allow for collaboration and alignment with Federal objectives in each region regarding the Blue Economy.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9255AE82CC73466289ECA9F366D78D44"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interagency coordination</header> 
<subparagraph id="HE9ADBE737DA6475AAA3EBF1CDCF2C647"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Secretary of Commerce and partnership liaisons</header><text>The Secretary of Commerce shall coordinate with the Director of Sea Grant, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development, the Department of Energy, the Maritime Administration of the Department of Transportation, the Environmental Protection Agency, the Bureau of Ocean Energy Management of the Department of the Interior, the Department of Agriculture, the Coast Guard, and such other Federal agencies, including bureaus of the Department of Commerce, as the Secretary of Commerce considers appropriate to increase technical knowledge exchange and opportunities for cross-sector collaboration with those agencies. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H29196A2F66A1482EAC0BA7852C8060B0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Secretary of Energy</header><text>With respect to matters relating to the nexus of the Blue Economy and the responsibilities and expertise of the Department of Energy, the Secretary of Energy—</text> 
<clause id="H1A61AAE858FF493AA19492819419434D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall provide advice and recommendations to the Secretary of Commerce in order to increase technical knowledge exchange and opportunities for cross-sector collaboration; and </text></clause> <clause id="H15E00EDCB40D4030A4FE43E190C39FA9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>may provide such advice and recommendations without any formal request from the Department of Commerce. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAB021B2600184CAF9A0C061A712D7798"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Development of economic impact metrics of Ocean Innovation Clusters</header><text>The Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the Director of the Bureau of Economic Analysis of the Department of Commerce, and the heads of other relevant Federal agencies shall use and refine the Marine Economy Satellite Account to measure the value to and impact of Ocean Innovation Clusters on the Blue Economy.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5CC0C2120B9A4170AE3FFAD224843FB4"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Areas of focus</header><text>The Director of Sea Grant, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development shall coordinate with each Ocean Innovation Cluster in the following areas of focus: </text> 
<paragraph id="H91E9D866080143319D075BF63ED45530"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Increasing pathways for new entrants into the Blue Economy for individuals and entities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H958ED3D57D524F188B5A088A04EB4198"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Intellectual property management.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1B2CBF59349F48FE99227244DDF34656"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Enhancing the sustainability of seafood supply chains, including with respect to food, transportation, processing, health and beauty products, animal feed, medical biotechnology, bioplastics, biofuels, and other value-added products, to strive for full use of harvested natural resources. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H52FE98FC16A84F169ADFF375A6A69DD3"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Providing significant and sustainable economic opportunity through advanced research, cross-sector science, and technology development.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC84CEA858F3D4088849D7603BB3AB2C3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Contributing new knowledge, processes, technology, and support for stakeholders in the Blue Economy, especially to advance sustainability in specific sectors. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8999E9FB7BC44CA88B689B806FD13A64"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Working with Federal, State, local, and Tribal agencies to clearly communicate laws, regulations, and agency practices affecting industry needs, planning, or growth opportunities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1FA4E8BA76884C68BAE4CD9EE7DA5D3B"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Creating investable opportunities through the development of economies of scale to enhance growth opportunities, job creation, sustainability, and expansion for small businesses within the Blue Economy. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB43366BE107C4B3BB4C2759FAA2F73BC"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Workforce development and training, business planning, identifying existing and needed technology and economic infrastructure, and coordinated research and development among small businesses, government, and industry.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5E77A5E3FF6740DB8FDCE62114D67C9E"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Research, development, and implementation of ocean energy, bioprospecting, and other innovative and sustainable ocean resource development endeavors.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5612244B6AD94AB7B00DB961F8497C5D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Ocean Innovation Centers for Cross-Sector Collaboration</header> <paragraph id="HFBE073A98F9D456B89097F57FD04662A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In order to foster collaboration and innovation and strengthen regional ocean sector economies while creating employment opportunities, the Director of Sea Grant, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development shall collaborate with cross-sector partners to jointly develop or designate at least 1 physical space for collaboration as an Ocean Innovation Center for Cross-Sector Collaboration within each of the 7 regions with an Ocean Innovation Cluster.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCCAD48CE95BF418898FF1D179D516226"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Management</header><text>An Ocean Innovation Cluster or a group of Ocean Innovation Clusters shall manage the Ocean Innovation Center for Cross-Sector Collaboration of the region in which the Cluster or Clusters is located.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA5C28933DCE44147A040CE29A9E03D95"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Functions</header><text>Each Ocean Innovation Center for Cross-Sector Collaboration shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H61C8110D922541F0AC3595D083944B30"><enum>(A)</enum><text>serve as a hub for partners within Ocean Innovation Clusters to work toward the areas of focus in described in subsection (h); </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H485E98DCC38D4B2E8E216C478521E54E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>support a community of entrepreneurs focused on strengthening vibrant marine-dependent communities and the Blue Economy;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9E303D36F05940FF895A41444A4B368D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>create workspaces and laboratories designed to promote collaboration, including through shared meeting rooms, access to technology, common spaces, and offices;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H561A331C64D74ACF9DC0F8936A90FF28"><enum>(D)</enum><text>strengthen relationships among industry sectors through shared scientific, staffing, and business resources;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H660643D15C474420BBB22E309874BAA4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>develop the critical networks with cross-sector partners that entrepreneurs need to grow effectively; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H23E841018A5D46DE89EEC4FA89ED05F2"><enum>(F)</enum><text>develop the next generation of Blue Economy workers by providing internships, apprenticeships, or training, as appropriate, including for underrepresented and Tribal communities and local trade schools. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8AF85333171344F3A023449D6D75490A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Grants for Ocean Innovation Clusters</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Stevenson-Wydler Technology Innovation Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/3701">15 U.S.C. 3701 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HABF05C63BA7F4A13A096ECCD3F3734B4"> <section id="H403C1B4E5E334E238D3F3F410895D256"><enum>31.</enum><header>Grants for Ocean Innovation Clusters</header> <subsection id="H0BEE320864234B65A9A531FAA545210D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Director of Sea Grant, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development, may award grants, on a competitive basis, to Ocean Innovation Clusters for the purposes described in subsection (b).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA8AA636117614DB48ABFD6CDAEB0B59E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purposes</header><text>The Secretary may award grants under subsection (a) for—</text> <paragraph id="HE4CF47CA7EAC4ADC864DDE8B5990C94D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the operation and administration of one or more Ocean Innovation Clusters under the <short-title>Ocean Regional Opportunity and Innovation Act of 2023</short-title>, with the goal that Ocean Innovation Clusters will become membership-based, self-sustaining entities; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9419A1D856A54184B482D148FC0B501D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>one-time capital investments made by one or more Ocean Innovation Clusters necessary—</text> <subparagraph id="H985318EFF4D44B248F4D79D147DF8F20"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to establish one or more Ocean Innovation Centers for Cross-Sector Collaboration; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFE0FF36F1326444A89541C88A57DFD37"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to foster cross-sector collaboration within Ocean Innovation Cluster regions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H96CAAD90833F426C98F11A89D90BBD17"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Input</header><text>In awarding a grant under subsection (a), the Secretary shall provide an opportunity for input from the Director of Sea Grant, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Oceans and Atmosphere, and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Economic Development. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4B0CFD6766F442698A898228B59EFEF2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Term of grants</header> 
<paragraph id="H6AEE24C5FBF44014AAA889FD4D60F1B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Operation and administration</header> 
<subparagraph id="HA69D531F2A444748AE260B1C5FA76D28"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term of a grant awarded under subsection (a) for a purpose described in subsection (b)(1) shall be 2 years.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD7006859E2874656A48F040405E6003E"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Renewal</header><text>The Secretary may renew a grant described in subparagraph (A) for additional periods of such duration as the Secretary determines to be appropriate and necessary for the Ocean Innovation Cluster that received the grant to provide regional economic benefits.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H843E4758B92741DE9E9BCF2FFEF80CA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Capital investment</header><text>The term of a grant awarded under subsection (a) for a purpose described in subsection (b)(2) shall be for a period determined to be appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HFE5B2ADB1D98481B9A3CC057CC4E834B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grants for infrastructure</header><text>Any grant awarded under subsection (a) to support the construction of facilities, upgrades to existing facilities, or site connectivity infrastructure shall be awarded pursuant to section 201 of the Public Works and Economic Development Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3141">42 U.S.C. 3141</external-xref>) and subject to the provisions of such Act, except that subsection (b) of such section and sections 204 and 301 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3144">42 U.S.C. 3144</external-xref>, 3161) shall not apply. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB0922293ABCD4380B6B531E80BD0D440"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Limitations on grant amounts</header> 
<paragraph id="H655503A1B0954F848766F66D0B83F940"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Operation and administration</header><text>A grant awarded under subsection (a) for a purpose described in subsection (b)(1) may not exceed $10,000,000.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC3652DD0962049BFACC9B80AD5088330"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Capital investment</header><text>A grant awarded under subsection (a) for a purpose described in subsection (b)(2) may not exceed $10,000,000.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H56903BE84BD7474DB9DB20A738B461CF"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to award grants under subsection (a) $50,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC55BC0155A5340B8A5E76D4CEE95E596"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section: </text> 
<paragraph id="HBCE52A1E58DB4DB79DDE64738FD08BBD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director of Sea Grant</header><text>The term <term>Director of Sea Grant</term> means the Director of the National Sea Grant College Program appointed under section 204(d)(1) of the National Sea Grant College Program Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1123">33 U.S.C. 1123(d)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4C7B69F7CDAA4A37B359225855160F29"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ocean Innovation Cluster; Ocean Innovation Center for Cross-Sector Collaboration</header><text>The terms <term>Ocean Innovation Cluster</term> and <term>Ocean Innovation Center for Cross-Sector Collaboration</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 2 of the <short-title>Ocean Regional Opportunity and Innovation Act of 2023</short-title>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

