<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3B7B3556D57B456C8581CDB289377E2F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4605 IH: Healthy Moms and Babies Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4605</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230713">July 13, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend titles XIX and XXI of the Social Security Act to improve maternal health coverage under Medicaid and CHIP, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HCD0781023C3C44D8B9F9515B7C5D0A0D" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HFDD74C6DDE2546E6A95201A3FA211059"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header> 
<subsection id="H28CD21DC8E0C4D3793E72BED360037EF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthy Moms and Babies Act</short-title></quote>.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HD8271183C1DB4279B52CB4BD0768E467"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text>The table of contents for this Act is as follows:</text> 
<toc> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HFDD74C6DDE2546E6A95201A3FA211059">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HD2F6066C6298481290617E198CFC6B4F">Sec. 2. Definitions.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H68AFC1CA1503495494C085C57EB64716">Sec. 3. Mandatory reporting by State Medicaid programs on adult health care quality measures of maternal and perinatal health.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H443C00D035EB472191717E8A809FAC83">Sec. 4. Medicaid quality improvement initiatives to reduce rates of cesarean sections; Medicare requirement for hospitals to report on data on cesarean births.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H07D28DB4DE134FA4B15DA5B08F10E517">Sec. 5. State option to provide coordinated care through a health home for pregnant and postpartum women.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HA326D851FC35472FB9D802A1013CAB22">Sec. 6. Guidance on care coordination to support maternal health.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H549B4EDD4CA04F9A8D5EDED426789B42">Sec. 7. National reskilling of the maternity care workforce.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H88F05FCD7C63499BB9CCF076737A5642">Sec. 8. MACPAC study on doulas and community health workers; guidance on increasing access to doula services under Medicaid.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H640F2EDB72A34EA2976E90C8C774E30E">Sec. 9. Demonstration projects to improve the delivery of maternal health care through telehealth.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HFFB736ACD77847FFBDFE4F4C55C63A54">Sec. 10. CMS report on coverage of remote physiologic monitoring devices and impact on maternal and child health outcomes under Medicaid.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H0E3E66DA5B474CE3B0C70D3024959F62">Sec. 11. Guidance on community-based maternal health programs.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H53A7B146DBE14300AFADA1C2318082DD">Sec. 12. Developing guidance on maternal mortality and severe morbidity reduction for maternal care providers receiving payment under the Medicaid program.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H273F0BA0577C4E389B234644B4F45C3D">Sec. 13. Program related to reducing cesarean births and increasing rates of vaginal birth after cesarean.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H7DF6537351774DC1AE3D8B2B465D5885">Sec. 14. Collection of information related to social determinants of the health of Medicaid and CHIP beneficiaries.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="HF4FF1566989A4632ADCFA9CFED10D0D0">Sec. 15. Report on payment methodologies for transferring pregnant women between facilities before, during, and after childbirth.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H8959B565FA5E42FDA9987BA0C56EF3E6">Sec. 16. Medicaid guidance on State options to address social determinants of health for pregnant and postpartum women.</toc-entry> 
<toc-entry level="section" idref="H6A594FCD36414F409B702BD470FCD7BB">Sec. 17. Payment error rate measurement (PERM) audit and improvement requirements.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD2F6066C6298481290617E198CFC6B4F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H92329C7D2F884182B007590153E86176"><enum>(1)</enum><header>CHIP</header><text>The term <term>CHIP</term> means the Children’s Health Insurance Program established under title XXI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397aa">42 U.S.C. 1397aa et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H093AE5A321DE4A74A53A08416FC344A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Comptroller General</header><text>The term <term>Comptroller General</term> means the Comptroller General of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0D5E6903626C4D8CAE256D22361101CC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Group health plan; health insurance issuer, etc</header><text>The terms <term>group health plan</term>, <term>health insurance coverage</term>, <term>health insurance issuer</term>, <term>group health insurance coverage</term>, and <term>individual health insurance coverage</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 2791 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300gg-91">42 U.S.C. 300gg–91</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE46A9FEF49EA4C9799A9ED64A54BF459"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Medicaid</header><text>The term <term>Medicaid</term> means the Medicaid program established under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE10AF06445F142D188DD8ED9A8F16111"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Medicaid managed care organization</header><text>The term <term>medicaid managed care organization</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1903(m)(1)(A) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b(m)(1)(A)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEC583A429E8041F2B1CC0A5404DFB79B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEF2D76B4F9AD456C834030A5DB1AB0F6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> has the meaning given that term for purposes of titles V, XIX, and XXI of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/701">42 U.S.C. 701 et seq.</external-xref> 1396 et seq., 1397aa et seq.). </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H68AFC1CA1503495494C085C57EB64716"><enum>3.</enum><header>Mandatory reporting by State Medicaid programs on adult health care quality measures of maternal and perinatal health</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1139B of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1320b-9b">42 U.S.C. 1320b–9b</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H831E76EE733247F1BC60CC5AA3F8C3DF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HD8DBE8047D22488FA8ED8A2E1434435E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)(B)—</text> <clause id="HEA5DD782B074456EB12E012693941E9A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the subparagraph heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">and maternal and perinatal health</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">behavioral health</header-in-text></quote>;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7677ECDE0D5E421F880C8F3BDEC8ED80"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>all behavioral health</quote> and inserting <quote>all behavioral health and maternal and perinatal health</quote>; and</text></clause> <clause id="H97A95BE3D26140A9A197329674FB83A4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and of maternal and perinatal health care for Medicaid eligible adults</quote> after <quote>Medicaid eligible adults</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA037E5BA166041A5BB5C751636BFDB48"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)(C)—</text> <clause id="H0917E7E6C83F49D5B08B47D0FA263250"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the subparagraph heading, by inserting <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">and maternal and perinatal health</header-in-text></quote> after <quote><header-in-text level="subparagraph" style="OLC">behavioral health</header-in-text></quote>; and </text></clause> 
<clause id="H8402822461994BBBACA6A92C6A95594E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and, with respect to Medicaid eligible adults, maternal and perinatal health measures</quote> after <quote>behavioral health measures</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF55EA59070F4E11B0D9B60B457F9706"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (d)(1)(A), by inserting <quote>and maternal and perinatal health</quote> after <quote>behavioral health</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H443C00D035EB472191717E8A809FAC83"><enum>4.</enum><header>Medicaid quality improvement initiatives to reduce rates of cesarean sections; Medicare requirement for hospitals to report on data on cesarean births</header> 
<subsection id="H22B159EEBABB420A8EB9CA4C93B047DB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Medicaid state plan amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1902(a) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H42CCD013CB804A8094B4AD531FC6FB92"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (86), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC18F09EB936E49719F6C946ADB51D22B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (87), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H22FD4AAD997B4361B9692B9A92731033"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (87) the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H63528188D8E048709BAF53DB2BE322FA"> 
<paragraph id="H14795D76289D4E6A944C90A80E214EC2"><enum>(88)</enum><text>provide that, not later than January 1, 2025, and annually thereafter through January 1, 2035, the State shall submit a report to the Secretary, that shall be made publicly available, which contains with respect to the preceding calendar year—</text> <subparagraph id="HA186626EA9BB41E694A5A620696C1DF2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the rate of low-risk cesarean delivery, as defined by the Secretary in consultation with relevant stakeholders, for pregnant women eligible for medical assistance under the State plan or a waiver of such plan in the State, as compared to the overall rate of cesarean delivery in the State; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE9215265325F4E01A86C454192B0BE90"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the State’s quality improvement activities to safely reduce the rate of low-risk cesarean delivery (as so defined) for pregnant women eligible for medical assistance under the State plan or a waiver of such plan in the State reported under subparagraph (A), including initiatives aimed at reducing racial and ethnic health disparities, hospital-level quality improvement initiatives, taking into account hospital type and the patient population served, and, if applicable, partnerships with State or regional perinatal quality collaboratives; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4A9AD599812E4580A35A74E87924E92A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>for each report submitted after January 1, 2025, the percentage change (if any) in the rate of low-risk cesarean delivery (as so defined) for pregnant women eligible for medical assistance under the State plan or a waiver of such plan in the State reported under subparagraph (A) from the rate reported for the most recent previous report; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H87257F66C46145CDAE64D17A8A4BCBE4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>such other relevant data and information as determined by the Secretary, and in consultation with relevant stakeholders, such as State initiatives and evaluations of quality improvement activities, cesarean delivery rates, and health outcomes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEB1A5F9CD06644289FB6B1F5FAA992E3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>GAO study regarding medicaid payment rates for cesarean births</header> <paragraph id="H6226CE98B163401C86296B7B7F677E17"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Comptroller General shall conduct a study regarding payment rates for cesarean births and vaginal births under State Medicaid programs. To the extent feasible and data are available, the study shall include analyses of the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H66ADE0E444894003918221144DD2DE43"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Payment rates for cesarean births and vaginal births paid by fee-for-service Medicaid programs and by Medicaid programs that contract with Medicaid managed care organizations to furnish medical assistance under such programs.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H12171DB185EA4835BAAE6965B5E8767B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>What is known about how Medicaid payment rates have changed over time.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2F0BD5640D2F4B2BB34D76DA04D0A026"><enum>(C)</enum><text>What is known about how payment rates for cesarean and vaginal births by Medicaid programs compare with the payment rates for such births by other sources of insurance coverage.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H81533A558E5A49359B153AEE26BD0B52"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Such other factors related to payment rates for cesarean and vaginal births under Medicaid as the Comptroller General determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0915070477514F20A5579504351B166E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to Congress a report containing the results of the study conducted under paragraph (1), together with recommendations for such legislation and administrative action as the Comptroller General determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HA5D1DE2312B340A88E3D350BEB137E89"><enum>(c)</enum><header>GAO study on racial disparities in cesarean births</header> <paragraph id="H994360FF60214545B4D386240F3C4D13"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Comptroller General shall conduct a study on racial disparities in the frequency of cesarean births. To the extent feasible and data are available, the study shall compare such information on low- and high-risk cesarean births, differences by payer (such as Medicaid and private payers), and hospital characteristics (such as location or hospital type). Such study may consider other factors related to racial disparities in maternal health as the Comptroller General deems appropriate.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA77684713D814E5A96AF9317911E929A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General shall submit to Congress a report containing the results of the study conducted under paragraph (1), together with recommendations for such legislation and administrative action as the Comptroller General determines appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCBA60516431A40A98F3FC2BD503858C0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Medicare requirement for hospitals To report data on cesarean births</header> <paragraph id="H56F46E1C66E74F2EA868DB6FAE0C7A4F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1866(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395cc">42 U.S.C. 1395cc(a)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB180D3231F894F2DAE4FFC0AE06CFDE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by moving the indentation of subparagraph (W) 2 ems to the left;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6AC0D534DBFB469FA3717E8B614669EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (X)—</text> 
<clause id="H0391F2AD79884B40AD99116CCA6706C7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by moving the indentation 2 ems to the left; and</text></clause> <clause id="H660572D6D3034EA69125FB50643BE0D9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H92EA73772EBF4C13B5654CF17A66F289"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in subparagraph (Y), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7C7235CA801749DEA337095B2343BA43"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (Y) the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6301161C841B4763BF40B4F005EB045F"> 
<subparagraph id="H7661F516C0544CB599003672618D1868" indent="up1"><enum>(Z)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the case of a hospital, to submit, in a form and manner, and at a time, specified by the Secretary, data on the Nulliparous, Term, Singleton, Vertex Cesarean section (NTSV C-section) rate with respect to the hospital for the preceding year.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC6301A88705843DF8C20BE2DE18D7EE3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Incorporation into hospital quality reporting</header><text>Section 1886(b)(3)(B)(viii) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395ww">42 U.S.C. 1395ww(b)(3)(B)(viii)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subclause:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H53A9651981B049EAA2BC89C1001D4478"> 
<subclause id="H8A26E5BF1EE84D738C3370C4BADDA836" indent="up4"><enum>(XIII)</enum><text>Effective for payments beginning with fiscal year 2025, in expanding the number of measures under subclause (III), the Secretary shall adopt a measure relating to the Nulliparous, Term, Singleton, Vertex Cesarean section (NTSV C-section) rate for hospitals in inpatient settings. Not later than 2025, the Secretary shall incorporate such measure into the designation of maternity care quality hospitals, as described in the final rule entitled <quote>Medicare Program; Hospital Inpatient Prospective Payment Systems for Acute Care Hospitals and the Long-Term Care Hospital Prospective Payment System and Policy Changes and Fiscal Year 2023 Rates; Quality Programs and Medicare Promoting Interoperability Program Requirements for Eligible Hospitals and Critical Access Hospitals; Costs Incurred for Qualified and Non-Qualified Deferred Compensation Plans; and Changes to Hospital and Critical Access Hospital Conditions of Participation</quote> (87 Fed. Reg. 48780 (August 10, 2022)).</text></subclause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section> <section commented="no" id="H07D28DB4DE134FA4B15DA5B08F10E517"><enum>5.</enum><header>State option to provide coordinated care through a health home for pregnant and postpartum women</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 1945A the following new section:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD4E5D73B8EE94EFBB764E33AD178B320"> 
<section commented="no" id="H9A13B4144A72428FA816063B432A2805"><enum>1945B.</enum><header>State option to provide coordinated care through a health home for pregnant and postpartum women</header> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H6F99A369F7944FD88C4611BDF992CD84"><enum>(a)</enum><header>State option</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HCA27C9BBD5454BE1BD4F1A8803C3EC40"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding section 1902(a)(1) (relating to statewideness) and section 1902(a)(10)(B) (relating to comparability), beginning April 1, 2026, a State, at its option as a State plan amendment, may provide for medical assistance under this title to an eligible woman who chooses to— </text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H13AB406FD66043C9A541DCF466961D67"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enroll in a maternity health home under this section by selecting a designated provider, a team of health care professionals operating with such a provider, or a health team as the woman’s maternity health home for purposes of providing the woman with pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HE8E3741546B940DEA17506221C72DF05"><enum>(B)</enum><text>receive such services from a designated provider, a team of health care professionals operating with such a provider, or a health team that has voluntarily opted to participate in a maternity health home for eligible women under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H189DAD8833E64D8AA182EC73A94743A8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Eligible woman defined</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible woman</term> means an individual—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H6B41B5ABDB9A4FA98EBFB470A3676049"><enum>(A)</enum><text>who is eligible for medical assistance under the State plan (or under a waiver of such plan) for all items and services covered under the State plan (or waiver) that are not less in amount, duration, or scope, or are determined by the Secretary to be substantially equivalent, to the medical assistance available for an individual described in subsection (a)(10)(A)(i); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H2A5FC57F8DC345BC9A28547A1ABCA9BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>who— </text> 
<clause commented="no" id="HD519985F918D4D7E8D1BA45079FA81ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is pregnant; or</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HA5EDEE603FD94C2592707B815C34B08E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>had a pregnancy end within the last 365 days.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H5FFE8E41CE0245CD9C350CF9ECC6C597"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Qualification standards</header><text>The Secretary shall establish standards for qualification as a maternity health home or as a designated provider, team of health care professionals operating with such a provider, or a health team eligible for participation in a maternity health home for purposes of this section. In establishing such standards, the Secretary shall consider best practices and models of care used by recipients of grants under section 330P of the Public Health Service Act. Such standards shall include requiring designated providers, teams of health care professionals operating with such providers, and health teams (designated as a maternity health home) to demonstrate to the State the ability to do the following: </text> <paragraph commented="no" id="HB01992DC6C1E4AFCA7872073177C0EE6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Coordinate prompt care and access to necessary maternity care services, including services provided by specialists, and programs for an eligible woman during her pregnancy and the 365-day period beginning on the last day of her pregnancy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H6A109EF3984A42AFAEE5F88403296C85"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Develop an individualized, comprehensive, patient-centered care plan for each eligible woman that accommodates patient preferences and, if applicable, reflects adjustments to the payment methodology described in subsection (c)(2)(B).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HC0DB00241C144B8CB1670281D10865FF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Develop and incorporate into each eligible woman’s care plan, in a culturally and linguistically appropriate manner consistent with the needs of the eligible woman, ongoing home care, community-based primary care, inpatient care, social support services, health-related social needs services, behavioral health services, local hospital emergency care, and, in the event of a change in income that would result in the eligible woman losing eligibility for medical assistance under the State plan or waiver, care management and planning related to a change in the eligible woman's health insurance coverage.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H367CE2BC79D54FCFB3C1CD33FFA96111"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Coordinate with pediatric care providers, as appropriate.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H6FB9577F232F46D79EC95FBA0AE32CDB"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Collect and report information under subsection (f)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HD7B7E451D5C34270BC76EBBAE355909A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Payments</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H3C6ADCF4C61F49E79A85A6072B0A3D96"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State shall provide a designated provider, a team of health care professionals operating with such a provider, or a health team with payments for the provision of pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services, to each eligible woman that selects such provider, team of health care professionals, or health team as the woman’s maternity health home or care provider. Payments made to a maternity health home or care provider for such services shall be treated as medical assistance for purposes of section 1903(a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H5EC433477779413EBC17BF069065CC7B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Methodology</header><text>The State shall specify in the State plan amendment the methodology the State will use for determining payment for the provision of pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services or treatment during an eligible woman's pregnancy and the 365-day period beginning on the last day of her pregnancy. Such methodology for determining payment—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HA6D2688943694812A3B291BE78273043"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may be based on—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H677D26DF9B1D4F22A4741034E29EE70A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a per-member per-month basis for each eligible woman enrolled in the maternity health home; </text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H6A2F46202F2842D2AC01530D2BBA5EF7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a prospective payment model, in the case of payments to Federally qualified health centers or a rural health clinics; or</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H8DE43A2FF3B545CCBF62AF77C74DE34F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>an alternate model of payment (which may include a model developed under a waiver under section 1115) proposed by the State and approved by the Secretary; </text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H16343C277694483BA1B08844B00A4E82"><enum>(B)</enum><text>may be adjusted to reflect, with respect to each eligible woman—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H28C44A01E05E46EF8239F343B5E9355B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the severity of the risks associated with the woman's pregnancy;</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H8CF5CC3A340142F2BB18E9BF89B8DE85"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the severity of the risks associated with the woman's postpartum health care needs; and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H83EE79BD74A143839B5838F567F5480F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the level or amount of time of care coordination required with respect to the woman; and</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H91D15FC9D7BE44DA8C734CE7B71C31E3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shall be established consistent with section 1902(a)(30)(A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H55F9D5504C4A41C097834E349EF47304"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordinating care</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="HB9EB1BCE1BAD47B196E73F81E44A49FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Hospital notification</header><text>A State with a State plan amendment approved under this section shall require each hospital that is a participating provider under the State plan (or under a waiver of such plan) to establish procedures in the case of an eligible woman who seeks treatment in the emergency department of such hospital for—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H635CCFD58C6D4FC28EE73C9ABFD2BDDC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>providing the woman with culturally and linguistically appropriate information on the respective treatment models and opportunities for the woman to access a maternity health home and its associated benefits; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H260255908FDD458F9340DE058E359ECC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>notifying the maternity health home in which the woman is enrolled, or the designated provider, team of health care professionals operating with such a provider, or health team treating the woman, of the woman's treatment in the emergency department and of the protocols for the maternity health home, designated provider, or team to be involved in the woman’s emergency care or post-discharge care.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H66D1ACDC73BB46029E826FF95C80D5F8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Education with respect to availability of a maternity health home</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H3DEEFD6E26974314A410DBA67BFDFD32"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In order for a State plan amendment to be approved under this section, a State shall include in the State plan amendment a description of the State’s process for—</text> <clause commented="no" id="H9B48E0DFC77F40EA8E17F6C7D9EB7AC0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>educating providers participating in the State plan (or a waiver of such plan) on the availability of maternity health homes for eligible women, including the process by which such providers can participate in or refer eligible women to an approved maternity health home or a designated provider, team of health care professionals operating such a provider, or health team; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H3D25686B634E4FAAB78EC4F5D4A297A9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>educating eligible women, in a culturally and linguistically appropriate manner, on the availability of maternity health homes. </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H6806C544EE544F8F9E94244B819106CC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Outreach</header><text>The process established by the State under subparagraph (A) shall include the participation of entities or other public or private organizations or entities that provide outreach and information on the availability of health care items and services to families of individuals eligible to receive medical assistance under the State plan (or a waiver of such plan).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H6B1A5D83AAB64A449AA8BBA025AECBA6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Mental health coordination</header><text>A State with a State plan amendment approved under this section shall consult and coordinate, as appropriate, with the Secretary in addressing issues regarding the prevention, identification, and treatment of mental health conditions and substance use disorders among eligible women.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H433956C43F4D4BA5AB0EBF196340530A"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Social and support services</header><text>A State with a State plan amendment approved under this section shall consult and coordinate, as appropriate, with the Secretary in establishing means to connect eligible women receiving pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services under this section with social and support services, including services made available under maternal, infant, and early childhood home visiting programs established under section 511, and services made available under section 330H or title X of the Public Health Service Act.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H61BCAE0DD6C248EDBFDD8F42734BDC7B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Monitoring</header><text>A State shall include in the State plan amendment—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="HA549337BEAFF4B21A9FE2B033637042E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a methodology for tracking reductions in inpatient days and reductions in the total cost of care resulting from improved care coordination and management under this section;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H7FDD529612474FFD8585B2DF4CEA727C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a proposal for use of health information technology in providing an eligible woman with pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services as specified under this section and improving service delivery and coordination across the care continuum; and </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HE9BC2E40BA894C1FB4A5473F614C8E3D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a methodology for tracking prompt and timely access to medically necessary care for eligible women from out-of-State providers.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HD7D5C90C37CD4139B9E2228722D45082"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Data collection</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HFC1387EEA8A443EE9417E91AC913D90D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Provider reporting requirements</header><text>In order to receive payments from a State under subsection (c), a maternity health home, or a designated provider, a team of health care professionals operating with such a provider, or a health team, shall report to the State, at such time and in such form and manner as may be required by the State, including through a health information exchange or other public health data sharing entity, the following information:</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H9D371FEE771145BEB616BDC58EF196FF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>With respect to each such designated provider, team of health care professionals operating with such a provider, and health team (designated as a maternity health home), the name, National Provider Identification number, address, and specific health care services offered to be provided to eligible women who have selected such provider, team of health care professionals, or health team as the women's maternity health home.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H663DE5126BEA4600914F10E4C695F9E7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Information on measures from the core sets of child health quality measures and adult health quality measures under sections 1139A and 1139B that are identified by the Secretary as being relevant to maternal, perinatal, or infant health. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC201946181204B0DAEB375F236B4DC5D"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information on all other applicable measures for determining the quality of services provided by such provider, team of health care professionals, or health team.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H48620C53C6134135BA301DE747E77F70"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Such other information as the Secretary shall specify in guidance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H0CBB0C6617004EFC8608F85863B51EA0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State reporting requirements</header> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H14F799FDF5964529B1AB197EFBC000AB"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Comprehensive report</header><text>A State with a State plan amendment approved under this section shall report to the Secretary (and, upon request, to the Medicaid and CHIP Payment and Access Commission), at such time, but at a minimum frequency of every 12 months, and in such form and manner determined by the Secretary to be reasonable and minimally burdensome, including through a health information exchange or other public health data sharing entity, the following information: </text> 
<clause commented="no" id="H57CED0E63950484DBA923A8D516AC3D5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Information described in paragraph (1).</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H6A6BCA52EB134FCB8897E97E6A1EF7B3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The number and, to the extent available and while maintaining all relevant protecting privacy and confidentially protections, disaggregated demographic information of eligible women who have enrolled in a maternity health home pursuant to this section.</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HF60DC56F02E14E309A9A823EE9242FB6"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>The number of maternity health homes in the State.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HEED4808FF368475BA150D23E8E5BA6BB"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>The medical conditions or factors that contribute to severe maternal morbidity among eligible women enrolled in maternity health homes in the State.</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HB3568C1E704E404D87174A08CBF9C59C"><enum>(v)</enum><text>The extent to which such women receive health care items and services under the State plan before, during, and after the women’s enrollment in such a maternity health home.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="H4DAB56DED9E7430CBAD87B9D90B3FF67"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Where applicable, mortality data and data for the associated causes of death for eligible women enrolled in a maternity health home under this section, in accordance with subsection (g). For deaths occurring postpartum, such data shall distinguish between deaths occurring up to 42 days postpartum and deaths occurring between 43 days to up to 1 year postpartum. Where applicable, data reported under this clause shall be reported alongside comparable data from a State’s maternal mortality review committee, as established in accordance with section 317K(d) of the Public Health Service Act, for purposes of further identifying and comparing statewide trends in maternal mortality among populations participating in the maternity health home under this section.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H81C8D6B12BEE4B28877425F5703A033A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after a State has a State plan amendment approved under this section, the State shall submit to the Secretary, and make publicly available on the appropriate State website, a report on how the State is implementing the option established under this section, including through any best practices adopted by the State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDFB1E33553A146CA9BE8931BCE426A5B"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text>A State with a State plan amendment under this section shall establish confidentiality protections for the purposes of subsection (f)(2)(A) to ensure, at a minimum, that there is no disclosure by the State of any identifying information about any specific eligible woman enrolled in a maternity health home or any maternal mortality case, and that all relevant confidentiality and privacy protections, including the requirements under 1902(a)(7)(A), are maintained. </text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HD184F1BAE68E46D185DB1A952A6DED92"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to require— </text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H4BDFF2B8CA5142CF917187730F9E757A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an eligible woman to enroll in a maternity health home under this section; or</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H1A813CB07E694FE2A2D68CBD15C25694"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a designated provider or health team to act as a maternity health home and provide services in accordance with this section if the provider or health team does not voluntarily agree to act as a maternity health home.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" id="H15D7B3503592442B8AF18CF1191CA237"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Planning grants</header> <paragraph commented="no" id="H025075630F134965B55754F6BCE66940"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Beginning October 1, 2025, from the amount appropriated under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall award planning grants to States for purposes of developing and submitting a State plan amendment under this section. The Secretary shall award a grant to each State that applies for a grant under this subsection, but the Secretary may determine the amount of the grant based on the merits of the application and the goal of the State to prioritize health outcomes for eligible women. A planning grant awarded to a State under this subsection shall remain available until expended.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HE20A2DFBC97B46D9BE8CB1CCA5DAF973"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriation</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $50,000,000 for the period of fiscal years 2024 through 2026, for the purposes of making grants under this subsection, to remain available until expended.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HC14CF5FD09E74B19B99478409751BCAC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The total amount of payments made to States under this subsection shall not exceed $50,000,000.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="HA703FC56ECC944D1A67D9F197689D718"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Additional definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H1965D779F8D148EBA5476B11796374B1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Designated provider</header><text>The term <term>designated provider</term> means a physician (including an obstetrician-gynecologist), hospital, clinical practice or clinical group practice, a medicaid managed care organization, as defined in section 1903(m)(1)(A), a prepaid inpatient health plan, as defined in section 438.2 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation), a prepaid ambulatory health plan, as defined in such section (or any successor regulation), rural clinic, community health center, community mental health center, or any other entity or provider that is determined by the State and approved by the Secretary to be qualified to be a maternity health home on the basis of documentation evidencing that the entity has the systems, expertise, and infrastructure in place to provide pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services. Such term may include providers who are employed by, or affiliated with, a hospital. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HB422C74665A74674BB4A50509DB28EFF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Maternity health home</header><text>The term <term>maternity health home</term> means a designated provider (including a provider that operates in coordination with a team of health care professionals) or a health team is selected by an eligible woman to provide pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H39F7CDD3F38242FF8839164CBA004759"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Health team</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>health team</term> has the meaning given such term for purposes of section 3502 of <external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/111/148">Public Law 111–148</external-xref>. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HD0C86B5D32584B8A81C1DE21E63E0A67"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H3821562662BB43E491AC5CFFE9EF6E64"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>pregnancy and postpartum coordinated care services</term> means items and services related to the coordination of care for comprehensive and timely high-quality, culturally and linguistically appropriate, services described in subparagraph (B) that are provided by a designated provider, a team of health care professionals operating with such a provider, or a health team (designated as a maternity health home). </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HC7B12114F60542F5896B8B64A3C53842"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Services described</header> <clause commented="no" id="H4ED0DE31263E44A38E0BD24CACBEB692"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The services described in this subparagraph shall include with respect to a State electing the State plan amendment option under this section, any medical assistance for items and services for which payment is available under the State plan or under a waiver of such plan. </text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H9FA7AE3DAA844879B0BE88FD65612586"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Other items and services</header><text>In addition to medical assistance described in clause (i), the services described in this subparagraph shall include the following:</text> <subclause commented="no" id="HE2C6CB165E4A403C95D185AE480EF00A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Any item or service for which medical assistance is otherwise available under the State plan (or a waiver of such plan) related to the treatment of a woman during the woman's pregnancy and the 1-year period beginning on the last day of her pregnancy, including mental health and substance use disorder services. </text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H98BF1F20352B4B47886EF9601C1BF9F9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Comprehensive care management.</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="H5E47CED353574FBA9BEAE0043B015B8D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Care coordination (including with pediatricians as appropriate), health promotion, and providing access to the full range of maternal, obstetric, and gynecologic services, including services from out-of-State providers.</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="H81AFD0C81AF44A309A9BB39644428B3F"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Comprehensive transitional care, including appropriate follow-up, from inpatient to other settings.</text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="H83DCCC8BF933464491B68316F984D44A"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Patient and family support (including authorized representatives).</text></subclause> 
<subclause commented="no" id="HD5E350EE0F5C4838810756991EE24297"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>Referrals to community and social support services, if relevant. </text></subclause> <subclause commented="no" id="H41ACEABD95FC47A49CE0F38385B926B5"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>Use of health information technology to link services, as feasible and appropriate.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="HE46D82514E6F42BABC5EB4D6D410A9E7"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Team of health care professionals</header><text>The term <term>team of health care professionals</term> means a team of health care professionals (as described in the State plan amendment under this section) that may—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="HB97403101B644340A14C7465BBF464B9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>include—</text> 
<clause commented="no" id="HEC2B938D5A72476BAA69EEDF57FAABE4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>physicians, including gynecologist-obstetricians, pediatricians, and other professionals such as physicians assistants, advance practice nurses, including certified nurse midwives, nurses, nurse care coordinators, dietitians, nutritionists, social workers, behavioral health professionals, physical counselors, physical therapists, occupational therapists, or any professionals that assist in prenatal care, delivery, or postpartum care for which medical assistance is available under the State plan or a waiver of such plan and determined to be appropriate by the State and approved by the Secretary;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HC6F03F64717E48258C89458F8EC2CBCC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an entity or individual who is designated to coordinate such care delivered by the team; and</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="H04E3B650AAC54E54828DC321E7891C9B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>when appropriate and if otherwise eligible to furnish items and services that are reimbursable as medical assistance under the State plan or under a waiver of such plan, doulas, community health workers, translators and interpreters, and other individuals with culturally appropriate and trauma-informed expertise; and </text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43A472A4BCF14D1FB3E55FBB9E0EED86"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide care at a facility that is freestanding, virtual, or based at a hospital, community health center, community mental health center, rural clinic, clinical practice or clinical group practice, academic health center, or any entity determined to be appropriate by the State and approved by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> 
<section id="HA326D851FC35472FB9D802A1013CAB22"><enum>6.</enum><header>Guidance on care coordination to support maternal health</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue guidance for State Medicaid programs on improved care coordination, continuity of care, and clinical integration to support the needs of pregnant and postpartum women for services eligible for Medicaid payment. Such guidance shall identify best practices for care coordination for such women, both with respect to fee-for-service State Medicaid programs and State Medicaid programs that contract with Medicaid managed care organizations or other specified entities to furnish medical assistance for such women, and shall illustrate strategies for— </text> <paragraph id="HF608836072D446D7BC8E9421D2C82D58"><enum>(1)</enum><text>enhancing primary care and maternity care coordination with specialists, including cardiologists, specialists in gestational diabetes, dentists, lactation specialists, genetic counselors, and behavioral health providers;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H058702AE95724603909B7E54A7DC3D56"><enum>(2)</enum><text>integrating behavioral health providers to provide screening, assessment, treatment, and referral for behavioral health needs, including substance use disorders, maternal depression, anxiety, intimate partner violence, and other trauma;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H081146889C164F09AB599C3B3BD277E6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>integrating into care teams or coordinating with nonclinical professionals, including (if licensed or credentialed by a State or State-authorized organization) doulas, peer support specialists, and community health workers, and how these services provided by such professionals may be eligible for Federal financial participation under Medicaid;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H328CBD3F9D1E43FA86C56DAF74FD97C0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>screening pregnant and postpartum women for social needs and coordinating related services during the prenatal and postpartum periods to ensure social and physical supports are provided for such women during such periods and for their children;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9151EC3269264B318458D92FB52888C8"><enum>(5)</enum><text>supporting women who have had a stillbirth;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H20CC2981181C4794A236ACC41BDFE339"><enum>(6)</enum><text>screening for maternal health, behavioral health, and social needs during well-child and pediatric care visits; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H82A79EAFC7584CBB83F1E32469C5FC1F"><enum>(7)</enum><text>streamlining and reducing duplication in care coordination efforts across and among providers, plans, and other entities for such women. </text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H549B4EDD4CA04F9A8D5EDED426789B42"><enum>7.</enum><header>National reskilling of the maternity care workforce</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part B of title III of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/243">42 U.S.C. 243 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after section 317L–1 the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H9C89C671FBA84FD9BF124397E806CADE" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC"> <section id="HEF79E10666744860B850E147CEB06F1D"><enum>317L–2.</enum><header>National reskilling of the maternity care workforce</header> <subsection id="H8A60631E1769467282062F81B98A340A"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of national expert group</header> <paragraph id="H39B661647AFE4F919A89665848784254"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a national expert group to evaluate national education on, and practice of, best birthing practices. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6CCD5463E7F24B9093BE010465960A05"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Members</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2936766F4AD5448FBE751CCF2329D697"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The group established under paragraph (1) shall be composed of such members as the Secretary appoints, including—</text> <clause id="H98F3CAC94BC54A0AA193FDF5DAD9A89B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>obstetricians and gynecologists, family medicine physicians, midwives, and nursing leaders;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HB6AE903D5DB749A49EEB503DD19D8257"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>hospital administrators;</text></clause> <clause id="H8B5EF37754CB461287D7B5AA08B05207"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>graduate medical education leaders;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF024F00B5D7D4F8DB22536F9F2BF1A37"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>doula leaders; </text></clause> <clause id="HE89CADC0CE6142D3BCF1EDECC4CBF2AB"><enum>(v)</enum><text>individuals with experience in community birth settings; </text></clause> 
<clause id="HA1E473F29E7B48ED843AB0A3704F712C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>patients; </text></clause> <clause id="HAE1FB8F6F7674E3887E67C313D81671C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>high-risk birth experts; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H65B8E907D6A2470DAF2BEA46EB6B0ADA"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>quality improvement leaders.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE70B463B9DF54205A2756B8E06B4F6DB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Geographic diversity</header><text>In appointing members under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall ensure a balance of members representing rural areas and members representing urban areas.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7B8DC7B294FD4F4391FECA0DAD4C330B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The group established under subsection (a) shall—</text> <paragraph id="HEBB46B09C1294287A36C94FB7B87E7D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>examine evidence, trends, and differential use or access by income, geographic area, and race and ethnicity associated with birthing practices that include—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H82B50D43A05A45CC983C294AFD1814D7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>cesarean sections, repeat cesarean, and vaginal birth after cesarean;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8BFE6DFF127E4A35BB72C764E7663F66"><enum>(B)</enum><text>electronic fetal monitoring and intermittent auscultation;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9F7462BA84554C64A8E695B0730DABE5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>birth positions, including upright positioning and ambulation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H5EFE2EE0A2854FEAB80B54B05BE8CEBC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>labor with doula support;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF5700F2DA38440A1A05CC293FC3D6A55"><enum>(E)</enum><text>evaluating indications for cesarean delivery, including cervical dilation and duration of pushing;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H698710E9AF4B4AC588E187CD52D89A73"><enum>(F)</enum><text>operative vaginal deliveries;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H20A4A3EB4D1A49229F232DD5286F9D7D"><enum>(G)</enum><text>manual fetal rotation;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA5F4E0F1865E4513A59D6B1DFBD38787"><enum>(H)</enum><text>amnioinfusion and scalp stimulation; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2DCA9ADFAD4B4216933FF79CBD9213B8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>cervical ripening methods;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC36EC2066D374D62B0B6377B8BF164EE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>assess the role of the culture of care, maternity care financing, and health education with respect to the trends under paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF5BC822A8F7548A49A499506788661F1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>identify case studies of the provision of exemplary birthing care.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HBD868006AE9647509E39D502A289F0BC"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Recommendations</header><text>The group established under subsection (a) shall, not later than 1 year after such establishment, issue—</text> 
<paragraph id="H70325228D4ED499C992EF8694AE8DE15"><enum>(1)</enum><text>best practices for—</text> <subparagraph id="H322038F4E11A4C8A8C5E0720D7A16CDF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>evaluating birthing skills;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE4FF8686C1B140CFB348E5D57D8BDCCE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>improving curricula for health professionals engaged in birthing; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8910BD36B17644BAB8923A42495D29EC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the incorporation of midwives and doulas into residency curricula for obstetricians; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA9C5406EC41040B2924035B2F7D42268" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text>recommendations for policies and practices to improve maternity care overall.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> <section id="H88F05FCD7C63499BB9CCF076737A5642"><enum>8.</enum><header>MACPAC study on doulas and community health workers; guidance on increasing access to doula services under Medicaid</header> <subsection id="H537F746626504A6093E3DF393FFD0758"><enum>(a)</enum><header>MACPAC study on doulas and community health workers</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE88B544711FC4469B8A12D7B7C74BC5E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of the first report required under section 1900(b)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396(b)(1)</external-xref>) after the date that is 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Medicaid and CHIP Payment and Access Commission (referred to in this section as <term>MACPAC</term>) shall include with such report a report on the coverage of doula services and the role of community health workers under State Medicaid programs, which shall include the following: </text> 
<subparagraph id="HAAAD4B3631904D9EA95D3E4C7EC9811E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Information about coverage for doula services and community health worker services under State Medicaid programs that currently provide coverage for such services, including the type of doula services offered (such as prenatal, labor and delivery, postpartum support, and traditional doula services) and information on the prevalence of doulas that care for individuals in their own communities. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H20918DA2E4CA4B72A206517292069778"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An analysis of strategies to facilitate the appropriate use of doula services in order to provide better care and achieve better maternal and infant health outcomes, including strategies that States may use to assist with services for which Federal financial participation is eligible under a State Medicaid plan or a waiver of such a plan by recruiting, training, and certifying a diverse doula workforce, particularly from underserved communities, communities of color, and communities facing linguistic or cultural barriers. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H01165C36B2614D4981687DB860AD9B7F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Provide examples of community health worker access in State Medicaid programs and strategies employed by States to encourage a broad care team to manage Medicaid patients.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2525BFCF6FA74025B6FCA33791697F05"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An assessment of the impact of the involvement of doulas and community health workers on maternal health outcomes. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HACB8DEE49CE14077BB32E98A7D93B8FD"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Recommendations, as MACPAC deems appropriate, for legislative and administrative actions to increase access to services that improve maternal health. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H433B8E6F51224E75806F248243A58574"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Stakeholder consultation</header><text>In developing the report required under paragraph (1), MACPAC shall consult with relevant stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H583C4B7E815D49A3969C4EB1A6E2CC4B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance on increasing access to doula services under Medicaid</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6124B57BE2B84340884FFBE8382C54BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date that MACPAC publishes the report required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall issue guidance to States on increasing access to doula services under Medicaid. Such guidance shall at a minimum include—</text> <subparagraph id="H2486C43F2BDB4FCFAFA24C10A718714D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>options for States to provide medical assistance for doula services under State Medicaid programs;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H438B3FFF3CE34B5891CB799935A4E62B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>best practices for ensuring that doulas, including community-based doulas, receive reimbursement for doula services provided under a State Medicaid program, at a level that allows doulas to earn a living wage that accounts for their time and costs associated with providing care and community-based doula program administration; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H05CA465F91B640C1A2F807000C18E463"><enum>(C)</enum><text>best practices for increasing access to doula services, including services provided by community-based doulas, under State Medicaid programs. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H996A7827BF8845AA9A2F8A54C61CC4F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Stakeholder consultation</header><text>In developing the report required under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall consult with relevant stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H473AA1293A4C435B85CE3C4991F85F8F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Relevant stakeholders</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of subsections (a)(2) and (b)(2), relevant stakeholders shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="HA1AC498F78A74E62B541E7396A9B3208"><enum>(1)</enum><text>States;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H81BBB77FDEBB4AA1B382262B4AB4C8FD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>organizations representing consumers, including those that are disproportionately impacted by poor maternal health outcomes;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H640FDA6B604B4CD7B752E0E876D2257E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>organizations and individuals representing doula services providers and community health workers, including community-based doula programs and those who serve underserved communities, communities of color and communities facing linguistic or cultural barriers; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA311969C41084BBCA6CDA86A40D90BDC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>organizations representing health care providers.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H640F2EDB72A34EA2976E90C8C774E30E"><enum>9.</enum><header>Demonstration projects to improve the delivery of maternal health care through telehealth</header> 
<subsection id="HE9E4ECB97A074111BFA95DCA3856F83B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall award grants to States to conduct demonstration projects under this section that are designed to expand the use of telehealth in State Medicaid programs for the delivery of health care to eligible pregnant or postpartum women. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H92D5384153F142429D1707E31029FC33"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible pregnant or postpartum woman defined</header> <paragraph id="H9EA4F55CB9C34F84B343A4D8CFD7CDA9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In this section, the term <term>eligible pregnant or postpartum woman</term> means a woman who is eligible for and receiving medical assistance under a State Medicaid plan (or waiver of such plan) and who is or becomes pregnant.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB8015143267642F3A5F17DC81993F483"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Postpartum women</header><text>Such term includes a woman described in paragraph (1) through the end of the month in which the 365-day period beginning on the last day of the woman's pregnancy ends, without regard to any change in income of the family of which she is a member.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3D31284DE4CD4A6E9269D68ED48CE5A6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application; selection of States; duration</header> <paragraph id="HFC4FF8DAFDD4483EAC2FBBA1ADDD1550"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Application</header> <subparagraph id="H0CE59330EA99486996C5C217F477CCE8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To conduct a demonstration project under this section, a State shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time and in such manner as the Secretary shall require. Under the demonstration project, a State may include multiple proposed uses of grant funds, and propose to focus on multiple populations, as otherwise allowable under this section, within a single application. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBAB17F0DEBFD43EB835C724A328DBA74"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Required information</header><text>A State application to conduct a demonstration project under this section shall include the following:</text> <clause id="H4FA954747F214F30B01C6457D6F4B6E4"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The population (such as individuals residing in rural or medically underserved areas) that the demonstration project will target. </text></clause> 
<clause id="HDB9C90120CB44017B252A9D9DCD1EEFF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A description of how the State proposes to use funds awarded under this section to conduct the demonstration project to integrate or increase the integration of telehealth into the State Medicaid program’s existing delivery system for furnishing medical assistance to and improving the health care outcomes of eligible pregnant or postpartum women.</text></clause> <clause id="HBA8A5F070FAB4CEB87976909BDDE3198"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A description of how the State will use funds to address racial or ethnic disparities in access to maternal health services or maternal health outcomes, barriers to care, including in rural or medically underserved communities, other barriers to using telehealth, such as those experienced by individuals with disabilities and individuals with limited English proficiency, and as applicable, barriers to the use of telehealth in tribal communities. </text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" id="HF297206587CA47C38481C437DE01A4D9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A certification that the application meets the requirements of subparagraph (C).</text></clause> <clause commented="no" id="HB5BE7590ED8D4976A71A71D3DBE5B04E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Such other information as the Secretary shall require.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H3907E88DC3BE41FEB14A3B377AE98FC8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Consultation with health care stakeholders</header><text>Prior to the submission of an application to conduct a demonstration project under this section, a State shall consult with health care systems and providers, health plans (if relevant), consumer organizations and beneficiary advocates, and community-based organizations or other stakeholders in the area that the demonstration project will target to ensure that the proposed project addresses the health care needs of eligible pregnant or postpartum women in such area. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBEAF7D58809B4A809283D5B4E9593903"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection of States and duration of projects</header> <subparagraph id="HA61A2CD41A924602B7E3649FF5491921"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award grants to States that apply and meet the application requirements to conduct 4-year demonstration projects under this section. A State may request, and the Secretary shall determine the appropriateness of, an application of up to $10,000,000. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H84EE5D1A07B4472A993F8A238BA7A6F6"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Selection of projects</header><text>In selecting a State to conduct a demonstration project under this section, the Secretary shall ensure that the State is aware of the 4-year duration of the project and shall determine the State has satisfied the application requirements. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HADC68CD3E6E84A4A8E2BBF427D98C913"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Waiver of statewideness and comparability requirement</header><text>The Secretary shall waive compliance with section 1902(a)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(1)</external-xref>) (relating to statewideness) and section 1902(a)(10)(B) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396a">42 U.S.C. 1396a(a)(10)(B)</external-xref>) (relating to comparability) to the extent necessary to allow selected States to conduct demonstration projects under this section. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0A775EE7390B49C0901FEE61C004E633"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of grant funds</header><text>A State may use funds from a grant awarded under this section to connect eligible pregnant or postpartum women to telehealth services delivered via telehealth that are furnished by—</text> <paragraph id="HAFEFF90403B3440587BE073C940614E0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>primary and maternity care providers;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDD278FE05CBE49F28F6C208B3D223F48"><enum>(2)</enum><text>health care specialists;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEBF1662E4063408BAD20B308EEC316FD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>behavioral health providers; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H01EB749291B54CC58F0DDCF0FFAE4F4B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>other categories of health care providers identified by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H80018EED48A542278075B8F2AC444A8C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header> <paragraph id="H64238E0778F94DAABC0CCA9CF61782C4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>State reports</header><text>Each State that is awarded a grant to conduct a demonstration project under this section shall submit the following reports to the Secretary:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1DA73BD3A83B4736A92955416A9FE2C1"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>An initial report on the first 18 months during which the demonstration project is conducted, not later than the last day of the 19th month of the demonstration project, as described in subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0D435C6DAF384CBFBB40C0C055E7067B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Final report</header><text> Not later than 6 months after the date on which the State’s demonstration project ends, a final report that includes the following:</text> 
<clause id="H6FF872FDCB704B68BC491C6B0353CCAB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The number of eligible pregnant or postpartum women served under the demonstration project.</text></clause> <clause id="HA8834FA1DA4E42E2AD3026A0D804D45C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>The activities and services funded under the demonstration project, including the providers that received funds under the demonstration project. </text></clause> 
<clause id="H5BF938AE2A0F44A496D26B59ED72FA32"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Demographic information about the eligible pregnant or postpartum women served under the demonstration project, if available. </text></clause> <clause id="H5FE177A6AF6B48EE8785879416A89FD6"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>A description of the types of models or programs developed under the demonstration project.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HDABFE0623BFC43B095D3AE85CA378604"><enum>(v)</enum><text>How such models or programs impacted access to, and utilization of, telehealth services by eligible pregnant or postpartum women, including a description of how such models or programs addressed racial or ethnic disparities in access or utilization. </text></clause> <clause id="HB330EC070DBC46B895862F20E586F9AF"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Qualitative information on beneficiary experience.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HAFBF7B9E1C5E43B2BEDF9B602BEC0AC4"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Challenges faced and lessons learned by the State in integrating (or increasing the integration of) telehealth into the delivery system for furnishing medical assistance to eligible pregnant or postpartum women in the areas targeted under the demonstration project.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61F62C4D72844C2D822D26208129574F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reports to congress</header> <subparagraph id="HC38FE07781834CF7869C5532BE8390CE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit a report to Congress summarizing the information reported by States under paragraph (1)(A).</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H112609A5E772478786D2D7C5AADBBACD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit a report to Congress summarizing the information reported by States under paragraph (1)(B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HFFB736ACD77847FFBDFE4F4C55C63A54"><enum>10.</enum><header>CMS report on coverage of remote physiologic monitoring devices and impact on maternal and child health outcomes under Medicaid</header> <subsection id="HDBAD2C8C727C4836871DEE159403B0B8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report containing information on authorities and State practices for covering remote physiological monitoring devices, including limitations and barriers to such coverage and the impact on maternal health outcomes, and to the extent appropriate, recommendations on how to address such limitations or barriers related to coverage of remote physiologic devices under State Medicaid programs, including, but not limited to, pulse oximeters, blood pressure cuffs, scales, and blood glucose monitors, with the goal of improving maternal and child health outcomes for pregnant and postpartum women enrolled in State Medicaid programs. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7373D81E0235456A807D2DC58EE17F3E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>State resources</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the submission of the report required by subsection (a), the Secretary shall update resources for State Medicaid programs, such as State Medicaid telehealth toolkits, to be consistent with the recommendations provided in such report. </text></subsection></section> <section id="H0E3E66DA5B474CE3B0C70D3024959F62"><enum>11.</enum><header>Guidance on community-based maternal health programs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue guidance to State Medicaid programs to support the use of evidence-based community-based maternal health programs, including programs that offer group prenatal care, home visiting services, childbirth and parenting education, peer supports, stillbirth prevention activities, and substance use disorder and recovery supports, under such programs, and any other programs as determined by the Secretary. </text></section> 
<section id="H53A7B146DBE14300AFADA1C2318082DD"><enum>12.</enum><header>Developing guidance on maternal mortality and severe morbidity reduction for maternal care providers receiving payment under the Medicaid program</header> 
<subsection id="HA8DAE6CA9BBD46D885E5B19A7BC0170B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, not later than 36 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall, in consultation with the Advisory Committee on Reducing Maternal Deaths established under subsection (c) and the Task Force on Maternal Mental Health established under section 1113 of division FF of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>), publish on a public website of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services guidance for States on resources and strategies for hospitals, freestanding birth centers (as defined in section 1905(l)(3)(B) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396d">42 U.S.C. 1396d(l)(3)(B)</external-xref>)), and other maternal care providers as determined by the Secretary for reducing maternal mortality and severe morbidity in individuals who are eligible for and receiving medical assistance under Medicaid or CHIP.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H660AFD0C9BFC4E1B9D4380539A63AB76"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Updates</header><text>The Secretary shall, in consultation with the Advisory Committee on Reducing Maternal Deaths established under subsection (c) and the Task Force on Maternal Mental Health established under section 1113 of division FF of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/328">Public Law 117–328</external-xref>), update the guidance and resources described in subsection (a) at least once every 3 years.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA51C6E82CB364C35BAB28C9C20B17266"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultation with advisory committee</header> 
<paragraph id="H5C07C14F4D8546E092623A44C7CCED07"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall establish an advisory committee to be known as the <term>National Advisory Committee on Reducing Maternal Deaths</term> (referred to in this section as the <term>Advisory Committee</term>). </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF21618EEB1F34BEDBB2887C5DFB08FBB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall provide consensus advice and guidance to the Secretary on the development and compilation of the guidance described in subsection (a) (and any updates to such guidance).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6C70ED0073414E6CA4D90C349FA107BC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Membership</header> 
<subparagraph id="H47FA98C5BEC64246BBA3B77AD31E6FA5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with such other heads of agencies, as the Secretary deems appropriate and in accordance with this paragraph, shall appoint not more than 41 members to the Advisory Committee. In appointing such members, the Secretary shall ensure that— </text> <clause id="H63F0D884E81E4834A5085876B423B280"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the total number of members of the Advisory Committee is an odd number; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H7A0A59C786754E1390A7E84B8AD2BA20"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the total number of voting members who are not Federal officials does not exceed the total number of voting Federal members who are Federal officials.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7C8E00BA69E34ACB8A6F2661E20B4E72"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Required members</header> <clause id="HC5B2D2F26A7E40C98643D0F66A4C83AC"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Federal officials</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall include as voting members the following Federal officials, or their designees:</text> 
<subclause id="H1AB7CA37879A4B688506265D5A573C78"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Secretary.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H1CD46A07FB954C62BD58396BB768DEF2"><enum>(II)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H2B40BDD308004FED8D46047424CBE320"><enum>(III)</enum><text>The Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HBD2BB31901464873B1E52AED0DFD5754"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>The Associate Administrator of the Maternal and Child Health Bureau of the Health Resources and Services Administration.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HE8B40C045A23468B94193A6569622B2E"><enum>(V)</enum><text>The Director of the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H8B95B0D00C6249FF9D871307E9119128"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>The National Coordinator for Health Information Technology.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H8ED00D46E4214B5488716CF89290FE54"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>The Director of the National Institutes of Health.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HDCA7F28B8170478F9BF0838D3188F49F"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H4FB2440FE36F4BD9A31B57C7D9D87D81"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>The Director of the Indian Health Service.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H856AD694884640D7B8FF0AAF404A7EB6"><enum>(X)</enum><text>The Deputy Assistant Secretary for Minority Health.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HCE6F406A39214B00988860919C273615"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>The Administrator of the Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration.</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0B5D53DFCDA54531B48DAF25B14F2DBF"><enum>(XII)</enum><text>The Deputy Assistant Secretary for Women's Health.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HED5DCB595EDA42BAA57A8C361E8C6D97"><enum>(XIII)</enum><text>Such other Federal officials or their designees as the Secretary determines appropriate.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H54B42999FC79469A8F9B91A38F12394B"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Non-Federal officials</header> <subclause id="H52FDF13C98CF48A18660C91EFFF0B1A8"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall include the following as voting members:</text> 
<item id="HB948684FBEAD4BDF8321B73A6749209D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a professional organization representing hospitals and health systems.</text></item> <item id="H4BD9E05785A842AF807E20A11A265F1D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a medical professional organization representing primary care providers.</text></item> 
<item id="H81EA8A0509F84DDE8B326507286F2D97"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a medical professional organization representing general obstetrician-gynecologists.</text></item> <item id="H45C5B60CC87B4F579D04B11F8C9243EC"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a medical professional organization representing certified nurse-midwives.</text></item> 
<item id="HBF822D59E1BE4E8682F30C81701C2F2C"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a medical professional organization representing other maternal fetal medicine providers.</text></item> <item id="HBBE96EC7D1C6457A9BEA76B195FC72D5"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a medical professional organization representing anesthesiologists.</text></item> 
<item id="HA35620FA76DB4FAE8B603F0CA6F1978A"><enum>(gg)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a medical professional organization representing emergency medicine physicians and urgent care providers.</text></item> <item id="H0CFFB88DBD994DF794642240DDDA786B"><enum>(hh)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a medical professional organization representing nurses.</text></item> 
<item id="HBBC7D72DC13B4C1CB339117653C949FC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a professional organization representing community health workers. </text></item> <item id="H35F6DE97E03C4CDC97F1A9283FE2FD10"><enum>(jj)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a professional organization representing doulas.</text></item> 
<item id="H00F026DC3C3F4ECAAB27D2467F28119D"><enum>(kk)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a professional organization representing perinatal psychiatrists. </text></item> <item id="H22D4F7A4577C428E8923C4915C37C649"><enum>(ll)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from State-affiliated programs or existing collaboratives with demonstrated expertise or success in improving maternal health. </text></item> 
<item id="HCC29D1017069464C81B32CE333C6483F"><enum>(mm)</enum><text>At least 1 director of a State Medicaid agency that has had demonstrated success in improving maternal health.</text></item> <item id="H2DA8D45F1A0F41C29A8DB3F7349AC93C"><enum>(nn)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from an accrediting organization for maternal health quality and safety standards.</text></item> 
<item id="H0F6BA5C6E9C644EDA46A5E10BC2AE6F3"><enum>(oo)</enum><text>At least 1 representative from a maternal patient advocacy organization with lived experience of severe maternal morbidity.</text></item> <item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4EDAEFE0C9B34F05A29164312D58DE74"><enum>(pp)</enum><text>At least 1 medical professional who is an expert in the treatment of pregnant women with substance use disorder.</text></item></subclause> 
<subclause id="H7F3860F8FF5647148113296EC8A110B1"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>Each individual selected to be a member under this clause shall—</text> <item id="HCE118D74CEB245629F961C217A07272B"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>have expertise in maternal health; </text></item> 
<item id="H18D63F5A9CED4D4DBBE0979BF0B2C391"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>not be a Federal official; and</text></item> <item id="H32F63F9BA8A747DB9832260F7E7ED804"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>have experience working with populations that are at higher risk for maternal mortality or severe morbidity, such as populations that experience racial, ethnic, and geographic health disparities, pregnant and postpartum women experiencing a mental health disorder, or pregnant or postpartum women with other comorbidities such as substance use disorders, hypertension, thyroid disorders, and sickle cell disease. </text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H776C9F15D1B44695A05181D9F2712CB8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Additional members</header> 
<clause id="H942E389E8A89435BB62E96CD83646B98"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to the members required to be appointed under subparagraph (B), the Secretary may appoint as non-voting members to the Advisory Committee such other individuals with relevant expertise or experience as the Secretary shall determine appropriate, which may include, but is not limited to, individuals described in clause (ii). </text></clause> <clause id="H940FFC52A3D644909A61E358DA4FB315"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Suggested additional members</header><text>The individuals described in this clause are the following:</text> 
<subclause id="H18AA9B35C9F2476C9AE36389C3645129"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Representatives from State maternal mortality review committees and perinatal quality collaboratives.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HE44DB15462164BB19694409FC2D8B156"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Medical providers who care for women and infants during pregnancy and the postpartum period, such as family practice physicians, cardiologists, pulmonology critical care specialists, endocrinologists, pediatricians, and neonatologists.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HF32F88682E784C0CAF9573778CEEE638"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Representatives from State and local public health departments, including State Medicaid Agencies. </text></subclause> <subclause id="H14EFDF274805467EA41135926EC62F44"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>Subject matter experts in conducting outreach to women who are African American or belong to another minority group.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H3E960DBC7B594879BA6BE8C3A6F7D2D2"><enum>(V)</enum><text>Directors of State agencies responsible for administering a State's maternal and child health services program under title V of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/701">42 U.S.C. 701 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subclause> <subclause id="H3DC7141327CC4DA48760037531BCA534"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>Experts in medical education or physician training.</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HF420A6FA0972458DA6BFFA7F9CB1BE63"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>Representatives from Medicaid managed care organizations.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA53403A76C134F04A4F525628F5E6006"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Applicability of FACA</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">Chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall apply to the committee established under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEC18A5154FF84B209F9AE626A665B985"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The guidance described in subsection (a) shall include, with respect to hospitals, freestanding birth centers, and other maternal care providers, the following:</text> <paragraph id="H15EB0598FA4C4D7DA213D2B3A258695B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Best practices regarding evidence-based screening and clinician education initiatives relating to screening and treatment protocols for individuals who are at risk of experiencing complications related to pregnancy, with an emphasis on individuals with preconditions directly linked to pregnancy complications and maternal mortality and severe morbidity, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6ECA90998B8B43EFA3B27221A4533D58"><enum>(A)</enum><text>methods to identify individuals who are at risk of maternal mortality or severe morbidity, including risk stratification;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEDE55809F1B6449190F227E81B30AFDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>evidence-based risk factors associated with maternal mortality or severe morbidity and racial, ethnic, and geographic health disparities; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3E39BEFF19BF49BA8A8843F03E370284"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evidence-based strategies to reduce risk factors associated with maternal mortality or severe morbidity through services which may be covered under Medicaid or CHIP, including, but not limited to, activities by community health workers (as such term is defined in section 2113 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397mm">42 U.S.C. 1397mm</external-xref>)) that are funded by a grant awarded under such section; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD685318A0C87438885FF4CEF63932DD7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>resources available to such individuals, such as nutrition assistance and education, home visitation, mental health and substance use disorder services, smoking cessation programs, prenatal care, and other evidence-based maternal mortality or severe morbidity reduction programs; </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF6631522799E480C8FED7B7BF99592E6"><enum>(E)</enum><text>examples of educational materials used by providers of obstetrics services; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3AB3C1032C054C7C8F4305353F0B18AD"><enum>(F)</enum><text>methods for improving community centralized care, including providing telehealth services or home visits to increase and facilitate access to and engagement in prenatal and postpartum care and collaboration with home health agencies, community health centers, local public health departments, or clinics;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H50640701018E41B8BB9211F11D197721"><enum>(G)</enum><text>guidance on medical record diagnosis codes linked to maternal mortality and severe morbidity, including, if applicable, codes related to social risk factors, and methods for educating clinicians on the proper use of such codes; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H53B1C0A48F6C487B8A8746882EC7D05E"><enum>(H)</enum><text>risk appropriate transfer protocols during pregnancy, childbirth, and the postpartum period; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE6CEE3A78FEB4AAC85A5514FB6BD6C08"><enum>(I)</enum><text>any other information related to prevention and treatment of at-risk individuals determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H629BC405A82248CDAF77EDE486622C7B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Guidance on monitoring programs for individuals who have been identified as at risk of complications related to pregnancy.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB8E1F40614F84E12AC299704FAB04635"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Best practices for such hospitals, freestanding birth centers, and providers to make pregnant women aware of the complications related to pregnancy.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCA3B7BC36859411D8CAB526C35F9A5FC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A fact sheet for providing pregnant women who are receiving care on an outpatient basis with a notice during the prenatal stage of pregnancy that—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCF42839BD15D4A18AF85F21852351C70"><enum>(A)</enum><text>explains the risks associated with pregnancy, birth, and the postpartum period (including the risks of hemorrhage, preterm birth, sepsis, eclampsia, obstructed labor), chronic conditions (including high blood pressure, diabetes, heart disease, depression, and obesity) correlated with adverse pregnancy outcomes, risks associated with advanced maternal age, and the importance of adhering to a personalized plan of care;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8260EC8835414E40BE86BFAAD68E98C6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>highlights multimodal and evidence-based prevention and treatment techniques;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBA6A4524402A414A8D5566BA9B068778"><enum>(C)</enum><text>highlights evidence-based programs and activities to reduce the incidence of stillbirth (including tracking and awareness of fetal movements, improvement of birth timing for pregnancies with risk factors, initiatives that encourage safe sleeping positions during pregnancy, screening and surveillance for fetal growth restriction, efforts to achieve smoking cessation during pregnancy, community-based programs that provide home visits or other types of support, and any other research or evidence-based programming to prevent stillbirths); </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HBEC9A27C545D49CD8E9999B93ED1AD7E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provides for a method (through signature or otherwise) for such an individual, or a person acting on such individual’s behalf, to acknowledge receipt of such fact sheet;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H068DA007134F4759A59FD768A33F0106"><enum>(E)</enum><text>is worded in an easily understandable manner and made available in multiple languages and accessible formats determined appropriate by the Secretary; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H43D868FAFC1B43DF89EA398F5C733439"><enum>(F)</enum><text>includes any other information determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3554A81303D2440FB43E38FEBAABC39D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A template for a voluntary clinician checklist that outlines the minimum responsibilities that clinicians, such as physicians, certified nurse-midwives, emergency room and urgent care providers, nurses and others, are expected to meet in order to promote quality and safety in the provision of obstetric services.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B74E80D680F4B8B95ADB6F9F5FF2349"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A template for a voluntary checklist that outlines the minimum responsibilities that hospital leadership responsible for direct patient care, such as the institution’s president, chief medical officer, chief nursing officer, or other hospital leadership that directly report to the president or chief executive officer of the institution, should meet to promote hospital-wide initiatives that improve quality and safety in the provision of obstetric services. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H19E332AF75724658B88D8693330EF9F5"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Information on multi-stakeholder quality improvement initiatives, such as the Alliance for Innovation on Maternal Health, State perinatal quality improvement initiatives, and other similar initiatives determined appropriate by the Secretary, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H7B1E1002D41149BE949EED09BF75587A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>information about such improvement initiatives and how to join;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H79A829AC70874B719F9939ECA23A2232"><enum>(B)</enum><text>information about public maternal data collection centers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA8CD2EBE6711476297D7F258E2CD9189"><enum>(C)</enum><text>information about quality metrics used and outcomes achieved by such improvement initiatives;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA1B0FE5CEAE84B9183C117287CFB7269"><enum>(D)</enum><text>information about data sharing techniques used by such improvement initiatives;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H85CF9D0B73E94EB395B9A0D4449540E4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>information about data sources used by such improvement initiatives to identify maternal mortality and severe morbidity risks;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HB664DDEDA7D543B28914BAD38C97EDFC"><enum>(F)</enum><text>information about interventions used by such improvement initiatives to mitigate risks of maternal mortality and severe morbidity; </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA99E2C758B2D48C1B3B2A523643BE354"><enum>(G)</enum><text>information about data collection techniques on race, ethnicity, geography, age, income, and other demographic information used by such improvement initiatives; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBCC434FE392349E0B580655F790F5479"><enum>(H)</enum><text>any other information determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H1184DC4D9FB5469DA64D3905C3BB5D75"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Inclusion of best practices</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of the publication of the guidance required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall update such guidance to include best practices identified by the Secretary for such hospitals, freestanding birth centers, and providers to track maternal mortality and severe morbidity trends by clinicians at such hospitals, freestanding birth centers, and providers including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H58EF9B3174E34DCFA8DDCF29264E3931"><enum>(1)</enum><text>ways to establish scoring systems, which may include quality triggers and safety and quality metrics to score case and patient outcome metrics, for such clinicians;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H354875F57DDB40798C4525F9C15CC55A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>methods to identify, educate, and improve such clinicians who may have higher rates of maternal mortality or severe morbidity compared to their regional or State peers (taking into account differences in patient risk for adverse outcomes, which may include social risk factors);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4AC539C763014F838BD8B8DE0D217BC9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>methods for using such data and tracking to enhance research efforts focused on maternal health, while also improving patient outcomes, clinician education and training, and coordination of care; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1F0F90089A594593942CB22E179435C4"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other information determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4EFDBD309F9940AABBC47EA3041413DD"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Cultural and linguistic appropriateness</header><text>To the extent practicable, the Secretary should develop the guidance, best practices, fact sheets, templates, and other materials that are required under this section in a trauma-informed, culturally and linguistically appropriate manner. </text></subsection></section> <section id="H273F0BA0577C4E389B234644B4F45C3D"><enum>13.</enum><header>Program related to reducing cesarean births and increasing rates of vaginal birth after cesarean</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 317K(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247b-12">42 U.S.C. 247b–12(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6C8A1AFAEEF948F48D4608DA3E2C81B9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (1)—</text> <subparagraph id="H59B6165F764C4C2D9C0F3099EA89A1E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>and to develop or support</quote> and inserting <quote>to develop or support</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1C36EE4A4DE84477AAD53B7A01E9FFBE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, and to establish a grant program, or extend the Alliance for Innovation on Maternal Health, for the establishment of perinatal quality collaboratives to reduce cesarean section rates and increase vaginal birth after cesarean rates</quote> before the period at the end; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD2A34B96152F4BB98A8E3321078548B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (2), by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H7085733786EA41F8BB4B0F5CE91E399D" display-inline="no-display-inline" style="OLC"> 
<subparagraph id="HDF9BB220749D4034B93B99A12415C0BE"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Secretary may establish a competitive grant program, or extend existing programs, including the Alliance for Innovation on Maternal Health, for the establishment or support of perinatal quality collaboratives, with a focus on maternity care health professional target areas and other areas with limited birthing resources, to reduce cesarean birth rates and increase vaginal birth after cesarean rates, including through—</text> <clause id="H178CAE219F7C44568802C5629A41FDEC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>coordination with hospitals, clinical teams, obstetricians and gynecologists, birthing centers and community-based maternal health organizations, public health agencies, midwives, doulas, patients and families, and other relevant entities;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H19015C31740342D48FA2F62B2005E449"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>providing support and training to hospital and clinical teams for quality improvement, as appropriate;</text></clause> <clause id="HE173C5C39CE9458EBF40EE9A3D4D65D7"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>employing strategies that provide opportunities for health care professionals and clinical teams to collaborate across health care settings and disciplines, including midwifery care, doula support, the integration of primary care and mental health, and blended case payment rates;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA2CCCA4A64EC4046ABF45F4F48572796"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>using data, disaggregated by race and ethnicity, to provide timely feedback across hospital and clinical teams, document baseline cesarean and vaginal birth rates, and measure progress; and </text></clause> <clause id="HEAA7678A5198476B88C8C29C7C680A90" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(v)</enum><text>promotion of existing evidence on the best practices for the safe reduction of primary cesarean births.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7DF6537351774DC1AE3D8B2B465D5885"><enum>14.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Collection of information related to social determinants of the health of Medicaid and CHIP beneficiaries</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4CB357BE8B9F40FBAB369DB966FA555B"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Implementation assessment report to Congress</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1E027F6BA844A2FB9F820C8CF1CBB1C"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit a report to Congress that includes a description of whether and how information related to the social determinants of health for individuals eligible for medical assistance under Medicaid or child health assistance or pregnancy-related assistance under CHIP may be captured under the data systems for such programs as in effect on the date such report is submitted, including—</text> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H51ACCB5AAFE9475D84599DB4D80809E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of whether and how ICD-10 codes (or successor codes) may be used to identify social determinants of health in programs such as Medicaid and CHIP, and whether other claims file or demographic information may be employed; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HFC10564F9AF74BF0A41FB584EF438CDC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of whether existing data systems under Medicaid and CHIP could be employed to capture such information, whether program or system changes would be required, how privacy and confidentiality as required under applicable law and regulations would be maintained, and the resources and timeframes at the Federal and State levels that would be needed to make such changes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H4431F40816A04F999DA15995FE7A4D34"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidance for States</header><text>The Secretary shall issue detailed guidance for States concurrent with the submission of the report to Congress under paragraph (1). Such guidance shall address—</text> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H82FA6BC824964562B1E6148C2FAD7F92"><enum>(A)</enum><text>whether and how information related to the social determinants of health for individuals eligible for medical assistance under Medicaid or child health assistance or pregnancy-related assistance under CHIP could be captured employing existing systems under such programs; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H443DB2CCF9CF44DCB42C161847DF2CEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>implementation considerations for capturing such information, including whether program or system changes would be required, whether additional steps would be needed to maintain privacy and confidentiality as required under relevant laws and regulations, and the resources and timeframes at that would be needed to make such changes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" id="H025196EA5F17432687C633B0B305444B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Stakeholder input</header><text>The Secretary shall develop the report required under paragraph (1) and the guidance required under paragraph (2) with the input of relevant stakeholders, such as State Medicaid directors, Medicaid managed care organizations, and other relevant Federal agencies such as the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the Health Resources Services Administration, and the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. </text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HC0A5BEA9948E4347B44571BC9410551D"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Action plan report</header> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H5569B5C573EC4FE6B85126A1BCA7DBC0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the Secretary determines in the report required under paragraph (1) that information related to the social determinants of health for individuals eligible for medical assistance under Medicaid or child health assistance or pregnancy-related assistance under CHIP cannot be captured under the data systems for such programs as in effect on the date such report is submitted, then, not later than 6 months after such date, the Secretary shall submit a second report to Congress that contains an action plan for implementing the program or data systems changes needed in order for such information to be collected while maintaining privacy and confidentiality as required under relevant laws and regulations. The action plan should be prepared so as to be implemented by the Federal Government and States not later than 2 years after the date on which the report required under this paragraph is submitted to Congress. </text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H6C0DEE9A82544602A519887CF864FE1B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Revised guidance for states</header><text>The Secretary shall revise and reissue the guidance for States required under paragraph (2) to take into account the action plan included in the report submitted to Congress under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H761773024194482EB7EB072AF4169AEC"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H66694EE573A54F989F08AC3E9AFC5999"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Federal costs</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary, $40,000,000 for purposes of preparing the reports required under this subsection and implementing the collection of information related to the social determinants of health for individuals eligible for medical assistance under Medicaid or child health assistance or pregnancy-related assistance under CHIP.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="HF7F4F82B615F413FA96727FAE0AC4F73"><enum>(B)</enum><header>State costs</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary, $50,000,000 for purposes of making payments to States in accordance with a methodology established by the Secretary for State expenditures attributable to planning for and implementing the collection of such information in accordance with subsection (d) of section 1946 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396w-5">42 U.S.C. 1396w–5</external-xref>) (as added by subsection (b)). </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02F4E215BC1143DEB1D4B4EA2A3AF29D"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Application to States</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1946 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396w-5">42 U.S.C. 1396w–5</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBA6E95ED4E1847AA8817E477D83507E0"> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7B115B2953A64F4AA7EE382900A21825"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Collection of information related to social determinants of health</header> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H07852E9C759244EABE5C65E0C71882DC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Development of collection methods</header> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8940EC1A438438F89FC3276F67C774D"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to paragraph (5), the Secretary, in consultation with the States, shall develop a method for collecting standardized and aggregated State-level information related to social determinants that may factor into the health of beneficiaries under this title and beneficiaries under title XXI which the States, notwithstanding section 1902(a)(7) and as a condition for meeting the requirements of section 1902(a)(6) and section 2107(b)(1), shall use to annually report such information:</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H785407D66E364BD6AD8CD9020A9DD7E7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>A model uniform reporting field through the transformed Medicaid Statistical Information System (T-MSIS) (or a successor system) or another appropriate reporting platform, as approved by the Secretary.</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7BEBD4CBBAB948EF8EA4DD04BBC173A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>A model uniform questionnaire or survey (which may be included as part of an existing survey, questionnaire, or form administered by the Secretary), for purposes of the State or the Secretary collecting such information by administering regularly but not less than annually a questionnaire or survey of beneficiaries under this title and beneficiaries under title XXI.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H26D053E597964826965CF55FE1FC2021"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>A model uniform form to be adapted for inclusion in the Medicaid and CHIP Scorecard developed by the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services, for purposes of the Secretary collecting such information.</text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H46C45EBE693A4A0FBB6D518441A6BF6F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>An alternative method identified by the Secretary for collecting such information.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H99F8623E8B294BFBA6454DE718EDA8E1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>In carrying out the requirements of subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall—</text> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBC3F8C2C8BA248DCA678E81040E4DACB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for purposes of the method described in clause (i) of such subparagraph, determine the appropriate providers and frequency with which such providers shall complete the reporting field identified and report the information to the State; </text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3A14A66942446C7A9BE33BD1B890039"><enum>(ii)</enum><text> for purposes of the method described in clause (ii) of such subparagraph, identify the means and frequency (which shall be no less frequent than once per year) with which a questionnaire or survey of beneficiaries is to be conducted; </text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4523797F7FD64748B8EDD65FEC5E4CB9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>with respect to any method described in such subparagraph, issue guidance for ensuring compliance with applicable laws regarding beneficiary informed consent, privacy, and anonymity with respect to the information collected under such method; </text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H64796EC713904A7FAEE3C4F5A4088819"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>with respect to the collection of information relating to beneficiaries who are children, issue guidance on the collection of such information from a parent, legal guardian, or any other person who is legally authorized to share such information on behalf of the child when the direct collection of such information from children may not otherwise be feasible or appropriate; and </text></clause> 
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3AA8443237A0414387D0BA23226E5613"><enum>(v)</enum><text>regularly evaluate the method under such subparagraph and the information reported using such method, and, as needed, make updates to the method and the information reported. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC4C690814CB744CD97136E02AE615739"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Social determinants of health</header><text>The information collected in accordance with the method made available under paragraph (1) shall, to the extent practicable, include standardized definitions for identifying social determinants of health needs identified in the ICD–10 diagnostic codes Z55 through Z65 (or any such successor diagnostic codes), as defined by the Healthy People 2020 and related initiatives of the Office of Disease Prevention and Health Promotion of the Department of Health and Human Services, or any other standardized set of definitions for social determinants of health identified by the Secretary. Such definitions shall incorporate measures for quantifying the relative severity of any such social determinant of health need identified in an individual.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H703FEB0D06DA4CCD8564189011B6018D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Federal privacy requirements</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to supersede any Federal privacy or confidentiality requirement, including the regulations promulgated under section 264(c) of the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 and section 543 of the Public Health Service Act and any regulations promulgated thereunder.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD3F49A6020474A8DAF7979F37DA60576"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Application to territories</header> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD0622543A3D14DD381E25995358F00C4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To the extent that the Secretary determines that it is not practicable for a State specified in subparagraph (B) to report information in accordance with the method made available under paragraph (1), this subsection shall not apply with respect to such State.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9E2173FC6ED54301BCEFAC10B8FE3F89"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Territories specified</header><text>The States specified in this subparagraph are Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Guam, American Samoa, and the Northern Mariana Islands.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H748871A856364028905042D1326866E5"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Application</header> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H75A5C53A3D044B6B8836486DB33E5040"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to subparagraph (B), the requirement for a State to collect information in accordance with the method made available under paragraph (1) shall not apply to the State before the date that is 4 years after the date of enactment of this subsection.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H456AECCF81BE41709802C7AB99D72659"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Alternative date</header><text>If an action plan is submitted to Congress under section 14(a)(4) of the <short-title>Healthy Moms and Babies Act</short-title>, in lieu of the date described in subparagraph (A), the requirement for a State to collect information in accordance with the method made available under paragraph (1) shall not apply to the State before the date specified in such action plan.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0ACAD3EA6B0A40C9ACAA7D8F38B0ABA8"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Appropriation</header><text>There is appropriated to the Secretary for fiscal year 2024 and each fiscal year thereafter $1,000,000 to carry out the provisions of this section and subsection (b)(2)(B).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H65EDCC6B20B34B5297D70EC34E9B4027"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report on data analyses</header><text>Section 1946(b)(2) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396w-5">42 U.S.C. 1396w–5(b)(2)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph commented="no" id="H9E41DDC1875243B785A5507B98F6C75A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Not later than</quote> and inserting the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H125E04F074AC447AA0A5A95EE6F458B1"> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H8A466DEE64E74CACA966B5D0FFC0A4F2"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Initial reports</header><text>Not later than</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H8313E441F11D4DB588AB27787119E2E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB93D690C2E0D4775BA842589739FF110"> 
<subparagraph commented="no" id="H43624106776E47C3AA099D85724D91E1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reports on collection of information related to social determinants of health</header> 
<clause commented="no" id="H335B26F3A805428FBC10B9D7B42C22A3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 5 years after the date on which the requirement to collect information under subsection (d) is first applicable to States, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report that includes aggregate findings and trends across respective beneficiary populations for improving the identification of social determinants of health for beneficiaries under this title and beneficiaries under title XXI based on analyses of the data collected under subsection (d).</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3053A5198FD34D4C9EB54BCBC680A15A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Interim report</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of enactment of this subparagraph, the Secretary shall submit to Congress an interim report on progress in developing, implementing, and utilizing the method selected by the Secretary under subsection (d)(1) along with any available, preliminary information that has been collected using such method.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" id="H9D9C44B1088A4E4E8BC6D2744ADF4475"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Conforming amendment</header><text>Section 2107(e)(1) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1397gg">42 U.S.C. 1397gg(e)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H89CAA758058B48AABEF9A950AB190F9B"> <subparagraph commented="no" id="H28E2A672F1FE4A8BB6AB39839C4E4411"><enum>(U)</enum><text>Section 1946 (relating to addressing health care disparities).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF4FF1566989A4632ADCFA9CFED10D0D0"><enum>15.</enum><header>Report on payment methodologies for transferring pregnant women between facilities before, during, and after childbirth</header> 
<subsection id="HBCC5D800ECB94474BB82CE3EA2B44D53"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the availability of appropriations, not later than 36 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the payment methodologies under Medicaid for the antepartum, intrapartum, and postpartum transfer of pregnant women from one health care facility to another, including any potential disincentives or regulatory barriers to such transfers.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H452FADA2C3A24B058EDB1CE77E4D0EEE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing the report required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall consult with the advisory committee established under section 12(c). </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H8959B565FA5E42FDA9987BA0C56EF3E6"><enum>16.</enum><header>Medicaid guidance on State options to address social determinants of health for pregnant and postpartum women</header> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02C7C2478868449DBBFC09C5027E853B"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue guidance to States and conduct one or more learning collaboratives to promote cross-state learning regarding options States may employ to address social determinants of health, as defined by the Healthy People 2030 and related initiatives of the Office of Disease Prevention and Health Promotion of the Department of Health and Human Services, including for pregnant and postpartum women. </text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD8974669382442F599C88A419E118412"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The guidance required under subsection (a) shall, at a minimum, describe the authorities that States may leverage to support addressing the social determinants of health for pregnant and postpartum women and outline best practices for such efforts. </text></subsection> 
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7F1F33BF1A148E39C823FB41710D5E9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Learning collaborative requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The learning collaboratives required under subsection (a) shall, at a minimum, include opportunities for States and other stakeholders to share innovative practices and approaches as they are being considered and developed, share solutions related to challenges that multiple urban and rural States face, and promote the uptake of approved, effective interventions addressing social needs and determinants covered by the Medicaid program.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H6A594FCD36414F409B702BD470FCD7BB"><enum>17.</enum><header>Payment error rate measurement (PERM) audit and improvement requirements</header> <subsection id="H00EF447BBE3D4141B701C876ADD1EAEF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Biennial PERM audit requirement</header><text>Beginning with fiscal year 2025, the Administrator shall conduct payment error rate measurement (<term>PERM</term>) audits of each State Medicaid program on a biennial basis.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE8AA3C9C41FF474C8E352A1AF0F3A607"><enum>(b)</enum><header>PERM error rate reduction plan requirement</header><text>Beginning with fiscal year 2025, any State with an overall PERM error rate exceeding 15 percent in a PERM audit conducted with respect to the State in the previous fiscal year shall publish a plan, in coordination with, and subject to the approval of, the Administrator, for how the State will reduce its PERM error rate below 15 percent in the current fiscal year. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H1DF11EC14C8B4343B17B710B4C7A62A8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Notification; identification of sources of improper payments</header> <paragraph id="H3BAC900781234A8E846C9515505BF077"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall notify the contractor conducting PERM audits of the Administrator's intent to modify contracts to require PERM audits not less than once every other year in each State.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE2532EBB820E4A7A9B2671B0107E1473"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Identification of sources of improper payments</header><text>The Administrator shall direct the contractor conducting PERM audits of State Medicaid programs to identify areas known to be sources of improper payments under such programs to identify program areas or components known to be sources of high risk for improper payments under such programs. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HC8A9E437D9B44725B8C78164333766F0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>State Medicaid director letter</header><text>Not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall issue a State Medicaid Director letter regarding State requirements under Federal law and regulations regarding avoiding and responding to improper payments under State Medicaid programs.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7DC91B2DD856410AA7AE9F0A0F68E2BF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>State improper payment mitigation plans</header> 
<paragraph id="H7EB83860CB504CFBA4788D2DE4B21B40"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than January 1, 2024, each State Medicaid program shall submit to the Administrator a plan, which shall include specific actions and timeframes for taking such actions and achieving specified results, for mitigating improper payments under such program.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H517EC325C28843838098CCFC1E9FFC55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication of State plans</header><text>The Administrator shall make State plans submitted under paragraph (1) available to the public.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0F9A812BA98E459AA6FE2C31B97AD628"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H4F5D943390204281A2BE0642610D3B1F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text>The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H02D356335C634A5996813F550DD38E64"><enum>(2)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> has the meaning given such term for purposes of title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05F6FB2C91F846C793736E3D65636FEA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>State Medicaid program</header><text>The term <term>State Medicaid program</term> means a State plan under title XIX of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396">42 U.S.C. 1396 et seq.</external-xref>), and includes any waiver of such a plan. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


