<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H142EFC4361574028A9F1CB157BF93D4B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1578 IH: Success in the Middle Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1578</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230314">March 14, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide grants to States to ensure that all students in the middle grades are taught an academically rigorous curriculum with effective supports so that students complete the middle grades prepared for success in secondary school and postsecondary endeavors, to improve State and local educational agency policies and programs relating to the academic achievement of students in the middle grades, to develop and implement effective middle grades models for struggling students, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H329608E7729E4B5A8A351305BB398F3E" style="OLC">
<section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H50D7B7BCCF084226A5FF93BDF5EC695C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Success in the Middle Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H66012125066F4DB3A45C3CF12EE9BF33"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HD05BE02AB05D470F8609F7320F08B64E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Research shows that Federal funding for students in middle school and high school, particularly grades 6 through 12, is significantly lower than funding for elementary and postsecondary students.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB49116116BD64C2AA78988197D359C29"><enum>(2)</enum><text>International comparisons indicate that students in the United States do not start out behind students of other nations in mathematics and science, but that they fall behind by the end of the middle grades.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDC56C2E527334FC1AB429583FF0FF4AE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In reading, 31 percent of students in grade 8 read at or above the proficient level on the 2022 National Assessment of Educational Progress. Average reading scores were lower at grade 8 for most racial/ethnic groups compared to 2019.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1FD3D39509464A55B534C99FA559A143" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In mathematics, 27 percent of students in grade 8 displayed skills at or above the proficient level on the 2022 National Assessment of Educational Progress. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H398F8CCB5919400595ADE5564B9DC283"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Evidence demonstrates unfinished learning for the Nation’s students, including students from the middle grades, resulting from the COVID–19 pandemic. Black and Hispanic students, in particular, were less likely to have access to the prerequisites of learning—devices, internet access, and live contact with teachers. Left unaddressed, these opportunity gaps could translate into wider achievement gaps.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2812CE04AC8A4BEB93F286FEC82BAD02"><enum>(6)</enum><text>By grade 6, a student who attends school less than 80 percent of the time, receives unsatisfactory marks for mild but sustained misbehavior, or who fails English or mathematics, has only a 10 to 20 percent chance of graduating on time. Without effective interventions and proper supports, these students are at risk of subsequent failure in secondary school, or of dropping out.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HC7789AA999AC4F62979A65F26E6FAE11"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to Gallup, student engagement is strong at the end of elementary school, with nearly <fraction>3/4</fraction> of 5th graders (74%) reporting high levels of engagement. But similar surveys have shown a gradual and steady decline in engagement for older students, with approximately <fraction>1/2</fraction> of students in middle school reporting high levels of engagement.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC819F17406464F8992321F41E7BFD378"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Student transitions from elementary school to the middle grades and to secondary school are often complicated by poor curriculum alignment, inadequate counseling services, and unsatisfactory sharing of student performance and academic achievement data between grades.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB82029EFC5E442BA8CD8876EEC95181F"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Middle grades improvement strategies should be tailored based on a variety of performance indicators and data, so that—</text> <subparagraph id="H314B5B3BEB32480F85AAAECC48738B44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>educators can create and implement successful school improvement strategies to address the needs of the middle grades; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE5DD150CBA0D41F9B3757F7A01C1D685"><enum>(B)</enum><text>teachers can provide effective instruction and adequate assistance to meet the needs of at-risk students.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD2BA914E2BE8499D9C2BB55523162E0A"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Middle grade teachers face unique challenges due to the increased individual subject matter focus of the curriculum combined with the physical, intellectual, and emotional changes faced by early adolescents transitioning from elementary school to high school.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H73832737F9F84CF1AD3F60A67FAAAF4B"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Combining measures of academic achievement and motivation, social engagement, and self-regulation—the behavioral domains essential for success across the school and work continuum—provides a more holistic picture of students, including their likelihood of enrolling in an institution of higher education following high school graduation. This information, available in middle school, allows for early identification of and intervention with students who may be less likely to complete secondary school and attend an institution of higher education.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDB33204E4D714C99A2B3E59E01FEA530"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Appropriate academic accommodations, age-appropriate discipline, access to assistive technology, and evidence-based interventions must be used with students with disabilities, particularly in the middle grades, as—</text>
<subparagraph id="HDEC3544145A1495DA84154CB4FDFE98F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the dropout rate for learning disabled students is more than twice the dropout rate of all students;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0D04EA173A4E4D3EBED03A53C3AF690F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>nearly half of young adults with learning disabilities have been involved in the justice system; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7BC709F7942745578C7A3B6E3B9B68BA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>students with disabilities have a graduation rate nearly 20 percentage points lower than the graduation rate for general education students.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBC7D7B3952CC4F0EA2DE5CCA9C5437D6"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Local educational agencies and State educational agencies often do not have the capacity to provide support for school improvement strategies. Successful models do exist for turning around low-performing middle grades, and Federal support should be provided to increase the capacity to apply promising practices based on evidence from successful schools.</text></paragraph></section>
<section id="H5ECC144B132149C4AE7315FED4A4A6E9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HD22007621A6C4F549FA8B27CEA8442CB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>ESEA definitions</header><text>The terms <term>educational service agency</term>, <term>elementary school</term>, <quote>English learner</quote>, <quote>evidence-based</quote>, <term>local educational agency</term>, <term>outlying area</term>, <term>high school</term>, <term>secondary school</term>, and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given the terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4F630D88EA21438A9253347F85255F86"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chronic absenteeism</header><text>The term <term>chronic absenteeism</term> means the percentage of individual students missing 10 percent, or more, of the days of school in a school year.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF562F8F146F84C38A0207496EE43DF06"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means a partnership that includes—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA8F47838851A492D8A3C7420AB6B96E7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not less than 1 eligible local educational agency; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFFFD1D5AB019441B8CA19181E52D1C61"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">One of the following:</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1FD96C19A11642A695BE7032D81A512C"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An institution of higher education.</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2C8BDD6D0931464E853166016C93AEA1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An educational service agency.</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6657FCAB0F8044249A2B93BD3D09CE02"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A nonprofit organization with demonstrated expertise in high-quality middle grades intervention.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H05ED54D7DAEA48E3B91AA94D780E01F0"><enum>(4)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligible local educational agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible local educational agency</term> means a local educational agency that serves not less than 1 eligible school.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDD78C2F566004429970615CD6915CDD4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Eligible school</header><text>The term <term>eligible school</term> means an elementary school or secondary school that contains not less than 2 successive grades of grades 5 through 8 and for which—</text> <subparagraph id="HBB1025E220DA4EBB944E056574B3DC41"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a high proportion of the middle grades students attending such school will attend a secondary school with a graduation rate of 67 percent or less;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HBB8DEC6B259F45CDB9D1D1B040B90DAD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>more than 25 percent of the students who finish grade 6 at such school, or the earliest middle grade level at the school, exhibit 1 or more of the key risk factors and early risk identification signs, including—</text> <clause id="HDC9243B0AD89489C9322A45190B81764"><enum>(i)</enum><text>student attendance below 90 percent;</text></clause>
<clause id="H07E60FDBF52D46B895DB8517FF70CCFC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a failing grade in a mathematics or reading or language arts course;</text></clause> <clause id="HEDA037C2F8584F37B783B0149BC0C93E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>2 failing grades in any courses; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HBA05301307AB49BA9B65EBA84600F67E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>out-of-school suspension or other evidence of at-risk behavior; or</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H32096BE4382D402CAC18808565FD4785"><enum>(C)</enum><text>more than 50 percent of the middle grades students attending such school do not perform at a proficient level on State student academic assessments required under section 1111(b)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(b)(2)</external-xref>) in mathematics or reading or language arts.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H20B739AE66B04E0FADD1B1D11FF6EC1D"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H0CFD4B74ADB74401875ECF1A2960FAC4"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Middle grades</header><text>The term <term>middle grades</term> means any of grades 5 through 8.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2D9380B694984A988A258996FD7F5665"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB12BF042886C4ADEBEE5EE8A693D8EE7"><enum>(9)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each of the 50 States, the District of Columbia, and the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE5D4F125D4794DCDA1C77696030BB861"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Student with a disability</header><text>The term <term>student with a disability</term> means a student who is a child with a disability, as defined in section 602 of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1401">20 U.S.C. 1401</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> <title commented="no" id="HA8CAFE99468341EBB3087B0FCE6F3618" level-type="subsequent"><enum>I</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Middle grades improvement</header> <section id="HEFCDD5D03F7142AD9CA8D7E09539AEF0"><enum>101.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this title are to—</text>
<paragraph id="HFB5701FB317F47DFA1CD946A73524A87"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop middle grade students' social, emotional, and academic competencies and deep content knowledge to ensure they are equipped to think critically, solve problems, communicate effectively, collaborate with others, and be self-directed so that they can enter high school on-track and graduate from high school on time and ready for postsecondary and career pathways;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3EDBC7AE3E5B4F86953CC8F5FC70F7F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide student and teacher supports for middle grades education, including funding and curricula, that align with the student and teacher supports provided for elementary school and secondary school grades within and across local educational agencies;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE077115E22A3416FA144E316C2451A91"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide resources to State educational agencies and local educational agencies to collaboratively develop and implement middle grade improvement plans in order to deliver evidence-based support and technical assistance to schools serving middle grade students;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B426D03072E4336B2B0C6D137C9E773"><enum>(4)</enum><text>provide resources for schools serving middle grade students to develop positive learning communities where educators and students feel engaged, and share high expectations of student success, as exhibited by mutual respect, fair discipline approaches, and rigorous academic curriculum; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H775F218F13394DBC967BF94C94AB5C4F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>increase the capacity of States and local educational agencies to develop effective, sustainable, and replicable school improvement programs and models and evidence-based or, when available, scientifically valid student interventions for implementation by schools serving students in the middle grades.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H76765EA478EA4DD5BE1C230CA20FB7F8"><enum>102.</enum><header>Formula grants to State educational agencies for middle grades improvement</header> <subsection id="HC1274FCDF0EA44D88DD1EBDE2FA47CCA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>From amounts appropriated under section 107, the Secretary shall make grants under this title for a fiscal year to each State educational agency for which the Secretary has approved an application in an amount equal to the allotment determined for such agency under subsection (c) for such fiscal year.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HD60201359E1840B8BB550D3DEB1CDA53"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reservations</header><text>From the total amount made available to carry out this title for a fiscal year, the Secretary—</text> <paragraph id="HB4689598CC3B4BBF9A0F98D06E641C95"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall reserve not more than 1 percent for the Secretary of the Interior (on behalf of the Bureau of Indian Education) and the outlying areas for activities carried out in accordance with this section;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H78001F2D1D284AFCBBAD423A17D9EF71"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall reserve 1 percent to evaluate the effectiveness of this title in achieving the purposes of this title and ensuring that results are peer-reviewed and widely disseminated, which may include hiring an outside evaluator; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H77B8439C70EC463DA48AC70D24406DEC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall reserve 2 percent for technical assistance and dissemination of best practices in middle grades education to States and local educational agencies.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H33BE2B12CE53421EA31FA7FCD8F308F2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Amount of State allotments</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7960964AC395405DA04DB446C1105CEA"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (2), of the total amount made available to carry out this title for a fiscal year and not reserved under subsection (b), the Secretary shall allot such amount among the States in proportion to the number of children, aged 5 to 17, who reside within the State and are from families with incomes below the poverty level for the most recent fiscal year for which satisfactory data are available, compared to the number of such individuals who reside in all such States for that fiscal year, determined in accordance with section 1124(c)(1)(A) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6333">20 U.S.C. 6333(c)(1)(A)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23EF610CFFA0455E92BB9BAC038F35AE"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Minimum allotments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No State educational agency shall receive an allotment under this subsection for a fiscal year that is less than <fraction>1/2</fraction> of 1 percent of the amount made available to carry out this title for such fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6FE2954256C9453BBB1C53E2E1F3CF75"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Special rule</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For any fiscal year for which the funds appropriated to carry out this title are less than $500,000,000, the Secretary is authorized to award grants to State educational agencies, on a competitive basis, rather than as allotments described in this section, to enable such agencies to award subgrants under section 104 on a competitive basis.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAC542A5B9C314EF0B31B4EBE3BA5C4A5"><enum>(e)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reallotment</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3680E094379B41BA8CDA65C055494AAB"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Failure to apply; application not approved</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any State educational agency does not apply for an allotment under this title for a fiscal year, or if the application from the State educational agency is not approved, the Secretary shall reallot the amount of the State's allotment to the remaining States in accordance with this section.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB308B434033D4167B943D5931490B3DE"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Unused funds</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may reallot any amount of an allotment to a State if the Secretary determines that the State will be unable to use such amount within 2 years of such allotment. Such reallotments shall be made on the same basis as allotments are made under subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23CED13820874AA1B50B71C617511319"><enum>(f)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In order to receive an allotment under this title, a State educational agency shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the Secretary may reasonably require, including a State middle grades improvement plan described in section 103(a)(4).</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFF3129D0ECA548C288E3CEEA22BA5E7F"><enum>(g)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Peer review and selection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary—</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA021ECF63C294AA48C4FBAC0543DF74B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall establish a peer-review process to assist in the review and approval of proposed State applications;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H261AD9B2734846989149B32FC3240BFA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall appoint individuals to participate in the peer-review process who are educators and experts in identifying, evaluating, and implementing effective education programs and practices (including in the areas of teaching and learning, educational standards and assessments, school improvement, school climate, rates of suspension and expulsion, and academic and behavioral supports for middle grades students, and in addressing the needs of students with disabilities and English learners in the middle grades), which individuals may include recognized exemplary middle grades teachers and middle grades principals who have been recognized at the State or national level for exemplary work or contributions to the field;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H17A57A1FC15143FAA4B59996882BDF5A"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall ensure that State educational agencies are given the opportunity to receive timely feedback, and to interact with peer-review panels, in person or via electronic communication, on issues that need clarification during the peer-review process;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H60990ED75E16426EA9EF0E3850D38A6D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall approve an application submitted under this title not later than 120 days after the date of submission of the application unless the Secretary determines that the application does not meet the requirements of this title;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA741A47685F1475CA346EE8FF1FB015C"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may not decline to approve an application from a State educational agency before—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2DFE997EBA554D11942E6F3C401796A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">offering the State educational agency an opportunity to revise the application;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5A09C311CE2E40309EB3A60FF99DA16C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing the State educational agency with technical assistance in order to submit a successful application; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA7B2FDF50C714EA29CC4345E67955F1B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing an opportunity for a hearing to the State educational agency; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H57A1971326F74824A32AE131BF5A7F5E"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall direct the Inspector General of the Department of Education to—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC5A29D25C8C54462894918ADE54D521A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">review final determinations reached by the Secretary to approve or deny State applications;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5B4D7379316044C882FF317920FF4F3B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">analyze the consistency of the process used by peer-review panels in reviewing and recommending to the Secretary approval or denial of such State applications; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6F2C07DD743418784B68FB0D726CB70"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">report the findings of this review and analysis to Congress.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H203650241BC54CFE8EE2319468F8DFDE"><enum>103.</enum><header>State plan; authorized activities</header> <subsection id="HB0C307B7361940BA8955EB714BB2266D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mandatory Activities</header> <paragraph id="H77F8FA5647774F1C95F1AA0FC0E78EFF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this title shall use the grant funds—</text>
<subparagraph id="H8CDB7C09F28A4104B8ED468B22AA5F9B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to prepare and implement the needs analysis and middle grades improvement plan, as described in paragraphs (3) and (4), of such agency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H38AE95CC290B4A698B70C213439FC8F3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to make subgrants to eligible local educational agencies or eligible entities under section 104; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEAD3DECBB2E34D1490B2C17C5179C5F0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>to assist eligible local educational agencies and eligible entities, when determined necessary by the State educational agency or at the request of an eligible local educational agency or eligible entity, in designing a comprehensive schoolwide improvement plan and carrying out the activities under section 104.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF50DEE67A5E948289076FDCDCEB942C0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Funds for subgrants</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this title shall use not less than 90 percent of the grant funds to make subgrants to eligible local educational agencies or eligible entities under section 104.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA3B3B05D6E39430DB360DA16164DF4FD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Middle grades need assessment</header>
<subparagraph id="H85D1348F716C459199D7582D7B5806C0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Comprehensive assessment</header>
<clause id="HCC68C0A66F7D463A825AF2C4C83E2F4C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this title shall conduct a comprehensive needs assessment that analyzes how to strengthen the programs, practices, and policies of the State to target support for students in the middle grades to improve positive student outcomes that prepare students for high school, postsecondary, and career success.</text></clause> <clause id="HC49524D7FCB548C8AE35A7FA41A400CD"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Contracting ability</header><text>A State educational agency receiving a grant under this title may enter into a contract, or similar formal agreement, to work with entities such as national and regional comprehensive centers (as described in section 203 of the Educational Technical Assistance Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9602">20 U.S.C. 9602</external-xref>)), institutions of higher education, or nonprofit organizations with demonstrated expertise in high-quality middle grades reform to conduct a comprehensive needs assessment.</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD4042D5A059A48088FCAFDA9ADF4E42C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Preparation of assessment</header><text>In preparing the assessment under subparagraph (A), the State educational agency shall examine policies and practices of the State, and of local educational agencies within the State, affecting, with respect to middle grades—</text> <clause id="HCBC951B764214A969A9E96A5156A0384"><enum>(i)</enum><text>curriculum alignment, assessment, and instruction;</text></clause>
<clause id="H6DFBE1496AE544CB88FEBE9744CEA8B0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the State system of annual meaningful differentiation, as described under section 1111(c)(4)(C) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(c)(4)(C)</external-xref>);</text></clause> <clause id="H8B23B97E777C45979105EBD8F1D578CE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>teacher and school leader preparation, quality, experience, and equitable distribution;</text></clause>
<clause id="HAB504DA74DCB44CD80C537B76248EEB0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>interventions both in-school and out-of-school that support student learning;</text></clause> <clause id="HC843F29EABEE41EF99B0255243D451E5"><enum>(v)</enum><text>student engagement activities;</text></clause>
<clause id="H5134B5732A8E4C70ADC1410943049250"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>disproportionate use of exclusionary disciplinary practices, including in-school and out-of-school suspensions;</text></clause> <clause id="H3CB5103CFEB04627B9328920791ADD2F"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>family and community engagement in education;</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" id="H6FE0E91CF77748DFB8B5D76A9210FE8C"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">equitable distribution of resources; and</text></clause> <clause id="H983E2206E9AE4B3A8D68F6E6E325550F"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">student and academic support services, such as effective school library programs and school counseling on the transition to secondary school and planning for entry into postsecondary education and the workforce.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDAC9AFB91412435B8E7E15A0943888E6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Middle grades improvement plan</header>
<subparagraph id="H71802D61B4C6453BB8E72FB94193B2F9"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this title shall develop a middle grades improvement plan that—</text> <clause id="H52A73AE4DFEE434E8D94772F1E93C0CC"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be a statewide plan to improve student academic achievement in the middle grades, based on the needs assessment described in paragraph (3); and</text></clause>
<clause id="H63CA7152E5694A439CF4254B0390B06C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>describes what students are required to know and do to successfully—</text> <subclause id="H641970D5A43B4FD791812DA953F1B4C4"><enum>(I)</enum><text>complete the middle grades;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H7BEDC68FE258415D872F4F615DDE4796"><enum>(II)</enum><text>develop the competencies of—</text> <item id="HB071EFE254DB47D6883F3DFA86ABB0E4"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the ability to acquire and use deep content knowledge to solve problems;</text></item>
<item id="H82170D4B65024494A387290615CEFD38"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>critical thinking;</text></item> <item id="H286283CA5C9E437597013079269F4A31"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>effective communication;</text></item>
<item id="HA95AAB3EBFCF45728B419C0472676629"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>self-direction; and</text></item> <item id="H9C149F8AF5884625B6D898ECDC8D30A4"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>the ability to collaborate; and</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="H4B84CBCE08D84EAF9026E6313889AC9C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>make a successful transition to academically rigorous secondary school coursework that prepares students to graduate from secondary school ready for higher education and a career.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H238473AD3A6F4D47BA86B7C6C8166D50"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Plan components</header><text>A middle grades improvement plan described in subparagraph (A) shall also describe how the State educational agency will do each of the following:</text>
<clause id="H16B2ED7BEFA84D6499FAD098B7B97FAA"><enum>(i)</enum>
<subclause commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H94A251FAED8F4095BDEE92C4BF4D1C98"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Align State standards and assessments for middle grades education with State standards and assessments for secondary schools and prepare students to take challenging secondary school courses and successfully engage in postsecondary education.</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB2D139AADAC348929C9EBAE912106CBC" indent="up1"><enum>(II)</enum><text>Coordinate, where applicable, with the activities carried out through grants under section 6201(c)(1) of the America COMPETES Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9871">20 U.S.C. 9871(c)(1)</external-xref>) for alignment of P–16 education, as defined in section 6201(b) of such Act.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H4F29EBAD2E9A4AAD99E928675DC94980" indent="up1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>Support the transition from elementary school to the middle grades through programs that promote successful social, emotional, and cognitive development.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HB8A4429F56A54CBF8DA82147D5D3C7DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Provide professional development to school leaders, teachers, and other school personnel in—</text>
<subclause id="HE7FCD446EA864D16B3823F1BF4E16E73"><enum>(I)</enum><text>addressing the needs of diverse learners, including students with disabilities and English learners;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H59D481783C86426BA222DEEB1914D72A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>using challenging and relevant research-based best practices and curricula;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H2C46DE882BAB434EB1EEB1A8981C1CB3"><enum>(III)</enum><text>using data to inform instruction; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HDB31653166F44FB7B2B2556F86AB68A8"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>increasing student engagement and social and emotional learning competencies.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HD7C8761926454262A4AC7849C7DC903B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Identify and disseminate information on effective schools and instructional strategies for middle grades students based on high-quality research.</text></clause> <clause id="H90282703BC414653A830A0F96F3F47B9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Identify and provide support for students most at risk of not graduating from secondary school, including English learners, students with disabilities, and low-income students.</text></clause>
<clause id="H522B34C2668145AD8A046EF400A578FD"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Provide technical assistance to eligible entities to develop and implement their early warning indicator and intervention systems, as described in section 104(d)(2)(D).</text></clause> <clause id="H803F02D07710455199674A0BC91E081D"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Define a set of school performance indicators that shall be used, in addition to the indicators used to identify schools for comprehensive support and improvement under section 1111(c)(4)(D)(i) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(c)(4)(D)(i)</external-xref>), to evaluate school performance and guide the school improvement process, such as—</text>
<subclause id="HB3C7B7A7F3C943F0BCE3C44319503FEC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>student attendance and chronic absenteeism;</text></subclause> <subclause id="HC4B2DCDB804F44F09197C99D146D7376"><enum>(II)</enum><text>earned on-time promotion rates from grade to grade;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HC9B36EF53DFF42FB83B5A37654A3EA93"><enum>(III)</enum><text>percentage of students failing a mathematics, reading or language arts, or science course, or failing 2 or more of any courses;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H1EDE7226D8FC426CB1E6BF5AB2C8D440"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>teacher preparation, experience, effectiveness, and attendance measures;</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H9032990520B54223BF436056ACC8D5C0"><enum>(V)</enum><text>in-school and out-of-school suspension or other measurable evidence of at-risk behavior, including any disparities in rates among subgroups of students, as defined in section 1111(c)(2)) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(c)(2)</external-xref>);</text></subclause> <subclause id="H0DFD5750DD4840CC82E7BC9B65D10861"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>data collected by the Civil Rights Data Collection survey conducted by the Office of Civil Rights of the Department of Education; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H8CD0DECCB9404BAD8B8AB3AA8286130A"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>additional indicators proposed by the State educational agency and approved by the Secretary, based upon any peer-review evaluation of indicators conducted under section 102(b)(2).</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H267CBB224363410C964F92EB9F279AE8"><enum>(vii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensure that such plan is coordinated with State activities to turn around schools identified for comprehensive support and improvement under section 1111(c)(4)(D)(i) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(c)(4)(D)(i)</external-xref>), including State activities to improve secondary schools and elementary schools.</text></clause>
<clause id="H52991CE123E14C7AB588DEA2859923E2"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>Ensure that such plan includes specific provisions to improve family and community engagement in education in the middle grades.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2FB0600BC22A47E0A549119AE3F9C44E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Permissible activities</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this title may use the grant funds to—</text>
<paragraph id="H39531F9289D440529654FC4A1A92EB0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>develop and encourage collaborations among researchers at institutions of higher education, State educational agencies, educational service agencies, local educational agencies, and nonprofit organizations with demonstrated expertise in high-quality middle grade interventions, to expand the use of effective practices in the middle grades and to improve middle grade education;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="H3933536733DE4AC48C7260A5A6490124"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and facilitate collaboration among institutions of higher education, nonprofit organizations, and other stakeholders involved in teacher and school leader preparation to improve the quality and delivery of preservice and in-service middle grades teacher and school leader preparation to ensure new and existing middle grade educators are prepared for the specific and unique needs of middle grades students;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HA660E193BE7A49359F63504ED563D902"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support local educational agencies in implementing effective middle grades practices, models, and programs that—</text> <subparagraph id="H94A4456220CB431AB3B38961CBE09515"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">are evidence-based; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H8232C1B151E2444598B4DF582AA2C993"><enum>(B)</enum><text>lead to improved student academic achievement;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBB659D72FCC4AA18ED0A2F9FFF35B17"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support collaborative communities of middle grades teachers, administrators, school librarians, and researchers in creating and sustaining informational databases to disseminate results from rigorous research on effective practices and programs for middle grades education; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H873361791FAD4899A0F768EE65E9E129"><enum>(5)</enum><text>increase middle grades student and academic support services, such as—</text> <subparagraph id="H4CF1C2BF62E2479EA48F90F68AC5AAB7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>effective school library programs; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HC4A0D31D02724043B53F0C544E3C7855"><enum>(B)</enum><text>school counseling on the transition to secondary school, such as summer bridge programs and student mentors, and planning for entry into postsecondary education and the workforce.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HE7EF843999C04574A3FEF781F2BF07EE"><enum>104.</enum><header>Competitive subgrants to improve low-performing middle grades</header> <subsection id="H2224DBE465B14F3BB99C4B7E5925C891"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State educational agency that receives a grant under this title shall make competitive subgrants to eligible local educational agencies and eligible entities to enable the eligible local educational agencies and eligible entities to improve low-performing middle grades in schools served by the agencies or entities.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HDB0C1DE2D4B344178341F971C802E442"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Priorities</header><text>In making subgrants under subsection (a), a State educational agency shall give priority to eligible local educational agencies or eligible entities based on—</text> <paragraph id="H04CDF1E14AED4170BE47648278B52ED6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the respective populations of children described in section 102(c)(1) served by the eligible local educational agencies that are participating in the subgrant application process; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB2852994E7FD441CAA08889A8F26D11D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the respective populations of children served by the participating eligible local educational agencies who attend eligible schools.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H07EDA6FC47B14C9BB402583565821473"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible local educational agency or eligible entity that desires to receive a subgrant under subsection (a) shall submit an application to the State educational agency at such time, in such manner, and accompanied by such information as the State educational agency may reasonably require, including—</text>
<paragraph id="H40B9E57825594E23A223F632373AAAAE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a middle grade improvement plan described in subsection (d); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47A4D2FF68114C89858D22A2D20882BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of how activities described in such plan will be complementary to, and coordinated with, school improvement activities for elementary schools and secondary schools that serve the same students within the participating local educational agency.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3A75769D46F74A8A9207F6931E3D458D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Middle grades improvement plan</header><text>An eligible local educational agency or eligible entity that desires to receive a subgrant under subsection (a) shall develop a comprehensive middle grades improvement plan for the middle grades that shall—</text> <paragraph id="H7B7D45C69E1F4942BA17BB81E6FF16FF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>describe how activities described in such plan will be coordinated with activities specified in schoolwide program plans under section 1114 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6314">20 U.S.C. 6314</external-xref>);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H75C84F960AE54261A001A07D56287082"><enum>(2)</enum><text>describe how the eligible local educational agency or eligible entity will—</text> <subparagraph id="H8D021A28FFA145DB94DD6CF78EF92D5E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify eligible schools;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H69A384B3E8BC4AD793C911BE3EC4A862"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that funds go to eligible schools with the highest percent of low-income students first, based on the eligible schools’ populations of children described in section 102(c)(1);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF16B4FE34C2B4AAA8FD1DC871DE623EA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>use funds to close achievement gaps and improve the academic achievement of all students, including English learners and students with disabilities, in eligible schools;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HED54F36B0D054DEDA6C7ADA3D823E8AB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>implement an early warning indicator and intervention system to alert schools when students begin to exhibit outcomes or behaviors that indicate the student is at increased risk for low academic achievement or is unlikely to progress to secondary school graduation, and to create a system of evidence-based interventions to be used by schools to effectively intervene, by—</text> <clause id="H4E1D772F7EF44219B0638244D847B5DA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying and analyzing, such as through the use of longitudinal data of past cohorts of students, the academic and behavioral indicators in the middle grades that most reliably predict dropping out of secondary school, such as attendance, chronic absenteeism, behavior measures (including suspensions, officer referrals, or conduct marks), academic performance in core courses, and earned on-time promotion from grade-to-grade, and other relevant indicator of student academic performance as included in schoolwide program plans under section 1114 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6314">20 U.S.C. 6314</external-xref>);</text></clause>
<clause id="HD8F052A86DC340128FEBD077BE32A97F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>analyzing student progress and performance on the indicators identified under clause (i) to guide decision making;</text></clause> <clause id="H69234EBA8E9E403AB2ACBD3F2C2FC818"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>analyzing academic indicators to determine whether students are on track to graduate on time, and developing appropriate evidence-based intervention; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H25556578873D4ADDA78CC636CC5F46EC"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>identifying or developing a mechanism for regularly collecting and reporting—</text> <subclause id="HC22175A9A12148B28C3444902E144BCA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>student-level data on the indicators identified under clause (i);</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HDDA2354DD21C4663A8D8F4D63BCDA190"><enum>(II)</enum><text>student-level progress and performance, as described in clause (ii);</text></subclause> <subclause id="H219EA1B1E5554C32919EC5ED98DA4375"><enum>(III)</enum><text>student-level data on the indicators described in clause (iii); and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H00FE5D6E20624BDDB211CDCA0079011A"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>information about the impact of interventions on student outcomes and progress;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1897739CA1B34E16AD899EFD51791E86"><enum>(E)</enum><text>increase academic rigor and foster student engagement to ensure students are entering secondary school prepared for success in a rigorous college- and career-ready curriculum, including a description of how such readiness will be measured;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H619D8FA0310C4364895BD4419156DCC9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>implement a systemic transition plan for all students and encourage collaboration among elementary grades, middle grades, and secondary school grades to support the successful transition between grades;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H65EE277281B742D08795B7E6CA2DCAA7"><enum>(G)</enum><text>increase community and family engagement in education in the middle grades to support student success; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H87ABDCAD92E14057B442D8016CEC12E7"><enum>(H)</enum><text>provide evidence that the strategies, programs, supports, and instructional practices proposed under the middle grades improvement plan are new and have not been implemented before by the eligible local educational agency or eligible entity; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H90840BF57DBA4D62BC967EA80CD1058F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide evidence of an ongoing commitment to sustain the plan for a period of not less than 4 years.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC4471FEFE68F4936AA32CC158F84F71D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Review and selection of subgrants</header><text>In making subgrants under subsection (a), the State educational agency shall—</text> <paragraph id="HFEFA0E98839A4DEC80585C4616FFBDC7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish a peer-review process to assist in the review and approval of applications under subsection (c); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5C1BD964C3474AF8B981962D8286BFE7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>appoint individuals to participate in the peer-review process who are educators and experts in identifying, evaluating, and implementing effective education programs and practices, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HC711A885170A4BC89DAE5B3352806EC9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>experts—</text>
<clause id="HB8EE93E9C2444123A781DF14F77061C3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in areas of teaching and learning, educational standards and assessments, and school improvement;</text></clause> <clause id="H57C4478F0BD34B2E9C22102244846AB1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in addressing the needs of students with disabilities and English learners in the middle grades; and</text></clause>
<clause id="HAF4419A4EF144C939EDD071C8897326A"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in the academic and behavioral supports for middle grades students; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H587E975DFA1C412BB0370EF10ADDC947"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recognized exemplary middle grades teachers and principals who have been recognized at the State or national level for exemplary work or contributions to the field.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7213E32935C843CC890558567DA9E2A6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Revision of subgrants</header><text>If a State educational agency, using the peer-review process described in subsection (e), determines that an application for a grant under subsection (a) does not meet the requirements of this title, the State educational agency shall notify the eligible local educational agency or eligible entity of such determination and the reasons for such determination, and offer—</text> <paragraph id="HF7A59F8D8E2B4AB5ACF628F3FE8D1D00"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the eligible local educational agency or eligible entity an opportunity to revise and resubmit the application; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H68ACB71242F744A1B9E459D6730A4DC9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>technical assistance to the eligible local educational agency or eligible entity, by the State educational agency or a nonprofit organization with demonstrated expertise in high-quality middle grades interventions, to revise the application.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9656290129BA423AA8AD9CEB8CF80D02"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Mandatory uses of funds</header><text>An eligible local educational agency or eligible entity that receives a subgrant under subsection (a) shall carry out the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HB1430AD5C45644039E596563345039FE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Align the curricula for grades kindergarten through 12 for schools within the local educational agency to improve transitions from elementary grades to middle grades to secondary school grades.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5734C64418B24BCC95A7911E774C5A96"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In each eligible school served by the eligible local educational agency receiving or participating in the subgrant:</text>
<subparagraph id="H6D16FDAA1CEE41809440FE3E8CA76CDA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Align the curricula for all grade levels within eligible schools to improve grade to grade transitions.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0FD423053CC341DF81509864C2B56904"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Implement evidence-based instructional strategies, programs, and learning environments that meet the needs of all students and ensure that school leaders and teachers receive professional development on the use of these strategies.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HB9443A714DC1456BA28A35B1C2232C1C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Provide professional development for school leaders, teachers, specialized instructional support personnel, school librarians, and other school staff on the developmental stages of adolescents in the middle grades and how to deal with those stages appropriately in an educational setting.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H73C1FCF0446A4A87B8C064CF41E43489"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Implement organizational practices and school schedules that allow for effective leadership, collaborative staff participation, professional development, effective teacher instructional teaming, and parent and community involvement.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HEB5C34264A7B4DA0AFCE7B292BF45C1C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Create a more personalized and engaging learning environment for middle grades students by developing a personal academic plan for each student and assigning not less than 1 adult who has received the appropriate training to monitor, evaluate, and support the progress of each individual student attending the eligible school.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAF3765625698456E8D6E9D4EAE9BDCF1"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Provide all students, and the students’ families, with information about, and assistance with, the requirements for secondary school graduation, admission to an institution of higher education, and career success.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H9EF30C1160A74A0A81D375980F5B2910"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Utilize data from an early warning indicator and intervention system described in subsection (d)(2)(D) to identify struggling students and assist the students as the students transition from elementary school to middle grades to secondary school.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF50941002F2244D59C620564B9AF682B"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Implement academic supports, such as effective school library programs, and effective and coordinated additional assistance programs to ensure that students have a strong foundation in reading, writing, mathematics, science, and technology skills.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HF208ACE102B5453BA11F7DD5F8442A8A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>Develop and use effective, age- and level-appropriate, formative assessments to inform instruction.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1D2F57F91DAE4ACD825C2C4AB9740C6B"><enum>(J)</enum><text>Provide integrated student support services, such as access to student health services, mental health and trauma-informed care, and individualized school counseling, to address the comprehensive needs of students attending eligible schools.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2FC13980E7374743978CB34B0784D441"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Permissible uses of funds</header><text>An eligible local educational agency or eligible entity that receives a subgrant under subsection (a) may use the subgrant funds to carry out the following:</text> <paragraph id="H226CFE9BEE6740BC8A857F053AE62892"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Implement extended learning opportunities in core academic areas, including more instructional time in literacy, mathematics, science, technology, history, and civics in addition to opportunities for language instruction and understanding other cultures and the arts.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H7594A50206C542049FC5B7BAA1B1ADA5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Provide evidence-based professional development activities with specific benchmarks to enable teachers and other school staff to appropriately monitor academic and behavioral progress of, and modify curricula and implement accommodations and assistive technology services for, students with disabilities, consistent with the students’ individualized education programs under section 614(d) of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1414">20 U.S.C. 1414(d)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE349155813FE47C3A5E48BDB3E259919"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Employ and use instructional coaches, including literacy, mathematics, and English learner coaches.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2CB96E7A127844E0AE4AB1173D8453B7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Provide professional development for content-area teachers and school librarians on working effectively with English learners and students with disabilities, as well as professional development for English as a second language educators, bilingual educators, and special education personnel.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFC3E12F916744308B49B87B7347255ED"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Provide professional development in areas that support improving school climate and increasing student engagement such as culturally responsive pedagogy, restorative justice programs, social and emotional learning, response to intervention, and positive behavior intervention support.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9414DE33DD214522AF71A5CBE8D2035C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Encourage and facilitate the sharing of data among elementary grades, middle grades, secondary school grades, institutions of higher education, and other postsecondary educational institutions.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC3E6EC766B5240298E311CEB51B5C61C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Create collaborative study groups composed of principals or middle grades teachers, or both, among eligible schools within the eligible local educational agency receiving or participating in the subgrant, or between such eligible local educational agency and another local educational agency, with a focus on developing and sharing methods to increase student learning and academic achievement.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H191AA295965F40A5AB3789028B3FAA9F"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Incorporate as school quality and student success indicators into the State system of annual meaningful differentiation, as described under section 1111(c)(4)(C) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(c)(4)(C)</external-xref>), for middle grades schools that feed into secondary schools, rates of first-year secondary school attendance, retention, and achievement to the accountability system of each middle grades school that feeds into the secondary school.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HEEFAC71FB364464A816FB487B8CA68F1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Non-Recipient planning subgrants</header> <paragraph id="HFFC38FCF63EB4777818029DBF99DA74E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In addition to the subgrants described in subsection (a), a State educational agency may (without regard to the preceding provisions of this section) make planning subgrants, and provide technical assistance, to eligible local educational agencies and eligible entities that have not received a subgrant under subsection (a) to assist the local educational agencies and eligible entities in meeting the requirements of subsections (c) and (d).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H255CDF51304E4BF9B4CF2182E97FDDBF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Amount and duration</header><text>Each subgrant under this subsection shall be in an amount of not more than $100,000 and shall be for a period of not more than 1 year in duration.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H2767E4352F394B42A8704C6B57181803"><enum>105.</enum><header>Duration of grants; supplement not supplant</header> <subsection id="H23989087642546A8A47902CCB7D1133B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Duration of grants</header> <paragraph id="H073BF25AD38D473BBDC2291B55525DF1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), grants under this title and subgrants under section 104(a) may not exceed 3 years in duration.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2BC3060EC5BE47168672196C87BC7378"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Renewals</header>
<subparagraph id="H954B110369EA4972B48F87D88A5F72B6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Grants under this title and subgrants under section 104(a) may be renewed in 2-year increments.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD64A8DABF5414BDD9BC06488CC1EAD00"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Conditions</header><text>In order to be eligible to have a grant or subgrant renewed under this paragraph, the grant or subgrant recipient shall demonstrate, to the satisfaction of the granting entity, that—</text>
<clause id="H86A45FF6A7B14351A10E9E89E25FE2D6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the recipient has complied with the terms of the grant or subgrant, including by undertaking all required activities; and</text></clause> <clause id="H2BD5FE4610E54CEDB7056F2926D76CEB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>during the period of the grant or subgrant, there has been significant progress in—</text>
<subclause id="H3EA4CE1042874587BFB968B922DCE44F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>student academic achievement; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H6B10D84920C64AF2A8638FD7A96B75C9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>positively impacting other key risk factors such as attendance, chronic absenteeism, and on-time promotion.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H622B8252F1FB4D2ABAD0F731F2EE9DDF"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Federal funds To supplement, not supplant, non-Federal funds</header>
<paragraph id="H06D00B3FEE8B43C78E8C1C90358712A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A State educational agency, eligible local educational agency, or eligible entity shall use Federal funds received under this title only to supplement the funds that would, in the absence of such Federal funds, be made available from non-Federal sources for the education of students participating in programs assisted under this title, and not to supplant such funds.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H332D6E7351BF4857BA0737A2DFD60CFF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Special rule</header><text>Nothing in this title shall be construed to authorize an officer, employee, or contractor of the Federal Government to mandate, direct, limit, or control a State, local educational agency, or school’s specific instructional content, academic achievement standards and assessments, curriculum, or program of instruction.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="HE64A8D1E2EA542A29930177040CCE443"><enum>106.</enum><header>Evaluation and reporting</header>
<subsection id="H68E28BB30A4D4CCA9377B246C3CD2FBA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for the period of the grant, each State educational agency receiving a grant under this title shall—</text> <paragraph id="H7CE6C42ECF36429385ADD55A71B4C456"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conduct an evaluation of the State’s progress regarding the impact of the changes made to the policies and practices of the State in accordance with this title, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H5F23FFE8977B4A8DAA2A591D20B03709"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of the specific changes made, or in the process of being made, to policies and practices as a result of the grant;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3C0A965F0FFF4872ADAAC8937654853F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a discussion of any barriers hindering the identified changes in policies and practices, and implementation strategies to overcome such barriers;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD572B528770D4573A8E93A6CBD15B352"><enum>(C)</enum><text>evidence of the impact of changes to policies and practices on behavior and actions at the local educational agency and school level; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1930427DE1C846B3A8727431746C13F0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>evidence of the impact of the changes to State and local policies and practices on improving measurable learning gains by middle grades students;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9968E49021024255A2105D26A0445784"><enum>(2)</enum><text>use the results of the evaluation conducted under paragraph (1) to adjust the policies and practices of the State as necessary to achieve the purposes of this title; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H32A75277D95244CA9AFBEE629AD6FF17"><enum>(3)</enum><text>submit the results of the evaluation to the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HC8E65ED9D91F4BB180993EFC86D99C7C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Availability</header><text>The Secretary shall make the results of each State educational agency’s evaluation under subsection (a) available to other States and local educational agencies.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H4EB773DE22CE4932BD578BD62CAEA501"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Local educational agency reporting</header><text>On an annual basis, each eligible local educational agency and eligible entity receiving a subgrant under section 104(a) shall report to the State educational agency and to the public on—</text>
<paragraph id="H1912D3B1EE0D47FFABEE2683BA4CBB0C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the performance on the school performance indicators (as described in section 103(a)(4)(B)(vi)) for each eligible school served by the eligible local educational agency or eligible entity, in the aggregate and disaggregated by each of the subgroups of students, as defined in section 1111(c)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(c)(2)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H20800BE669084E6598A615B18C366CAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the use of funds by the eligible local educational agency or eligible entity and each such school.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HE9A7095784584B87AC323C5CA8AAC0DD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>State educational agency reporting</header><text>On an annual basis, each State educational agency receiving grant funds under this title shall report to the Secretary and to the public on—</text> <paragraph id="H5C3C24BB67F842D799BFED4B2293B34C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the performance of eligible schools in the State, based on the school performance indicators described in section 103(a)(4)(B)(vi), in the aggregate and disaggregated by each of the subgroups of students, as defined in section 1111(c)(2) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(c)(2)</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1A3009B9CAC94B42AF394FA0793D7D53"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the use of such funds by each eligible school, eligible entity, and eligible local educational agency in the State receiving such funds.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3437AF9B898C4AA6838E4318B4C4D67B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Every 2 years, the Secretary shall report to the public and to Congress—</text>
<paragraph id="H734D95026EE342F8AE1C0A9C64FB4170"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a summary of the State educational agency reports under subsection (d); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9E68F5AD195D4774B3ACDD90C063E8E9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the use of funds by each State educational agency under this title.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H8AC004D8DBC746F5A0D87FEFFFBBF1BD"><enum>107.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this title—</text> <paragraph id="HA02BCC888C1D4D55BBB65AD7DDD20411"><enum>(1)</enum><text>$500,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H17685C604646438DA6F977B2FBE144D3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>$525,000,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCA2A970C88DD485BAE1F1481B4476C73"><enum>(3)</enum><text>$550,000,000 for fiscal year 2026;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HBD1C2BBEE277494A8D559D57D788D93F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>$600,000,000 for fiscal year 2027; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC99E5E8CB6394D86B5E41DE175EE778F"><enum>(5)</enum><text>$650,000,000 for fiscal year 2028.</text></paragraph></section></title>
<title id="H2BB46A5713C341D28249F67C03696132"><enum>II</enum><header>Research recommendations</header>
<section id="H0B232D402C82463E9342B45774855F5E"><enum>201.</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purpose of this title is to facilitate the generation, dissemination, and application of research needed to identify and implement effective practices that lead to continual student learning and high academic achievement in the middle grades.</text></section> <section id="H5AEFF775976A41BEA29EAD4294444765"><enum>202.</enum><header>Study on promising practices</header> <subsection id="H362C39F039B14AC797EAA7EC7DFA6E31"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study on promising practices</header> <paragraph id="H30943E864DBC46DEBC77636689420AA7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall study and identify promising practices for the improvement of middle grades education. The Secretary may contract with an independent third party, such as a nonprofit organization, nongovernmental organization, or institution of higher education to satisfy this requirement.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H77DAA4F56B8D4A0AA8328E77145DD7E7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Content of study</header><text>The study described in paragraph (1) shall identify promising practices currently being implemented for the improvement of middle grades education. The study shall be conducted in an open and transparent way that provides interim information to the public about criteria being used to identify—</text> <subparagraph id="HD1FB1D3DCDC147EFACECC6B8FCE361C4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such promising practices;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H158885AB7B8E46349C71FC3DCE65D835"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the practices that are being considered; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF5DAE6C66A704C5980C8704FD89B9FEC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the kind of evidence needed to document effectiveness.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H62EA974962164ED0ADC7BC8AE284894B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The contract entered into pursuant to this subsection shall require that the independent third party submit to the Secretary, the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives a final report regarding the study conducted under this section not later than 1 year after the date of the commencement of the contract.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" id="HA57C4A68C6284AB5B91BB8D644C38C34"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make public and post on the website of the Department of Education the findings of the study conducted under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0831BE8F3D284768AEC5B7D83B8F3DE8"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Synthesis study of effective teaching and learning in middle grades</header>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H14828D9313E34A5D9602DEF036100B38"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall enter into a contract with the National Academies to review existing research on middle grades education, and on factors that might lead to increased effectiveness and enhanced innovation in middle grades education.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2DC9703FA27A4229A02CCD547F070490"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Content of study</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The study described in paragraph (1) shall review research on education programs, practices, and policies and research on the cognitive, social, and emotional development of children in the middle grades age range, in order to provide an enriched understanding of the factors that might lead to the development of innovative and effective middle grades programs, practices, and policies. The study shall focus on—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H02481AE2E5634A5EBAEFA9AFBDA56DCA"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the areas of curriculum, instruction, and assessment (including additional supports for students who are below grade level in reading, writing, mathematics, and science, and the identification of students with disabilities) to better prepare all students for subsequent success in secondary school, postsecondary education, and cognitively challenging employment;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFC824F86C9E149B0B116153C55FB916A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the quality of (including experience, certification, and demonstrated effectiveness), and supports for, the teacher workforce;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDF667B55B94E4082B2E611FED1DD3A2E"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">aspects of student behavioral and social development, and of social interactions within schools that affect the learning of academic content;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE727A12D76494F9A81CE2656D0634B03"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the ways in which schools and local educational agencies are organized and operated that may be linked to student outcomes;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4A607A7A24DF48E6B462119674A9BD58"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how development and use of early warning indicator and intervention systems can reduce risk factors for dropping out of school and low academic achievement; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB1513ADB4A114C459AD3CBC8D8836369"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identification of areas where further research and evaluation may be needed on these topics to further the development of effective middle grades practices.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H653CFFDE47B54113AFE5B91A510669D7"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The contract entered into pursuant to this subsection shall require that the National Academies submit to the Secretary, the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate, and the Committee on Education and the Workforce of the House of Representatives a final report regarding the study conducted under this subsection not later than 2 years after the date of commencement of the contract.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1B5E7518FE3C477E8C3EC46F9E426612"><enum>(4)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Publication</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make public and post on the website of the Department of Education the findings of the study conducted under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5994F524CAC644DEA1455111466E3504"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall carry out each of the following:</text> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD6D7BA7A0C3949D281C3E813E92DD3E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Create a national clearinghouse, in coordination with entities such as the What Works Clearinghouse of the Institute of Education Sciences, for research in best practices in the middle grades and in the approaches that successfully take those best practices to scale in schools and local educational agencies.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H41183D0087AB42E78B672398357BF4A1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Create a national middle grades database accessible to educational researchers, practitioners, and policymakers that identifies factors at the school, classroom, and system level that facilitate or impede student academic achievement in the middle grades.</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE1E1276C99304B68B13520FEE5EB8AA5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Require the Institute of Education Sciences to develop a strand of field-initiated and scientifically valid research designed to enhance performance of schools serving middle grades students, and of middle grades students who are most at risk of educational failure, which may be coordinated with the regional educational laboratories established under section 174 of the Education Sciences Reform Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9564">20 U.S.C. 9564</external-xref>), institutions of higher education, agencies recognized for their research work that has been published in peer-reviewed journals, and organizations that have such regional educational laboratories. Such research shall target specific issues such as—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2AC6B4FA381E443ABB68AC493ACA267F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">effective practices for instruction and assessment in mathematics, science, technology, and literacy;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEE576A58BDF744A6837C82EBA86B239E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">effective practices for developing in students the competencies of—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1BD5C056EF594212AEC83E4BBDD7A8DE"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the ability to acquire and use deep content knowledge to solve problems;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5674493FD110425E8D86D4D5F5EA573B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">critical thinking;</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFA7AF6A4F60B479E86D12B06FDD5A86C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">effective communication;</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H210EC3713BF94F4580DCE195395F2B36"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">self-direction; and</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC93FB42DA765490BBF805CA5D9557816"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the ability to collaborate;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8DAC18D6A5FA4F27B50A928686C6516C"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">academic interventions for adolescent English learners;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB0070B3AE7A04714AAE2957ECCCCB11B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">school improvement programs and strategies for closing the academic achievement gap between the different groups described in section 1111(b)(2)(B)(xi) of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/6311">20 U.S.C. 6311(b)(2)(B)(xi)</external-xref>), and for decreasing rates of suspension and expulsion;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H832C0E2E9F66488B9F8CAB3A3ACD1E9B"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evidence-based or, when available, scientifically valid professional development planning targeted to improve pedagogy and student academic achievement and student engagement; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5BB5C16E5FC245BFBDA66C67A5AFF4BC"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effects of decreased class size or increased instructional and support staff.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H129407A38E5D474CA846D9C6617B3826"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Strengthen the work of the existing national research and development centers under section 133(c) of the Education Sciences Reform Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/9533">20 U.S.C. 9533(c)</external-xref>), as of the date of enactment of this Act, by adding an educational research and development center dedicated to addressing—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H23AE7C7D390F47E8A5EA4093D126463B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">curricular, instructional, and assessment issues pertinent to the middle grades (such as mathematics, science, technological fluency, and the needs of English learners and students with disabilities);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2DEE392ECB414BB08C9E5A8520432707"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">comprehensive reforms for low-performing middle grades; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HCD1C12DDF4F74244A862438D6678EA49"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">other topics pertinent to improving the academic achievement of middle grades students.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H739C108F32A8495DB0D9C982736AB729"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provide grants to nonprofit organizations, for-profit organizations, institutions of higher education, and others to partner with State educational agencies and local educational agencies to develop, adapt, or replicate effective models for turning around low-performing schools serving middle grades students.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
<section id="H189B07CE23494E31B42EB951A0EFF8AA"><enum>203.</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations; reservations</header>
<subsection id="H4560FF6BFB0849E1B89EF30CD5E20073"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this title $50,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, which amount shall remain available for obligation through fiscal year 2028.</text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H96DDE7F2830B4E17B4D53E2DF40525F5"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reservations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">From the total amount made available to carry out this title, the Secretary shall reserve—</text>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7AF159B0D9B2418B8320A1B435DA6322"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">2.5 percent for the studies described in subsections (a) and (b) of section 202;</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8A5328FD650042158563513C0AAFD45C"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">5 percent for the clearinghouse described in section 202(c)(1);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H227DD513C41B4D509B636D74AFA70969"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">5 percent for the database described in section 202(c)(2);</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H227B564EDA584895B0AEEB8346D1D52B"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">42.5 percent for the activities described in section 202(c)(3);</text></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H396E98B3E51E44D38A45CB16030E2F77"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">15 percent for the activities described in section 202(c)(4); and</text></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H192CB41588574300B26B225AD45CAFC5"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">30 percent for the activities described in section 202(c)(5).</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


