<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA870FB6CC6744BD3973A3E859CF41D8E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1008 IH: Combat Harmful Algal Blooms Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1008</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001127">Mrs. Cherfilus-McCormick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act to include algal blooms in the definition of a major disaster, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H958CFBE5B83F432182559849A60528D8" style="OLC"><section id="H22020AB552B049E89928A8CA7ABF2361" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Combat Harmful Algal Blooms Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HBBB4BA0F6CF54149866305F72CCDC685" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings; sense of Congress</header><subsection id="HC283F8EADD1C46879FEEE33E33F311AE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HAB427A0481584B0EA0845D67B6A00FCC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The presence of harmful algal blooms threaten public health, interrupt economic activity, and contribute to the ongoing degradation of ecological communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6C353D3033D46DCAC88E3324FFB6756"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Algal blooms are part of healthy and productive freshwater and saltwater systems, but harmful algal blooms may become intense, long-lasting, expansive, and may contain enough poisonous neurotoxins to harm marine life and humans alike.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34ECEC1673D14B62BEB17FF04C95E7D5"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Water conditions and ecological balance in marine environments depend on nutrient and salinity conditions, which are often influenced by—</text><subparagraph id="H65BB1B3B3F2347DE9DA872DD8A4F0953"><enum>(A)</enum><text>tidal flow and circulation;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A1E02F2CB9A474D8495EE1982394FF7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>freshwater input from the land; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD5D1F246EDEF43AEA24911169A6A02F3"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coastal nutrient recycling; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EE4D2FE7DF14335AF09C4EF44B79B72"><enum>(D)</enum><text>urban development.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC636A5D1FD704E09980DFE5747FF41DA"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Harmful algal blooms, depending on the severity, may result in the widespread mortality of marine life and aquatic specimens, which may result in unpleasant sights and smells around the impacted body of water.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H432399004C934F10B53525BAE0662B14"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Harmful algal blooms can force the closure of beaches, impose fishing and shellfish harvesting restrictions, and could even result in banning the sale of seafood at restaurants.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD44942497F9049CFB91CEDF83F441A11"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Tourism numbers can drop dramatically during harmful algal blooms, which may result in a significant economic impact to certain economies that heavily depend on bringing in visitors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA32DE77D55FB4D48B08CDEDFFCCB7AE1"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Property values near water sources that experience harmful algal blooms may decrease substantially.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8F8439ECE73645EE9EF03AFEC940562C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that Congress should focus on decreasing the overarching impact of harmful algal blooms on public health, the economy, and the degradation of ecological communities.</text></subsection></section><section id="H6FABD60105C84ED9A59EEB606503CE8F" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Algal blooms</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 102(2) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5122">42 U.S.C. 5122(2)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>or drought</quote> and inserting <quote>drought, or algal blooms</quote>.</text></section><section id="H378B5CC8F67546E18A20F59EB04409BD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Impacts of algal blooms on air quality</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 365 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention shall submit to the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate, the Committee of Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate, the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate, the Committee on Oversight and Accountability of the House of Representatives, the Committee on Science, Space, and Technology of the House of Representatives, and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a detailed study relating to the health effects of exposure to cyanotoxins in the air that result from algal blooms.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

