<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDF2241F602724A2DB8967A728B91D381" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2365 IH: National Plan to End Parkinson’s Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-29</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2365</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230329">March 29, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001038">Mr. Higgins of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to carry out a national project to prevent and cure Parkinson’s, to be known as the National Parkinson’s Project, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9532D3EF69404E3F804BC559C42A7774" style="OLC"><section id="H5C6BC037FC894F1EA3A63ADB39EA670D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Plan to End Parkinson’s Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5B47CDDE640144939EAF6EEACD5E0C60"><enum>2.</enum><header>National Parkinson’s Project</header><subsection id="HBC032E94857147CCAFCE5DD85236E468"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition of Parkinson’s</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Parkinson’s</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H62F61D5685E843CCAB9EFD2A0515F9D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Parkinson’s disease; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C4C117F837A44468180238F225BDD35"><enum>(2)</enum><text>other neurodegenerative Parkinsonisms, including, but not limited to, multiple system atrophy, Lewy body disease, corticobasal degeneration, progressive supranuclear palsy, and Parkinson’s-related dementia.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8CDCE772812D452CBF929AC43802D189"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall carry out a national project to prevent and cure Parkinson’s, ameliorate its symptoms, and slow or stop its progression, to be known as the National Parkinson’s Project (referred to in this section as the <quote>Project</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H838180C49160420C8F958A2FD22DFC84"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Activities carried out through Project</header><text>In carrying out the Project, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H1B52F1A408EE4F73815477E6A7E4B123"><enum>(1)</enum><text>create, maintain, and periodically update an integrated national plan to prevent and cure Parkinson’s, ameliorate its symptoms, and slow or stop its progression;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7082ACB521B4EF8B4AC0DDED9872C1C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>carry out the annual assessment under subsection (d);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBCA86CA733744BDB1FABA81F12F00EF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>provide information (including an estimate of the level of Federal investment necessary to prevent and cure Parkinson’s, ameliorate its symptoms, and slow or stop its progression), and coordination of Parkinson’s research and services, across all Federal agencies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19FC6B295E90472182203E7F4F68E1B5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>encourage the development of safe and effective treatments, strategies, and other approaches to prevent, halt, or slow the course of Parkinson’s or to enhance functioning and improve quality of life;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7A8232B6C0042E29216AD8E053F6D8C"><enum>(5)</enum><text>promote the—</text><subparagraph id="H7D078F44D1D54240AB9C50E71D8E404D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>early diagnosis of Parkinson’s; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDB71581FEC043098EA478191943A038"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordination of the care and treatment of individuals with Parkinson’s;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H81ADD703113C474AA4C6F706E724B973"><enum>(6)</enum><text>review the impact of Parkinson’s on the physical, mental, and social health of those living with Parkinson’s and their care partners;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE3D98F9E3EE04E3284EE5C451182871C"><enum>(7)</enum><text>coordinate with international bodies, to the degree possible, to integrate and inform the global mission to prevent and cure Parkinson’s, ameliorate its symptoms, and slow or stop its progression; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H553E308126CE4F17A31F5C6E57383BF8"><enum>(8)</enum><text>carry out other such activities as the Secretary deems appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEFA3B81D1FC8418DB457D87AC4B2159C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Annual assessment</header><text>Not later than 24 months after the date of enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall carry out an assessment of the Nation’s progress in preparing for and responding to the escalating burden of Parkinson’s, including—</text><paragraph id="H85758BDF85934ED5B3E7BEE93E14D63E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the formulation of recommendations for priority actions based on the assessment;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E4DE69AC9B34D1984ED7A0CAD4703D2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the steps that have been or should be taken to implement the recommendations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD9AA909959E47F686C63C6DCC57CA1D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such other items as the Secretary deems appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2A7640A535064E1AA79C9FF3C80D698F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Advisory Council</header><paragraph id="HAF74B242795A424AB48E1F49329F81B6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish and maintain an Advisory Council on Parkinson’s Research, Care, and Services (referred to in this section as the <quote>Advisory Council</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC27B17E24BC4AB4AB76757850915465"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><subparagraph id="HC83C26DBA1F942E5BF06EFAA71B7CF5B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Federal members</header><text>The Advisory Council shall be comprised of diverse and inclusive representatives from—</text><clause id="H342DEED07B9D4B4E805003616CC2F22E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;</text></clause><clause id="H5F1306E2796841A7A170191B0EAD85BC"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the Administration on Community Living;</text></clause><clause id="HEC6894264835494CA315911094584DDA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services;</text></clause><clause id="H1448B6AC57D74884A0BFB4BBEF4037E4"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Office of the Director of the National Institutes of Health;</text></clause><clause id="H45C5BB6CCA3D43B4897894991EEBAB83"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke;</text></clause><clause id="HF8F432829E0A49908E02B7512DC4E804"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences;</text></clause><clause id="HCC4A5EEE6C49406E900BBBF357065E67"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>the Department of Veterans Affairs;</text></clause><clause id="HD00E4B66E99846D6BD63BB6BC4C4495B"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>the Food and Drug Administration;</text></clause><clause id="HBC67D2F81B7D45008E893121E4940A63"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>the Department of Defense;</text></clause><clause id="HDFBA3FD017754AA4808C22908C95692C"><enum>(x)</enum><text>the Environmental Protection Agency;</text></clause><clause id="H955B0FE0DB2146D7B0F45203941C0F02"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>the Office of Minority Health;</text></clause><clause id="H2C771310B345474195976BC8BB3A3C9D"><enum>(xii)</enum><text>the Indian Health Service; and </text></clause><clause id="H7D393875D67346ABA22371B872AF0678"><enum>(xiii)</enum><text>other relevant Federal departments and agencies as determined by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8EF6A000A4414B00AB31E331528CAAC5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Non-Federal members</header><text>In addition to the members listed in subparagraph (A), the Advisory Council shall include 10 expert members from outside the Federal Government, to be appointed by the Secretary, which members shall include—</text><clause id="H08EBC49ED8EA4B1E9B551EEA0844FB67"><enum>(i)</enum><text>2 Parkinson’s patient advocates, at least 1 of whom is living with young-onset Parkinson’s;</text></clause><clause id="H14B7296143D54D6F93DE76FCBC3BB2DF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>1 Parkinson’s family caregiver;</text></clause><clause id="H7EEB295BB7B840708A9636076CD66F67"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>1 health care provider;</text></clause><clause id="H4A5782F626FB43529C5BC7BCC611D7E9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>2 biomedical researchers with Parkinson’s-related expertise in basic, translational, clinical, or drug development science;</text></clause><clause id="H69C147F981AC4953A2F79AC9A4E2725E"><enum>(v)</enum><text>1 movement disorder specialist who treats Parkinson’s patients;</text></clause><clause id="HAD8FB1DDFF9147E2BCD6FC1B349B9195"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>1 dementia specialist who treats Parkinson’s patients; and</text></clause><clause id="H3425C5BAEF8543B2AF3A9428480A29E4"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>2 representatives from nonprofit organizations that have demonstrated experience in Parkinson’s research or Parkinson’s patient care and other services.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3994B329B69C4BD0B6BE9068C9770437"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Meetings</header><subparagraph id="HE03714240D354D5C97AE3770295AD438"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Quarterly meetings</header><text>The Advisory Council shall meet at least once each quarter.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CFA92D5A24C4F7A89E6C999996ED232"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Biannual research meeting</header><text>Not later than 24 months after the date of enactment of this Act, and every 2 years thereafter, the Advisory Council shall convene a meeting of Federal and non-Federal organizations to discuss Parkinson’s research.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20C7373ADCB84E39B1A967488E4AACE8"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Open meetings</header><text>The meetings of the Advisory Council shall be open to the public.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4792A702BC8949768114DEEAF46C1C89"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Advice</header><text>The Advisory Council shall advise the Secretary on Parkinson’s-related issues.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F20E889C41440228127D40BCD9D068E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Biannual report</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, and every 2 years thereafter, the Advisory Council shall provide to the Secretary and Congress a report containing—</text><subparagraph id="H63A5896A0DB34849AFFD1F2E0769FD87"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an evaluation of all federally funded efforts in Parkinson’s research, prevention, clinical care, and institutional-, home-, and community-based programs and the outcomes of such efforts;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC42FAAA8C07F4DB1931CE8ADF2693858"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recommendations for priority actions to expand, eliminate, coordinate, refocus, or condense Federal programs based on each program’s performance, mission, and purpose;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9B55150C8C484CF897B95C12DC86B43A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recommendations to—</text><clause id="HF4B55B5799BC483CA576315F076EF126"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reduce the financial impact of Parkinson’s on—</text><subclause id="HF8DD98EACBC848E68DFA8161F2122083"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Medicare program and other federally funded programs; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H17431933197241CCAE3159FAC5E77FD3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>families living with Parkinson’s;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HCDADAECC044B4676BECC176240C4BED3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>improve health outcomes and quality of life;</text></clause><clause id="H09F1FD93CD2B4B36B606F08F6AAFF2F0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>prevent Parkinson’s; and</text></clause><clause id="HBB41E94A686945F9BC29389AD3121F6D"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>research the association between environmental triggers and Parkinson’s to help reduce exposure to potential triggers; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H964B033FAAB24811953CF77E4D40B1AD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an evaluation of the implementation, including outcomes, of the national plan under subsection (c)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6B2C1F5D2D24F1596E298FA15766004"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Advisory Council shall terminate at the end of calendar year 2035.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H96F783F3F1B1435B98543871F6C3652F"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Data sharing</header><text>Agencies both within the Department of Health and Human Services and outside of the Department that have data relating to Parkinson’s shall share such data with the Secretary of Health and Human Services, or the Secretary’s designee, consistent with the statutory obligations regrading disclosure of information for that department or agency, to enable the Secretary, or the Secretary’s designee, to complete the report described in subsection (g).</text></subsection><subsection id="H69CA24DFCEF745A2987A3AE1E44B9A01"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Biannual report</header><text>The Secretary shall submit to the Congress—</text><paragraph id="HF219070BD1F744628E60294D3E739DC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a Biannual report that includes an evaluation of all federally funded efforts in Parkinson’s research, prevention, diagnosis, treatment, clinical care, and institutional-, home-, and community-based programs and the outcomes of such efforts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H781CFE7578804B87B1D259EE07DF6D22"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an evaluation of all such programs based on performance, mission, and purpose;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BABE32041B34260B6CB950997FD1995"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommendations for—</text><subparagraph id="HC47CF8B3672E4DF29ADC3257931FFB4A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>priority actions based on the evaluation conducted by the Secretary and the Advisory Council to—</text><clause id="HC6C59183E71744758113BDDFF89C5F85"><enum>(i)</enum><text>reduce the financial impact of Parkinson’s on—</text><subclause id="H799E639DD8E14811BE6305843A814206"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Medicare program and other federally funded programs; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H762752B6706A4D3AA1ABC2B570975A88"><enum>(II)</enum><text>families living with Parkinson’s disease;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H72D46E0D033E486C8109A7003CC6C777"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>improve health outcomes and quality of life;</text></clause><clause id="H84488B07E9F24D53BCCB057DB668375E"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>prevent Parkinson’s; and</text></clause><clause id="HB31F4677145C42179A6D2BD675CB5DE1"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>research the association between environmental triggers and Parkinson’s to help reduce exposure to potential triggers;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5866DCBA32D64DE58774DF37B8477E99"><enum>(B)</enum><text>priority actions to improve all federally funded efforts in Parkinson’s research, prevention, diagnosis, treatment, clinical care, and institutional-, home-, and community-based programs; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E735A8A198D492A820C7D08F69A8CC3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>implementation steps to address priority actions described in subparagraphs (A) and (B); and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7F98C1CC79F475FA428FFDCE592C1D2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an up-to-date version of the national plan under subsection (c)(1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF5A0B8D602E941FA87A24487E363C73A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>The section shall cease to be effective at the end of calendar year 2035. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

