<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3A5E5E75D1084146879E1F4E17A1497E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1523 IH: Property Tax Reduction Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1523</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="L000600">Mr. Langworthy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XIX of the Social Security Act to reduce Federal financial participation for certain States that require political subdivisions to contribute towards the non-Federal share of Medicaid.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFB4BB44461D844F6A512315F03A52F96" style="OLC"><section id="H83A5783773824423A69F02520777DD3F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Property Tax Reduction Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H481DC0198CAE47E9B99354B85A5D5C48"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reduction of Federal financial participation (FFP) for certain States that require political subdivisions to contribute toward non-Federal share of Medicaid</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1903 of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1396b">42 U.S.C. 1396b</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3DB5612E8B744EA3946728D178C51064" style="traditional"><subsection id="H6EB8038FC536400FBDFBAEF764FE5346"><enum>(cc)</enum><header>Reduction in FFP for contributions required by political subdivisions</header><paragraph id="HAC8E1C331FE9430FA644F0AE21F01EFC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding the previous provisions of this section, in the case of a State that had a DSH allotment under section 1923(f) for fiscal year 2023 that was more than 6 times the national average of such allotments for all the States for such fiscal year and that requires political subdivisions within the State to contribute funds towards medical assistance or other expenditures under the State plan under this title (or under a waiver of such plan) for a quarter in a fiscal year (beginning with fiscal year 2025), in determining the amount that is payable to the State for expenditures in such quarter under subsection (a)(1), other than contributions described in paragraph (2), the amount of such expenditures shall be reduced by the applicable percentage described in paragraph (3), with respect to such fiscal year, of the amount that political subdivisions in the State are required to contribute under the plan.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17B7272E777D459AAE15273BB997B8DA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Excepted contributions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The contributions described in this paragraph for a fiscal year are the following:</text><subparagraph id="HCC8030329AA841EBBB778919ABD014E9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Contributions required by a State from a political subdivision that, as of the first day of the calendar year in which the fiscal year involved begins—</text><clause id="H7BB4D7E36ED2446EA4725EFBD42F7FE2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>has a population of more than 5,000,000, as estimated by the Bureau of the Census; and</text></clause><clause id="H86EDC2E6169A4076B4F3DD0ECBAAF6AB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>imposes a local income tax upon its residents.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H64AFC6131B51439DBBD35B978154FAF8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Contributions required by a State from a political subdivision for administrative expenses if the State required such contributions from such subdivision without reimbursement from the State as of January 1, 2023.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5C01965D8084F56938DE828850129E9"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Applicable percentage</header><text>For purposes of paragraph (1), the applicable percentage described in this paragraph is—</text><subparagraph id="HB936971E529548E3B8DF9840AF9E5C10"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to fiscal year 2025, 25 percent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D1EAA36749F48979ADACFC25F1258A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to fiscal year 2026, 50 percent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A6BECAC05F74E688A0C8AD639C092D7"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to fiscal year 2027, 75 percent; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E647AA40FBA46D8B8EA68EDDF19ABAC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>with respect to fiscal year 2028 and each subsequent fiscal year, 100 percent.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

