<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC2A4C1E1F7C34F64A60E6CA36D82367B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 3249 IH: Protecting Circuit Boards and Substrates Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3249</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001213">Mr. Moore of Utah</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide incentives for the domestic production of printed circuit boards, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H005BF674065F4F6994EE6778833AE3C8" style="OLC"><section id="HA10FCFDE05A04B6B9012BCF1FD310030" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protecting Circuit Boards and Substrates Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" id="HE018959B23304631AEEDA4A0C0E63525"><enum>2.</enum><header>Tax credit for the purchase or acquisition of printed circuit boards manufactured in the United States</header><subsection id="H2D665D95829A48CE8F37D57250DAC533"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subpart D of part IV of subchapter A of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/26/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by inserting after section 45Z the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H4AEC25D9D5C242B5AE31E10C27375203" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HF9960BEDBC904058A3EE5984D6B6C1A1"><enum>45AA.</enum><header>Credit for the purchase or acquisition of printed circuit boards fabricated in the United States</header><subsection id="H2B836511CD47458F849CA881C26666CC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of section 38, the credit determined under this section for the taxable year is an amount equal to 25 percent of the cost paid or incurred by the taxpayer for the purchase or acquisition of printed circuit boards fabricated in the United States for the taxable year.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3E376C75CC0D4007B424C8F0705810DA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For the purposes of this section—</text><paragraph id="H321395E2ABDC4BE1B3E69441E569A580"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Printed circuit board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>printed circuit board</term> has the meaning given such term in section 3(a) of the Protecting Circuit Boards and Substrates Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D2F81FB06044472A8204E22B4B6EB10"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fabricated</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>fabricated</term> means the use of raw materials to manufacture a connected composite structure featuring electrically conductive and non-conductive elements by subtractive, additive, or other technique.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD5EDCDC806954E14B2AABA5C94D73278"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Regulations and guidance</header><text>The Secretary shall, in consultation with the Secretary of Commerce, promulgate such regulations and guidance as may be necessary or appropriate to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H19B307C16A944A1CAD185A71F22C0B5C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for subpart D of part IV of subchapter A of chapter 1 of such Code is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 45Z the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21D04497CDAA45B9B0DA12529B458EC2"><toc><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">Sec. 45AA. Credit for the purchase or acquisition of printed circuit boards fabricated in the United States.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H924F1A342DA24F0986DD5A9D2CB1D9F8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Credit made part of general business credit</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/38">Section 38(b)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><paragraph id="HB273A789C95C47BC9066329CB4CC4B79"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (37), by striking <quote>plus</quote>,</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF918983B7DD47CB8D53A949659CB87E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (38), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>, plus</quote>, and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H157B867CB69948698793CCB2391CDF07"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HEEF48AD1FD434629BAB6C8203A14B592" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HEED900820BA24E33A3404005AE87BA86"><enum>(39)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the credit for the purchase or acquisition of printed circuit boards fabricated in the United States determined under section 45AA.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H98A4A39BDB334B798ACEC55914B1F04D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to amounts paid or incurred after December 31, 2022.</text></subsection></section><section id="H4C32C5A6A04C4E0C9EF0B7244B423304"><enum>3.</enum><header>Incentives for printed circuit board manufacturing and research and development</header><subsection id="H778BCA36619C4CEAA94548EA7AFECA45"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HDEEB18A25B28464D8AF1C2238CD22F6B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Active component</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>active component</term> means, with respect to a printed circuit board, an electronic component within an electronic circuit that relies on an external power source to control or modify electrical signals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1C111EB8DF074CEE9C5CD1DAFC209CDD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered entity</header><text>The term <term>covered entity</term> means a private entity, a consortium of private entities, or a consortium of public and private entities with the ability to substantially finance, construct, expand, or modernize a facility relating to manufacturing or research and development of printed circuit boards and integrated circuit substrates.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H766139EF74454CD1BD89CF101A4171E7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Covered incentive</header><text>The term <term>covered incentive</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HDA8097984851476B84CAB96B4E4F8E6F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an incentive used for the purposes of constructing, expanding, or modernizing a facility described in paragraph (2) that will be located in the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H48FB1E55135A4D5CAB853A9959CD5A59"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a workforce-related incentive (including an agreement to provide grants for workforce training or vocational education), any concession with respect to real property, funding for research and development with respect to printed circuit boards, and any other incentive determined by the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of State, to be appropriate and related to encouraging investment in facilities and equipment in the United States for manufacturing or research and development of printed circuit boards.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F238FFC6F17417D8F9479E06D497A94"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Economically disadvantaged individual</header><text>The term <term>economically disadvantaged individual</term> means an individual described in section 8(a)(6)(A) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/637">15 U.S.C. 637(a)(6)(A)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74378A7593FF48C5809188894B5F8527"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Foreign entity; foreign entity of concern</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>foreign entity</term> and <term>foreign entity of concern</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 9901 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/4651">15 U.S.C. 4651</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCC1AFBCCE06D408B9E075796C551F66A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Historically Black college or university</header><text>The term <term>historically Black college or university</term> has the meaning given the term <term>part B institution</term> in section 322 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1061">20 U.S.C. 1061</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04E79F5446054220850671F076077EA6"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given such term in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2461B7BC8B1F4ED0AF9A4622E2E68A56" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Integrated circuit substrate</header><text>The term <term>integrated circuit substrate</term> means a thin composite structure of layered electrically conductive materials and organic electrically non-conductive materials that electrically connects integrated circuits to an underlying structure, including a printed circuit board.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9C1402ACD73A408A94FCFEFB6FADE019"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Intelligence community</header><text>The term <term>intelligence community</term> has the meaning given that term in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBCB17A284C44FBBAFE8EDA6EE56758F"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Minority-owned business and women-owned business</header><text>The terms <term>minority-owned business</term> and <term>women-owned business</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 704B(h) of the Equal Credit Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1691c-2">15 U.S.C. 1691c–2(h)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H844262E915614F07A92CC979AAECC26C"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Minority-serving institution</header><text>The term <term>minority-serving institution</term> means any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="H7D89B7E8041C4A7F925D544A5CD7BDE1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An Alaska Native-serving institution (as that term is defined in section 317(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059d">20 U.S.C. 1059d(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC83A253A952743889E35E04B0149E31A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A Native Hawaiian-serving institution (as that term is defined in section 317(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059d">20 U.S.C. 1059d(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC533120647C4C44982DB4433BF4D385"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A Predominantly Black institution (as that term is defined in section 371(c) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1067q">20 U.S.C. 1067q(c)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC5B0F6E11274BF6B51FC77A63AACFA5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An Asian American and Native American Pacific Islander-serving institution (as that term is defined in section 320(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059g">20 U.S.C. 1059g(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A145591930D49BAAF5F461D5FF4EA11"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A Native American-serving, nontribal institution (as that term is defined in section 319(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059f">20 U.S.C. 1059f(b)</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7496F2D9C67F495C86A499F09122C7AB"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Passive component</header><text>The term <term>passive component</term> means, with respect to a printed circuit board, an electronic component within an electronic circuit that functions using the existing electronic current within the electronic circuit to control or modify electrical signals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0C132D901015420EA09F4B488DF7AA4B"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Person</header><text>The term <term>person</term> means an individual or entity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8588AEF8ACD444E08AEC6548F659140D" commented="no"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Printed circuit board</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>printed circuit board</term> means a composite structure of layered electrically conductive and non-conductive materials that provides interconnections with other micro-electronics or electronics systems or subsystems and electrical connections between active and passive components, and may include components embedded in the composite structure.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADCAE4EFB0A54FBB9942AD3212496E38"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Program</header><text>The term <term>Program</term> means the program established under subsection (b)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF218514BBF9442BBC0DC2A39A7CF777"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CB43F0726364F38992A9AF03EAA6F7C"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Small business</header><text>The term <term>small business</term> has the meaning given the term <term>small business concern</term> under section 3(a) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632(a)</external-xref>), except that section 121.103 of title 13, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation) shall not apply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6E4A68F0F674CE088002C4B69F6E692"><enum>(18)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> means each State of the United States, the District of Columbia, each commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20FA925D7DE44862A416CA64D30C18D4"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Veteran-owned business</header><text>The term <term>veteran-owned business</term> has the meaning given the term <term>small business concern owned and controlled by veterans</term> in section 3(q) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632(q)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA33E8C56E7EA4E8D81EBC4B0C97363BE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Financial assistance program</header><paragraph id="H00265595203B4CCEB6E5A7712AF23906"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a program that, in accordance with the requirements of this section and subject to the availability of appropriations for such purposes, provides Federal financial assistance to covered entities to incentivize investment in facilities and equipment in the United States for manufacturing or research and development of printed circuit boards and integrated circuit substrates.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H428A8E49389A4BF1A287B8E5C3F5CD99"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Procedure</header><subparagraph id="H2809AC0AF1734E3E9571B396C0ACBDE7"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A covered entity shall submit to the Secretary an application that describes the project for which the covered entity is seeking financial assistance under the Program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA0D8F22DD97C4BCE906FF132AE16DAB1"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>Except as provided in subparagraph (C), in order for a covered entity to qualify for financial assistance under the Program, the covered entity shall demonstrate to the Secretary, in the application submitted by the covered entity under subparagraph (A), that—</text><clause id="H674E1AD60A46420499A2F6C392D62F61"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the covered entity has a documented interest in carrying out a project that is a covered incentive; and</text></clause><clause id="H105A7545545F469DAEAB7F72AF7E7337"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>with respect to the project described in clause (i), the covered entity has—</text><subclause id="H4B2E3B44E0D3413095568BBE2E92E0B7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a plan the Secretary determines to be executable to sustain the covered incentive described in clause (i) without additional Federal financial assistance under the Program for facility support;</text></subclause><subclause id="H8326A30159F94B23864D77EEB57DF3E9"><enum>(II)</enum><text>made commitments to worker and community investment, including through—</text><item id="H019A98F4068849448EB972918225132F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>training and education benefits provided by or paid for by the covered entity; and</text></item><item id="HBB3B605D42E040EF95956D1FCF4E7465"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>programs to expand employment opportunity for economically disadvantaged individuals; and</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H029CB18680034E99BA56A3F2782B594D"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">secured commitments from regional educational and training entities, postsecondary vocational institutions (defined in section 102(c) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002(c)</external-xref>)), or institutions of higher education to provide workforce training, including programming for training and job placement of economically disadvantaged individuals.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDB7D714230C491FA2C49730D23B3547"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Small business exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirements in subclauses (II) and (III) of subparagraph (B)(ii) do not apply to small businesses.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5FE639C233548C3A3B7AC9A78269887"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Due diligence</header><text>With respect to the review by the Secretary of an application submitted by a covered entity under subparagraph (A), the Secretary may not approve the application unless the Secretary—</text><clause id="HDBFB437CFD3D4E8D9A900A7CEAEAA273"><enum>(i)</enum><text>confirms that the covered entity has satisfied the applicable eligibility criteria under subparagraph (B); and</text></clause><clause id="HE973ACE3FCFD4A61B30CBF6A9DDA26EF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>determines that the project to which the application relates is in the interest of the United States.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4285DB8774BA4191A57A2D3CA13A3856"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Considerations for review</header><clause id="H23BC779F2FC648D9BDF119A3CBA02225"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), with respect to the review by the Secretary of an application submitted by a covered entity under subparagraph (A), the Secretary shall consider whether the covered entity has—</text><subclause id="HBE58244A403A418F9A4393F9F151EDC3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>previously received financial assistance under the Program; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H2021CC0F488F419EB836168C6D157839"><enum>(II)</enum><text>demonstrated that it is responsive to the national security needs or requirements established by the intelligence community (or an agency thereof), the National Nuclear Security Administration, or the Department of Defense.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9A90C4EB7D084C219209B7933D2825D1"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Small businesses excluded</header><text>Clause (i)(I) does not apply with respect to an application submitted by a small business under subparagraph (A).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1ABBD4AA489740FB88F2C7351D3F6B49"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Preferences</header><clause id="H7C0C4E6858E8438F8FA5A99FAE4BB296"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall, when practicable, give preference with respect to the approval of an application submitted under subparagraph (A) by a covered entity that—</text><subclause id="HF8CCD340159445709F379F7DFF447E55"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is a small business, minority-owned business, women-owned business, or veteran-owned business;</text></subclause><subclause id="HBF5CD751D2354D6E9DBCFDF0BA58DA71"><enum>(II)</enum><text>expands the United States production capacity of integrated circuit substrates;</text></subclause><subclause id="H08824004EBCD4D998F24874315B84674"><enum>(III)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is relocating a manufacturing facility of printed circuit boards currently located in an area owned by, controlled by, or subject to the jurisdiction or direction of a foreign entity of concern; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HDA798BFFEE024263A9381368F13C30DC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>includes a workforce training program that is—</text><item id="H154FCEA1DFF54361B19957B6DB108C14"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>a historically Black college or university;</text></item><item id="H408A78741E4047F9A8E49851EDC96E80"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>a Hispanic-serving institution (as such term is defined in section 502(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1101a">20 U.S.C. 1101a(a)</external-xref>));</text></item><item id="H39E2ACD8983C4640B4CB2ADA6B3B291D"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>a Tribal College or University (as such term is defined in section 316(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1059c">20 U.S.C. 1059c(b)</external-xref>));</text></item><item id="HEC7EB7DDF55141909EC7E2D081C1DE46"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>a minority-serving institution;</text></item><item id="H263031FEAA5449CAB7081A759C8593D7"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>a rural-serving institution of higher education (as such term is defined in section 861(b) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1161q">20 U.S.C. 1161q(b)</external-xref>)); or</text></item><item id="H7F9A0BC3ABAA4ECBBC455A421BE3370C"><enum>(ff)</enum><text>a workforce training organization that offers industry-recognized, stackable, and portable credentialing programs.</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H4A09CEFD12094EE1A457A87CB87E2A08"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subparagraph:</text><subclause id="HC32CABCD663D4D8FB018B6C90931D9B4"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Stackable</header><text>The term <term>stackable</term> means a credential that is part of a set of sequenced, related credentials that demonstrating the increasing qualifications of the individual acquiring the credentials for advancement along a specific career path or to a more senior position in the same or related career path.</text></subclause><subclause id="HEB550D69F8E14CCEAB18507AF0A6F4DB"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Portable</header><text>The term <term>portable</term> means a credential that is generally recognized and accepted by a wide variety of entities and in multiple geographic locations as verifying the qualifications of an individual.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H125622E5F45A403B9E12B2C613F6674B"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Foreign entities of concern exclusion</header><clause id="H48645DC9A3984203B83C4A50CACBA5ED"><enum>(i)</enum><text>The Secretary may not approve an application of a covered entity if the Secretary determines that the covered entity is a foreign entity of concern.</text></clause><clause id="HCFACFBDDF8D7444493A9F92E8168D9ED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>None of the funds authorized to be appropriated to carry out this subsection may be provided to a foreign entity of concern.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46C6EA4313DA4547A42B83BF2888281B"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Records production</header><clause id="H575D8E3ABD384D4D9D2C2AF6EBE3B24D"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may request from a covered entity that submits an application under subparagraph (A) any records and other information that the Secretary determines necessary for the purposes of ascertaining whether an award under the Program will be used for the covered incentive for which such award is sought, including records or other information regarding the status of such project.</text></clause><clause id="HFB17FEEB817B474CA87DCC35228B7482"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Funding restriction</header><text>No covered entity that fails to provide records or information requested by the Secretary under this subparagraph shall be eligible for Federal financial assistance under the Program if such records or information are reasonably available to such covered entity.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H05B78A3D562543098F2056388A06FDF5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Amount</header><subparagraph id="H3737B4E711A4450FA56F996CCDDADBDF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall determine the appropriate amount and funding type for each financial assistance award made to a covered entity under the Program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F6CF0590F29477CAF9483FD8C616AA9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Larger investment</header><text>The amount awarded under the Program with respect to any individual project may not exceed $300,000,000 unless the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Defense and the Director of National Intelligence, recommends to the President, and the President notifies Congress, that a larger award is necessary to—</text><clause id="H5D9439640FD54128AFAF7659642583AA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">significantly increase the supply of reliable, domestically produced printed circuit boards that are relevant for the national security and economic competitiveness of the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="H5E3699B0D4794087B058E148630F63DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>meet the needs of national security.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD749BD9F2E8403A887317C3B6451E35"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><subparagraph id="HBB11462B0BAE493E98DF1A99A31850DD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided by subparagraph (B), a covered entity that receives a financial assistance award under the Program may only use the financial assistance award amounts—</text><clause id="HA61712E26ABF4C80B434AB20FFC23156"><enum>(i)</enum><text>for a covered incentive; and</text></clause><clause id="H00C0B5DBBC5A47EF92B5D3B9E5D17A2C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>to pay reasonable costs related to the operating expenses for such covered incentive, including costs relating to the specialized workforce, essential materials, and complex equipment maintenance, as determined by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H843D41516C5446B585C5FC7E945FD6C9"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Larger investments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the amount awarded under the Program with respect to the project is more than $300,000,000, the covered entity that received such award may use such amounts only for the purposes described in subparagraph (A) to the extent that such use meets the national security needs or enhances the economic competitiveness of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H06784159603144B795823EEB8449057F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Clawback</header><subparagraph id="HB1D9A8B88BA2448E8C4A1D45327F7E54"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Delay clawback</header><clause id="H2EA11BDDC21F46418B87FA4BDDCC3CE7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Target dates</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to any award made under the Program, the Secretary shall—</text><subclause id="H463D8C54D741434BA43E060FBF0ED2EC"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determine target dates by which the project with respect to which such award was made shall commence and complete; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD07EE8A868B244D9A911CE2EBD0CFB25"><enum>(II)</enum><text>set such dates by the time of the award.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HC794B53F008442158C7CCAD53C7C90D9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Progressive recovery for delays</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a project is not commenced and completed by the dates determined under clause (i) for such project, the Secretary shall progressively recover from the recipient of the award for such project up to the full amount of such award.</text></clause><clause id="H10F994AB924D457BB093E8C69C1CAA6A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text>In the case of a project that is not commenced or completed by the dates determined under clause (i) for such project, the Secretary may waive elements of the clawback provisions incorporated in the award made under the Program for such project only if, prior to granting such waiver, the Secretary—</text><subclause id="H20E223D0320A463B90C5C08E36C752DA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>makes a formal determination that circumstances beyond the ability of the covered entity to foresee or control are responsible for delays; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H91CDDEEE6C68441A86A2063F10939963"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submits a notice to Congress.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB86E524E858342088FA40A1599B5F16D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Technology clawback</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may recover the full amount of any award made under the Program from the recipient of the award if, during the period determined under subparagraph (A)(i) for the project with respect to which such award was made, the recipient knowingly engages in any joint research or technology licensing effort with a foreign entity of concern that relates to a technology or product that raises national security concerns, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0C25F0F1E74840258D73B95044073E20"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Notification to Congress</header><clause id="H3C02DCF9D67E4863B9AC07A3EFA0F535"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall notify Congress of—</text><subclause id="HB63C8F394A934F169E6DF9B6F7B04D8B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the clawback provisions attending each award described in subparagraph (A)(i); and</text></subclause><subclause id="H714224C96D9A4CBE846CF8BA1064954E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>each waiver provided under subparagraph (A)(iii) not later than 15 days after the date on which the Secretary provides such waiver.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H81ED45CF2F1041C1BD26364E44652C2E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Waiver notice contents</header><text>The notice required under clause (i)(II) shall include—</text><subclause id="H273B91F719814085AD6B4E778CA159A3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the elements of the clawback provisions that were waived under subparagraph (A)(iii);</text></subclause><subclause id="H06F094BBFD304B4BA8DC8BDEA3FED3CB"><enum>(II)</enum><text>an explanation of why such waiver was provided;</text></subclause><subclause id="HADF6ECD142594A3297757E29A56E56D8"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the duration of the delay with respect to which such waiver was granted; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H7883F75354734E288BCFDB1F2390F9C8"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the name of the covered entity that was granted such waiver.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFD2AF411902D49F98CA941E091308E8B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the Program, the Secretary shall coordinate with—</text><paragraph id="H4E6286A20DE44E1D9152AB4CF11B5D9A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary of State;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1740FEBE33540978DF89F36CF626F4D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary of Defense;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05231C20F81649A1BF6AC3AB3C8B8FD4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Secretary of Energy;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B29FBF8B26C4EB2943194DA547CF0BE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Director of National Intelligence;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H029EB1D8C96B4328884269FF0D4690A8"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Director of the Minority Business Development Agency of the Department of Commerce;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9336B7F0ADCD47B9A5DF50F2C8DE93D5"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the Administrator of the Small Business Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H731AF3E4B45647048E9EE07597D3AEE4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Director of the National Institute of Standards and Technology;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H83968B773AB84EEE9DB56CA386F09058"><enum>(8)</enum><text>the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Agency; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8ABF3291CC4542C99AF2FE28CD90B4C0"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Director of the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7D8567CFFC434120B4F0A21337D45CED"><enum>(d)</enum><header>GAO reviews</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall—</text><paragraph id="H1E0F93FA866F400F81B158BDB865F8E6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 2 years after the date of disbursement of the first award under the Program, and biennially thereafter for 10 years, conduct a review of the Program, which shall include—</text><subparagraph id="H97F7F9EBC734480689A95D9A335EF861"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a determination of the number of awards provided under the Program during the two-year period immediately preceding the review;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H97B3C5AC8B6C44E1A4C179955B322D6E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an evaluation of how—</text><clause id="H2EDB729FB80A4E47A4425688780F248D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such program is being carried out, including how recipients of awards under the Program are being selected; and</text></clause><clause id="HD17AD5D69ADF44B3926CAA476D584EC3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>other Federal programs are leveraged for manufacturing, research, and training to complement the awards made under the Program; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBDBE70F6A167400DA523EBBF034ABE81"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a description of the outcomes of projects supported by awards made under the Program, including a description of—</text><clause id="H6D37DF219A4247CD8C51DF86D0F78CFD"><enum>(i)</enum><text>facilities described in subsection (b)(1) that were constructed, expanded, or modernized as a result of such awards;</text></clause><clause id="HD12E838E402946DC9516C76829306739"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>research and development carried out with such awards;</text></clause><clause id="HDA46C8F2F462472480AA1A5E86236444"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>workforce training programs carried out with such awards, including efforts to hire economically disadvantaged individuals; and</text></clause><clause id="H5C69D220D6204C9D8A9975670D22634F"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the effects of such projects on the United States share of global printed circuit board production; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FA9F785782449D1BA29EC6C6CC0A780"><enum>(2)</enum><text>notify Congress of the results of each review conducted under paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H70BE0472DB554790A4CD45194D1EA617" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is authorized to be appropriated $3,000,000,000 for fiscal year 2024, to remain available through fiscal year 2025, to carry out this section.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

