<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="H6E308004A9C94C00A71FDBD2A6E27466" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6408 RH: To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to terminate the tax-exempt status of terrorist supporting organizations.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 270</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6408</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–331]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231114">November 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000465">Mr. Ferguson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000376">Mr. Kelly of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000600">Mr. Diaz-Balart</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on November 14, 2023</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to terminate the tax-exempt status of terrorist supporting organizations.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HWM00" reported-display-style="italic" id="HB1BC899405C94DCEA49745B023D6672A"><section id="H328A486C02BC48068A3159BED8E63744" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Termination of tax-exempt status of terrorist supporting organizations</header><subsection id="H187E4ABAF1634D00AD4C614496A3C6B7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">Section 501(p)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HD47A7574F5414851A8CD1A367FFBFBFB" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="added" reported-display-style="italic" committee-id="HWM00"><paragraph id="H03530965394C4ECFA850A2DAF225ED88"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Application to terrorist supporting organizations</header><subparagraph id="H1EBEF4D80EFC4AB4BE1F5A19EAB0BDFF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this subsection, in the case of any terrorist supporting organization—</text><clause id="H8E3356AC9465490FBE89A40F2BF3C8C8"><enum>(i)</enum><text>such organization (and the designation of such organization under subparagraph (B)) shall be treated as described in paragraph (2), and</text></clause><clause id="H0A714194A7D44FB29A3F609BCD47E31F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the period of suspension described in paragraph (3) with respect to such organization shall be treated as beginning on the date that the Secretary designates such organization under subparagraph (B) and ending on the date that the Secretary rescinds such designation under subparagraph (D).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2D55BA032C034219AC23C32855C9F011"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Terrorist supporting organization</header><text>For purposes of this paragraph, the term <term>terrorist supporting organization</term> means any organization which is designated by the Secretary as having provided, during the 3-year period ending on the date of such designation, material support or resources (within the meaning of section 2339B of title 18, United States Code) to an organization described in paragraph (2) (determined after the application of this paragraph to such organization) in excess of a de minimis amount. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8BD6A127ECCB4559BE578DA6EBBE931F"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Designation procedure</header><clause id="H5F6E4E016BB14107BE9CE6FDB518A3BF"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Notice requirement</header><text>Prior to designating any organization as a terrorist supporting organization under subparagraph (B), the Secretary shall mail to the most recent mailing address provided by such organization on the organization’s annual return or notice under section 6033 (or subsequent form indicating a change of address) a written notice which includes—</text><subclause id="HC13F5E699CBA4A57B2A56AA0FC21D51D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a statement that the Secretary will designate such organization as a terrorist supporting organization unless the organization satisfies the requirements of subclause (I) or (II) of clause (ii),</text></subclause><subclause id="H427C67440C10475A86EDF53056EA9C7F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the name of the organization or organizations with respect to which the Secretary has determined such organization provided material support or sources as described in subparagraph (B), and</text></subclause><subclause id="HF9D703BA81264159B9C7E76D92141FE6"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a description of such material support or resources to the extent consistent with national security and law enforcement interests.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H77042A70E609462E8C7D84EA79983E18"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Opportunity to cure</header><text>In the case of any notice provided to an organization under clause (i), the Secretary shall, at the close of the 90-day period beginning on the date that such notice was sent, designate such organization as a terrorist supporting organization under subparagraph (B) if (and only if) such organization has not (during such period)—</text><subclause id="H82CA46DF7282423B97CA8B88D0430F9F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>demonstrated to the satisfaction of the Secretary that such organization did not provide the material support or resources referred to in subparagraph (B), or</text></subclause><subclause id="HE176CF23FA0C4553A36DD19A306631C3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>made reasonable efforts to have such support or resources returned to such organization and certified in writing to the Secretary that such organization will not provide any further support or resources to organizations described in paragraph (2).</text></subclause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="clause">A certification under subclause (II) shall not be treated as valid if the organization making such certification has provided any other such certification during the preceding 5 years.</continuation-text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFD2CA00FD08D4C25AC964E4785B16207"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rescission</header><text>The Secretary shall rescind a designation under subparagraph (B) if (and only if)—</text><clause id="H5E48D2A4A0AA44DEA0A83A48238EAAC7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the Secretary determines that such designation was erroneous,</text></clause><clause id="H74F20534351640E9A7245484F5371464"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>after the Secretary receives a written certification from an organization that such organization did not receive the notice described in subparagraph (C)(i)—</text><subclause id="H987A49A8D1DF4C01B400F8254BF98DCC"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the Secretary determines that it is reasonable to believe that such organization did not receive such notice, and</text></subclause><subclause id="HC450734F250842FCA2D1C14E8CFA4646"><enum>(II)</enum><text>such organization satisfies the requirements of subclause (I) or (II) of subparagraph (C)(ii) (determined after taking into account the last sentence thereof), or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H4D48EBC010DB4918BFC4B0DC9B5D1258"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Secretary determines, with respect to all organizations to which the material support or resources referred to in subparagraph (B) were provided, the periods of suspension under paragraph (3) have ended.</text></clause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subparagraph">A certification described in the matter preceding subclause (I) of clause (II) shall not be treated as valid if the organization making such certification has provided any other such certification during the preceding 5 years.</continuation-text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA4499C62D7994320970D8E020F9536B8"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Administrative review by Internal Revenue Service Independent Office of Appeals</header><text>In the case of the designation of an organization by the Secretary as a terrorist supporting organization under subparagraph (B), a dispute regarding such designation shall be subject to resolution by the Internal Revenue Service Independent Office of Appeals under section 7803(e) in the same manner as if such designation were made by the Internal Revenue Service and paragraph (5) of this subsection did not apply.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE15A9DDF887E4446B8AEC2A335A5282C"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Jurisdiction of United States courts</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding paragraph (5), the United States district courts shall have exclusive jurisdiction to review a final determination with respect to an organization’s designation as a terrorist supporting organization under subparagraph (B). In the case of any such determination which was based on classified information (as defined in section 1(a) of the Classified Information Procedures Act), such information may be submitted to the reviewing court ex parte and in camera. For purposes of this subparagraph, a determination with respect to an organization’s designation as a terrorist supporting organization shall not fail to be treated as a final determination merely because such organization fails to utilize the dispute resolution process of the Internal Revenue Service Independent Office of Appeals provided under subparagraph (E).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HD6B2FEB05CF64649A9F96CB9DC39E3BC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendment made by this section shall apply to designations made after the date of the enactment of this Act in taxable years ending after such date.</text></subsection></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20231219">December 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported with an amendment, committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union, and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

