<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1CBA4ADEF2B745CD9FC893E707588B0D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1378 IH: Veterans’ Appeals Backlog Improvement Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1378</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230307">March 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001220">Mr. McGarvey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001315">Ms. Budzinski</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to establish an internship program within the Board of Veterans’ Appeals, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBF7D23458CB84B7597066894672F5CD0" style="OLC"><section id="H052606094416472EA027E60CF3465DBA" section-type="section-one" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>1.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Short title; table of contents</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans’ Appeals Backlog Improvement Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HB4DEC8F6AE554137BFF1B70FBF3BB700" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Board of Veterans' Appeals internship program</header><subsection id="H977DA673FB94474CB685CD32B37DAAC7" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/71">Chapter 71</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section: </text><quoted-block id="HA69AEBEC41CA408FB59A544356154045" style="USC" act-name="" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HF5C08F248A104A339E0CD2A56921DE77" section-type="subsequent-section" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>7114.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Internship program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish a competitive internship program within the Department for the purpose of providing an opportunity for high-achieving students at law schools accredited by the American Bar Association to gain experience with the Board.</text></section><after-quoted-block display="yes">.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HAE94E122252F4391A0B0AE0B9A2E7EBE" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections at the beginning of chapter 71 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following new item: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB3C1CFD84EBF47C3B79810CA49CA761D"><toc><toc-entry level="section" bold="off">7114. Internship program.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block display="yes">.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H659E7DF40A6E4F6D8928E658AD9EABC2" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish the internship program required by section 7114 of such title, as added by subsection (a), not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act. </text></subsection></section><section id="HFB5CE5D28D9B4F98BFD13714C505CC04" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Pilot program on establishment of Department of Veterans Affairs honors program</header><subsection id="HB4249AE041F04429AA6345B737FAB10B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall establish a nine-year pilot program under which the Secretary shall carry out a competitive honors program within the Department of Veterans Affairs for the purpose of recruiting high-achieving law school students, recent law school graduates, and entry-level attorneys for employment with the Department.</text></subsection><subsection id="H49160FAB26F64CC2B42A78EF8972C177" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Qualifications</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to participate in the competitive honors program under the pilot program, an individual shall have graduated from a law school accredited by the American Bar Association and shall be a member in good standing of the bar of a state, territory, or the District of Columbia. The Secretary shall give priority consideration in application for the honors program to individuals who successfully complete the internship program established under section 7114 of title 38, United States Code, as added by section 2(a).</text></subsection><subsection id="H81034EE2FA514EFEBB8BE11DED292283" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Student loan repayment benefits</header><paragraph id="H04693A3AD4474A6A996AA41CCB45800D" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to an agreement under paragraph (2), the Secretary shall provide student loan repayment benefits under section 5379 of title 5, United States Code, to each participant in the pilot program who is eligible for student loan repayment benefits under such section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H96434978828F461291882305CB1614E7" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Participant agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall enter into an agreement with each participant in the pilot program who will receive benefits described in paragraph (1), in accordance with such section. Each such agreement shall specify that—</text><subparagraph id="H0FA04BE30FEC4D04BB9CF71A8855A4D7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the participant agrees to remain in the service of the Department for a period of not less than three years, unless involuntarily separated, in accordance with subsection (c) of such section; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF88B98EB764E41F2B5B3ED2520827C51"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if separated involuntarily on account of misconduct, or voluntarily, before the end of the period specified in the agreement, the participant shall repay to the Government the amount of any benefits received by the individual from the Department in accordance with subsection (c) of such section 5379.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4A13B59EFA994499BD4DF8C7F6BD00AB" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Professional development activities</header><paragraph id="H7C77ED74E5D74EE7BDD988C42BDB8740" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assignment of mentors</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date on which an individual begins participating in the pilot program established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall assign the participant a mentor who is an employee of the Department who is—</text><subparagraph id="HD54466D7302040B08A739A0ED94C899A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, a managerial employee; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B0113A63745496FBD4FF520C04EA31A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>outside the participant's chain of command.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H515DDE44465F49FA8C95B86934C025A9" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assignments to Office of General Counsel</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall provide each participant in the pilot program at least one assignment within the Office of General Counsel of the Department that includes full-time legal responsibilities in order to further the professional development of the participant. Such assignment shall be for a period of not less than 120 days and not more than 180 days, or longer at the discretion of the Secretary. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77BE18449C7F4ED0907AEDCB21DE77E4" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Other rotational assignments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may provide a participant in the pilot program one or more other short-term rotational assignments. Such an assignment shall be for a period of not less than 30 days and not more than 180 days, at the discretion of the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H415F915A06E24EE79B234BA9DE404A24" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Periodic reports</header><paragraph id="HF8AA5A9FE4604CE9B7A5D8468A3D4762" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Reports required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than three years after the date on which the Secretary first accepts a participant into the competitive honors program carried out under the pilot program, and not less frequently than once every three years thereafter for the duration of the pilot program, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on the findings of the Secretary with respect to the pilot program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FF536D0EF04403CB1E281563A4F1E56" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each report submitted under paragraph (1) shall include the following:</text><subparagraph id="HD3EE401BFC21470B9A82C4E8AE8DA2D5" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The findings of the Secretary with respect to the feasibility and advisability of establishing a permanent competitive honors program within the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC77620EBD78841B29C845A2B1805B26A" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such recommendations as the Secretary may have for legislative or administrative action to improve recruitment and retention of staff at the Department.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H19B10095BECD49A99696A630E7F6BC3B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>4.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Report on improving access to Board of Veterans' Appeals telehearings</header><subsection id="H339832303F4A46869E52DBAEB422C264" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall submit to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Veterans' Affairs of the House of Representatives a report on improving access to hearings before the Board of Veterans’ Appeals held by picture and voice transmission.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBE3F40E0D5BE46C6A6FCAA042F198B51" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required by subsection (a) shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H5CBB3D8BBFD04272B205B185B52E4B79" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations on the feasibility and advisability of reimbursing veterans for expenses incurred for travel from the home of a veteran to the location at which a hearing before the Board of Veterans’ Appeals is held by picture and voice transmission, if the Secretary determines that travel to such location is reasonably necessary for such a hearing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE631F5FE263648839C8BDFCEB42FCF2C" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations on establishment of pilot programs to assess the feasibility and advisability of using other methods that could improve veteran access to hearings before the Board of Veterans’ Appeals held by picture and voice transmission from a veteran’s home.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B366EB9214549B0A0B94B3596CEE446" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such other recommendations to improve access to hearings before the Board of Veterans’ Appeals held by picture and voice transmission as the Secretary may receive from stakeholders.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

