<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H47A8459AE55E425FBADACABF71845779" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6299 IH: COOL Online Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-08</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6299</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231108">November 8, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require origin and location disclosure for new products of foreign origin offered for sale on the internet.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFE2A951DFA47472CBBB16D3F64F01DD8" style="OLC"><section id="HDBC86C2F91C64ACA84834CCD2D21F67E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>COOL Online Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6FEF247B87FC4D8CA4B12ED25A68F9F6" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Mandatory origin disclosure for new products of Foreign origin offered for sale on the internet</header><subsection id="HE7C78C4988D44463844394A6573E34BA" changed="not-changed"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Mandatory disclosure</header><paragraph changed="not-changed" id="HB04705BC3D0640F895D64B5E58CE43D2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><subparagraph id="HE157137A814F4C519F52B45547E47EDD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Disclosure</header><text>Subject to the succeeding provisions of this paragraph, it shall be unlawful for an online store, an online marketplace, or a seller to introduce, sell, or offer for sale on an internet website a product that is marked or required to be marked under section 304 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1304">19 U.S.C. 1304</external-xref>) unless the country of origin is disclosed in a conspicuous manner on the online store or online marketplace’s online description of the product and in a manner consistent with the regulations prescribed under such section 304 at the time of the product’s importation, or anticipated importation, into the customs territory of the United States. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph changed="not-changed" commented="no" id="H5FB81A3CDB7B46088A347596168E63FA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><clause id="HE8B39F8EF69D4CCA971F08DFCA61AE14"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Agricultural products</header><text>The disclosure requirements under subparagraph (A) shall not apply to—</text><subclause id="HC74AAC3D70B547AEB6172769152F9A5E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a covered commodity (as defined in section 281 of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1638">7 U.S.C. 1638</external-xref>));</text></subclause><subclause id="HA6DC61AC2238428FBB0D87BAC36A22B7"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a meat or meat food product subject to inspection under the Federal Meat Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/601">21 U.S.C. 601 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></subclause><subclause id="H9549F7211DB74AD19545DBE81D70D885"><enum>(III)</enum><text>a poultry or poultry product subject to inspection under the Poultry Products Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/451">21 U.S.C. 451 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subclause><subclause id="H566C3BF7DC5343C883F6EF187DD26707" commented="no"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>an egg product subject to regulation under the Egg Products Inspection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/1031">21 U.S.C. 1031 et seq.</external-xref>). </text></subclause></clause><clause changed="not-changed" commented="no" id="H16B6174FB8254D8EA552418A28D57629"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Food and drugs</header><text>The disclosure requirements under subparagraph (A) shall not apply to a food or drug (as those terms are defined in paragraphs (f) and (g), respectively, of section 201 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/321">21 U.S.C. 321</external-xref>)) that is subject to the jurisdiction of the Food and Drug Administration. </text></clause><clause id="H13EE5E4F14F74EDA94DE8EFA7E3B433A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Used or previously owned products</header><text>The disclosure requirements under subparagraph (A) shall not apply to any used or previously owned products sold in interstate commerce. </text></clause><clause id="H1EB477CB8B7A4481819ED008A643A2C0"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Small seller</header><text>The disclosure requirements under subparagraph (A) shall not apply to goods listed by a small seller. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H471000B8A3DB42D5BA2B69765D9A706C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Limitation of liability</header><clause id="HB264BC4BDA1E45B0AD77A310847CA3C2"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Online store</header><text>An online store is not in violation of the requirements under subparagraph (A) if the online store provided its third-party manufacturer, distributor, supplier, or private labeler with—</text><subclause id="HC1E3491F27414880922DEF03E26471F3"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a notice of their obligation to provide the country of origin to the store, if applicable; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HCDC162DC44CD4FF78B151B64C486E6AA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the means to list directly, or provide to the online store for listing, the country of origin of the product. </text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0BC29F6671784E129CAF4776324B073C"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Online marketplace</header><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1A463980F0594A599E16296245E29529"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to subclause (II), an online marketplace is not in violation of the requirements under subparagraph (A) if the online marketplace provided its sellers with—</text><item commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9EAE06CA5A2F4CCF804DD6AF848326FE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a notice of the seller's obligation to provide country of origin information when selling a product; and</text></item><item id="HE45F7000CF0E4A4CA92A816D8DE45559"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>the means to list the country of origin in the product’s description.</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H1BB042AD2B6A43ACB78B7DB55C3AFDF4" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Subclause (I) shall not apply when the online marketplace is selling the product itself, rather than only facilitating a sale by a seller and relying on a seller for that product’s information.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HCD130BB088AC4F7991CCD1A2387437B3"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Seller</header><text>A seller is not in violation of the requirements under subparagraph (A) if the online marketplace did not provide the seller with—</text><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3F01095FAE52409F9FD5556415EE0756"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the notice described in clause (ii)(I)(aa); or</text></subclause><subclause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0791F8F03AF1497FBDFCAF8D896D2496"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the means to list the county of origin in the product’s description as described in clause (ii)(I)(bb).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B038D56600443BC9A40786AB0F46B1C" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Fungible goods or materials</header><text>For the purposes of subparagraph (A) and in accordance with section 102.12(f) of title 19, Code of Federal Regulations, an online store, an online marketplace, or a seller is in compliance with the disclosure requirements under subparagraph (A) if it lists multiple countries of origin for products that are fungible goods or materials. Products shall be considered to be <quote>fungible goods or materials</quote> if the goods or materials, as the case may be, are interchangeable for commercial purposes and have properties which are essentially identical.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50C8C29586034C11A902DC2C54118512"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Safe harbor</header><text>An online store, an online marketplace, or a seller satisfies the disclosure requirements under subparagraph (A) if the online store, online marketplace, or seller relies on the country of origin representation provided by a third-party manufacturer, importer, distributor, supplier, or private labeler of the product.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph changed="not-changed" id="HDE765DCF253D4C2E8DE7731AC532D74F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certain drug products</header><text>It shall be unlawful for an online store, an online marketplace, or a seller to offer for sale in commerce to consumers on an internet website a drug that is not subject to section 503(b)(1) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/353">21 U.S.C. 353(b)(1)</external-xref>) and that is required to be marked under section 304 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1304">19 U.S.C. 1304</external-xref>) unless the internet website description of the drug indicates in a conspicuous place the name and place of business of the manufacturer, packer, or distributor that is required to appear on the label of the drug in accordance with section 502(b) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/352">21 U.S.C. 352(b)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA00EC5547E6F47EF865BDF07F844714E"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Obligation to provide</header><text>A manufacturer, importer, distributor, supplier, or private labeler seeking to have a product introduced, sold, advertised, or offered for sale in commerce shall provide the marking information required by section 304 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1304">19 U.S.C. 1304</external-xref>) to the relevant online store, an online marketplace, or a seller who wishes to offer the product for sale on an internet website.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H95AD2579136648359899E68952221979" changed="not-changed"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Enforcement by the Commission</header><paragraph id="H6AE14EE5B77F4C528720906C2F404C12" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Unfair or deceptive acts or practices</header><text>A violation of subsection (a) or a regulation promulgated thereunder shall be treated as a violation of a rule defining an unfair or deceptive act or practice under section 18(a)(1)(B) of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/57a">15 U.S.C. 57a(a)(1)(B)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF63528E1E1504741B60558DDE3E693FB" changed="not-changed"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Powers of the Commission</header><subparagraph id="H4ACB1D58A2364D43B7FB2909B4346295" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission shall enforce this section in the same manner, by the same means, and with the same jurisdiction, powers, and duties as though all applicable terms and provisions of the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) were incorporated into and made a part of this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7B2556497F4D465C8518FA1B2396F711" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Privileges and immunities</header><text>Any person that violates subsection (a) shall be subject to the penalties and entitled to the privileges and immunities provided in the Federal Trade Commission Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/41">15 U.S.C. 41 et seq.</external-xref>) as though all applicable terms and provisions of that Act were incorporated and made part of this section.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5C1DCBE1E3E49E8A0510C992DEAE4EC" changed="not-changed"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Authority preserved</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to limit the authority of the Commission under any other provision of law.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB8B1680EE9F04DA386AFF4512B59971A" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0857305EE673425183D8F83C566304E7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall promulgate in accordance with section 553 of title 5, United States Code, such rules as may be necessary to carry out this section. </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6B11A913D6F441EF8C783B5EE5BA8370"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In promulgating any regulations under clause (i), the Commission shall consult with U.S. Customs and Border Protection.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H45888CC4C24C475BA7319746093E4ACF" changed="not-changed"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Interagency agreement</header><text>Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Commission, the Commissioner for U.S. Customs and Border Protection, the Commissioner of Food and Drugs, the United States Trade Representative, and the Secretary of Agriculture shall— </text><subparagraph id="HDE6259D9C5ED41B9A412AB228559C04E" changed="not-changed"><enum>(A)</enum><text>enter into a Memorandum of Understanding or other appropriate agreement for the purpose of providing consistent implementation of this section; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5A1F322D1A834059B5BA5FD100111292" changed="not-changed"><enum>(B)</enum><text>publish such Memorandum of Understanding or other agreement in order to provide public guidance. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H974C78ACE2EC4530A3BC6865E2B9C9BA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority preserved</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4883CBDCB58C448BB491969AE0DCEA6A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">limit the authority of the Department of Agriculture, the Food and Drug Administration, or U.S. Customs and Border Protection under any other provision of law; or </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0A07E605184541E8B1E6C1F5B3A06915"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">require the Commission to interpret, modify, or enforce regulations promulgated by such agencies unless as provided by the Memorandum of Understanding or other agreement entered into under subsection (b)(3)(A).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H69B382D7F20449E7BEFDE7ED296EC112"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>This section shall take effect 1 year after the date of the publication of the Memorandum of Understanding or other agreement under subsection (b)(3)(B).</text></subsection><subsection id="H1796473E2C0E48AE8D191D93F7764B42"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed to require an online store, an online marketplace, or a seller to include a description of a product introduced, sold, or offered for sale in interstate commerce other than a notice of the country of origin as required by subsection (a). </text></subsection><subsection id="HE6ED7B8E49564FC6AE18ABACF7FE81E0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H9B02E8108C5643708795219101124226" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" changed="not-changed"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commission</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Commission</term> means the Federal Trade Commission. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B89BDDD9A674ECC92692314C05B1CEA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Online marketplace</header><text>The term <term>online marketplace</term> has the meaning given such term in section 301(f) of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45f">15 U.S.C. 45f(f)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCCC4818068EA4A7BB0DE7C0E45A297E1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Online store</header><text>The term <term>online store</term> means a person or entity that operates a consumer-directed, electronically based or accessed website that sells products to consumers over the internet for itself or on behalf of third-party sellers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEA3A5287D674F4FA0D0CDE37745DA0B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Product</header><text>The term <term>product</term> has the meaning given the term <quote>article of foreign origin</quote> in section 304 of the Tariff Act of 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/1304">19 U.S.C. 1304</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BC35316F3A94F5999FDDF7C47A8D246" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Seller</header><text>The term <term>seller</term> has the meaning given such term in section 301(f) of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2023 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/45f">15 U.S.C. 45f(f)</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9521C17B708C4F6F966F3E9EFEA2A729"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Small seller</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H52353E2803CD46DABA7D82F959CA1F96"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>small seller</term> means a seller on an online marketplace that, in any consecutive 12-month period during the previous 24 months, has—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H76F169CB6A414E1A9CB69EC6A440BCBA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">annual sales of less than an aggregate total of $20,000 in gross revenues; and </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HAC1ED2AD239541A6BACAAE38BFD75258"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">fewer than 200 discrete sales or transactions (excluding sales of used or previously owned products).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7474711BEF7A41BEA03DB8C69BCCBBEF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>For the purposes of calculating the number of discrete sales or transactions or the aggregate gross revenues under subparagraph (A), a seller shall only be required to count sales or transactions made through the online marketplace and for which payment was processed by the online marketplace, either directly of through its payment processor. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H50DAF5773308430787E69A0C32A7DB23" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Used or previously owned product</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>used or previously owned product</term> means a product that was previously sold or offered for sale in interstate commerce.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8EE4AF84207D433CB6CE5A078A503C7E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Country of origin labeling for cooked kingcrab and tanner crab and cooked and canned salmon</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 281(7)(B) of the Agricultural Marketing Act of 1946 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1638">7 U.S.C. 1638(7)(B)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H4EB31E453AA54D2AAACB76A01659689D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the period at the end and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7E5040C7B9D43208A981D9803137FB9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>includes a fillet</quote> and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H16694542D6454D119D82DD2CE6D4ACA2" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text>includes—</text><clause id="HC4829CDF6A624197B6D86051A30DA875"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a fillet</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EFBA155AE1148A4A297966EFE0F1888"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HC5CC6FDC64ED401C81166D5A66628AA7" style="OLC"><clause id="H22BE74A5A4734954B149EE5D14D8C451"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>whole cooked king crab and tanner crab and cooked king crab and tanner crab sections; and</text></clause><clause id="H5EFF38EE905E408C8A9516D785A0532B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>cooked and canned salmon.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

