<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEB1A9A6FE026430A81A3CF0489A9DD4E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2692 IH: Addressing Social Isolation and Loneliness in Older Adults Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2692</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230418">April 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XX of the Social Security Act to provide grants and training to support area agencies on aging or other community-based organizations to address social isolation among vulnerable older adults and adults with disabilities.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HBEB0219AB6974D9DBDCB5F618A77C8BD" style="OLC"><section id="HB2BFEBC919EC4AB5BAA0288942C250E7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Addressing Social Isolation and Loneliness in Older Adults Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>Addressing SILO Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA8686D9312104819B271A4EF54834A76" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>2.</enum><header>Incentives for developing and sustaining structural competency in providing health and human services</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Part II of subtitle B of title XX of the Social Security Act (42 U.S.C. 1397m–1397m-5) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H40D710A9558D49589D6751E6728EDCF1" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H06CFD13821E744938CE8E4A2B3461238"><enum>2047.</enum><header>Incentives for developing and sustaining structural competency in providing health and human services</header><subsection id="H8C38576798BA41479EC22251F9379E7D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grants and training To support area agencies on aging or other community-Based organizations To address social isolation among vulnerable older adults and adults with disabilities</header><paragraph id="H594D23201A5E4D5AB30A7B28BA05D1EC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Grants</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall make grants to eligible area agencies on aging or other community-based organizations for the purpose of—</text><subparagraph id="H775F2761FD2E4BA7B5BC16FD80E2E7A1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">conducting outreach to individuals at risk for, or already experiencing, social isolation or loneliness, through established screening tools or other methods identified by the Secretary;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H639FE0F1AC384D849508405D81FC3AAF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing community-based interventions for the purposes of mitigating loneliness or social isolation (including evidence-based programs, as defined by the Secretary, developed with multi-stakeholder input for the purposes of promoting social connection, mitigating social isolation or loneliness, or preventing social isolation or loneliness) among at-risk individuals;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8E4EEA32D0394C11915A13D3DD5E3838"><enum>(C)</enum><text>connecting at-risk individuals with community social and clinical supports; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2F4C1456C1B14EFC84C94FAB37D8EF77"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">evaluating the effect of programs developed and implemented under subparagraphs (B) and (C).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A4C6931C0CF433B8F8957DC68F1AEB5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall establish programs to provide and improve training for area agencies on aging or community-based organizations with respect to addressing and preventing social isolation and loneliness among older adults and adults with disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDE88DA99A94645A4B0DCA53B40E0641C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><text>Not later than 3 years after the date of the enactment of this section and every 3 years thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Congress a written report which assesses the extent to which the programs established under this subsection address social isolation and loneliness among older adults and people with disabilities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC5A7B7955FE478884BDF15CDB046526"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Appropriation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, there are appropriated to the Secretary $62,500,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2027 to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE9D8005648D048DDB3195061925C2860"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall coordinate with resource centers, grant programs, or other funding mechanisms established under section 411(a)(18) of the Older Americans Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3032">42 U.S.C. 3032(a)(18)</external-xref>), section 417(a)(1) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/3032F">42 U.S.C. 3032F(a)(1)</external-xref>), or other programs as determined by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7F4BB7B802E54F4388DE0E1290521C91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H67410EB72C9D4397B6D73C4F1C4C0A69"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Area agency on aging</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>area agency on aging</term> means an area agency on aging designated under section 305 of the Older Americans Act of 1965.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBAE9F707A294160AEE9D2A21D087CBE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Social isolation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>social isolation</term> means objectively being alone, or having few relationships or infrequent social contact.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC09006C544B94A54BC804350947CDB5D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Loneliness</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>loneliness</term> means subjectively feeling alone, or the discrepancy between one’s desired level of social connection and one’s actual level of social connection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B17D39351C94AE49B5DCCE2D2BFD9B8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Social connection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>social connection</term> means the variety of ways one can connect to others socially, through physical, behavioral, social-cognitive, and emotional channels.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBD384468F994063A59DA2129EF21B64"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Community-based organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>community-based organization</term> includes, except as otherwise provided by the Secretary, a nonprofit community-based organization, a consortium of nonprofit community-based organizations, a national nonprofit organization acting as an intermediary for a community-based organization, or a community-based organization that has a fiscal sponsor that allows the organization to function as an organization described in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/501">section 501(c)(3)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 and exempt from taxation under section 501(a) of such Code.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

