<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3BC195EB5C8B44A7B2FC566933E8BD2B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3896 IH: Airport Infrastructure Resilience Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3896</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230607">June 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish an airport infrastructure resilience pilot program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2CAE6ED0DE5F48A4B855CAB4ABCCA546" style="OLC"><section id="H0056623F53E94FD99DC19BD5B298C8DC" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Airport Infrastructure Resilience Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC31B6093A42945E881A951C44418A9EE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Airport infrastructure resilience pilot program</header><subsection id="HEA13FF7B5FC04C66BA229E6C493F8231"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3A67433AA7A1426CA8069C38BAA3226B"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establishment</header><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7F35CBB4C62C444A9DAD87FD51D27242"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall establish a pilot program to provide competitive grants to sponsors of airports to incentivize the planning and design and construction of projects that make improvements to infrastructure that is subject to, or that faces increased long-term future risks with respect to, the following:</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7AC58A68888F4CD887FF6F913836A4B2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Changing conditions, such as sea level rise or permafrost thaw.</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F6F1C554A244942A116631034407DD3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Weather events and natural disasters, such as severe storms, flooding, drought, levee and dam failures, wildfire, rockslides, mudslides, sea level rise, permafrost thaw, extreme weather, including extreme temperature, and earthquakes. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HADC1444CE50847E8879791F361AE1744"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Projects funded under the pilot program under this section may be for new projects as well as for making improvements to existing infrastructure and may include the purchasing of monitoring equipment or services.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF5A9620226CB478F95FC759025AB50FD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In establishing the pilot program under paragraph (1), the Secretary shall—</text><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H80F5FE62150A4A5AB00B0E35884389D0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">engage in a public comment period; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF564E6CB3EDB479F9CF12026B7CC5518"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">consult with—</text><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA313F6352AE64BCFB252C7A405FFC903"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration; </text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H35570388357044DE83424836FBB1926D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency;</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF7D6C14A43254E4AA6145D096B418722"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the Administrator of the National Oceanic Atmospheric Administration; and</text></clause><clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H15FDC2109E3D45338B7694E1814C42B0"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE86B87A7924B4864B55E64EDD5D5B283"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In awarding grants to sponsors under the pilot program under this section, the Secretary shall consider the following with respect to projects funded under the grant:</text><subparagraph id="HD219D6D9419448B2AF4ED96CC6EB4918"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Whether the project is natural infrastructure or nature-based.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA6F400C297048289C9F4DA833836AE9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Whether the project is based on the best available science and engineering standards.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9534F1A216C4629ADA3F8F7C8506F9A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Whether the project will mitigate the airport’s impact on the environment.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HDDAA0CB057DD404CBD519EC116DE0AD3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Other items determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FD67685C9F04151ACF4FFF534662D00"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligibility</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under the pilot program under this section, a sponsor of an airport shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. Such information shall include a description of how the proposed project is projected to benefit and potentially impact both the airport and the surrounding communities regarding changing conditions, weather events, and natural disasters.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8FE082966F6541EF8183054514557367"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Reports to Secretary</header><text>A sponsor of an airport that is awarded a grant under the pilot program under this section shall submit to the Secretary periodic reports on the use of the funds. Such reports shall be submitted at such time, in such form, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H276B7E8347014DFBB866A7D7D38C94A7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Distribution for regional airports</header><text>In conducting the pilot program under this section, the Secretary shall ensure that not less than 15 percent of the funds made available under subsection (e) is used to award grants to sponsors of regional airports. </text></subsection><subsection id="H56C1A933D24D42AFBB456682ADC3070C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Federal share</header><text>The United States Government's share of allowable project costs for a project carried out with a grant under the pilot program shall be the United States Government's share of allowable project costs specified under section 47109 of title 49, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5917DE228ED64FEFB3A3DE14667A9A5F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The construction work for a project funded with grant under the pilot program shall be subject to the requirements under section 47112 of title 49, United States Code. </text></subsection><subsection id="HDF913F6BBEDB46E48E3F26A0656CC4BF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0AB01B0DBC7743DDA89CFBB524C1C109"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the Secretary first awards a grant under the pilot program under this section, and annually thereafter for as long as the Secretary is conducting the pilot program under this section, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives a report that evaluates the pilot program established under this section. Each such report shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HB0C951E3514E4DA58FCFC41440209E4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a description of each project funded under the program, including the changing condition or weather event or natural disasters the project is addressing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0BAB0701AD642EE840F8240FCFCFC88"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of the applications under the program;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC1A6782B0FD44CDEAA229021A148C307"><enum>(C)</enum><text>recommendations to improve the administration of the program, including whether assistance from additional or fewer agencies to carry out the program is appropriate;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4D5BDB52737C4FC28CC0E9A2910106AF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a description of the period required to disburse grant funds to sponsors based on applicable Federal coordination requirements; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H982D338A71814DCF8AB929FD1C69FC3B"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a description of the facilities that repeatedly require repair or reconstruction due to weather events and natural disasters (as described in subsection (a)); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA29B2EA6C95341AA8D779BB1D901C2BF"><enum>(F)</enum><text>other items determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H04C27D5EA47F4C05BB473D55DEEC8365"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary shall post each report submitted under paragraph (1) on the public internet website of the Department of Transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0D19E64E39D847C59C76213E136FCA36"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Funding</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary $300,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2024 through 2028 to carry out this section. Such sums shall remain available until expended. </text></subsection><subsection id="H9FB141A39E2B4E6784BAC5E7FDC4D4AA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H423D3CCCF5F34CC88417A1AC0B1B162B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Airport</header><text>The term <term>airport</term> has the meaning given that term in section 40102 of title 49, United States Code. </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC1804D3A32C14D0A833423796DB6275F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Regional airport</header><text>The term <quote>regional airport</quote> means a small hub airport, a nonhub airport, a nonprimary airport, and a reliever airport (as such terms are dined in section 47102 of title 49, United States Code).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F923B836F67438FAE2AE5556C5BA5B2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Transportation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

