<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2AE73F0A5137474182F910C5A070C3CB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3579 IH: Tribal Trust Land Homeownership Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3579</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Bureau of Indian Affairs to process and complete all mortgage packages associated with residential and business mortgages on Indian land by certain deadlines, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEA22B466D6A345BBB27BEF29139B4544" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H69E9964C66FE4868911A380B0293D008"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Tribal Trust Land Homeownership Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6C35A282E80A4327AE567C202DBB1CF9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="HBF38DF553A44430AA846D5598186C0B6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Applicable Bureau office</header><text>The term <term>applicable Bureau office</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="H04A1266AF3164C3083CA9CC070F29392"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a Regional office of the Bureau;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D4A051C3CDA4E699BFC145A43B350CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an Agency office of the Bureau; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1FE73EA3F7B4E98A27BDB0AEDFA95D1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a Land Titles and Records Office of the Bureau.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E51352A7A74496DBD301980F3FAEFEF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Bureau</header><text>The term <term>Bureau</term> means the Bureau of Indian Affairs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5FE7CDCC2154B6A8BD4BE932D5BC686"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text>The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Bureau.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD06EFEA5495C4FE0B6627B49D0FDD821"><enum>(4)</enum><header>First certified title status report</header><text>The term <term>first certified title status report</term> means the title status report needed to verify title status on Indian land.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5DC0229E894346E889583E8698AC1A4E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Indian land</header><text>The term <term>Indian land</term> has the meaning given the term in section 162.003 of title 25, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5174C448C16D42ECB54113276D91332F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Land mortgage</header><text>The term <term>land mortgage</term> means a mortgage obtained by an individual Indian who owns a tract of trust land for the purpose of—</text><subparagraph id="HB38234E81CDE4FEA89CBE0673FC617ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>home acquisition;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21B36577BEFA4A69B5406D76496DEDC8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>home construction;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB3BEFC01DC214971AEA13450D105AC96"><enum>(C)</enum><text>home improvements; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE74335E0CC40470A9052365CBC1D44AF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>economic development. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H40EBC35092B0472F80C04A3E6D6D251F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Leasehold mortgage</header><text>The term <term>leasehold mortgage</term> means a mortgage, deed of trust, or other instrument that pledges the leasehold interest of a lessee as security for a debt or other obligation owed by the lessee to a lender or other mortgagee.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD68111C2A0F46189AE6DB3901B58193"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Mortgage package</header><text>The term <term>mortgage package</term> means a proposed residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, land mortgage, or right-of-way document submitted to an applicable Bureau office under section 3(a)(1).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H71AEB1733EBA49E2A022E483B9257F42"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Relevant Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>relevant Federal agency</term> means any of the following Federal agencies that guarantee or make direct mortgage loans on Indian land:</text><subparagraph id="HB35E6968472D499D868865A0A3273983"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Department of Agriculture.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE38395612B5F49D4BDC28A905667C68E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H808F4E4406574F82ADA3BBE81C291640"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Department of Veterans Affairs. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FEB2296768D415BA95B859D75276E43"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Right-of-way document</header><text>The term <term>right-of-way document</term> has the meaning given the term in section 169.2 of title 25, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FBE690D207E4B5190DCC51B91633500"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Subsequent certified title status report</header><text>The term <term>subsequent certified title status report</term> means the title status report needed to identify any liens against a residential, business, or land lease on Indian land.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HFFC542DC3E43448CB810D0E408251211"><enum>3.</enum><header>Mortgage review and processing</header><subsection id="H49E36A484DE247A2ACDC78A170E5B5E2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Review and processing deadlines</header><paragraph id="H393E0594B95B452DAC74AF3EFA6D20B1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As soon as practicable after receiving a proposed residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, land mortgage, or right-of-way document, the applicable Bureau office shall notify the lender that the proposed residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, or right-of-way document has been received.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H66DA75C9B54F4D15981F54819577650C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Preliminary review</header><subparagraph id="H29FE5BFDB6934C1C829A70F2DB6E886E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 10 calendar days after receipt of a proposed residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, land mortgage, or right-of-way document, the applicable Bureau office shall conduct and complete a preliminary review of the residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, land mortgage, or right-of-way document to verify that all required documents are included.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC291F58516B441DD8022302376A3DC14"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Incomplete documents</header><text>As soon as practicable, but not more than 2 calendar days, after finding that any required documents are missing under subparagraph (A), the applicable Bureau office shall notify the lender of the missing documents.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H619451895E134CF8A488AD70C29740BB"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Approval or disapproval</header><subparagraph id="HB4ED1AC04AFD4F7D8581C368934B7CFC"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Leasehold mortgages</header><text>Not later than 20 calendar days after receipt of a complete executed residential leasehold mortgage or business leasehold mortgage, proof of required consents, and other required documentation, the applicable Bureau office shall approve or disapprove the residential leasehold mortgage or business leasehold mortgage.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49D0398AF45C40B68C950C003139A79C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Right-of-way documents</header><text>Not later than 30 calendar days after receipt of a complete executed right-of-way document, proof of required consents, and other required documentation, the applicable Bureau office shall approve or disapprove the right-of-way document.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H131DF562B72B4BA1AD5A30FA4871A846" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Land Mortgages</header><text>Not later than 30 calendar days after receipt of a complete executed land mortgage, proof of required consents, and other required documentation, the applicable Bureau office shall approve or disapprove the land mortgage.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H724A8ED5E8F946B6A774B4DEBD63B98F"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The determination of whether to approve or disapprove a residential leasehold mortgage or business leasehold mortgage under subparagraph (A), a right-of-way document under subparagraph (B), or a land mortgage under subparagraph (C)—</text><clause id="H7240A4FDF15141B08D5A7D87AFA3556D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be in writing; and</text></clause><clause id="HA021E5083AC641B795BFC4B754433406"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of a determination to disapprove a residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, right-of-way document, or land mortgage shall, state the basis for the determination.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7AAE66EE04A446D90E6251E5FF99BFE"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Application</header><text>This paragraph shall not apply to a residential leasehold mortgage or business leasehold mortgage with respect to Indian land in cases in which the applicant for the residential leasehold mortgage or business leasehold mortgage is an Indian tribe (as defined in subsection (d) of the first section of the Act of 1955 (69 Stat. 539, chapter 615; 126 Stat. 1150; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/415">25 U.S.C. 415(d)</external-xref>)) that has been approved for leasing under subsection (h) of that section (69 Stat. 539, chapter 615; 126 Stat. 1151; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/415">25 U.S.C. 415(h)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8116722D9787463FB5C3DDAD70ACA9AB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Certified title status reports</header><subparagraph id="HBA276F9AB8F34F678F276A5F17345949"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Completion of reports</header><clause id="H121ADD8BB9384DF4940FB5893D2736A3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 10 calendar days after the applicable Bureau office approves a residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, land mortgage, or right-of-way document under paragraph (3), the applicable Bureau office shall complete the processing of, as applicable—</text><subclause id="HF323E9E6A3D843A1B132B4690CC7DE52"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a first certified title status report, if a first certified title status report was not completed prior to the approval of the residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, land mortgage, or right-of-way document; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H91D609E868D44C898DDD1B85B81B11F8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a subsequent certified title status report.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H717E8C41881A45C18B30F6A6F28253FB"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Requests for first certified title status reports</header><text>Notwithstanding clause (i), not later than 14 calendar days after the applicable Bureau office receives a request for a first certified title status report from an applicant for a residential leasehold mortgage, business leasehold mortgage, land mortgage, or right-of-way document under paragraph (1), the applicable Bureau office shall complete the processing of the first certified title status report.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9D638638A64D4582B43281FBB10F8976"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Notice</header><clause id="H4595750331D4473B89F76D84B241FDA3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As soon as practicable after completion of the processing of, as applicable, a first certified title status report or a subsequent certified title status report under subparagraph (A), but by not later than the applicable deadline described in that subparagraph, the applicable Bureau office shall give notice of the completion to the lender. </text></clause><clause id="HEFFD1CB573444FE2956CC9E9E0544BCF"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Form of notice</header><text>The applicable Bureau office shall give notice under clause (i)—</text><subclause id="H4FD744D451B344EE97340231F85777DE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>electronically through secure, encryption software; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H51B41A8BCFC840B0874E8A45FC44C225"><enum>(II)</enum><text>through the United States mail.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H8C576090841D49DF9BA452BD0500387B"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Option to opt out</header><text>The lender may opt out of receiving notice electronically under clause (ii)(I).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H12656AA5C4F64F9FAFBF63A9480A111C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notices</header><paragraph id="H9CF4818DC34243DCA59DF6E08B76156A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If the applicable Bureau office does not complete the review and processing of mortgage packages under subsection (a) (including any corresponding first certified title status report or subsequent certified title status report under paragraph (4) of that subsection) by the applicable deadline described in that subsection, immediately after missing the deadline, the applicable Bureau office shall provide notice of the delay in review and processing to—</text><subparagraph id="HA14460F398E5463695E0DADDF1E1F944"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the party that submitted the mortgage package or requested the first certified title status report; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F7EE2A366024E329FA975B46D5F7DFB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the lender for which the mortgage package (including any corresponding first certified title status report or subsequent certified title status report) is being requested.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC1B5345B6FDE43ABB911C8B6F19659B6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requests for updates</header><text>In addition to providing the notices required under paragraph (1), not later than 2 calendar days after receiving a relevant inquiry with respect to a submitted mortgage package from the party that submitted the mortgage package or the lender for which the mortgage package (including any corresponding first certified title status report or subsequent certified title status report) is being requested or an inquiry with respect to a requested first certified title status report from the party that requested the first certified title status report, the applicable Bureau office shall respond to the inquiry.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1744ADDC7F204A26AD95729A3D2643C3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Delivery of first and subsequent certified title status reports</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, any first certified title status report and any subsequent certified title status report, as applicable, shall be delivered directly to—</text><paragraph id="H5469750B35D5483F8C900120F0B5211C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the lender;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34F9F01361114F318D717D6AD2B42EE1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any local or regional agency office of the Bureau that requests the first certified title status report or subsequent certified title status report;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2090B2410C8146498EA23159F95FA1BD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in the case of a proposed residential leasehold mortgage or land mortgage, the relevant Federal agency that insures or guarantees the loan; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0244503FE7014E1A882C4759C9D0160D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>if requested, any individual or entity described in section 150.303 of title 25, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5E30C92F19604A86A835E4A3E00CBF43"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Access to trust asset and accounting management system</header><text>Beginning on the date of enactment of this Act, the relevant Federal agencies and Indian Tribes shall have read-only access to the Trust Asset and Accounting Management System maintained by the Bureau.</text></subsection><subsection id="H89022D3828084FFCA8004AC1AC7DDA91"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual report</header><paragraph id="HBE268BF1BFBD49218AC275A496B18C7D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than March 1 of each calendar year, the Director shall submit to the Committee on Indian Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives a report describing—</text><subparagraph id="HC74E5E8C1C9343D6AE00B87A695B9C77"><enum>(A)</enum><text>for the most recent calendar year, the number of requests received to complete residential leasehold mortgage packages, business leasehold mortgage packages, land mortgage packages, and right-of-way document packages (including any requests for corresponding first certified title status reports and subsequent certified title status reports), including a detailed description of—</text><clause id="HB0E314A0DB9B4DDE80AA7B90D8BC7A00"><enum>(i)</enum><text>requests that were and were not successfully completed by the applicable deadline described in subsection (a) by each applicable Bureau office; and</text></clause><clause id="H94CF02FD39D446C9B1285ED9CC269A5A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the reasons for each applicable Bureau office not meeting any applicable deadlines; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H06221A4ADCE449558FE807DF1DB0E9C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the length of time needed by each applicable Bureau office during the most recent calendar year to provide the notices required under subsection (b)(1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD12A59E7551F4865813808A936840671"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text>In submitting the report required under paragraph (1), the Director shall maintain the confidentiality of personally identifiable information of the parties involved in requesting the completion of residential leasehold mortgage packages, business leasehold mortgage packages, land mortgage packages, and right-of-way document packages (including any corresponding first certified title status reports and subsequent certified title status reports).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4C388A97F3DA47BEAAD93CEB5F3F0C5D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>GAO study</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit to the Committee on Indian Affairs of the Senate and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives a report that includes—</text><paragraph id="HBED4E48890BB4E6A8428D75DEFC709C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an evaluation of the need for residential leasehold mortgage packages, business leasehold mortgage packages, land mortgage packages, and right-of-way document packages of each Indian Tribe to be digitized for the purpose of streamlining and expediting the completion of mortgage packages for residential mortgages on Indian land (including the corresponding first certified title status reports and subsequent certified title status reports); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8906DB79BFA748F2AC9EB202F1172750"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an estimate of the time and total cost necessary for Indian Tribes to digitize the records described in paragraph (1), in conjunction with assistance in that digitization from the Bureau.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2F57215FBC5F442586DF16B97EE27F1A"><enum>4.</enum><header>Establishment of Realty Ombudsman position</header><subsection id="HAA80FCF01B1142E993AB40430998562B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Director shall establish within the Division of Real Estate Services of the Bureau the position of Realty Ombudsman, who shall report directly to the Secretary of the Interior.</text></subsection><subsection id="H69A171D880EC44D992AE25F27453C9EA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Functions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Realty Ombudsman shall—</text><paragraph id="H1B775E9CC17F45E788C7A9F64F4A8F56"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that the applicable Bureau offices are meeting the mortgage review and processing deadlines established by section 3(a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9B1498B25D584D5BBD8605A89907E2CA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ensure that the applicable Bureau offices comply with the notices required under subsections (a) and (b) of section 3;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD455EF7603874A86B81DEA52DCCA467F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>serve as a liaison to other Federal agencies, including by—</text><subparagraph id="HC3F32A4CF3E94EE390F71B6623440F3E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensuring the Bureau is responsive to all of the inquiries from the relevant Federal agencies; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFBBCDC1C308A448C8445CC4B01063CE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>helping to facilitate communications between the relevant Federal agencies and the Bureau on matters relating to mortgages on Indian land;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8243820B158A46109A60110EDDB613E8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>receive inquiries, questions, and complaints directly from Indian Tribes, members of Indian Tribes, and lenders in regard to executed residential leasehold mortgages, business leasehold mortgages, land mortgages, or right-of-way documents; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF037B79218B341BBA6081CFA01C0E489"><enum>(5)</enum><text>serve as the intermediary between the Indian Tribes, members of Indian Tribes, and lenders and the Bureau in responding to inquiries and questions and resolving complaints. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

