<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H028C44706DA041909C157493A96F0B85" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6821 IH: Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6821</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Food Security Act of 1985 to establish a pilot program that focuses Department of Agriculture conservation funding on reducing the most problematic nutrients in the highest-impact areas, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H55FBF56E602345E69BEE134F287F5005" style="OLC"><section id="H94380EB2AA654827A14D769FB7F82600" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H5ED068D717C044C985AD0B874E0E71BC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text><paragraph id="H897A29F7FFC647B0A1E3CF3A1911A0A4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Great Lakes, the Chesapeake Bay, and other water bodies of national significance are integral to the health and wealth of millions of Americans;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE41E43EC7BB4140A61AF97D34A60D2E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>excessive loading of nutrients in these water bodies leads to eutrophication, harmful algal blooms, and dead zones that threaten human health and adversely impact fish and wildlife resources, tourism, and industry;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7AB246E93F44D45A71481FEB501E365"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Federal Government, State and local governments, non-profit organizations, and private entities have expended billions of dollars to reduce nutrient loading in the Great Lakes, the Chesapeake Bay, and other water bodies of national significance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9A9D72DA53C499F9202CB053FA33B85"><enum>(4)</enum><text>despite the investments described in paragraph (3), harmful algal blooms and dead zones continue to occur in the Great Lakes, the Chesapeake Bay, and other water bodies of national significance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB791A20B978D46D68FA894CE4819FEE2"><enum>(5)</enum><text>phosphorus, particularly dissolved reactive phosphorus, is a primary driver of eutrophication in the Great Lakes, the Chesapeake Bay tributaries, and other water bodies of national significance;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB70A455C98EC4036A19AD9970427079A"><enum>(6)</enum><text>targeted, strategic assistance to producers in agricultural sub-watersheds with high levels of dissolved reactive phosphorus loading has the potential to significantly improve water quality the Great Lakes, the Chesapeake Bay, and other water bodies of national significance; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE767FD9EC71E42F79BE09B941BF5716E"><enum>(7)</enum><text>the Natural Resources Conservation Service of the Department of Agriculture is well positioned to provide the targeted, strategic assistance described in paragraph (6) through its conservation programs.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H70CA1E21D55C4B1D8854AAEB3D64809B"><enum>3.</enum><header>Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Subchapter A of chapter 4 of title XII of the Food Security Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/3839aa">16 U.S.C. 3839aa et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block id="HAF6A4704609946619FEFC76824F06FE6" style="OLC"><section id="H75517A01C5A047F8B9379D31454283C2"><enum>1240H–1.</enum><header>Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program</header><subsection id="HB54CE087DF9C4BAA8192D165D37CD364"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H517EC6CE1C984CA28124B2A408C83E7A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Covered agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered agreement</term> means a contract or agreement under the program or a covered program entered into for purposes of the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program carried out under this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA0C775152765488A93BD7C8AF1E0750F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered program</header><text>The term <term>covered program</term> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="H5F2B455D8BCA4BF38D6C7350EBFCC6D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The agricultural conservation easement program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4881D0C849304642875E43295887D87D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The regional conservation partnership program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE6A6ED1CBBA2453FB2F01F6395DCE765"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The conservation stewardship program, not including the grassland conservation initiative under section 1240L–1.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10DC4639839F4BC8B5EDD6C3B1E1AB69"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The conservation reserve program.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB3B5B9090FE34C49A2444C5A7B7CD11D"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The programs established by the Secretary to carry out the Watershed Protection and Flood Prevention Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1001">16 U.S.C. 1001 et seq.</external-xref>), except for any program established by the Secretary to carry out section 14 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1012">16 U.S.C. 1012</external-xref>) of that Act.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8446AAAE898844179D4EF1421BB1C03D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Eligible activity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible activity</term> means a practice, activity, agreement, easement, or related conservation measure that is available under the statutory authority for the program or a covered program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA12403F1E0754C81898DCC5CFD855D5F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Eligible partner</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible partner</term> means an eligible partner under the regional conservation partnership program established under subtitle I.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8EBF992395F40938793E020346B7014"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Priority watershed</header><text>The term <term>priority watershed</term> means a watershed that is—</text><subparagraph id="H7867CFCC27884135AB8B86F97DC76DC0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>delineated at the hydrologic unit code level 12 in the Watershed Boundary Dataset managed by the United States Geological Survey;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6F119FF4A8894FBE96ADC12AD4AD02C2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>located in an area designated by the Secretary as a critical conservation area under section 1271F; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD6DEA6C561614BDE869A45BFDF17DC1C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>designated by a Federal interagency task force or council, or other appropriate Federal interagency group, as a watershed most in need of phosphorus reduction from agricultural activities to improve water quality in a large body of water of regional, national, or international significance.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFB5318F645CB4A02B89CDABDEA448884"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall carry out a pilot program, to be known as the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program, to maximize reduction of dissolved reactive phosphorus in priority watersheds through the implementation of eligible activities in such watersheds under the program and covered programs in fiscal years 2025 through 2031.</text></subsection><subsection id="H1882558DFA804C6686156B0C82401C5A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Action plans</header><paragraph id="H446ADB44798343AD9AD32B1A9173CE16"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Using funds made available under this subchapter, the Secretary shall select priority watersheds for purposes of the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program and prepare for each priority watershed so selected an action plan to maximize reduction of dissolved reactive phosphorus through implementation of eligible activities in the watershed under the program and covered programs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CB39787E8D1412A8C630A9DC7B618A3"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Elements</header><text>An action plan prepared under paragraph (1) shall include—</text><subparagraph id="HBB3FF47A2F2B4C0F857CFF51D735217B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an appraisal of the extent to which each eligible activity available for implementation in the watershed under the program or a covered program is effective at reducing dissolved reactive phosphorus, based on existing data and analysis;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7F7AE3E518804589B390604541655F49"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identification of target implementation goals for each eligible activity available for implementation in the watershed under the program or a covered program that is determined by the Secretary to be effective at reducing dissolved reactive phosphorus;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H07C8044971754537A0889F3B4CB609A4"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a strategy to monitor and adaptively manage implementation of the action plan, including implementation of applicable eligible activities, that—</text><clause id="HE152C3C189CA4BAEBCE128598338C3B2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>leverages, to the maximum extent practicable, ongoing water quality monitoring activities carried out in the watershed by non-profit organizations, colleges and universities, and Federal, State, and local government agencies; and</text></clause><clause id="H207FF849BCD541868A1020B42A6FFD35"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>provides for the development and validation of integrated, reliable, and easy-to-use models for predicting changes in dissolved reactive phosphorus arising from implementation of such eligible activities; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB44AE51C96C4313A6E6007F2310C48F"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a strategy for enhanced outreach to identify and recruit eligible partners and producers in the watershed to increase adoption of eligible activities determined to be effective by the Secretary under subparagraph (B).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBB44F7EAD6E0466A9BD47766B40BEBC5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Prioritization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prioritize entering into covered agreements to demonstrate—</text><paragraph id="HD604EC27C8234FFBA9561F9485D978DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>non-digester methods to transition from wet manure handling and storage to dry manure handling and storage, including open solar drying or composting of manure onsite, conversion of dairy and livestock operations to pasture-based management, solid separation technologies, vermifiltration, and scrape conversion, provided that such methods do not otherwise result in the discharge or runoff of wastewater with high dissolved phosphorus content into a watershed;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2C1BCD772CAA4DC182E17713E2612991"><enum>(2)</enum><text>methods to reduce dissolved reactive phosphorus inputs to a priority watershed from land characterized by phosphorus—</text><subparagraph id="H530B6195E0984AD7A4FF7B4F15BC9EAD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that has accumulated from prior agricultural land management activities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E8C5D29562B40CEBD33839919FD6FFE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the levels of which exceed agronomic rates; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF5DC9CD5AC4B4B34A4492063F707C847"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">strategies to overcome barriers to implementation of methods to reduce dissolve reactive phosphorus inputs to priority watersheds on vacant and leased land.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H145D704A7FD746F4AB373723663E3053"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Incentive payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any otherwise applicable limitation on payments under the program or a covered program, during the period described in subsection (b), the Secretary is authorized to make payments to producers and eligible partners under covered agreements in accordance with a graduated scale of payment amounts based on measured, quantitative reductions in dissolved reactive phosphorus achieved through the implementation of eligible activities under the covered agreements.</text></subsection><subsection id="H53AD10736BFE46C2BB1B2907FCD50905"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Interpretation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to affect—</text><paragraph id="HB2E8879ECB9E4687B54DE8C405B80112"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the duration authorized for a contract or agreement under the program or a covered program;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4246309E806450CB7C4DEAA687B3566"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any contract or agreement entered into under the program or a covered program prior to the date of enactment of the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Act of 2023, including the process or criteria for renewing or extending such a contract or agreement; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF130B6C2A0294009BA7E5419820E4865"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any requirements relating to the program or a covered program for any other purpose for which the program or covered program is implemented.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDD76A2E552CC4E629731715909ABB983"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Coordination and consistency</header><paragraph id="HAFC9E7FCCF6E4E3AA6C19D350861E138"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program, the Secretary shall coordinate with relevant Federal agencies and State and local governments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD7E3BB1A98C44E5DA3D50F743C3A09E1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Action plans</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that any action plan prepared for a priority watershed under subsection (c) is consistent to the maximum extent practicable with any State water quality management plan that includes the priority watershed.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6C3EB3D67C424739AD21A7043CA5C9B7"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Assistance provided under the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program shall supplement, not supplant, assistance provided to eligible partners or producers in a priority watershed under the program or a covered program for purposes other than the purposes of the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA4B550E64D244E9FA7DB54AE4F1C1662"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>The Secretary shall provide to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and to the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate—</text><paragraph id="HA2DFCD755CD048C1AFA4B32F2185E34A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than January 1, 2027, an interim report on implementation of the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1B7744F7E9B46C299007493125D078E"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than June 1, 2032, a final report on implementation of the Healthy Farms Healthy Watersheds Action Program.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section></legis-body></bill> 

