<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA2BD3BF6355E42049501730E9EF8FD6E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3847 IH: Securing Unhoused Peoples’ Program for Outreach Resources and Transportation For SNAP Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3847</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20230606">June 6, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To improve nutrition assistance for people experiencing homelessness, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H2F7B2634ED30423F91B63F62896F7074" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H66B46E8E55604E84A451E358A211C312" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This bill may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Securing Unhoused Peoples’ Program for Outreach Resources and Transportation For SNAP Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SUPPORT For SNAP Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HA12C3A824C0147969DBC229554F22903"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program to connect people experiencing homelessness with snap resources</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2011">7 U.S.C. 2011 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="H77972EBFADAD418C94F234805FE39237" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HE6D4AC8B4A6D4AE8AC30D05426E410C4"><enum>31.</enum><header>Enrollment and outreach pilot program for people experiencing homelessness</header> 
<subsection id="HE2BF24374FEF45868F71BFB7216A1A86"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H16196F9DA1BA4D0F8E36022D691479F4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text>The term <quote>eligible entity</quote> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H701C9AD7B80C4BE9809605BACABBF341"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a State or local government agency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H79D52C25826848A39C607555B7538A4B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an Indian tribe or Tribal organization;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCF48FEB1484D49538CEAF191BE84A2A1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization, including a public or nonprofit provider of services;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0791B943EB3F493D9DC72AD522C0286B"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a community-based organization;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H92D11C58D0F3440884B2B1C9F4BBF2F7"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a continuum of care;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H29BBF22D0E6F43F59A5D062373BC0DB5"><enum>(F)</enum><text>a community action agency;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCBA2E17918B143C38BFE6A162B545D97"><enum>(G)</enum><text>a public housing agency; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0EA74E2A1A4D4DE69038A8EF2A07FC38"><enum>(H)</enum><text>a consortia of 2 or more entities under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H390CE97ABB2E4B1792DC75F270097EA6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Public housing agency</header><text>The term <quote>public housing agency</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3(b)(6) of the United States Housing Act of 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1437a">42 U.S.C. 1437a(b)(6)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA07ABC4FD5E4470BA1B3F9A2D71D01B7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Community action agency</header><text>The term <quote>community action agency</quote> means an eligible entity (which meets the requirements of paragraph (1) or (2), as appropriate, of section 680(c)) of subtitle B of title VI of the Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1981 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/9901">42 U.S.C. 9901 et seq.</external-xref>) that delivers multiple programs, projects, and services to a variety of low-income individuals and families.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H346986279BEF4640820F5A737BD026AB"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Continuum of care</header><text>The term <quote>continuum of care</quote> means a collaborative applicant established and operating for a geographic area for purposes of the Continuum of Care Program under subtitle C of title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11381">42 U.S.C. 11381 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF4E858276A44B7A90EA44740E8EB349"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Pilot program</header><text>The term <quote>pilot program</quote> means the pilot program established under subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H44F229076BD0499784E76BB2E5B11A7F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the effective date of this section, the Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, shall establish a pilot program, to be known as the <quote>Enrollment and Outreach Pilot Program for People Experience Homelessness</quote>, under which the Secretary shall award grants to eligible entities—</text> <paragraph id="H2EA0083D6827448E8FF31A46E03B9982"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to raise awareness among homeless individuals of the availability, eligibility requirements, application procedures, and benefits of the supplemental nutrition assistance program, including the excess shelter expense deduction and the deduction for homeless households referenced in Section 5(e)(6);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF6BAA10822074088BBE08B2D7C021E1F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to support homeless individuals in enrolling in that program; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9A1F7F504B4748B18DCFE2E6E4303619"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to train outreach workers, caseworkers, and any other appropriate employees in supporting homeless individuals, the requirements of and application for the supplemental nutrition assistance program, and other relevant matter as determined appropriate by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE34978294A9E41809DA10C880D404389"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Priority</header><text>In awarding grants under the pilot program, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that—</text> <paragraph id="HA85CDA6A0FFD401F80230C7A0CF50541"><enum>(1)</enum><text>provide services to homeless individuals;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72F4179609FC47FEA85504FF17632603"><enum>(2)</enum><text>are located in jurisdictions that assume costs are being incurred and do not require documentation in the case record in affirming a standard homeless shelter deduction is being allowed when implementing the standard homeless household deduction under section 5(e)(6);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7CD871492F464F09AD06B4FCD577B16E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>have experience implementing grants under the Continuum of Care program under subtitle C of title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11381">42 U.S.C. 11381 et seq.</external-xref>) or grants under the Emergency Solutions Grant program under subtitle B of title IV of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11371">42 U.S.C. 11371 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H341BD162EF554FE0AB39E9D481913636"><enum>(4)</enum><text>have experience implementing programs administered by the Food and Nutrition Service; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H47A56D48812A41E9A7AC75F6474335E7"><enum>(5)</enum><text>receive, plan to receive, or demonstrate an ability to partner with a program that receives funding under the Continuum of Care program under subtitle C of title IV of the McKinney-Vento Homeless Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11381">42 U.S.C. 11381 et seq.</external-xref>), grants under the Emergency Solutions Grant program under subtitle B of title IV of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/11371">42 U.S.C. 11371 et seq.</external-xref>), or nutrition programs administered by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H85378103C51B47FAA0935616BAA26CA3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligible activities</header><text>An eligible entity receiving a grant under the pilot program shall use the grant to carry out 1 or more of the following activities:</text> <paragraph id="HD85D773DDF0F4F259B8D848B0EC3F51F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Application assistance, including—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H5753207BC9734074B94E8E875AB52A86"><enum>(A)</enum><text>eligibility prescreening;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7849CE3CC97D4886990DF51D661638E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>assistance completing an application for the supplemental nutrition assistance program benefits;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H18D7947C08604B05A4ADEAA13AD315EF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>assistance obtaining application verification documents;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1A295199FEBB4731A1E54E5B2946EDAE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>excess shelter expense deduction and the deduction for homeless households deduction counseling;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H273C37DFA7664F44AC32324541409D2A"><enum>(E)</enum><text>translation of materials and bilingual accommodation; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6BED08D428B442448EA732F4611745E9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>improving State agency applications and screening for the supplemental nutrition assistance program to better capture potential eligibility of homeless individuals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H67152D80E87244FABBB28DC14054F17F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Tailored information dissemination about the supplemental nutrition assistance program, including through—</text> <subparagraph id="H9BB53E5F86914C3282C2AA68D7F382E2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>community-based outreach workshops and events;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFB2CE4B736F343F1B2FB18F4BC8534EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>street outreach activities;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF20BFF9FBED74584B929D4387FF6B098"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a toll-free hotline to provide information about Federal, State, and local food resources;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H44BEA7CE7A5641318714FB2D3AFC2BFB"><enum>(D)</enum><text>informational websites and other social media sites; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H9A5B2E1039874EDEA003029F1BBFB41C"><enum>(E)</enum><text>printed or digital informational content.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2CB2335FF8C14956AF3F843E173AB8A5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Transportation, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H5E40A9BA127E47F283111A92096E9240"><enum>(A)</enum><text>transportation to or from a local office of the supplemental nutrition assistance program; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H8E4CE9BF23B6406D895DDAF4DEF1CA06"><enum>(B)</enum><text>administration of vouchers or similar items for the transportation described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H31ED4A43A7A44D80BB1F47BFD7FBF5C1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Identification, implementation, analysis, and dissemination of replicable and scalable models for increasing enrollment in the supplemental nutrition assistance program among households with homeless individuals.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2BFF99DE31B8476EA86BF001A17D4496"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Training for staff on supplemental nutrition assistance program requirements and best practices for outreach to homeless individuals.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H9C76D61984CB4F6FB106C86B743696B8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grants</header> <paragraph id="HFA63443835664C0293786A156D5F3D9D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Maximum amount</header><text>A grant awarded under the pilot program to an eligible entity for a fiscal year shall be not less than $50,000, but not more than $500,000.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC784FD8DA3694FDD9CCDB84F3B13C8C8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duration</header><text>An eligible entity may be awarded a grant under the pilot program for not more than 5 years.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H2E4F63BF87D24DDEB737D5EF224EDBB8"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the effective date of this section, and annually thereafter for the duration of the pilot program, the Secretary shall submit a report to the Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate regarding the implementation of the pilot program, including—</text> 
<paragraph id="H1ECBFA8BB69D49F59E65EBE10E73C6A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an evaluation of the pilot program;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD04B99C583FB4AF39667576E880808C9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the number of awards made under the program;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCC17A4329EBF4A4E827F277040F3C0E4"><enum>(3)</enum><text>description of projects conducted with funding under the pilot program;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA38ED73EF3F8466B94FE1EEB698BF632"><enum>(4)</enum><text>demographic information of homeless individuals contacted or served with pilot programs funds; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBFC8FBEEEAF4452281E5A7AB72AF5187"><enum>(5)</enum><text>number of homeless individuals served by the supplemental nutrition assistance program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HAF704E6BDFDD4D6C80EA76A9C06EA52E"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Funding</header> <paragraph id="H668FA37CC8B243428AF8412C93EEB165"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authorization</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $12,500,000 for each of the fiscal years 2024 through 2029.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF020F6C3B83B4BDA87E31DC320DCA207"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrative costs</header><text>Of the amounts made available under paragraph (1), not more than 3 percent may be used by the Secretary for administrative costs.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HABE7FC067477476CB6680EF57CE7F616"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Technical assistance</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, shall provide technical assistance and publish best practices to carry out this section and may use no more than 2 percent of the amounts made available under paragraph (1) to do so.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H31271C08EB37485484C03FCE9F54C3C6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Supplement not supplant</header><text>As a condition of receiving funds under this section, an eligible entity shall use funds received under this section only to supplement the level of State or local funds that would, in the absence of the receipt of funds under this section, be available.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

