<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H79733F0DF0C948CA8495FCEE7D64D24E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5234 IH: Risk Management for Derivatives Clearing Organizations Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5234</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230818">August 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001189">Mr. Austin Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act to permit certain non-designated clearinghouses access to a deposit account at a Federal reserve bank, to apply certain risk management standards to non-designated clearinghouses receiving certain services from a Federal reserve bank, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFBEB8D46A6E24614A8257365C289AB44" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H8C15E03416C14CC0B720779CF0C81044" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Risk Management for Derivatives Clearing Organizations Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H26BA11701E514BC5A921A6F5ABB233D3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Access to Federal reserve bank accounts and services</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 806 of the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/5465">12 U.S.C. 5465</external-xref>) is amended—</text> 
<paragraph id="HF52DC748962543A095F6E2B17A834F4B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <subparagraph id="HE9922F4D1ED64D46955BAE531A06246B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>a designated financial market utility and</quote> and inserting <quote>a designated financial market utility, a derivatives clearing organization registered with the Commodity Futures Trading Commission under the Commodity Exchange Act that has been approved to hold such an account by the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, or a clearing agency registered with the Commission under the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 that has been approved to hold such an account by the Commission, and</quote>;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE2BE02D93E594AF7A927659475866DDA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>designated financial market utility that</quote> and inserting <quote>financial market utility that</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HDBDC37A9B0E34E3CB38FDEE33BB2A87F"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting after <quote>by the Board of Governors</quote> the following: <quote>, as well as any applicable rules, orders, standards, or guidelines, including, in particular, liquidity requirements, prescribed by the financial market utility’s primary financial regulatory agency. Access to discount and borrowing privileges may only be provided to a financial market utility in accordance with subsection (b)</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4959D5A0465E494AAED30646ABDDEB40"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c), by striking <quote>designated financial market utility</quote> and inserting <quote>financial market utility</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H34458AFC22EB4A149F93F31CEF7C4E94"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (d), by striking <quote>designated financial market utility</quote> each place such term appears and inserting <quote>financial market utility</quote>.</text></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

