<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0F7DF3624E9A4E2A91CDBDD94AFC5096" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>103 HR 1024 IH: Humane and Existing Alternatives in Research and Testing Sciences Act of 2022</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1024</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C000059">Mr. Calvert</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to ensure that nonanimal methods are prioritized, where applicable and feasible, in proposals for all research to be conducted or supported by the National Institutes of Health, to provide for the establishment of the National Center for Alternatives to Animals in Research and Testing, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4BDB0AFE4A354DE4A6D9E28C1EED9540" style="OLC"><section id="H23E16E30681A41EB9912761C95BA99A9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Humane and Existing Alternatives in Research and Testing Sciences Act of 2022</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HEARTS Act of 2022</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H30D1B7B517C3499BA443C8A7CB0378B4" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text><paragraph id="HA6150CB5E5A44E7EA7A04F4C56DC444E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The National Institutes of Health (NIH) has supported life-saving research that has greatly improved the health and well-being not only of Americans but also of people around the world.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8E84A623F00C4C729A6E584F714D7DE5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Much of this research has relied on animals. It is estimated that between 17,000,000 and 100,000,000 animals are used annually in the United States in research, education, and testing. However, the precise number of animals used in research in the United States is unknown. Such imprecise numbers make it impossible to effectively track and reduce the numbers of animals used.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3437FB39D6F3479FA20B881A8E83DDDD"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the NIH, <quote>approximately 30 percent of promising medications have failed in human clinical trials because they are found to be toxic despite promising pre-clinical studies in animal models. About 60 percent of candidate drugs fail due to lack of efficacy.</quote>. These statistics indicate that new, human-focused biology is needed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1351F8667341436CACD09F182C3D167F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The laboratory use of animals has also long been a matter of public concern because, among other things, there is very little publicly available data provided by the NIH about the number and species of animals used in research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD6294D60FE8241BAB49EFE5438D36B93"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Effective alternatives to animals are becoming available, and their number is growing. Cutting-edge technologies have forged new frontiers in toxicology, biology, and medicine that have produced human-relevant models, including organoid cell cultures, multiphysiological systems, genomics, induced pluripotent adult stem cells, 3D modeling with human cells, molecular imaging, computer models, in silico trials, digital imaging, artificial intelligence, and other innovative methods, all of which have launched a technological revolution in biomedical research. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA3CE21EE978244A8B363BB0D80A0CD19"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Animal Welfare Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/89/544">Public Law 89–544</external-xref>) requires researchers to consider alternatives to animal use for painful procedures and stresses that researchers should not unnecessarily duplicate previous experiments. However, oversight is lacking, and these provisions are not implemented the way that Congress intended. As a result, researchers are not capitalizing on nonanimal models that might more effectively recapitulate human biology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17CF09EE07434DA18E85FF93521FAB06"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A system of active incentives is needed to encourage researchers to develop and utilize humane, cost-effective, and scientifically suitable nonanimal methods based on human biology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17CDCB60C8EF461E9495F8F81D509236"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Further, under the National Institutes of Health Revitalization Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/103/43">Public Law 103–43</external-xref>), the NIH is supposed to outline a plan for reducing the use of animals in research. Section 404C(a)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/283e">42 U.S.C. 283e(a)(1)</external-xref>), as added by section 205 of the National Institutes of Health Revitalization Act of 1993, calls for the NIH to <quote>conduct or support research into… methods of biomedical research and experimentation that do not require the use of animals [and] methods of such research and experimentation that reduce the number of animals used in such research</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC03EF11C787F440AB5DD33C02E0F2666"><enum>(9)</enum><text>A dedicated center that provides resources, funding, and training to encourage researchers to utilize humane, cost-effective, and scientifically suitable nonanimal methods based on human biology will result in more progress toward understanding human diseases and their treatments and cures. It will complete the vision that Congress set out in the National Institutes of Health Revitalization Act of 1993 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/103/43">Public Law 103–43</external-xref>), which has been thwarted because of lack of oversight.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H8D3CE0A73D3E4612AB87202301D3C37E"><enum>3.</enum><header>Animals in research</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 495 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/289d">42 U.S.C. 289d</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H507714CA7E094F4D9AB962D508199A35"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H8C7318F7A4B7453791DB2B06E7DF0544"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)—</text><clause id="H0A236A6B387845559584A7E6369E4796"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the matter preceding subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>paragraph</quote> and inserting <quote>subparagraph</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H29094C45A0744E7EAAF1FA775B02C0A6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (A) and (B) as clauses (i) and (ii), respectively, and moving the margins of such clauses (as so redesignated) two ems to the right;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5071F9105885436DB12FEF8CBDEC535B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating paragraphs (1), (2) (as so amended), and (3) as subparagraphs (A), (B), and (C), respectively, and moving the margins of such subparagraphs (as so redesignated) two ems to the right; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0865B96C06524BC7A9D175D9A3B3D85A"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) (as so redesignated), by striking <quote>shall establish guidelines for the following:</quote> and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="traditional" id="HCF352F12D5CF4A579963A692B3020630" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><text>, with respect to all research conducted or supported by the National Institutes of Health, do the following:</text><paragraph id="H5D61A3E7774C4ABDAA9E2E3A14B8D33C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish and maintain animal care guidelines for the following:</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H227C453E5CBC4E3697A64F4256DAA0BE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="traditional" id="HC8E31D346F754028BE2C43D1163D9482" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H5501347C2D8A49C59E06E69173153E41"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish a system of meaningful incentives to encourage the use of existing humane and scientifically satisfactory nonanimal methods in research proposals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8B08504CD3345E996B65EED797CC08E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensure that, before any research involving the use of animals is approved or performed all scientifically satisfactory nonanimal methods for obtaining the results sought have been fully evaluated.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H517BAEEF52484B25880FFAD010CFCCC0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Ensure that—</text><subparagraph id="H823A97BA73B54F53B78F17C14C2C2A99"><enum>(A)</enum><text>research proposals are reviewed by at least one person who has expertise in nonanimal research methods; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H86AEBC1A3662474EAB0283B7296AA0E4"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">reviewers of the research proposals have access to a reference librarian with expertise in evaluating the adequacy of the searches for nonanimal methods described in the research proposals.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F40079FB065425A995969CAB7461183"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Establish and maintain research proposal guidelines for conducting thorough searches for nonanimal alternatives to the use of animals for biomedical and behavioral research.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9F15C1951B5442468A1EE943D761B972"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c)(1)—</text><subparagraph id="H085453524EBA42508B8D3891D6941508"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F77F21574614102BFAF1906749BCF65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="traditional" id="H1D9DC19E70FB42678FF59641C00B1412" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H43D954D01BA94F798BFE4D92939CAD89"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a statement of assurance that a scientifically satisfactory nonanimal method of obtaining the result sought is not available; and </text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="HC237DC5888E74259860766B5C1219501"><enum>4.</enum><header>National Center for Alternatives to Animals in Research and Testing</header><subsection id="H926FF33041AB4031A443FCB3E07F4F07"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Addition to list of institutes and centers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401 of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/281">42 U.S.C. 281</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HCFDB07E08CFB4A95AA54ADA06328FEC1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (25) as paragraph (26); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H77EC8635352E488799524E78DF1B57E4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (24) the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H250F46511D674F84947433EEED86AC67" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H8DE1672A825B4824AFC0AA90CF0CFC0B"><enum>(25)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The National Center for Alternatives to Animals in Research and Testing.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA0CAD5B98EFC4D86A763C4893DE6A17C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming change to number of institutes and centers</header><text>Section 401(d)(1) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/281">42 U.S.C. 281(d)(1)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>27</quote> and inserting <quote>28</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H405FE594B85946348D7B6C5B75D31059"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Establishment; duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part E of title IV of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/287">42 U.S.C. 287 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by inserting after subpart 5 of such part E (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/287c-21">42 U.S.C. 287c–21</external-xref>) the following new subpart:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H91A3D682DAE24AEDAFD9C6FE0231B141" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subpart id="HE4C427A6982D40DF88A8DA718FF15B7E"><enum>6</enum><header>National Center for Alternatives to Animals in Research and Testing</header><section id="HEA0A8BADF70042D999FEAF046B00B644"><enum>485E.</enum><header>Establishment; duties</header><subsection id="H1E8045179837485185B6ADBC661AFF89"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Humane and Existing Alternatives in Research and Testing Sciences Act of 2022,</short-title> the Secretary shall establish a National Center for Alternatives to Animals in Research and Testing (in this subpart referred to as the <quote>National Center</quote>) within the National Institutes of Health. The Center shall be headed by a director, who shall be appointed by the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5FC00DEF5BAE4343B57EC5E6DAE031A3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The general purpose of the National Center shall be—</text><paragraph id="H2DDB8144E02C47619ADB6D9C5A675F2F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>developing, promoting, and funding alternatives to animal research and testing; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC678B21FD0DF49CDA914FF2E8A914C7B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>developing a plan for reducing the number of animals used in federally funded research and testing.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H835AF46DB55746689970161E0CF8DB80"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Director of the National Center shall—</text><paragraph id="HCE35D16FC3CD43BCB06C0A42A4AD4780"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide assistance (including funding) to federally funded researchers to incentivize the development and qualification of nonanimal methods, such as advanced cell cultures or technology such as 3D organoids, microphysiological systems, induced pluripotent adult stem cell models, in silico modeling, advanced imaging systems, artificial intelligence, and other innovative methods;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE0F26BABE12647919B2597D04B1FDBBF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">train and inform scientists about the methods developed pursuant to paragraph (1);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29A4F8A7F6374C96A81E9D06F629BCE3"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish collaborations among research institutions so that scientists who lack resources (such as bioengineering and advanced bio-imaging equipment) can develop and use methods developed pursuant to paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4EB565454EA24A2EB67F8D08031862D2"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collect information regarding the numbers of animals used in federally funded research and testing, and make such information available to the public in a timely manner. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></subpart><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H149BDE7030734D9B9A87B27D629B0A6A"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reporting by federally funded research entities on numbers of animals used in research and testing</header><subsection id="HF81DF7D8EB7D4385BB5B5A1A43C59EE6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each covered reporting entity shall do the following:</text><paragraph id="H209CD056104445B9AE1B23448029981F"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, report to the National Center for Alternatives to Animals in Research and Testing and make publicly available—</text><subparagraph id="H366703D6862B4B3EAAE70A4808E2E1B7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the number of animals used by the covered reporting entity in federally funded research and testing at facilities of the covered reporting entity, disaggregated by species; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC7A7BCC6111C411DB3EAFA8D815230A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the total number of such animals that were bred or acquired by the covered reporting entity for research or testing purposes, disaggregated by species.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2078C37ECD474DC3A42706E015FF0401"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Every 2 years thereafter—</text><subparagraph id="H12B8BA9B32A34CCBB0311D7348FF9645"><enum>(A)</enum><text>update the latest report of the covered reporting entity under this section and make publicly available such updated report to measure the progress of the covered reporting entity in reducing the number of animals used in federally funded research and testing; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H19086912A3F94580984C60DB4D82DF0B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop and submit to the National Center for Alternatives to Animals in Research and Testing and make publicly available a plan for reducing the numbers described in subparagraphs (A) and (B) of paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H52D072FB37FD4257AAFD04AA59C4FDF7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Standardized process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director of the National Center for Alternatives to Animals in Research and Testing shall establish a standardized process for submitting and updating reports and plans under subsection (a), including for making such reports and plans publicly available.</text></subsection><subsection id="HF758405E336945D493949AD2C29611C3"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HAFDB25555BFA4CA0B9DF90FD513CD605"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Animal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>animal</term> means any live, nonhuman vertebrate animal or cephalopod used or intended for use in research, research training, experimentation, or biological testing, or for related purposes.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H149DC20177144F118B82C4CEE6A58029"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered reporting entity</header><text>The term <term>covered reporting entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HC28104BACBDC4449BA71267B26AF19E1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any entity that—</text><clause id="HDFF67798B3254F94A989B55FB866CCF5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>receives Federal funds for research or testing; and</text></clause><clause id="H53D7DD2BD7E445C3A57298965BB26278"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>uses animals in research and testing; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H20F8253839E44B76A396E867BE46E883"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any Federal department or agency that uses animals in research or testing.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

