<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H32F9A40D76C143E585EBCB3AF00DEA4F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3983 IH: Drone Safety and Efficiency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3983</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230609">June 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001221">Mr. Molinaro</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000828">Mr. Williams of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to adopt a performance- and risk-based approach in reviewing requests for certain certificates of waiver, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8338DF5261314F4AAC7D3F4980E5251B" style="OLC"><section id="HE93590EE4E104D62B6C2B59CC64883EF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Drone Safety and Efficiency Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H77C9F8CD640642FFA2A92EC7F12A50EC" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>14 CFR part 107 waiver improvements</header><subsection id="H3875874AAD6445AFB7860C2903B668FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall adopt a performance- and risk-based approach in reviewing requests for certificates of waiver under section 107.200 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE4C881BD46524AD299D6155DD8BB658F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Standardization of waiver application</header><paragraph id="H661684A67B294DCDA3BC5179FC93650F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Administrator shall improve the the process established to submit requests for certificates of waiver described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2AB5985EBE14531A20F294F02A6B663"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Format</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Administrator may not require the use of open-ended descriptive prompts that are required to be filled out by an applicant, except to provide applicants the ability to provide the Administration with information for an unusual or irregular operation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H388D0B1C82FE4EC380B9BE9C8205360A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Data</header><subparagraph id="H1F579B4AFB7A484B96A27D486E997B30"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Administrator shall leverage data gathered from previous requests for certificates of waivers.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68BB2A792B214055BBA0809FE9240CF5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Considerations</header><text>In carrying out subparagraph (A), the Administrator shall safely use—</text><clause id="HE0408250E68B497D99B696F75AC97914"><enum>(i)</enum><text>big data analytics; and</text></clause><clause id="HFAE5D9847AA348428342BDF1A48A2F40"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>machine learning. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBF11957ABCD84BE69BE6242CDC08AABD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consideration of property ownership interest</header><paragraph id="H48155B45B33B4197A8A02F6B46B635BF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In determining whether to issue a certificate of waiver under section 107.200 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, the Administrator shall—</text><subparagraph id="H094EAEA3BE5449C1970A4DDAD286D319"><enum>(A)</enum><text>consider whether the waiver applicant has control over access to all real property on the ground within the area of operation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H935D53B5384E4F7F8D98916E366F738B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>recognize and account for the safety enhancements of such controlled access.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H044E1D573C8149D18F910EC8487D3D6F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to direct the Administrator to consider the lack of control over access to all real property on the ground within an area of operation, or a lack of property interest in such area of operation, as negatively affecting the safety of the operation intended to be conducted under such certificate of waiver.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0E0184B813E9490E85DD80DFE56F3B78"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Public availability of waivers</header><paragraph id="H6AD648CE4A4C483698E5512CFBC1D5BB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall publish all certificates of waiver issued under section 107.200 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, on the website of the Administration, including, with respect to each issued certificate of waiver—</text><subparagraph id="H9AA5D6342ED74B358F7271C043133A16"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the terms, conditions, and limitations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA9146D4E77EC48829493F9095802D5EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the class of airspace and any restrictions related to operating near airports or heliports.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3BBE4AF91F245DCBCE0A42CE0809FBB"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Publication</header><text>In carrying out paragraph (1), the Administrator shall ensure that published information is made available in a manner that prevents inappropriate disclosure of proprietary information.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB4E86CF0804A460D951085B134146BF3"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Precedential use of previously approved waivers</header><paragraph id="HBA026047E78448C1BA37B3D798D6F2E4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Waiver approval precedent</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (3), if the Administrator determines, using criteria for a particular waiver, that an application for a certificate of waiver issued under section 107.200 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, is substantially similar (or is comprised of elements that are substantially similar) to an application for a certificate of waiver that the Administrator has previously approved, the Administrator may streamline, as appropriate, the approval of applications with substantially similar conditions and limitations as a previously approved application.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4BED1EBA1A94D019A4A0D1AD48C7A85"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in paragraph (1) shall be construed to preclude an applicant for a certificate of waiver from applying to modify a condition, or remove a limitation of, such certificate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H31C1698A6D0A46F28F10DF0AD7B3875D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Modification of waivers</header><paragraph id="H27DAAAE619A14C63927B774BE5028560"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Administrator shall establish an expedited review process for a request to modify or renew certificates of waiver previously issued under section 107.200 of title 14, Code of Federal Regulations, as appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H070B394DB77B404EB37C9BFD14C744A9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of review process</header><text>The review process established under paragraph (1) shall be used to review certificates of waiver that cover operations that are substantially similar in all material facts to operations covered under a subsequently issued certificate of waiver.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

