<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H24D4D2BDA6534F7FBDDBD820811A6489" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4729 IH: Taiwan Tax Agreement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4729</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230719">July 19, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001282">Mr. Barr</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001114">Mr. Curtis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To authorize negotiation and conclusion and to provide for congressional consideration of a tax agreement between the American Institute in Taiwan (AIT) and the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office (TECRO).</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H3FCB3E12CF7C47E7B372AC0D71A92266" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9295D0B0C1684E7EB8DB1EC4C1BEE326" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Taiwan Tax Agreement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEA749755262B4D148C482D49089D2FD6"><enum>2.</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> Congress makes the following findings:</text> 
<paragraph id="H54DA5ECF7EF9447782015834E1754A30"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The United States has entered into tax treaties covering 65 jurisdictions, which facilitate economic activity, strengthen bilateral cooperation, and benefit United States businesses and other United States taxpayers.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5AFE79D705D34008A4B3EE7081FA5957"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Taiwan is a one of the largest trading partners of the United States and one of the world’s largest economies, and further bolstering economic ties between the United States and Taiwan remains critical, especially given Taiwan’s strategic importance and the increasing threat posed by the People’s Republic of China.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H095DB5837D194F819E38E0460D2D5E18"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A tax agreement with Taiwan would play a key role in facilitating and promoting increased bilateral investment and trade between the United States and Taiwan, fortifying the relationship between the two more generally, and encouraging other nations to increase their economic linkages to Taiwan.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H22C8D7486EBD454FB843DEF6767A1D62"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authorization to negotiate and conclude</header> <subsection id="H0D3FC9F12F5E4D87927C967E03470076"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President is authorized to negotiate and enter into a tax agreement relative to Taiwan through the American Institute in Taiwan (AIT) (hereinafter the <quote>Agreement</quote>).</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0990D04347D345F383F281B2F0236211"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements of agreement</header><text>The Agreement authorized to be negotiated and concluded under this section shall conform with the provisions customarily contained in United States bilateral income tax conventions, as exemplified by the 2016 United States Model Income Tax Convention, and shall include the following elements:</text> <paragraph id="H13701E4ACD4F405EAA8D5FF6EE4BD864"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Application to tax residents of the United States, Taiwan, or both, exclusive of enterprises headquartered in the People’s Republic of China or in third states that do not have a comprehensive income tax treaty with the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCBF9E50A8DE149E8A5992BFD0D9533C2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Relief from double taxation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4492A0D24DF1440ABD5119DCAB4EAB54"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Measures aimed at limiting the risk of tax evasion or avoidance.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9FC34E9394134311A8B62492A50925AD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Entry into force conditioned upon confirmation by the President of approval by the United States Congress, as described in section 5, and relevant authority in Taiwan and necessary steps taken to enable implementation.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H95BC0981A01246EEBFB92F57DB6D410D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Agreement authorized to be negotiated and concluded under this section may not include elements outside the scope of the 2016 United States Model Income Tax Convention.</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H923BD78FD8E3487C805419C04341B8A1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Consultation</header> 
<subsection id="H3D28E15DBF8D4BCCBAC1FB1EAA080253"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Notification upon commencement of negotiations</header><text>The President shall provide written notification to the appropriate congressional committees of the commencement of negotiations between AIT and TECRO on the Agreement at least 15 calendar days before such commencement.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC5EED136A13B42139549F33F179F685A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Briefings</header><text>Not later than 90 days after commencement of negotiations on the Agreement, and every 180 days thereafter until conclusion of the Agreement, the President shall provide a briefing to the appropriate congressional committees providing an update on the status of negotiations, including a description of elements under negotiation.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HA7A44AFF6AD24EA293682069CE36FD4F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Consultations during negotiations</header><text>In the course of negotiations conducted under the authorities of this Act, the Secretary of the Treasury, in coordination with the Secretary of State, shall—</text> <paragraph id="H4518B21038DC4CE4872A2D74ABDC3303"><enum>(1)</enum><text>meet, upon request, with the Chairman or Ranking Member of the appropriate congressional committees regarding negotiating objectives and the status of negotiations in progress; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAA6572D5CC574968971B5B595622B346"><enum>(2)</enum><text>consult closely, on a timely basis, and keep fully apprised of the negotiations, the appropriate congressional committees.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HD67F752A5B304E35AB1BB1AB1FF126F5"><enum>5.</enum><header>Approval of the Agreement</header> <subsection id="HB849D5C4B88B41A88A3A62FAEC79BB21"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Submission of agreement</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the Agreement is concluded, the Secretary of State shall provide the Agreement and technical explanation to the appropriate congressional committees.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE940496121C947FD95839CDA76EACD7C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Approval</header><text>The Agreement shall not take effect until after Congress passes a concurrent resolution of approval as described in subsection (c).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H96D92FA6EA0345D489777A82A80C0971"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Terms of concurrent resolution of approval</header> <paragraph id="H49584C77D4074088B762DA40D61F348F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of subsection (b), the term <term>concurrent resolution of approval</term> means only a concurrent resolution—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4BE4D672833343B3B0275D1C448EF7BA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>which does not have a preamble;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H34C0E4F31ACE49418EA0206E1DD88CF3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>which includes in the matter after the resolving clause the following: <quote>That Congress approves the Tax Agreement concluded between the American Institute in Taiwan and the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office, as submitted by the President on ____.</quote>, the blank space being filled in with the appropriate date; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDAE5D025E7FE4E43866B3B82B154273F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the title of which is as follows: <quote>Concurrent resolution approving the Tax Agreement concluded between the American Institute in Taiwan and the Taipei Economic and Cultural Representative Office.</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFB2AC3990B6941CF87AE33148687CF55"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Referral</header><text>A resolution described in this subsection that is introduced in the Senate shall be referred to the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate. A resolution described in this subsection that is introduced in the House of Representatives shall be referred to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H156D62D6034E450FB610044DF0553DC5"><enum>6.</enum><header>Entry into force and legal effect of the Agreement</header> 
<subsection id="H5E0C824ADFD242D9841BED5C4BD55D85"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Entry into force</header><text>Upon passage of the concurrent resolution of approval, the President may bring the Agreement into force. </text></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0E3E673F48D442E3BFF8B9C68769A18C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Legal effect</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon entry into force, the Agreement shall be afforded the same treatment as a treaty for purposes of the laws of the United States. </text></subsection></section> 
<section id="H4FAC4C87EA6641BBBA3C02AFC0C542E8"><enum>7.</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Finance of the Senate and the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives. </text></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

