<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H99A4CD54592C4163A3770EACAFB540EB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 6571 IH: Promoting Resilient Supply Chains Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6571</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231204">December 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish a critical supply chain resiliency and crisis response program in the Department of Commerce, and to secure American leadership in deploying emerging technologies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD86CF149CB984E00AB41C5674B6577C0" style="OLC"><section id="HEE2AEB17A80B4B8E87CD7326DBE0EAD4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Resilient Supply Chains Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HC0734A452E434D2389C1A9D07816F1AD"><enum>2.</enum><header>Definitions</header><subsection id="H6F14B127FD784C07BEB47D918484BBD7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HEFD4947D598045CE90AE2889D7E78621"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agency</header><text>The term <quote>agency</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 551 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBA580306D29481EA173EB8C0032F7D5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ally or key international partner nation</header><text>The term <quote>ally or key international partner nation</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="H4BAF31A3A18D42FC9739C6C824715234"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means countries that are critical to addressing critical supply chain weaknesses and vulnerabilities; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF6D76B2552A14DD3B580C88FA3E9E13D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include—</text><clause id="H71429DDE1852418F8A86B8C4BC5C1B98"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a country that poses a significant national security or economic security risk to the United States; or</text></clause><clause id="H7850B1C328264404A7F954F4E6E7C7A3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a country that is described in section 503(b) of the RANSOMWARE Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/238">Public Law 117–238</external-xref>: 136 Stat. 5564).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BAEDC525A1541A496AA30535D68593B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Assistant secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Assistant Secretary</quote> means the Assistant Secretary of Commerce assigned by the Secretary to direct the office of Industry and Analysis.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC2FA26EBAE8048ACAC1DCBB3C85B9423"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Critical good</header><text>The term <quote>critical good</quote> means any raw, in process, or manufactured material (including any mineral, metal, or advanced processed material), article, commodity, supply, product, or item of supply the absence of which would have a significant effect on—</text><subparagraph id="HAA8F552DD2994E02A1D591F107CF8FF5"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the national security or economic security of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H724532F829684B6E8EE26F3FA29F6CF6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>either</text><clause id="H294288E2BDC54DB98F213072A50F4873"><enum>(i)</enum><text>critical infrastructure; or</text></clause><clause id="H8F24373477424A75A4F11DE1ABD54C51"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>emerging technologies</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H403CA1EF5005491187A39CA278C5287F"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Critical industry</header><text>The term <quote>critical industry</quote> means an industry that is critical for the national security or economic security of the United States, considering critical goods.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CA89801982742BABC4A3C8AB490ECC1"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Critical infrastructure</header><text>The term <quote>critical infrastructure</quote> has the meaning given to that term in the Critical Infrastructures Protection Act of 2001 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5195c">42 U.S.C. 5195c</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E6A34A48C7C407B80635EA533310E8F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Critical supply chain</header><text>The term <quote>critical supply chain</quote> means a critical supply chain for a critical good.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA116545979F444E18175CC8FF5DF15AD"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Critical supply chain information</header><text>The term <quote>critical supply chain information</quote> means information that is not customarily in the public domain and relating to—</text><subparagraph id="H668613BF83CD4D2BA5AF381A545F53EE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>sustaining and adapting supply chains during a supply chain shock;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H82DC8CC821374631B442467F3BF3A2D1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>critical supply chain risk mitigation and recovery planning with respect to a supply chain shock, including any planned or past assessment, projection, or estimate of a vulnerability within the critical supply chain, including testing, supplier network assessments, production flexibility, risk evaluations, risk management planning, or risk audits; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD1CAFF7AADF4866975B754112C08906"><enum>(C)</enum><text>operational best practices, planning, and supplier partnerships that enable enhanced resilience of critical supply chains during a supply chain shock, including response, repair, recovery, reconstruction, insurance, or continuity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H930630A07A964E5AB80EBA255F6A4C5E"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Domestic enterprise</header><text>The term <quote>domestic enterprise</quote> means an enterprise that conducts business in the United States and procures a critical good.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H350EB86F647D4F90AB816D254C2A3E09"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Domestic manufacturer</header><text>The term <quote>domestic manufacturer</quote> means a business that conducts in the United States the engineering, or production activities necessary for manufacturing.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BF84966D0604AC9B1A70E5D09DF106B"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Emerging technology</header><text>The term <quote>emerging technology</quote> means technologies that are critical for the national security and economic security of the United States, including—</text><subparagraph id="H81F70F390B074B52BD616F5FA7176A1A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>technologies included in the American COMPETE Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/260">Public Law 116–260</external-xref>; 134 Stat. 3276); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H394000B7290B459AAC3683CF737B6DE7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the following technologies:</text><clause id="H35B5AD6690D3435FB388ECB4B7D6A352"><enum>(i)</enum><text>artificial intelligence;</text></clause><clause id="H28FB93904803460EB28EC00C2F157675"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>automated vehicles and unmanned delivery systems;</text></clause><clause id="HFCD00CF9C9F4491FBF89F7FB6C57E72F"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>blockchain and other distributed ledger, data storage, data management, and cybersecurity technologies;</text></clause><clause id="HEFCEEE3C346C4194B83E29E6E4FE6BA9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>quantum computing and quantum sensing;</text></clause><clause id="HA9FDAF093C634CAF9462A4E30966C263"><enum>(v)</enum><text>additive manufacturing;</text></clause><clause id="H1A16E6F1CAAF4C64A098CD7A571A6475"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>advanced manufacturing and the Internet of Things;</text></clause><clause id="H8DADC6E002FA4013BF4128A266DF041C"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>nano technology;</text></clause><clause id="HE0917B0F5BFF4AEBB8CF7B00B5D93464"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>robotics;</text></clause><clause id="HEE4E22A137144153A8B3032D8A8108C8"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>microelectronics, optical fiber ray, and high performance and advanced computer hardware and software;</text></clause><clause id="HD1E2D5663F724A769E921EBD5660AA05"><enum>(x)</enum><text>semiconductors;</text></clause><clause id="H21199D5DB4E74257A3CAA372E6D01559"><enum>(xi)</enum><text>Advanced materials science, including composition 2D, other next gen materials, and related manufacturing technologies.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB07FC9C07C1F4F77A3B657684A4F9119"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text>The term <quote>institution of higher education</quote> has the meaning given that term under section 101(a) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3E06D4DB4B9F40708E78B401E900036A"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Manufacture</header><text>The term <quote>manufacture</quote> means any activity that is necessary for the development, production, processing, distribution, or delivery of any raw, in process, or manufactured material (including any mineral, metal, and advanced processed material), article, commodity, supply, product, critical good, or item of supply.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF46666561F264BD49DF1A4786EF7C6A3"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Manufacturing technology</header><text>The term <quote>manufacturing technology</quote> means technologies that are necessary for the manufacturing of a critical good.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF9663A0E5BCC43E9BE20EAE111013E65"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Non-governmental organization</header><text>The term <quote>non-governmental organization</quote> means organizations that are described in section 2155(b) of title 19 of U.S. Code, excluding non-federal governments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9FCBC91F1F3D401381040F1880677A80"><enum>(16)</enum><header>Production equipment</header><text>The term <quote>production equipment</quote> means any component, subsystem, system, equipment, tooling, accessory, part, or assembly necessary for the manufacturing of a critical good.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE424D896239547439FD53D8EB67149CE"><enum>(17)</enum><header>Program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>program</quote> means the critical supply chain resiliency program established pursuant to section 4.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H961B5A0CDE554149BB3944CEA9A82CDF"><enum>(18)</enum><header>Relevant committees of congress</header><text>The term <quote>relevant committees of Congress</quote> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="H3E24250A84984C34BF7ABE19329AB5A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF62C618A90304E57A6ACD7CC3F95B7D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7634E8337144C1AB3AE10B783FF2AC9"><enum>(19)</enum><header>Resilient critical supply chain</header><text>The term <quote>resilient critical supply chain</quote> means a critical supply chain that—</text><subparagraph id="HD80D0F5E1C224B6297CE12D437E746B6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>ensures that the United States can sustain critical industry (including critical industries for emerging technologies), production, critical supply chains, services, and access to critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology during supply chain shocks; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF3201A40E0D4DA0B1BE7AB306B98AC6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has key components of resilience that include—</text><clause id="HB351BD5B8001452B9B6787F7AE48A8C2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>effective private sector risk management and mitigation planning to sustain critical supply chains and supplier networks during a supply chain shock;</text></clause><clause id="H839F37BB6F9F4693ADCCD27D488D6817"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>minimized or managed exposure to supply chain shocks; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H44F59174A2EA454FB1709CF8266E5B51"><enum>(20)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <quote>Secretary</quote> means the Secretary of Commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28D097FAA4BE400FBD90ACD0948D893D"><enum>(21)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <quote>State</quote> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, each commonwealth, territory, or possession of the United States, and each federally recognized Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBA21CF3F9874EE2A38D671540CE43BB"><enum>(22)</enum><header>Supply chain shock</header><text>The term <quote>supply chain shock</quote> includes the following:</text><subparagraph id="HC7BC4AB0AD8443BBB6AFD1EBB1FB744E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A natural disaster.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE6983E337F14D30896BBBFBE335F87D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A pandemic.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C3ECEAA9E934A5E8817E3EEC8C437DD"><enum>(C)</enum><text>A biological threat.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H152F35A0D7504E91BC2540705B7F87E4"><enum>(D)</enum><text>A cyber attack.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B603C1DCE41436094E52F5FDCAC8EEB"><enum>(E)</enum><text>A great power conflict.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAEB7A07D98D24844AF92FCB61E181972"><enum>(F)</enum><text>A terrorist or geopolitical attack.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9E7E7EE07F3B4541A3B528B329F4751A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>An event for which the President declares a major disaster or an emergency under section 401 or 501, respectively, of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (42 U.S.C. 5170 and 5191).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H66A9B8AEE9834E0CA58CF3B01BB4B0E0"><enum>(H)</enum><text>Any other critical supply chain disruption or threat that affects the national security or economic security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H501F0B8B561B46F7872D70118ADF4D07"><enum>3.</enum><header>Responsibilities assigned to Assistant Secretary</header><subsection id="H3A74F45D66224EC2B87F696B5B588A24"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Additional responsibilities</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall have the following additional responsibilities:</text><paragraph id="HC27E36FDA8B64A5C8209E8D80A54EEC4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Promote the leadership of the United States with respect to critical industries, critical supply chains, and emerging technologies that—</text><subparagraph id="H34189E619A7F4BBC9CDA5D1D39F31A44"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Strengthen the national security of the United States; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54702F2C717944BB9F9C892655BBE708"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Have a significant effect on the economic security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E75ED25BEE443B9B9E75C786A73160E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Encourage consultation with other Federal agencies, and partnerships with non-governmental organizations, industry, institutions of higher education, and State and local governments in order to—</text><subparagraph id="H3B54B30F60E246C9A4EF012B2CBDC085"><enum>(A)</enum><text>promote resilient critical supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54EDC85410BB42A698DC00BE21D08373"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify, prepare for, and respond to supply chain shocks to—</text><clause id="H0A83422814ED4877B2A3D9D403E029D2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>critical industry;</text></clause><clause id="H91B66AEF57ED45A89945C2648CD58B3F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>critical supply chains; and</text></clause><clause id="HFEC0821110F042DF8721B6471A899E89"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>emerging technologies.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF608BC3FA59B42419BB4316D83F2068E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>encourage the growth and competitiveness of United States productive capacities and manufacturing in the United States of emerging technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33771E3982DA40AFB0DEC5573ABA2FE7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Monitor the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of critical supply chains, critical industries and emerging technologies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H031D6D0250D2416287B16639907C00A6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Support the availability of critical goods from domestic manufacturers, domestic enterprises, and manufacturing operations in the United States and in countries that are allies or key international partner nations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AC3F1BDB37F442087121358C28DEC5C"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Assist the Federal Government in preparing for and responding to critical supply chain shocks, including by improving the flexible manufacturing capacities and capabilities in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91899EFDEE214CC480DD8E5785B4F0EF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Consistent with United States obligations under international agreements, encourage and incentivize the reduced reliance of domestic entities and domestic manufacturers on critical goods from countries of concern.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EC94BEB7B8C44B2A1DF287432B6A816"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Encourage the relocation of manufacturing facilities that manufacture critical goods from countries of concern to the United States and countries that are allies and key international partner nations to strengthen the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of critical supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H045A186B5A2A46349580CBEFF9E2C1E9"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Support the creation of jobs with competitive wages in the United States manufacturing sector.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2BAD66D71D344D79F43180AB07D67D9"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Encourage manufacturing growth and opportunities in rural and underserved communities.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3AAC176D6F214555A1D5ACCD7F1B331C"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Promote the health of the economy of the United States and the competitiveness of manufacturing in the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2AC3549752B8425A8B9AB79BF3BD23AC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Expertise and staffing</header><text>In executing the responsibilities under subsection (a), the Assistant Secretary—</text><paragraph id="HA9A4DF9D304F490888D8E1892E5284E2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall establish capabilities to—</text><subparagraph id="H151EB27FFCA642D3AEE0E4041D1A0132"><enum>(A)</enum><text>assess the state of technology, innovation, and production capacity in the United States and other nations; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A4D36403965453597A55B528D78B6E1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>conduct other activities deemed to be critical for the use of analytic capabilities, statistics, datasets, and metrics related to critical technologies and innovation; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA84A2EE8A2D4E4A8EBE207FAFCE8077"><enum>(2)</enum><text>may utilize external organizations to provide independent and objective technical support.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H96AA7FE0B0FC48259FE84ADA26ACD24C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Critical supply chain resiliency and crisis response program</header><subsection id="HF281692C2DFD48D2B978AA035CEDF22F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary shall establish in the Department of Commerce a supply chain resiliency program to carry out the activities described in subsection (b).</text></subsection><subsection id="H7F42E8725DC34E8AABE2B49E82077BF1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>Under the program, the Assistant Secretary shall carry out activities—</text><paragraph id="H3943344B508F46B986AFB2EC548BACCC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in coordination with the coordination group established under subsection (c), to—</text><subparagraph id="HDEA4328ED5C84587BFD9B266CB7F55A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>map, monitor, and model critical supply chains, including emerging technology supply chains, which may include—</text><clause id="HC5758024C08249B7995B80A23F98B0D3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>modeling the impact of supply chain shocks on critical industries (including critical industries for emerging technologies), critical supply chains, domestic enterprises, and domestic manufacturers;</text></clause><clause id="HE2AF7F6547C14DF5A811B82479D8870B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>monitoring the demand for and supply of critical goods and services, production equipment, and manufacturing technology needed for critical supply chains, including critical goods and services, production equipment, and manufacturing technology obtained or purchased from a person outside of the United States or imported into the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="H06FD2118EE97412BA836720354FAB83B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>monitoring manufacturing, warehousing, transportation, and distribution related to critical supply chains; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC9D9281D6ED47DBA48F73D645B23BD3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>identify high priority critical supply chain gaps and vulnerabilities, which may include single points of failure in critical supply chains, critical industries, and emerging technologies that—</text><clause id="H6F8F190355F04331B54F4300DE038285"><enum>(i)</enum><text>exist as of the date of the enactment of this section; or</text></clause><clause id="HAA2DEF135C2048B9B88927855F5D1FE4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>are anticipated in the future;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9852F417E0774428AC339D4FEC2612A3"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identify potential supply chain shocks that may disrupt, strain, compromise, or eliminate a critical supply chain, including emerging technology supply chains;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H37036CC2871A431BA657627D43C61AAF"><enum>(D)</enum><text>evaluate the capability and capacity of domestic manufacturers or manufacturers located in countries that are allies or key international partner nations to serve as sources for critical goods, production equipment, or manufacturing technology needed in critical supply chains, including emerging technology supply chains;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2ADA4285BB1435C9DE5FB8A55EE5242"><enum>(E)</enum><text>evaluate the effect on the national security and economic competitiveness of the United States, including on consumer prices, job losses, and wages, that may result from the disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination of a critical supply chain;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA32F3EAAC5244887AC21CD940C091EA9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>evaluate the state of the manufacturing workforce, including by—</text><clause id="HDDD16A6A99FB4E52962087952742CE27"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identifying the needs of domestic manufacturers; and</text></clause><clause id="H772CEA9A8B4740838C78F9FA003B25EE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identifying opportunities to create high-quality manufacturing jobs; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEA9E145878DB4AB0B33B1842EF1DC330"><enum>(G)</enum><text>identify investments in critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology from non-Federal sources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H55D4AD3155B14FC8AE735CF4FE628277"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in coordination with the State and local governments, and the coordination group established under subsection (c), and, as appropriate, in cooperation with the governments of countries that are allies or key international partner nations of the United States, to—</text><subparagraph id="H8CA75DCBEC534436AEC228719D5BFF10"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identify opportunities to reduce critical supply chain gaps and vulnerabilities in critical supply chains, critical industries, and emerging technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE2BA29E3E103420B9B0F583897203EAD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>encourage consultation between the Federal Government, and partnerships between industry, non-governmental organizations, institutions of higher education, and State and local governments to—</text><clause id="H46EE41086AB946F2A79AA9F5545F985B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>better respond to supply chain shocks to critical supply chains, critical industries, and emerging technologies; and</text></clause><clause id="H1733804328104FF7B0A2E99BD5C90A99"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>coordinate response efforts;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA6F8A4767250473B93B41312C5643DDF"><enum>(C)</enum><text>encourage consultation between the Federal Government and the governments of countries that are allies or key international partner nations of the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB82966B5BFC847449924C2E22B10787E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>develop or identify opportunities to build the capacity of the United States in critical supply chains, critical industries, and emerging technologies; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H49325BE4C68F4FC982CBB4DAC399D1D9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>develop or identify opportunities to build the capacity of countries that are allies or key international partner nations of the United States in critical industries (including critical industries for emerging technologies), and critical supply chains;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H85926B3B7D9F44F1B1976A22C001AE77"><enum>(F)</enum><text>develop contingency plans and coordination mechanisms to improve critical supply chain, critical industry, and emerging technology supply chain response to supply chain shocks; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF113B0427D224DD9921553CB08D46FE3"><enum>(G)</enum><text>support methods and technologies, including blockchain technology, distributed ledger technology, and other emerging technologies as appropriate, for the authentication and traceability of critical goods;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFE32DF39B6D4E72ABDD8114E9D0DB38"><enum>(3)</enum><text>acting within the existing authorities of the Department of Commerce, and in consultation with the Secretary of State and the United States Trade Representative, consult with governments of countries that are allies or key international partner nations of the United States to promote diversified and resilient critical supply chains that ensure the supply of critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology to the United States and companies of countries that are allies or key international partner nations of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBE0197A48FC543AEAC06E113677F7C57"><enum>(4)</enum><text>consult with other offices and divisions of the Department of Commerce and other Federal agencies to leverage existing authorities, as of the date of the enactment of this Act, to encourage the resilience of supply chains of critical industries and emerging technologies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD5ADC438AA984EF38C7BACB465DEBF2B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>to determine what emerging technologies may assist in accomplishing the activities described in this subsection and promote emerging technologies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA4C99978C5AE48838D1A0DDFC6ADF922"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Coordination group</header><text>In carrying out the applicable activities under subsection (a), the Assistant Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H0936E30A325B4A3DBCF213B5B77E1105"><enum>(1)</enum><text>establish a unified coordination group led by the Assistant Secretary, which shall include, as appropriate, private sector partners, and non-governmental organizations, to serve as a body for consultation among agencies described under subsection (g) to plan for and respond to supply chain shocks and support the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of critical supply chains;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48C47B68A6084BB9988F41F4C2B28597"><enum>(2)</enum><text>establish subgroups of the unified coordination group if established under paragraph (1), led by the head of an appropriate agency; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4F60C81FC2B44CE82C159E7C0982E96"><enum>(3)</enum><text>through the unified coordination group established under paragraph (1)—</text><subparagraph id="H19496D40E1124AC69DB248D4A5D810CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>acquire on a voluntary basis technical, engineering, and operational critical supply chain information from the private sector, in a manner that ensures any critical supply chain information provided by the private sector is kept confidential and is exempt from disclosure under section 552(b)(3) of title 5, United States Code (commonly known as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9A68179386A641938D988B9D85F27808"><enum>(B)</enum><text>study the critical supply chain information acquired under subparagraph (A) to assess critical supply chain, including emerging technology supply chain resilience, and inform planning;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4152C48264BA4CD697FC0671CF72D833"><enum>(C)</enum><text>convene with relevant private sector entities to share best practices, planning, and capabilities to respond to potential supply chain shocks;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD4A4225EB7AA43F789C92112B6FA7F29"><enum>(D)</enum><text>develop contingency plans and coordination mechanisms to ensure an effective and coordinated response to potential supply chain shocks; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD02229165154D57819B1FE1B4E73888"><enum>(E)</enum><text>factor in any relevant findings from the studies required in the American COMPETE Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/260">Public Law 116–260</external-xref>; 134 Stat. 3276).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE8F47A2C02554602B8A25B3D3A415BB2"><enum>(4)</enum><header>International cooperation</header><text>The Secretary, in consultation with other relevant Federal agencies, may consult with governments of countries that are allies or key international partner nations of the United States relating to enhancing the security and resilience of critical supply chains in response to supply chain shocks.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1389F0F1445403D94F80BE58D8397FD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Designations</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H969632DFB0264C3E9BA4ED5CBF16FC87"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 270 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, designate—</text><subparagraph id="HB30154974E3C425DB8B02BEF32966717"><enum>(A)</enum><text>critical industries;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC8DF3D63838456CB6441AE13DBE9267"><enum>(B)</enum><text>critical supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3B6F1CD3CCC648BBBF43A61E5EE62B3A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>critical goods;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H923807F7664E40D08E06F351BB502B4A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provide for a period of public comment and review in carrying out paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBBEEC2A8D3EF4C6FB87DA48EF9D106C6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>update the designations made under paragraph (1) not less frequently than once every four years, including designations for technologies not provided in the initial list described in section 2(a)(11)(B) that the Assistant Secretary deems necessary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC7A94A366344EE8B569F9D1EDC1E514"><enum>(e)</enum><header>National strategy and review on critical supply chain resiliency and manufacturing in the united states</header><paragraph id="H1C2D5C5508AF4E2781CB3031EE5EE08A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this section, and not less than once every 2 years thereafter, the Assistant Secretary, in consultation with the head of each relevant agency, non-governmental organization, industry, institutions of higher education, and State and local governments, shall submit to the relevant committees of Congress and post on the website of the Assistant Secretary a report that—</text><subparagraph id="H9761C25010144B4789139F421335B02D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>identifies—</text><clause id="HA29CAD9E944045BEA4E29B37841B6184"><enum>(i)</enum><text>critical infrastructure that may assist in fulfilling the responsibilities described in section 3;</text></clause><clause id="H1F8F4D39198345DFBD1FEECCE6B5694E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>emerging technologies that may assist in fulfilling the responsibilities described in section 3 and the program described in subsection (a), and such technologies that may be critical to addressing critical supply chain preparedness, weaknesses, and vulnerabilities;</text></clause><clause id="H321A5CD47806423D975FA5F860837B66"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>critical industries, critical supply chains, and critical goods designated under section 4(d);</text></clause><clause id="H39C3BF4C45F548FA803255F4C231983A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other goods, supplies, and services that are critical to the crisis preparedness of the United States;</text></clause><clause id="H88314D85775D4EE69270B07BC6C0E98A"><enum>(v)</enum><text>substitutes for critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology;</text></clause><clause id="H9CB1D6EAB73C48D3A3DCF84A98029351"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>methods and technologies, including blockchain technology, distributed ledger technology, and other emerging technologies as appropriate, for the authentication and traceability of critical goods; and</text></clause><clause id="HA470C03E47EC495E9E61907118BDFB4B"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>countries that are critical to addressing critical supply chain weaknesses and vulnerabilities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF347A19A67E145EAB2F36F87BF860C83"><enum>(B)</enum><text>describes the matters identified and evaluated pursuant to section 4(b)(1), including—</text><clause id="HC82F347910C246C3A93CC8954D46B26A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the manufacturing base and critical supply chains and emerging technologies in the United States, including the manufacturing base and critical supply chains for—</text><subclause id="H3097206371E44C3BBD334BA62B48F26B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>essential materials;</text></subclause><subclause id="HE0D3399D7CF24B49AF312A744124CD6F"><enum>(II)</enum><text>production equipment;</text></subclause><subclause id="HE103C0B509BA44B5875B405C9AE4A11D"><enum>(III)</enum><text>critical goods, including raw materials, microelectronics and semiconductors, and rare earth permanent magnets, that are essential to the production of technologies and supplies for critical industries, including emerging technologies; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HA70602A2BE8F474F903F3A055326CAEE"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>manufacturing technology;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H7FC0C340B4B24AA5A2544EEBB549E2D8"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the ability of the United States to—</text><subclause id="HB43015B035C74B4B94528A6AE1FE17D0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>maintain readiness with respect to preparing for and responding to supply chain shocks; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H06812E067DA04120B07A1049F21C1058"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in response to a supply chain shock—</text><item id="HF5CF3F36F8334D578CFB8C25D2C51ED1"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>surge production in critical industries;</text></item><item id="H4BDB3C3769B144E1BE5FF19FA39DE1E2"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>surge production of critical goods and production equipment; and</text></item><item id="HD9819ACE7CC540819013B567B1E6D0B1"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>maintain access to critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology;</text></item></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD592DAF6D4744169C773F6D75FF122C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an assessment and description of—</text><clause id="H582066AB91F649D9ADECF0B331A1C679"><enum>(i)</enum><text>demand and supply of critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology;</text></clause><clause id="HEDE6A503D7A84EA7BA14A7CD107D0928"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>production of critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology by domestic manufacturers;</text></clause><clause id="HA46AF49D576D4F8BBAB04B9C835EEBD0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>the capability and capacity of domestic manufacturers and manufacturers in countries that are allies or key international partner nations of the United States to manufacture critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology; and</text></clause><clause id="HD50B645F2AE24A70B2B90521F8390C54"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>how supply chain shocks could affect rural, Tribal, and underserved communities;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DA7F4C09A87495293096CB2E2D9346A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>identifies threats and supply chain shocks that may disrupt, strain, compromise, or eliminate critical supply chains, critical goods, and critical industries, including emerging technologies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFF19B4FE8A244154B4B55733D5F0A341"><enum>(E)</enum><text>with regard to any threat identified in subparagraph (D), lists any threat or supply chain shock that may originate from a country, company, or individual from such country that—</text><clause id="HC567992516274E16863A6BC656349281"><enum>(i)</enum><text>is described in section 503(b) of the RANSOMWARE Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/238">Public Law 117–238</external-xref>: 136 Stat. 5564); or</text></clause><clause id="H0F9247C062AC476C93FF60844D593CDE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>poses a significant national security or economic security threat to the United States;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6939EAB76C354C22B5E22E281782EB5F"><enum>(F)</enum><text>assesses—</text><clause id="HE7EBC39AFE9F4540ADB2504770A030D1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the resilience and capacity of the manufacturing base, critical supply chains, and workforce of the United States and allies and key international partner nations that can sustain critical industries, including emerging technologies, through a supply chain shock; </text></clause><clause id="H566C15D2741749328ED9C927A7589822"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the effect innovation has on domestic manufacturing; and</text></clause><clause id="HCAA3AA06D65C415C9F250BA1FA3A902C"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>any single points of failure in the critical supply chains described in clause (i);</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H824DE7A743C24A57BB31BD966B50C4D4"><enum>(G)</enum><text>with respect to countries that are allies or key international partner nations of the United States, review the sourcing of critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology associated with critical industries from those countries;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1B251F41619A4AB2A6FD5B23DBA4B238"><enum>(H)</enum><text>assesses the flexible manufacturing capacity and capability available in the United States in the case of a supply chain shock;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7CC20FC916AE49E29682302C5B8BB79B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>develop a strategy for the Department of Commerce to support the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of critical supply chains and emerging technologies to:</text><clause id="H327A1AABA75B4BE1B45EBBDC64765424"><enum>(i)</enum><text>Support sufficient access to critical goods by mitigating critical supply chain vulnerabilities, including critical supply chains concentrated in countries of concern.</text></clause><clause id="H1896DAE5002A4F2CB8A48BF1357AACCD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>Collaborate with other relevant Federal agencies to assist allies or key international partner nations build capacity for manufacturing critical goods.</text></clause><clause id="H263357EA114443659BF289842EF65CCB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Recover from supply chain shocks.</text></clause><clause id="HB646730BE22E4AA99220FA33F6FBFF7E"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>Identify, in consultation with other relevant Federal agencies, actions relating to critical supply chains with which the United States might—</text><subclause id="H785A3CF8267F4718A9BD2AE37DD2B3A7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>raise living standards;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC253D664317D4F3D9D53BD0428979D5A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>increase employment opportunities; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HD69CA002FB5D47D1BFCD0C3C766E012C"><enum>(III)</enum><text>improve response to supply chain shocks.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H9430241986E4454D8940F52735D09230"><enum>(v)</enum><text>Protect against supply chain shocks from countries of concern relating to critical supply chains.</text></clause><clause id="H38CC6EB24B3D4AD686B6B7F64104D961"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>Support methods and technologies, including blockchain technology, distributed ledger technologies, and other emerging technologies as appropriate, for the authentication and traceability of critical goods.</text></clause><clause id="H3E855855BBCB4BC7AD56CE53CD685F8E"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>Make specific recommendations to effectuate the strategy under this section and improve the security and resiliency of manufacturing capacity and supply chains for critical industries, including emerging technologies, by—</text><subclause id="H3F2F044177A249F292DA4081244D56BA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>developing long-term strategies;</text></subclause><subclause id="HABDDF46D36624F1E9989C02A9D987576"><enum>(II)</enum><text>increasing visibility into the networks and capabilities of suppliers and domestic manufacturers;</text></subclause><subclause id="H418ABFF2586340B68C8D8A0FF61B8D0E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>identifying industry best practices;</text></subclause><subclause id="H7CB871C4CAF64545B6032A2920C97C8F"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>evaluating how diverse supplier networks, multi-platform and multi-region production capabilities and sources, and integrated global and regional critical supply chains can enhance the resilience of—</text><item id="H83D311E3BEB34FE09C27D2B36E7C139E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>critical industries in the United States;</text></item><item id="H840D13FBE7914144915B9036AF195986"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>emerging technologies in the United States;</text></item><item id="H9BB1495125AA48D7982D4EAB990D9173"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>jobs in the United States;</text></item><item id="HB6A2B1C8D94C44B0B56EAC521FD25497"><enum>(dd)</enum><text>manufacturing capabilities of the United States; and</text></item><item id="HBEB7951B150941D3B85FBE9D5B1B7180"><enum>(ee)</enum><text>the access of the United States to critical goods during a supply chain shock;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H2264F40A0A8E4313B6BE10EACF5500AE"><enum>(V)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identifying and mitigating risks, including—</text><item id="HD1509C6C51614FCCADA6F5219DAA79BE"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>significant vulnerabilities to supply chain shocks; and</text></item><item id="HFA0C1F2663654BCDBA72101B3AFE373D"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>exposure to gaps and vulnerabilities in domestic capacity or capabilities and sources of imports needed to sustain critical industries (including critical industries for emerging technologies), or critical supply chains;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H22FA65C4DDA94B9993F6ED278AE7E312"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>identifying enterprise resource planning systems that are—</text><item id="H7BA6100513224A5A9FF954BAA4349831"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>compatible across critical supply chain tiers; and</text></item><item id="H79283BF4B0F448C4A2EDB62A84C3EFBA"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>affordable for all sizes of business and for startups;</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H712E9155529144009B3358BDE773B679"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>understanding the total cost of ownership, total value contribution, and other best practices that encourage strategic partnerships throughout critical supply chains;</text></subclause><subclause id="H75C2687569AC45EB8A6FA4623748286B"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>understanding Federal procurement opportunities to increase resiliency of critical supply chains for goods and services and fill gaps in domestic purchasing;</text></subclause><subclause id="HF3B3AF677DD94D7A9C229DA816A4DBD3"><enum>(IX)</enum><text>identifying opportunities to consult with allies or key international partner nations of the United States to build more resilient critical supply chains and mitigate risks;</text></subclause><subclause id="H6D578119104249FE9E1E05AF01727D81"><enum>(X)</enum><text>identifying opportunities to reuse and recycle critical goods, including raw materials, to increase the resilience of critical supply chains;</text></subclause><subclause id="HAD37CBEDB7D64CE98EE85DF54A2DBB0D"><enum>(XI)</enum><text>consulting with countries on—</text><item id="HA909C9682BC34A87B672BD380F09803D"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>sourcing critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology; and</text></item><item id="H89545490DF19452A8D1291CFD8BD1277"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>developing, sustaining, and expanding production and availability of critical goods, production equipment, and manufacturing technology during a supply chain shock; </text></item></subclause><subclause id="H6DB3CB287EFE4B11AC89E2048F6BBD78"><enum>(XII)</enum><text>identifying such other services as the Assistant Secretary determines necessary;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD9B4AE79F64C448D8C3DE7BFEA2F5689"><enum>(XIII)</enum><text>provides guidance to the Department of Commerce and other relevant agencies with respect to technologies and supplies that should be prioritized to ensure United States leadership in the deployment of such technologies.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AA03D702DC243C5970F1B6B8252F6AD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>The report submitted under paragraph (1) may not include—</text><subparagraph id="H01C63E9EA83C4EC89575CF71316ED5F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>critical supply chain information that is not aggregated;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2E108E9A8A234A17A68A9625F9568FEC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>confidential business information of a private sector entity; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H601532C0F1FE4ECA828DBE1BC648AC17"><enum>(C)</enum><text>classified information.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9CE1D9A164B74A5CBE889DC245DE26E2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary shall enter into agreements with the head of any relevant Federal agency to obtain any information, data, or assistance that the Assistant Secretary determines to be necessary for developing the report.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB6EF7A609E76454981EE8454C38BBCBA"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Form</header><text>The report, and any update submitted thereafter, shall be submitted to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate in unclassified form and may include a classified annex.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8272F1A4E75647588E80170286A4A87A"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Public comment</header><text>The Assistant Secretary shall provide for a period of public comment and review in developing the report.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H05F52572C4EC4F128869AABFFA981155"><enum>(6)</enum><text>With regard to any threat identified in subparagraph (C), lists any threat that may originate from a country, company, or individual from such country that—</text><subparagraph id="H70B8BC3FF75B47ACA1C7A1CF405C6E2B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is described in section 503(b) of the RANSOMWARE Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/238">Public Law 117–238</external-xref>: 136 Stat. 5564); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H690C014AED7D481FB664C3B85037CC65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>poses a significant national security or economic security threat to the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4536CEFFC13E4AFD84BD4A0AF08605D5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Concurrent with the annual submission by the President of the budget under section 1105 of title 31, United States Code, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate and post on the website of the Assistant Secretary a report that contains a summary of every activity carried out under this Act during the year covered by the report. Such report shall be submitted in unclassified form and may include a classified annex.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA149D9CDF64E4EE28E5886B111E8784C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In implementing the program, the Assistant Secretary may, as appropriate, consult with the heads of relevant Federal agencies.</text></subsection><subsection id="H759CD3C9BD3144E9AF860805502D7806"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to require any private entity—</text><paragraph id="HEF0E397B02514C75ABE00601F5A3A4D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to share information with the Secretary or Assistant Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD5D8F82B490495DAAACB00A7846E79C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to request assistance from the Secretary or Assistant Secretary; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB15759DDF7B2440A88F886810C210A3C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to implement any measure or recommendation suggested by the Secretary or Assistant Secretary in response to a request by the private entity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H92382155FCC94B9CACA79BD32F698CD7"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Protection of voluntarily shared critical supply chain information</header><paragraph id="H4788B14C8BF347DA8E1CB07AE1A32F1E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Protection</header><subparagraph id="H09B5DD94AA6E43D088ACC2521E20F6A4"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, critical supply chain information (including the identity of the submitting entity) that is voluntarily submitted by a private entity under this section to the Department of Commerce for use by the Department for purposes of this section, when accompanied by an express statement specified in subparagraph (B)—</text><clause id="H6C2EEF1AC5EC40D089C9B732C5410F9B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall be exempt from disclosure under section 552(b)(3) of title 5, United States Code (commonly referred to as the <quote>Freedom of Information Act</quote>);</text></clause><clause id="HD36DA641D6B649E9A2D484F121392EB9"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is not subject to any agency rules or judicial doctrine regarding ex parte communications with a decision making official;</text></clause><clause id="HD45CF89C6EE14A0D8C8CB500A4A49320"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>may not, without the written consent of the entity submitting such information, be used directly by the Department of Commerce, any other Federal, State, or local authority, or any third party, in any civil action arising under Federal or State law if such information is submitted in good faith;</text></clause><clause id="HFBD439AC6562450ABF25D25C201B84CE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>may not, without the written consent of the entity submitting such information, be used or disclosed by any officer or employee of the United States for purposes other than the purposes of this section, except—</text><subclause id="H8DC63D68DFC340FB9F0A1A90B28078B0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in furtherance of an investigation or the prosecution of a criminal act; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HC7E9FBD255534464914B7542F2CC7A02"><enum>(II)</enum><text>when disclosure of the information would be—</text><item id="H8DC7EF8F036E4C6EAF77D247D3F88710"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>to either House of Congress, or to the extent of matter within its jurisdiction, any committee or subcommittee thereof, any joint committee thereof, or any subcommittee of any such joint committee; or</text></item><item id="HFB149B28A19E49A398D36E85BC23F573"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>to the Comptroller General of the United States, or any authorized representative of the Comptroller General, in the course of the performance of the duties of the Government Accountability Office;</text></item></subclause></clause><clause id="H2C1B8F8E64DC45518696E406B51CF7BF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>may not, if provided to a State or local government or government agency—</text><subclause id="H142F355DD3514C5DA2FBE836B46E19E7"><enum>(I)</enum><text>be made available pursuant to any State or local law requiring disclosure of information or records;</text></subclause><subclause id="H52A4669483224C8D9A8345CB70C593C8"><enum>(II)</enum><text>otherwise be disclosed or distributed to any party by such State or local government or government agency without the written consent of the entity submitting such information; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H173080CA16514577AA6AF4EBE787F62B"><enum>(III)</enum><text>be used other than for the purpose of carrying out this section, or in furtherance of an investigation or the prosecution of a criminal act; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H98F345A3F2B744649B8D2D0FDC91E58C"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>does not constitute a waiver of any applicable privilege or protection provided under law, such as trade secret protection.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9FB9AC5E3C994AF18ACD68C0BB3AAFCB"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Express statement</header><text>The express statement described in this subparagraph, with respect to information or records, is—</text><clause id="HCAAF1B43DB564948895ABE1B8D7834D6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in the case of written information or records, a written marking on the information or records substantially similar to the following: <quote>This information is voluntarily submitted to the Federal Government in expectation of protection from disclosure as provided by the provisions of the _______ Act of 2023.</quote>; or</text></clause><clause id="HA9E1778F558D4F9C8472787D6659C75E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in the case of oral information, a written statement similar to the statement described in clause (i) submitted within a reasonable period following the oral communication.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA00D78D934B8441AB4914D2C76AA0881"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>No communication of critical supply chain information to the Department of Commerce made pursuant to this section may be considered to be an action subject to the requirements of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC2838DA51C246A4ACCADC48421C204D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Independently obtained information</header><text>Nothing in this subsection may be construed to limit or otherwise affect the ability of a State, local, or Federal Government entity, agency, or authority, or any third party, under applicable law, to obtain critical supply chain information in a manner not covered by paragraph (1), including any information lawfully and properly disclosed generally or broadly to the public and to use such information in any manner permitted by law. For purposes of this subsection a permissible use of independently obtained information includes the disclosure of such information under section 2302(b)(8) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB98E0B09579D4F2DADB9356B9366AF5B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Treatment of voluntary submittal of information</header><text>The voluntary submittal to the Department of Commerce of information or records that are protected from disclosure by this section may not be construed to constitute compliance with any requirement to submit such information to an agency under any other provision of law.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA70ABC28AAC84B8591EBC0D44B050F70"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Inapplicability to semiconductor incentive program</header><text>This subsection does not apply to the voluntary submission of critical supply chain information by a private entity in an application for Federal financial assistance under section 9902 of the William M. (Mac) Thornberry National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2021 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/283">Public Law 116–283</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H34E97D61F9224F989E78588885548435"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text>the program established under this section shall terminate no later than 7 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="H8DECBA6A679642F1B8C640C3CCF2E498"><enum>5.</enum><header>Critical supply chain innovation and best practices</header><subsection id="HF034375A1A5B4ADEACF80FCEDC849073"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subject to the availability of appropriations, the Assistant Secretary shall, on an ongoing basis, facilitate and support the development and dissemination of guidelines, best practices, management strategies, methodologies, procedures, and processes for domestic manufacturers and entities manufacturing, purchasing, or using a critical good to—</text><paragraph id="HDA4C4875F7224560B08D0A91BAC95244"><enum>(1)</enum><text>measure the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of the critical supply chains of such manufacturers and entities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF2DBB732B8BF41538C9B6207BF62A0C1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>quantify the value of improved resilience, diversity, security, and strength of critical supply chains to such manufacturers and entities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFA4EAB680B154E5DA56AA4022ADEEFB1"><enum>(3)</enum><text>design and implement measures to reduce the risks of disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination of critical supply chains of such manufacturers and entities; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84A640C694DC430CA181E598574AF082"><enum>(4)</enum><text>support the authentication and traceability of critical goods using blockchain technology, distributed ledger technologies, and other emerging technologies as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F0B78646EAF40FE96D56A8C1DF0A186"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>In carrying out subsection (a), the Assistant Secretary shall do the following:</text><paragraph id="H7CB51EDDD78D4FBEBFDAFA6EC07BD82A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Consult closely and regularly with relevant private sector personnel and entities, manufacturing extension centers established as part of the Hollings Manufacturing Extension Partnership, Manufacturing USA institutes as described in section 34(d) of the National Institute of Standards and Technology Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/278s">15 U.S.C. 278s(d)</external-xref>), and other relevant stakeholders and incorporate industry expertise.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE086EB5A9B48485F9CFFDD39E0AC5590"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Consult with the head of any relevant Federal agency, including those with jurisdiction over critical supply chains, States, local governments, Tribal governments, allied and key international partner nations, and international organizations, as necessary.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC25C7E07ABCC498286BEDBE417F5135C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Collaborate with private sector stakeholders to identify prioritized, flexible, repeatable, performance-based, and cost-effective critical supply chain resilience approaches that may be voluntarily adopted by domestic manufacturers and entities purchasing or using a critical good to achieve the goals of subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H596D5EAA3F484EC1AAB14830B4766CA8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Facilitate the design of—</text><subparagraph id="H3B7C213620314A7FAED40F14D2730BDB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>voluntary processes for selecting suppliers that support the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of critical supply chains; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDB64A9314744524AA8D5AEDF20476D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>methodologies to identify and mitigate the effects of a disruption, strain, compromise, or elimination of a critical supply chain.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H94E96BBEBBF44E7DBE0F9EF32795E6E6"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Facilitate the identification or application of methods and technologies, including blockchain technology, distributed ledger technologies, and other emerging technologies as appropriate, for the authentication and traceability of critical goods.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CECEE36A00648FB90D270795C5C8847"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Disseminate research and information to assist domestic manufacturers redesign products, expand domestic manufacturing capacity, and improve other capabilities as required to improve the resilience, diversity, security, and strength of critical supply chains.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58DB2B4C06BF400ABFE735DA6C6544B1"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Incorporate relevant industry best practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H43A524EA4C2A49389316E59D16820CF2"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Consider private sector, including small business concerns.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8704EE43CBF041EF8064A8DAA0938491"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Leverage existing mechanisms for the Federal Government to provide critical supply chain solutions, including manufacturing technology, to include providing products, tools, and workforce development solutions related to critical supply chain resilience to manufacturers, including for small and medium sized manufacturers.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE9E4E9382AC0436F8E1AE71F92206280"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed to—</text><paragraph id="H43A2BC322F0E40CC9761DEE002B770E7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>require any private entity to share information with the Secretary or Assistant Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H237E9CE9512B4B65BDC1D62F2EE3F853"><enum>(2)</enum><text>require any private entity to request assistance from the Secretary or Assistant Secretary;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E9C6CE877254DE3A97D40F7881294C5"><enum>(3)</enum><text>require any private entity to implement any measure or recommendation suggested by the Secretary or Assistant Secretary in response to a request by the private entity; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19590C09ECE54E1986AF6C5AA5F77BDC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>require the adoption of the guidelines, best practices, management strategies, methodologies, procedures, and processes described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HF9C1BE5339844C00BD5DDDDDC5551420"><enum>6.</enum><header>Department of Commerce capability assessment</header><subsection id="H3AAC7878AD754F77A9875E197C92E131"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Assessment</header><text>The Secretary shall, not later than two year after the date of the enactment of this Act, produce a report—</text><paragraph id="H0DE0192AAF434CC298EA07573F0F8CE8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identifying the duties, responsibilities, resources, programs, and expertise within the offices and bureaus of the Department of Commerce relevant to critical supply chain resilience and manufacturing innovation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29126E6D220D4ED88C78E5D3C6ABC459"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identifying and assessing the purpose, legal authority, effectiveness, efficiency, and limitations of each office and bureau identified under paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8963A7959F0C4CF5AC67565C44176698"><enum>(3)</enum><text>providing recommendations to enhance the activities related to critical supply chain resilience and manufacturing innovation of the Department of Commerce including—</text><subparagraph id="HDA08D08D302A4059B30844A95B6DD1D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>improving the effectiveness, efficiency, and impact of the offices and bureaus identified under paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BA799AA12BC45E3A9A129694829D6AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>coordination across offices and bureaus identified under paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE800092EBEC5402F8444E814891F5284"><enum>(C)</enum><text>consult with Federal agencies implementing similar activities related to critical supply chain resilience and manufacturing innovation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC0371D9DB2D4429D91FF53F155217B9F"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Secretary shall provide the report required under subsection (a) to the relevant committees of Congress, along with a strategy to implement, as appropriate and as determined by the Secretary, the recommendations under the report.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

