<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF833231FB2904ECB8165366B9745109A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5983 IH: Clean Water Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5983</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231018">October 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000560">Mr. Larsen of Washington</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001218">Ms. Stansbury</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000148">Mr. Auchincloss</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001318">Ms. Balint</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000299">Ms. Escobar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001094">Ms. Hoyle of Oregon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000009">Ms. Kaptur</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001227">Ms. McClellan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001220">Mr. McGarvey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001206">Mr. Morelle</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001226">Ms. Salinas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000487">Ms. Tokuda</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000136">Mr. Vasquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Water Pollution Control Act to restore a national minimum standard of protection for the water resources of the United States while providing certainty to regulated entities.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H03179D17B1DE4061801ECE07486D831D" style="OLC"><section id="H96E966C60F694238A76163CD5374EC27" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Clean Water Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H570868E8AEA94C80ACC462956EF69168"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline"> The purposes of this Act are as follows:</text><paragraph id="H96B7BF0018534625A7F0144ABC55CB83"><enum>(1)</enum><text>To reaffirm the commitment of Congress to restore and maintain the chemical, physical, and biological integrity of the Nation’s protected water resources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD1A540A899824AC5A778A2E2232340AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To clearly define the Nation’s protected water resources that are subject to the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1252">33 U.S.C. 1252 et seq.</external-xref>) (commonly known as the <quote>Clean Water Act</quote>) based on the best available scientific evidence and decades of partnership between the Federal, State, and Tribal governments to protect water quality.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3981F8C58344F55B3264B570501393D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To eliminate the confusion initiated by the Supreme Court’s overly narrow interpretation of the term <term>navigable waters</term> and to reestablish the comprehensive authority necessary to meet the codified objective of the Clean Water Act. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC3BAEEA321C4376ABBAEBA70091263A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To restore a national minimum standard of protection of the Nation’s protected water resources to the fullest extent of the legislative authority of Congress under the Constitution.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H6E1E41677FE94A1CBC8FDECAE66CBF36"><enum>3.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HB6663A83D9E4489BB6ED7D10510347BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Water is a singular and precious resource that sustains all life and is fundamental to civilization’s survival, cultural practices, and indigenous ways of life.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1B0FBEE5E984D519A5156893AF909D4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Clean and abundant water is important for public health, agriculture, transportation, flood control, energy production, recreation, fishing, and municipal and commercial uses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64D968C3B41E42FB9FDEFEE40B6FA3FB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Rivers, streams, wetlands, and other water bodies are hydrologically connected within their watersheds, and scientific evidence shows that the pollution, impairment, or destruction of a water body in one location may significantly affect the chemical, physical, and biological integrity of other waters.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF284D4C1C6F24BDF87A8179FA145F8FB"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Supreme Court’s decision in Sackett v. EPA, 598 U.S. 651 (2023), reduces the protections of the Clean Water Act contrary to, and impairing, the congressional objective of restoring and maintaining the chemical, physical, and biological integrity of the Nation’s protected water resources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0405F143FE1B413785272E4FC6AE4493"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The decision eliminates Clean Water Act protections for tens of millions of acres of wetlands, including wetlands that perform vital functions such as storing water to help reduce flooding, improving water quality by filtering pollutants, providing critical and important habitats for aquatic and other species, and recharging groundwater that provides drinking water and contributes to downstream flows.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26AB3D675EB84C55B8E5530F73D79F5E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The decision also puts at risk Clean Water Act protections for millions of miles of small, intermittent, and ephemeral streams that—</text><subparagraph id="HBE0A4B278D7143FCB4D6E553A9CA803B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>comprise the majority of stream miles in the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H71589D4526D9446ABC571B9ECDE34A99"><enum>(B)</enum><text>transport large volumes of water to downstream rivers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA489C4791D364C69A80BB4CC30E32E47"><enum>(C)</enum><text>reduce the introduction of pollutants to large streams and rivers;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD8ECE9374EF54F60AEA3708999BBF2EE"><enum>(D)</enum><text>provide and purify drinking water supplies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H63B47B5527924712B23316498DA76D92"><enum>(E)</enum><text>are especially important to the life cycles of aquatic organisms; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD523702C93E4977B55BD3DAF84AB363"><enum>(F)</enum><text>aid in flood prevention.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9D263C7349DF44EDB9F18F869598DE99"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The peer reviewed scientific literature unequivocally demonstrates that—</text><subparagraph id="H4BEF911FC78A4345AC7BBCA4F179AA4D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>streams, regardless of their size or frequency of flow, are connected to, and strongly influence the function of, downstream waters; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H45E8DB44E1274CA19674CA2128508801"><enum>(B)</enum><text>wetlands, including wetlands that lack surface water connections, are physically, chemically, and biologically connected to, and affect the integrity of, other protected water resources.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B09C42B7307403DB91CB0094D7956CA"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Restoring and maintaining the Nation’s protected water resources, including intrastate waters, is necessary to prevent significant harm to interstate commerce and sustain a robust system of interstate commerce in the future.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74BB68782E334233B44D9F9BBE4C93DB"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act restores Clean Water Act protections to the Nation’s protected water resources to ensure their chemical, physical, and biological integrity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD44BF6DA0AFF4FC584C2E59EE0EC1021"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The pollution or other degradation of the Nation’s protected water resources, individually and in the aggregate, has a substantial relation to and effect on interstate commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64A5265DE91C4EF9BA51A0A416B5B39B"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Protected water resources, including streams and wetlands, provide protection from flooding, and draining or filling wetlands and channelizing or filling streams can cause or exacerbate flooding, placing a significant burden on interstate commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6DB78A433CD49E6A41916FC4188FF54"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Millions of individuals in the United States depend on the Nation’s protected water resources, including streams and wetlands, to filter water and recharge surface and subsurface drinking water supplies, protect human health, and create economic opportunity.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA75391C73DC14BA89F4D514F3086551F"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Source water protection areas containing small, intermittent, and ephemeral streams replenish public drinking water supplies serving more than 110 million individuals in the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9A214B4C0EC45439F42DB017574A817"><enum>(14)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H57DC92DE0EE94133BB41DA6BFEFA4717"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Millions of individuals in the United States enjoy recreational activities that depend on protected water resources, including streams and wetlands, such as waterfowl hunting, bird watching, fishing, paddling, and photography.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33766C24FCD24757BE9D7381BBE12F5A" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Those activities and associated travel generate hundreds of billions of dollars of income each year for the travel, tourism, recreation, and sporting sectors of the economy of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC405CC7583D446B9AE1E3C0A97BC5E4E"><enum>(15)</enum><text>Regionally specific protected water resources, such as prairie potholes in the upper Midwestern prairies, pocosins in the Atlantic coastal plain, playa lakes in the southern High Plains, and Carolina and Delmarva bays along the eastern coast of the United States, provide unique and critical benefits to their surrounding regions, including sustainable water quality and availability, groundwater recharge, wildlife habitat, and ecological benefits.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4340EA701BE48BAA73F2A56F1522005"><enum>(16)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Activities that result in the discharge of pollutants into the Nation’s protected water resources, including through dredging and filling, are commercial or economic in nature, and, in the aggregate, have a substantial effect on interstate commerce.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H27285E2B6CC04A4083D31CAE51048899"><enum>(17)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Restoring and maintaining the quality of, and regulating activities affecting, the Nation’s protected water resources is essential to fulfilling the United States treaty obligations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92346E410A454B7DBEADFC590B16DEA4"><enum>(18)</enum><text>Restoring and maintaining wetlands and other protected water resources is essential to North American wildlife, hunters, and anglers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H980FD3EB0D244AA681BAF9BCDA1BABAC"><enum>(19)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Restoring and maintaining the quality of, and regulating activities affecting, the Nation’s protected water resources is necessary to protect Federal land and waters from degradation.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB39BF398BC0E4DA895B8E1488059D8AD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Protected water resources</header><subsection id="HD73A531F8B974919B034CA522322CF40"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 502 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1362">33 U.S.C. 1362</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H40CBFF34E7494C8DA62DE8132541B35C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (7) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H57540091FC9E49F79468F9B6F0E62A92" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H6A1C51E8AC8A460188ED9339BA937591"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Protected water resources</header><subparagraph id="HB1CACE27E02C4EFFB51D11DECECE6236"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The term <term>protected water resources</term> means all waters subject to the ebb and flow of the tide, the territorial seas, and all interstate and intrastate waters (and their tributaries), including lakes, rivers, streams (including intermittent and ephemeral streams), wetlands, and all impoundments of the foregoing, to the fullest extent that these waters are subject to the legislative power of Congress under the Constitution.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADC3106B5D3D448D8889DE252C2EC67F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>protected water resources</term> does not include—</text><clause id="H5A8C7E6B2A654B3CA962D17A257C3C7B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>any category of water body or feature listed in paragraphs (1) through (8) of section 120.2(b) of title 40, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on March 20, 2023; or</text></clause><clause id="H6F79B86395704BE4B492AA9D79508E80"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other category of water body or feature excluded by the Administrator in accordance with subparagraph (C).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H42054337CDF149239FA5D35E249B339B"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Review and modifications</header><clause id="H522CDBFA80BD4913BD36BE5CEA7DE62C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Review required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Clean Water Act of 2023</short-title>, and periodically thereafter, the Administrator shall, by rule, review the categories of water body or feature excluded under subparagraph (B) to determine, based on the best available scientific evidence, whether the implementation of such exclusions, or any individual exclusion, has a significant cumulative adverse effect on—</text><subclause id="H43923C2D4743484E945A7C08F7D12CD8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the chemical, physical, or biological integrity of—</text><item id="HE8C57180939A45EB96F451D1340AEF04"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>the waters described in subparagraph (A); or</text></item><item id="H84C77C6E91974BFF86094D68615F554F"><enum>(bb)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">surface waters, other than those described in subparagraph (A), that are sources of water for public water systems, as such term is defined in section 1401 of the Safe Drinking Water Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/300f">42 U.S.C. 300f</external-xref>);</text></item></subclause><subclause id="H3397048409754037979F440551423C19"><enum>(II)</enum><text>environmental justice communities; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HA6F17DB449CA41A58E2572009051BD93"><enum>(III)</enum><text>water resources described in section 518(e)(2).</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H25D5857FEA1E4D038E806311AED5B7B9"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Modifications and removal</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Administrator determines under clause (i) that the implementation of the exclusions, or any individual exclusion, under subparagraph (B) has a significant adverse effect described in clause (i), the Administrator shall, by rule and concurrent with such determination—</text><subclause id="H91F2A51552CF4F77A7675ABE4F7D5298"><enum>(I)</enum><text>modify the category of water body or feature so excluded to ensure that, based on the best available scientific evidence, the implementation of such category will not have a significant cumulative adverse effect described in clause (i); or</text></subclause><subclause id="H54B47185AC204497BB25FE56B7232A74"><enum>(II)</enum><text>remove such category.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H24C73E8043DA4720BBCD741D902874D5"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Additional exclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may, by rule, exclude an additional category of water body or feature under subparagraph (B) if the Administrator determines, based on the best available scientific evidence, that the implementation of such additional exclusion will not have a significant cumulative adverse effect described in clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H742AA5B9B9424AA78D209FDA21F2AA61"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H73DC12C50D3847229361F548B8D149B9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H54DD375A428E4ED58ACA73DA58BE20DA"><enum>(28)</enum><header>Wetlands</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>wetlands</term> means those areas that are inundated or saturated by surface or ground water at a frequency and duration sufficient to support, and that under normal circumstances do support, a prevalence of vegetation typically adapted for life in saturated soil conditions.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4D4EF4485B6B45C38C08B7E5DAAB16C6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><paragraph id="H40096ABABEEC4FB296CBBA5AA22EE888"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal Water Pollution Control Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1251">33 U.S.C. 1251 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H460EB06568D64484902C28B57860190F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in sections 101, 102, 104, 106, 208, 301, 302, 303, 304, 319, 401, 404, 405, and 511(c), by striking <quote>navigable waters</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDBD4F3CF3DF843D6BC1422CF640B6003"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in section 303(c)—</text><clause id="H8FCBD650ACB9442B84E64227E92ADE63"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in paragraph (2)(A), by striking <quote>such waters</quote> and inserting <quote>such protected water resources</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HB5ED2CB3F44B4E13A4277F56F0635A95"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in paragraph (4)(A), by striking <quote>such waters</quote> and inserting <quote>such protected water resources</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H373384D8716B46A5972513B70683EA98"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in section 304(<italic>l</italic>)(1) by striking <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">navigable waters</header-in-text></quote> in the heading and inserting <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">protected water resources</header-in-text></quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB57D59897DD1496DABE0EC9BE99BD33E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>in section 305—</text><clause id="H7B9A94DC33764899BD1DEB6608F74402"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (a), by striking <quote>navigable waters</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H47BA80D591D343AEB3275F2B6534119B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (b)(1)—</text><subclause id="HCDAF1B278E1F4FE6B9A9D77D93ECCA2C"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>navigable waters</quote> and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H88174863B154422FB8BD27016D7F74FE"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subparagraph (B), by striking <quote>navigable waters of</quote> and inserting <quote>protected water resources in</quote>;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DA3CC5BEF5F4BE68F818D043B07FE55"><enum>(E)</enum><text>in section 311—</text><clause id="H06B5985812274ADAA99FA8221D7DEB3B"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsections (a)(11), (b), and (m), by striking <quote>navigable waters of the United States</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HB5183C91734743E994EFBDD61F180828"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsections (c) and (j), by striking <quote>navigable waters</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5CBBEC6A442C43E3887AB5CAEAD7C0B9"><enum>(F)</enum><text>in section 312—</text><clause id="H202109DEABD54114B8926EF939C915D2"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsections (a) and (b), by striking <quote>navigable waters</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HC8DD89B186C74C8AA64ABB92530D3DE2"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsections (h), (<italic>l</italic>), and (n), by striking <quote>navigable waters of the United States</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8C1C8A5BE0D843CFACB7F00DDB05D27A"><enum>(G)</enum><text>in section 319, by striking <quote>such waters</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>such protected water resources</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6C81767F1A7D46949890ADD04859B795"><enum>(H)</enum><text>in section 402—</text><clause id="H4FB2D0EF70084B68B3766098308938BB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(4), by striking <quote>into the navigable waters</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H2FAA780F45354C3D902847AA1D4EF995"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsections (b), (g), and (n)(1), by striking <quote>navigable waters</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HA9C0E4D821C7496096BEB42FF969F1B5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (n)(2), by striking <quote>navigable waters of</quote> and inserting <quote>protected water resources in</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H33C4B55EE5174A009ACC2D80A101CF5F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in section 404—</text><clause id="H0A74399DA3644F22AFA4CCBD5E78469E"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subsection (f)(2), by striking <quote>such waters</quote> and inserting <quote>such protected water resources</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="HC0701ABAA7FB4C1AA32365BDF4ADC5BD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>in subsection (g)(1)—</text><subclause id="HF799A57950D74C929F986112317332D8"><enum>(I)</enum><text>by striking <quote>those waters</quote> and inserting <quote>those protected water resources</quote>; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HC3973596D36F457293FA46B3DBB48FBE"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by striking <quote>all waters</quote> and inserting <quote>all protected water resources</quote>;</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7FA6CDE7F9124FE6B8C147B916003DF0" commented="no"><enum>(J)</enum><text>in paragraphs (11) and (12) of section 502, by striking <quote>navigable waters</quote> each place it appears and inserting <quote>protected water resources</quote>; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB337ABC33E6C48FC99BAEAA2A3630D60"><enum>(K)</enum><text>in section 511(b), by inserting <quote>as discharges of pollutants into protected water resources</quote> after <quote>shall be regulated</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB1AB360E65A04085A5CAEE4AAD196F9B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Oil Pollution Act of 1990</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1001(21) of the Oil Pollution Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/2701">33 U.S.C. 2701(21)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>waters of the United States, including the territorial sea</quote> and inserting <quote>protected water resources (as defined in section 502 of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act)</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

