<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE6ED612B21B741EB9F23598B52357C86" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6580 IH: Land And National Defense Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6580</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231204">December 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require that a foreign purchaser of agricultural land be subject to the same restrictions as are applicable to United States citizens and nationals in the home country of such foreign purchaser.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA6E62F115C0B4B318FFCFA5974C7DA6C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H28D49176E3514EA7BA9B167DFBAC9CB8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Land And National Defense Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>LAND Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="HA47CC6241F6F406EB1B0B847020C1357"><enum>2.</enum><header>Restrictions on foreign purchasers</header> <subsection id="H5B02B719F23349DBAC93C5FA5E31A3BE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a sale of agricultural land, a foreign purchaser of such land shall be subject to the same restrictions and limitations as a United States citizen or national would be subject to with respect to the purchase of agricultural land in the home country of such purchaser. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2183528CD28649AC9B7552B5F27B99AA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Determination of home countries of foreign purchasers</header> 
<paragraph id="HA49A576DCD7C471492CEA92500A60F04"><enum>(1)</enum><header>United States citizens</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"></text> <subparagraph id="H530837D4727D41E3B789B9F896F5718F"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Dual citizen</header><text>For purposes of applying subsection (a), in the case of a foreign purchaser who is a citizen of the United States and 1 other country, the other country shall be treated as the home country of such purchaser.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1C4AA50AE9EA4B58B7959ABBFFA47DA7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Multiple citizenship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of applying subsection (a), in the case of a foreign purchaser who is a citizen of the United States and more than 1 other country, the other country (other than the United States) with the most restrictive laws with respect to the purchasing of agricultural land, as determined by the Task Force, shall be treated as the home country of such purchaser. </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBFC6B4B2DCE4FBC976F3CDE4DF7F2F5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Non-United States citizens</header> <subparagraph id="HCADBE5955AA041FBA4C6750C5B1B909C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>For purposes of applying subsection (a), in the case of a foreign purchaser who is a not a United States citizen and is a citizen of 1 country, the country in which such purchaser is a citizen shall be treated as the home country of such purchaser.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC80A6921B96E47CAA970AF6DE4B0BFD5"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Multiple citizenship</header><text>For purposes of applying subsection (a), in the case of a foreign purchaser who is a not a United States citizen and is a citizen of more than 1 country, the country with the most restrictive laws with respect to the purchasing of agricultural land, as determined by the Task Force, shall be treated as the home country of such purchaser.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC1A6FA97F24B4946809F5CBD6DB27A8C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Companies</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of applying subsection (a), in the case of a foreign purchaser that is a company, the country with the most restrictive laws with respect to the purchasing of agricultural land, as determined by the Task Force, and of which the citizens of such country hold at least 5 percent of such company shall be treated as the home country of such purchaser. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0312E60C036A434197A13135E8966626"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foreign governments</header><text>For purposes of applying subsection (a), in the case of a foreign purchaser that is a foreign government, the country such government represents shall be treated as the home country of such purchaser.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5ED1EDB04D634E73B6E8ED13464623B4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Notification</header> <paragraph id="H863ABEAB802E4451AD13CACA8DA6C1B4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a sale of agricultural land to a foreign purchaser, the seller of such agricultural land shall report such sale to the Secretary of Agriculture.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H6C38BBAA8C9E41C59D65B9031B268214"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Congressional notification</header><text>With respect to each notification of a sale of agricultural land to a foreign purchaser under paragraph (1), the Secretary of Agriculture shall notify—</text> <subparagraph id="H1D3AC3B148A84ABFB4D50F1848E4465F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the members of the Senate from the State in which the agricultural land is located; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HDF4DAC6E5C8E47F896426BA599E50C6A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the member from the Congressional District in which such agricultural land is located.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </subsection> <subsection id="H3078B9EA99DF402DAC3C59F8608E55C2"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Task Force</header> <paragraph id="HE90BF5F6799E407CAEC431B3D21D727D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is established a Task Force (to be known as <quote>U.S. Land Protection Task Force</quote>) to identify violations of subsection (a).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF86E2F21CB7648C38652D64AC6A5BF99"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Task Force shall be composed of the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HBCFC7BAA87E048E3B21024B663C8A81E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Secretary of Agriculture, who shall serve as Chair of the Task Force.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7488ECDDD94846BD99D547C650386BF2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Committee on Foreign Investment in the United States.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H875263742D9B4D7E96AC01B05FBC17B9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The National Security Division of the Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H073E13E3D5ED486581057B0CD4FA739F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Secretary of State.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD28FCC741BB5489E9BF14AEC82326D59"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>Not later than 1 after the date of the enactment of this Act and every 6 months thereafter, the Task Force shall submit to Congress a report that includes with respect to the 6-month period preceding the report—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H60B731D8F9E24B21A533FECF964FD72B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the percentage of agricultural land (disaggregated by land type) that was sold to foreign purchasers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H97DAC729E9034F22AE4BCDDFF921C77C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the States in which such land was sold;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5EB1F63B5C044C8BB38236A24047BC6B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the average purchase cost of such land;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H78699884DE77478594B6EEBF5B0990E5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>with respect to each such purchase of agricultural land, the title history with respect to the agricultural land purchased; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H869825C7EB524B089C8BE6846B9D5C83"><enum>(E)</enum><text>whether any of the purchased agricultural land is located within 100 miles of a military installation. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE44EF84C100245EAB2D2DE91EE17DC1A"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Severability</header><text>If any provision of this Act (or the application of that provision to particular persons or circumstances) is held invalid or found to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act (or the application of that provision to other persons or circumstances) shall not be affected. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H847ED9728AA24E1DAA9218224AF20041"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H9D81BA0ADD0E485295B06DE0FDE62642"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Agricultural land</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>agricultural land</term> has the meaning given the term in section 9 of the Agricultural Foreign Investment Disclosure Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3508">7 U.S.C. 3508</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H25BCD8EB91FE42BDA191A4BBD3FC3517"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign purchaser</header><text>The term <term>foreign purchaser</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H0CA29F073D8247B08B7B5EE3E8B83D33"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a foreign person (as defined in section 9 of the Agricultural Foreign Investment Disclosure Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/3508">7 U.S.C. 3508</external-xref>)); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1622D15A473D4244A38C90141B3C29CC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a United citizen who is a citizen of another country.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

