<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8C74A563F37641D5BE14B0B63B68CF80" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 453 IH: Allowing Military Exemptions, Recognizing Individual Concerns About New Shots Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 453</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001052">Mr. Harris</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001095">Mr. Hunt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000825">Mrs. Boebert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide remedies to members of the Armed Forces discharged or subject to adverse action under the COVID–19 vaccine mandate.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1D2B999A60B74725A0E374F813EB3950" style="OLC"><section id="H04AA6CA422EB4D80B14DA6B71750E612" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Allowing Military Exemptions, Recognizing Individual Concerns About New Shots Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>AMERICANS Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H51E5127E81AF488B802BE6B1F67BD899"><enum>2.</enum><header>Remedies for members of the Armed Forces discharged or subject to adverse action under the COVID–19 vaccine mandate</header><subsection id="HBE1D5C7C53BF411983E75280DBCF6CA6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation on imposition of new mandate</header><text>The Secretary of Defense may not issue any COVID–19 vaccine mandate as a replacement for the mandate rescinded under section 525 of the James M. Inhofe National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2023 absent a further Act of Congress expressly authorizing a replacement mandate.</text></subsection><subsection id="H20D92E917A204859B62A5905B36A20C4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Remedies</header><text>Section 736 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/81">Public Law 117–81</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/10/1161">10 U.S.C. 1161</external-xref> note prec.) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H53730F5869C0472F8D47A9AEA4C85B38"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in the section heading, by striking <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="section">to obey lawful order to receive</header-in-text></quote> and inserting <quote><header-in-text style="OLC" level="section">to receive</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2EFC0B5CF65B4095BED286DF0CD34CFC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a)— </text><subparagraph id="HFCAF476AA2EC42E3AC1D1F986B4329A8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>a lawful order</quote> and inserting <quote>an order</quote>; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6053CBB96B5A479AAC40D69CDB95E8AA"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>shall be</quote> and all that follows through the period at the end and inserting <quote>shall be an honorable discharge.</quote>; </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HEC0FB04154B94EDDADC12F8C888FA23C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (b) as subsection (e); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB14D18F78E1A4E9B844214BCA918C129"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (a) the following new subsections:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HB5DF4404459D425BA4B2CF3D6C859E04"><subsection id="H699075256C90481BA64AE81207D97CF3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Prohibition on adverse action</header><text>The Secretary of Defense may not take any adverse action against a covered member based solely on the refusal of such member to receive a vaccine for COVID–19. </text></subsection><subsection id="H82F8D63695A945FAB2F8E75C445968C6"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Remedies available for a covered member discharged or subject to adverse action based on COVID–19 status</header><text>At the election of a covered member discharged or subject to adverse action based on the member's COVID–19 vaccination status, and upon application through a process established by the Secretary of Defense, the Secretary shall— </text><paragraph id="HF40723696B6948FB9C53AD6BC14403FB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>adjust to <quote>honorable discharge</quote> the status of the member if—</text><subparagraph id="H71D626E1EDD540E2A4C8BC540C9BCE75"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the member was separated from the Armed Forces based solely on the failure of the member to obey an order to receive a vaccine for COVID–19; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17632F73988E481182EE9FDAAB615C36"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the discharge status of the member would have been an <quote>honorable discharge</quote> but for the refusal to obtain such vaccine;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9425DE5163C24764A833835C86BC6A4B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reinstate the member to service at the highest grade held by the member immediately prior to the involuntary separation, allowing, however, for any reduction in rank that was not related to the member’s COVID–19 vaccination status, with an effective date of reinstatement as of the date of involuntary separation;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFD168A13C5FD4174ADD5DA87D68D3E46"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for any member who was subject to any adverse action other than involuntary separation based solely on the member’s COVID–19 vaccination status—</text><subparagraph id="H7D792C13BE3349CF8516EF06D17B8019"><enum>(A)</enum><text>restore the member to the highest grade held prior to such adverse action, allowing, however, for any reduction in rank that was not related to the member’s COVID–19 vaccination status, with an effective date of reinstatement as of the date of involuntary separation; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89E5ADB6E28848E6ABF979A74D01AA65"><enum>(B)</enum><text>compensate such member for any pay and benefits lost as a result of such adverse action;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFBF13CA46E04423B01FE4A6F196E4A8"><enum>(4)</enum><text>expunge from the service record of the member any adverse action, to include non-punitive adverse action and involuntary separation, as well as any reference to any such adverse action, based solely on COVID–19 vaccination status; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6540336DF52F428397F99E97A651B46D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>include the time of involuntary separation of the member reinstated under paragraph (2) in the computation of the retired or retainer pay of the member. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H074C07B4F9294497A0156D8B20D5487A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Retention and development of unvaccinated members</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall—</text><paragraph id="H06482A5F5F85406484770234EC1DBDE4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>make every effort to retain covered members who are not vaccinated against COVID–19 and provide such members with professional development, promotion and leadership opportunities, and consideration equal to that of their peers; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H309DC06820DE4AA69B4A9021AEB3B5AA"><enum>(2)</enum><text>only consider the COVID–19 vaccination status of a covered member in making deployment, assignment, and other operational decisions where—</text><subparagraph id="H2902693154CA42CCA201560A42F559C3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the law or regulations of a foreign country require covered members to be vaccinated against COVID–19 in order to enter that country; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F9FB91FD06D46F2819E23CEFBC09F7A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the covered member’s presence in that foreign country is necessary in order to perform their assigned role; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB48F562DBF84771A2D2E254512C69A9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>for purposes of deployments, assignments, and operations described in paragraph (2), create a process to provide COVID–19 vaccination exemptions to covered members with—</text><subparagraph id="H6A04061F6E7A442FB9B49CA1706EBB18"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a natural immunity to COVID–19;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27D6F1852EF84BFD9D9BEA5621153C96"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an underlying health condition that would make COVID–19 vaccination a greater risk to that individual than the general population; or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H850EDFFD5FB24D9CBFFBB3F79EC16D18"><enum>(C)</enum><text>sincerely held religious beliefs in conflict with receiving the COVID–19 vaccination.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H17B9B6F4E8E54C5799674EEAAD816C92"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Applicability of remedies contained in this section</header><text>The prohibitions and remedies described in this section shall apply to covered members regardless of whether or not they sought an accommodation to any Department of Defense COVID–19 vaccination policy on any grounds.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

