<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H270B509518E64EAD8BFF2DD3E12C12EF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 127 IH: Protection from Obamacare Mandates and Congressional Equity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 127</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to provide an exemption to the individual mandate to maintain health coverage for individuals residing in counties with fewer than 2 health insurance issuers offering plans on an Exchange; to require Members of Congress and congressional staff to abide by the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act with respect to health insurance coverage; and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9160247B944641D89F711DF0EEE34416" style="OLC"> 
<section display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H49BA252121D04E63B866430398FA11C7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Protection from Obamacare Mandates and Congressional Equity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCEC7E77CBEFB4DDA90897686162AD3FE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modifications to exemption from requirement to maintain health coverage</header> <subsection id="H6D4B6765CE8A4BC5A84D1807965D27B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Exemption for individuals in areas with fewer than 2 issuers offering plans on an exchange</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5000A">Section 5000A(e)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H68F650011DEC41C7A027ECA41DB77CCB" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="H077776FAA3B245ADABE01E3A73B0D44B"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Individuals in areas with fewer than 2 issuers offering plans on an exchange</header>
<subparagraph id="HBFDEB455DC1F4DE29D9FBA15C636A9EA"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any applicable individual for any period during a calendar year if there are fewer than 2 health insurance issuers offering qualified health plans on an Exchange for such period in the county in which the applicable individual resides.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2C54C6A403F54EAFA976670E4F2238EC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Aggregation rules</header><text>For purposes of subparagraph (A), all health insurance issuers treated as a single employer under subsection (a) or (b) of section 52, or subsection (m) or (o) of section 414, shall be treated as a single health insurance issuer.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H423525DBEB9C4E8F96995BF9A0EC5C1C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to months beginning after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H44B22A6FE42B4DBBA2DF7DF9E070E12C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Health insurance coverage for certain congressional staff and members of the executive branch</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1312(d)(3)(D) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/18032">42 U.S.C. 18032(d)(3)(D)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<paragraph id="H88D13A8920CD46F4AE52E12A97F8AF72"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking the subparagraph heading and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3EE98469E803492091AE6F1427E937D5" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H0CEB2BC56B554A10AC2E5DC260597D97"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Members of Congress, congressional staff, and political appointees in the exchange</header></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE670F60E14A546139EF3D5D088D92A53"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (i), in the matter preceding subclause (I)—</text>
<subparagraph id="HC00D689981A6416A97242F6392069D1C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and congressional staff with</quote> and inserting <quote>, congressional staff, the President, the Vice President, and political appointees with</quote>; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7D6E48F71DC34FDFB9E9C526D521CEE5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or congressional staff shall</quote> and inserting <quote>, congressional staff, the President, the Vice President, or a political appointee shall</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2F77C91A898A432C9DDB08C92988DDB8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in clause (ii)—</text> <subparagraph id="HEAE8CD63609945879BD1421C9571E2D2"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subclause (II), by inserting after <quote>Congress,</quote> the following: <quote>of a committee of Congress, or of a leadership office of Congress,</quote>; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H6CF7BF44252B41FC8E9F294298C34B34"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3AA07B0A2C274465B56AEF11EB11D709" style="OLC"> <subclause id="HE02DBC44532C47229F94187DB49F9407"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Political appointee</header><text>The term <term>political appointee</term> means any individual who—</text>
<item id="HAD49F2494AF5450981EC7B2951A8E90E"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>is employed in a position described under sections 5312 through 5316 of title 5, United States Code (relating to the Executive Schedule);</text></item> <item id="H1765D0909FFB430A9BCC08250399B1D1"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>is a limited term appointee, limited emergency appointee, or noncareer appointee in the Senior Executive Service, as defined under paragraphs (5), (6), and (7), respectively, of section 3132(a) of title 5, United States Code; or</text></item>
<item id="H74D43FDDB1FE4552867ACBAE642D4063"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>is employed in a position in the executive branch of the Government of a confidential or policy-determining character under schedule C of subpart C of part 213 of title 5 of the Code of Federal Regulations.</text></item></subclause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDA523C42E2C24344BC70AC7FEB9CDC23"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6C0A11DEF9A344729AE2EFA29D3E34BE" style="OLC">
<clause id="H473FB291C7024828A6281D0196613AE4"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Government contribution</header><text>No Government contribution under section 8906 of title 5, United States Code, shall be provided on behalf of an individual who is a Member of Congress, a congressional staff member, the President, the Vice President, or a political appointee for coverage under this paragraph.</text></clause> <clause id="H47358E26224144688D1BDE61F4A73509"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Limitation on amount of tax credit or cost sharing</header><text>An individual enrolling in health insurance coverage pursuant to this paragraph shall not be eligible to receive a tax credit under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/36B">section 36B</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 or reduced cost sharing under section 1402 of this Act in an amount that exceeds the total amount for which a similarly situated individual (who is not so enrolled) would be entitled to receive under such sections.</text></clause>
<clause id="H4D8547553B8448CC9D19EDE0015C92DE"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Limitation on discretion for designation of staff</header><text>Not­with­stand­ing any other provision of law, a Member of Congress shall not have discretion in determinations with respect to which employees employed by the office of such Member are eligible to enroll for coverage through an Exchange.</text></clause> <clause id="H5059645450E84171955D292A1EF7FDBA"><enum>(vi)</enum><header>Clarification</header><text>The terms <term>small employer</term> (as defined under section 1304(b)(2)) and <term>qualified employers</term> (as defined under subsection (f)) do not include the Congress, with respect to enrollments in an Exchange and a SHOP Exchange.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

