<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H02E07BF9A032494F81F1D05A0DBCDF88" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6119 IH: State Department Security Notification Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6119</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231030">October 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of State to notify Congress when the security clearances of certain senior members of the Department of State are suspended or revoked, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H568B08F5F3D641E3AE35C58A16220F43" style="OLC"><section id="HDB36074F85F042469D0F7668923FA7EF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>State Department Security Notification Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HCF4FA4A4E7264055A94AB1391D59E5F1"><enum>2.</enum><header>Notification of suspension or revocation of clearances</header><subsection id="HD086850C7D0D425DB84C77188C92B679"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to each covered official whose security clearance is suspended or revoked, the Secretary of State shall—</text><paragraph id="H882E9096F40B4F1B9DD5FE80C6E5904D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate congressional committees a notification, not later than 15 days after the suspension or revocation of such clearance, that identifies the individual whose clearance was so suspended or revoked; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3637D59D7FD14A4DA6E862666E4C6BAE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">brief the appropriate congressional committees not later than 30 days after such suspension or revocation on—</text><subparagraph id="HA1AC8E6BB333466EBCCD7865AF61C453"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the documentation notifying the individual of the suspension or revocation of the clearance; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H16790902D033467C97461E3556C6408F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the present employment status and conditions of such individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1B18C90A57E3404B9FB638C69B155383"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered official defined</header><text>For purposes of the notification requirement under subsection (a), the term <term>covered official</term> means any of the following:</text><paragraph id="H0A5C11830E714CBB805F1DEA70FE94D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any individual holding a position at or higher than the level of Assistant Secretary or its equivalent in the Department of State.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB09681EBBEB24EACA3386B37A56973AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Any individual holding the position of chief of mission or principal officer at any diplomatic or consular post.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4A0CFA174BD84881AF72F162D7CFCC31"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any individual holding the rank and status of an ambassador or otherwise holding a position that reports directly to the Secretary of State, such as a special envoy.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDF1FD0FDA515417AB4ECCF0D2649BC3C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>For purposes of this section, the term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

