<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H050EA23E7F1C41E6A59BB8E61DE6729E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6120 IH: Negating Opportunities for Oil Income Leveraged for Terrorists Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6120</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231030">October 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001204">Mr. Meuser</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To restore and require the imposition of certain sanctions previously waived with respect to Iran, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDDAFCBB7F2A74239A23E385AB1B36425" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4695C57199974BCC8D5C498D3E7DD4DF" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Negating Opportunities for Oil Income Leveraged for Terrorists Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>NO OIL for Terrorists Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC330EC5BD5814A689BAFE17887344C1A" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H604830362ED443118A5A580372D4A03E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Islamic Republic of Iran continues to engage in serious violations of its international obligations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7FD9756933C24CA082CB84E4244CB710"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The Government of Iran provides funding, material support, and resources to terrorist organizations, including Hamas, which conducts terrorist attacks against Israel.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FA945563C11413D9A47C3C61A62D514"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The actions of the Government of Iran pose an ongoing threat to the national security of the United States, our allies, and international stability.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5A52E50F235B4743917E7E3791665B52"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The reimposition of sanctions is a necessary and appropriate measure to counter Iran’s destabilizing activities and encourage Iran’s compliance with international obligations.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="H554E798D15DA415394BCE3B3EA7CB0EE"><enum>3.</enum><header>Reimposition of sanctions</header> 
<subsection id="H3B8494B738A64203AE4C4B665548399D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Oil export sanctions</header><text>The President shall use all powers granted to the President under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) to block all property and interests in property within the United States, or within the possession or control of any United States person, of any foreign person determined to have knowingly engaged in a significant transaction for the purchase, acquisition, sale, transport, or marketing of petroleum, petroleum products, or petrochemical products from Iran.</text> </subsection> <subsection id="HDE2BEBAF1CCB44F59120699D5227BBF0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) shall apply to violations of the regulations prescribed under subsection (a) to the same extent as such penalties apply to a person that commits an unlawful act described in section 206(a) of that Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB862029AD93B480CA94681646A42ECEA"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> 
<paragraph id="HA2701D694AFC400F914F9E3BBF91A6AB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may grant waivers on a case-by-case basis to a foreign person if the President—</text> <subparagraph id="HF6EFBBC0763A44E39BACB145046A4523"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determines that—</text> 
<clause id="HB17C09A87158454D8A567CCC398F7C5F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the country of which the foreign person is a national or under the laws of which the foreign person is organized has significantly reduced its volume of crude oil purchases from Iran; and</text></clause> <clause id="HE787B24FF4E24BAC9D8520C41E7CB7F7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the waiver is critical to the national security interests of the United States; and</text></clause></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1D54788D7A5F44AE944D0D71A9D002B8"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submits written notification to the Speaker and the Minority Leader of the House of Representatives, as well as the Majority and Minority Leaders of the Senate, of the intent to issue such a waiver.</text></subparagraph> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H312A15711FE74F17AEF9305F5D873440"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Humanitarian needs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The requirement to impose sanctions under this section shall not apply to transactions for or incidental to the sale of agricultural commodities, food, medicine, or medical devices to Iran.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HBC3A6903F6E54B1AB47419C42C47F55F"><enum>4.</enum><header>Sanctions on financial institutions</header> 
<subsection id="HCCC7AF31DF044354B2AAC015092140D7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Finding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Government of Iran uses its banking sector to facilitate Iran’s nuclear programs, its support for terrorism, and its malign regional influence.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HF5BC10963A704724A3A4DFBF8300BF78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions</header> <paragraph id="HDCB2C09F34E8490299F14C9BA04252BD"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President shall prohibit the opening, and prohibit or impose strict conditions on the maintaining, in the United States of a correspondent account or a payable-through account by any foreign financial institution that knowingly conducts or facilitates any significant financial transaction with the Central Bank of Iran or any other Iranian financial institution included in the List of Specially Designated Nationals and Blocked Persons maintained by the Office of Foreign Assets Control of the Department of the Treasury pursuant to the imposition of sanctions relating to Iran’s proliferation of weapons of mass destruction or Iran’s support for international terrorism.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72E8F63848EB4C0FA7A8B3FCCE38948B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Waiver</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may, on a case-by-case basis, waive the sanctions required by paragraph (1) with respect to transactions the President determines are necessary to the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="HB1FD0E95236A48E694E76FB1BA6875D3"><enum>5.</enum><header>Reporting requirement</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and every 180 days thereafter, a report that includes each of the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H5AF781AA5DE848D087A6C6565343287D"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The progress of the Government of Iran in complying with international nuclear obligations.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8F512EEF78064CFAB1D660D3BB459965"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The status of Iran’s support for international terrorism, including its financing and support of Hamas and other terrorist organizations.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HDED0372FB7744434991AD1654BF4B7ED"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measures taken to impose and enforce the sanctions required by this Act.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H5B64B70A0E154AABB2CD7D0855DD4767"><enum>6.</enum><header>Sunset clause</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall cease to have effect on date on which the President certifies to Congress that Iran has ceased to finance international terrorism.</text></section> 
<section id="H936DB523438144CD8F1537369719823F"><enum>7.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act—</text> <paragraph id="H0F8FB35463AE42308E625D91E6415B03"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA6E95EB79A4340EEA2FDD23FE147B412"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the Committee on Financial Services, the Committee on Ways and Means, and the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H268E71CBD4DF43BC8C9BF62CB8017152"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, the Committee on Finance, and the Select Committee on Intelligence of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HFAB774ED71294A6093455281B608F657"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign financial institution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>foreign financial institution</term> has the meaning given that term in section 561.308 of title 31, Code of Federal Regulations.</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H2531799EF1CF4E0D9AEF17BA30A17E14"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>foreign person</term> means a person who is not a United States person.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H37718E155FE64F79A20866DBE006A7CC"><enum>(4)</enum><header>United States person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>United States person</term> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H4570258E9DFE4D769F3990CAB842DA5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a citizen or national of the United States or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H3228A146CA2F45ADB7D20DEBFD4C9AC6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or any jurisdiction within the United States including a foreign branch of such an entity.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section> </legis-body></bill>

