<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H5A18810FAD1F4C6AB289928C42859E15" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1834 IH: To direct the Secretary of Labor to award grants to develop, administer, and evaluate early childhood education apprenticeships, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1834</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230328">March 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Labor to award grants to develop, administer, and evaluate early childhood education apprenticeships, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA12FC371A6AF4D529071F2EC042502D8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H85C60A1CEF514ED6AF3CE9B9E0871EA8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Grants for early childhood education apprenticeship programs</header>
<subsection id="HD80595BAD9544DF7A22D76663865B1B8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of Education, shall award grants to States to develop, administer, and evaluate apprenticeships.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC523153D62A9490F820E747A10B0F3B2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A State seeking a grant under this Act shall submit an application to the Secretary for approval at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H418D5E56B90F478685673BE7FE2AA863"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Uses of funds</header>
<paragraph id="H880B33FD5EB848E78CD05394FF5C7322"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Required uses</header><text>A grant under subsection (a) shall be used for activities that develop, administer, and evaluate an apprenticeship, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H7C7DB3300E8E4C0B9BCA8CA8ADAD8B35"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">equipping apprentices with specialized knowledge, skills, and competencies required to work in early childhood education;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H1B3506A80A8F45F6A5B8F5156C3A6F7E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the number of apprentices (including apprentices that are in areas that are underserved or rural) with a recognized postsecondary credential, a certificate of completion of an apprenticeship, or a degree from an institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0FF7518D8F324D30B7BEB36A9CA24BCA"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">promoting recruitment and retention of apprentices;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCE156BC70ABA43F8974E4F5FE080986C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">providing a pathway to career advancement for apprentices by assisting such apprentices in completing an apprenticeship and tracking the percent of such completions, including the apprentices who—</text> <clause id="HC37F9A4B31DA4122B68C743A98BF4D24"><enum>(i)</enum><text>attend an institution of higher education after completing an apprenticeship; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H0903732F61CE49929663ADB0E6C064A6"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">enter into employment that is unsubsidized after completing an apprenticeship;</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H53437DC7E418456185D1982D511081FC"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting partnerships with institutions of higher education in the State, businesses, and other entities participating in an apprenticeship to provide for academic credit for instruction related to the apprenticeship and the application of such credit toward a degree at an institution of higher education; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H518727F7FEDA4F4B815DE9A7643E2DAB"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">developing strategies to hire and retain qualified supervisors for apprentices that support such apprentices through—</text> <clause id="H3DE1C9B8A93E4400A5E1BC03713C5829"><enum>(i)</enum><text>professional development;</text></clause>
<clause id="H48432E8B1C1D4480AA4F06582A2BDC8D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>mentorship;</text></clause> <clause id="HD593A0770951437E948E5D403F288E36"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>evaluation; and</text></clause>
<clause id="H7DC3CACE5F5C447B9A558A8A636DF7E8"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>training.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H41DF03F9E14C479C828FB48351865233"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Permitted uses</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to the requirements under paragraph (1), a grant under subsection (a) may be used to—</text>
<subparagraph id="H1AB714C8446A41F7919F0F54877332A4"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate with the State apprenticeship agency to determine and disseminate best practices, recommended curricula, or other resources on administering effective apprenticeships for businesses, institutions of higher education, or other entities participating in an apprenticeship; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD5B7E2AF3F1F4D2390BE05915373D004"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish primary indicators of performance with respect to apprentices and individuals who have completed an apprenticeship to be shared on State and national workforce registries (commonly known as <quote>Registered Apprenticeship Partners Information Data Systems</quote>), including—</text>
<clause id="H91D52A6D3B234EDC913E593B7E8D8607"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of individuals who have completed an apprenticeship and remain employed full-time in early childhood education—</text> <subclause id="H1BE15AA357A4472196F4925F36DC1D00"><enum>(I)</enum><text>6 months after completing such apprenticeship; and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H7835BBBEB54447059602A7B6E47F5A48"><enum>(II)</enum><text>1 year after completing such apprenticeship;</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H2A438F7EAA6B4852A333F06B453741D5"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the median earnings of individuals who have completed an apprenticeship and are employed full-time in early childhood education within 6 months after completing such apprenticeship;</text></clause>
<clause id="H144629778EAF4FCB973FCBDBCE6B0AFD"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of apprentices who obtain a recognized postsecondary credential, a secondary school diploma, or the recognized equivalent of such diploma while participating in an apprenticeship; and</text></clause> <clause id="H476D198E1C444268A0E96DC518A01C76"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of individuals who have completed an apprenticeship and who begin or obtain a recognized postsecondary credential or degree, a secondary school diploma, or the recognized equivalent of such diploma within 1 year after completing an apprenticeship.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HAAF545B0F6404556A53579B65E44C5D9"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Priority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall prioritize State applicants that—</text> <paragraph id="H1CA177CDBCF3472CB87BE7DD1C107808" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have developed partnerships with—</text>
<subparagraph id="H9C03810739564BA491076BF5E581C33B" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Indian Tribes in such State; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF0522ABE932E489EAA5F5A9523479E9D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>institutions of higher education that serve minority populations;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HB3F853C0AE71426A8B93FECBCA6F76A6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">have a statewide credit articulation agreement in place that ensures credit transfer between participating institutions of higher education in the State and other relevant credential programs; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD75FCF16F7B44365BB1DA4256CBEA723"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assure that no less than 25 percent of the grant funds will be used to support apprenticeships in underserved or rural communities.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD043BE75F8294DA28F05CA1DEA67A5C2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Grant term and limitation</header>
<paragraph id="H0F535BB203B84CFFA1E1A7BDD39BE873"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Term</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term of a grant made under this Act shall be 3 years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF13638B9A39D4986BBBD233B3E0FC8A0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>The Secretary shall award no greater than 20 grants each fiscal year.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD6455F62238E4EDEAA197F9050271D62"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Cost-Sharing</header>
<paragraph id="H699AE50A8D6741D8947A8C5906C6ED4F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Federal share of the cost of any activity carried out using a grant made under this Act shall be not more than 75 percent.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H707C240339794A6DBFF81F81C37A278C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>In-kind contributions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The non-Federal share of the total cost of any activity carried out using a grant made under this Act may be in the form of donations or in-kind contributions of goods or services fairly valued.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H2DB28586102143AAA27B25048B5E6FEA"><enum>(g)</enum><header>State evaluation and report to Secretary</header>
<paragraph id="H011D45F22E7E4A3CABF27A65034D5AA2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Evaluation and report</header><text>Not later than 1 year after receiving a grant under this Act, and annually thereafter for the duration of the grant, a State shall submit to the Secretary a report containing an evaluation of the apprenticeships to determine which program strategies made progress toward—</text> <subparagraph id="H990F8DB190494144A85E687155123F3D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>increasing the aggregate number of apprentices; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HE0E3F12756A741C49D791B3A4264D11F"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">increasing the retention rates of apprentices.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H899D84220D1C4B59A9AB0D616A8E4ABA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule for reporting data</header><text>The disaggregation of data under this Act shall not be required when the number of apprentices in a category is insufficient to yield statistically reliable information or when the results would reveal personally identifiable information about an apprentice.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1C30B0F8C40D484F8671DD46C3EA2A03" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 5 years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on the effectiveness of each State that received a grant under this Act to develop, administer, and evaluate apprenticeships, including evaluating—</text> <paragraph id="H299DFA5F62FF46E08389D0C8DACE4674" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an increase in the number of apprentices in early childhood education;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEE4A5A5369CE49EAB710FF5CE0B775AA" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an increase in the retention rates of individuals who work in early childhood education after completing an apprenticeship;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF0DF2DB78E9642A6AE355B8B9F8E6A00" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the career path of apprentices and individuals who have completed an apprenticeship; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H0804462DC479454486358435DFDD5023"><enum>(4)</enum><text>an increase in the number of credentials and degrees obtained by apprentices.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H13201609196E4FB9993035328597490E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To carry out the grant program under this Act, the Secretary shall use amounts allocated under section 414(c) of the American Competitiveness and Workforce Improvement Act of 1998 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3224a">29 U.S.C. 3224a</external-xref>).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HFDCC483B22B54C22A9E0BFB6FFC939CF"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HA791EA93D5B749A684F8E958D28466AB"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Apprentice</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>apprentice</term> means an individual participating in a registered apprenticeship program focused on early childhood education as that term is defined under section 103 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1003">20 U.S.C. 1003</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF52D55F3BF324918B09947CD7E4CB83E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Apprenticeship</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>apprenticeship</term> means a registered apprenticeship program that trains apprentices.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H382E50E75C4F4ED7A969A8D8CA58F749"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Institution of higher education</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>institution of higher education</term> has the meaning given the term under section 102(a)(1) of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1002">20 U.S.C. 1002(a)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H45B7762194C84D5687685323F317BE9C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Registered apprenticeship program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>registered apprenticeship program</term> means an apprenticeship program registered under the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEEA2B5EF52D4413C9A6552643B6290F2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3B2DC054533D48F489F2AB33D7571E60"><enum>(6)</enum><header>State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>State</term> means each of the several States, the District of Columbia, and the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

