<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H7A26FABBC75941EBA458BEABC3BA79A9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4506 IH: Timely Evaluation of Acquisitions, Mergers, or Transactions with External, Lawful Entities to Clear Owners and Management Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4506</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230710">July 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000292">Mr. Johnson of Ohio</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act to establish an interagency national security review process, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H288DB8965E5743CE93371AF0424109CD" style="OLC"><section id="HE1E58490923146408798B744A205D609" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Timely Evaluation of Acquisitions, Mergers, or Transactions with External, Lawful Entities to Clear Owners and Management Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>TEAM TELECOM Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H6F588D1B2F3D47A9911512B8B5FC268D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Establishment of interagency national security review process</header><subsection id="HD6579F4500B64724B9A7B7E7FC484880"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Part A of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/901">47 U.S.C. 901 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAF204F8FE24E4046957201737D249D37" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="H4C3475B26C9F45CEA18E0BC901E6E0E2"><enum>106.</enum><header>Establishment of interagency national security review process</header><subsection id="HAB872D3B8F7A46038B9623E1057AFEFD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Assistant Secretary, in coordination with the head of each appropriate Federal entity, shall develop and issue procedures for, and establish, an interagency review process (which shall include each appropriate Federal entity) that considers the law enforcement and national security policy implications of the approval of a covered application that may arise from the foreign ownership interests held in the covered applicant that submitted the covered application.</text></subsection><subsection id="H13D02141487545E9A0661B237944DF5D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any covered application pending before the Commission that was submitted by a covered applicant with more than the threshold foreign ownership limit, after the covered applicant declines an opportunity to remedy the foreign ownership of the covered applicant, is subject to review under the review process established pursuant to subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HF9C68FB41C37411D92F6702772CB3330"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Process and procedural requirements</header><paragraph id="H13E3D6F9D1534BC8AFDF75ED5DE5223D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Referral for review</header><subparagraph id="HC9D2D54309094DDDA74E71B9E3ACDB3B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Requirement for FCC to refer complete application</header><text>The Commission shall refer any covered application subject to the review process established pursuant to subsection (a) to the Assistant Secretary promptly after the Commission determines that the covered application, under the rules and regulations of the Commission, is complete.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BED1086FCA8455CB258631ADF1BDDFA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Referral of other requests</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission may refer for review under the review process established pursuant to subsection (a) any other request for action by the Commission for which the Commission determines review is necessary under such process.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6A85209E22242BFBEEA007DA8901D71"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Interagency review deadline; determination</header><subparagraph id="H45303DF486C243C3A8525968710E947A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date on which the Assistant Secretary receives a referral from the Commission pursuant to paragraph (1)—</text><clause id="H095D57FCB067444B8E7CB0CFD200E5B3"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the review of the covered application or other request under the review process established pursuant to subsection (a) shall be completed;</text></clause><clause id="H163150A67F1F403AAB188BBB33494BB0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Assistant Secretary, in coordination with the head of each appropriate Federal entity, shall make a determination—</text><subclause id="HD9E497F459AE4DAAB1B58C83511BA1F2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>to recommend to the Commission that the Commission grant, grant conditioned on mitigation, or deny the application or other request; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H3453F0A71DD844C3A0066F3718282166"><enum>(II)</enum><text>that the Assistant Secretary cannot make a recommendation with respect to the covered application or other request; and</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H0FFDE00A668E4635AF01B10A0E93DCFA"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>if the Assistant Secretary determines under clause (ii) that the Assistant Secretary cannot make a recommendation with respect to the covered application or other request, the President shall make a determination to recommend to the Commission that the Commission grant, grant conditioned on mitigation, or deny the covered application or other request.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H013EEF7477E54C39B8AC065D5569DBAF"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extension</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Secretary, in coordination with the head of each appropriate Federal entity, may extend the deadline described in subparagraph (A) an additional 45 days.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD964D4C36F74641BC98DAC11B7EDD66"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Notification of extension</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Assistant Secretary, in coordination with the head of each appropriate Federal entity, extends the deadline pursuant to subparagraph (B), the Assistant Secretary shall notify the covered applicant or other requesting party of the extension.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5C6EEBBF96C3403C9776031759650C68"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Notification of determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 3 days (excepting Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays) after the Assistant Secretary or the President (as the case may be) makes a determination under paragraph (2)(A) to recommend that the Commission grant, grant conditioned on mitigation, or deny the application or other request, the Assistant Secretary shall notify the Commission and the covered applicant or other requesting party of the determination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H37B6173EE2A848069239400C54D0115B" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Disclosure of status of review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 5 days (excepting Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays) after receiving an inquiry from a covered applicant or other requesting party for an update with respect to the status of review of the covered application or other request of the covered applicant or other requesting party that was referred by the Commission for review under the review process established pursuant to subsection (a), the Assistant Secretary, in coordination with the head of each appropriate Federal entity, shall provide, consistent with the protection of classified information and intelligence sources and methods, a complete and accurate response to the covered applicant or other requesting party, the Commission, and the appropriate congressional committees.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB909F76A64A4ACABA808D4248F5BBA3"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Standardization of information required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the review process established pursuant to subsection (a), the Assistant Secretary, in coordination with the head of each appropriate Federal entity, shall establish a list of questions requesting information from a covered applicant or other requesting party that shall be made publicly available and posted on the internet website of NTIA. Such questions shall, to the maximum extent possible, be standardized for any potential covered applicant or other requesting party.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D029CA7414A46C2BA8B5D5272149408"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Deadline for provision of information requested</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 10 days after the date on which the Assistant Secretary, in coordination with the head of each appropriate Federal entity, requests information from a covered applicant or other requesting party, the covered applicant or other requesting party shall submit to the NTIA complete and accurate responses.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAC5ED84934904C969BA9F81BECD44B52"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed as limiting, superseding, or preventing the invocation of any privileges or defenses that are otherwise available at law or in equity to protect against the disclosure of information.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5E58B272EF084D019D629913FEE74905"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H4A5C779F353C42A18D34A0F66822CBA9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H57CE47E5770D45D28676FB1A5FA9B218"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate Federal entities</header><text>The term <term>appropriate Federal entities</term> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="HD1CE0424951E4257B0399237006D81F0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Department of Commerce.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE876F2392D34AAA9F81979098329497"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Department of Defense.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C8C5981BC5B4266B763AFAB537AC6C9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The Department of Energy.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89553633954E4EA292F4FFDF6E583B5E"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The Department of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30C610F60C8D40A79231856B334CE339"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The Department of Justice.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0ABA79D83D24270BF6A13C2504C9AF7"><enum>(F)</enum><text>The Department of the Treasury.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8CDE7FC26BAF4C719E0AF5F205B77FD5"><enum>(G)</enum><text>The Department of State.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBB6308C14EE248DABF1290EC5C47E2C9"><enum>(H)</enum><text>The United States Trade Representative.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3A65A57B36E844A6AFD42F03B8745FD6"><enum>(I)</enum><text>The Federal Bureau of Investigation.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB24D73436CB3411A89A76F5C034FD8B1"><enum>(J)</enum><text>The Executive Office of the President.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H8C28C6A2758E4B79B8750F1978BD6F91" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The term <term>classified information</term> means any information or material that has been determined by the Federal Government pursuant to an Executive order, statute, or regulation, to require protection against unauthorized disclosure for reasons of national security.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H56ADF8A23A6246F7874D87162432FEF0"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered applicant</header><text>The term <term>covered applicant</term> means an entity seeking approval of a covered application from the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F8F06F2B2404FD0804B50C8E8ED5CC8"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Covered application</header><text>The term <term>covered application</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HA1C2C0A6170E4813A0BFE46AD2F271BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an application under section 214(a) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/214">47 U.S.C. 214(a)</external-xref>) for authorization to undertake the construction of a new line or of an extension of any line, or to acquire or operate any line, or extension thereof, or to engage in transmission over or by means of such additional or extended line;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H182FBA1EEBA6486EA84CDB52014EE68A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an application under the Act entitled <quote>An Act relating to the landing and operation of submarine cables in the United States,</quote> approved May 27, 1921 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/34">47 U.S.C. 34 et seq.</external-xref>; 42 Stat. 8) for—</text><clause id="HD4C92CBDECE64524B2DAB42D6CDFF0E1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a submarine cable landing license; or</text></clause><clause id="HABBB494C229948F583A0343EACEB5C4E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>an assignment or transfer of control of a submarine cable landing license; or</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB9124E4C438B4F4A86E069CB40F5F0B6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an application for a new license, or for the transfer, assignment, or disposal of an existing license under section 310(d) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/310">47 U.S.C. 310(d)</external-xref>), that is—</text><clause id="HEBCD0CAD43664C05B7531A276450CC56"><enum>(i)</enum><text>subject to approval by the Commission under section 310(b)(4) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/310">47 U.S.C. 310(b)(4)</external-xref>); or</text></clause><clause id="H1739CBE8C743473E8BD624095DEACAE3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">eligible, under the rules of the Commission, for forbearance under section 10 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/160">47 U.S.C. 160</external-xref>) from the application of paragraph (1), (2), or (3) of section 310(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/310">47 U.S.C. 310(b)</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HDD895560DFD84F4E9612F0CFEB76E1A2"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Threshold foreign ownership limit</header><text>The term <term>threshold foreign ownership limit</term> means foreign ownership of, as applicable—</text><subparagraph id="HC69F843B9FBB4611ACCBC61CBA8B1D01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>at least the amount determined by the Commission under section 214(a) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/214">47 U.S.C. 214(a)</external-xref>), in the case of an application described in paragraph (5)(A) of this subsection;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H512CFA593A274E5BA0CD26D25A84A8BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any amount, in the case of an application described in paragraph (5)(B) of this subsection; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE68286BC907438C9DBC0444ADCA4A65" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at least an amount sufficient for section 310(b) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/310">47 U.S.C. 310(b)</external-xref>) to apply, in the case of an application described in paragraph (5)(C) of this subsection.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HDDBF00A4359F48FF95BB421D0D79C1C5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>This section, and the amendment made by this section, shall apply to any covered application (as such term is defined in section 106 of the National Telecommunications and Information Administration Organization Act, as added by subsection (a)) filed on or after the date on which the review process is established pursuant to such section 106.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

