<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCCCEF784CF054EFCB09E282DD0E27362" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 908 IH: Presidential Tax Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 908</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="P000096">Mr. Pascrell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000454">Mr. Foster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000380">Mr. Kildee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001163">Ms. Matsui</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001069">Mr. Courtney</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 to require the disclosure of tax returns of Presidents and Vice Presidents and certain candidates for President and Vice President, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H78B4E0F7A1CE4256BE947EE02FCDEB4F" style="OLC"><section id="HCBC3A79687CF4B45BE820BEA04D472E5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Presidential Tax Transparency Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H9CFDC7FBBD004C5798BE2B401C8BE1F6" section-type="subsequent-section" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>2.</enum><header>Presidential and Vice Presidential tax transparency</header><subsection id="HB9B47A394D7E4ACE9D07C6E0CC79DCD8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text><paragraph id="HBD886DFC474D4CADB810FDA2F9D1E20B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>covered candidate</term> means a candidate of a major party in a general election for the office of President or Vice President.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5067F5260B0A4656BB2A54D1F702436D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <term>major party</term> has the meaning given the term in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/9002">section 9002</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4CAF160A768247A99EE12B8D3F887047"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>income tax return</term> means, with respect to an individual, any return (as such term is defined in <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">section 6103(b)(1)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, except that such term shall not include declarations of estimated tax) of—</text><subparagraph id="HB43217CFF28245A9B5641202753CD022"><enum>(A)</enum><text>such individual, other than information returns issued to persons other than such individual; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA237BD03164B4AC29AF2431A623A784D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">of any corporation, partnership, or trust in which such individual holds, directly or indirectly, a significant interest as the sole or principal owner or the sole or principal beneficial owner (as such terms are defined in regulations prescribed by the Secretary of the Treasury or his delegate). </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B6F630F28494E9E8DEB58278756E613" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of the Treasury or the delegate of the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4943FB9EE8CB4F9D9264F5A20517523E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Disclosure</header><paragraph id="HCC45AEFA95D443F2801D143A4AFBE700"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><subparagraph id="HA4D580EC22B34CDDA70708378467567C"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Candidates for President and Vice President</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the date that is 15 days after the date on which an individual becomes a covered candidate, the individual shall submit to the Federal Election Commission a copy of the individual’s income tax returns for the 10 most recent taxable years for which a return has been filed with the Internal Revenue Service.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CD9CB3B0A5F4D1390EA8160F55CC8DA"><enum>(B)</enum><header>President and Vice President</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to an individual who is the President or Vice President, not later than the due date for the return of tax for each taxable year, such individual shall submit to the Federal Election Commission a copy of the individual’s income tax returns for the taxable year and for the 9 preceding taxable years.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7C698C49D806468BA3560B2B709985F6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Transition rule for sitting Presidents and Vice Presidents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the date that is 30 days after the date of enactment of this section, an individual who is the President or Vice President on such date of enactment shall submit to the Federal Election Commission a copy of the income tax returns for the 10 most recent taxable years for which a return has been filed with the Internal Revenue Service.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H70D4D5C3D437414C9C55FB81ADB9B2D8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Failure to disclose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any requirement under paragraph (1) to submit an income tax return is not met, the chairman of the Federal Election Commission shall submit to the Secretary a written request that the Secretary provide the Federal Election Commission with the income tax return.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74668BB39B0B45F1AEDF60DB24CFA4DD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Publicly available</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The chairman of the Federal Election Commission shall make publicly available each income tax return submitted under paragraph (1) in the same manner as a return provided under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">section 6103(l)(23)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by this section).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCAE2D51CB14E45BA938F814B0BAFC025"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Treatment as a report under the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971, any income tax return submitted under paragraph (1) or provided under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">section 6103(l)(23)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 (as added by this section) shall, after redaction under paragraph (3) or subparagraph (B)(ii) of such section, be treated as a report filed under the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1971.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C9130DDC3174CD49D41FBDC9B5EC933"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Disclosure of returns of Presidents and Vice Presidents and certain candidates for President and Vice President</header><paragraph id="HB4A94749072948F0824E3A8E61B41A21"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/6103">Section 6103(l)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HF634878B22E1470093E23429AE5E236F"><paragraph id="HB3F45AF4BF0A45EBB139D1AA74521133"><enum>(23)</enum><header>Disclosure of return information of Presidents and Vice Presidents and certain candidates for President and Vice President</header><subparagraph id="HA6EB83A30C0A4A0DA94018ED37EC5D6B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Upon written request by the chairman of the Federal Election Commission under section 2(b)(2) of the <short-title>Presidential Tax Transparency Act</short-title>, not later than the date that is 15 days after the date of such request, the Secretary shall provide copies of any return which is so requested to officers and employees of the Federal Election Commission whose official duties include disclosure or redaction of such return under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE277EB0A2B26419FB0AFD2BB80AE8B42" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Disclosure to the public</header><clause id="HD1A16A2CF3FF4AE383CC6A84F2671BEE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The chairman of the Federal Election Commission shall make publicly available any return which is provided under subparagraph (A).</text></clause><clause id="HF760179DDC1C439C86387EF2A32228D4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Redaction of certain information</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before making publicly available under clause (i) any return, the chairman of the Federal Election Commission shall redact such information as the Federal Election Commission and the Secretary jointly determine is necessary for protecting against identity theft, such as social security numbers.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H5921F91A19694221A980AD1D304F1C4F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 6103(p)(4) of such Code is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H594DC3DDEE644F5981A96550681D6599"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in the matter preceding subparagraph (A) by striking <quote>or (22)</quote> and inserting <quote>(22), or (23)</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H870B6EB5EB0A492C95FC0C9AD6FEB8B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subparagraph (F)(ii) by striking <quote>or (22),</quote> and inserting <quote>(22), or (23)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB1519AFFF644D34880DA00F0F885D9C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to disclosures made on or after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

