<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H79A9F5C3B4FB4A159CBD08883C97F7B8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6579 IH: Congressional Pension Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6579</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231204">December 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000614">Mr. Pappas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001119">Ms. Craig</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide that, if an individual is expelled from Congress, any Member service previously rendered by that individual shall be noncreditable for purposes of determining eligibility for or the amount of any benefits which might otherwise be payable out of the Civil Service Retirement and Disability Fund based on the service of that individual, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HB641C4B39F9145D99740E193FC53C7F6" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H544ECB7DA32B4BB8BD143FC21E142360" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Congressional Pension Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H783709C99A1943B89951DDBF4A0D2A3D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Provisions relating to the civil service retirement system</header> <subsection id="H6E72AF9345D44AF6AC3EC74AF4D84648"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Subchapter III of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/83">chapter 83</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/8333">section 8333</external-xref> the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HD008FE80AE19493FA7FBFEC4C38C5F3F" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H8F58E65410A94938A695E50A16E7130A"><enum>8333a.</enum><header>Expulsion from Congress</header> 
<subsection id="HE4A95EE544544B858709A9EC06F6B227"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Noncreditability of member service</header><text>If an individual is expelled from Congress, all Member service previously performed by such individual shall be noncreditable for purposes of determining eligibility for or the amount of any annuity which might otherwise be payable out of the Fund based on the service of such individual under this subchapter.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC11F16AD76F04D388D0F5E5130865521"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Refund of contributions and deposits</header><text>If an individual’s Member service becomes noncreditable by reason of subsection (a), that portion of such individual’s lump-sum credit which is attributable to such Member service (less any amount previously refunded or paid as annuity benefits) shall, on proper application, be payable to such individual or, if deceased, to the appropriate person determined under section 8342.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0E0FCC3E6A754CDAAC2A7B905C20E9B5"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Amounts properly paid not affected</header><text>An individual whose Member service is made noncreditable by reason of subsection (a) is not thereafter required to repay any part of an annuity under this subchapter otherwise properly paid to such individual before the date of the expulsion, if any.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HAA446664104A43D099042C9A79881F21"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Coordination provision</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be considered to supersede or otherwise affect the application of subchapter II.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H31BC31842484439288900E3DA195099D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Office of Personnel Management shall prescribe any regulations necessary to carry out the purposes of this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="HD0A89C7F9F9C46AD9CEFF31AD8277277"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/83">chapter 83</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/8333">section 8333</external-xref> the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="H02EC3DF0A08B48C0A1DD8C29528124D7" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> 
<toc-entry level="section">8333a. Expulsion from Congress.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
<section id="H7C9A26DCDDED4153A3DD2B3BB36CB5AA"><enum>3.</enum><header>Provisions relating to the federal employees’ retirement system</header> 
<subsection id="HE5929D09C7DF4F018A56068FC6D7949D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/84">Chapter 84</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/8410">section 8410</external-xref> the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H6299F23EAD634493ABB31D76EFBE3A67" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <section id="H53F97812EFC34927971F29D6FB85EF67"><enum>8410a.</enum><header>Expulsion from Congress</header> <subsection id="H1ED99FBF99F64CD5A9F968327533D27E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Noncreditability of member service</header><text>If an individual is expelled from Congress, all Member service previously performed by such individual shall be noncreditable for purposes of determining eligibility for or the amount of any annuity which might otherwise be payable out of the Fund based on the service of such individual under this chapter.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H36C11C220BCE4DF69BA648FC0D915A32"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Refund of contributions and deposits</header><text>If an individual’s Member service becomes noncreditable by reason of subsection (a), that portion of such individual’s lump-sum credit which is attributable to such Member service (less any amount previously refunded or paid as annuity benefits) shall, on proper application, be payable to such individual or, if deceased, to the appropriate person determined under section 8424.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HBB14DDC5849D4719BC3AF73EC335B18F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Amounts properly paid not affected</header><text>An individual whose Member service is made noncreditable by reason of subsection (a) is not thereafter required to repay any part of an annuity under this chapter otherwise properly paid to such individual before the date of the expulsion, if any.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE87E02101CB94378AC9D5BEC3453534B"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Forfeiture of government contributions to thrift savings plan</header><text>If an individual’s Member service becomes noncreditable by reason of subsection (a), all contributions made by the Government for the benefit of that individual under section 8432(c) while that individual was performing Member service, and all earnings attributable to such contributions, shall be forfeited.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5CA9CA20BECE4F0FB4F25E0D126B4A77"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Coordination provision</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be considered to supersede or otherwise affect the application of subchapter II of chapter 83.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7D685F870FBF4CCA81C96D3AC148C205"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>For the purpose of this section, the term <quote>Member service</quote> means, in the case of an individual subject to this chapter, service performed by such individual as a Member (as defined by section 8331 or 8401), including the period from the date of the beginning of the term for which elected or appointed to the date on which he takes office as such a Member.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8DEF715A30B249FFB61877798E915585"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>The Office of Personnel Management shall prescribe any regulations necessary to carry out the purposes of this section, including provisions for the reduction or elimination of any payment under section 8421 and any other similar payment under this chapter supplemental to any annuity or survivor annuity reduced or eliminated under subsection (a).</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="H9EF36C4D5AF84DCCBC31947CCA9F6387"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/84">chapter 84</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by inserting after the item relating to <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/8410">section 8410</external-xref> the following:</text> <quoted-block style="USC" id="H2BB35860489B4F919B1F8385C72B6614" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">8410a. Expulsion from Congress.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> <section id="H0E33FAF0B94B456DA4234D92427880F9"><enum>4.</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Sections 8433(a) and 8437(d) of title 5, United States Code, are amended by inserting <quote>or 8410a(d)</quote> after <quote>8432(g)</quote>.</text></section> 
<section id="H2AE523D0FAE442FE90BA9C28476F1954"><enum>5.</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The amendments made by this Act shall apply with respect to any expulsion which is based, in whole or in part, on any act committed or conduct engaged in after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

