<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H76614AEF835647E6A1A42F4AD7A07712" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5006 IH: To direct the Secretary of State to take certain actions for the declassification and publication of materials relating to the Afghanistan withdrawal, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5006</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to take certain actions for the declassification and publication of materials relating to the Afghanistan withdrawal, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFBD3BF1D6DDD417D829D345540EB64C6" style="OLC"><section id="H9CC24AB0E43A4ED3A36F28D8703434D8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Declassification review and publication of materials relating to Afghanistan withdrawal</header><subsection id="HD918E2A7C52E42398EF11A72DE066F6D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the American people deserve to understand the events and decision-making which resulted in the chaotic withdrawal of United States personnel from Afghanistan in 2021.</text></subsection><subsection id="H475140653DC84CA189AA6CDAE441CB90"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Dissent channel cable relating to Afghanistan withdrawal</header><paragraph id="H1838220D28654EA2AEE531541CE33FED"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><subparagraph id="HDD5D2880A6804E4EBDADCF90938F4F03"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>Not later than 5 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a complete (and, except as provided in subparagraph (B), unredacted) copy of—</text><clause id="H351B9F132C444057B840EB5C311D0742"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the dissent channel cable of the Department of State written on or about July 13, 2021, describing the likely consequences of United States withdrawal from Afghanistan; and</text></clause><clause id="HFC7A1DBD62FB47B595E99C12C6F41D1F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the official response of the Department of State with respect to such dissent channel cable.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCCB1897C0FC4CD997A9112B13F1EADC"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Authorized redactions</header><text>The Secretary may redact the name of any signatory to the dissent channel cable specified in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D5FBAD6FFA4498FB3BB7ED0FC4DD8D8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Declassification review; publication</header><subparagraph id="H389AF4637A984287BF1292127BDFD8DE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall—</text><clause id="H16E9EFE7C3F845058E57E76B336A4AC3" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">complete a declassification review to determine what, if any, information contained within the dissent channel cable or the official response specified in paragraph (1)(A) may be declassified in accordance with the standards under subsection (d);</text></clause><clause id="H513694D06B95417D81DF74E6F048F3BB"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">declassify any information so determined; and</text></clause><clause id="H2B30128F7444402980450B4E818E12E9"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>publish on a publicly available internet website of the Department of State such dissent channel cable and official response, in unclassified form and containing, in addition to any information previously unclassified, any other information declassified as a result of such declassification review.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC515C143DC794B25B3171916168EB955"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Required redactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In publishing the dissent channel cable pursuant to subparagraph (A)(iii), the Secretary shall redact the name, and any other personally identifiable information, of each signatory to such dissent channel cable.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B624EB8151E47C593176F8E95416A98"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Declassification and publication of after-Action review of Department of State</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of State shall—</text><paragraph id="H03135AEC6A684CC88CCC4C2C8E5A47FD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>complete a declassification review to determine what, if any, additional information contained within the after-action review of the Department of State developed with respect to the Afghanistan withdrawal (in this section, referred to as the <quote>after-action review</quote>) may be declassified in accordance with the standards under subsection (d);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF23E868D1E6E442BBFDB31CE56AC7017"><enum>(2)</enum><text>declassify any information so determined; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8AC9A7D685414E2DB50E018507239B09"><enum>(3)</enum><text>publish on a publicly available internet website of the Department of State a complete version of such after-action review containing, in addition to information previously unclassified, any other information declassified as a result of such declassification review.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H498D2F6FABB340BBA7D4E37173BA60FF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Standards for declassification</header><text>In conducting each declassification review under this section with respect to given information, the Secretary of State shall declassify such information unless the Secretary determines the declassification would be incompatible with the national security interests of the United States or otherwise inconsistent with the protection of intelligence sources and methods.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

