<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF396AAD6F8E54993B904BBC049651FE8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2427 IH: Hmong Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-30</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2427</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230330">March 30, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000576">Mr. Grothman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Z000018">Mr. Zinke</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000299">Mr. Johnson of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001052">Mr. Harris</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001096">Ms. Hageman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001108">Mr. Comer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001051">Mr. Carter of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000377">Ms. Granger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000165">Mr. Tiffany</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001213">Mr. Steil</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000471">Mr. Fitzgerald</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001205">Mrs. Miller of West Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000589">Mrs. Lesko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001095">Mr. Hunt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000821">Mr. Westerman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000135">Mr. Van Orden</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000467">Mr. Thompson of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000478">Mr. Fry</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000401">Mr. Kiley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="O000086">Mr. Owens</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To award a Congressional Gold Medal to the Hmong people, in recognition of their highly distinguished service in the Vietnam war and the fight against communism.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H250BD26104204B89A163DDB31266AD37" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H169F5FAB9CBF45F8B65CE0ADB7AD8EF9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Hmong Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H55D648B0B6D246B19C3D297C58F257B7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HF450DFB54A7B4525BB2CCCE796C7586B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>As the Vietnam war spread south and west into Laos, the Central Intelligence Agency recruited and trained Hmong tribesmen to fight back against the communist North Vietnamese and Pathet Lao.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE659F6E34209454A8F3D41595603BF6B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Over 30,000 Hmong men fought the ground war, flew combat missions, gathered intelligence on North Vietnamese troop movements, interrupted the Ho-Chi-Min Supply Trail, and rescued American pilots downed behind enemy lines.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H70493BA7F63B444C9F2AD98E2B2C6CC9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Hmong people suffered heavy casualties, and their soldiers died at a rate ten times as high as that of American soldiers in Vietnam.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE666D4EEA022434FAB619E78F55D935B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Following the Vietnam war, many Hmong were displaced from their villages as they were either bombed or burned down by the North Vietnamese and over 150,000 Hmong fled Laos when the nation fell to communist forces on May 14, 1975.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF9995CD07C45419A91502F9850DC115A"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Due to their ties to the American military, many Hmong who fled Laos came to the United States as refugees to start a new life.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD1D2ADA3A02746ECBA465594607C07BA"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Currently, there are over 327,000 Hmong living in the United States, with the majority residing in California, Minnesota, and Wisconsin.</text></paragraph></section> 
<section id="HDAE1F6E0E5804AE197F2593764A51E2F"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header> 
<subsection id="H4150635C327641019F92E8467C7BDBA6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presentation authorized</header><text>The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the presentation, on behalf of the Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design to the Hmong people, in recognition of their highly distinguished service in the Vietnam war and the fight against communism.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H6EDF0C34D33D42CB8A297D4324AFB84C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text>For the purposes of the presentation referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (referred to in this Act as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike a gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H3839C494EAB542C59DC7191833DAF877"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Smithsonian institution</header> 
<paragraph id="HA2F49AD436834DAFBAE9D1AB647C1028"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Following the award of the gold medal under subsection (a), the gold medal shall be given to the Smithsonian Institution, where it shall be available for display as appropriate and made available for research.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H72203B2B1BD04ABDBE9E9BD8F6F4164B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Smithsonian Institution should make the gold medal received under paragraph (1) available for display elsewhere, particularly at other appropriate locations associated with the Hmong people’s service in the Vietnam war, and that preference should be given to locations affiliated with the Smithsonian Institution.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HD22BDE95E80C4550B32AFA2B35B3FA13"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck pursuant to section 3 under such regulations as the Secretary may prescribe, at a price sufficient to cover the cost thereof, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></section> <section id="H0DF8B212C63E4A6A9A30F4C2C7753E78"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header> <subsection id="HCEDBFD7EC1D84CDA8BF7B61BBC148F56"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text>The medals struck pursuant to this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H692868D7A5AF4D2EB734C3720920BD78"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of section 5134 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

