<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H673BACDA113D46CF917914E21E8C47C7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5516 IH: To amend title 38, United States Code, to clarify the employment and reemployment rights of members of the uniformed services to other law.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5516</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to clarify the employment and reemployment rights of members of the uniformed services to other law.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4741C63A1FFC4ABE99E03A3FF0CFC78C" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H38017835F9D040149E4288E1A10CB207" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Clarifications regarding scope of employment and reemployment rights of members of the uniformed services</header>
<subsection id="H8A4C3C332B23443E950657B25E72D7CB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Clarification regarding definition of rights and benefits</header><text>Section 4303(2) of title 38, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H4AD55A4366DF44BF982327CA207B58D3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>—</quote> after <quote><quote>rights and benefits</quote></quote>;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1D5F8A0FEAE74585B45E33E508FC3D41"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by redesignating the text beginning with <quote>means</quote> and ending with <quote>employment.</quote> as a subparagraph (A);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4883A8DC5BF5417BBF55C8ABCC7025A6"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in such subparagraph (A), as so redesignated, by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HCD363E8156FE4631861CC742A32355DE"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> <quoted-block id="HBAB7DC74A7CE4450A770C17712310AA0" style="OLC"> <subparagraph id="H32AE33115E3C4A7D8148114F09007C61" display-inline="no-display-inline" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes any procedural protections or provisions set forth in this chapter.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="HD7276AB7142E45EEA5684163AA795A44"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clarification regarding relation to other law and plans for agreements</header><text>Section 4302 of such title is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> <quoted-block id="H583876AA0F1B4E0BA7ED8FB4F733147B" style="OLC"> <subsection id="H231E270A250848EA8028CD76D8FDAA50"><enum>(c)</enum> <paragraph id="H3200ECF8ECF340ABAC8A90F8EEC8559B" display-inline="yes-display-inline"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Pursuant to this section and the procedural rights afforded by subchapter III of this chapter, any agreement to arbitrate a claim under this chapter is unenforceable, unless all parties consent to arbitration after a complaint on the specific claim has been filed in court or with the Merit Systems Protection Board and all parties knowingly and voluntarily consent to have that particular claim subjected to arbitration.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4A6BD40A18C54E399DA78C74B6F741E1" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>For purposes of this subsection, consent shall not be considered voluntary when a person is required to agree to arbitrate an action, complaint, or claim alleging a violation of this chapter as a condition of future or continued employment, advancement in employment, or receipt of any right or benefit of employment.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

