<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFA6C2A9FEDB44F8F98375BEAB733146F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2838 IH: National Association for Stock Car Auto Racing (NASCAR) 75th Anniversary Commemorative Coin Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2838</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230425">April 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000577">Mr. Graves of Louisiana</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="J000308">Mr. Jackson of North Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of the Treasury to mint coins in commemoration of the 75th anniversary of what is recognized as the first sanctioning body created to promote a unified series of competitions, with an organized group of race car drivers. The first such recognized race was held at Daytona Beach on February 15, 1948, under the sanctioning of the <quote>National Association for Stock Car Auto Racing</quote> (NASCAR).</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAA8DF9AF9CEB468F8DF8ACC84601A757" style="OLC"><section id="HBBB9789AFCBE46DFB22C8F52443117F4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>National Association for Stock Car Auto Racing (NASCAR) 75th Anniversary Commemorative Coin Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDE26DCDFB3CE428699904E64047B1EA9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HD2B6A094A3034149A6747BAF50070D67"><enum>(1)</enum><text>On February 15, 2023, the National Association for Stock Car Auto Racing (NASCAR) observed the 75th anniversary of the first race hosted by a sanctioning body, held at Daytona Beach, Florida.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBAD0B7BC2424E9498BE33A5AB64F47F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>In December 1947, Bill France, Sr., organized several meetings at the Streamline Hotel in Daytona Beach, Florida, at which time his vision of an organized group of race car drivers was conceived.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H20DA2ECB93244CBDA8EC8BE796443417"><enum>(3)</enum><text>On February 15, 1948, Red Bryon won the first sanctioned body event, defeating Marshall Teague on the Daytona Beach road course.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H251A271D8D084F3D8FF134E8A9CC4B75"><enum>(4)</enum><text>More than 41,000 fans attended the Inaugural Daytona 500 on February 22, 1959, won by Lee Petty.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41DC94BF9CC240C498F8125AA326E565"><enum>(5)</enum><text>At the Jacksonville, Florida, Speedway on December 1, 1963, Wendell Scott became the first Black driver to win a NASCAR sanctioned race.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H736FFB2F2A0740A3AF0E0D8EECFE5888"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In 1977, Janet Guthrie became the first woman to compete in the Daytona 500.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3349FF91D9BF4D199E2DA55CEE667C57"><enum>(7)</enum><text>On February 18, 1979, CBS televised the first live coverage of the Daytona 500.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4E27B955B9AE4057B44DBDF04523614E"><enum>(8)</enum><text>In August 1994, the Indianapolis Motor Speedway was added to the race schedule.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50D57CC60689406E8AF3D802C8A13703"><enum>(9)</enum><text>Betty Jane France founded The NASCAR Foundation in 2006, supporting causes that work to improve the lives of children in need.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B2132D8D4EF4614B351ECE94E7AF6E7"><enum>(10)</enum><text>On May 23, 2020, the inaugural NASCAR Hall of Fame class (Bill France, Sr., Bill France, Jr., Richard Petty, Dale Earnhardt, and Junior Johnson) is inducted in Charlotte, North Carolina.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7545932482CE407E95EE5D37167B4A6E"><enum>(11)</enum><text>Danica Patrick becomes the first female to win a pole in the Daytona 500 in 2013.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H985889F9E667486CB2383E6A213DB2D4"><enum>(12)</enum><text>Jimmie Johnson makes history with his record-tying seventh race championship on November 20, 2016.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A269F6CC76844FCAC1FAE7E2FCD0AA1"><enum>(13)</enum><text>Before a sold-out crowd of 101,500 fans at the Daytona International Speedway on February 20, 2022, the Next-Gen car debuted in the 64th annual Daytona 500.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAD12B3E0567D4F95A8196E6C2A92C7BB"><enum>(14)</enum><text>NASCAR has grown from the small organization formed on the sands of Daytona Beach to one of the most popular sports in the world.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HF3A2C616104647B4889CE48AEEB5032D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Coin specifications</header><subsection id="HF2CD1E2416E74A458B50AA195B281E29"><enum>(a)</enum><header>$1 silver coins</header><text>The Secretary of the Treasury (hereafter in this Act referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall mint and issue $1 coins in recognition of the NASCAR 75th anniversary, which shall—</text><paragraph id="HE4A69BC79D384E12A4FD5F903451BE21"><enum>(1)</enum><text>weigh 26.73 grams;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFFC1B53440A64B749ECFA567D7972C3E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>have a diameter of 1.500 inches; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H736C1FDCC43A4B208558EB4BE924FA5D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>contain not less than 90 percent silver.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAE75194339B342A79F700C27D3892196"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Legal tender</header><text>The coins minted under this Act shall be legal tender, as provided in section 5103 of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9D3F84F6C7B143EF99CC42913F613706"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of sections 5134 and 5136 of title 31, United States Code, all coins minted under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section><section id="HB49A484273B64498A16AE82694E767EB"><enum>4.</enum><header>Designs of coins</header><subsection id="H0208C80E738B41AD8658356C9DCDA622"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Design requirements</header><paragraph id="HF6464CFFD5094BCA80EBC0A18DDE5ED7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The design of coins minted under this Act shall be emblematic of the National Association for Stock Car Auto Racing and the competitive spirit of American auto racing enthusiasts.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DE93147F4A747CBAFB3090BD7BB00EE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Designs and inscriptions</header><text>On the coin minted under this Act, there shall be—</text><subparagraph id="H94C6546CE3564EF1AFB2489064D2337A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a designation of the value of the coin;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4B223D9A95B44F96BFA90D41FF1B3D99"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an inscription of the year <quote>2023</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0B45B597C4A43CAA920B1344E7135EC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>inscriptions of the words <quote>Liberty</quote>, <quote>In God We Trust</quote>, <quote>United States of America</quote>, and <quote>E Pluribus Unum</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA5F923060392409292389D48C2F74103"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Selection</header><text>The designs for the coins minted under this Act shall be—</text><paragraph id="H4B6193FCF30D4B4BBC7A6CA2068A3770"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">selected by the Secretary, after consultation with the NASCAR Foundation and the Commission of Fine Arts; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H31C292FF509B4241B970FAB1C774E35B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>reviewed by the Citizens Coinage Advisory Committee.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H76DA5F9134DF4532B7A7235CC8E6EBC1"><enum>5.</enum><header>Issuance of coins</header><subsection id="H37171A3D4C624E0AB7788CA4C1D8D6A8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Quality of coins</header><text>Coins minted under this Act shall be issued in uncirculated and proof qualities.</text></subsection><subsection id="H28B6A2AAEC2A4579B06B3F5BE95F8518"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Mint facility</header><text>Only 1 facility in the United States Mint may be used to strike any particular quality of the coins minted under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3BF83E30DBC149FDB0EB170883733311"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Period for issuance</header><text>The Secretary may issue coins minted under this Act only during the 1-year period beginning on January 1, 2023.</text></subsection></section><section id="H7CC5D96DAAE543B78449BDED76C76961"><enum>6.</enum><header>Sale of coins</header><subsection id="HD3CFD6B4CBDA433EAA078B24AF2B9A71"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sale price</header><text>The coins issued under this Act shall be sold by the Secretary at a price equal to the sum of—</text><paragraph id="H7AB4113359FC46EFA4FE4B4068F4F6F6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the face value of the coins;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF6C01D1679E4AD08250F52529D96C2A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the surcharge provided in section 7(a) with respect to such coins; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A7BF2CF130C401AB8A6CD8748D1DC4F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the cost of designing and issuing the coins (including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, overhead expenses, marketing, and shipping).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H10D8889061414CBA8204E4E959276F5E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Bulk sales</header><text>The Secretary shall make bulk sales of the coins issued under this Act at a reasonable discount.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEE57D0C795A34410874647A2D3F4EC40"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Prepaid orders</header><paragraph id="H09A972074875422CA073779B2DA5BF54"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall accept prepaid orders for the coins minted under this Act before the issuance of such coins.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB591B371F1AF4894A7D2512234371A9E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Discount</header><text>Sale prices with respect to prepaid orders under paragraph (1) shall be at a reasonable discount.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC691E68C52494C74917B55DADE13215C"><enum>7.</enum><header>Surcharges</header><subsection id="H9FD65DD54BC24EE48899B81FC7E73EE6"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>All sales of coins issued under this Act shall include a surcharge of $20 per coin for the $1 coin.</text></subsection><subsection id="H836427E7A9BE42E1A88E8CCA7B099800"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Distribution</header><text>Subject to section 5134(f)(1) of title 31, United States Code, all surcharges received by the Secretary from the sale of coins issued under this Act shall be promptly paid by the Secretary to The NASCAR Foundation for application to general expenses associated with the fulfillment of the mission of The NASCAR Foundation.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2EDA5B17D6FE42439B9254ABAF97A119"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Audits</header><text>The Comptroller General of the United States shall have the right to examine such books, records, documents, and other data of each of the organizations referred to in subsection (b) as may be related to the expenditures of amounts paid under that subsection.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE285F534A9EA468183E709820E73A6F3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text>Notwithstanding subsection (a), no surcharge may be included with respect to the issuance under this Act of any coin during a calendar year if, as a result of the time of such issuance, the issuance of such coin would result in the number of commemorative coin programs issued during such year to exceed the annual 2 commemorative coin program issuance limitation under section 5112 (m)(1) of title 31, United States Code (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this Act). The Secretary of the Treasury may issue guidance to carry out this subsection.</text></subsection></section><section id="H9CB34C8DF9914DB48B5BC7A4BA520F9E"><enum>8.</enum><header>Financial assurances</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary shall take such actions as may be necessary to ensure that—</text><paragraph id="H3AD9978607C8424DAFC58B991934C86F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>minting and issuing coins under this Act will not result in any net cost to the United States Government; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD67D2E78B3CB4A92A95A4F7236596709"><enum>(2)</enum><text>no funds, including applicable surcharges, are disbursed to any recipient designated in section 7 until the total cost of designing and issuing all of the coins authorized by this Act (including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, overhead expenses, marketing, and shipping) is recovered by the United States Treasury, consistent with sections 5112(m) and 5134(f) of title 31, United States Code.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HC0E869A20FEB4A1EAF1A003202805D9B"><enum>9.</enum><header>Budgetary effects</header><subsection id="HBD527B3DE77241E290F8912EF79A9023"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Statutory pAYGO scorecards</header><text>The budgetary effects of this section shall not be entered on either PAYGO Scorecard maintained pursuant to section 4(d) of the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010 (U.S.C. 933(d)).</text></subsection><subsection id="H5DC892DFD093440B86E8CC213E48D1E6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Senate pAYGO scorecards</header><text>The budgetary effects of this section shall not be entered on any PAYGO scorecard maintained for purposes of section 4105 of H. Con. Res.71 (115th Congress).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

