<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF8AEA432E65D48E19DA7F0F0325B8EA7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2512 IH: Congressional Foreign Entanglement Disclosure and Reduction Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2512</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230406">April 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to require Members of Congress to disclose business ties with foreign entities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H8F07DBBEEE7043FC8813F6A2E126EB9D" style="OLC"><section id="HC65845368D1B429DB8BA024C873DEB15" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Congressional Foreign Entanglement Disclosure and Reduction Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDA9459F712C34DDC87E0DF46CA1FAA83" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Disclosure by Members of Congress of business ties with foreign entities</header><subsection id="HE91BBCD3189245E1A01684A91407D633"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 13104 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2026465922EE4825972B084CA4ABE4CA" style="OLC"><subsection id="H0BCF418FB66A410AAB526152C5B0A36D"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Foreign entity business ties of Members of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any report filed pursuant to section 13103(d) by a Member of Congress shall include the disclosure of any business ties the Member or any member of the Member’s immediate family has (if any) with a foreign entity. If a Member of Congress makes an affirmative disclosure of any such ties, the Member shall include information detailing the nature of the business tie, the name of the applicable foreign entity, and the total value of any income received by the Member or immediate family member as a result of such tie during the calendar year covered by the report submitted pursuant to such section 13103(d) and the preceding four calendar years.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HBBE910415E994B33B263C1219DE93BE0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (a) shall apply to any report filed pursuant to section 13103(d) of title 5, United States Code, after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

