<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC704D3CD75A3450CB2A07C5CBFD82803" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5557 IH: Combatting Foreign Surveillance Spyware Sanctions Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5557</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230919">September 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To impose sanctions against certain persons engaged in the proliferation or use of foreign commercial spyware, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF7F8A58979054BA6A3EEBA221B644E5A" style="OLC"><section id="HCE373C9E6ECB4DF8B574E65F99BBDB79" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Combatting Foreign Surveillance Spyware Sanctions Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H13F64356038C4E1B8F23A6B4AE45D398" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sanctions for proliferation or use of foreign commercial spyware</header><subsection id="H259AD4DC0F4E4C7AB525B61F681DDDCB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Policy</header><text>It is the policy of the United States—</text><paragraph id="H019B4C177D8B41F1A12416FF8CF5B7C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to act decisively against counterintelligence threats posed by foreign commercial spyware by degrading the ability of companies selling foreign commercial spyware to provide their services to users who act contrary to the national security or foreign policy interests of the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0B77DB13B8248DE8276202F02C71F59"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to act decisively against the individuals who lead entities selling foreign commercial spyware and who are involved in activities contrary to the national security or foreign policy interests of the United States; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H97E8F376C6734F22B6EE8A6972224C8A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>to deter the use of foreign commercial spyware for improper purposes, such as to—</text><subparagraph id="H3BD2A979092649E69DC5262B0DE01282"><enum>(A)</enum><text>target and intimidate perceived opponents;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H116D0FCD1F0D4D5585C6BED45C328F91"><enum>(B)</enum><text>curb dissent;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15287A65A7854ED583905B4D66AA06A0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>limit freedoms of expression, peaceful assembly, or association;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H52F3A72F5BFA4B06B449AAC69B535EC6"><enum>(D)</enum><text>enable other human rights abuses or suppression of civil liberties; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4E3076413DA9408DA7910C7EC3BFE358"><enum>(E)</enum><text>track or target United States persons.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC95167D703A46B9A937F38BE3B3DF31"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Discretionary sanctions</header><text>In order to advance the policy objectives under subsection (a), the President may impose the sanctions described in subsection (c) with respect to—</text><paragraph id="H23AE9ABEAD6B4785963099D40EE97676"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a covered entity the President determines to pose a risk to the national security of the United States which knowingly develops, maintains, owns, operates, brokers, markets, sells, leases, licenses, or otherwise makes available spyware that has enabled the targeting of United States Government officials, or personnel of the intelligence community;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB4C340152EFD43769A727197DC849537"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any foreign person who—</text><subparagraph id="H6EC00F533ABA486C987075D5F283B4C7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a current or former senior officer of an entity described in paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H507998A0A5324F9EA9343E8700626B6D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly engages in the sale of foreign commercial spyware that allows for the targeting of United States Government officials, or personnel of the intelligence community; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HD4EBB94B99B3459898777A1CD7BA2801"><enum>(3)</enum><text>any foreign person who—</text><subparagraph id="H480262DE15764D8CBF34E0A35E895C2B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is an official of a foreign government or is acting for or on behalf of such official; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1577FF0738F44CDAC73CFCC0D3F740A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">knowingly engages in the targeting of United States Government officials, or personnel of the intelligence community through the use of foreign commercial spyware.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H501EB5FCF0344BD6BEFF289DE6DEC9DB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H768B8548DD2448C3A25A6CBFA7C715E7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text>The President may exercise all of the powers granted to the President under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) (except that the requirements of section 202 of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref>) shall not apply) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in property and interests in property of a person determined by the President to be subject to subsection (b) if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9EB8E37BE83F44F49E6185521EB983B0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inadmissibility to the United States and revocation of visa or other documentation</header><subparagraph id="HA42444D95A894E709A1F8FED7D320C5B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visa, admission, or parole</header><text>In the case of a foreign person determined by the President to be subject to subsection (b) who is an individual, the foreign person is—</text><clause id="HEBCDCBD81AB4458EA8C82476C393A8F1"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></clause><clause id="H309A1A376BAA4DBA97E5706C5CCB1FB7"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></clause><clause id="H41904D80EF7F45D0B03FD07BB5F009AE"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9260BBFCF9104B03A39D012F9735DD7F"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Current visa revoked</header><text>In the case of a foreign person determined by the President to be subject to subsection (b) who is an individual, the visa or other entry documentation of the person shall be revoked, regardless of when such visa or other entry documentation is or was issued. A revocation under this subparagraph shall take effect immediately and automatically cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the person’s possession.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAE419CCB31C24CE38220965A743E4ABB"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Exception to comply with international obligations</header><text>Sanctions under this subsection shall not apply with respect to a foreign person if admitting or paroling the person into the United States is necessary to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF36208ACB23044369CBE291EAE3907D3"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Implementation; penalties</header><paragraph id="HFACD76BB286742F9B181493C08BD581B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The President may exercise all authorities provided under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to carry out this subsection and shall issue such regulations, licenses, and orders as are necessary to carry out this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC871B510B7C4D7D9071BF3260B2D426"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Any person that violates, attempts to violate, conspires to violate, or causes a violation of this subsection or any regulation, license, or order issued to carry out paragraph (1) shall be subject to the penalties provided for in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H518AAA2B6F854EA5B8A16B9731092046"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Intelligence and law enforcement activities</header><text>Sanctions under this section shall not apply with respect to—</text><paragraph id="H4D2AA7FFDA9542E5B444C23BD9030166"><enum>(1)</enum><text>any activity subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B48AF7990C54598845929EBC7812178"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any authorized intelligence or law enforcement activities of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8BC271544EA54C628397572DF597A14D"><enum>(f)</enum><header>United states government activities</header><text>Nothing in this Act may be construed to prohibit transactions associated with the official business of the Federal Government as carried out by employees, grantees, or contractors.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5392301996064DEF82546F165E8E2480"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Humanitarian activities</header><text>The President may not impose sanctions under this section with respect to any person for conducting or facilitating a transaction for the sale of agricultural commodities, food, medicine, or medical devices or for the provision of humanitarian assistance.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCE2BCB8C7D5347839D68F30FDB150A5E"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Exception relating to importation of goods</header><paragraph id="H05EE46C43F854B6CBD39910E0D7488F4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The authorities to impose sanctions authorized under this section shall not include the authority to impose sanctions on the importation of goods.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0317AC735684016A9D8096C7A710FE4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Good defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>good</quote> means any article, natural, or manmade substance, material, supply, or manufactured product, including inspection and test equipment, and excluding technical data.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4023A7DB3E5A42D1AFB6BC99F8408805"><enum>(i)</enum><header>International financial institutions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of the Treasury may instruct the United States Executive Director at the international financial institutions (as defined under section 1701(c) of the International Financial Institutions Act) to use the voice and vote of the United States to oppose financial assistance to a foreign government that the Secretary finds has targeted United States Government officials or personnel of the intelligence community with foreign commercial spyware. </text></subsection><subsection id="H77DADD018CDA4459A3787EAF41742098"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Sunset</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority to impose a new sanction under subsection (b) shall terminate on the date that is 7 years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H24D0294A248D46CE840731A313EF628A"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H2629CE2BB40B4982B79B79F4238F29A6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Foreign commercial spyware; foreign company; spyware; covered entity</header><text>The terms <quote>foreign commercial spyware</quote>, <quote>foreign company</quote>, <quote>spyware</quote>, and <quote>covered entity</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 1102A of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3231">50 U.S.C. 3231 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H51F70B1B6B234CE794AF94AF8A46843F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign person</header><text>The term <quote>foreign person</quote> means a person that is not a United States person.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE980DFDE38314748B59F58BFFD0C797D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Knowingly</header><text>The term <quote>knowingly</quote> with respect to conduct, a circumstance, or a result, means that a person has actual knowledge, or should have known, of the conduct, the circumstance, or the result.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1B5F954CFD5949B884621CBA39C5CB1E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>United States person</header><text>The term <quote>United States person</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H5E86C90A6A814F8EAC497F03C585B3F9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen or an alien lawfully admitted for permanent residence to the United States;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A4E03B64B18407DAE5F6B58180A5255"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD22EE5A01E294EB78BB5B59AD2BEF518"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a person in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

