<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H479EEBF6C8EB42789435C8B57647CFE2" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3664 IH: To prohibit the availability of Federal funds to the World Health Organization pending the conduct of an investigation relating to the influence over such organization by Chinese Communist Party, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3664</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001222">Mr. Santos</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the availability of Federal funds to the World Health Organization pending the conduct of an investigation relating to the influence over such organization by Chinese Communist Party, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD21F976A8DC54D86825722C0C5F769B6" style="OLC"><section id="HCEFD8508B7B34916B720D753DA31FBF3" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal funding to World Health Organization pending investigation</header><subsection id="H75D1037822FC4C088F22CFCDE907BF67"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no Federal funds may be made available, directly or indirectly, to the World Health Organization until the President—</text><paragraph id="H472A4E54154641E687C1512C9D04CE41"><enum>(1)</enum><text>conducts an investigation, with the compliance of the Director-General of the World Health Organization, to assess and determine the level of influence by the Chinese Communist Party over the operations of the World Health Organization (including with respect to influence regarding the origin of COVID–19 and any coverup relating to such origin); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8D8160F1B468400AB1BADEA3352A201B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submits to the appropriate congressional recipients a report containing the findings of such investigation.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD40F0F891C9F4FCE965DBC22F25F6B49"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional recipients defined</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>appropriate congressional recipients</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="HBE9C43C071144E00998AB177725DE43D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary and the Committee on Ways and Means of the House of Representatives;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4548771863B429581B1E8443A6F61AF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on the Judiciary and the Committee on Finance of the Senate;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDA3B784D83C846E29764545F641CCBC9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Speaker and minority leader of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22C200F0EBF0471398FA77673F939CED"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the majority leader and minority leader of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

