<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H031133928AA84F0AAFD92FEC7ED19143" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4969 IH: Ending the Cycle of Dependency Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4969</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001316">Mr. Burlison</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="B001317">Mr. Brecheen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 to restore and standardize work requirements for able-bodied adults enrolled in the supplemental nutrition assistance program and limit participation to 5 years for able-bodied adults.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5D154AB066DB4527AA62777F65E537ED" style="OLC"><section id="HE5912641FB98444280E8DAE3BD8413A4" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Ending the Cycle of Dependency Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HDC00E14E2D834C889A8BA76B0E2E099F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Modification of work requirement exemptions for able-bodied adults in the supplemental nutrition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(o)(3) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2015">7 U.S.C. 2015(o)(3)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="HF39027690F654C958E7D24015077BA50" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H7064CC5EACCE401284B21AF0FF665C63"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Paragraph (2) shall not apply to an individual if the individual is—</text><subparagraph id="H63705F40ED76468FB6C021D001C6F7CE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>under 18 or over 65 years of age;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD599F566A25440393E4FC137EC33173"><enum>(B)</enum><text>medically certified as physically or mentally unfit for employment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F5893DAACE040CF9E0EBF03640F9A5E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a parent or other member of a household with primary responsibility for a dependent child under 6 years of age;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0DBCEFC68FEE45C486EC7F709FD2C01C"><enum>(D)</enum><text>otherwise exempt under subsection (d)(2); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCBC02DEF1485437CB259E0C1D0C73D08"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a pregnant woman.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H3586F676E731424FB3A4B921ED164ABD"><enum>3.</enum><header>Repealing waiver of geographic work requirements in the supplemental nutrition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(o)(4) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2015">7 U.S.C. 2015(o)(4)</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></section><section id="H2E9633D2557F4906A8B85886B387ED72"><enum>4.</enum><header>Eliminating no good cause work requirements exceptions in the supplemental nutrition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(o)(6) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2015">7 U.S.C. 2015(o)(6)</external-xref>) is repealed.</text></section><section id="H36556960A8BA47FAB5C1C52DB52F4C52"><enum>5.</enum><header>Standardizing work requirement age limit rules in the supplemental nutrition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(d)(1)(A) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2015">7 U.S.C. 2015(d)(1)(A)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H5A3718C258B74B9A8D179B36A2660116" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H92DD8B9B0DF140A1BEDAFF4F3C6C7986"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No physically and mentally fit individual over the age of 15 and under the age of 65 shall be eligible to participate in the supplemental nutrition assistance program if the individual—</text><clause id="HE007FFB769F64F02A51C44A583004419"><enum>(i)</enum><text>refuses, at the time of application and every 12 months thereafter, to register for employment in a manner prescribed by the Secretary;</text></clause><clause id="HD84170C0D27049399EFAC093F5F621DE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>refuses without good cause to participate in an employment and training program established under paragraph (4), to the extent required by the State agency;</text></clause><clause id="H06D9D57870E2477E8B2ED0256975B284"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>refuses without good cause to accept an offer of employment, at a site or plant not subject to a strike or lockout at the time of the refusal, at a wage not less than the higher of—</text><subclause id="HDFDFD9D49D854ED2A4E7EBC3C169FB13"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the applicable Federal or State minimum wage; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H2952F46821F5431E937E551C2DC3DBDA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>80 percent of the wage that would have governed had the minimum hourly rate under section 6(a)(1) of the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/206">29 U.S.C. 206(a)(1)</external-xref>) been applicable to the offer of employment;</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HD1C08DB872EB4CF18F5D6779F9C918DE"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>refuses without good cause to provide a State agency with sufficient information to allow the State agency to determine the employment status or the job availability of the individual;</text></clause><clause id="H17E3895FB1F244E1B372B0034A7A32AF"><enum>(v)</enum><text>voluntarily and without good cause—</text><subclause id="H82B3A5FD53C34A28AB64DF2F014C1F13"><enum>(I)</enum><text>quits a job; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H7E0E5F26696340B2BB453AF3F3B0C4CA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>reduces work effort and, after the reduction, the individual is working less than 30 hours per week; or</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H50E4F61A98E848E0B5A79D3C3D5DCECC"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>fails to comply with section 20.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HFCD0A245C7A14C268D175C52B87486B2"><enum>6.</enum><header>Standardizing work requirement exemptions in the supplemental nutrition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6(d)(2) of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2015">7 U.S.C. 2015(d)(2)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3A185F298E4E4BC5987F4714E4741797" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H6969268385274788877BB2940DAD7546"><enum>(2) </enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person who otherwise would be required to comply with the requirements of paragraph (1) of this subsection shall be exempt from such requirements if he or she is (A) currently subject to and complying with a work registration requirement under title IV of the Social Security Act, as amended (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/602">42 U.S.C. 602</external-xref>), or the Federal-State unemployment compensation system, in which case, failure by such person to comply with any work requirement to which such person is subject shall be the same as failure to comply with that requirement of paragraph (1); (B) a parent or other member of a household with primary responsibility for the care of a dependent child under 6 years of age; (C) a bona fide student enrolled at least half time in any recognized school, training program, or institution of higher education (except that any such person enrolled in an institution of higher education shall be ineligible to participate in the supplemental nutrition assistance program unless he or she meets the requirements of subsection (e) of this section); (D) a regular participant in a drug addiction or alcoholic treatment and rehabilitation program; (E) employed a minimum of thirty hours per week or receiving weekly earnings which equal the minimum hourly rate under the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938, as amended (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/206">29 U.S.C. 206(a)(1)</external-xref>), multiplied by thirty hours; or (F) a person between the ages of sixteen and eighteen who is not a head of a household or who is attending school, or enrolled in an employment training program, on at least a half-time basis.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H9C76ED080A4D4E6FA33B2B7730675177"><enum>7.</enum><header>Lifetime benefit limit for able-Bodied adults in the supplemental nutrition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 6 of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2015">7 U.S.C. 2015</external-xref>) is amended by adding a new subsection to read as follows:</text><quoted-block id="H729237EDDF6946559BA83EB581E6825C" style="OLC"><subsection id="H75C2F7B77B52403992B77094E801E22E"><enum>(t)</enum><header>No assistance for able-Bodied enrollees for more than 5 years</header><paragraph id="H4EE5C6F7AD544FC9A68A593C60E4C45D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No member of a household shall be eligible to participate who resides in a household that includes an individual who has participated for 60 months (whether or not consecutive).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H702E0447537644D9B7CE3BD52687814A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Minor child exception</header><text>In determining the number of months for which an individual participated, the State shall disregard any month for which such assistance was provided with respect to the individual and during which the individual was—</text><subparagraph id="H3E6195F26D3E4CEDAE1397C62E90D23C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a minor child; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFFB25E088CEC4EFEB449E431A9D7FDA2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>not the head of a household or married to the head of a household.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4AF4C1F682AD41B2B18CBFD7D8FC34B6"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Additional exceptions</header><text>Paragraph (1) shall not apply to an individual if the individual is—</text><subparagraph id="H5A6C66E79EFA47FF837AE487AF38CDBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>under 18 or over 64 years of age;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD9201CC96464E7383BE33C49FD22D19"><enum>(B)</enum><text>medically certified as physically or mentally unfit for employment;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H13CB8D0F06994603AC65169AD6F9B6CE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a parent or other member of a household with primary responsibility for a dependent child under 6 years of age; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H54B409F7FE784E2A94474472FEAAC043"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a pregnant woman.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HE9854BE8F6C54F239421614C7D04A193" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>8.</enum><header>Repealing suspension of work requirements due to covid–19 for able-bodied adults without dependents in the supplemental nutrition assistance program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2301 of the Families First Coronavirus Response Act (P.L. 116–127, division B, title III, section 2301) is repealed.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

