<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Referred-in-Senate" dms-id="H247D983F49A346FAACA635D34F84E8B1" public-private="public" key="G" bill-type="olc" stage-count="1"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 1176 : Taiwan International Solidarity Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IIB</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1176</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20230726">July 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Received; read twice and referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>AN ACT</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Taiwan Allies International Protection and Enhancement Initiative (TAIPEI) Act of 2019 to provide that the United States, as a member of any international organizations, should oppose any attempts by the People’s Republic of China to resolve Taiwan’s status by distorting the decisions, language, policies, or procedures of the organization, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body id="HC247B1CD580240AA95AB63E3FF3D90FD" style="OLC"><section id="H92F49F5BDD4345439124918976B91889" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Taiwan International Solidarity Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF1AEB987C0844483BF3F2E4F3EC8382F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Clarification regarding United Nations General Assembly Resolution 2758 (XXVI)</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (a) of section 2 of the Taiwan Allies International Protection and Enhancement Initiative (TAIPEI) Act of 2019 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/135">Public Law 116–135</external-xref>) (relating to diplomatic relations with Taiwan) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraphs:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H48146E6E19A64A63AA6BFCCF6E835033" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HEF9DA75F5DC345B49D7399D1391B7A8D"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">United Nations General Assembly Resolution 2758 (XXVI) established the representatives of the Government of the People’s Republic of China as the only lawful representatives of China to the United Nations. The resolution did not address the issue of representation of Taiwan and its people in the United Nations or any related organizations, nor did the resolution take a position on the relationship between the People's Republic of China and Taiwan or include any statement pertaining to Taiwan’s sovereignty.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HACD368159C8C4D35ACACEACA2294B793"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States opposes any initiative that seeks to change Taiwan's status without the consent of the people.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HC5658EE99E0941BCB5D3C45674423411"><enum>3.</enum><header>United States advocacy for international organizations to resist the People’s Republic of China’s efforts to distort the <quote>One China</quote> position</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 4 of the Taiwan Allies International Protection and Enhancement Initiative (TAIPEI) Act of 2019 (relating to the policy of the United States regarding Taiwan’s participation in international organizations) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H598E8EF99B3844B3A3BE3E26CC5E034C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF846D2AC468049E5A1E5E748038AA4DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H410FC036A306402B9AF5DB3268C5A82E"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HA49293F801FA404DA8F656121B408975" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="HEBA969FBD6F2440C920FE0919EE5F6BE"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to instruct, as appropriate, representatives of the United States Government in all organizations described in paragraph (1) to use the voice, vote, and influence of the United States to advocate such organizations to resist the People’s Republic of China’s efforts to distort the decisions, language, policies, or procedures of such organizations regarding Taiwan.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H669C40329BAD4C1FB2AEB26F2125BCE1"><enum>4.</enum><header>Opposing the People’s Republic of China’s efforts to undermine Taiwan’s ties and partnerships internationally</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subsection (a) of section 5 of the Taiwan Allies International Protection and Enhancement Initiative (TAIPEI) Act of 2019 (relating to strengthening ties with Taiwan) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H48C4F73F1FEC4B5FA1BD35838A77207A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CC2C8C497934390B2FB1C8A30E8F71F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H50E99DBDFB0C46659CAE42BF3BC7802D"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H8A73317153BD47459F48A802554509E0" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H009C2B671AE5457E9188619BE4496F5E"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">encourage, as appropriate, United States allies and partners to oppose the People’s Republic of China’s efforts to undermine Taiwan’s official diplomatic relationships and its partnerships with countries with which it does not maintain diplomatic relations.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H56DCAACDE33E4E4683028E75C55C6EB4"><enum>5.</enum><header>Report on the People’s Republic of China’s attempts to promote its <quote>One China</quote> position</header><subsection id="HC244C3933AEF4BE5BF402A419122E666"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (b) of section 5 of the Taiwan Allies International Protection and Enhancement Initiative (TAIPEI) Act of 2019 (relating to strengthening ties with Taiwan) is amended by inserting before the period at the end the following: <quote>, as well as information relating to any prior or ongoing attempts by the People’s Republic of China to undermine Taiwan’s membership or observer status in all organizations described in section (4)(1) and Taiwan’s ties and relationships with other countries in accordance with subsection (a) of this section</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE3F8B0FCF6714305A5279FD80D69A05C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The amendment made by subsection (a) shall take effect on the date of the enactment of this Act and apply beginning with the first report required under subsection (b) of section 5 of the Taiwan Allies International Protection and Enhancement Initiative (TAIPEI) Act of 2019, as amended by subsection (a), that is required after such date.</text></subsection></section></legis-body><attestation><attestation-group><attestation-date date="20230725" chamber="House">Passed the House of Representatives July 25, 2023.</attestation-date><attestor display="yes">Kevin F. McCumber,</attestor><role>Clerk.</role></attestation-group></attestation></bill> 

