<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H47B17ED5B68B4E0C8A3F9A2982459941" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1430 IH: Determination of NEPA Adequacy Streamlining Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1430</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230307">March 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of the Interior and the Secretary of Agriculture to use certain previously completed environmental assessments and environmental impact statements to satisfy the review requirements of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HFE787E613C1D4B0BBFC2343D047A3A87" style="OLC"><section id="H5EA2093487B447259D2AB0E3EB2C8F51" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Determination of NEPA Adequacy Streamlining Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H2D46352B6D3D4ADBB1D91E2D3212B985"><enum>2.</enum><header>Determination of National Environmental Policy Act adequacy</header><subsection id="HB49B011DF60044F5B0EDAAF19E6DCF57"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary concerned shall use previously completed environmental assessments and environmental impact statements to satisfy the requirements of section 102 of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332</external-xref>) with respect to any major Federal action if such Secretary determines that—</text><paragraph id="H06D0706AF9924B3686704BD8B00CA5EF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the new proposed action is substantially the same as a previously analyzed proposed action or alternative analyzed in a previous environmental assessment or environmental impact statement; and </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFCCB6F0CD324B55A39AADC83D885227"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the effects of the proposed action are substantially the same as the effects analyzed in such existing environmental assessments or environmental impact statements. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4458ED8B13C54B25969613C6B50FF7A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Secretary concerned</header><text>In this section, the term <term>Secretary concerned</term> means—</text><paragraph id="H62A2C79043154B23BFA3B70AFE61D0C3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>with respect to public lands, the Secretary of the Interior; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H885DBE3072E04E89B344FDF0A88A6721"><enum>(2)</enum><text>with respect to National Forest System Lands, the Secretary of Agriculture.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

