<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H79B8204F99604438B7C2F398E4E9077B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1244 IH: The original legislation awarding a historic Congressional Gold Medal, collectively, to Africans and their descendants enslaved within our country from August 20, 1619, to December 6, 1865</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-28</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1244</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230228">February 28, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000172">Ms. Ocasio-Cortez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000370">Ms. Adams</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000382">Ms. Kuster</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001143">Ms. McCollum</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000375">Mr. Keating</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001224">Ms. Bush</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001084">Mr. Cicilline</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001157">Mr. David Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000576">Mr. Ruppersberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000296">Mr. Evans</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001078">Mr. Connolly</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001131">Mr. Casar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001160">Ms. Moore of Wisconsin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000537">Mr. Clyburn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000309">Mr. Jackson of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000687">Mr. Mfume</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001303">Ms. Blunt Rochester</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000468">Mrs. Fletcher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000462">Ms. Lois Frankel of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000482">Mrs. Trahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000131">Mr. Veasey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000607">Mr. Pocan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000187">Ms. Waters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000476">Mr. Frost</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000788">Ms. Williams of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000371">Mr. Aguilar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000385">Ms. Kelly of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000490">Mr. Bishop of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000562">Mr. Lynch</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001278">Ms. Bonamici</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000477">Mrs. Foushee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000581">Mr. Vicente Gonzalez of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HBU00">the Budget</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To posthumously award a historic Congressional Gold Medal, collectively, to Africans and their descendants enslaved within our country from August 20, 1619, to December 6, 1865.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H912809F2011B4F0AAA4CC6EC7451443E" style="OLC"><section id="HF2CC29FB7A66406D8E83FB1F79C097CB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>The original legislation awarding a historic Congressional Gold Medal, collectively, to Africans and their descendants enslaved within our country from August 20, 1619, to December 6, 1865</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H7980444E170F4957A36C5F8CB78DD0C0"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text><paragraph id="H9E1D831BE2D047E890D54B428A424054"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Human beings were systematically abducted from the continent of Africa and placed against their will onto ships that would cross the Atlantic Ocean.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2ACCA91D47864A408BC7E10B1199738D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>These persons were chained within the holds of ships in horrendous conditions for the duration of the transatlantic journey, which lasted up to six months.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB688F029D0544037AA45B3FBE1854C33"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Upon arrival in North America, they were forced into labor among the English and European colonies that would later become the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H258BADAEBA5740A29C2C9F73C77B7E60"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Their enslavement was concentrated on farms and plantations that produced crops such as cotton, tobacco, and sugar cane.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H33FB095394C94CEC97A646262C121B65"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The practice of slavery continued up to and past the eventual American Revolution against England and the founding of the United States of America.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDB35D5D0A9DB403D8EA1801ED69AA334"><enum>(6)</enum><text>In the ensuing decades, slavery persisted primarily in States where the economy was based significantly on farming.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFB0A801649B042DD9F950364D144899A"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The treatment of enslaved people continued to be horrendous in nature, including exploitation, family separation, rape, torture, and degradation, among other cruelties.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB66725690F824636829D0915B9FB3191"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Slave labor was essential to the functioning of many farms and plantations and therefore was essential to the growth of the United States economy as a whole.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE79122453944C4390FF0B71C7431B0F"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Slave labor was used to build notable buildings and monuments in the United States, including the United States Capitol Building, the White House, the Washington Monument, Mount Vernon, which was the home of George Washington, and Monticello, which was the home of Thomas Jefferson.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3122B20A8B045EA975F3D1B6C0DE4D0"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The profits from and involvement of slave labor were also essential to the construction of the Smithsonian Institution, Wall Street, Harvard University, Georgetown University, and Fort Sumter.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBB17EE57B18642B695D901A057B3863C"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It has been estimated that the total economic value of slave labor is between $5.9 trillion and $14.2 trillion in 2009 dollars.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25D0FCB1DA4243E88029528EFF3610FF"><enum>(12)</enum><text>The United States became increasingly divided between slaveholding and non-slaveholding States and territories, including as to whether slavery should be expanded to new States and territories or abolished altogether.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H508B6ECDDEEC4C93A483D3BA99F918F4"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The secession of States from the United States began on December 20, 1860, and led to the formation of the Confederate States of America on February 4, 1861.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB93F2594536C43B1ADEF56DAA4ADDAE0"><enum>(14)</enum><text>The American Civil War began on April 12, 1861, with the attack on Fort Sumter by Confederate forces.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7642672A5C2D439787BE4DC19483D849" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(15)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On January 1, 1863, President Abraham Lincoln issued the Emancipation Proclamation declaring that <quote>all persons held as slaves</quote> in Confederate States <quote>henceforward shall be free</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H594139E8815947F89E1B2860C59243A2"><enum>(16)</enum><text>After four years of grueling battle and conflict, the Civil War concluded with the surrender of the commander of the Confederate forces on April 9, 1865, although fighting continued until November 6, 1865, and the Civil War was proclaimed to be over by President Andrew Johnson on August 20, 1866.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6E6F86389B2348AA91788680D855B8DD"><enum>(17)</enum><text>The 13th Amendment to the United States Constitution abolishing slavery passed the Congress on January 31, 1865, and was ratified by the required number of States on December 6, 1865.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42352476DB13447B87DB155B48411FDC"><enum>(18)</enum><text>The text of the 13th Amendment states that, <quote>Neither slavery nor involuntary servitude, except as a punishment for crime whereof the party shall have been duly convicted, shall exist within the United States, or any place subject to their jurisdiction.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H58C982572AAD4255A1378BFF9A01C27F"><enum>(19)</enum><text>The use of slave labor over hundreds of years resulted in immense suffering and deprivation among the people who fell victim to these abhorrent practices.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE46F7C927D434ABEA349A4F9901FFF22"><enum>(20)</enum><text>At the same time, the extensive, long-term use of unpaid labor advantaged the United States economy immeasurably.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H7C37FAB2F77846EA87FE42D670BCE149"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header><subsection id="H9F8A62AC4A7F43DFA10B8B954DAF7BC4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Award authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the award, on behalf of the Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design dedicated to the enslaved persons collectively in recognition of their service as the greatest contributors to the foundation of America’s economic greatness.</text></subsection><subsection id="H3B3AB9E92F00439F90E8E670BF69623A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text>For the purposes of the award referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury shall strike the gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="HCFA61D77EEA3476281AA11A526B526B0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Smithsonian institution</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the award of the gold medal described in subsection (a), the gold medal shall be given to the Smithsonian Institution, where it will be displayed at the National Museum of African American History &amp; Culture and made available for research.</text></subsection></section><section id="H466E40861F05426487A4B0F501D7A2F8"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><subsection id="H9BBE0E6EEBB048FEBEE1AEEBC77B9329"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck under section 3, at a price sufficient to cover the costs of the bronze medals, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFB7EA5314F2347AC85100CEBC9EEE1D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sales</header><text>The amounts received from the sale of duplicate medals under subsection (a) shall be deposited in the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5B03AD47FAE149088C6D3FA689D2A081"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck under this Act.</text></subsection></section><section id="HFD587C2F4F1B4EE0A47B8FD44A373F56"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The gold medal struck pursuant to this Act is a national medal for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></section><section id="HB8D952F2C8E24EA78ABC8E98B76A059C"><enum>6.</enum><header>Determination of budgetary effects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The budgetary effects of this Act, for the purpose of complying with the Statutory Pay-As-You-Go Act of 2010, shall be determined by reference to the latest statement titled <quote>Budgetary Effects of PAYGO Legislation</quote> for this Act, submitted for printing in the Congressional Record by the Chairman of the House Budget Committee, provided that such statement has been submitted prior to the vote on passage.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

