<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF62204AF2A8F4E258C2C4AFF56903A40" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 486 IH: To prohibit the government of the District of Columbia from using Federal funds to allow individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in any election, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 486</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230124">January 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000609">Mr. Palmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000071">Mr. Ellzey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001116">Mr. Clyde</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000596">Mrs. Greene of Georgia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit the government of the District of Columbia from using Federal funds to allow individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in any election, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HCAEE9AD7EB874FB3A88DE37591E669BA" style="OLC"><section id="H4896C018C17F45A8BEC76090E7000435" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Prohibition on Federal funds</header><subsection id="HEE288AAAF79540A48C2281FB40915940"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, no Federal funds made available to the District of Columbia may be used to allow individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in any election.</text></subsection><subsection id="H82DD10B10A4340729976425FA7737145"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification</header><text>Upon application for, approval for, or receipt of any Federal funds, the government of the District of Columbia shall certify that the government does not permit individuals who are not citizens of the United States to vote in any election.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFEF5CB4A641F4422A72774250FB5064F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text>The requirements under this section shall apply with respect to any Federal funds applied for, approved for, received by, or made available to the District of Columbia on or after the date on which this bill is introduced in the House of Representatives.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

