<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3EB0520CDA974B478894A2ED6D8AE08F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3266 IH: Peace and Tolerance in Palestinian Education Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3266</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of State to submit annual reports reviewing the curriculum used by the Palestinian Authority, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEB176347C6024D15A8519DE46F48C64D" style="OLC"><section id="H3C9F2FF78F26406C9B983AA1F37B88D5" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Peace and Tolerance in Palestinian Education Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA8BE133ED8974D14B9BA54901CAEBF1C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HCD1861BFDA4046C4B8668787B93AD513"><enum>(1)</enum><text>In 2016 and 2017, the Palestinian Authority published modified curricula for school-aged children in grades 1 through 11.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB42FCC6964724521A9B051753C15D741"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Textbooks used by the Palestinian Authority (PA) in the West Bank and Gaza include graphics portraying violence against Israeli soldiers, positive portrayals of individuals who have committed attacks against citizens of Israel, and references to Palestinian efforts to target the <quote>Zionists</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H130697B44EA84A359A5E2E1C3B55545C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">PA textbooks are used at schools sponsored by the United Nations Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA) because UNRWA schools use the textbooks of the host government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF52AA0FCD92C4810A6C06468A77D0719"><enum>(4)</enum><text>On April 26, 2018, the Government Accountability Office (GAO) published a report that found the following:</text><subparagraph id="H16937C3A6DB8466E9BFBC96F614826A6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Textbooks in PA schools feature inaccurate and misleading maps of the region and include militaristic, adversarial imagery and content that incite hatred.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5F87816F15A04A75975C851A291047C5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Department of State raised with Palestinian officials the objectionable content in textbooks, including a specific math problem using the number of Palestinian casualties in the First and Second Intifadas.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H645C9B60C9754F9E8F8DEB92C94C38AB"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United Nations Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA), in its review of the textbooks, identified content not aligned with United Nations values, the majority of which content related to neutrality or bias issues, including issues related to maps and references to Jerusalem as the capital of Palestine.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section id="H6352E4317FE34748B75E00F1ED4AE39D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Palestinian Authority has not sufficiently eliminated content and passages encouraging violence or intolerance toward other countries or ethnic groups from the curriculum used in their schools.</text></section><section id="HD26479BDC68D42EA9B116CC6F0C58436"><enum>4.</enum><header>Reports required</header><subsection id="HCB0B2A728C214A2D88CC04623B14C97F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter for two years in accordance with subsection (c), the Secretary of State shall submit to the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate a report reviewing curriculum, including textbooks, leaflets, pamphlets, magazines, and other instructional materials, used in schools in areas controlled by the Palestinian Authority or located in Gaza and controlled by any other entity. Each such report shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="H36C121AD3ADF43D8AA19C97042C0185F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A determination of whether there is content or passages encouraging violence or intolerance toward other countries or ethnic groups in such curriculum, and a detailed explanation of the reasons for reaching such determination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8C0D2D16F7D470EBE219D803CA40A8E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>An assessment of the steps the Palestinian Authority is taking to reform such curriculum at schools to conform with standards of peace and tolerance in the Declaration of Principles on Tolerance by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (adopted November 16, 1995).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H231E96D8295540A4B9C0040E40A876E8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A determination whether United States foreign assistance is used, directly or indirectly, to fund the dissemination of such curriculum by the Palestinian Authority.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AB493D7FEDF4ACBB0302D6C5E02A6FF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>A detailed report on how United States assistance is being used to address curriculum that encourages violence or intolerance toward other nations or ethnic groups.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59FED6F61A4B42E3BCDC71934A5BCAD0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A detailed report about United States diplomatic efforts in the preceding five years to encourage peace and tolerance in Palestinian education.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE9EEB4C70014865AAF31F7E12B9F01E"><enum>(6)</enum><text>If any diplomatic efforts referred to in paragraph (5) were stopped by the Secretary of State, the reasons for such stoppages.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H437B19DF8F0D4E5ABEAD517FF0D2402E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary of State shall post on a publicly available website of the Department of State each report required under subsection (a).</text></subsection><subsection id="HEE88C355BFBE45438F4A864C8740A86C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Subsequent deadlines</header><text>Each report required by subsection (a), other than the first such report, shall be submitted not later than 90 days after the date on which a new school year begins for schools controlled by the Palestinian Authority.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

