<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD54DFE96E5324FCEABB58CF12FFD4A1D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5050 IH: Cryptocurrency Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5050</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 5, United States Code, to require Members of Congress to disclose financial interests in cryptocurrency, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H76F1EE2CC52E48DDB9335432FF387F74" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H41C79AF894C444F2BC0C63EF4F7BEE45" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Cryptocurrency Accountability Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H7EAB5091BDDC4D5D85E778054E605C4D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Members of Congress; disclosure of financial interests in cryptocurrency</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 13104 of title 5, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H03D560DAED074871BF7751602E5C24B5" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subsection id="H7313B618082849D594D4AAA311505ECD"><enum>(j)</enum> 
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H1FE48317E7514AB6987B547C468B32B0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Any report filed under section 13103 by a Member of Congress shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H686BDBA653DA456FBB89C8527106C9C8" indent="up1"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a brief description, the date, and category of value of any purchase, sale, or exchange in cryptocurrency by the Member or spouse or dependent child of the Member during the preceding calendar year which exceeds $1,000; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HF82B6638BDF14DDAAC9C0284700DC887" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the identity and category of value (expressed as a dollar amount) of any interest in cryptocurrency held during the preceding calendar year by the Member or spouse or dependent child of the Member.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCDB3B372F50A4C19BEBEF0C880A9D772" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 45 days after receiving notification of any transaction required to be reported under paragraph (1)(A), a Member of Congress, if required to file a report under any subsection of section 13103, shall file a report of the transaction.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8FC5F482CFB7487EA4449DBC4ED9A7EE" indent="up1"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any Member of Congress who fails to file or report, by the applicable deadline for such filing or reporting, any information that such individual is required to report with respect to crytpocurrency pursuant to paragraph (1) or (2) shall be assessed a fine, at the direction of and pursuant to regulations issued by the applicable supervising ethics office, in an amount equal to the greater of—</text> <subparagraph id="HAC7D935E26AD42C995887EEF0AA74E69"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$500, or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H7C4230BE48E64645B39DE732D9E86905"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an amount equal to 5 percent of the value (expressed as a dollar amount) of the purchase, sale, or exchange or interest (as the case may be) that the Member so failed to file or report by such deadline.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H9D51C5AEA87F4B0597C3C258FB34EF1A" indent="up1"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Notwithstanding section 13106(a), the Attorney General may bring a civil action in any appropriate United States district court against any Member of Congress who knowingly and willfully falsifies or who knowingly and willfully fails to file or report any information that such Member is required to report pursuant to paragraph (1) or (2) of this subsection. The court in which such action is brought shall assess against such Member a civil penalty in an amount equal to the greater of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H723CD2E91CEE47A586B0C8327D3C93FE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>$66,000, or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H74A1BF8A088F498EB32B93764FE31E47"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an amount equal to 5 percent of the value (expressed as a dollar amount) of the purchase, sale, or exchange or interest (as the case may be) that the Member so falsified or failed to file or report.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H54244FCC9C364183A5717B0EF9BE3A75" indent="up1"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this subsection, the term <term>cryptocurrency</term> means any digital representation of value which is recorded on a cryptographically secured distributed ledger or any similar technology.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

