<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1FB2E3D5990B4D468E746D18FC3E1E82" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3710 IH: Fighting Fertility Fraud Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3710</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000600">Ms. Perez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000624">Mrs. Dingell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to prohibit health professionals from providing false or misleading information with respect to assisted reproduction, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H0C9455BFB13F403AB1545D138C9DEE64" style="OLC">
<section id="H6D6946BC6077486ABC03967C6A741281" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fighting Fertility Fraud Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HE8A0730B82034FA88550BCBED54D9F23"><enum>2.</enum><header>Fighting fertility fraud</header> <subsection id="H6B4BD931188D4434AD2E3CD6634CF426"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/47">Chapter 47</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H32543F624A3343C5AA9792FE9BA70B3C" display-inline="no-display-inline">
<section id="H145965718131423BB1A06FFFB9956959"><enum>1041.</enum><header>Fraud in connection with the use of human reproductive material</header>
<subsection id="H2E3606CC74E9482AAB48C42ACF2289B2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Offense by a person, health professional, or health facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A person, health professional, or health facility, in any of the circumstances described in subsection (d), that knowingly provided materially false or misleading information relating to assisted reproduction, including—</text> <paragraph id="H202EF186F6534DBD96CEE10AD8E68291"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the human reproductive material provided or used for assisted reproduction;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H2AC33B00A03F484AA3D15D28714481CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the identifying information of the gamete provider including their name, birth date, or address at the time of gamete provision; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H03A9AAB566B6401C9F21094D8D9F9116"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a gamete provider’s medical history including any known physical and mental health illness, the social, genetic, family medical history of the gamete provider, or the gamete provider’s educational level, ethnicity, religious background, </text></paragraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="subsection">shall be imprisoned not more than 10 years, fined in accordance this title, or both. </continuation-text></subsection>
<subsection id="HEEE9B4DB1FEE4CB18A54ABA2D0A2B803"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Offense by health professional or health facility</header>
<paragraph id="HF411AEE291674EA68E54990C28DDBCA4"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A health care professional or health facility, in any of the circumstances described in subsection (d), that knowingly uses or provides—</text> <subparagraph id="H0CDC332C0E1B4E078B6D0DB9D5CF4EB7" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">human reproductive material for assisted reproduction other than the selected human reproductive material for which patient gave consent in writing to use; or</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCCD9FF2F47634C4C8C57A14FDBD264BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a patient with human reproductive material in assisted reproduction without the gamete provider’s consent or in a manner or to an extent other than that to which the gamete provider consented to, </text></subparagraph><continuation-text continuation-text-level="paragraph">shall be imprisoned not more than 10 years, fined in accordance with this title, or both.</continuation-text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H40008A2908794660A85AF4BE84C897F4" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Not a defense</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A health care professional or health facility found to have violated paragraph (1) may not use as a defense that a patient consented in writing to the use of human reproductive material from an anonymous gamete provider. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H70B8B2B19910443FB77A9D5609D29A2E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Circumstances described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purposes of subsections (a) and (b), the circumstances described in this subsection are that—</text> <paragraph id="HA465B6AFA63A444D892E5FA36FF21ECA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the conduct described in such subsections occurs during the course of, or as the result of, the travel of the defendant or covered individual—</text>
<subparagraph id="HCEF54FBB21364EC283028DDCE2AF0C46"><enum>(A)</enum><text>across a State line or national border; or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6F4A51535C7C4CD088AAEFF2E444056D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>using a channel, facility, or instrumentality of interstate or foreign commerce; </text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H652B4E088D2A4CD3970070BDC2FFFC4A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the defendant uses a channel, facility, or instrumentality of interstate or foreign commerce in connection with the conduct described in such subsections;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2EFDF4A500AD4D889EC06EF6D462CEF3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the conduct described in such subsections—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0B07EA4E1DC84D769CED4B33CA65F2CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>interferes with commercial or other economic activity in which the defendant or covered individual is engaged at the time of the conduct; or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4A791A79B67E4D0C9F7CD690BCE0BE20"><enum>(B)</enum><text>otherwise affects interstate or foreign commerce;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H15A1C7BB9D7A4671A48A19A3FE61C482" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the conduct described in such subsections occurred within the special maritime and territorial jurisdiction of the United States or within any territory or possession of the United States; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H270569071E2A421FB2842192E4934336"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any payment of any kind was made, directly or indirectly, in furtherance of or in connection with the conduct described in subsection (a) using any means, channel, facility, or instrumentality of interstate or foreign commerce or in or affecting interstate or foreign commerce.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H291EE3EB2E1C49158AF264B4C409EF0F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cause of action</header>
<paragraph id="HE1692DF400184A56B6A3FA8F7ED06CBE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A cause of action may be brought for a violation of subsection (a) or (b) against a health professional, health facility, or gamete provider by a donor conceived individual born as a result of such violation.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H01D698E6FD484BE1BD475D7FA047889F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certain other individuals</header><text>A cause of action may be brought for a violation of subsection (a) or (b) against a health professional, health facility, or gamete provider by a patient or patient’s spouse for each donor conceived individual born as a result of such violation.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDE87F98F6F7F4816947E39CDB7E81A40"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Gamete provider</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A cause of action may be brought for a violation of subsection (a) or (b) against a health professional or health facility by a gamete provider.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H08B141596AF14BE09782EC3EA0B535D1"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Relief</header> <paragraph id="H5623A9D2BB174C7884FF7A09CAD8E53C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In an action under subsection (e), the court may award appropriate relief, including temporary, preliminary, or permanent injunctive relief and compensatory and punitive damages, as well as the costs of suit and reasonable fees for attorneys and expert witnesses. With respect to compensatory damages, the plaintiff may elect, at any time prior to the rendering of final judgment, to recover, in lieu of actual damages, an award of statutory damages in the amount of $20,000 per violation.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HEEBCDE9F58244DB684108EF67BC1EA9B"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Compensatory damages</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Compensatory damages awarded pursuant to paragraph (1) shall include the amount of all medical expenses incurred by the patient and any donor conceived child as a result of a violation of subsection (a) or (b), including the cost of any procedure, treatment, and any other medical expense for the patient and any donor conceived child. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD8D77F636BD84CF7988E9EE65308FE6B"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Statute of limitations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An action brought under subsection (e) may not be brought more than five years after the date on which the violation of subsection (a) or (b) was discovered by a covered individual. </text></subsection>
<subsection id="H78636028200E420E86EE1789E5DBF115"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="HBEC1200A9F6C474BB13F54946A409BD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Assisted reproduction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>assisted reproduction</quote> means a method of causing pregnancy involving medical or scientific intervention, other than sexual intercourse.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H6A9CD84617EA4199A49E2F67AA6BCD84"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Assisted reproductive technology</header><text>The term <quote>assisted reproductive technology</quote> means any fertility treatment in which either eggs or embryos are handled.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H069F8B1D9BC04CEDA139BC89FAC3DB9B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consent</header><text>The term <quote>consent</quote> means consent in writing that is freely given, knowledgeable, and informed.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H438D0B88E409449BB8981B64589A6464" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered individual</quote> means the patient, patient’s spouse, gamete provider, or a donor conceived individual born as a result of a violation of subsection (a) or (b).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF95E63A1F1E447F789DC4DBC8D6F10A2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Donor conceived individual</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>donor conceived individual</quote> means an individual conceived from one or more gametes from a gamete provider.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H1A0C2A7BE49B4DFF8AB2EC7C8684E3DB"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Family medical history</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>family medical history</quote> means any known medical history information about an individual’s first and second degree relatives. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD90BEC990BC94A278BCF95CE50FED20F"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Fertility fraud</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>fertility fraud</quote> means any misrepresentation or false information provided in assisted reproduction.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HFD2CDDE560FD46D58393655AC4A0E533"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Gamete</header><text>The term <quote>gamete</quote> means an unfertilized egg or sperm. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7F27F1FFC98A411A9690C04130ADEF84"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Gamete provider</header><text>The term <quote>gamete provider</quote> means an individual who provides gametes intended for use in assisted reproduction, whether or not for consideration.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HF2CDA82442E74F05A6C94512D9604754"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Health facility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>health facility</quote> means a hospital, clinic, bank, laboratory, facility, or other health care institution involved in any aspect of assisted reproduction. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3EAE8F8D283C4215AAB220FDAB2A7193"><enum>(11)</enum><header>Health professional</header><text>The term <quote>health professional</quote> means an individual licensed, registered, certified, or otherwise authorized to engage in a health profession.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H71D1234EB95248E1B185D6745D117A04"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Human reproductive material</header><text> The term <quote>human reproductive material</quote> means a human sperm, egg, or a human organism at any stage of development from fertilized ovum to embryo.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE2B8900DFF024EA69DDE3FA9B916536D"><enum>(13)</enum><header>Medical history</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>medical history</quote> means information about any known physical, social, and mental health of an individual known to be, or that could be, inheritable according to medical standards. </text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H19101B9AEB0C440E9C7D6734E314546F"><enum>(14)</enum><header>Patient</header><text>The term <quote>patient</quote> means an individual under the care of a health professional.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H919D71821078461DB054800DC2003FC9"><enum>(15)</enum><header>Patient’s spouse</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>patient’s spouse</quote> means the spouse or partner of the patient at the time at which the assisted reproduction occurred.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection>
<subsection id="H8E2C3BF2DCD6429FA78383D293BF3A50"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections at the beginning of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/47">chapter 47</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="H773C1159B8DC416DA356E39E03A57B30" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">1041. Fraud in connection with the use of human reproductive material.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

