<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF27C967B43F3443BAEA87ED8932E7DE1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4488 IH: American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Voter Identification Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4488</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230706">July 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000596">Ms. Greene of Georgia</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">Committee on House Administration</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Help America Vote Act of 2002 to establish certain photo identification requirements for voting in District of Columbia elections and to require proof of citizenship to register to vote in District of Columbia elections, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H34044C1F32D243ED9269FAE78A802B80" style="OLC"><section id="H08009077383345F58F0890D50B8BFF65" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Confidence in Elections: District of Columbia Voter Identification Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H57E5D749DB6D4C1C82385E8DE8E648EC" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Requirements for photo identification and proof of citizenship with respect to District of Columbia elections</header><subsection id="HCA5EABEF849745F9A56BD90C4C8C78FB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Title III of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21081">52 U.S.C. 21081 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H3E7AAF52BEDA46989879B58517F320C9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating sections 304 and 305 as sections 306 and 307, respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7F1AA625EF74F8F977AD2221D5770FF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 303 the following new sections:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HFC7470C4A2324ECFA77E786A2B2E9F06" display-inline="no-display-inline"><section id="HBAB9237228A44B599973D3B509DA3F8A"><enum>304.</enum><header>Requirements for photo identification in District of Columbia elections</header><subsection id="H1C4FD0175DFA48ED9A87543E45270E7E" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requiring provision of identification To receive a ballot or vote</header><paragraph id="HD1B6CE96EC4B4389B271B4779B7849B2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Individuals voting in person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A District of Columbia election official may not provide a ballot for a District of Columbia election to an individual who desires to vote in person unless the individual presents to the official an identification described in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H74FACF2F4FB54419AC12CD229FC53A80"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Individuals voting other than in person</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A District of Columbia election official may not provide a ballot for a District of Columbia election to an individual who desires to vote other than in person unless the individual submits with the application for the ballot a copy of an identification described in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB649DD12E2AB4F6BBE8E441B3C14AB99"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Identification described</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification described in this paragraph is, with respect to an individual, any of the following:</text><subparagraph id="HEE201A9FC3D345BD9E47D3A913E0136A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A current and valid motor vehicle license issued by the District of Columbia or any other current and valid photo identification of the individual which is issued by the District of Columbia or the identification number for such motor vehicle license or photo identification. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE5F1E56EACE549D99A6115E2E5ECC9DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>A current and valid United States passport, a current and valid military photo identification, or any other current and valid photo identification of the individual which is issued by the Federal Government.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2EF7166E6567464E9FB8CDCAED4B6079"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Any current and valid photo identification of the individual which is issued by a Tribal Government.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4A5F673BFD1A4A9A94518216CBEECF08"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A student photo identification issued by a secondary school (as such term is defined in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>)) or an institution of higher education (as such term is defined in section 101 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1001">20 U.S.C. 1001</external-xref>)).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE600C728EAAF44CE9AA8A942FF023BF1"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The last 4 digits of the individual's social security number.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H01B24361368C4B0D8A74112B81035B4C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Ensuring proof of residence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If an individual presents or submits an identification described in paragraph (3) which does not include the address of the individual’s residence, the District of Columbia election official may not provide a ballot to the individual unless the individual presents or submits a document or other written information from a third party which—</text><subparagraph id="HA265DC34A1864E0F945EF3C980EDF13A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provides the address of the individual’s residence; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E81A165486A41FEB951B300F82FD516"><enum>(B)</enum><text>such document or other written information is of sufficient validity such that the election official is reasonably certain as to the identity of the individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF6F8C23954A4494AB2A5A1C3E25A5F6D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Provision of identification without cost to indigent individuals</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the District of Columbia charges an individual a fee for an identification described in subsection (a)(3) and the individual provides an attestation that the individual is unable to afford the fee, the District of Columbia shall provide the identification to the individual at no cost.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5907F28D216C4C598888F0226B603713"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Special rule with respect to sincerely held religious beliefs</header><text>In the case of an individual who is unable to comply with the requirements of subsection (a) due to sincerely held religious beliefs, the District of Columbia shall provide such individual with an alternative identification that shall be deemed to meet the requirements of an identification described in subsection (a)(3).</text></subsection><subsection id="HC427C0AC870442A78EEDD1F2F63B7ACE"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Designation of District of Columbia agency To provide copies of identification</header><text>The Mayor of the District of Columbia shall designate an agency of the District of Columbia government to provide an individual with a copy of an identification described in subsection (a)(3) at no cost to the individual for the purposes of meeting the requirement under subsection (a)(2). </text></subsection><subsection id="H473B29DE5D94427E8669D6C7311476B8"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Inclusion of photos in poll books</header><paragraph id="HE886E0DEF61540AC88F19049E143EDCA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Methods for obtaining photos</header><subparagraph id="H57ECECED4CE645E38B1DA4E03A80BF07"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Provision of photos by offices of District of Columbia government</header><text>If any office of the District of Columbia government has a photograph or digital image of the likeness of an individual who is eligible to vote in a District of Columbia election, the office, in consultation with the chief election official of the District of Columbia, shall provide access to the photograph or digital image to the chief election official of the District of Columbia.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE951734F318847CEB000C0043DBC2407"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Taking of photos at polling place</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a photograph or digital image of an individual who votes in person at a polling place is not included in the poll book which contains the name of the individuals who are eligible to vote in the District of Columbia election and which is used by election officials to provide ballots to such eligible individuals, the appropriate election official shall take a photograph of the individual and provide access to the photograph to the chief election official of the District of Columbia.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1047BAA87357475E9D440ACD7FEAB5BF"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Copies of photos provided by individuals not voting in person</header><text>The election official who receives a copy of an identification described in subsection (a)(3) which is submitted by an individual who desires to vote other than in person at a polling place shall provide access to the copy of the identification to the chief election official of the District of Columbia.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF0610A7724C74BA88BA01B173A9F4523"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inclusion in poll books</header><text>The chief election official of the District of Columbia shall ensure that a photograph, digital image, or copy of an identification for which access is provided under paragraph (1) is included in the poll book which contains the name of the individuals who are eligible to vote in the District of Columbia election and which is used by election officials to provide ballots to such eligible individuals.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H86333651F1024713AD63A3747A5985B5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Protection of privacy of voters</header><text>The appropriate election officials of the District of Columbia shall ensure that any photograph, digital image, or copy of an identification which is included in a poll book under this subsection is not used for any purpose other than the administration of District of Columbia elections and is not provided or otherwise made available to any other person except as may be necessary to carry out that purpose.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H20CC3C24450446B8AF97975B01ACDAFF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This section does not apply with respect to any individual who is—</text><paragraph id="HF9C4B95E56F743B8A2CBA58A3342DCE9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>entitled to vote by absentee ballot under the Uniformed and Overseas Citizens Absentee Voting Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20301">52 U.S.C. 20301 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4451877645B4F97A4C098FF64B40E8A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provided the right to vote otherwise than in person under section 3(b)(2)(B)(ii) of the Voting Accessibility for the Elderly and Handicapped Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/20102">52 U.S.C. 20102(b)(2)(B)(ii)</external-xref>); or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0A960D69E81840BA9FDF1330A836A6BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>entitled to vote otherwise than in person under any other Federal law.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H24CF467CF73741AC8DEFA168A0B12DB1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>For the purposes of this section, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="H6D8FA03B42054554BB8039A639C01A0C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>District of Columbia election</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>District of Columbia election</term> means any election for public office in the District of Columbia, including an election for Federal office, and any ballot initiative or referendum. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA61921EC50D74AC285848316CA211D5C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Indian tribe</header><text>The term <term>Indian Tribe</term> has the meaning given the term <term>Indian tribe</term> in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H35287FBB6BAD47C3BBAFF718B2C828E2"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Tribal government</header><text>The term <term>Tribal Government</term> means the recognized governing body of an Indian Tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H6A42FC03123545FA99711CF1CE1CC55B" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>305.</enum><header>Requiring proof of United States citizenship to register to vote in a District of Columbia election</header><subsection id="HCB8368797477440D828A3189F5120080"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An individual may not register to vote in a District of Columbia election unless, at the time the individual applies to register to vote, the individual provides documentary proof that the individual is a citizen of the United States.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4D20527011484B7DAFA8629BB73D1FC0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>District of Columbia election defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>District of Columbia election</term> means any election for public office in the District of Columbia, including an election for Federal office, and any ballot initiative or referendum. </text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6C20C14C8558457C85CE41ECA0E517AB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment relating to enforcement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 401 of the Help America Vote Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/52/21111">52 U.S.C. 21111</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>and 303</quote> and inserting <quote>303, 304, and 305</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA7AEE67935D44E4F9721B2ADA25BC1E1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of such Act is amended—</text><paragraph id="HDB025BCDA97D42449BBF1AF63CE1144A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating the items relating to sections 304 and 305 as relating to sections 306 and 307, respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17811FBE1039447EABC9D29BC4A434F5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after the item relating to section 303 the following new items:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H1DA380E442A44EDF8431A5E33A602659" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 304. Requirements for photo identification in District of Columbia elections.</toc-entry><toc-entry level="section">Sec. 305. Requiring proof of United States citizenship to register to vote in a District of Columbia election.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

