<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HCD28A8E1F0904E73A439EA0FCDF7002F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5626 IH: Rural Disaster Declaration Fairness Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5626</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001295">Mr. Bost</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require rulemaking by the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency to address considerations in evaluating the need for public and individual disaster assistance, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6590B291A4324977897B95041C4AB9C1" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="H455904EF9E8F495A931715FDF1778C0E"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Rural Disaster Declaration Fairness Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCF567134759145E49B12AF7882D746FE"><enum>2.</enum><header>Regulatory action required</header> <subsection id="H8EC206BF319E47CA9330DA703858018B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency (in this Act referred to as the <quote>Administrator</quote> and <quote>FEMA</quote>, respectively) shall amend the rules of the Administrator under section 206.48 of title 44, Code of Federal Regulations, as in effect on the date of enactment of this Act, in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H57C2A877E93C4EF58D97BD1970D98FF1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>New criteria required</header><text>The amended rules issued under subsection (a) shall provide for the following:</text> <paragraph id="HA2C85A5377074619A5FFA870F54BE951"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Public assistance program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Such rules shall provide that, with respect to the evaluation of the need for public assistance, FEMA shall consider the economic circumstances of the local economy of the affected area, including factors such as the local assessable tax base and local sales tax, the median income, and the poverty rate.</text> </paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3E758A589CDA4E4F80712822B65D3837"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Individual assistance program</header><text>Such rules shall provide that, with respect to the evaluation of the severity, magnitude, and impact of the disaster and the evaluation of the need for assistance to individuals, FEMA shall consider the economic circumstances of the affected area, including factors such as the local assessable tax base and local sales tax, the median income, and the poverty rate.</text> </paragraph></subsection> <subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1F78478B8AA043FF9688FE3AC87DDA50"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amended rules issued under subsection (a) shall apply to any disaster for which a Governor requested a major disaster declaration under the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5121">42 U.S.C. 5121 et seq.</external-xref>) and was denied on or after January 1, 2012.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H37B040ADE7B64591B6B380FCB3708A8F"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cost sharing</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 406(b) of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5172">42 U.S.C. 5172</external-xref>) is amended by striking paragraph (1) and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block style="OLC" id="HAEE6FC7A06AB4504B279C28A5BB254FE" display-inline="no-display-inline"> <paragraph id="H9D668D02322C4D7F9621405AB1D85A42"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Minimum non-Federal share</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The non-Federal share of assistance under this section shall be not less than 10 percent of the eligible cost of repair, restoration, reconstruction, or replacement carried out under this section.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

