<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFECBA27D168547CEA958AEEE211E8A49" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6899 IH: To require the Assistant Secretary of the Army for Acquisition, Logistics, and Technology submit to Congress a report on light tactical wheeled vehicles of the Army, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6899</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231222">December 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Assistant Secretary of the Army for Acquisition, Logistics, and Technology submit to Congress a report on light tactical wheeled vehicles of the Army, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H68452C3EFC0D424095B0E94238388E60" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6C4CDE3F64364FB5939C0B1EF8C5831C" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Report on light tactical wheeled vehicles of Army</header> 
<subsection id="HD9315507E06B408A858B6D56CE27C583"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Assistant Secretary of the Army for Acquisition, Logistics, and Technology, in coordination with the Commanding General of Commander of the Army Futures Command, shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report on light tactical wheeled vehicles.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8043DBBAD8FC4AB48E4901A92F45C806"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Matters</header><text>The report under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HBE3F672B094D41E29EEF32366A6A1D21"><enum>(1)</enum><text>An analysis of the requirements of the Army for light tactical wheeled vehicles, including any such requirements with future applicability.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAA9E2B6C919C4A48AF793EB70F0D290B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A risk assessment regarding the availability of light tactical wheeled vehicles from entities in the defense industrial base, including a description of measures that may be taken to manage and mitigate such risk.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8EFC4D83A6E845C19C87FD8AA7CEA974"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed description of any plans of the Army for the development or acquisition of light tactical wheeled vehicles.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCBC190D37212435B9334852B525CDC3E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification of the funding profile for light tactical wheeled vehicles included in the most recently submitted future-years defense program submitted to Congress under section 221 of title 10, United States Code.</text> </paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

