<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC3E70498F77D452E86CBAE59BC5D9172" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1538 IH: Emerging Business Encouragement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1538</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230310">March 10, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001156">Ms. Sánchez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000587">Ms. Garcia of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001055">Mr. Case</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="L000601">Mr. Landsman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To amend the Small Business Act to provide for contracting preferences and other benefits for emerging business enterprises, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H8FD13ACD82624CC98A071D27A6FB737D" style="OLC">
<section id="HBBC39FFD891A4191BF6D6940414E905A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Emerging Business Encouragement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H03A4244265A14CCBAD1E0D066CF414AC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Emerging business enterprises</header> <subsection id="HBA517982DACF4FF69BA2C220C257C0D8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text>Section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HA0A42923CD104956B684803D300EBAF9" style="OLC">
<subsection id="H49C9786B26894CF09F6D422EB61AD36E"><enum>(gg)</enum><header>Emerging business enterprise</header>
<paragraph id="HBC3E45A6B5204F9AA2C6FF052493C167"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act, the term <term>emerging business enterprise</term> means a concern designated by the Administrator in accordance with this section.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H78C22D9EF484460498C95C845AD323C5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria for designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of enactment of this subsection, the Administrator shall establish criteria for designation of a small business concern as an emerging business enterprise which shall include the following:</text>
<subparagraph id="H41AD16B7D11147919145D9C905693723"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Number of employees</header><text>That the highest number of employees of the concern during the year preceding the date of application is less than the larger of—</text> <clause id="H01EAE239D9724FC7887A0E19DBB411B2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>10 percent of the number of employees that a small business concern within that industry category may employ, if that small business concern is so classified by reason of a size standard under subsection (a) pertaining to the number of employees of the concern; or</text></clause>
<clause id="H27AACDA629164EA6921F081FFB1F61AA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>25 employees.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF615404E3E8F4E55860388E1681FBE9D"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Age of business</header><text>That the small business concern has been in operation for less than 5 years on the date of application.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2D4A1B864EF54CBC88E1B002332119B9"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Salary requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">That the small business concern does not, in the Administrator’s determination, pay to an individual who owns any part of the concern or who is in a management position a salary greater than 200 percent of the mean annual salary for an individual in the Managers of Companies and Enterprises sector (as assigned a North American Industry Classification System code beginning with 55) or the equivalent from the most recent employment and wage estimates developed by the Secretary of Labor.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H73C5CA679AA04A3EB653E7D827C395CC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Deadline</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall complete review of an application for designation as an emerging business enterprise and either issue or deny such designation not later than one year of receipt of such application.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE299A065784A4E1A9F458633F3719E18"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Termination of designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A designation as an emerging business enterprise shall terminate on the date on which the concern is no longer in compliance with the criteria under paragraph (2), except that—</text> <subparagraph id="H938C2A38BAC547E1803B895C5072E7CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to the requirement in paragraph (2)(A), such designation shall terminate only if the concern employs 50 percent or more employees than the number of employees that a small business concern within that industry category may employ; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H58544EB204584BC1ACB0A3765B5F5F38"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with respect to the requirement in paragraph (2)(C), such designation shall terminate only if the concern exceeds such requirement and employs not more than 10 percent of the number of employees that a small business concern within that industry category may employ, if that small business concern is so classified by reason of a size standard under subsection (a) pertaining to the number of employees of the concern.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD7EE4C4D0FFC482BA9BEBDAA01D2DA3C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Public notification</header><text>The Administrator shall take appropriate action to publicize the establishment of the procedures for designations under this paragraph, including by conducting outreach to eligible small business concerns.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5C75B9FFF841476091FE70CBB8AA4597" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Contractor training</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall provide training on Federal procurement specifically for emerging business enterprises on an Internet website of the Administrator, which shall be available to the public at no charge. </text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H6F29E1B7DB024FE58C564C32B8835CAB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contracting preference</header><text>Section 15(g)(2) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/644">15 U.S.C. 644(g)(2)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="HBF8D49B6B41F42218A0BC8BA14E089E1" style="OLC">
<subparagraph id="H616EDE8E78C2416DAD4FAB9EF85F1473"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Emerging business enterprises</header>
<clause id="H9AEC0B329A0F46E4BECA9E2A3C4D9B0A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The head of each Federal agency shall, after consultation with the Administrator, establish goals for participation by emerging business enterprises in not less than 3 percent of all prime contracts and subcontracts of such agency for each fiscal year.</text></clause> <clause id="H4E4422BA6A7E44378F1A36D3BB0C6711"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The head of a Federal agency—</text>
<subclause id="H27AF4092607F417E81FD3BD66235E879"><enum>(I)</enum><text>shall make consistent efforts to annually expand participation by emerging business enterprises from each industry category in contracts of the agency; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="H230693F64F794191BE419190CA3FC9A6"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">shall, subject to clause (iii), award a contract to an emerging business enterprise if the head of a Federal agency determines the agency will not meet the goals established under this subparagraph for a fiscal year.</text></subclause></clause>
<clause id="HD41C2E55680341C0AFDD0D42C874942E"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Preference</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The preference described in clause (ii)(II) shall take priority over any preference for procurement from the procurement list established pursuant to section 8503 of title 41, United States Code, or the Federal Prison Industries catalog described under section 4124(d) of title 18, United States Code. </text></clause> <clause id="HEE4C5942AB2442BF9F2BC7B2E242B738"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Reports</header> <subclause id="H665FCD87AE5D4B9AB1230DED484BF44D"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Reports from agencies</header><text>At the conclusion of each fiscal year, the head of each Federal agency shall report to the Administrator on the extent of participation by emerging business enterprises in procurement contracts of such agency. Such reports shall contain appropriate justifications for failure to meet the goals established under this subparagraph.</text></subclause>
<subclause id="H3D76CD277D0A40DA9F2FD4F371210FF7"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Reports to congress</header><text>The Administrator shall annually compile and analyze the reports submitted by agencies pursuant to subclause (I) and shall submit to the President and the Committee on Small Business and Entrepreneurship of the Senate and the Committee on Small Business of the House of Representatives the compilation and analysis, which shall include the following:</text> <item id="H21D13DC03A90400C9948BA551B6526E9"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>The goals in effect for each agency and the agency’s performance in attaining such goals.</text></item>
<item id="H1F4EE5002B17486690EE8C1FC7B97178"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>An analysis of any failure to achieve individual agency goals and the actions planned by such agency (that have been approved by the Administrator) to achieve the goals in the succeeding fiscal year.</text></item> <item id="HAD6F2D9D021742269A97A0C48B868CB8"><enum>(cc)</enum><text>The total number and dollar value of prime contracts and subcontracts awarded to emerging business enterprises for each agency.</text></item></subclause>
<subclause id="H5C79FCACCA164ED29DC3D9C0D5F308B1"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Annual presidential report on the state of small business</header><text>The President shall include the information required by subclause (II) in each annual report to the Congress on the state of small business prepared pursuant to section 303(a) of the Small Business Economic Policy Act of 1980 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/631b">15 U.S.C. 631b(a)</external-xref>).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> <subsection id="H620C7885EEE34D7494DD9CD86082BF78"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Fee waivers</header><text>Section 7(a) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/636">15 U.S.C. 636(a)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text>
<quoted-block id="H8BB26B31D7D0420AACC25A65378F45C6" style="OLC">
<paragraph id="H8F3E77B7CDA14EEB9101F7BB06FC16E2"><enum>(38)</enum><header>Fee waivers</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may not collect an origination fee or a guarantee fee described in paragraph (18) in connection with a loan made under this subsection to an emerging business enterprise, unless—</text> <subparagraph id="H77B8BC1F145E495481E5C0B751C49BF8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the President’s budget for the upcoming fiscal year, submitted to Congress pursuant to section 1105(a) of title 31, United States Code, includes a cost for the program established under this paragraph that is above zero; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H2D3BC9C133B448078D8AE829D6DAA0AF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Administrator determines carrying out this paragraph will have no adverse effect on the waivers provided under paragraph (31)(G) or (33)(E)(ii) for a fiscal year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE3BF0860F9884D36893453D42EB22CDB"><enum>(39)</enum><header>Emerging business enterprises</header> <subparagraph id="HB5DEE7253D0B49B991568DFAD17D3145"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Reports</header><text>On the date that is 1 year after the end of the first fiscal year for which a guaranteed loan is made to an emerging business enterprise under this subsection, and annually thereafter, each lender making such a loan shall submit to the Administrator a report with respect to the preceding fiscal year on the total number and dollar amount of such loans made and the number of waivers issued under paragraph (38).</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HDC60F1183E1544E39C00B498FB32F80B"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Verification</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A lender shall verify with the Administrator the status of a concern as an emerging business enterprise before making a loan guaranteed under this subsection to such emerging business enterprise.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6EF0BB8343B14718A4535ACB01230356"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Penalty</header><text>If a concern received a loan under this subsection and fraudulently misrepresented the status of the concern as an emerging business enterprise, that concern shall—</text>
<clause id="H2D0647FB77504EC9954727393B8E64A5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>repay the amount of the loan to the lender (from which amount the lender shall repay the amount of any guarantee paid on the loan to the Administrator); and</text></clause> <clause id="H2CF296B8BFDD4B44A236AF7DA1B79997"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">pay a fine to the Administrator in an amount determined by the Administrator.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section>
<section id="HCE2F7D05942043BA8F70F6B63FF83D2D" commented="no"><enum>3.</enum><header>Rulemaking</header>
<subsection id="HD50A7F6B60B04DAA93C00332E32A7CED" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later 1 year after the date of enactment of this subsection and for each industry category for which the Administrator of the Small Business Administration established a size standard under section 3(a) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632(a)</external-xref>), the Administrator shall issue a rule—</text> <paragraph id="H86113063C04C4CBA9E2B42A6D674010F" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing procedures for designating a small business concern in each such industry category as an emerging business enterprise that include the criteria under subsection (gg)(3) of section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>), as added by this Act, and a process for appealing designation decisions of the Administrator;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3213486E904545A2BDE8EE6E4768A1BE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing procedures for certification by the Administrator as an emerging business enterprise;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H069765B6446147F1BE0E17C905685764" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">requiring a small business concern to annually submit documentation to the Administrator to establish eligibility for designation as an emerging business enterprise; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE2EA521BCC9B45F199FBE9904395F472" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establishing compliance requirements for emerging business enterprises.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7874EF9F8DAF4ED18522B6FBA039275C" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text>
<paragraph id="H962C8B67A2A44949B7CBA4EFEEDA76C7" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Small business concern</header><text>The term <term>small business concern</term> has the meaning given under section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2526CD0757784C239EC9A65371FD60C6" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Emerging business enterprise</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>emerging business enterprise</term> has the meaning given under subsection (gg) of section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>), as added by this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


