<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HDDEB157D042144838045344D10CAFD66" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3682 IH: Cady Housh and Gemesha Thomas Student Suicide Prevention Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3682</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230525">May 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001061">Mr. Cleaver</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001208">Mrs. McBath</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001196">Mr. Moulton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001117">Mr. Casten</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000381">Mr. Kilmer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000400">Ms. Kamlager-Dove</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000081">Ms. Velázquez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001223">Mr. Bowman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000629">Ms. Davids of Kansas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001313">Ms. Brown</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Public Health Service Act to authorize certain grants (for youth suicide early intervention and prevention strategies) to be used for school personnel in elementary and secondary schools and students in secondary schools to receive student suicide awareness and prevention training, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3E0385B926704951A7E8100EF3DDCE8B" style="OLC"><section id="HEA067251FFA6460EA36012780E454749" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Cady Housh and Gemesha Thomas Student Suicide Prevention Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HE2CC7E56CFFB48E6B67BF211F6422005"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HB47F10AF725C4FD881836BD1FA009298"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> According to the National Institutes of Health, suicide is the second leading cause of death for young people between the ages of 10 and 34. Between 2007 and 2018, the national suicide rate among persons ages 1 to 24 increased 57.4 percent. From 2018 to 2021, the national suicide rate among persons ages 10 to 24 increased by 2.8 percent.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H072FD7FF54154032A97B44ADE73E9DE5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the 2021 Youth Risk Behaviors Survey of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 22.2 percent of high school students reported seriously considering suicide during the previous 12 months, and 10.2 percent reported actually attempting to take their lives during that period.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6DC942637FA41718E36B5ABE9A38E8B"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Eighty percent of students show warning signs before attempting suicide.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC94F76127B5E4C4A860FEB57FCDF7A19"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Prevention and awareness training will equip individuals to become aware of the warning signs of suicide, identify students in crisis, and provide resources for help.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E0E69912A7E4C279EDA23CF18A4F9FD"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Research shows that inquiring about suicide ideation, or discussing suicide in terms of recognizing risk factors and prevention methods—</text><subparagraph id="HE0D505E8654A4F33BCD1DC2B16827C03"><enum>(A)</enum><text>does not increase the chance of suicide; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H72DFDFD01D4149779F93E728373059CE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in fact, can lower the risk of suicide.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF33FD6D17C44FDD9387BD2D60D232EC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Sexual minority youth (LGBT+) are almost five times more likely to have attempted suicide compared to their heterosexual peers. According to the Trevor Project’s 2022 National Survey on LGBTQ Youth Mental Health, 45 percent of LGBT+ youth seriously considered suicide in the past year including more than half of transgender and nonbinary youth and 1 in 3 cisgender youth. Additionally, 14 percent of LGBT+ youth attempted suicide in that same period, including nearly 1 in 5 transgender and nonbinary youth and 1 in 10 cisgender youth.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA4021C626E684238BAFB7DBC160CF9F9"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, emergency department visits among adolescents increased during the pandemic. During the period of February 21 to March 20 in 2021, suspected suicide attempt emergency department visits were 50.6 percent higher among girls aged 12 to 17 years than during the same period in 2019.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H0105B58366E1408AA56F53C449914385"><enum>3.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of the Congress that—</text><paragraph id="H06BDA32D53E343A9931E10C562971DF7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>student suicide awareness, prevention training, and response materials should be available to all school personnel, including administrative personnel, teachers, counselors, and other school leaders;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H32199FDE75B1481B9F4E1BB1A8C2BD15"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">States should give autonomy to each local educational agency to—</text><subparagraph id="HB597513723874D40B90501120D14A4C9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>adopt a policy with respect to student suicide awareness and prevention; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H767315D9A3B747E5AD989E839D9A790B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>work collaboratively with local organizations, youth mental health experts, health care providers, and the Secretary of Health and Human Services to implement training for school personnel and students, including by sharing and disseminating—</text><clause id="HE7B4D1C7C015432DB04F4206C49CBD5B"><enum>(i)</enum><text>training materials and resources; and</text></clause><clause id="H8900069308744A389DCB2DADDD9D08C3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>information that is evidence-informed or promising on student suicide prevention;</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H457B7DBC5C73465EB8CB2617F228166C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Secretary of Health and Human Services should identify the highest unmet needs, specifically with at-risk student populations, such as—</text><subparagraph id="H8CC9CCA195254EE0940459D88DE0B074"><enum>(A)</enum><text>minority students;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1B96176F5554915B853BDF3FE34A5F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>LGBT+ identifying students;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD00CBE433B8E424E95B1EE815D7D88C1"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">students living with mental health conditions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0EB1DF895CEB4B269346B3F7A856FFBE"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">students living with substance use disorders;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4790EC3917D64269BB9A7AC35C336AD0"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">students who have engaged in self-harm or have attempted suicide; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D84D48B288842D4AE97D78CA2195227"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">students experiencing homelessness or out-of-home settings;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EEE1DBD1DF44BA39FC73508F59C28E7"><enum>(4)</enum><text>schools should offer these services to students in grades 9 through 12, with the support of organizations with demonstrated expertise in cultural competency, suicide awareness, response, and prevention training;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB00F5C0A43584F50877B7A5B20FC5E77"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">students who receive such training should not be taught to be counselors, but rather should be educated on how to—</text><subparagraph id="H4B201D7211764455ACD578C113A49A56"><enum>(A)</enum><text>recognize signs of suicide and depression;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18E52F0A8BCB423D83B8205713F6827B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>report these signs to appropriate staff; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8B8C5C717A1746A8A7E588E1A82B9FB9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>identify sources of care and support; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6FF89BE7F8EA4F5C8B619A6810915F00"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">schools should utilize school-based mental health professionals and other community partnerships.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H3EB64B628D6946DEBC4BE39134390D07"><enum>4.</enum><header>Student suicide awareness and prevention training</header><subsection id="HDE77D10699954E4089C8EFFCA6E737CE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Additional authorized use of grant funds</header><text>Section 520E(a) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290bb-36">42 U.S.C. 290bb–36(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H91004EA6FA7C454CB0E1848426C5115F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in paragraph (4), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H76FF2C47C355405FB8493C6A6AE2BAC5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7EC37554F23405EAFA4C460D1CFD511"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H8E6D06A5EB0A4A24A1E6622F2F3F4754"><paragraph id="H0EA62EA25E0D49CCAB96BB5BDD15365F"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish and implement a statewide policy requiring school personnel in elementary and secondary schools and students in secondary schools to complete student emotional well-being, mental health, and suicide awareness and prevention training in accordance with subsection (d).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC1B1CA57819A43E1AAE85AD9C1578103"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Training requirements</header><text>Section 520E of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290bb-36">42 U.S.C. 290bb–36(a)</external-xref>), as amended by subsection (a), is further amended—</text><paragraph id="HCD027F2C2676438CB3BD1B1D348C8DB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating subsections (d) through (m) as subsections (e) through (n), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H29245FAB902B4F289ED3F689DE9F9D64"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (c) the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBD7F4389B8B14CE6A5AB60CB884C5A56" style="OLC"><subsection id="HE98C736401934664A068934D65C4A4D8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Requirements for student suicide awareness and training programs</header><paragraph id="HF2EF8EF82A244CA18D1C712185828653"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>As a condition on receipt of funds under subsection (a)(6), an applicant shall agree to use the funds to establish or implement a statewide policy—</text><subparagraph id="H42226358BE554ABCB7A597EEC0B2DB52"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">requiring school personnel in elementary and secondary schools and students in secondary schools to complete student emotional well-being, mental health, and suicide awareness and prevention training that—</text><clause id="HB27BDDED26E5410C802958FBEAE6DAFF"><enum>(i)</enum><text>includes at least one classroom session each school year;</text></clause><clause id="HB76A2D099EE54576B310F08AF0099906"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is evidence-informed; and</text></clause><clause id="H8629838114934990A54AB629EC3EE9FF"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>includes training on—</text><subclause id="H6DE8593184F04669B538F5A40E5211C5"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the warning signs of, and elevated risk factors for, poor emotional well-being, mental health issues, and suicide of oneself and of others;</text></subclause><subclause id="HC753FE89E76B4636B9308B6807AFEE42"><enum>(II)</enum><text>suggested responses to such warning signs;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD0461DA2DC874E24A191726201AB0D33"><enum>(III)</enum><text>further suicide awareness and prevention resources; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H1236E22F761D45A0AF83D498EE259CBC"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>the method and manner of making an appropriate referral to a school-based mental health services provider; and</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H80B8EDBE9FF4424F9E83F794C03B9154"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">requiring, with respect to such school personnel, that such training include training on—</text><clause id="HE16881DFED66430AAB181F04A1689629"><enum>(i)</enum><text>cultural competency and intersectionality sensitivity; and</text></clause><clause id="HB76E198BE71F4702819EB207D27379CF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an overview of applicable Federal, State, and local law concerning reporting requirements.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF20F3AFD26947AF9A868B3F09DE17B7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>As used in subsection (a)(6) and this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H53B7CF60B50C40D2B12BEA0549328125"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>evidence-informed</term> means informed by practices that—</text><clause id="H47A2B8972B9A46A3981AC1EBDAB40F9F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>use the best available research and practice knowledge to guide program design and implementation;</text></clause><clause id="H4BAFFE7EC367482897187D45ED29ADDD"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>allow for innovation while incorporating the lessons learned from the existing research literature; and</text></clause><clause id="HE13720E085234DD6B009361FA3C5D315"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>are responsive to families’ cultural backgrounds, community values, and individual preferences.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB371766CC304BE48B28CB41E5AC9EB3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>school-based mental health services provider</term> includes a State-licensed or State-certified school counselor, school psychologist, school social worker, or other State-licensed or certified mental health professional qualified under State law to provide mental health services to children and adolescents.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0A6D6F4DDC148C691D83BC81B56E134"><enum>(C)</enum><text>The term <term>school personnel</term> means—</text><clause id="HFC4737B69B0A467F830FE33D7657B4EA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">principals or other heads of a school; other professional instructional staff (such as staff involved in curriculum development, staff development, or operating library, media, and computer centers); specialized instructional support personnel such as school counselors, school social workers, and school psychologists; and other qualified professional personnel, such as school nurses, speech language pathologists, and school librarians, involved in providing assessment, diagnosis, counseling, and educational, therapeutic, and other necessary services; and</text></clause><clause id="HABBE67B23EFE41DEAAFB74011D28F2E3"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>other school employees and contractors who interact with students, including bus drivers, cafeteria workers, coaches, janitorial staff, and after-school program employees.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H7298C6CFE9E14D058AC6B35818ECC47B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Funding</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subsection (n) of section 520E of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290bb-36">42 U.S.C. 290bb–36</external-xref>), as redesignated by subsection (b)(1), is amended—</text><paragraph id="H27E1832BC1674F46BFF84F1D86FE3930"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>For the purpose</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC8244680D4504BA79070AB775DA53B75" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H5AFEB0A7E5AD44E3A62F3D0A45A0B922"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For the purpose</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H8855E660E90741B48F8BBC1AF276FE5E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by striking <quote>$40,000,000</quote> and inserting <quote>$48,000,000</quote>; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9773B07EEDFE4B3F8403E897EFF6C0EA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H286F86DCF6734D668223CB716E95596F" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HB237ECD5B9C646CB949CCC2D62C2ECC0"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Allocation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the amounts made available to carry out this section for a fiscal year, not less than 15 percent of such amounts shall be used for grants or cooperative agreements to carry out subsection (a)(6) (to establish and implement a statewide policy requiring school personnel in elementary and secondary schools and students in secondary schools to complete student emotional well-being, mental health, and suicide awareness and prevention training).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

