<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H14E35223B7144821A6F0464455AAA3B1" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 305 IH: One School, One Nurse Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 305</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230111">January 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="W000808">Ms. Wilson of Florida</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To authorize the Secretary of Education to carry out a grant program to assist local educational agencies with ensuring that each elementary and secondary school has at least one registered nurse on staff.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6231011AF9C6441184F90B9CC16AC572" style="OLC"><section id="HDB3D6D6A3D0449E396B9EB7A4F052420" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>One School, One Nurse Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H01E79E941BB648C697491C8850A5E801"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purpose; findings</header><subsection id="H68F8A454FC6647F8BCA9770D7DFFEC6E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose of this Act is to assist States and local educational agencies with ensuring that every elementary and secondary school has at least one full-time registered nurse on staff, and to maintain recommended nurse-to-student ratios, including through the recruitment, hiring, and retention of registered nurses.</text></subsection><subsection id="H87FC785091A64284A43A9997ECEE56A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H917B6B82B44D40AFB26160EB6AB12180"><enum>(1)</enum><text>According to the American Academy of Pediatrics, every elementary and secondary school should have at least one full-time registered nurse on staff.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2FAE5D159C754C339B19333054D0838D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>According to the National Center for Education Statistics, during the 2015–2016 school year, only about half of all public schools had a full-time registered nurse and nearly 20 percent did not have any nurse on staff. Schools with higher free or reduced-price lunch program eligibility rates had lower rates of school nurses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB0DCD3E19BEB44A28FDC23F1EFD893DD"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to the Georgetown University Center for Children and Families, in 2019, roughly 6 percent of children in the United States were uninsured.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6EF9F374739345CF91C94037B6E52EBD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>For children who lack health care coverage, a school nurse is often a critical source of health services.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H771DD0A94CF6480285BCC463A2AB1D0B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Studies suggest that schools with a full-time registered nurse experience far-reaching benefits including fewer student absences, students spending more time in class, more accurate medical records, higher immunization rates, fewer student pregnancies, and better health outcomes for students with asthma or diabetes. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5439EAB60AB94B31A2EA4E2F76858571"><enum>(6)</enum><text>School nurses play a critical role in helping to manage the chronic physical, emotional, mental, and social health needs of students, conduct health screenings, facilitate vaccinations and immunization compliance efforts, reduce burdens on educators and other school staff, and support a positive and healthy school climate.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H0712F0802771450B9CD594DE54F9A778"><enum>3.</enum><header>One School, One Nurse grant program</header><subsection id="HDC220348551247F093BC6E873010F1A7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program authorized</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall establish a program to award grants, on a competitive basis, to eligible entities to carry out the activities under <internal-xref idref="H2AE6B9AC97A040279541FEC3C5822E12" legis-path="3.(d)">subsection (d)</internal-xref>. Grants awarded under this section shall be for a period of 5 years.</text></subsection><subsection id="H470AF16E6DA44C58AE156723FA47702E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Application</header><text>An eligible entity desiring a grant under this section shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require. Such application shall include—</text><paragraph id="H75411A0244AD4001978BF21186A3FE4E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a needs assessment of the eligible entity that demonstrates the existence of persistent shortages of school nurses or persistent shortages of full-time school nurses;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3456B5433916485ABBD289F1DA500594"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a description of the health and wellness needs of the student population served by the eligible entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H91FB133A49C1421BAF3CEC82389BEE9E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a comprehensive plan for the use of grant funds to address persistent shortages described in the needs assessment under <internal-xref idref="H75411A0244AD4001978BF21186A3FE4E" legis-path="3.(b)(1)">paragraph (1)</internal-xref>, including a description of how such activities shall address the health and wellness needs described under <internal-xref idref="H3456B5433916485ABBD289F1DA500594" legis-path="3.(b)(2)">paragraph (2) </internal-xref>and how such funds will be used to ensure that the eligible entity will continue to employ and retain school nurses after the completion of the grant period; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3A7B22478BF4DE5843028674998C395"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a description of how the eligible entity will prioritize recruiting individuals from the communities served by the eligible entity and from underrepresented populations in public health professions (as determined by the Secretary by regulation), and how the eligible entity will track progress in meeting any specified hiring goals.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H05AF42D401AB4748875E80312F8DB3BE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Selection and priority</header><text>In awarding grants under this section, the Secretary shall give priority to eligible entities that—</text><paragraph id="H5C718278A5644D99810D947B994C65C4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>are a high-need local educational agency, or are a partnership between a State educational agency and a consortium of high-need local educational agencies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H842395747B5F45C1AC58989F3AE1249B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>describe and set specific hiring goals towards increasing the share of school nurses who are from underrepresented populations in public health professions.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2AE6B9AC97A040279541FEC3C5822E12" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Activities</header><text>Grant funds awarded under this section shall be used by an eligible entity to carry out one or more of the following activities:</text><paragraph id="HA90EEED876E94E0BBACD1D93DDBF4DA3" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Recruit and hire school nurses.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB426C2A4111747859996038E587E9190" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Provide resources necessary to convert part-time school nurse positions at elementary or secondary schools served by the eligible entity into full-time school nurse positions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H357193F8530542F09071567BE545A982" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Support the retention of school nurses, including by increasing salaries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6CB27980E7794DE39DE32A82C934708A"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Maintain recommended nurse-to-student ratios (as determined by the Secretary by regulation).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0AF0D722072E4F2AA16106ED3279889E"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reporting</header><text>Each eligible entity awarded a grant under this section shall submit to the Secretary an annual report for each year of the grant award. Such report shall include—</text><paragraph id="H15459A69C44541D1B0E12CCE5CF33E94"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a summary of the eligible entity’s progress in employing at least one full-time registered nurse at each elementary and secondary school served by the eligible entity and maintaining recommended nurse-to-student ratios (as determined by the Secretary by regulation);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H98837E290B4B4957AD748B253D3673DE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">data on the number and percentage of full-time and part-time school nurses, disaggregated by major racial and ethnic groups and gender, employed at each elementary and secondary school served by the eligible entity; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9DA0BB1416F84CCC893BD1E2BD708570"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a summary of any progress made by the eligible entity in addressing the health and wellness needs identified in the needs assessment required under <internal-xref idref="H3456B5433916485ABBD289F1DA500594" legis-path="3.(b)(2)">subsection (b)(2)</internal-xref> as a result of activities carried out with a grant under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H782307F6163145A3B0C5584E9B694FBF"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 12 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H6FDA906E15E84BF78D55A9654A86F0DC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services—</text><subparagraph id="HB5F0C05A486045CB97369718BF141EA0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>specify in regulation the recommended nurse-to-student ratios for elementary and secondary schools;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5D45309DC29A49719D3BDC50F0506BE1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide for guidance and other technical assistance to eligible entities with respect to achieving and maintaining such ratios; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2BA2CB459A424681942FEA8DAE5D4D02"><enum>(C)</enum><text>specify in regulation the definition of <quote>underrepresented populations in public health professions</quote> for the purposes of this section; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7D66804D635452BA9941020BB138D4E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in consultation with the Secretary of Health and Human Services and the Secretary of Labor, specify in regulation the definition of <quote>full-time</quote> with respect to school nurses for the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H25222C901863482BA4B3CD110E977C99"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="HF32185BD93D74E66A43B0DFC2546A142"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible entity</term> means—</text><subparagraph id="HF2676F14E0B047A28A40449168D4835E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a local educational agency; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7986CEB2704C46B78BD798F725D7E993"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a partnership between a State educational agency and a consortium of local educational agencies in the State, entered into for the purposes of a grant under this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6F16CA84D7143708511AD0F52328273"><enum>(2)</enum><header>High-need local educational agency</header><text>The term <term>high-need local educational agency</term> has the meaning given such term in section 200 of the Higher Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/1021">20 U.S.C. 1021</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H62C01B2D41B84651991265661FDE6AA8"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Local educational agency; State educational agency</header><text>The terms <term>local educational agency</term> and <term>State educational agency</term> have the meanings given such terms in section 8101 of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/20/7801">20 U.S.C. 7801</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3624988FDAFF40A68CAF3B5F8FC2F32B" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>School nurse</header><text>The term <term>school nurse</term> means a registered nurse who is employed by a school or local educational agency or State or State educational agency and is qualified under State law to provide assessment, diagnosis, counseling, educational, therapeutic, and other health services to meet student needs.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEFF86E4861634D08B9AE3144EB517CA2"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Education. </text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

