<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF9D73364D7004DD0970F1262F47E2184" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5112 IH: Civilian Harm Review and Reassessment Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5112</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230801">August 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001121">Mr. Crow</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish procedures for the review and reinvestigation of certain allegations of civilian harm that resulted from United States military operations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H1EACB78F1A7D4C618B36283E13462601" style="OLC"><section id="HF7F6BEC1790A4943B3928973F9C9CBC8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Civilian Harm Review and Reassessment Act</short-title></quote> . </text></section><section id="H861A737601DC4E9E8DA9AC2AD0795F1D"><enum>2.</enum><header>Procedures for review and reinvestigation of allegations of civilian harm resulting from certain United States military operations</header><subsection id="H963329D1774246D188B5E06A05ECAC8B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Procedures required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall establish procedures under which the Secretary shall review and reinvestigate allegations of civilian harm that—</text><paragraph id="H452F912FD613460D853DA1D00D42AF67"><enum>(1)</enum><text>resulted from military operations involving the United States Armed Forces that were conducted between 2011 and 2023; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBD8CB25E711B4572A75412B00E8E99DC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary finds were likely incorrectly dismissed due to investigation errors or incomplete information.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD76245D664B41B4869B0A062CE81BE7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In establishing the procedures under subsection (a), the Secretary of Defense shall consult with nongovernmental organizations that focus on civilian harm and human rights.</text></subsection><subsection id="H48BA9B0FB4744094859E6B0DB14B65F7"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Policy updates</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the congressional defense committees a report that includes—</text><paragraph id="H925741EB0022407BB0D083D9C1ADBAED"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a description of any errors identified during the review and re-investigation process required under subsection (a);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC5C7869239034BDEA271C0D74AEBD967"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an identification of any revised credibility assessments and new credibility findings;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDC931A20933F4DB0AAFE76117F976A8C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a description of steps taken in response to new credibility findings, including any offers of ex gratia payments; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC43D90B2482546388C3B3423FC6F323D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>recommended steps to prevent similar errors in the future.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB9FAB8B3A1964E179ED455A57192E7E5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Congressional defense committees</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>congressional defense committees</quote> means—</text><paragraph id="HB851F4B406C140D7898355AE1C964B56"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H14DCCC3B98404CFB92D7EA22B9B2FC4D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Committee on Armed Services and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

