<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HF10D6C804AE846E9B571160E3066E4A5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 196 IH: Expediting Temporary Ratings for Veterans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 196</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230109">January 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to modify the information technology systems of the Department of Veterans Affairs to provide for the automatic processing of claims for certain temporary disability ratings, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H7A1F898DD89C45A5A7C1B1F4765B0A33" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H15D8A550735545B4A82B914426603202" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Expediting Temporary Ratings for Veterans Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H6A2B2DABA09944509F4BD3B78F6BC205"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Veterans Affairs automatic processing of certain claims for temporary disability ratings</header> <subsection id="H6928F1A1488F437496825F77D9C0BC3D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall modify the information technology systems of the Department of Veterans Affairs to provide for the automatic processing of claims for temporary disability ratings for veterans described in section 1156(a)(1)(C) of title 38, United States Code.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H41BF0FF4EAAA45AC8549A0CE600E4B5E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Additional requirements</header><text>In providing for the automatic processing of claims as required under subsection (a), the Secretary shall ensure that—</text> <paragraph id="HD6C8DDB6A410481AA14BB93E05DE7129"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">medical evidence is obtained from the corporate data warehouse of the Department;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9054F490EE254D2492BE69BEE4D936D9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>employees of the Department continue to determine whether a veteran is eligible for a temporary disability rating under section 1156(a)(1)(C) of title 38, United States Code; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H410A7E7E1D1D4EBD88C5EC24A0CC5393"><enum>(3)</enum><text>claims may be processed manually if the evidence of record is not sufficient to decide the claim or if the medical evidence is provided in a format that is not compatible with the system developed under subsection (a).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

