<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HBA0D873D0561428193B7ACC3C4540C24" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 589 RH: Mahsa Amini Human rights and Security Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 90</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 589</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–118, Part I]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230127">January 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001299">Mr. Banks</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001210">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001086">Mrs. Harshbarger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="W000797">Ms. Wasserman Schultz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsors: <cosponsor name-id="S001199">Mr. Smucker</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000574">Mr. Gallego</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="O000019">Mr. Obernolte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001047">Mr. Himes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000593">Mr. Levin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001190">Mr. Schneider</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001067">Mr. Hudson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000825">Ms. Wexton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000215">Ms. Eshoo</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001136">Mrs. McClain</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000585">Mr. LaHood</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000599">Mr. Posey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000579">Mr. Ryan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000148">Mr. Auchincloss</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001148">Mr. Simpson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000633">Mr. Duarte</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000483">Mr. Trone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000617">Ms. DelBene</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001159">Ms. Strickland</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000590">Mr. Green of Tennessee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000522">Mr. Smith of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001199">Mr. Mast</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001157">Mr. McCaul</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000399">Mr. Doggett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001216">Mr. Mills</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="A000376">Mr. Allred</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000377">Ms. Granger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000397">Ms. Lofgren</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000450">Ms. Foxx</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000623">Mr. DeSaulnier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000583">Mr. Loudermilk</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000188">Mr. Norcross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001059">Mr. Costa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001307">Mr. Baird</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001068">Mr. Huffman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001172">Mr. Smith of Nebraska</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001081">Mrs. Hayes</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000266">Mr. LaTurner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001215">Ms. Stevens</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. González-Colón</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="Y000067">Mr. Yakym</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001103">Mr. Carter of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000133">Mr. Van Drew</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000398">Mr. Kean of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001300">Ms. Barragán</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001309">Mr. Burchett</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001222">Mr. Miller of Ohio</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001194">Mr. Moolenaar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000566">Mr. Latta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001211">Mr. Stanton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C000059">Mr. Calvert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001296">Mr. Boyle of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000599">Mr. Ruiz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000469">Mr. Fulcher</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001066">Mr. Horsford</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000616">Mr. DesJarlais</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000304">Mr. Jackson of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000610">Mr. Reschenthaler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001216">Ms. Schrier</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001072">Mr. Carson</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001196">Ms. Stefanik</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001200">Mr. Soto</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000593">Mr. Gimenez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001287">Mr. Bera</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000391">Mr. Krishnamoorthi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001285">Ms. Brownley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000392">Mr. Kustoff</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="D000632">Mr. D'Esposito</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HFA00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc> Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means </committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>For text of introduced bill, see copy of bill as introduced on January 27, 2023</action-instruction></action><action></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To impose sanctions on the Supreme Leader of Iran and the President of Iran and their respective offices for human rights abuses and support for terrorism.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body display-enacting-clause="yes-display-enacting-clause" changed="added" style="OLC" committee-id="HFA00" reported-display-style="italic" id="H012084C8907C4E329A432F809D8F031F"><section id="HDF18E95EAEA54893B1B05744B7EEC100" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Mahsa Amini Human rights and Security Accountability Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>MAHSA Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H479F675F5A26451A9A625C9DCFAAE7EC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions on Iran’s Supreme Leader’s Office, its appointees, and any affiliated persons</header><subsection id="H2F12EB440A784D0C89C1F788B40CEFCF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H144FEA2487594857BC56697600C68EB7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Supreme Leader is an institution of the Islamic Republic of Iran.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H378ADCFC9E544EE085366FD5B13DB2F2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Supreme Leader holds ultimate authority over Iran’s judiciary and security apparatus, including the Ministry of Intelligence and Security, law enforcement forces under the Interior Ministry, the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps (IRGC), and the Basij, a nationwide volunteer paramilitary group subordinate to the IRGC, all of which have engaged in human rights abuses in Iran. Additionally the IRGC, a United States designated Foreign Terrorist Organization, which reports to the Supreme Leader, continues to perpetrate terrorism around the globe, including attempts to kill and kidnap American citizens on United States soil. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2E1AFC719F3C41B88020668D87C9A56C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The Supreme Leader appoints the head of Iran’s judiciary. International observers continue to criticize the lack of independence of Iran’s judicial system and maintained that trials disregarded international standards of fairness. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA62A3B2838614890B6B44B755F83E869"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The revolutionary courts, created by Iran’s former Supreme Leader Ruhollah Khomeini, within Iran’s judiciary, are chiefly responsible for hearing cases of political offenses, operate in parallel to Iran’s criminal justice system and routinely hold grossly unfair trials without due process, handing down predetermined verdicts and rubberstamping executions for political purpose.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE73015E2833645DBBA11A98B13FED3DF"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Iranian security and law enforcement forces engage in serious human rights abuse at the behest of the Supreme Leader.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6D3AC93AD2204E478CF75F1DB5980394"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Iran’s President, Ebrahim Raisi, sits at the helm of the most sanctioned cabinet in Iranian history which includes internationally sanctioned rights violators. Raisi has supported the recent crackdown on protestors and is a rights violator himself, having served on a <quote>death commission</quote> in 1988 that led to the execution of several thousand political prisoners in Iran. He most recently served as the head of Iran’s judiciary, a position appointed by Iran’s current Supreme Leader Ali Khamenei, and may likely be a potential candidate to replace Khamenei as Iran’s next Supreme Leader.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE12ACF3B0F6B4FCC98907E8C987AA7F6"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">On September 16, 2022, a 22-year-old woman, Mahsa Amini, died in the detention of the Morality Police after being beaten and detained for allegedly transgressing discriminatory dress codes for women. This tragic incident triggered widespread, pro-women’s rights, pro-democracy protests across all of Iran’s 31 provinces, calling for the end to Iran’s theocratic regime.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAE44731C95954DD29F13E0238CF7006B"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the course of the protests, the Iranian security forces’ violent crackdown includes mass arrests, well documented beating of protestors, throttling of the internet and telecommunications services, and shooting protestors with live ammunition. Iranian security forces have reportedly killed hundreds of protestors and other civilians, including women and children, and wounded many more.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8B9536EEB65437AB3D2DA8322FB9EC2"><enum>(9)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Iran’s Supreme Leader is the leader of the <quote>Axis of Resistance</quote>, which is a network of Tehran’s terror proxy and partner militias materially supported by the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps that targets the United States as well as its allies and partners.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H788EBFF7F20249168C54AC17073529D3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of Congress that—</text><paragraph id="HBF4FBE350DF34BEFAF6D592C0DE666AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States shall stand with and support the people of Iran in their demand for fundamental human rights; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE1D5095BA98445DCA6BA7842BA998648"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the United States shall continue to hold the Islamic Republic of Iran, particularly the Supreme Leader and President, accountable for abuses of human rights, corruption, and export of terrorism; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA7A9EDA4C35B4E38B6C32AFFF8F10080"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Iran must immediately end its gross violations of internationally recognized human rights. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9498A2C506194C12B756F61E558F0A81"><enum>(c)</enum><header>In general</header><paragraph id="H2863DE3C24944A3898CD5083F0DCB676"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Determination and report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the President shall—</text><subparagraph id="H70C1500F33D848B4905B053D9ABB10CC"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determine whether each foreign person described in subsection (d) meets the criteria for imposition of sanctions under one or more of the sanctions programs and authorities listed in paragraph (2);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H524FD84FBD094F84862F623AE2B0F900"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">impose applicable sanctions against any foreign person determined to meet the criteria for imposition of sanctions pursuant to subparagraph (A) under the sanctions programs and authorities listed in subparagraph (A) or (F) of subsection (c)(2) and pursue applicable sanctions against any foreign person determined to meet the criteria for imposition of sanctions pursuant to subparagraph (A) under the sanctions programs and authorities listed in subparagraph (B), (C), (D), or (E) of subsection (c)(2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA7EEFC7B5DD4DD9846CF12D95853117"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report in unclassified form, with a classified annex provided separately if needed, containing—</text><clause id="H1A52D46A01BB4D7C9A847764568BE665"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a list of all foreign persons described in subsection (d) that meet the criteria for imposition of sanctions under one or more of the sanctions programs and authorities listed in paragraph (2); and</text></clause><clause id="H0235BD7EC25F4BE1B3D603FBD52B28BE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>for each foreign person identified pursuant to clause (i)—</text><subclause id="H974F7BCE3B1E47DEBB06CFF221F3B54E"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a list of each sanctions program or authority listed in paragraph (2) for which the person meets the criteria for imposition of sanctions;</text></subclause><subclause id="H904BB873389648AAA761CBAFFEDD2AE3"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a statement which, if any, of the sanctions authorized by any of the sanctions programs and authorities identified pursuant to subclause (I) have been imposed or will be imposed within 30 days of the submission of the report; and </text></subclause><subclause id="H64C2CBB017204D5CAB99909B92D8FBA1"><enum>(III)</enum><text>with respect to which any of the sanctions authorized by any of the sanctions programs and authorities identified pursuant to subclause (I) have not been imposed and will not be imposed within 30 days of the submission of the report, the specific authority under which otherwise applicable sanctions are being waived, have otherwise been determined not to apply, or are not being imposed and a complete justification of the decision to waive or otherwise not apply the sanctions authorized by such sanctions programs and authorities.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H40BFCBA670E942A882DE334E8B131407"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sanctions listed</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The sanctions listed in this paragraph are the following: </text><subparagraph id="HD3D409E785184D95B63A8C8EDB2EACED"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions described in section 105(c) of the Comprehensive Iran Sanctions, Accountability, and Divestment Act of 2010 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/8514">22 U.S.C. 8514(c)</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H458A19C01AB646EBBBCAAAFE330A44BF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions applicable with respect to a person pursuant to Executive Order 13553 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property of certain persons with respect to serious human rights abuses by the Government of Iran).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5E214072AD5E40CB889192A40FE369DD"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions applicable with respect to a person pursuant to Executive Order 13224 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note; relating to blocking property and prohibiting transactions with persons who commit, threaten to commit, or support terrorism).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H89BBB21783A84B5DB3FFC450855C1776"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions applicable with respect to a person pursuant to Executive Order 13818 (relating to blocking the property of persons involved in serious human rights abuse or corruption).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8DD05AA0900F45E1ACC67152F3CFF227"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Sanctions applicable with respect to a person pursuant to Executive Order 13876 (relating to imposing sanctions with respect to Iran).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD802F3AA07BB445E88722E7FA0FE3549"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Penalties and visa bans applicable with respect to a person pursuant to section 7031(c) of the Department of State, Foreign Operations, and Related Programs Appropriations Act, 2021.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H48805E104F2F4CED98FB629080782029"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Form of determination</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The determination required by paragraph (1) shall be provided in an unclassified form but may contain a classified annex provided separately containing additional contextual information pertaining to justification for the issuance of any waiver issued, as described in paragraph (1)(C)(ii). The unclassified portion of such determination shall be made available on a publicly available internet website of the Federal Government. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8C69B6B50ABF4F64948A3CBBC3D672E0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Foreign persons described</header><text>The foreign persons described in this subsection are the following:</text><paragraph id="H71C2628126284530BE36F18184921DF6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Supreme Leader of Iran and any official in the Office of the Supreme Leader of Iran.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D645A2D15D24968B6B1BF6A062EB263"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President of Iran and any official in the Office of the President of Iran or the President’s cabinet, including cabinet ministers and executive vice presidents.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23CE54E498334695A093419E50CD3393"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any entity, including foundations and economic conglomerates, overseen by the Office of the Supreme Leader of Iran which is complicit in financing or resourcing of human rights abuses or support for terrorism.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H810205CA231C44489C345DE03F7E21F0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Any official of any entity owned or controlled by the Supreme Leader of Iran or the Office of the Supreme Leader of Iran.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H01E62A6601CD47D3936849352754B150"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any person determined by the President—</text><subparagraph id="H3DEBF57AB5984DAF8692B1B766A23148"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to be a person appointed by the Supreme Leader of Iran, the Office of the Supreme Leader of Iran, the President of Iran, or the Office of the President of Iran to a position as a state official of Iran, or as the head of any entity located in Iran or any entity located outside of Iran that is owned or controlled by one or more entities in Iran;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0653E91197264E0AAAA002890246FEA0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to have materially assisted, sponsored, or provided financial, material, or technological support for, or goods or services to or in support of any person whose property and interests in property are blocked pursuant to any sanctions program or authority listed in subsection (c)(2); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H17C9E883CEBF492DBE8E7A15B47A2881"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to be owned or controlled by, or to have acted or purported to act for or on behalf of, directly or indirectly any person whose property and interests in property are blocked pursuant to any sanctions program or authority listed in subsection (c)(2); or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H392C37204B8B48C8A6E49FC84F8EA2A3"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to be a member of the board of directors or a senior executive officer of any person whose property and interests in property are blocked pursuant to any sanctions program or authority listed in subsection (c)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3E88F45234F0412AA1549BFB732C10C7"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Congressional oversight</header><paragraph id="H7FD344B16D1045B196AD1C98845DF02E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 60 days after receiving a request from the chairman and ranking member of one of the appropriate congressional committees with respect to whether a foreign person meets the criteria of a person described in subsection (d)(5), the President shall—</text><subparagraph id="H1E30D71A6C7A4E63929C0ADC63947768"><enum>(A)</enum><text>determine if the person meets such criteria; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1248541EEE44638BDB950D66F5110EF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit an unclassified report, with a classified annex provided separately if needed, to such chairman and ranking member with respect to such determination that includes a statement of whether or not the President imposed or intends to impose sanctions with respect to the person pursuant to any sanctions program or authority listed in subsection (c)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4C16CDF7F71B4DAD9B453EB835805B2C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees defined</header><text>In this subsection, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H0E9FF28E010F4F309CAE32A203F278BD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE515C9AE5BE44ABDA6957A2C432612BE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HC2405F1626B34708B58302445BF9201C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">If any provision of this Act, or the application of such provision to any person or circumstance, is found to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this Act, or the application of that provision to other persons or circumstances, shall not be affected. </text></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name added-display-style="italic" committee-id="HFA00" deleted-display-style="strikethrough">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name> with an amendment</action-desc><action-date date="20230622">June 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc> Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means </committee-name> discharged; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

