<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HBCA2EF144BAF4A1B888E7F98825ACFC4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 934 IH: To require the Secretary of Agriculture to carry out activities to suppress wildfires, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 934</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230209">February 9, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001177">Mr. McClintock</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000578">Mr. LaMalfa</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Agriculture to carry out activities to suppress wildfires, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H77F495C08D294AB1BE254095A5259AA0" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H26809CD550824D158867A299036EAAD8" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Suppression of wildfires</header> 
<subsection id="HCF5DAECDAD044E4289A4BC214ADCEECD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to covered National Forest System lands, the Secretary of Agriculture, acting through the Chief of the Forest Service—</text> <paragraph id="H699638A3845B4F3A9246CFE834D073D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H444E8DF34ABC496F8699D1092446AE5C"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">use all available resources to carry out wildfire suppression with the purpose of extinguishing wildfires detected on such lands not later than 24 hours after such a wildfire is detected; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H863094A47B7A4703BFD37D5D3C80B9E9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>immediately suppress any prescribed fire that exceeds prescription; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HAFAE5C3D72014417973D129710AF0A43"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall not inhibit the suppression efforts of State or local firefighting agencies that are authorized to respond to wildfire on such lands;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1A17BA1A42F749399DD510E44CB27CC4"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">may only use fire as a resource management tool if the fire is a prescribed fire that complies with applicable law and regulations;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H529F8787856340A8BEE011512B4396FC"><enum>(4)</enum><text>may only initiate a backfire or burnout during a wildfire—</text> <subparagraph id="H81DEBB436ADB4667B862D181FD97A841"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by order of the responsible incident commander; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA8E5498B99034F4FBAADD887BB8A3C60"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in instances that are necessary to protect the health and safety of firefighting personnel; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HFD4788849B664F839DB71FE5087BF3D3"><enum>(5)</enum><text>shall use all available resources to control any such initiated backfire or burnout until extinguished.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEAEFFCC1109E40F0A738076BDE2E7188"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered national forest system lands defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>covered National Forest System lands</term> means any area—</text> <paragraph id="HAE26C2D60E3940AAA569D61585AE480F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>located within National Forest System lands; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H955F3F9A43264F01BE2D11BD02282274"><enum>(2)</enum><text>that—</text> <subparagraph id="HAE1D9DDAC0BD479FAEFF9965A0E44EA0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the U.S. Drought Monitor has rated as having a D2 (severe drought) intensity, D3 (extreme drought) intensity, or D4 (exceptional drought) intensity;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HFDF766CD14EC499398227D5F858A31AC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the National Interagency Fire Center declares has a National Wildland Fire Preparedness level of 5; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB042510830AC42A7B2A4E1F4BED302D5"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Forest Service has identified as being located in a fireshed ranked in the top 10 percent of wildfire exposure (as determined using the most recently published models of fireshed risk exposure published by the Forest Service).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


