<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H12DCCF0A0AEB46B6B3BDD8B8713EBD4E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1679 IH: Bipartisan Ban on Congressional Stock Ownership Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1679</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230321">March 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000298">Ms. Jayapal</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="A000148">Mr. Auchincloss</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000216">Ms. DeLauro</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000002">Mr. Nadler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000618">Ms. Porter</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000472">Mr. Takano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001297">Mr. Buck</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Agriculture</committee-name>, <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To prohibit stock trading and ownership by Members of Congress and spouses of Members of Congress, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA5B1AF5E1DE747B28B2EABF92EBCBB83" style="OLC"><section id="H0D4C35508FA34E628A9A4967F2592A9E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Bipartisan Ban on Congressional Stock Ownership Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H34B69459E9D846CA9356268278DE9680"><enum>2.</enum><header>Bar on stock trading and ownership by Members of Congress and spouses</header><subsection id="H6A8EB88509B64622B757A18FAC2F2459"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H83F3F52755AC4C499A5925FBB7968AD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Commodity</header><text>The term <term>commodity</term> has the meaning given that term in section 1a of the Commodity Exchange Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1a">7 U.S.C. 1a</external-xref>). </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H08B8606EA3D24291A660CC70CB288E9A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Congressional ethics committee</header><text>The term <term>congressional ethics committee</term> has the meaning given that term in section 13101 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HAC12F065E0C14A64B2E3FB9E4624A4E3"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Diversified</header><text>The term <term>diversified</term>, with respect to an investment fund, means that the investment fund does not have a stated policy of overly concentrating its investments. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA213C3B2ECF4B6F884A8075226C0907"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Member of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Member of Congress</term> has the meaning given that term in section 13101 of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H163909691D31406583C209C48C4DAF21"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Security</header><text>The term <term>security</term> has the meaning given that term in section 3(a) of Securities Exchange Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/78c">15 U.S.C. 78c(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3B8B5ABD0C5140F4A3D1910947A54700"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Small business concern</header><text>The term <term>small business concern</term> has the meaning given that term under section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2AC3F7C23BB5461F8172277163FABB94"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Widely held investment fund</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>widely held investment fund</term> means a widely held investment fund described in 13104(f)(8) of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F3E9A85DD03422297AE9FB2766C813A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Divestment</header><paragraph id="HED88A058D772463CB5066CEBD7E87C97"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in subsection (c), no Member of Congress or spouse of a Member of Congress may own an interest in or trade (except as a divestment) any stock, bond, commodity, future, or other form of security, including an interest in a hedge fund, a derivative, option, or other complex investment vehicle.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H435C7BD3C6A14F0982CA3842738B1F8D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Implementation</header><subparagraph id="H31B66F476F3048B084D3567F7C7DB4C6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Current Members</header><clause id="H60BF36812060423C8CA1B14732E1D620"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), an individual who is a Member of Congress on the date of enactment of this Act, or the spouse of such an individual, shall complete the divestment of any asset described in paragraph (1) by not later than 180 days after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></clause><clause id="H25D0949B8638427DA9AA25754C497EC0"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Certain assets</header><text>For an asset described in paragraph (1) that is an interest in a hedge fund, venture capital fund, or other privately held complex investment vehicle, an individual who is a Member of Congress on the date of enactment of this Act, or the spouse of such an individual, shall complete the divestment of the asset by not later than 5 years after the date of enactment of this Act.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA8A0D3A173374EFDACAFD548D8FEFB22"><enum>(B)</enum><header>New Members</header><clause id="HAE68EB935B854B668722295F230F692E"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in clause (ii), an individual who becomes a Member of Congress after the date of enactment of this Act, or who is the spouse of such an individual, shall complete the divestment of any asset described in paragraph (1) by not later than 180 days after the date on which the individual becomes a Member of Congress.</text></clause><clause id="H7B96D120F1E6438CADC2B71A90F52D18"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Certain assets</header><text>For an asset described in paragraph (1) that is an interest in a hedge fund, venture capital fund, or other privately held complex investment vehicle, an individual who becomes a Member of Congress after the date of enactment of this Act, or who is the spouse of such an individual, shall complete the divestment of the asset by not later than 5 years after the date on which the individual becomes a Member of Congress. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFA05E2869209423CB59B7EAA60096F47"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Divestment of assets received while a Member</header><text>An individual serving as a Member of Congress, or the spouse of such an individual, who receives any asset described in paragraph (1) during the period of such service, such as from an inheritance, shall complete the divestment of the asset by not later than 180 days after the date on which the individual or spouse receives the asset. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0C4B667D288449F7B3E9975F7FE78381"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions</header><text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent— </text><paragraph id="H48A3C6CE253B4002A9EEB7197F77DC38"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a Member of Congress or spouse of a Member of Congress from owning or trading—</text><subparagraph id="H2F2C2AC7DCE84346AB5EDCB6A8E41765"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a widely held investment fund, if the widely held investment fund— </text><clause id="H8EB218DF793F42D4A08B2243CBBEDBB0"><enum>(i)</enum><text>does not present a conflict of interest; and</text></clause><clause id="H6DE71D0162B941DCB5061B8622036943" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>is diversified; </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAF42D5759A7443B5B9F1597C27A5C296"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shares of Settlement Common Stock issued under section 7(g)(1)(A) of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1606">43 U.S.C. 1606(g)(1)(A)</external-xref>); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7186C5E215304F2BB807C31FE1CABFE2"><enum>(C)</enum><text>shares of Settlement Common Stock, as defined in section 3 of the Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/43/1602">43 U.S.C. 1602</external-xref>); </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD0EC2221DE594893A5356F7CA560B2D9"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a United States Treasury bill, note, or bond;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H68F0AA23F7E94E20BB6193CD02EDAA34"><enum>(E)</enum><text>an investment fund held in a Federal, State, or local government employee retirement plan; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H697A3F6899634B719365ED8F02960ADB"><enum>(F)</enum><text>an interest in a small business concern, if the small business concern does not present a conflict of interest; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE4B4AC0C359F4F17B0CE388F8CE3E026"><enum>(G)</enum><text>any asset described in subsection (b)(1) received as compensation from the primary occupation of the spouse; or</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D3B4E8AECC8437BA1ADE83E427DBBC2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a spouse of a Member of Congress from trading any asset described in subsection (b)(1) that is not owned by the spouse or Member of Congress in the course of performing the primary occupation of the spouse. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HCC39086FB9D34345AE7238379FEBA8EA"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Civil fines</header><text>The Attorney General or the Special Counsel may bring a civil action in the appropriate United States district court against any Member of Congress or spouse of a Member of Congress who engages in conduct constituting a violation of this section and, upon proof of such conduct by a preponderance of the evidence, such Member of Congress or spouse shall be subject to a civil penalty of not more than $50,000 for each violation. The imposition of a civil penalty under this subsection does not preclude any other criminal or civil statutory, common law, or administrative remedy, which is available by law to the United States or any other person.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2EAED7CB362E489EAE32CEE6A10D0815"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Nonrecognition of gain</header><paragraph id="HD2FD39BB12064DEA925C0F71A94705EA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Paragraph (1) of <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/1043">section 1043(b)</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986 is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H262F67CA0A6646F392A91401A6715A6A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end of subparagraph (A);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA111D3E4D22D4A9E8108A3D09EF641CD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraph (B) as subparagraph (C);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEE64B616C877403A9CC00E45DADE3D1B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H792118B4FA82426C8B2BD4841ACCA455"><subparagraph id="H0D6EE19D1E90431DBAD03575770DAFFE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any Member of Congress or Member of Congress-elect, but only with respect to a divestment of property required by the <short-title>Bipartisan Ban on Congressional Stock Ownership Act of 2023</short-title>, and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15004EC5E7C44EA9ABEB140D5AED00E3"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by striking <quote>subparagraph (A)</quote> in subparagraph (C), as so redesignated, and inserting <quote>subparagraph (A) or (B), whichever is applicable</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HAF08F0873CB242BA9672D6662B71743A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certificate of divestiture</header><text>Subparagraph (B) of section 1043(b)(2) of such Code is amended—</text><subparagraph id="HA0B9F824DDAC43B78E90DA12A473C4ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by striking <quote>or by</quote> and inserting <quote>by</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H21F6AB5BFA0F48DEBB8C3931D94181C8"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, or by the applicable congressional ethics committee, in the case of Members of Congress, Members of Congress-elect, and spouses of Members of Congress and Members of Congress-elect</quote> after <quote>judicial officers</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H07F6C8F4AEFD458FB8076DC9083A41B1"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>The amendments made by this subsection shall apply to sales of property after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H629C7351F3FE49E0B57B6C763CE5A9D6"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Interpretive guidance</header><text>The Select Committee on Ethics of the Senate and the Committee on Ethics of the House of Representatives shall issue interpretive guidance regarding relevant terms not defined in this Act or elsewhere in statute. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

