<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H75E3AC9203334865BF9196B9A33FF07F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6425 IH: To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a working group to develop and coordinate an artificial intelligence initiative among the Five Eyes countries, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6425</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231115">November 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="K000389">Mr. Khanna</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HIG00">Intelligence (Permanent Select)</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to establish a working group to develop and coordinate an artificial intelligence initiative among the Five Eyes countries, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HE460DAB4FDE0490E98D48CAF458BE61C" style="OLC"><section id="H6012ACB45C454B79ACECA0845016DC12" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Establishment of working group for artificial intelligence initiative among Five Eyes countries</header><subsection id="H731B27DAEA2140C0A13EAA27F83CA845"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text>Not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in coordination with the Director of National Intelligence, shall establish a working group to be known as the <quote>Five AIs Strategic Artificial Intelligence Working Group</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Working Group</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="HDD59655204D846B0A9410169013C0DBB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose of the Working Group shall be to develop and coordinate an artificial intelligence initiative among the Five Eyes countries.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7E167DDA627240E4884D708B2592DD88"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Organization</header><paragraph id="HE8D247FFAC5F45CB856612374E582B93"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Designation of head</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense, in coordination with the Director of National Intelligence, shall designate a senior civilian officer of the Department of Defense or senior military officer with experience leading relevant efforts, as determined by the Secretary, to serve as the head of the Working Group.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8112F6328C9041499A9C2DC7AB9E4D08"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Participation by other member countries</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense, in coordination with the Director of National Intelligence, shall encourage participation in the Working Group by the members of the Five Eyes Intelligence Oversight and Review Council.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDEB523AFBA434558998D5679FCF8DF5D"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Responsibilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The responsibilities of the Working Group shall be to develop and coordinate efforts to implement an artificial intelligence initiative between the Department of Defense, the Office of the Intelligence Community Inspector General of the United States, and the other members of the Five Eyes Intelligence Oversight and Review Council to—</text><paragraph id="H1770DDA187394059B89A9F79EA2BAC80"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compare—</text><subparagraph id="HC88E7624E9F04F6BADA2E0842B6BE13D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the various artificial intelligence systems and the elements thereof (including machine learning and generative artificial intelligence such as large language models) used for covered operational uses by such members; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03256534BCE5495A8A1DBBD93CFE5C87"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the respective practices associated with the employment of such systems for covered operational uses by such members;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8605F3D68344E09B8A2CA88573A6AD5"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify (including by experimenting, testing, and evaluating) potential solutions to advance and accelerate the interoperability of artificial intelligence systems used for intelligence sharing, battlespace awareness, and other covered operational uses;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC3FB262AD63B41BABDF14606763448D0"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">test and evaluate the effects of artificial intelligence model redundancy, including the risks and safety measures associated with operating multiple artificial intelligence systems, including in tandem with one another;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H23F859AAFCC648EEBE7416007B1BED8F"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop a shared strategy for the research, development, test, evaluation, and employment of artificial intelligence systems for covered operational uses carried out jointly by the Five Eyes countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD92C3035F57046138AFB41E5887D07DB"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop a shared strategy for—</text><subparagraph id="H9484F3D96CCE45F5A2C4F2013C774811"><enum>(A)</enum><text>managing data-informed artificial intelligence systems; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H539AF4B81B954BE69C4F874E5625BAF7"><enum>(B)</enum><text>testing and evaluating artificial intelligence systems with combined data sets at the unclassified and classified levels;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H836C79E547274E3F898B097F12C24F97"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">test and evaluate the capabilities of the defense industrial base of the Five Eyes countries to incorporate artificial intelligence systems into systems used for covered operational uses; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4598455B6932443C8B774326A3D4FF2B"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">compare and use ethical frameworks to accelerate technological advancements with respect to artificial intelligence systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H894760E37DEB4FFA834C55650F4E494C"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">expand innovation efforts by the Five Eyes countries and share among such countries best practices for the accelerated procurement and adoption of artificial intelligence technologies for covered operational uses;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H300A69F98D784B11A9F06C2DA3F2D396"><enum>(9)</enum><text>leverage commercially available artificial intelligence technologies to advance near-term jointness between the armed forces and intelligence components of the Five Eyes countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8786B113305843B1A105D1BA5959EA0D"><enum>(10)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">jointly identify and source artificial intelligence systems, as practicable, and advise Five Eyes countries with respect to export controls applicable to such systems;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1FA7132B6DD74E3480CCE16B63D84B83"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">share, to the extent practicable and as agreed upon by the Working Group, the results, opportunities, and frameworks assessed or otherwise identified by the Working Group for the informed use of artificial intelligence with allies and partners of the United States other than Five Eyes countries; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA8D5B9CBEEBE485388F0749FA0C32F37"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">carry out such other activities as the Secretary of Defense, in consultation with the Director of National Intelligence and any members of the Five Eyes Intelligence Oversight and Review Council participating in the Working Group, determines to be relevant to such responsibilities.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0FF0669FA90D403D90F43C9C17284199" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Control of knowledge and technical data</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Defense shall seek to ensure that any knowledge or technical data produced by a Five Eyes country under any cooperative project carried out by the Working Group shall be controlled by that country under the export control laws and regulations of that country and shall not be subject to the jurisdiction or control of any other Five Eyes country.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD9737F5D14294E0289154AB9C0C58AF8" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Plan and reports</header><paragraph id="H2AE7A56BFAD945ABAC457ACFC1957CA6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Plan</header><subparagraph id="HB60886E89E604285999AF92C5DDA4313"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Submission</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense, in coordination with the Director of National Intelligence, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a plan for the establishment and activities of the Working Group.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15E7E0CD3E494C7D9498C04390665B9C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The plan under subparagraph (A) shall include—</text><clause id="HB2697E3C624B4F649A5C7C6CB4E8D66D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a plan for the establishment of the Working Group, including for efforts to engage with the members of the Five Eyes Intelligence Oversight and Review Council with respect to such establishment;</text></clause><clause id="H9A3178C8791B41088E3264313EB3AD88"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a description of any funding requirements or administrative support necessary to carry out this section;</text></clause><clause id="HE9D2C432BABC4C998D26FFCB90EAD475"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of any additional statutory authorities necessary to carry out this section;</text></clause><clause id="H90A823B5C3E24CC6A02DF086B5C2E3A5"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a plan for the fulfilment of responsibilities under subsection (c) by the Working Group;</text></clause><clause id="HD0484066E7BB4F6CB887EE5FF35C34AB"><enum>(v)</enum><text>an evaluation of existing joint efforts by the Five Eyes countries to fulfill similar responsibilities;</text></clause><clause id="H8986D9DF5EC14FB99CBCC5BCA4419CC6"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a plan for the integration of the artificial intelligence initiative developed and coordinated by the Working Group with other programs and initiatives of the elements of the Department of Defense or the Office of Director of National Intelligence with responsibilities relating to mutual security and artificial intelligence efforts among the Five Eyes countries;</text></clause><clause id="H6556A864311842C1AED4913AFFE2E7FD"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>performance indicators by which the activities of the Working Group will be assessed; and</text></clause><clause id="HCF5F186D831A4AB3B67857D18225FFF2"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a description of how efforts of the commanders of the combatant commands relating to military interoperability and test and evaluation of artificial intelligence systems will be tasked and executed by and through the Working Group.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C9796A1CFCB477CA72DD3189DD1AD69"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Biannual report</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and on a biannual basis thereafter until the date of termination under subsection (f), the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the activities and milestones of the Working Group. Each such report shall include, with respect to the period covered by the report—</text><subparagraph id="H7AEE8D9CC1B044FD85874C0347EEDC27"><enum>(A)</enum><text>an assessment of the activities of the Working Group based on the performance indicators set forth in the plan under paragraph (1)(B)(vii); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBBEC51647BE74F87974F2D688DC842EB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a description of any efforts of the commanders of the combatant commands taken in support of the responsibilities of the Working Group.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3515EBCCD42C4810A4D863F92403FF18"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Termination</header><paragraph id="HEBBA3ECF67A1435D8E3EF8AA9E1F0B54"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), the Working Group shall terminate on September 30, 2028.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5590B91C8A304299B612043B629D9CC1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Authority to extend</header><text>The Secretary of Defense may extend the termination date under paragraph (1) if the Secretary determines such extension to be in the national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H42A2A1CC1F7E41BB80F57159FEF2B0E1"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H910B410DECBF46259EC9918C26F1D161"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HB4781E9F2E414E02A28E3441AD1AD24C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the congressional defense committees, as such term is defined in section 101 of title 10, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6CD8C95695E34A73826204D80E0D6670"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the congressional intelligence committees, as such term is defined in section 3 of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3003">50 U.S.C. 3003</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3934D51C124D4E728FD8332650F0A16D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The term <quote>battlespace awareness</quote> has the meaning given that term in the Joint Publication 1–02 of the Department of Defense, titled <quote>Department of Defense Dictionary of Military and Associated Terms</quote>, or successor publication.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HED513AE4E9804139A938294DFE1769FA"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered operational use</quote> means use by a government for operations in a defense or intelligence context.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7D0E97B5181349E0B11C752466072FA2"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The term <quote>Five Eyes countries</quote> means the following:</text><subparagraph id="HCC0C408BB3BF4412A1E476786257993A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Australia.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB2BE15A3E5F745DA8A5B9DBD6078F0BD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Canada.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H09BC69B205A942F784727633EF18673D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>New Zealand.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF759E982C3544DFCA3090E48AE1DF602"><enum>(D)</enum><text>The United Kingdom.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10755CE7F53447D1A67F4AB957E4E211"><enum>(E)</enum><text>The United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H39660CEBFDA44DEDACB609F4EEE41FD2"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Five Eyes Intelligence Oversight and Review Council</quote> means the council established pursuant to the agreement entered into between the Inspector General of the Intelligence Community of the United States and the relevant foreign counterparts of the governments of the Five Eyes countries, titled <quote>Charter of the Five Eyes Intelligence Oversight and Review Council</quote>, done on October 2, 2017.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

