<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H48A922D8079E4C2D848FB8A9D7550F22" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3190 IH: To limit the availability of certain funds for Mexico until the President makes a certification to Congress regarding cooperation by Mexico with respect to fentanyl, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3190</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230510">May 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001195">Mr. Mooney</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To limit the availability of certain funds for Mexico until the President makes a certification to Congress regarding cooperation by Mexico with respect to fentanyl, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H898352A810A840CBABDE382CC091D99F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H9426E023EC5B46DD80555B5495BFDD82" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Limitation on availability of funds under Economic Support Fund for Mexico</header> 
<subsection id="H50485BC877E940F784C6901049DFF881"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Limitation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">No amounts made available under chapter 4 of part II of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2346">22 U.S.C. 2346 et seq.</external-xref>) (relating to the economic support fund) for assistance for Mexico that are unobligated as of the date of the enactment of this Act may be obligated or expended until the President submits to Congress a written certification that Mexico is cooperating with the United States to reduce the flow of fentanyl across the southern border of the United States.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5C07292BBDB3437293A185172C51FB5D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nothing in subsection (a) shall be construed as limiting the obligation or expenditure of funds made available for assistance to Mexico for international narcotics control under chapter 8 of part I of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2291">22 U.S.C. 2291 et seq.</external-xref>) or for immigration enforcement purposes.</text> </subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

