<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H63C0A1E3727A47A6A56B22221FF9A11F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 669 IH: Restricting First Use of Nuclear Weapons Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-31</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 669</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230131">January 31, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000551">Mr. Grijalva</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000312">Mr. McGovern</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000597">Ms. Pingree</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001145">Ms. Schakowsky</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001068">Mr. Cohen</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001188">Ms. Meng</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000617">Ms. Pressley</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000574">Mr. Blumenauer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000179">Mrs. Napolitano</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000034">Mr. Pallone</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Armed Services</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To restrict the first-use strike of nuclear weapons.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9078C0A22C6B4E8EA8DEA9BFFFE245E3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H371EAF03F64B45F9A333FF4CF2B5258A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Restricting First Use of Nuclear Weapons Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HC81D11BC2A154F44AD2C9B686131CD9D" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings and declaration of policy</header> <subsection id="HE5953C649F244795A1952CCF37E885C2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text>
<paragraph id="HFD280DE18D1048E8A543AB593D6CBECA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Constitution gives Congress the sole power to declare war.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB7577C0F0770479CA5AC2B74D73E7ED4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The framers of the Constitution understood that the monumental decision to go to war, which can result in massive death and the destruction of civilized society, must be made by the representatives of the people and not by a single person.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H72B9AB1B8CE44DF3A4E8B8CDA6E45CA8"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As stated by section 2(c) of the War Powers Resolution (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/93/148">Public Law 93–148</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1541">50 U.S.C. 1541</external-xref>), <quote>the constitutional powers of the President as Commander-in-Chief to introduce United States Armed Forces into hostilities, or into situations where imminent involvement in hostilities is clearly indicated by the circumstances, are exercised only pursuant to (1) a declaration of war, (2) specific statutory authorization, or (3) a national emergency created by attack upon the United States, its territories or possessions, or its armed forces</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3ADB30BF62F44A9895D73654858021BD"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Nuclear weapons are uniquely powerful weapons that have the capability to instantly kill millions of people, create long-term health and environmental consequences throughout the world, directly undermine global peace, and put the United States at existential risk from retaliatory nuclear strikes.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3AF8DFF28D054254B5D84671841B7B84"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A first-use nuclear strike carried out by the United States would constitute a major act of war.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H60F9169329544DB587C984E3C83FA728"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A first-use nuclear strike conducted absent a declaration of war by Congress would violate the Constitution.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE1C6C74634F24819B67A45843C9A35BF"><enum>(7)</enum><text>The President has the sole authority to authorize the use of nuclear weapons, an order which military officers of the United States must carry out in accordance with their obligations under the Uniform Code of Military Justice.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8285450D888F403EA6956BE5CCEDDD12"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Given its exclusive power under the Constitution to declare war, Congress must provide meaningful checks and balances to the President’s sole authority to authorize the use of a nuclear weapon. </text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1C47B271BB11408F85E69F6E4D9D847C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Declaration of policy</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States that no first-use nuclear strike should be conducted absent a declaration of war by Congress.</text></subsection></section> <section id="H389B6A117F8B4DB78909BE2594B6225D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition on conduct of first-use nuclear strikes</header> <subsection id="H8A8D693140D8466AB78C537B2CFEB390"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>No Federal funds may be obligated or expended to conduct a first-use nuclear strike unless such strike is conducted pursuant to a war declared by Congress that expressly authorizes such strike.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HCA0C5CE14A5F4F219D1B6F62F3E1DBA5" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(b)</enum><header>First-Use nuclear strike defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>first-use nuclear strike</term> means an attack using nuclear weapons against an enemy that is conducted without the Secretary of Defense and the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff first confirming to the President that there has been a nuclear strike against the United States, its territories, or its allies (as specified in section 3(b)(2) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2753">22 U.S.C. 2753(b)(2)</external-xref>)). </text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

