<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3DADD52F30A3462986D01324DD5B83D8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1553 IH: Helping Angels Lead Our Startups Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-10</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1553</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230310">March 10, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000583">Mr. Gottheimer</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Securities and Exchange Commission to revise rules relating to general solicitation or general advertising to allow for presentations or other communication made by or on behalf of an issuer at certain events, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H946EC2A28C7842A9BC34300F51E7FE9C" style="OLC"><section id="H1D7F1FD212074C3F8AA51F543C45D08F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Helping Angels Lead Our Startups Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>HALOS Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HED68380A886B4152BDD951F20B9382FC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Clarification of general solicitation</header><subsection id="H67858118D38B4766A6EC69E8FCCACC3B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes of this Act and the revision of rules required under this Act:</text><paragraph id="HC29236D1707A460DA893E104BF79E1F6"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Angel investor group</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>angel investor group</term> means any group that—</text><subparagraph id="H1F8B580ED0D442E5B279AF8D1A15005D"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is composed of accredited investors interested in investing personal capital in early-stage companies;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H79EC6DE5DDE04B079320F19D6FECB414"><enum>(B)</enum><text>holds regular meetings and has defined processes and procedures for making investment decisions, either individually or among the membership of the group as a whole; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC86BA4596A74BEABC917294B3582CE6"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is neither associated nor affiliated with brokers, dealers, or investment advisers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB403B82788214E5EA55FC200F62BC312"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Issuer</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>issuer</term> means an issuer that is a business, is not in bankruptcy or receivership, is not an investment company, and is not a blank check, blind pool, or shell company.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFE1BC3CED08F4A0BABD003BA55B136C2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 6 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Securities and Exchange Commission shall revise Regulation D of its rules (17 CFR 230.500 et seq.) to require that in carrying out the prohibition against general solicitation or general advertising contained in section 230.502(c) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, the prohibition shall not apply to a presentation or other communication made by or on behalf of an issuer which is made at an event—</text><paragraph id="H1C45D5BDA4A24566A70B7D9A8F02BDEB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>sponsored by—</text><subparagraph id="H487B080CE9ED496283005D257F0E70F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the United States or any territory thereof, the District of Columbia, any State, a political subdivision of any State or territory, or any agency or public instrumentality of any of the foregoing;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE1D4CF32D2FA4C739D607468790CEEA6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a college, university, or other institution of higher education;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCE9D0BB57950483A8B1375B667B730BA"><enum>(C)</enum><text>a nonprofit organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4832BFF3DF1D42588D2CCB1670CCE71D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an angel investor group;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H521E5903ABAA40BA9F6FD103A376EC53"><enum>(E)</enum><text>a venture forum, venture capital association, or trade association; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H8A48C44CA1FF4BC2AB97153BB5CA48D3"><enum>(F)</enum><text>any other group, person, or entity as the Securities and Exchange Commission may determine by rule;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F18848D18724E7BA2AAF22B7C3D3043"><enum>(2)</enum><text>where any advertising for the event does not reference any specific offering of securities by the issuer;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9AABC92E7F99425E972767B111E6723C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the sponsor of which—</text><subparagraph id="HC0CD329F77D14D5EB96580E95C8149EB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>does not make investment recommendations or provide investment advice to event attendees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6B60B39486724828BFDDA43F7B08AD1F"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not engage in an active role in any investment negotiations between the issuer and investors attending the event;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD7F858F645FE489D90E32D106A3AE21E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>does not charge event attendees any fees other than reasonable administrative fees;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAC3C132CCFB348D2835E7B6BE4B398E0"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not receive any compensation for making introductions between investors attending the event and issuers, or for investment negotiations between such parties;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H50233006840F4A19BE451C6C5DDA3196"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">makes readily available to attendees a disclosure not longer than one page in length, as prescribed by the Securities and Exchange Commission, describing the nature of the event and the risks of investing in the issuers presenting at the event; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph commented="no" id="HD7AB94CA6CD74B9585BBF568CF81D743"><enum>(F)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not receive any compensation with respect to such event that would require registration of the sponsor as a broker or a dealer under the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, or as an investment advisor under the Investment Advisers Act of 1940; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF8814E11E74A4CA497041CA20AA9116C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>where no specific information regarding an offering of securities by the issuer is communicated or distributed by or on behalf of the issuer, other than—</text><subparagraph id="H2BB027058D85400A90066F3CA640123A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>that the issuer is in the process of offering securities or planning to offer securities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF5F52C6BC83D4DC7A500D109A058072D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the type and amount of securities being offered;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC3C521D46D44F0C99CE4F5E73FA2725"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the amount of securities being offered that have already been subscribed for; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46AFB8ED9B11445DAE3A51ECA7F02485"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the intended use of proceeds of the offering.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H97A78B724A684060AA52A786AE59E325"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Subsection (b) may only be construed as requiring the Securities and Exchange Commission to amend the requirements of Regulation D with respect to presentations and communications, and not with respect to purchases or sales.</text></subsection><subsection id="HFA6A670A00B84CC48CBCFDE16B6E6583"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No pre-Existing substantive relationship by reason of event</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Attendance at an event described under subsection (b) shall not qualify, by itself, as establishing a pre-existing substantive relationship between an issuer and a purchaser, for purposes of Rule 506(b).</text></subsection></section><section id="HC7A0674533AB453B8E85C9C9A63DF099"><enum>3.</enum><header>Restrictions on new filing requirements in connection with a general solicitation</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">With respect to any offer or sale of a security under Regulation D (17 CFR 230.500 et seq.) that is exempt from the prohibition against general solicitation or general advertising contained in section 230.502(c) of title 17, Code of Federal Regulations, the Securities and Exchange Commission may not issue any rule that would apply additional filing requirements (including requirements to file information with the Commission before or after a general solicitation or general advertising) to a general solicitation or general advertising of such a security that were not in effect on the date of enactment of this Act.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

