<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9D6712FF75364D0D901E2229C6AA6798" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6254 IH: Public Buildings Accountability Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6254</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231107">November 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="V000135">Mr. Van Orden</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Comptroller General of the United States to conduct a review on the Public Buildings Service, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H386340B83E8448BFB3A4862C1DA745B6" style="OLC">
<section id="HCE2CBBA44D3748D7BCE8E5E5DE55DDFA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Public Buildings Accountability Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF6E5ACD4E004420E83C2ADBC5EEE35F4" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on Public Buildings Service</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall conduct a review of the Public Buildings Service and submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Environment and Public Works of the Senate a report containing the results of such review, including—</text>
<paragraph id="H88CE88FC2A494A068B75D9B44DEEC4D8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review of the administration and management of all Public Buildings Service real estate programs and activities, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HED0E1B3083A3460E889A7BC05226016B"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a review and accounting of the number of employees and contract workers, including functions and the sources of funding (for example building operations, reimbursable work, project-specific funding) categorized by region and organizational, management, and oversight structure within the Public Building Service, including identification of components, programs, and reporting structures;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H0FB62F9F95F24586B447A513BE60E236"><enum>(B)</enum><text>an accounting of in-person attendance by employee category and function;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H8B2ECD1A6C5A440289F87843218D8C2D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an analysis, trends, and comparisons of staffing numbers and associated costs and other administrative costs over the 10 years preceding the review; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H7B119234EF9C44238546AB5057574342"><enum>(D)</enum><text>an analysis of the effectiveness of organizational structure, management, and oversight in carrying out the mission of the Public Buildings Service; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50D47616AD7941FE82AE18218742428A"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a review of the building operations account of the Federal Buildings Fund established by section 592 of title 40, United States Code, including activities and costs associated with conferences, training, and travel and transportation.</text> </paragraph></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

