<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H528C10981462417FA5FC729C196B540F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1502 IH: Comprehensive Opioid Recovery Centers Reauthorization Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-09</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1502</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230309">March 9, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001275">Mr. Bucshon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title V of the Public Health Service Act to reauthorize comprehensive opioid recovery centers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5DDFCB4253E74A93BB38D02F767AFEBB" style="OLC"><section id="H3362AB4A35B54CAEA4202137C292B5DE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Comprehensive Opioid Recovery Centers Reauthorization Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H1565A7071A984B2EA6F2492EE0A94ABC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Comprehensive opioid recovery centers</header><subsection id="H1E884FCBEEFC4A6DB78D0B88DBA7AC45"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reauthorization</header><text>Section 552(j) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290ee-7">42 U.S.C. 290ee–7(j)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>2019 through 2023</quote> and inserting <quote>2024 through 2028</quote>.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD52F32BC13CC4EE78EC1789CC0AC3BFC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Documentation for evidence of capacity To carry out required activities</header><text>Section 552(d) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290ee-7">42 U.S.C. 290ee–7(d)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H5EC06AD749D14CD9B41EC6D5F9948D42" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H764ADEEA5C6842C2A50EFD50317BB52C"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Documentation</header><subparagraph id="HF0E1A175B35A414284DE81642F6A51D6"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Evidence required to be provided under paragraph (1) may be provided through a letter of intent from partner agencies or other relevant documentation (as defined by the Secretary).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2AE370CFC11E42C3B9366A191412AFD7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Partner agency defined</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this paragraph, the term <term>partner agency</term> means a non-governmental organization or other public or private entity—</text><clause id="H6EC6AB05AC8F4EDB94B82FDFE8495CF5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the primary purpose of which is the delivery of mental health or substance use disorder treatment services; and</text></clause><clause id="H7EF6D613687E4C118EF070C1B9202D8A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">with which the applicant coordinates to provide the full continuum of treatment services (as specified in subsection (g)(1)(B)) that the applicant is unable to offer on site.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HA983DBD0AC9046BD92B94AD5DF352CA8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Center activities carried out through third parties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 552(g) of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/290ee-7">42 U.S.C. 290ee–7(g)</external-xref>) is amended in the matter preceding paragraph (1) by striking <quote>Each Center shall</quote> and all that follows through <quote>subsection (f):</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>Each Center shall, at a minimum, carry out the activities specified in this subsection directly, through referral, or through contractual arrangements. If a Center elects to carry out such activities through contractual arrangements, the Secretary may issue guidance on best practices to ensure that the Center is capable of carrying out such activities, including carrying out such activities through technology-enabled collaborative learning and capacity building models described in subsection (f) and coordinating the full continuum of treatment services specified in subparagraph (B). Such activities include the following:</quote>. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

