<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H28852894CF3A475D90B34BB964DAF361" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4681 IH: Illicit Captagon Trafficking Suppression Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4681</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230717">July 17, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="H001072">Mr. Hill</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="M001217">Mr. Moskowitz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To provide for the imposition of sanctions with respect to illicit captagon trafficking.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="HB85D3ABE41874E2D9FBCC09503BA98F3" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6B5735F7B29B4CD2B7F3FE8932B12EBE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Illicit Captagon Trafficking Suppression Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H1E2332156E7A4DFF81534580373B34D6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H29F3854730814F3082DD377405C8825C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Industrial scale production of the amphetamine-type stimulant also known as captagon, and the illicit production of precursor chemicals, in territories held by the regime of President Bashar al Assad in Syria are becoming more sophisticated and pose a severe challenge to regional and international security. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC1F165AF6ED24E5894E3FAE37431AE14"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Elements of the Government of Syria are key drivers of illicit trafficking in captagon, with ministerial-level complicity in production and smuggling, using other armed groups such as Hizballah for technical and logistical support in captagon production and trafficking.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7245C327465A4414A9A044AA2D5276B9"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As affiliates of the Government of Syria and other actors seek to export captagon, they undermine regional security by empowering a broad range of criminal networks, militant groups, mafia syndicates, and autocratic governments.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="HA52A402F09E242E6B755720B8A38BCB9"><enum>3.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States to target individuals, entities, and networks associated with the Government of Syria to dismantle and degrade the transnational criminal organizations, including narcotics trafficking networks, associated with the regime of President Bashar al Assad in Syria and Hizballah. </text></section> 
<section id="HFAB7F99548444D358D118C153DC1E97D"><enum>4.</enum><header>Imposition of sanctions with respect to illicit captagon trafficking</header> 
<subsection id="H217D16AE19034371A0DEB695AEE9716D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The sanctions described in subsection (b) shall be imposed with respect to any foreign person the President determines, on or after the date of enactment of this Act—</text> <paragraph id="HFC867CA1FD5A48A3B66A6B2B877E9339"><enum>(1)</enum><text>engages in, or attempts to engage in, activities or transactions that have materially contributed to, or pose a significant risk of materially contributing to, the illicit production and international illicit proliferation of captagon; or </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB591492F4C094BA699DB26F63E5598AC"><enum>(2)</enum><text>knowingly receives any property or interest in property that the foreign person knows—</text> <subparagraph id="HDF369F7F54C5485DA61B74486841E72A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">constitutes or is derived from proceeds of activities or transactions that have materially contributed to, or pose a significant risk of materially contributing to, the illicit production and international illicit proliferation of captagon; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEBF2F481A53E4AA9A742CB093575C347"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">was used or intended to be used to commit or to facilitate activities or transactions that have materially contributed to, or pose a significant risk of materially contributing to, the illicit production and international illicit proliferation of captagon.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5DA57639C8A649419AF6623733FE6218"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Sanctions described</header><text>The sanctions described in this subsection are the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HD7D7DB967AFB4FCC815EE68D249B925C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Blocking of property</header><text>The President shall exercise all authorities granted under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701 et seq.</external-xref>) to the extent necessary to block and prohibit all transactions in property and interests in property of the foreign person if such property and interests in property are in the United States, come within the United States, or come within the possession or control of a United States person.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H682C0ECF735A412F8200ECB2546C95ED"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ineligibility for visas, admission, or parole</header> <subparagraph id="HFA68D467636D42A4B16C293B0D23D0F0"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Visas, admission, or parole</header><text>An alien described in subsection (a) shall be—</text> 
<clause id="H0A8852E6961241039402C24AB61FC276"><enum>(i)</enum><text>inadmissible to the United States;</text></clause> <clause id="H807057029C554F7CAA467BD3FF2A4B23"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ineligible to receive a visa or other documentation to enter the United States; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H1B0C2F6C24474C2181F3FB755EF4C6D0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>otherwise ineligible to be admitted or paroled into the United States or to receive any other benefit under the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H17822CE438FD4D14A62A5F49870DC905"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Current visas revoked</header> <clause id="H9AEA4D28DA604FCDA228E833CC3ACED3"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The visa or other entry documentation of any alien described in subsection (a) is subject to revocation regardless of the issue date of the visa or other entry documentation.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HC85609C57AAE4A73BB653D727B0287EC"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Immediate effect</header><text>A revocation under clause (i) shall, in accordance with section 221(i) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1201">8 U.S.C. 1201(i)</external-xref>)—</text> <subclause id="H852534B04F754D5EBFFBCA1DAEF57CEA"><enum>(I)</enum><text>take effect immediately; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HACFE796704E643FCA55C777906D2FCFA"><enum>(II)</enum><text>cancel any other valid visa or entry documentation that is in the possession of the alien.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD0532FBB0E05405D8A98F2805D4F6E2C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties</header><text>Any person that violates, or attempts to violate, subsection (b) or any regulation, license, or order issued pursuant to that subsection, shall be subject to the penalties set forth in subsections (b) and (c) of section 206 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1705">50 U.S.C. 1705</external-xref>) to the same extent as a person that commits an unlawful act described in subsection (a) of that section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE6F810A991C64F829BE5341DB77C0962"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Waiver</header> 
<paragraph id="H48998DE1F86C4BD8BCE8CB269EDD60D9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President may waive the application of sanctions under this section with respect to a foreign person only if, not later than 15 days prior to the date on which the waiver is to take effect, the President submits to the appropriate congressional committees a written determination and justification that the waiver is in the vital national security interests of the United States.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6489945D4BA0430B8A5D923E3AB671E9"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Briefing</header><text>Not later than 60 days after the issuance of a waiver under paragraph (1), and every 180 days thereafter while the waiver remains in effect, the President shall brief the appropriate congressional committees on the reasons for the waiver.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC12749EAD6134DCB9F17E985BA50755D"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>The President may exercise all authorities provided under sections 203 and 205 of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (50 U.S.C. 1702 and 1704) to carry out this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB3D1FC670F474C11BC9E181CDEE7EEFA"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations</header> <paragraph id="H881AB7FC92C0439CBF069B2D3E7DCDCA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall, not later than 120 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, promulgate regulations as necessary for the implementation of this section.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7F861384B3454E3D9BA7F5E83273EE43"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Notification to congress</header><text>Not later than 10 days before the promulgation of regulations under this subsection, the President shall notify the appropriate congressional committees of the proposed regulations and the provisions of this section that the regulations are implementing.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H5A8AB9DFFA7944B48910C4B65383CF01"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> <paragraph id="H740D19C418B8487CBEDF33CB3085A4AC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Exception for intelligence activities</header><text>Sanctions under this section shall not apply to any activity subject to the reporting requirements under title V of the National Security Act of 1947 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/3091">50 U.S.C. 3091 et seq.</external-xref>) or any authorized intelligence activities of the United States.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H46E51AE163384AE89BF951A8E8396C59"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exception to comply with international obligations and for law enforcement activities</header><text>Sanctions under this section shall not apply with respect to an alien if admitting or paroling the alien into the United States is necessary—</text> <subparagraph id="HC1EDA08ED0324239ACB0C02EBDEEFEE7"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to permit the United States to comply with the Agreement regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947, between the United Nations and the United States, or other applicable international obligations; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0132E63B4FB84040ABEFE410CE87A4B4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to carry out or assist authorized law enforcement activity in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H76A2B3D4AFF0462284013690C80C5E6D"><enum>5.</enum><header>Determinations with respect to the Government of Syria, Hizballah, and networks affiliated with the Government of Syria or Hizballah</header> <subsection id="H4950131CBAE84194A9858485D4C6FEC3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the President shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H177703C157CA446292668C7CA63DA8CB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine whether each foreign person described in subsection (b) meets the criteria for sanctions under this Act; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H4A6F1FDF03214439B3CE7B311BC9F5D2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report containing—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H1B45503E7AFE4A4F8E6197715CBFF586"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a list of all foreign persons described in subsection (b) that meet the criteria for imposition of sanctions under this Act;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H66E64AFAB5284D128BCA1145C99E4399"><enum>(B)</enum><text>for each foreign person identified pursuant to subparagraph (A), a statement of whether sanctions have been imposed or will be imposed within 30 days of the submission of the report; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H14DDCC9A658B41899F965D5502D8E561"><enum>(C)</enum><text>with respect to any person identified pursuant to subparagraph (A) for whom sanctions have not been imposed and will not be imposed within 30 days of the submission of the report, the specific authority under which otherwise applicable sanctions are being waived, have otherwise been determined not to apply, or are not being imposed and a complete justification of the decision to waive or otherwise not apply such sanctions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H931D988F52C14FB2AA65E9360C2A6E5A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Foreign persons described</header><text>The foreign persons described in this subsection are the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="HCFAE5FD2FEE64F02B0A108CE5D9315A3"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Maher Al Assad.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H436B95584D1545FD8890B0C9D44E05A3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Imad Abu Zureiq.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H8C2338D500FE47DF839DE528520343BC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Amer Taysir Khiti.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE8ACC363CC9F499DA05FC1B1E40BFCBF"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Taher al-Kayyali.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H62220F7A77B642EC850655139D5874B0"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Raji Falhout.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H073E0BF8A6EA4BDFBA2D97F3A3C28B77"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Mohammed Asif Issa Shalish.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H337B0BC5572C4B788D24010BE00B5A83"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Abdellatif Hamid, a Syrian national.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7B2B6EC0FC424BEFA9E913CDBDDFD945"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Mustafa Al Masalmeh.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H484C3C56357044E4A000BA0FC2767BE7"><enum>6.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H7B4F1B55DD3947608C82ED98DA1AB6B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term “appropriate congressional committees” means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H6F8AE19E297B4C80BE87905EC5361ED0"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6158547C9D7A4945AB511F3B115F5ECC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations, the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB1B5BCEE44D4483DBCFCCB05DE60151E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Captagon</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>captagon</term> means any compound, mixture, or preparation which contains any quantity of a stimulant in schedule I or II of section 202 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/812">21 U.S.C. 812</external-xref>), including—</text> <subparagraph id="H0D4ECC9549A7460193EEC092513DCE5D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>amphetamine, methamphetamine, and fenethylline;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H906F9AAD328C43689D262F0A7A967658"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any immediate precursor or controlled substance analogue of such a stimulant, as defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/21/802">21 U.S.C. 802</external-xref>); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA112A53B164B4024B3F9B5006A11C6DE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any isomers, esters, ethers, salts, and salts of isomers, esters, and ethers of such a stimulant, whenever the existence of such isomers, esters, ethers, and salts is possible within the specific chemical designation.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE9AA3C7AE6974BBEB4E142120C750AED"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign person</header><text>The term “foreign person”—</text> <subparagraph id="H47210DF51C924013B8326AF4CABD6C62"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means an individual or entity that is not a United States person; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC62141EB81F74CAB93EE7C7CEEBFC398"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes a foreign state (as such term is defined in section 1603 of title 28, United States Code).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDE7FE304B34049D08CDFB649439912F6" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Illicit proliferation</header><text>The term <term>illicit proliferation</term> refers to any illicit activity to produce, manufacture, distribute, sell, or knowingly finance or transport.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF3472D3D0882446E83448E17D5AAC0FF"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Knowingly</header><text>The term “knowingly” has the meaning given that term in section 14 of the Iran Sanctions Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/104/172">Public Law 104–172</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/50/1701">50 U.S.C. 1701</external-xref> note).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7174ABEB55F64143AF53F644DAFD5E98"><enum>(6)</enum><header>United States person</header><text>The term “United States person” means—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HCB3493947F7D4E228D635426A745ED6C"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a United States citizen;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H3E209772E54A4D91958609ADF1F29BA3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a permanent resident alien of the United States;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H06913D73A0904DB0B9F794DE5A2F1AF1"><enum>(C)</enum><text>an entity organized under the laws of the United States or of any jurisdiction within the United States, including a foreign branch of such an entity; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD35BB26C05934CD797B53276E80383D8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>a person in the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> </section> 
</legis-body>
</bill> 


