<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB40830388B7244BDA0EF83248E43574B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4669 IH: DOE and SBA Research Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-17</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4669</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230717">July 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Small Business</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for Department of Energy, National Laboratories, and Small Business Administration joint research and development activities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HAD91E5EFD7F843C78DB5D4342975AF65" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HD76D0B79EF714089BF6BC00ECD92D74D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DOE and SBA Research Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF1F1D63D4F334EBEA94C2185966D1BE6"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Energy and Small Business Administration joint research and development activities</header> <subsection id="H9F97F6DE255040D99E1C086496DF9DEE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Energy, the appropriate head of a National Laboratory (as defined in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>)), and the Administrator of the Small Business Administration (in this section referred to as the <quote>covered officials</quote>) shall enter into a memorandum of understanding or other appropriate agreement to carry out cross-cutting and collaborative research and development activities focused on the joint advancement of Department of Energy and Small Business Administration mission requirements and priorities.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HC3F80DF572A44D1087E2409E851305FC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Memorandum of understanding or agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The covered officials shall carry out and coordinate the activities described in subsection (a) by entering into one or more memoranda of understanding or other appropriate agreements, as jointly determined by the covered officials.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HE6EED69EEC9542E5AE42878C21001B93"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Inclusion of small business concerns</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the activities described in subsection (a), the covered officials shall ensure the inclusion of small business concerns (as defined under section 3 of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/632">15 U.S.C. 632</external-xref>)) in such activities, as appropriate.</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H0CCBCFC4125843A387A0C5E338A9FCB1"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Other requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out the activities described in subsection (a), the covered officials may—</text> <paragraph id="H767CF5951FA44C0187CCF999C7A50C44"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">carry out reimbursable agreements between the Department of Energy, the Small Business Administration, and appropriate entities in order to maximize the effectiveness of research and development activities carried out pursuant to a memorandum or agreement described in subsection (b); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC57DCC2F1C184E5EBD3B88FBD897E691" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>collaborate with other Federal agencies as appropriate to carry out such activities. </text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H669E1324D4254B67BB44870234D70EF2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than two years after the date of the enactment of this Act, the covered officials shall submit to Congress a report on activities carried out pursuant to a memorandum or agreement described in subsection (b) that includes the following:</text> 
<paragraph id="H36D96E0F33FF47B7BE37C393D54561EE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordination between the covered officials involved in such activities.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC63E39DE38DA4BBFB041D27260DCB1AE"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Potential opportunities to expand the technical capabilities of the Department of Energy and the Small Business Administration.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2F71A2E4D08D4763857429C8E9624978"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Collaborative research achievements.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF62DBEFF31845848524659B6E42825D"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Areas of future mutually beneficial success.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H06F3B5C985F24E3BB750A40A44AE08F4"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Continuation of coordination activities between the Department of Energy and the Small Business Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H397437E3E75D420B9B51467FA0BCA71B" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Research security</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The activities carried out pursuant to a memorandum or agreement described in subsection (b) shall be applied in a manner consistent with subtitle D of title VI of the Research and Development, Competition, and Innovation Act (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/167">Public Law 117–167</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/19231">42 U.S.C. 19231 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section> 
<section id="HF364233CE2B8461E97A5B5851D92676C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Compliance with CUTGO</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No additional amounts are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act or the amendments made by this Act. Such Act and amendments shall be carried out using amounts otherwise appropriated to the Administrator of the Small Business Administration, the Secretary of Energy, or the head of a National Laboratory (as defined in section 2 of the Energy Policy Act of 2005 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/15801">42 U.S.C. 15801</external-xref>)).</text></section> </legis-body></bill>

