<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H474C6C94FCF24955B316ED07ECFDC756" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6056 IH: More Child Care and Jobs for Military Families Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6056</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="B001298">Mr. Bacon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001219">Mr. Moylan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Defense to submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on at-home child care programs of the Department of Defense, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H32001F61EF57446091AEFF86BAE8EA39" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HBBB08D535AFA47199DA95D67CD003994" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>More Child Care and Jobs for Military Families Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7CFD0F9936E049F8B0058973346A151E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Report on at-home child care programs of the Department of Defense; feasibility study</header> <subsection id="H672A9D50B3914035A5FBCB61B61671B0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 39 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report on at-home child care programs offered by each military department. Such report shall include—</text> 
<paragraph id="H28513B90D385477799C3785F2E03C62D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>an identification of the number of such at-home child care programs that have opened, closed, or relocated during the period beginning on the date of enactment of this Act and ending on the date that this three years after such date;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD8772667899F4EDD833A6786424FE8F8"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a summary of difficulties, if any, experienced by military spouses employed at such at-home child care programs with respect to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H088310A8311F465D9C588C114B176CF8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>obtaining necessary certifications or licences; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H7AE59E585BB74229B49D4AEBE5241D94"><enum>(B)</enum><text>opening, closing, or relocating such an at-home child care program; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HD27017940C82453D89A3B0A9B5F1AC30"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a summary of effects, if any, that the opening, closing, or relocation of such an at-home child care program has on the employment rate of military spouses residing in geographic proximity to such at-home child care program.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H8DA9DFCAFA4E46E196DB1C9022069992"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Feasibility study</header> <paragraph id="H7311DF5694394472A6B8F815721A9B99"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Defense shall conduct a feasibility study on—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HE05313A2C62D4952BAF337C8C05526A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>standardizing the requirements of each military department relating to licensing and certification for at-home child care providers;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HE20728C3FEEF4570B57ECBF279D38DC9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>removing barriers, if any, to the expansion of at-home child care programs described in subsection (a); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H20C312744D96459E94DA5B1044E92E2B"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">supporting the employment of military spouses in such at-home child care programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H50932E1255F84732A550E0BD31B13E88"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the submission of the report under subsection (a), the Secretary of Defense shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report that includes the findings of such feasibility study.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

