<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD1CF51E4816E4139A35A6461902DD164" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1344 IH: To rename the Dallas Veterans Affairs Medical Center in Dallas, Texas, as the “Eddie Bernice Johnson VA Medical Center”.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1344</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230303">March 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001130">Ms. Crockett</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To rename the Dallas Veterans Affairs Medical Center in Dallas, Texas, as the <quote>Eddie Bernice Johnson VA Medical Center</quote>.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA3F97BC3EC8043A4A0603A7446CEC91D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6D13D3DFCC7E42EB9F408C284BDFDCB9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text> <paragraph id="H20A6D721CB784CD4B14EB648F5F30084"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Congresswoman Eddie Bernice Johnson served the veteran community diligently during her 16 years working as the Chief Psychiatric Nurse of the Dallas VA Medical Center.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H528FD455D999411C81BFB2268200B4AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Throughout her 30 years in Congress, Eddie Bernice Johnson introduced numerous bills that sought to honor and serve the patriots who so nobly served their country.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAC0D650F8BF34A6DB8690498B43BEC15"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Congresswoman Johnson introduced, and won passage of, the Dr. James Allen Veteran Vision Equity Act of 2007 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/110/157">Public Law 110–157</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/38/101">38 U.S.C. 101</external-xref> note), which assists those wounded in service in receiving the treatment they need, and increases the dignity shown to those who gave their last full measure of devotion to the country that they served.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H75363D6613D443679F8B9179420B2182"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Congresswoman Eddie Bernice Johnson was a trailblazer who worked tirelessly on behalf of American veterans and has earned the respect and honor of her native city of Dallas, State of Texas, the United States, and the Congress.</text></paragraph></section> <section id="H57924DD37EAF448EB70C4301A1ECDE56"><enum>2.</enum><header>Designation of the Eddie Bernice Johnson VA Medical Center</header> <subsection id="HF27AFAE3AA4E43FABCC6AC386E197615"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Dallas Veterans Center of the Department of Veterans Affairs located at 4500 South Lancaster Road, Dallas, Texas, shall, after the date of the enactment of this Act, be known and designated as the <quote>Eddie Bernice Johnson VA Medical Center</quote>.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6EEEEEF4B66A4964A22C26BC36DCA6AD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Reference</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any reference in any law, regulation, map, document, paper, or other record of the United States to the veterans center referred to in subsection (a) shall be considered to be a reference to the Eddie Bernice Johnson VA Medical Center.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

