<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC98215D5242C4C56A2F9FF29BDEEEE7B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 517 IH: Standing with Moms Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 517</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230125">January 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M000194">Ms. Mace</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000569">Mr. Luetkemeyer</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000246">Mr. Fallon</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000564">Mr. Lamborn</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="F000450">Ms. Foxx</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to furnish tailored information to expecting mothers, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H099E53CFA5F3403780E66A482BE60724" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H6BB628208F3441B38D92D75C5A6F64B7" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Standing with Moms Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HA1F5225A1D314876815954D688D0E37F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Awareness for expecting mothers</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Public Health Service Act is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B277C0A58A44496AB22BFFEF370FDB4"> 
<title id="H55B635A55CAC4312A6EE0BE946CA2531"><enum>XXXIV</enum><header>Awareness for expecting mothers</header> 
<section id="H20319A6A242E40E0A3AA915333604633"><enum>3401.</enum><header>Website and portal</header> 
<subsection id="H40062E19F11B4B16BAD1EB870D817FE8"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Website</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall publish a user-friendly public website, life.gov, to provide a comprehensive list of Federal, State, local governmental, and private resources available to pregnant women including—</text> <paragraph id="HE9B98B6CE70B491BAA56770A15484666"><enum>(1)</enum><text>resources to mental health counseling, pregnancy counseling, and other prepartum and postpartum services;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H657B7CB44E3D4E95AC467DDBF605A43C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>comprehensive information on alternatives to abortion; </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H32DC13DCED3C4A3FB7DB0F059DE764FE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>information about abortion risks, including complications and failures; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0614BA1BDB3D4D26A519F819DE34167D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>links to information on child development from moment of conception.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE36EA4063EEE43919ED470F056C55F91"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Portal</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of this section, the Secretary shall publish a portal on the public website of the Department of Health and Human Services that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H5068F384A60E47BE830396648EFFDC8A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>through a series of questions, will furnish specific tailored information to the user on what pregnancy-related information they are looking for, such as—</text> <subparagraph id="H9BDA868FF76D4210B4E960B52EFC2675"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Federal, State, local governmental, and private resources that may be available to the woman within her ZIP Code, including the resources specified in subsection (c); and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H74F61724CACD40738ED155A08B24C7D5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>risks related to abortion at all stages of fetal gestation; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8C30AB152EB240F497F77CA2FCA9216C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>provides for the submission of feedback on how user-friendly and helpful the portal was in providing the tailored information the user was seeking.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB29186F11BAA49B8BA92DC2AFEFDA49F"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Resources</header><text>The Federal, State, local governmental, and private resources specified in this subsection are the following:</text> <paragraph id="H8F17AAA70E3E42408AFB07332DBE3AA7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Mentorship opportunities, including pregnancy help and case management resources.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5471CDE9EE614030B2524975FBAC9801"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Health and well-being services, including women’s medical services such as obstetrical and gynecological support services for women, abortion pill reversal, breastfeeding, general health services, primary care, and dental care.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2581DC9E569D400EA8ADA98CA8CE0950"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Financial assistance, work opportunities, nutrition assistance, childcare, and education opportunities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF1E7F6D5B9D84262957CAABCAA5F5806"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Material or legal support, including transportation, food, nutrition, clothing, household goods, baby supplies, housing, shelters, maternity homes, tax preparation, legal support for child support, family leave, breastfeeding protections, and custody issues.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE42D2B69E03A45ECB79BFFAA79B992C1"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Recovery and mental health services, including services with respect to addiction or suicide intervention, intimate partner violence, sexual assault, rape, sex trafficking, and counseling for women and families surrounding unexpected loss of a child.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE6D9AE4A92E24FF99CE9F0159C0802D3"><enum>(6)</enum><text>Prenatal diagnostic services, including disability support organizations, medical interventions for a baby, perinatal hospice resources, pregnancy and infant loss support, and literature on pregnancy wellness.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBFA5CBE1569C4CF1A37A6627EEEE93D4"><enum>(7)</enum><text>Healing and support services for abortion survivors and their families.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H7030CB3F150F4F499EC09A36A480BB9F"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Services providing care for children, including family planning education, adoption, foster care, and short-term care resources.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H7BAD01E7C336437AABDC3C0A45D80F08"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The Secretary may not delegate implementation or administration of the portal established under subsection (b) below the level of the Office of the Secretary.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HF959D3C750FE434CBB6681C2402E9DBF"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Follow-Up</header><text>The Secretary shall develop a plan under which—</text> <paragraph id="H7E1E896C153043B1A19FF17F29801356"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Secretary includes in the portal established under subsection (b), a mechanism for users of the portal to take an assessment through the portal and provide consent to use the user’s contact information;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H0BEDBE8369B44902B61C8614DB3F4703"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Secretary conducts outreach via phone or email to follow up with users of the portal established under subsection (b) on additional resources that would be helpful for the users to review; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC98181D8FE794B6799B2F78622DDF6F3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>upon the request of a user of the portal for specific information, after learning of the additional resources through the portal, agents of the Department of Health and Human Services make every effort to furnish specific information to such user in coordination with Federal, State, local governmental, and private health care providers and resources.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H13C0A10FBF674CA1B5395463B1797580"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Resource list aggregation</header> 
<paragraph id="HFB4D01C3160D4B51A66D5198C24EC93B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Pursuant to criteria developed in subsection (e)(2), each State shall provide recommendations of State, local governmental, and private resources under subsection (b)(1)(A) to include in the portal.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6934A1664B184FC6AB93B011F6F387F7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Criteria for making recommendations</header><text>The Secretary shall develop criteria to provide to the States to determine whether resources recommended as described in paragraph (1) for inclusion in the portal can appear in the portal. Such criteria shall include the requirement that the resource provider is not a prohibited entity and the requirement that the resource provider has been engaged in providing services for a minimum of 3 consecutive years.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HBD84086B5F354D19A507D8055B2EDC2B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Grant program</header> 
<subparagraph id="H46CE2278ACF04C958713CDE9CC11B2CF"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary may provide grants to States to establish or support a system that aggregates the resources described in subsection (b)(1)(A), in accordance with the criteria developed under paragraph (2), and that may be coordinated, to the extent determined appropriate by the State, by a statewide, regionally-based, or community-based public entity or private nonprofit.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H558A33F4024B4133BFE996DC3B08A248"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Applications</header><text>To be eligible to receive a grant under subparagraph (A), a State shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require, including a plan for outreach and awareness activities, and a list of service providers that would be included in the State system supported by the grant.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H75883B92E8C94BE1A48E821E2D3F57AB"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Maternal Mental Health Hotline</header><text>The Secretary shall ensure that the Maternal Mental Health Hotline of the Health Resources and Services Administration—</text> <paragraph id="H8B265ABDB1BB484AA97F7441E6442836"><enum>(1)</enum><text>disseminates information regarding, and linkages to, the life.gov website and portal described in subsections (a) and (b);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H75FF29A3057043CE9F4754BA7CE54859"><enum>(2)</enum><text>has the capacity to help families in every State and community in the Nation; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA2756C2ACAB346EB9F0032CAC85E85AF"><enum>(3)</enum><text>includes live chat features, 24 hours a day, to connect individuals to the information the portal hosts. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H44BFD62C5DC1499FA56DB1F183603A7D"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Prohibition regarding certain entities</header><text>The resources listed on the life.gov website, and made available through the portal and hotline established under this section may not include any resource offered by a prohibited entity.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H30B800CE3BFF4EC68B9F09D658A87CBE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Services in different languages</header><text>The life.gov website and hotline shall ensure the widest possible access to services for families who speak languages other than English.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4D526E09047F4C78A71E6BEA77D1EA8F"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Reporting requirements</header> 
<paragraph id="H74A6B374322543EE914BE394FD54A22D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date on which the life.gov website and portal are established under subsection (a), the Secretary shall submit to Congress a report on—</text> <subparagraph id="H684E6742CB054E1DACFB8DE8749DF0B4"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the traffic of the website and the interactive portal;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H735B4E1CF6394DCA9E82B319D4444BE0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>user feedback on the accessibility and helpfulness of the website and interactive portal in tailoring to the user’s needs;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H020693C5177844AD9B979DEABE1CB8D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>insights on gaps in Federal, State, local governmental, and private programming with respect to services for pregnant and postpartum women; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H766508667C9240168A0C05A77D1551F0"><enum>(D)</enum><text>suggestions on how to improve user experience and accessibility based on user feedback and missing resources that would be helpful to include in future updates.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7ADD0D4A8E624CF6BAF0761DA45C32E2"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Confidentiality</header><text>The report under paragraph (1) shall not include any personal identifying information regarding individuals who have used the website or portal.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HAEF783E63942422E8EE8EC0520D6E6C4"><enum>(k)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H13DE919B4D324797961FAAC06C052291"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Abortion</header><text>The term <term>abortion</term> means the use or prescription of any instrument, medicine, drug, or other substance or device to intentionally— </text> 
<subparagraph id="H0C11B651CFD94943B873D74B6F6B99D8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>kill the unborn child of a woman known to be pregnant; or </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H38B040D255584A92B510B00926201ED9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>prematurely terminate the pregnancy of a woman known to be pregnant, with an intention other than to— </text> 
<clause id="H065738857DE84511BE0F8A6C88F896A7"><enum>(i)</enum><text>increase the probability of a live birth or of preserving the life or health of the child after live birth; or </text></clause> <clause id="H13EF002B5904469B83D008ABE2C60752"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>remove a dead unborn child. </text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3840CFC3FE6D47DFB74EDDFA78DA8B88"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Born alive</header><text>The term <term>born alive</term> has the meaning given such term in section 8(b) of title 1, United States Code.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3E005B9A534E43C79CDF4E848671337A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Prohibited entity</header><text>The term <term>prohibited entity</term> means an entity, including its affiliates, subsidiaries, successors, and clinics that performs, induces, refers for, or counsels in favor of abortions, or provides financial support to any other organization that conducts such activities.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9514FC71CC944D6FB0EB93924C5ABC4C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Unborn child</header><text>The term <term>unborn child</term> means an individual organism of the species homo sapiens, beginning at fertilization, until the point of being born alive.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></title><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

