<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H82AB685497154679B2E68706CDB1B145" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"> 
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5932 IH: Fortify Israel Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code> 
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session> 
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5932</legis-num> 
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231011">October 11, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001183">Mr. Schweikert</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001120">Mr. Crenshaw</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000193">Mr. Nunn of Iowa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001224">Mr. Self</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000246">Mr. Edwards</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000446">Mr. Feenstra</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001126">Mr. Carey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001218">Mr. McCormick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="R000103">Mr. Rosendale</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc> 
</action> 
<action display="yes"> 
<action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date> 
<action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Committee on Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc> 
</action> 
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type> 
<official-title display="yes">To authorize additional assistance to Israel using assets confiscated from the Iran, and for other purposes.</official-title> 
</form> 
<legis-body id="H3549D9F1F6A045CCA00A50D6FCC36AAA" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H025B7A5901C148CFA8C559CA5A580AAB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fortify Israel Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5BA3CCE349E34079B11636825BA388B5" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Prohibition on release of blocked Iranian assets</header> <subsection id="HED46C937768C43DCA01C8F8A04B035FC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No Iranian asset that is blocked or immobilized by the Department of the Treasury before the date of the enactment of this Act may be released or mobilized until the President certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6BC6E50AF8D744E0B7977BA280791326"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hostilities between Hamas and other Iranian-backed groups and Israel have ceased; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H67340555F3454C3FB7EDE02381FF8744"><enum>(2)</enum> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7F4FAB46B5784555B534D955744927D9"><enum>(A)</enum><text>full compensation has been made to Israel for harms resulting from the invasion of Israel by Hamas and other Iranian-backed groups; or</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H2A4A91C261744F2EB44320070F754932" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Iran is participating in a bona fide international mechanism that, by agreement, will discharge the obligations of Iran to compensate Israel for all amounts determined to be owed to Israel.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF6EB4D5DF2414087B08292F8F7C35675"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Notification</header><text>Not later than 30 days before the release or mobilization of an Iranian asset that previously had been blocked or immobilized by the Department of the Treasury, the President shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6A16FE682F9C40D48EC3AE461D6D3609"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a notification of the decision to release or mobilize the asset; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H845F662C2E2A47C5A3B938F34511A2BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a justification in writing for such release or mobilization.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB4629AF3E37746EE818C11A33A62F84A"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Joint resolution of disapproval</header> 
<paragraph id="H388165563325450B9A6E9115EE7C551F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No Iranian asset that previously had been blocked or immobilized by the Department of the Treasury may be released or mobilized if, within 30 days of receipt of the notification and justification required under subsection (b), a joint resolution is enacted prohibiting the proposed release or mobilization.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF4E787005A754954B4317B2EF01615F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Expedited procedures</header><text>Any joint resolution described in paragraph (1) introduced in either House of Congress shall be considered in accordance with the provisions of section 601(b) of the International Security Assistance and Arms Export Control Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/94/329">Public Law 94–329</external-xref>; 90 Stat. 765), except that any such resolution shall be amendable. If such a joint resolution should be vetoed by the President, the time for debate in consideration of the veto message on such measure shall be limited to 20 hours in the Senate and in the House of Representatives shall be determined in accordance with the Rules of the House.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H6AD7B98511A3416AB9DC109B26D04655" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Cooperation on prohibition of release of certain Iranian assets</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may take such action as may be necessary to seek to obtain an agreement or arrangement between the United States, Israel, and other countries that have blocked or immobilized Iranian assets to prohibit such assets from being released or mobilized until an agreement has been reached that discharges Iran from further obligations to compensate Israel. </text></subsection></section> <section id="H4301CD78580D4B6085AD984C8FED5502"><enum>3.</enum><header>Authority to ensure compensation to Israel using confiscated Iranian assets</header> <subsection id="HABCB6302F5E14DA487D4C18617946C99"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Confiscation</header> <paragraph id="H80F7DD811F244A70A644405C2DC49784"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The President may confiscate any Iranian assets subject to the jurisdiction of the United States, including assets that are within the scope of the Iranian assets authorized to be transferred from South Korea to the oversight of Qatar on September 11, 2023.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H44A3D3515226483BA72854CB26F26854"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Liquidation and deposit</header><text>The President shall—</text> <subparagraph id="HE7934AC4CB8A450EA3D4D6B8F928DCBA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>deposit any funds confiscated under paragraph (1) into the Fund established under subsection (b);</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HCC635F0C6DDE49749545FCE88632786D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>liquidate or sell any other property confiscated under paragraph (1) and deposit the funds resulting from such liquidation or sale into the Fund established under subsection (b); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HB01B6E2513BE4194A130D16556C06D1B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>make all such funds available for the purposes described in subsection (b)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC4FEED53E5F34654BC725F040FF8AF50"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Vesting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">All right, title, and interest in Iranian assets confiscated under paragraph (1) shall vest, if necessary, in the Government of the United States while being held in the Fund established under subsection (b).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H422DE94650AB448EB6903B13E3F512D0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of a Fund To provide assistance to Israel</header> <paragraph id="H96DDDF9C43164EF1B99F4384B172FCC8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall establish a non-interest-bearing account to consist of the funds deposited into the account under subsection (a).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1C8CC42E3B284AA0BDA6C14CF0664275"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of funds</header><text>Amounts in the account established under paragraph (1) are authorized to be made available for the procurement of defense articles and services for Israel.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HCF1FA7509E744708B87886F13A4B318B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Judicial review</header> <paragraph id="HB878BFB7956B4730B24C089C53DF9B8C"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The confiscation of Iranian assets under subsection (a)(1) shall not be subject to judicial review.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2D22BB0F9AFF493AACF5B70178CE09A7"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Rule of construction</header><text>Nothing in this subsection shall be construed to limit any private individual or entity from asserting due process claims in United States courts.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HDE5A0178632A482CA2EF54069979A291"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Exception for United States obligations under Vienna Conventions</header><text>The authorities provided by this section may not be exercised in a manner inconsistent with the obligations of the United States under—</text> 
<paragraph id="H91C8EEBF510F4213A75399DD47DBEA7F"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Convention on Diplomatic Relations, done at Vienna April 18, 1961, and entered into force April 24, 1964 (23 UST 3227);</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7E8986D85ECB47578D4DEC75E85DEF8B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Convention on Consular Relations, done at Vienna April 24, 1963, and entered into force on March 19, 1967 (21 UST 77);</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H05200AF624F5466B9739205B07ADA404"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Agreement Regarding the Headquarters of the United Nations, signed at Lake Success June 26, 1947, and entered into force November 21, 1947 (TIAS 1676); or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF98D558DF2C4416A87E531F07A73263"><enum>(4)</enum><text>any other international agreement governing the use of force and establishing rights under international humanitarian law.</text></paragraph></subsection> </section> 
</legis-body> 
</bill> 


