<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H20703B0B55F24A86A64140E43A0D26CF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3534 IH: Justice is Beneficial Limitation on Investments and Necessary Disclosure Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-18</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3534</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230518">May 18, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000288">Mr. Johnson of Georgia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000147">Ms. Norton</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001225">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000582">Mr. Lieu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000551">Ms. Lee of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000481">Ms. Tlaib</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000194">Mr. Nickel</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000474">Mrs. Torres of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001177">Mr. Sablan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000096">Mr. Davis of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000586">Mr. García of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001205">Ms. Scanlon</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000559">Mr. Garamendi</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require justices, judges, magistrate judges, or bankruptcy judges and their spouses and dependent children to place certain assets into qualified blind trusts, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H999A02958BF8444FAEB076C2577BB291" style="OLC"><section id="H3E218C59F89F415781AF556680A5FFEB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Justice is Beneficial Limitation on Investments and Necessary Disclosure Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or as the <quote><short-title>Justice is BLIND Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HF247BA64F3A24D86A82BA9F54CA6D3EB"><enum>2.</enum><header>Placement of certain assets of justices, judges, magistrate judges, or bankruptcy judges and their spouses and dependent children in blind trust</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 455 of title 28, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1474EAA7292040A2B8C75024EF25FEAA"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (c), by inserting the following: <quote>though such efforts should not include seeking information about the identity of the financial instruments contained in any qualified blind trust other than the initial assets of the qualified blind trust established by a justice, judge, magistrate judge or bankruptcy judge, or the spouse or dependent child of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge, to comply with subsection (g)</quote> before the period at the end; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H80801B856B2F4A2B81084FEBD6439F0E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="USC" id="H18E5DC18B05D436CA41018F9666285DF" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H78DAC8E7F1F444249F01EC829A91C135"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Placement of certain assets of justices, judges, magistrate judges, or bankruptcy judges and their spouses and dependent children in qualified blind trust</header><paragraph id="HCCA2E65028C44466931F3C1BBB499983"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><subparagraph id="H7EDAE6A3B9D14B1EBF290E0E25325C61"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge occupying office on date of enactment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the effective date of this subsection, a justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge and any spouse or dependent child of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge shall place any covered financial interest of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge or by any spouse or dependent child of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge, into a qualified blind trust.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H58F8AECCB8AF498D8E752FE9C5B2661A"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge assuming office after date of enactment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date an individual becomes a justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge, such individual and any spouse or dependent child of such individual shall place any covered financial interest of such individual, spouse, or dependent child into a qualified blind trust.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H28FAA806929B491B80E4954AF7996724"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Mingling of assets</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A spouse or dependent child of a justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge may place a covered financial interest in a qualified blind trust established by such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge under subparagraph (A) or (B). A justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge may place a covered financial interest in a qualified blind trust established by the spouse of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge under subparagraph (A) or (B).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA700A661C804D7C8DD6C2EF40905F9C"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Assets upon separation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge and any spouse or dependent child of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge may not dissolve any qualified blind trust in which a covered financial interest has been placed pursuant to subparagraph (A) or (B), or otherwise control such a financial interest, until the date that is 180 days after the date such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge ceases to be a justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6DFDF85A4CCC436D956BB75039A27042"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Accountability</header><subparagraph id="H9550B78AB09F49C48A5AF863AB9C7FDD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge shall—</text><clause id="H018967D5D7D242A8B6B718E652A42A32"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">not later than 15 days after the date a qualified blind trust is established under paragraph (1), attest in writing that such trust has been established and that any covered financial interest of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge or a spouse or dependent child of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge has been placed in such trust; or</text></clause><clause id="H1F6291F8ABED465BB148934286DF6D1A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">attest in writing that neither such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge nor a spouse or dependent child of such justice, judge, magistrate judge, or bankruptcy judge have any financial interests.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA510BE18A7FB43B89F6E3CA720F9D4D0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrative Office of the United States Courts shall make available on the searchable internet database established under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-act" parsable-cite="usc-act/Ethics in Government Act of 1978 /105">section 105(c)</external-xref> of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/5/13107">5 U.S.C. 13107(c)</external-xref>) any attestation made under subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H51BC81596D444E9982783233773E9033"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Exception</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A spouse or dependent child who receives compensation from their primary occupation through any covered financial interest shall not be required to place such covered financial interest in a qualified blind trust under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H68BEAF7382364139A305AF5234B36158"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this subsection:</text><subparagraph id="H84E1C48249B84179910B192052BB799B"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Commodity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>commodity</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1a of the Commodity Exchange Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1a">7 U.S.C. 1a</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF8A755473FB5412887C16EA9154448C7"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Covered financial interest</header><text>The term <term>covered financial interest</term>— </text><clause id="H23886F3A55874ECE8FDC6AA7F223E2B6"><enum>(i)</enum><text>means a financial interest in a security, a commodity, or a future, or any comparable economic interest acquired through synthetic means such as the use of a derivative; and</text></clause><clause id="H1041BBA7C0FB4BA4B20B5D08AE36235A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>does not include—</text><subclause id="HA92C5869ADF2487F849AFD0EB88FD812"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a widely held investment fund described in section 13104(f)(8) of title 5 that is diversified and registered as a management company under the Investment Company Act of 1940 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/80a-1">15 U.S.C. 80a–1 et seq.</external-xref>); or</text></subclause><subclause id="H9797FE55A90E4DA6A5478977DAA3FF73"><enum>(II)</enum><text>a United States Treasury bill, note, or bond.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFEC1066778714BABAFFBFAE80E980493"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Dependent child</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>dependent child</term> has the meaning given that term in section 13101 of title 5.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FCB3B6CB9F14E5C9BFB5DBA86CF94A1"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Qualified blind trust</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>qualified blind trust</term> has the meaning given that term in section 13104(f)(3) of title 5.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9288C30BD77E4CC685337468447D82AA"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Severability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If any provision of this subsection or the application of such provision to any person or circumstance is held to be unconstitutional, the remainder of this subsection and the application of the remaining provisions of this subsection to any person or circumstance, shall not be affected.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

