<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HE781527C3B924D828FF1470EB0188B77" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6836 IH: Preserving Home and Office Numbers in Emergencies Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6836</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231214">December 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="N000189">Mr. Newhouse</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Communications Act of 1934 to provide for a moratorium on number reassignment after a disaster declaration, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H3AB998AFF93E4BACBF2E59E4C4E7B1E1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H2C022E857F8848D3BD780F761553214D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Preserving Home and Office Numbers in Emergencies Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>PHONE Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H86AA8A63F3094E448B2EA11EDE31C2B7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Moratorium on number reassignment after disaster declaration</header> <subsection id="HE27338C44D4043EB8703957BFB493EA4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 251(e) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/251">47 U.S.C. 251(e)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HF9817CE70FF744D5B654F7947420A3D8" style="OLC"> 
<paragraph id="HFA8FD0CB17824806953D255BE137B2CB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Moratorium on number reassignment after disaster declaration</header> 
<subparagraph id="HD81D48937E5F4067B3C592B82FA00042" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a number assigned to a subscriber for the provision of fixed wireline voice service at a location in a designated area during a covered period—</text> <clause id="H95202AD2EE7346BF91560288966A9F8D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the number may not be reassigned, except at the request of the subscriber; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="H0E747B2BF34E4846B7E22D3A51FC1850"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the assignment of the number may not be rescinded or otherwise modified, except at the request of the subscriber.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H6572FACBDF3B4ADB84F8BC5677B1AF73" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extension at request of subscriber</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">During the covered period, at the request of a subscriber described in subparagraph (A), the prohibition in subparagraph (A) shall be extended for the number for 1 year after the date on which the covered period expires.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H16C77395F35142A0BC1179C1C9AE70B6"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Subscriber right to cancel and resubscribe</header> 
<clause id="HCD9950E1A86C4727ABB9B7A5D12A690D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In the case of a number described under subparagraph (A) or (B), if the subscriber assigned to such number demonstrates to the provider of the service (or, under subclause (II), any other provider of fixed wireline voice service that serves the local area) that the residence where the number is located is inaccessible or uninhabitable—</text> <subclause id="HACE277AC36214D4D9ADD89F719EBDEE4" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the provider may not charge the subscriber an early termination or other fee in connection with the cancellation of such service, if cancelled during the covered period or the extension of the period described in subparagraph (B); and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H77E331DABE634078B2E492E59F990519"><enum>(II)</enum><text> if the subscriber cancels the service during the covered period or the extension of the period described in subparagraph (B), the provider (or any other provider of fixed wireline voice service that serves the local area)—</text> <item id="HA0B81CEF260B481CB6074AFBB42B5C0F"><enum>(aa)</enum><text>shall permit the subscriber to subscribe or resubscribe, as the case may be, to fixed wireline voice service with the number at the residence or at a different residence (if such number is available in the location of such different residence); and</text></item> 
<item id="H112CA7DD99894E9DB2A01A1CE79BD28F"><enum>(bb)</enum><text>may not charge the subscriber a connection fee or any other fee relating to the initiation of fixed wireline voice service.</text></item></subclause></clause> <clause id="H67BAE37F80DF4DC1A1B37F7C1C5E402A" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Cancellation without demonstration of inaccessibility or uninhabitability</header><text>If a subscriber cancels the provision of service assigned to a number described in subparagraph (A) or (B) and does not demonstrate to the provider of such service that the residence where the number is located is inaccessible or uninhabitable as described under clause (i), the number is no longer subject to the prohibition under subparagraph (A) or (B).</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H42EFFE46E793420C8E07AE49C3397C4B"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Identification on commission website</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall publicly identify on the website of the Commission each designated area that is in a covered period, not later than 15 days after the submission of a public designation by a State under subparagraph (E)(iii) with respect to such area. In identifying a designated area under subparagraph (E)(iii), a State shall consult with providers of fixed wireline voice service that serve such area and coordinate with the Federal Emergency Management Agency to reasonably limit the designated area to areas that have sustained covered damage.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFBAB3F1AD20E42A2B94B723105527B6D"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this paragraph:</text> 
<clause id="H0358ABBD92924A929826129ADB36D0E9"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Covered damage</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>covered damage</quote> means, with respect to an area—</text> <subclause id="H179A4DC8B7B849F09787FB893B04F96F"><enum>(I)</enum><text>damage that renders residences in such area inaccessible or uninhabitable; or</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="HF65101B6A2BB4F368AA7126A6247EA4A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>damage that otherwise results in the displacement of subscribers from or within such area.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="HA75579EEADE3438892A35BA5B654888E"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Covered period</header><text>The term <term>covered period</term> means a period that—</text> 
<subclause id="H77AF2DDED1254B0FA4AD362ABA1C08EE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>begins on the date of a declaration by the President of a major disaster under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>) with respect to a designated area; and</text></subclause> <subclause id="HB307EFCDE8984E31873D53154BE54F81"><enum>(II)</enum><text>ends on the date that is 1 year after such date.</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H196A99B9C5354141ABB5CBD231E9F41E" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Designated area</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>designated area</term> means a geographic area for which a State has submitted a public designation to the Commission, within 15 days after a declaration by the President of a major disaster under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>) with respect to such area, stipulating that the State has determined that—</text> <subclause id="HF2D5C1DFA10F457F9C6D33A2C7753C2B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>covered damage was sustained in such area; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H5D4ED248F601436FA44140ED48F21D3A"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the prohibitions described in this paragraph are necessary and in the public interest.</text></subclause></clause> <clause id="H38452958D0ED42F08768B7E2700784DA"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Voice service</header><text>The term <term>voice service</term> has the meaning given the term <term>voice service</term> in section 227(e)(8).</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection> 
<subsection id="HB06934F0AACF4FEAB4F4EF4D76743B0A"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendment of FCC rules required</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Federal Communications Commission shall amend its rules to reflect the requirements of paragraph (5) of section 251(e) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/251">47 U.S.C. 251(e)</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB4379DCF1304462A8AD392A5C7428D97"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Paragraph (5) of section 251(e) of the Communications Act of 1934 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/47/251">47 U.S.C. 251(e)</external-xref>), as added by subsection (a), shall apply with respect to a major disaster declared by the President under section 401 of the Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/5170">42 U.S.C. 5170</external-xref>) after the date that is 180 days after the date on which the Commission announces that the Commission is capable of publicly identifying a designated area on the website of the Commission under subparagraph (D) of such paragraph (5).</text></subsection> </section> 
</legis-body></bill>

