<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2F25067D3EF9489EAACE9AA6E0DE1073" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5621 IH: 2023 WHIP+ Reauthorization Ac</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5621</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230921">September 21, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="A000379">Mr. Alford</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To extend the wildfire and hurricane indemnity program to cover certain crop losses in calendar year 2023, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDB0C86C0CB7A4FD8A115BE0D105A3A6D" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H90CA5CC1F8A74F77BD4991AD7F9F1776" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>2023 WHIP+ Reauthorization Ac</short-title>t</quote>.</text></section> <section id="H5D9B9A9699FB4E4495175A230BC764C9"><enum>2.</enum><header>Disaster indemnity program</header> <subsection id="HD39938F7A613487796672229B9DACB3E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as otherwise provided in this section, with respect to the coverage period, the Secretary shall carry out—</text> 
<paragraph id="HFF57AFE43929454C8C3CF2CAB89D1D50"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a disaster indemnity program in the same manner as the WHIP+ program is carried out under subpart O of part 760 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section); </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H59ED780536D04524912AE65270A956A8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>an on-farm storage loss program in the same manner as the program carried out under subpart P of part 760 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section); and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H847BCC4FA7B9402BAF177E10F358A686"><enum>(3)</enum><text>a milk loss program in the same manner as the program carried out under subpart Q of part 760 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H847E097D392A4B339C258F571D8CCAE0" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered losses</header><text>In carrying out the programs under this section, the Secretary shall make payments to producers in accordance with subsection (c) for qualified losses of covered crops, including milk, that occurred during the coverage period. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H809CE0DE890847ABB461E0542A5B03CD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Payments</header> 
<paragraph id="H44E67A256A5241F295FE4ACA975F6C57"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Payments to producers for qualified losses of covered crops, including milk, under the programs under this section shall be administered, except as provided in paragraph (2), in the same manner as payments under the relevant programs in subsection (a).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAEF5143F6B494BAABE7446A6281689F1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Exceptions</header> <subparagraph id="H9102B463B4B2433EB4AA8B2AE4E4D2BE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Direct payments required</header><text>The Secretary shall make payments under the programs under paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (a) as direct payments to producers or processors, at the election of the processor.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H5932BCAFAC354A3AA56E2AEE94AA4F9C"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Special rule for unharvested acres</header><text>The Secretary shall make payments under this section with respect to qualified losses of unharvested acres of a covered crop in the same manner as payments are made with respect to eligible crop losses under the noninsured crop assistance program under section 196 of the Federal Agriculture Improvement and Reform Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/7333">7 U.S.C. 7333</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H496A1537EFED4B0BA467CDD49A6E0F78"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Payment limitations</header> <clause id="HFD46A4D8E5BD492EB824EC91DA4CA275"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in clauses (ii), (iii), (iv), and (v), the Secretary shall impose payment limitations consistent with section 760.1507 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section).</text></clause> 
<clause id="H919B7FD446E244A39087B82DD42CF653"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception for specialty crops or high value crops</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of specialty crops or high value crops, as determined by the Secretary, the Secretary shall impose payment limitations consistent with section 760.1507(a)(2) of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on January 1, 2019).</text></clause> <clause id="HB8A8F11873AB42598032B0446AE43E66"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Tax year basis</header><text>In applying the payment limitations under this subparagraph, the Secretary shall determine a person or legal entity’s average adjusted gross income and average adjusted gross farm income based on the 2019, 2020, and 2021 tax years.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HA8712C1F6B6B45DEB66889282EB0611F" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Annual renewal</header><text>With respect to the payment limitations described under this subparagraph, the Secretary shall apply separate payment limits for each of the years under the covered period.</text></clause> <clause id="HCE6AE947F49F48A6BF2B3B33395B3634"><enum>(v)</enum><header>Entity rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to payments to a corporation, limited liability company, limited partnership, trust, or estate under this section, the Secretary shall—</text> 
<subclause id="H88A508E4ADD24E929ECCE9D1E298DBF9"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">determine average adjusted gross income and average adjusted gross farm income in accordance with clause (iii); and </text></subclause> <subclause id="H463F6B9E314F4FB9B2B6966CB0EBC640"><enum>(II)</enum><text>apply rules in the same manner as subsections (d) and (e) of section 9.7 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H1B7734E4726549DB8BBE10690879060A" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><header>Net indemnities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In calculating payments under the programs under paragraphs (1), (2), and (3) of subsection (a), the Secretary shall net out crop insurance indemnities, less any insurance premiums paid by the producer. </text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H48F37D88A8334E39AACF65D773429A3F"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Payments to sugar and dairy processors</header> <clause id="HCB308A1A41D942E28100C3EA64F1FF7F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">At the election of a processor eligible for a loan under section 156 of the Federal Agriculture Improvement and Reform Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/7272">7 U.S.C. 7272</external-xref>) or a cooperative processor of dairy, in lieu of payments to producers provided under a program described in subsection (a), the Secretary shall make payments to a processor to be paid to producer members, as determined by such processors under the same terms and conditions as payments made to processors pursuant to section 791(c) of title VII of division B of the Further Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/94">Public Law 116–94</external-xref>). </text></clause> 
<clause id="H798F13E5F79B44759F5803A1846B4C61"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Non-election</header><text>Notwithstanding section 760.1503(j) of title 7 of the Code of Federal Regulations, in the event that a processor described in clause (i) does not elect to receive payments under such clause, the Secretary shall make direct payments to producers under a program described in subsection (a).</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0D4FEA74E70741099EEB020107B7293D"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Block grants</header><text>The Secretary may provide payments in the form of block grants to States and processors described in subparagraph (E).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0EEC461CEDE1471499C2A98BED6D281A" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header> 
<paragraph id="HB416707BBB354E7782FB2C1B8EC609B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to carry out this section $8,500,000,000.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2B19FE6FEE944CE2A2F946E7F1E84072"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administration</header><text>The Secretary may use not more than 1 percent of the funds appropriated pursuant to paragraph (1) to carry out the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H35EE449DB246452898A26CB9DBC389B0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Streamlining the application process.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H84BC1BA02FC046DE9C5EAF59BBB65E22"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Utilizing information technology to enable the electronic transfer of data used in such application process between the Risk Management Agency and the Farm Service Agency.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0062D87D92DC49FD948E24CB3EEF9914"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Activities that with respect to county office employees, reduce the workload of such employees in carrying out this section.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H98A0CA0ABE164133A6EEAF031B013EEC"><enum>(D)</enum><text>To the maximum extent practicable, providing the necessary information to, and assisting crop insurance agents with, providing application information on behalf of insured producers.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H99585EF91EAC436680647654BDB06E3B"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Exemption</header><text>Notwithstanding the Federal Funding Accountability and Transparency Act of 2006 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/109/282">Public Law 109–282</external-xref>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/31/6101">31 U.S.C. 6101</external-xref> note), the requirements of parts 25 and 170 of title 2, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations), shall not apply with respect to assistance received under this section. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H795EA66E4263495BBDAC8628D0EEE2F0"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text> 
<paragraph id="H7B1FFF50F7914D8C86FFA1C8001B48A5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Coverage period</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>coverage period</term> means, with respect to a covered crop, including milk, and a qualifying disaster event described in paragraph (6)(A)(i), calendar years 2023 and 2024.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1ED5759D534B4DEE9AEC04F542DA7505"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Covered crop</header><text>The term <term>covered crop</term> means a crop, tree, bush, or vine described in section 760.1503 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section), including wine grapes, which shall include all insured acreage (regardless of whether such acreage is the initial acreage or not).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2722EB5C19E14B1FB1CBC643CAA268A7"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Milk loss program</header><text>The term <term>milk loss program</term> means the milk loss program under subpart Q of part 760 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD0D5E3C0FE7E4505B2C747C6280B7B82"><enum>(4)</enum><header>On-farm storage loss program</header><text>The term <term>on-farm storage loss program</term> means the on-farm storage loss program under subpart P of part 760 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section)</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5E6FE50D4AE749E78CD79E6EE4B2EF8C"><enum>(5)</enum><header>State</header><text>In this section, the term <term>State</term> has the meaning given the term in section 1111(20) of the Agricultural Act of 2014.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H763E5B3FB7E446FCBCE64A7132AD20BE"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Qualified loss</header><text>The term <term>qualified loss</term>—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HA5B89E2D31E34EAF80D584D55B8FFB65"><enum>(A)</enum><text>with respect to a covered crop not described in subparagraph (B), the loss of such crop during the coverage period—</text> <clause id="H0338C6CEF89B45CC88362433D0E55767"><enum>(i)</enum><text>due to a qualifying disaster event described in the definition of <quote>qualifying disaster event</quote> in section 760.1802 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section);</text></clause> 
<clause id="H007B9F5F2F2845A385D170C7644AA98D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>due to high winds, derechos, excessive heat, or freeze (including a polar vortex);</text></clause> <clause id="H41A2B6B5BCC64C54AD6DB58647A84D83"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>due to a drought in—</text> 
<subclause id="H97F2BF369BE44AE9B3302BEA1C7D56E9"><enum>(I)</enum><text>a county the Secretary designated for drought; or</text></subclause> <subclause id="HF41E126CF16341AFA00080E137B874AB"><enum>(II)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a county contiguous to a county described in subclause (I); or</text></subclause></clause> 
<clause id="H529305F9CACA4A16BCCB389E9201AC5A"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>due to other disruptions (including power outages or curtailments) that are associated with the effects of a qualified disaster event under this section; and</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H474C4BBEB3C4483C845A2C9AA582A5A4"><enum>(B)</enum><text>with respect to smoke tainted wine grapes, the loss (including a quality loss) of such crop during the coverage period due to wildfire, as determined by the Secretary.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H2B1A52D288F04B43A4E60455DB06C3ED"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H177F34B06FC4495BAA5BE087E8BA382D"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Whip+ program</header><text>The term <term>WHIP+ program</term> means the WHIP+ program under subpart O of part 760 of title 7, Code of Federal Regulations (as in effect on the date of the enactment of this section).</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

