<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB1A5834702C146A89F83358674EC1871" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5287 IH: Veterans Access to Direct Primary Care Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5287</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230825">August 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="R000614">Mr. Roy</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="C001132">Mr. Crane</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000589">Mr. Gooden of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000816">Mr. Williams of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001311">Mr. Bishop of North Carolina</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to establish a pilot program to provide veteran health savings accounts to allow veterans to receive primary care furnished under non-Department direct primary care service arrangements, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H55853810514B4163A38258B11CDE192F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H49EBF5760A54490C8F785C1B7B6FE355" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Veterans Access to Direct Primary Care Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H477A4F207AB64220B97EA84572A3C97A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Pilot program on establishment of veteran health savings accounts to allow veterans to access direct primary care service arrangements</header> <subsection id="H459F795EB2D3495AA99D67A029271693"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Beginning one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall carry out a five-year pilot program under which the Secretary shall provide eligible veterans with the option to choose to receive primary care services furnished by a non-Department of Veterans Affairs health care provider under a direct primary care service arrangement through the use of a veteran health savings account described in subsection (c). The pilot program shall be conducted under the Center for Innovation for Care and Payment under section 1703E of title 38, United States Code.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HCD24501D109E4287B5ED3B37A3C1D10C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligible veteran</header><text>For purposes of the pilot program under this section, an eligible veteran is a veteran who is enrolled in the patient enrollment system of the Department of Veterans Affairs under section 1705 of title 38, United States Code.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H9DECD57A445B424F901A3C1CD7D41C87"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Veteran health savings accounts</header><text>The Secretary shall provide to an eligible veteran who participates in the pilot program a veterans health savings account that may be used—</text>
<paragraph id="H80846D6D6A3446058D567341476AF98C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to purchase primary care services furnished through a non-Department direct primary care service arrangement; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HC99B4930703C474ABF7266A02AA7E084"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for associated costs, including—</text>
<subparagraph id="H0CFEE754D5B347CEA3A298BED4787D87"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">periodic fees paid to a physician for a defined set of medical services or for the right to receive medical services on an as-needed basis;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H68763172C4AF46229BCF6281C09E148C"><enum>(B)</enum><text>amounts paid or prepaid for medical services designed to screen for, diagnose, cure, mitigate, treat, or prevent disease and promote wellness; and</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HCFB7698B81594991B88AB8EED29A9F41"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prescription or non-prescription medicines or drugs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0AFD64E2693C43C093331F34C05C5138"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Eligibility for Department medical care</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A veteran who chooses to receive a veteran health savings account described under subsection (c) may not receive medical care furnished by the Department of Veterans Affairs that is included in the direct primary care service arrangement described in such subsection during the period the veteran participates in the pilot program.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HFD3AB89EB24640B3BFBFEB64B25D7BA9"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Prevention of fraudulent activity</header><text>The Secretary shall establish a mechanism to prevent fraudulent activity in connection with payments made under this section and to ensure participating veterans use health savings accounts only as authorized under this section.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HC3CD90BB0BD64068BD166B844AE3A1C4"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Amounts deposited in accounts</header><text>The Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall—</text>
<paragraph id="HD395594E5CE2442A9AD2D8E1083284BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text>determine the annual amount to be deposited in a veteran health savings account described in subsection (c) using calculations conducted by the Secretary and in consultation with an actuarial service; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3D80636CC2724AF5854256D0C1BA6210"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that each participating eligible veteran receives such amount on an annual basis during the period the veteran participates in the pilot program.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H81643C9B4DF2445CB316BCD8C77BFABC" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Direct primary care service arrangement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <term>direct primary care service arrangement</term> means an agreement under which a defined set of medical services are provided to a patient by a physician for fixed periodic fees. </text></subsection> <subsection id="H8B4DF364F8FE46D09CD4D72F3701D17B"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Reports</header> <paragraph id="H43E1D8C87B614FD5A029FE92F6BA8A68"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Implementation reports</header><text>For each calendar quarter during the two-year period beginning on the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on the implementation of this section. One such report shall include a description of the final design of the pilot program.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDBDDC015941B4820950120918AF82399"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date on which the final implementation report required by paragraph (1) is submitted, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate and House of Representatives a report on the results of the pilot program under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HF551666A29924777839D6432F69E2744"><enum>(i)</enum><header>No additional appropriations</header><text>Amounts required to carry out this section shall be made available from amounts otherwise authorized to be appropriated for the Veterans Health Administration.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HD00B083D2A0B4EDBA0E03A98245365C1"><enum>(j)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The authority of the Secretary to deposit funds in a veteran health savings account under this section shall terminate on the date that is five years after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

