<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9E8A682FB41446838ABAF9FEA73AFCC8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 285 IH: Cybersecurity Vulnerability Remediation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 285</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230111">January 11, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to provide for the remediation of cybersecurity vulnerabilities, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6146801D2F104A7B8CC96A2772E566FD" style="OLC"><section id="H585034E8056B4D7CB664A038AFD651A1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Cybersecurity Vulnerability Remediation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H007E3E536C5E4D51857F5FCC1063DED7"><enum>2.</enum><header>Cybersecurity vulnerabilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2209 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/659">6 U.S.C. 659</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HBEA7602079074CB4A96E8F67DBCCF5A8"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="H23F8122F435344D3ABC78F5BF98D7120"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraphs (6) through (9) as paragraphs (7) through (10), respectively; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H221687AF6262448CB2DECCDA3F733AAD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (5) the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE43EC3B141534B46B7D2048D9B130252" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H5BE4939F4A9947FFAF61698DABB23022"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the term <quote>cybersecurity vulnerability</quote> has the meaning given the term <quote>security vulnerability</quote> in section 102 of the Cybersecurity Information Sharing Act of 2015 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/1501">6 U.S.C. 1501</external-xref>); and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A57C66BFBA14E768E3562635776BD82"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (c)—</text><subparagraph id="HF2442C9F7C7A476582AF005A13B808C0"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (5)—</text><clause id="H2A2277C6F0D94D6BB92A11B30BD3CF54"><enum>(i)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by striking <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon at the end;</text></clause><clause id="HAC476AECD11A46B080437B42C721D35E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating subparagraphs (B) and (C) as subparagraphs (C) and (D), respectively;</text></clause><clause id="HBBA06E739208419581D6001F5D390007"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting after subparagraph (A) the following new subparagraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6E4A0E09A6634EA6A0CA3555C68A38E6" style="OLC"><subparagraph commented="no" id="HB47341C7F5E74F60A93A1F7064F19985" indent="up1"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">sharing mitigation protocols to counter cybersecurity vulnerabilities pursuant to subsection (n); and</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause><clause commented="no" id="HC7892CA16D834E3CAD9112A4FE063034"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (C), as so redesignated, by inserting <quote>and mitigation protocols to counter cybersecurity vulnerabilities in accordance with subparagraph (B)</quote> before <quote>with Federal</quote>; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H330CE682D0B0433AA02AA42933572805"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (9), by inserting <quote>mitigation protocols to counter cybersecurity vulnerabilities,</quote> after <quote>measures,</quote>;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC76B8BD88FDA4CD0A19C4C0059CA26D7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by redesignating the second subsections (p) and (q) (relating to coordination on cybersecurity for SLITT entities and a report, respectively) as subsections (r) and (s), respectively; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBC3F2F98954B495BA18516351347CE51"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subsection:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43AD8B2842354C9EB5A839E6799CEA16" style="OLC"><subsection id="HD93568FC9C67440F84A4F4FF3F33A998"><enum>(t)</enum><header>Protocols To counter certain cybersecurity vulnerabilities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director may, as appropriate, identify, develop, and disseminate actionable protocols to mitigate cybersecurity vulnerabilities to information systems and industrial control systems, including in circumstances in which such vulnerabilities exist because software or hardware is no longer supported by a vendor.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="HB6B37972E9E94D3681F9F9B3A3E8C2F6"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on cybersecurity vulnerabilities</header><subsection id="HD83C7262480A4EFAA2579CA151EA9BFD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency of the Department of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate a report on how the Agency carries out subsection (n) of section 2209 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to coordinate vulnerability disclosures, including disclosures of cybersecurity vulnerabilities (as such term is defined in such section), and subsection (t) of such section (as added by section 2) to disseminate actionable protocols to mitigate cybersecurity vulnerabilities to information systems and industrial control systems, that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="H9BCEA0908F7E4E42A5F65DC347DF2172"><enum>(1)</enum><text>A description of the policies and procedures relating to the coordination of vulnerability disclosures.</text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" id="H6EAE0FD3E92C4473867787DB4A452FF4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A description of the levels of activity in furtherance of such subsections (n) and (t) of such section 2209.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E959AAA60514007B485CB2EEF9B4E13"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any plans to make further improvements to how information provided pursuant to such subsections can be shared (as such term is defined in such section 2209) between the Department and industry and other stakeholders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5AE827FA349F4F1C9EBD4F19E79B54BC"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any available information on the degree to which such information was acted upon by industry and other stakeholders.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H477C09ADC7E544259E9BE1A1D3BB7D6B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>A description of how privacy and civil liberties are preserved in the collection, retention, use, and sharing of vulnerability disclosures.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H436E906757A64E58BDCD3E55DBE8CBA8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report required under subsection (b) shall be submitted in unclassified form but may contain a classified annex.</text></subsection></section><section id="H02A1EE83F52245D0B1A04ADC69281B63"><enum>4.</enum><header>Competition relating to cybersecurity vulnerabilities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Under Secretary for Science and Technology of the Department of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency of the Department, may establish an incentive-based program that allows industry, individuals, academia, and others to compete in identifying remediation solutions for cybersecurity vulnerabilities (as such term is defined in section 2209 of the Homeland Security Act of 2002, as amended by section 2) to information systems (as such term is defined in such section 2209) and industrial control systems, including supervisory control and data acquisition systems.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

