<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H435BB2E7F1EC4C64A7278D752B96119B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4770 IH: Chesapeake Bay Science, Education, and Ecosystem Enhancement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4770</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230720">July 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001168">Mr. Sarbanes</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S000185">Mr. Scott of Virginia</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000804">Mr. Wittman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="K000399">Mrs. Kiggans of Virginia</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To reauthorize the Chesapeake Bay Office of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC0B0EEAB10B140FFA33860C4E914CEFE" style="OLC"><section id="HCE2B775630F840C8B0B47EE33277A250" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short Title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Chesapeake Bay Science, Education, and Ecosystem Enhancement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2731661D74D54AC79F5EF12ABB60647F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration’s Chesapeake Bay Office should be the primary representative of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in the Chesapeake Bay watershed.</text></section><section id="HF13E093429E447E7B1A1B77BA1CCBBEC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Reauthorization of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Chesapeake Bay Office</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 307 of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Authorization Act of 1992 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/1511d">15 U.S.C. 1511d</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="H8E50B230B7CE4BE6B011B83D1894F160"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text><subparagraph id="HB7B5B28F234248CBA2497F36D24E2D36"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1) by striking <quote>(in this section</quote> and all that follows and inserting a period;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFDEB40D1C2974CC1AE58D4CCF9832851"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending paragraph (2) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H2A253D61AD63473CA100A7CE5C1D0DD2" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HF352CE30B85741789F137E6249CADBCC" indent="up1"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Office shall be headed by a Director, who—</text><subparagraph id="HAB352ABD99AA43A0B6D4CA15C4B138E8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>shall have knowledge and experience in research or resource management efforts in the Chesapeake Bay; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H18FF0F4723AD4BC2BC16640728B85425"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall be responsible for the administration and operation of the office and the implementation of this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7315AB396448428F811057CC56500805"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by striking paragraph (3);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A9429ECF782473994BE50C225647296"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (b)—</text><subparagraph id="HC2BAEDD22D614A639F4D7BF3FE452597"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (2), by striking <quote>Secretary of Commerce</quote> and inserting <quote>Administrator</quote>;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BC534A33D034A72A3CDF8D57C699067"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3)—</text><clause id="HA7F0D3F9BFDA44E4A3AC28A36E6163E5"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by inserting <quote>with and represent</quote> after <quote>coordinate</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H7F3B3208D8884914A1788217CD33332C"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by striking <quote>, the Chesapeake Bay Regional Sea Grant Programs, and the Chesapeake Bay units of the National Estuarine Research Reserve System,</quote> and inserting <quote>for the Chesapeake Bay Program and that relate to the Chesapeake Bay watershed in furtherance of such Administration’s coastal resource stewardship mission,</quote>;</text></clause><clause id="H464BB7C6DA0B4269941E5FA2C4A838C4"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A)—</text><subclause id="H095DA5BFEEF742308E07B723E80A97CE" commented="no"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clauses (vi) and (vii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H017BA523FBBA4CADAF4CDF3AD00F654B"><enum>(II)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1B74AA9544A8413B8850D2A877419943" style="OLC"><clause id="HA50F8A0433A74F30B5267C60A927A9FF" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coastal hazards and climate change; and</text></clause><clause id="H53C2A81240584BC88B2B6233D7500061"><enum>(ix)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">education; and</text></clause><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause><clause id="H90B7E692AFDB4341AB0C5DF9DFF75A28"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subclause id="H1EEA007DEA674ABD8B981E5DA3A2C91B"><enum>(I)</enum><text>in clause (iii), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subclause><subclause id="HD40021C396F84E32AFC9FBDC97853640"><enum>(II)</enum><text>in clause (iv), by inserting <quote>and</quote> after the semicolon; and</text></subclause><subclause id="HED8D6BD6C8E14C579ACB4A30CE79769E"><enum>(III)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B9D5C285C0C47479B1BBB96138809D0" style="OLC"><clause id="HBB24CC35CA454D76A2812BFC64136D71"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">integrated ecosystem assessments;</text></clause><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1D3385832D8A4C2EBE45CA428EFEB5D0"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in paragraph (4)—</text><clause id="HCFE50B6F5F244E11A60A5AB038970648"><enum>(i)</enum><text>by striking <quote>Environmental Protection Agency</quote> and inserting <quote>Chesapeake Executive Council</quote>; and</text></clause><clause id="H7B17D68912B3438D92B0F9A580325565"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by inserting before the semicolon at the end the following: <quote>as appropriate to further the purposes of this section</quote>;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H2A91C9704A154D8A87865EE1995CC6A5"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by striking paragraphs (5) and (7);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB83497675DB84A51B7A224AAA8B75EF4"><enum>(E)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (6) as paragraph (5); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6611284486A543E6BA5D048E0DFD9D55"><enum>(F)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBFED43A39FE04AD6BE617110A0D94EE2" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H20138D65081644E8B792E780561DC596"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">perform any functions necessary to support the programs referred to in paragraph (3).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB440F61A46E04F7AB9E512C594BFC9AC"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by striking subsections (c), (d), and (e); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1DE2DB21B7C54D798AEB943A2399656B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H21249B2A2AF04266B3F4979554CC2A0A" style="OLC"><subsection id="H7B05D4A5C93A401AA6BF49280174C6DE"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Program Activities</header><paragraph id="H8431B6199B894B44B3628615B61B11C2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, through the Director, shall implement the program activities authorized by this section to support the activity of the Chesapeake Executive Council and to further the purposes of this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7A475500C7CE43B7BEC33DA3B0B76624"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Ensuring scientific and technical merit</header><text>The Director shall—</text><subparagraph id="HCB4AD9A13991423A8DEC50DA8281D5ED"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish and use an effective and transparent mechanism to ensure that projects funded under this section have undergone appropriate peer review; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC4B35C2ACE3E4849A01754C3CD699AB7"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide other appropriate means to determine that such projects have acceptable scientific and technical merit for the purpose of achieving maximum use of available funds and resources to benefit the Chesapeake Bay area.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H13BD9F29506D41719E5094509F9285AC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Consultation with Chesapeake Executive Council</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director shall, in the implementation of the program activities authorized under this section, consult with the Chesapeake Executive Council, to ensure that the activities of the Office are consistent with the purposes and priorities of the Chesapeake Bay Agreement and plans developed pursuant to the such agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA90777438C43469DB1A3F99AA0112FC6"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Integrated coastal observations</header><subparagraph id="H3FE94D99602B4EAB84877427D35EF215"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, through the Director, may collaborate with scientific and academic institutions, State and Federal agencies, non-governmental organizations, and other constituents in the Chesapeake Bay watershed, to support an integrated observations system for the Chesapeake Bay consistent with the purposes of the Integrated Coastal and Ocean Observation System Act of 2009 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/3601">33 U.S.C. 3601 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9EB0D0DD2528430B99C87D1FCA02D9CE"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Specific requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To support the system referred to in subparagraph (A) and provide a complete set of environmental information for the Chesapeake Bay, the Director shall—</text><clause id="H198EEAB1807D4DE2B43289C7BEDA7424"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">coordinate monitoring with Federal and State agencies in the tidal portions of the Chesapeake Bay to understand impacts of water quality on living marine resources;</text></clause><clause id="H1A19FAB692D54CF0B50C2108C601DB64"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify new data collection needs and deploy new technologies, as appropriate;</text></clause><clause id="H0ECB6EDA92854181B290E5211F069A6B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">collect and analyze the scientific information necessary for the management of living marine resources and the marine habitat associated with such resources; and</text></clause><clause id="H60184195DC044C5FB9DF5D4E71B0CFD9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">organize the information described in clause (iii) into products that are useful to policy makers, resource managers, scientists, and the public.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4888E84C6EA146E0BDB44FED9F1E5562"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Chesapeake Bay Interpretive Buoy System</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To further the development and implementation of the Chesapeake Bay Interpretive Buoy System and associated monitoring assets to improve weather and ecological forecasts, monitor habitat conditions for living marine resources, the Director may—</text><clause id="H445B2F8484244DD888D9D0FFA11861F4"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">support the establishment and implementation of the Captain John Smith Chesapeake National Historic Trail;</text></clause><clause id="HEAFF8437524A416CA8F57EF73F8405ED"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">delineate key waypoints along the trail and provide appropriate real-time data and information for trail users;</text></clause><clause id="HEC6F459CF9734715AD1CDA78B41D45AB"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">interpret data and information for use by educators and students to inspire stewardship of Chesapeake Bay; and</text></clause><clause id="H1AE2F6BE0B7B45A287588EAD18229D58"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">incorporate the observational data from the Chesapeake Bay Interpretive Buoy System into the Integrated Ocean Observing System regional observing system network.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4D5E2C5A5EA94A3F83A8545A06E4C96E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Chesapeake Bay Watershed Education and Training Program</header><subparagraph id="H26891EB63DA4497692512F8CDCC1E5E8"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, through the Director, may establish a Chesapeake Bay watershed education and training program. The program shall—</text><clause id="H7B57ED3F6A4242B890FD9CCA94484D7D"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">continue and expand the Chesapeake Bay watershed education programs offered by the Office immediately before the enactment of the Chesapeake Bay Science, Education, and Ecosystem Enhancement Act of 2023;</text></clause><clause id="H104CC26504AE40A886201D2C7E2BC006"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">improve the understanding of elementary and secondary school students and teachers of the living resources of the ecosystem of the Chesapeake Bay;</text></clause><clause id="HBE798483E9A044549C87BA8E7394A6B0"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide education and career pathway internships; and</text></clause><clause id="H20FDD9D41DF443E98853FD07741A29E9"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">meet the educational goals of the Chesapeake Bay Watershed Agreement.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H087B2350006243F88F2C9B0FF4D74669"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Grant program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Director may award grants for the purposes of this paragraph. Grants awarded under this subparagraph may be used to support education and training projects that enhance understanding and assessment of a specific environmental problem in the Chesapeake Bay watershed or a goal of the Chesapeake Bay Program, or protect or restore living resources of the Chesapeake Bay watershed, including projects that—</text><clause id="H0CA0C83E8A6A4F6B998D57332A77F46A"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide classroom education, including the development and use of distance learning and other innovative technologies, related to the Chesapeake Bay watershed;</text></clause><clause id="HE263DE782F5442329E677EE71217D651"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide meaningful watershed educational experiences in the Chesapeake Bay watershed;</text></clause><clause id="H3BE26504FBEB4A0BAA509FB78F941CF2"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">provide professional development for teachers related to the Chesapeake Bay watershed and the dissemination of pertinent education materials oriented to varying grade levels;</text></clause><clause id="HDC3340CF379C403FA5EA9D8575626675"><enum>(iv)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrate or disseminate environmental educational tools and materials related to the Chesapeake Bay watershed;</text></clause><clause id="HAFF709394FF840C796AC7D9F4A93AE6D"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">demonstrate field methods, practices, and techniques including assessment of environmental and ecological conditions and analysis of environmental problems; and</text></clause><clause id="H8C245CC7207D4E98A13F602E6F207B81"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">build the capacity of school districts and their partners to deliver high quality environmental education programs.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3C7EEF696CA34C2EB355F72F7F692116"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Coordination</header><text>The Director shall implement the education and training program in coordination with the heads of other Federal agencies, as the Director determines appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC7FB0FC1C62147689BB6A4CD6393F77A"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Coastal and Living Resources Management and Habitat Program</header><subparagraph id="H4021C795BC1A4778AB08DE5B77CD0FDD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, through the Director, may establish a Chesapeake Bay Coastal Living Resources Management and Habitat Program to support coordinated management, protection, characterization, and restoration of priority Chesapeake Bay habitats and living resources, including oysters, blue crabs, submerged aquatic vegetation, and economically and ecologically important fish species such as striped bass and menhaden. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E1C47A5D0574F1EA2036D9CFC42B082"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Under the Chesapeake Bay Coastal Living Resources Management and Habitat Program, the Director may carry out or enter into grants, contracts, and cooperative agreements and provide technical assistance to support—</text><clause id="H15806487A5DB49739D19ECA0298D23E9"><enum>(i)</enum><text>native oyster research and restoration;</text></clause><clause id="H17C5C86F95DE4D38A8437953CBBAF7AE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>fish and shellfish aquaculture that is carried out in accordance with a valid Federal or State permit;</text></clause><clause id="HAE4515A3F34E4E99842100D14D66C77B"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>establishment of submerged aquatic vegetation restoration programs;</text></clause><clause id="HEFFA6FB4A8AB42DCA75CB01628DC9731"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>the development of programs that restore, protect, and build the resilience of critical coastal habitats and communities;</text></clause><clause id="HB8950BF48B66445C9C1BBEC5845B41F6"><enum>(v)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">habitat mapping, characterization, and assessment techniques necessary to identify, assess, and monitor Chesapeake Bay conditions and restoration actions;</text></clause><clause id="HF5FCEEA2C33545A2AA37FCBCD96A6341"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>application and transfer of applied scientific research and ecosystem management tools to fisheries and habitat managers;</text></clause><clause id="HF7FFB1469FB941B79C62E00DBAEF67E3"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>collection, synthesis, and sharing of information to inform and influence coastal and living resource management issues;</text></clause><clause id="H730FFA92A4A943C1B1B026C16987FC98"><enum>(viii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">ecologically and economically important fish and shellfish research; and</text></clause><clause id="H579CE9EF50B24C8E92B3B0BCF82E2B84"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>other activities that the director determines are appropriate to carry out the purposes of such program.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H566B152A272E4824B9EDB0E0EC6B1FEC"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Delegation</header><paragraph id="H9DBE295CF77A44DEB956CED370182A93"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Authority</header><text>The Administrator shall delegate to the Director such authority as may be necessary to carry out this section.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCB7A148370F74CEF8E67F59B337FB290"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Staff</header><text>The Administrator shall delegate to the Director appropriate staff representing expertise that covers the breadth of the duties of the Office.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H9ECC32EE81E54E31BC8438028DA15937"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Reports</header><paragraph id="H68ECC65DB26B4741835926AA6C48A05E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, through the Director, shall submit a biennial report to the Congress and the Secretary of Commerce on the activities of the Office and on progress made in protecting and restoring the living resources and habitat of the Chesapeake Bay.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9739721C3434489686C4D86126F1DD78"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Action plan</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each such report shall include an action plan for the 2-year period following submission of the report, consisting of—</text><subparagraph id="H287E61618087493F826C50C0902B423F"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a list of recommended research, monitoring, and data collection activities necessary to continue implementation of the strategy under subsection (b)(2); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDED9901956DB48A494F13CE4C582F47B"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommendations to integrate National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration activities with the activities of the partners in the Chesapeake Bay Program to meet the commitments of the Chesapeake Bay Agreement and subsequent agreements.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3AA655DD58FF418BAE12E1AA14A592CE"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Agreements</header><paragraph commented="no" id="H6FDB2DC22D5F4668AEF625EDA006DF32"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, through the Director, may enter into and perform such contracts, leases, grants, or cooperative agreements as may be necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B9791D50E16452BA282B8697E968006"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Use of other resources</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For purposes related to the understanding, protection, and restoration of Chesapeake Bay, the Director may use, with consent and with or without reimbursement, the land, services, equipment, personnel, and facilities of any Department, agency, or instrumentality of the United States, or of any State, local government, Indian Tribe, or of any political subdivision thereof.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1940F376FBB3411993C20A37E5BD4489"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section, the following definitions apply:</text><paragraph id="HFFCF713F77154257A3CA9CAD5A724680"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H139C5531F84D46F6957BE7DBAD8D31D4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Chesapeake bay agreement; Chesapeake bay ecosystem; Chesapeake bay program; Chesapeake executive council</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>Chesapeake Bay Agreement</term>, <term>Chesapeake Bay ecosystem</term>, <term>Chesapeake Bay Program</term>, and <term>Chesapeake Executive Council</term> have the meanings given those terms in section 117(a) of the Federal Water Pollution Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/33/1267">33 U.S.C. 1267(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6526C11249284733A33EE64130E7F0CF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Director</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Director</term> means the Director of the Office.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H09C557DE03AC40F3BE9194377ECCF98B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Office</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Office</term> means the Chesapeake Bay Office established under this section.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4106643D6F1A454BA08BA1F0279D1D03"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text>There is authorized to be appropriated to the Secretary to carry out this section—</text><paragraph id="HDB462BFF3A1241C1B380397E67F8265A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$17,000,000 for fiscal year 2024;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEAF9AF4ADE7740B5ACBDFFCC20F925C0"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$18,700,000 for fiscal year 2025;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H61E1A6C600FF47CDB8AB6D77F38B517F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$20,570,000 for fiscal year 2026; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B7D6B3ADFD14B9EB47B2E9BC4CDDA66"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">$22,627,000 for fiscal year 2027.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

