<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H1752071C1A50461FBBF283784FF990CB" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6033 IH: Supporting Patient Education And Knowledge Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6033</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231024">October 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001135">Mrs. Steel</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="G000585">Mr. Gomez</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001133">Mr. Ciscomani</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="E000297">Mr. Espaillat</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001097">Mr. Cárdenas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000594">Ms. De La Cruz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="K000397">Mrs. Kim of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001080">Ms. Chu</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000613">Mr. Panetta</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000129">Mr. Valadao</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="V000130">Mr. Vargas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001112">Mr. Carbajal</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000590">Ms. Lee of Nevada</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001185">Ms. Sewell</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to establish a task force to improve access to health care information technology for non-English speakers.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H4997609912C24477BF375F67C71AF6AE" style="OLC"><section id="H932E1721B7B24AC59F5C900E9EBCFA8E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting Patient Education And Knowledge Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SPEAK Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H35CA1FF775224DFAB1BC12090BDCDE4F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="H2857D78444154DAC9BB0498B9EA25A0B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Telehealth has become a critical source of health care for patients.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3EC99C9C9F2D4B6FA6D27D014A3080B0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Patients with limited English proficiency have lower telehealth use rates than proficient English speakers.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD54112F11B0A4913AD6B430E96AEBF78"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Patients with limited English proficiency are less likely to utilize video telehealth options for primary care visits.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB73181CECE2747FE9926EA1036A2905D"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Physicians providing telehealth services for people with limited English proficiency would benefit from additional resources and support. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEEFFE2DC2907467EAF8A3EBAC7CE6049"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Access to telehealth saves patients money through reduced travel costs, as well as time-related tradeoffs.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HB7246BF303D94FAA99EBB6AD04635263"><enum>3.</enum><header>Improved access to health care information technology for non-English speakers task force</header><subsection id="H4FC13228AEF74EE48015BBA035DE19A1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Within 180 days of the passage of this legislation, the Secretary of Health and Human Services (in this section referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall convene a task force known as the <quote>Improved Access to Health Care Information Technology for non-English Speakers Task Force</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Task Force</quote>) to—</text><paragraph id="H73ED78805D7D40298010B19614C5581B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>assess current barriers to health information technology services, including telehealth platforms and patient portals, for people with limited English proficiency; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H70B34F6706444C6684BF4F80E41ED891"><enum>(2)</enum><text>develop recommendations and best practices for addressing identified barriers including—</text><subparagraph id="H4569EE8DFD734A7787E296B65B4E03F6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how health information technology platforms can be designed to maximize access for people with limited English proficiency, including those with additional barriers such as living in rural locations or with communications-related disabilities;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H04A39134D04C4DC084179D6A94F8938E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>how health information technology platforms and language service providers, including providers of remote video interpretation, can improve integration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7A1EF08683F34DB19EE0F54072846D0F"><enum>(C)</enum><text>how health care providers can best facilitate access to health information technology for their patients with limited English proficiency.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H81F8DF78E44140099DB11F5CD0BDE0F5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Task Force shall be composed of representatives of—</text><paragraph id="H0D3F45AFD5D54C7B9110325105C0BB16"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBF8683297B07453E8B5962CDBA896BF3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD76D97AF6E0A479BA9D2CE47692A18DA"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the Health Resources and Services Administration;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H15D87EF307D54403B1A3D6501FED82DD"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Office of Minority Health;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H299BBE86917948A5A879D6D76FF4ED17"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the Office for Civil Rights;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC8E8B80B11B84B99AB36BD2C8EF83134"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">health information technology service providers, including electronic medical record, remote patient monitoring and tele- and mobile-health vendors and companies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H04C83B84B65B40A5B94304EEE27B8CAC"><enum>(7)</enum><text>health care providers, including practicing physicians, and hospitals;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8F5FAED17AD4AA1B12C522C0B189E67"><enum>(8)</enum><text>health care insurance companies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H22F27C4FC1D342C29474E19E908D2965"><enum>(9)</enum><text>language service companies;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1BD08BC2728247668A650351C7B79860"><enum>(10)</enum><text>interpreter and translator professional associations;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D7105869BDE44229B0FB27FED3BD896"><enum>(11)</enum><text>health and language services quality certification organizations; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H75F69B66F3FB46E29D9EC2CA4C445382"><enum>(12)</enum><text>patient and consumer advocates, including but not limited to those working directly with limited English-proficient populations; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3ED287D5413C4D92A410D299F84BF847"><enum>(13)</enum><text>any other entity determined necessary by the Secretary.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFDB759E93611440893685CFCE2F7E563"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Request for information</header><paragraph id="H69D80FFE3B874DC1879D1CFACBB5F5E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall issue a request for information for health care providers, insurance plans, consumer organizations, language service providers, interpreters and other relevant parties on barriers to providing telehealth services to people with limited English proficiency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC4E29A61E6114F24A50C7FBAB1BCEC15"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Summary of responses</header><text>The Secretary shall compile and summarize the responses to the request for information for the Task Force which shall utilize them in completing its duties under section (a).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF8F504F1B7044BE2850C9E0F80FEB7D4"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Submission to Congress</header><paragraph id="H61E95D41C69B41A2AD38B38F2108BE4E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Interim report</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of enactment of this section, the Task Force shall submit to Congress a report on the progress of the Task Force in carrying out subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5B3A775E2A0C4DDBB87922D182B6F004"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Final report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this section, and annually thereafter, the Task Force shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the activities of the Task Force in carrying out subsection (a), including—</text><subparagraph id="HE4511C45C04E41A1B3A055F484AE17CA"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the results of the assessment under subsection (a)(1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDF5DC0D9BFD64618AFC0BDE4A5546C5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text>any recommendations and best practices developed under subsection (a)(2).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H42ED1774974640BFB0B8798F493EE5FF"><enum>4.</enum><header>Best practices publication</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No later than 90 days after completion of each report described in section 2(d), the Secretary of Health and Human Services shall publish, publicize, and maintain a website for the purposes of informing health care and technology providers about best practices for connecting people with limited English proficiency to health care information technology services. The website shall provide guidance and resources, identifying best practices in—</text><paragraph id="HD55AB45608FA45F5BC62E60188E134AE"><enum>(1)</enum><text>facilitating and integrating use of interpreters during telehealth sessions;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEA0D67D998E4E8A97D7E2CF3715970C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>providing accessible instructions on how to access telehealth platforms for people with limited English proficiency;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HADBA33A60DB94C3A8D012E8B828BCCA3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>improving access to digital patient portals; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB2B64B8A5CB4431F9387752CAF417B56"><enum>(4)</enum><text>other topics need appropriate by the Secretary, as advised by the Task Force established under section 3.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

