<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD786FF02A25C490E92B5453B08677482" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 551 IH: No Taxpayer Funding for the Chinese Communist Party Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 551</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230126">January 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000595">Mr. Good of Virginia</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000795">Mr. Wilson of South Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000615">Mr. Duncan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001211">Mrs. Miller of Illinois</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001302">Mr. Biggs</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Attorney General to report to Congress on how United States taxpayer-funded research has benefitted China, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HEFF7E05642FB4F1BAD93C424C7EFD98A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H363392255DEB406B95353AF1847CD868" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>No Taxpayer Funding for the Chinese Communist Party Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H8D94B7FD9B044C75A665A06AA45DD389"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following: </text> 
<paragraph id="HE1541083869A4DA88A0B14EA127BDD7D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>United States taxpayer-funded research should not be used to benefit the People’s Republic of China, especially as China undertakes the largest theft of intellectual property in history, as was stated by Secretary of Defense Mark Esper.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA1788CAAE97645F297780286DE5D0216"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">According to a Congressional Report, the Chinese Communist Party’s intellectual property theft costs the United States, and ultimately the American taxpayer, $225,000,000,000 to $600,000,000,000 worth of intellectual property every year. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H4C77548319CE4D48B1870491E959896C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>According to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate, there were more than 35,000 foreign nationals including 10,000 from China conducting research in the Department of Energy’s National Labs. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HCFBC44CBA1A84E2EA3D94CF7F13F1D76"><enum>(4)</enum><text>According to the Department of Education <quote>one university received research funding from a Chinese multinational conglomerate to develop new algorithms and advanced biometric security techniques for crowd surveillance capabilities,</quote> while another <quote>had multiple contracts with the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC8B10824E08C4C23B42D0C7361916671"><enum>(5)</enum><text>The Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs of the Senate found in a November 2019 report that <quote>American taxpayer funded research has contributed to China’s global rise over the last 20 years</quote>.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HBF00EBE3B2214FDE9E2E2A784D970D17"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Federal Bureau of Investigation has found that China’s government has used some students and professors in science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) fields as nontraditional collectors of intellectual property, but has also noted that <quote>the vast majority of the 1.4 million international scholars on U.S. campuses pose no threat to their host institutions, fellow classmates, or research fields. On the contrary, these international visitors represent valuable contributors to their campuses’ achievements, providing financial benefits, diversity of ideas, sought expertise, and opportunities for cross-cultural exchange</quote>.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H3A9EDC988F8949FDA772DB3D91DFF381"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In 2021, the Department of Justice announced that four Chinese nationals were charged with an operation to hack into the computers of dozens of companies, universities and government agencies in the United States and other countries between 2011 and 2018. </text></paragraph></section> <section id="H0541BE9B73734953828FF6E3A5B90497"><enum>3.</enum><header>Report on China benefitting from United States taxpayer-funded research</header> <subsection id="H8538B2C9F28C454E9D9CF0174D7F6276"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of enactment of the Act, the Attorney General, in consultation with the Secretary of the Treasury, the Secretary of Commerce, the Secretary of State, and the Director of National Intelligence, shall submit to the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate a report on the extent to which China has benefitted from United States taxpayer-funded research. </text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE37CF91E98C4493AA8084301B12F08DE"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Elements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The report under subsection (a) shall include the following:</text> <paragraph id="H4FE230D72B7A404D8724E699ACBA2105"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The extent to which United States taxpayer-funded research has benefitted China, including a list of United States Government-funded entities, such as research institutions, laboratories, and institutions of higher education, which have hired Chinese nationals or allowed Chinese nationals to conduct research, including an estimate in the number of nationals hired or involved in research projects. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5256F081A2474973BC2D039FDD51B838"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A list of United States Government programs, grants, and other forms of research funding in the fields of science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) fields that have directly or indirectly cooperated or affiliated with research institutions in China or Chinese Communist Party entities. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H25121166E9A44B72AB00D8E2C87E097C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The extent to which China’s funding of United States taxpayer-funded research institutions has benefitted China. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB00AEEC993954FDD87216F5109577A0C"><enum>(4)</enum><text>How the Government of China and the Chinese Communist Party have used United States taxpayer-funded research, including as part of China’s efforts to support <quote>civil-military fusion</quote> and human rights abuses.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H0483FAA3D11749D1B1B06F86851EECCD"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this Act, the term <term>United States taypayer-funded research</term> means research—</text> 
<paragraph id="H9E7137D745894F0EA7E36D50A0D7C132"><enum>(1)</enum><text>funded by a grant from the Federal Government or a State government; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7C87E37FA6FA457EAF5BAA26F90074D7"><enum>(2)</enum><text>conducted at an institution that receives funding from the Federal Government or a State government. </text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

