<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HEC8584907E1D45AAA7243753EB94CBC0" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5158 IH: Accountability for Endless Wars Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-08-04</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5158</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230804">August 4, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001150">Mr. Schiff</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="O000173">Ms. Omar</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To terminate authorizations for the use of military force and declarations of war not later than 10 years after the enactment of such authorizations or declarations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H383AC4E9B5E944308CBF25253A2A6F62" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H293BAD9ABD9D4CE3ABAAFE1F82670BF5"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Accountability for Endless Wars Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="HA07AEA4EC66A4865B6659EB9C73C19A5"><enum>2.</enum><header>Termination of authorizations for use of military force and declarations of war</header><subsection id="H26B65FE04FA4483AB42F9B99B125A251"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Future authorizations for use of military force and declarations of war</header><text>Any authorization for the use of military force or declaration of war enacted into law on or after the date of the enactment of this Act shall terminate on the date that is not later than 10 years after the date of the enactment of such authorization or declaration, as the case may be. </text></subsection><subsection id="HE8FE4EB88BC740ED88EA5D0E7958C80D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Existing authorizations for use of military force and declarations of war</header><text>Any authorization for the use of military force or declaration of war enacted into law before the date of the enactment of this Act and in effect as of such date of enactment shall terminate on the date that is 180 days after such date of enactment.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

