<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H093446329C904CCFAD62A0BE7DE487B8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4997 IH: Grizzly Bear Review and Resource Restart Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-07-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4997</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230727">July 27, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000469">Mr. Fulcher</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Committee on Natural Resources</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for determination of the grizzly bear species consistent with the Endangered Species Act of 1973, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H74B3C045E78C4EB59ECAFB1D748983A7" style="OLC"><section id="H2D8BB80D9A544100AE64BAC8F66094D9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Grizzly Bear Review and Resource Restart Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF5D0D4A0A8C942D59606CB0823E51B8F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds that—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H5333ED7730854442A9BDA94AE8DAABE5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the entity of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) in the conterminous lower 48 States of the United States, included on the List of Endangered and Threatened Wildlife under section 17.11(h) of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation), is not a species (as defined in section 3 of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1532">16 U.S.C. 1532</external-xref>)), a threatened species (as defined in that section), an endangered species (as defined in that section), a taxonomic species, a taxonomic subspecies, or a distinct population segment that interbreeds when mature, and should not be subject to the protections of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2165BCD7EBA243F193F2212093745DE0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>removal of protections for the entity of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) in the conterminous lower 48 States of the United States under the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>), when those protections are inconsistent with that Act or otherwise unnecessary, supports prioritization of Federal conservation actions and resources for species in much greater need of protections under that Act; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD9CB99EB3E5F488ABE9E581EB613719C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>continuing protections under the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>) for the entity of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) in the conterminous lower 48 States of the United States to not later than the date that is 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act provides adequate time for the Secretary of the Interior (referred to in this Act as the <term>Secretary</term>) to determine, by regulation promulgated in accordance with section 4(a) of that Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1533">16 U.S.C. 1533(a)</external-xref>), whether any distinct population segment of grizzly bear that interbreeds when mature is an endangered species or a threatened species that should be added to the List of Endangered and Threatened Wildlife pursuant to that Act.</text></paragraph></section><section commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H801F98C7AA654372A1E5F76FF5EA0EB4"><enum>3.</enum><header>Determination of grizzly bear species under the Endangered Species Act of 1973</header><subsection id="HD91E3CBEE2E84F60A80B858DD57A6CFB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall remove the entity of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) in the conterminous lower 48 States of the United States and the associated entity of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) in portions of the States of Idaho and Montana listed as an experimental population from the List of Endangered and Threatened Wildlife under section 17.11(h) of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation).</text></subsection><subsection id="H9AA99A8C4AAB4551A3DF0A1645348661"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Effect on other determinations</header><text>Nothing in this Act limits the ability of the Secretary to make future determinations of threatened species or endangered species, by regulation promulgated in accordance with section 4(a) of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1533">16 U.S.C. 1533(a)</external-xref>), for any distinct population segment of brown bear (Ursus arctos) that interbreeds when mature, including any distinct population segment of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) or other brown bear subspecies, subject to the conditions that the Secretary shall not—</text><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HBE4AE88E082D4D5FAFB43C679F04B65A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">add any distinct population segment of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) to the List of Endangered and Threatened Wildlife under section 17.11(h) of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation), unless the Secretary identifies objective, measurable criteria that, when met, would result in a determination that the distinct population segment be removed from the list; and </text></paragraph><paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H7DDDC1A554DD451AA0A7910E49F5C75B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">be required to designate critical habitat for a distinct population segment of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) described in paragraph (1).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H2F9A29B712CD4CF69B4DBEE2F9CA604D"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Delisting process for distinct population segments</header><text>If the Secretary identifies a distinct population segment of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) in the conterminous lower 48 States of the United States that has met the established recovery criteria for that distinct population segment, the Secretary shall initiate the process to remove that distinct population segment from the List of Endangered and Threatened Wildlife under section 17.11(h) of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation). </text></subsection><subsection id="H6A7A1B5FF47143E88F7C2B267F7F8192"><enum>(d)</enum><header>No judicial review</header><text>The removal of the entity of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) in the conterminous lower 48 States of the United States and the associated entity of grizzly bear (Ursus arctos horribilis) in portions of the States of Idaho and Montana listed as an experimental population from the List of Endangered and Threatened Wildlife under section 17.11(h) of title 50, Code of Federal Regulations (or a successor regulation), pursuant to subsection (a) shall not be subject to judicial review.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

