<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H85C6BF9F2AF746B89BC146A35D58F2F5" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5392 IH: Timely Access to Coverage Decisions Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5392</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230912">September 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000628">Mr. Dunn of Florida</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="T000478">Ms. Tenney</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title XVIII of the Social Security Act to ensure timely review of local coverage determination requests under the Medicare program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDDF4FAD93E644D568C4987DFCCA043EB" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H3CE5D95C8FB24A1183F54F388692AEF6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Timely Access to Coverage Decisions Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text> </section> <section id="H9AF20AEA04634B699B61292277267D92" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Ensuring timely review of local coverage determination requests under the Medicare program</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1862(l)(5) of the Social Security Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/1395y">42 U.S.C. 1395y(l)(5)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text> 
<quoted-block style="OLC" id="H98FB22B6EB7F4B82AB274C3A23E4E7A1" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<subparagraph id="H39562536A2B34819ACBBAAA10E505FD3"><enum>(E)</enum><header>Timeframe for decisions on requests for local coverage determinations</header> 
<clause id="H7CB681ADA39D42F0B0265D975347FF68"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall require each Medicare administrative contractor that receives a document that identifies itself as a request for a local coverage determination on or after the date that is 90 days after the date of the enactment of this subparagraph to determine whether such request is a complete request or an incomplete request not later than 30 days after such contractor receives such document.</text></clause> <clause id="HFDA7761F352C48C59A5FA70CEDA22C94"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Notification with respect to incomplete requests</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case a Medicare administrative contractor makes a determination described in clause (i) with respect to a document so described that such document is an incomplete request for a local coverage determination, not later than 60 days after the date on which such contractor received such document, such contractor shall transmit to the entity that submitted such document a notification of such determination that includes a specification of each item of additional information needed to make such document a complete request for a local coverage determination.</text></clause> 
<clause id="HEEB9B6525B1F46F1B3F5431C32E18399"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Decision timeline for complete requests</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case a Medicare administrative contractor makes a determination described in clause (i) with respect to a document so described that such document is an complete request for a local coverage determination, not later than 9 months after the date on which such contractor received such document, such contractor shall—</text> <subclause id="H994407CDBA4F42B29C231F57B753836A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>complete any necessary research relating to such request;</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H9443DC87ADC44D8B848F2AB55A70FD46"><enum>(II)</enum><text>consult with outside experts on such request;</text></subclause> <subclause id="H3AC5B9BCE3F346C8886CF65052A45F78"><enum>(III)</enum><text>undertake a 45-day public comment period on such request; and</text></subclause> 
<subclause id="H48B1E6981A5A45ED8E4F4C9F9DF40D73"><enum>(IV)</enum><text>issue a decisions with respect to such request.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

