<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3B6EFA043A024BAF8B59BCEF0C4CF881" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5680 IH: American Volunteering Corporation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5680</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230922">September 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="K000394">Mr. Kim of New Jersey</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and the Workforce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To transfer the Peace Corps and the Corporation for National and Community Service under the umbrella of an American Volunteering Corporation, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HC9A6533DC7944116BF199DD5E2BF68C7" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HF4028B8FB1DB4FBBA4C2808A8DA72A95" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>American Volunteering Corporation Act</short-title></quote> . </text></section> <section id="H0999F794504543F7AE65D1B68BDB41B6"><enum>2.</enum><header>American Volunteering Corporation</header> <subsection id="HCDE3FA1409404D0BB8FA3948EB739FC7"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established as an independent agency within the executive branch of the Federal Government the American Volunteering Corporation, to coordinate and promote service at all levels across the country and internationally.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H1E7994098AB74B42B8EFC7669BE1652D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The American Volunteering Corporation shall be headed by an Administrator of the American Volunteering Corporation who shall be appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H91C0B45CCA03463496224DA889005488"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Director of the Peace Corps</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be a Director of the Peace Corps and a Deputy Director of the Peace Corps, who shall be appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate. The Director shall report directly to the Administrator appointed under subsection (b).</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HD7FA7808FC91465D8A18C3FE8AE933AD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>CEO of Corporation for National and Community Service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be a Chief Executive Officer for National and Community Service, who shall be appointed by the President, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate. The Chief Executive Officer shall report directly to the Administrator appointed under subsection (b). </text></subsection></section> <section id="HEAA8DBA62526418DA18F484A4C589BD3"><enum>3.</enum><header>Modifications to Peace Corps operations</header> <subsection id="H4987276FD75A4DD8A42C9FB87C6164D0"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header> <paragraph id="H51E03F616F7347DC8EC98D7FA8660733"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Director of the Peace Corps</header><text>The authorities, duties, and responsibilities of the Director of the Peace Corps appointed pursuant to section 4 of the Peace Corps Act, as of the day before the date of the enactment of this Act, are transferred as of such date of enactment to the Director of the Peace Corps established under <internal-xref idref="H91C0B45CCA03463496224DA889005488" legis-path="2.(c)">section 2(c)</internal-xref> of this Act.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE4BE23D794A94105856931F47507A71D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Peace Corps</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The assets, liabilities, and obligations of the Peace Corps, as of the day before the date of the enactment of this Act, are transferred as of such date to the American Volunteering Corporation established under <internal-xref idref="HCDE3FA1409404D0BB8FA3948EB739FC7" legis-path="2.(a)">section 2(a)</internal-xref> of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF12A1A72510E4362A14C36BD1B6B793F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>References</header><text>Any reference in law or regulation to the <quote>Director of the Peace Corps</quote>, on and after the date of the enactment of this Act, shall be treated as a reference to the Director of the Peace Corps established under <internal-xref idref="H91C0B45CCA03463496224DA889005488" legis-path="2.(c)">section 2(c)</internal-xref> of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H1DBE3051257248AEA98EEE3136EFBC9E"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Peace Corps Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2503">22 U.S.C. 2503</external-xref>) is amended in section 12(c)(3), by inserting <quote>the Administrator of the American Volunteering Corporation,</quote> after <quote>or their designees,</quote>.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HEEB1F7ABC1084B6A96EB22AA4FCD79B4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Modification to Americorps operations</header> <subsection id="H5BDDB4827FB542B88F51E6EF25829F22"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Corporation for National and Community Service</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authorities, duties, and responsibilities of the Corporation for National and Community Service under section 193A of the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12651d">42 U.S.C. 12651d</external-xref>), as of the day before the date of the enactment of this Act, are transferred as of such date of enactment to the Chief Executive Office for National and Community Service established under <internal-xref idref="HD7FA7808FC91465D8A18C3FE8AE933AD" legis-path="2.(d)">section 2(d)</internal-xref> of this Act.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HAB9CCB4CD70240C3BE8BCD44C3392271"><enum>(b)</enum><header>National service programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The assets, liabilities, and obligations of the national service programs under the National and Community Service Act of 1990 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/12501">42 U.S.C. 12501 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Domestic Volunteer Service Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4950">42 U.S.C. 4950 et seq.</external-xref>), as of the day before the date of the enactment of this Act, are transferred as of such date to the American Volunteering Corporation established under <internal-xref idref="HCDE3FA1409404D0BB8FA3948EB739FC7" legis-path="2.(a)">section 2(a)</internal-xref> of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HB41B7ACE082D492FBFC0F5BCD4725880"><enum>(c)</enum><header>References</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any reference in law or regulation to the <quote>Chief Executive Officer for National and Community Service</quote> shall be treated as a reference to the Chief Executive Officer for National and Community Service established under <internal-xref idref="HD7FA7808FC91465D8A18C3FE8AE933AD" legis-path="2.(d)">section 2(d)</internal-xref> of this Act.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

