<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H8F7C55CBDB814B8DB4553510830B7814" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3742 IH: To direct the Comptroller General of the United States to evaluate the Federal Government’s collection and sharing of public health data to respond to public health emergencies.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-26</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3742</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230526">May 26, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000608">Mr. Peters</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000558">Mr. Guthrie</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Comptroller General of the United States to evaluate the Federal Government&#8217;s collection and sharing of public health data to respond to public health emergencies.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0E3393015CF144D9B83C7B2EDB3ED06F" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H293679AC2B2A478283B3839B832D01BE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Study on Federal public health data collection and sharing</header> 
<subsection id="HCDB66A802BF24D9EAEC3F3E9410865C1"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall evaluate the Federal Government’s collection and sharing of public health data to respond to public health emergencies involving infectious disease outbreaks or biological threats, such as the COVID–19 pandemic, and provide as appropriate recommendations to address the collection and sharing of public health data.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H286601D99BE346D290385166172DE989"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Topics</header><text>The evaluation under subsection (a) shall include a review of what is known about—</text> 
<paragraph id="H588AE37BD0F347EA95BB5DFCF0ABD401"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the authorities, policies, and operational tools used by the Secretary of Health and Human Services to collect public health data from, and share public health data with, other Federal agencies, State, local, territorial, and Tribal governments, and other partners, including—</text> <subparagraph id="HCF929E74A01C48F491D9BE54B9354C1F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>how those authorities, policies, and tools were used during the COVID–19 public health emergency;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H15ECADCCD3BD4F8291C1319254FFC0F9"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">how Federal funds were expended for the purpose of public health data collection and sharing during the COVID–19 public health emergency;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H94217A60BBAC4CADBE1E1EDB4B77F171"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any challenges posed by redundant data reporting requirements placed on State, local, territorial, and Tribal governments and other partners during the COVID–19 public health emergency, including whether these requirements conflicted with the needs of State, local, territorial, or Tribal communities or other partners; and</text> </subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H35C48CD95DEB49A48597969EF99CC7D8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any publicly available resources to track how public health data is being collected, shared, and used with other Federal agencies, State, local, territorial, and Tribal governments, and other partners; </text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HA0AFAAB53AD9420FA215D02E2F89A1A6"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any limitations on the authorities, policies, and tools used during declared public health emergencies, including throughout the COVID–19 public health emergency, that affect the Federal Government’s ability to respond to declared public health emergencies;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HE6CFAEB86260453D85A3D559EA8ACFDC"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any redundancy or overutilization in the authorities, policies, and tools used during declared public health emergencies, including throughout the COVID–19 public health emergency, including whether any redundant data reporting requirements conflicted with the needs of State, local, territorial, or Tribal communities or other partners; and</text> </paragraph> <paragraph id="H4305B5AD7DB1491EB1EC4C35C5DE4A60"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the Federal Government’s data collection, sharing, and epidemiological modeling during the COVID–19 public health emergency compared with the data collection, sharing, and epidemiological modeling of nonprofit and private sector stakeholders, including how the Secretary developed tools, or used already existing tools, to collect, share, model, and disseminate public health data in comparison to the development of tools and use of existing tools for such purposes by the nonprofit and private sectors.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HEEF8727D5AB745C7B93E3C866B7FB42C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Report to Congress</header><text>Not later than 18 months after the date of enactment of this Act, the Comptroller General of the United States shall submit a report to the Congress on the results of the evaluation under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="H16BA46F544AF48408323B313BCC9F441"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <term>other partners</term> includes—</text>
<paragraph id="HADBAC87269D648538EDEF44A2C0BDE85"><enum>(1)</enum><text>hospitals and physician practices;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H1FBBAA06D3A84D8F8F32CEAA05A1ACE1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>health systems and health plans;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE5A7A348B8F145A398B20B118AB52231"><enum>(3)</enum><text>manufacturers and distributors; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF9D9DD64E0854792BC54D90EC2071323"><enum>(4)</enum><text>clinical laboratories.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>


