<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H0D08A37718664F7E8282721A462C6114" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>116 HR 5460 IH: Bolstering Security Against Ghost Guns Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5460</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230914">September 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000193">Mr. Thompson of Mississippi</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="J000032">Ms. Jackson Lee</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001067">Ms. Clarke of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000604">Mr. Payne</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000468">Ms. Titus</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001193">Mr. Swalwell</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000822">Mrs. Watson Coleman</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001110">Mr. Correa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001125">Mr. Carter of Louisiana</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000488">Mr. Thanedar</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M001223">Mr. Magaziner</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000058">Mr. Ivey</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000599">Mr. Goldman of New York</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000598">Mr. Robert Garcia of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000617">Mrs. Ramirez</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001226">Mr. Menendez</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Committee on Homeland Security</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Department of Homeland Security to bolster security against threats posed by ghost guns, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H9F1739FE6DFE4083AD0301A89B0BA7CB" style="OLC"><section id="H215E57385DAC4963B889F9A9F7B9A187" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Bolstering Security Against Ghost Guns Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H1CC2A88799674DA4B11B8D1DA793E51E"><enum>2.</enum><header>Department of Homeland Security policy to bolster security against threats posed by ghost guns</header><subsection id="H0B9D1FDFA30B40DFA92E505DE7B345AB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Homeland Security, acting through the Under Secretary for Strategy, Policy, and Plans of the Department of Homeland Security, shall issue a Department-wide strategy to bolster security against threats posed by ghost guns. Such strategy shall—</text><paragraph id="H05D504E0EF8F4625A9E25C61172D910B"><enum>(1)</enum><text>identify activities across the Department related to ghost guns and approaches to enhance cross-component information sharing and collaboration to improve prevention, preparedness, and response to homeland security threats, such as an act of terrorism or targeted violence, associated with ghost guns; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BC30BC8C09749108380EFBB835FA2B4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>identify activities with Federal, State, local, Tribal, and territorial partners related to ghost guns and approaches to enhance the Department’s collaboration with such partners to improve prevention, preparedness, and response to homeland security threats, such as an act of terrorism or targeted violence, associated with ghost guns.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H55660DE9E6164CCE99F160D8205DFFB0"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Office of Intelligence and Analysis activities</header><paragraph id="H5747C59185E34E31AD864FC20FFDCC39"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Use in terrorist activity</header><text>Section 5716 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2020 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/116/92">Public Law 116–92</external-xref>) is amended—</text><subparagraph id="H4EC25AE50C7F4CA4AF4B6AC294C8111D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by amending subsection (a) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3BA852BC9855446C8CDCAA63487DA7F2" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="HBE2A636C0CA24B04B98A88F1CAFD6A45"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Reports</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this subsection and annually thereafter, the Under Secretary for Intelligence and Analysis of the Department of Homeland Security, in consultation with the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, shall develop and submit to the entities in accordance with subsection (b) a report assessing homeland security threats of ghost guns and unfinished frames and receivers associated with a foreign terrorist organization or other individual in furtherance of an act of terrorism or targeted violence. Each report shall—</text><paragraph id="HDF374A5A5705403D9B37973F253FAFF5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">assess the range of sources for acquiring, manufacturing, and trafficking ghost guns and unfinished frames and receivers;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC845BE38F9A84CA88E683D978D4D18B3"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">identify each type of homeland security threat associated with ghost guns and unfinished frames and receivers; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7920BDFB035D45999EF8AA37D656F4DE"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">specify the level of threat associated with each threat identified pursuant to paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9F4DD307367A4C70A864D82AF6E72AE6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by amending subsection (c) to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HC208E0621F7B461696CE32889C19EFF9" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H07459593F54748A6BD1AEAD95689F008"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="H31DAB9195CC04534A62732692F7E6A19"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Act of terrorism</header><text>The term <quote>act of terrorism</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3077 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H34EDAD871B8A47AD869B6E3A193BF960"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H7DF5BEE9084B4953BB7F7F8560702168"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Homeland Security, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H691BF41930C04BB1BAB7AC1EB4CB5977"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Select Committee on Intelligence, the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs, and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H130C7422F2384438849C2CA5637CCFCD"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Domestic terrorism</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>domestic terrorism</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 2331 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F2ABDAB59CF498E9931E3F753153EB9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Foreign terrorist organization</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>foreign terrorist organization</quote> means an organization designated as a foreign terrorist organization under section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HCF207ECDFC354B4080F48AF9D956A16B"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Ghost gun</header><text>The term <quote>ghost gun</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="HAEBD74ECD4ED466781FEF81594BB3EE8" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means a firearm, including a frame or receiver, that is privately made or which lacks a unique serial number engraved or cast by a licensed gunsmith, manufacturer, or importer, or was removed, obliterated, or altered in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0322170F4ECB4000A123D918D3A9358A"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include—</text><clause id="H0229FDACE8384B90AC2BB92EAF5A69BB"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a firearm that has been rendered permanently inoperable;</text></clause><clause id="HDD545D8DAFD64D9C8D2753E4945CC274" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a firearm identified by means of a unique serial number assigned by a State agency and engraved or cast on the firearm before the effective date of this Act in accordance with a State law;</text></clause><clause id="H6C7BAF977904476CA27E38CEFFE64BDB" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a firearm manufactured or imported before December 16, 1968, or unless the Attorney General has provided otherwise by regulation with respect to the specific make and model of firearm on or before January 1, 2024; or</text></clause><clause id="H174DF49FDD404C4D817CF7F69C8A3CB2"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a firearm identified as provided for under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5842">section 5842</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H239A73788E2C4F9C86524E7FA6A9E68F"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Targeted violence</header><text>The term <quote>targeted violence</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 6418 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/124h-1">6 U.S.C. 124h–1</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H317A0F129CBE416191E821D97E3926BE" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Unfinished frame or receiver</header><text>The term <quote>unfinished frame or receiver</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HF315FDF44D604079BAE1C2F7B45A75BC" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a forged, cast, printed, extruded, or machined body or similar article that is designed to, or may readily be completed, assembled, or otherwise converted to, provide the housing or structure, without regard to whether such housing or structure has been indexed, drilled, or machined in any way, and without regard to whether such body or article is sold, distributed, or marketed with or for any associated template, jig, mold, equipment, tool, instructions, or guide; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD606F9B5693547B8B4611ABE4BBA5233" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an object that is marketed or sold to become or be used as the frame or receiver of a functional firearm once completed, assembled, or converted.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H92B4E056E65F420D95B3500C7B55EC1D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Cross-border threats</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary for Intelligence and Analysis of the Department of Homeland Security, in coordination with the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, the Director of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement, and the heads of other appropriate Federal partners, shall develop and disseminate a homeland security threat assessment regarding cross-border threats associated with United States-sourced ghost guns and unfinished frames and receivers, with special attention to ghost guns and unfinished frames and receivers used by transnational criminal organizations involved in illicit activity that pose a threat to the border.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE99DDF91E53742A1BAE91B994BD0AA6B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>United States Secret Service activities</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the United States Secret Service, acting through the Chief of the National Threat Assessment Center, in coordination with appropriate Federal partners, shall carry out research and issue public reports that provide guidance on how to prevent, prepare for, and respond to homeland security threats, such as an act of terrorism or targeted violence, associated with ghost guns.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA5119E15C9E14B44A5F6E19ABF279888"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Transportation Security Administration activities</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act and annually thereafter, the Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration shall report to the Committee on Homeland Security of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation of the Senate regarding the number of violations of subsection (a) of section 1540.111 of title 49, Code of Federal Regulations, and any other incidents involving the unauthorized carriage of a firearm at a passenger screening checkpoint, including information regarding which such violations and incidents during the period of time covered by each such report were committed by individuals while receiving expedited screening, which were repeat offenses, and which involved a ghost gun. Such reporting shall also include information regarding trends in the rates of violations and incidents on a per passenger basis, as well as a description of Transportation Security Administration efforts during the period of time covered by each such report to increase public awareness of the prohibition of unauthorized carriage of a firearm at a passenger screening checkpoint.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAFE71673A91B4F448A9EB1087607354C"><enum>(e)</enum><header>U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement, acting through the Executive Associate Director of Homeland Security Investigations, shall, in coordination with the Commissioner of U.S. Customs and Border Protection and appropriate Federal partners—</text><paragraph id="HFF125FE827374FE097C43E98F0375F97"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">prepare an analysis that includes data from Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives and other Federal partners regarding homeland security threats, including border security threats, and cross-border illicit smuggling trends and patterns associated with United States-sourced firearms, including ghost guns, recovered in Mexico;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2945B1C547A844DE986AD85CD1CAD322"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">research and develop a mechanism to share aggregated Federal information regarding United States-sourced firearms, including ghost guns, recovered in Mexico in support of carrying out subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H64683BC4DC354F558D52700CBE792D02"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">develop performance measures to assess the effectiveness of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement activities aimed at combatting homeland security threats, including border security threats, and illicit cross-border activities involving United States-sourced firearms, including ghost guns. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H08AA8C2CDEEC4483B782658610850633"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H5C9AE0FC37FB4C67ABFDD36C565A486E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Act of terrorism</header><text>The term <quote>act of terrorism</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 3077 of title 18, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H49F9C9A9B6054E9E8A9BD447EE74B9DB" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Fire control component</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>fire control component</quote> means a component necessary for a firearm to initiate or complete the firing sequence, including a hammer, bolt or breechblock, cylinder, trigger mechanism, firing pin, striker, and slide rails.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H044AA6ACAD2742E595B6B4019E9D8587"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Foreign terrorist organization</header><text>The term <quote>foreign terrorist organization</quote> means an organization designated as a foreign terrorist organization under section 219 of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1189">8 U.S.C. 1189</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D4757D6E41C4AEAA0B8E300259158CD"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Ghost gun</header><text>The term <quote>ghost gun</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="H48AB3C84113E4127A84CE827E63B8336" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">means a firearm, including a frame or receiver, that is privately made or which lacks a unique serial number engraved or cast by a licensed gunsmith, manufacturer, or importer, or was removed, obliterated, or altered in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/18/44">chapter 44</external-xref> of title 18, United States Code; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0E581569AE6C400185F404D55AB5BD99"><enum>(B)</enum><text>does not include—</text><clause id="H2ABE1BE227D54D569F6582BFD16C9A8D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a firearm that has been rendered permanently inoperable;</text></clause><clause id="H62F827FE0603436D92807CA20692704F" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a firearm identified by means of a unique serial number assigned by a State agency and engraved or cast on the firearm before the effective date of this Act in accordance with a State law;</text></clause><clause id="HAC193F7C39D844F08CC6B6B7D7E210AF" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>a firearm manufactured or imported before December 16, 1968, or unless the Attorney General has provided otherwise by regulation with respect to the specific make and model of firearm on or before January 1, 2024; or</text></clause><clause id="H46D6516C36374993AC75453FC215C893"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>a firearm identified as provided for under <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/26/5842">section 5842</external-xref> of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA201718EE13C46D3B3998E9F0A129E98"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Targeted violence</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>targeted violence</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 6418 of the National Defense Authorization Act for Fiscal Year 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/6/124h-1">6 U.S.C. 124h–1</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0D626EEA856740FBA4E3D9B298FB9856"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Unfinished frame or receiver</header><text>The term <quote>unfinished frame or receiver</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="HE811C5320A8345579407716EE6E1D160" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a forged, cast, printed, extruded, or machined body or similar article that is designed to, or may readily be completed, assembled, or otherwise converted to, provide the housing or structure, without regard to whether such housing or structure has been indexed, drilled, or machined in any way, and without regard to whether such body or article is sold, distributed, or marketed with or for any associated template, jig, mold, equipment, tool, instructions, or guide; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4012D39574684EFBA8929E71B013C5EA"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">an object that is marketed or sold to become or be used as the frame or receiver of a functional firearm once completed, assembled, or converted.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

