<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HFD9EE72120854D8FB6326440804D3EE4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1801 IH: Safeguarding Human Rights in Arms Exports Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-27</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1801</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230327">March 27, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001137">Mr. Meeks</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000826">Ms. Wild</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001209">Ms. Spanberger</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="J000305">Ms. Jacobs</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001091">Mr. Castro of Texas</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To enhance the consideration of human rights in arms exports.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H3EDF7934D48E498EAD7E87F58276117A" style="OLC">
<section section-type="section-one" id="HAD6DF2A636334089B0365A3AA393F042"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Safeguarding Human Rights in Arms Exports Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SAFEGUARD Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HF45169181D3C4F868AFA3A9837EA2C38"><enum>2.</enum><header>Statement of policy on control of defense exports and protection of human rights</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States that one of the purposes for controlling the export of defense articles and defense services to foreign countries is to prevent such exports from being used in violation of international humanitarian law or internationally recognized human rights, to require accountability for any such violations, and to ensure that the sale, export, or transfer of such articles and services serves to encourage governments of foreign countries to fully comply with international humanitarian law and observe internationally recognized human rights.</text></section>
<section id="HF850FFEF06F64FB09CE7E5DAE9FBD1BC"><enum>3.</enum><header>Prohibition of arms sales to countries committing genocide or war crimes</header>
<subsection id="HD224A839E7DD43B4A33A32C0472B9120"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>No sale, export, or transfer of defense articles or defense services may occur to any country if the Secretary of State has credible information that the government of such country has committed or is committing genocide or violations of international humanitarian law after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H366D7E9619304BC8A2BE1EEE3C3FEEA3"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>The restriction under subsection (a) shall not apply if the Secretary of State certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that—</text>
<paragraph id="H6E5B346EDEA44D149410A03B64A67A21"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the government has adequately punished the persons directly or indirectly responsible for such acts through a credible, transparent, and effective judicial process;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF9F414BC9E584E3D96FAAE4F7391C41B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>appropriate measures have been instituted to ensure that such acts will not recur; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H9B620688005D4398AD8F7249BF208A79"><enum>(3)</enum><text>other appropriate compensation or appropriate compensatory measures have been or are being provided to the persons harmed by such acts.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H39EE5D496B54436C9635EE93EEAA50C4"><enum>4.</enum><header>Misuse of arms sales for human rights abuses</header> <subsection id="HE9CDC23BB63C4CCEA5759EC2B9752AFD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The President shall ensure that—</text>
<paragraph id="H00BA4E3BB18049879BE462075D65B24D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the sale, export, or transfer of any defense article or defense service to a foreign country or international organization shall be pursuant to an agreement that the government of such country or such international organization will not use such article or service in the commission, or to enable the commission, of a violation of international humanitarian law or internationally recognized human rights;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDE128A5EC4C349C1B616ED218560683B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the United States Government has the legal right to require the return of any defense articles sold, exported, or transferred to a foreign country or international organization if the government of such country or such organization has used United States-origin defense articles in the commission, or has enabled the commission, of a violation of international humanitarian law or internationally recognized human rights; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H5F447492536949C99D5E0615508434C8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>if defense articles are sold, exported, or transferred to a foreign country in a manner in which the intended end-user has not been identified at the unit level for human rights vetting, the agreement for such sale, export, or transfer includes a list of units ineligible to receive such articles, consistent with applicable provisions of United States law.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD4F0627CD3F24807A37F0C5180168943"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Eligibility for defense services or articles</header> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HFE362E9AF9564F478F19307AC1BAEE1A"><enum>(1)</enum><header display-inline="yes-display-inline">Arms Export Control Act</header><text>Section 3(a) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2753">22 U.S.C. 2753(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<subparagraph id="H26BBC6B0977448CA8BDD3537B92BBF2F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (1), by striking <quote>and promote world peace</quote> and inserting <quote>, promote world peace, and is unlikely to contribute to human rights abuses</quote>;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H40C8B89BB33B49789F833C0EF3C57FFB"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H3414B0B2A9574EEDB77424003BC60FEC"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (4) as paragraph (5); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HD0A50CCA0B354225A6C8917F9D041C99"><enum>(D)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (3) the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3654609A80314CD293D3EE98FA02B6E4">
<paragraph id="HDB4813386EFB4EA68B483A0FF6E9035E"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the country or international organization has agreed not to use such article or service in the commission, or to enable the commission, of a violation of international humanitarian law or internationally recognized human rights; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6EFD6F4E5AC24692B267B68BB85E454C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Foreign Assistance Act of 1961</header><text>Section 505 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2314">22 U.S.C. 2314(a)</external-xref>) is amended—</text>
<subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4E344FD43BDB4517A12E11397ACB66D3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in subsection (a)—</text> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HF8DBC65A31B9434EB2649D1002BBCD13"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"> in paragraph (3), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></clause>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD2E29494B5874FAFBD7C67D4D10A26C0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (4) as paragraph (5); and</text></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H6454AB716F7D4ECE874485BD96BC0493"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (3) the following new paragraph:</text>
<quoted-block id="HDD4B0325A19B4C108750051971CF8C41" style="OLC" act-name="">
<paragraph id="H3997D58640534383BC4E121FB5AF82E0"><enum>(4)</enum><text>the country or international organization has agreed not to use such articles or service in the commission, or to enable the commission, of a violation of international humanitarian law or internationally recognized human rights; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HE8C94A7A2E4048B3863279055B19DD71"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in subsection (e), by striking <quote>subsection (a)(1) or (a)(4)</quote> both places it appears and inserting <quote>subsection (a)(1) or (a)(5)</quote>.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H862FEA270FF04F4B8B41954EA20F06D9"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Authorized purpose for military sales</header><text>Section 4 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2754">22 U.S.C. 2754</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H425AA7C20CEC4C50B622D951D9C00022"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>legitimate</quote> before <quote>internal security</quote>; and</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HDECAD4A60C4F4F38980EBC802BE57E9B"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>, provided that such defense articles and defense services will not present a significant risk of being used to violate international humanitarian law or internationally recognized human rights</quote> after <quote>such friendly countries</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> <section id="H946F84CD2A7E4B6295E2E7C338D1C565"><enum>5.</enum><header>Consideration of human rights and democratization in arms exports</header> <subsection id="HE54170A0DF0346BDBEE755C30E731305"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In considering the sale, export, or transfer of defense articles and defense services to foreign countries, the Secretary of State shall—</text>
<paragraph id="H2DDBCB301C544FAE9A9BEFAF27BE91C1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>also consider the extent to which the government of the foreign country protects human rights and supports democratic institutions, including an independent judiciary; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HD9521C9F791A46FBBB697D09DE8F90E6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>ensure that the views and expertise of the Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor of the Department of State in connection with any sale, export, or transfer are fully taken into account.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H3CA7417EFFE64F54B00BA07348B47011"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inspector General oversight</header><text>Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for four years, the Inspector General of the Department of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on the implementation of the requirement under subsection (a) during the preceding year.</text></subsection></section> <section id="HD266FB663C79402A8E33C2A4AAF67A95"><enum>6.</enum><header>Enhancement of congressional oversight of human rights in arms exports</header> <subsection id="HCFA5B57B1C3645C9926987BFFDDBCD37"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any letter of offer to sell, or any application for a license to export or transfer, defense articles or defense services controlled for export shall be subject to the congressional review and disapproval requirements, regardless of monetary value, of section 36 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2776">22 U.S.C. 2776</external-xref>) if the Secretary of State has credible information, with respect to a country to which the defense articles or defense services are proposed to be sold, exported, or transferred, that—</text>
<paragraph id="HC69204E5BD6743B9B41005740EBB5E3A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the government of such country on or after the date of enactment of this Act has been deposed by a coup d’etat or decree in which the military played a decisive role, and a democratically elected government has not taken office subsequent to the coup or decree; or</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB63F8DA718BC4EA5A3FFC0422564E486"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a unit of the security forces of the government of such country—</text>
<subparagraph id="HF40507F2B8B0493CADBD8F01B435E23A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>has violated international humanitarian law and has not been credibly investigated and subjected to a credible and transparent judicial process addressing such allegation; or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFFA12AE46F18452DA1091E6532E99480"><enum>(B)</enum><text>has committed a gross violation of human rights, and has not been credibly investigated and subjected to a credible and transparent judicial process addressing such allegation, including, inter alia—</text>
<clause id="H95E9A14090C24C9699C3B9B1A669361C"><enum>(i)</enum><text>torture or rape;</text></clause> <clause id="H6F439AC95DDB4F5F8B68151CC6EA534A"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>ethnic cleansing of civilians;</text></clause>
<clause id="H0999B8B482984024A35D7016368053B1"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>recruitment or use of child soldiers;</text></clause> <clause id="H738B78EF7CDE450780B66972CDDF5106"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>unjust or wrongful detention;</text></clause>
<clause id="H843ADBEEBA8B4F5B9DAF7380417E07B2"><enum>(v)</enum><text>the operation of, or effective control or direction over, secret detention facilities; or</text></clause> <clause id="H76F0A5E18C1F410F83E1D9CE2791D56B"><enum>(vi)</enum><text>extrajudicial killings, whether by military, police, or other security forces.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H36FE217A49BD4E28AC8AE7B55E23E715"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Inclusion of information in human rights report</header><text>The Secretary of State shall also provide to the appropriate congressional committees the report described in section 502B(c) of the Foreign Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2304">22 U.S.C. 2304(c)</external-xref>) biannually for the period of time specified in subsection (c) of this section regarding any country covered under subsection (a).</text></subsection> <subsection id="HFE23532200244B0D849EFE6508AB337B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duration</header> <paragraph id="HCE8E2F2CA9E146E7A51BD5D62C503897"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to a letter of offer to sell or an application for a license to sell, export, or transfer described in subsection (a), the letter or application shall be subject to the requirements and procedures for congressional review and disapproval under section 36 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2776">22 U.S.C. 2776</external-xref>) for 2 years after the date on which the Secretary of State receives the information described in subsection (a).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE4D66C89325248BC9199E1C619B05BFD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Termination</header>
<subparagraph id="HF5CAD46839734088B819F31C914C0A67"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to such a letter or application, the enhanced congressional oversight under subsections (a) and paragraph (1) of this subsection shall terminate on the date on which the Secretary of State determines and so informs the appropriate congressional committees that—</text> <clause id="H85E073383E724201853715D146B3A00D"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the credible information described in subsection (a)(2) is inaccurate; or</text></clause>
<clause id="HC1225F040CFD47B387914B7336A0F5A1"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the activity has ceased, and the government of the applicable country has taken appropriate steps to ensure that such activity does not recur, including appropriate punishment for the person or persons involved in such activity.</text></clause></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H420AA59292544A1E901BA8737FA3E932"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Information supporting determination</header><text>The Secretary of State shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees all information forming the basis for a determination under subparagraph (A). The determination shall, to the fullest extent possible, be unclassified, but may include a classified annex.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HA25881F080CD4E4AAC4D7908415950AD"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Modification of prior notification of shipment of arms</header><text>Section 36(i) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2776">22 U.S.C. 2776(i)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>subject to the requirements of subsection (b) at the joint request of the Chairman and Ranking Member</quote> and inserting <quote>subject to the requirements of this section at the request of the Chairman or Ranking Member</quote>. </text></subsection></section> <section id="H00551E001A444BB1A487A92BF98CDF30"><enum>7.</enum><header>Limitation on sales to security forces involved in gross violation of human rights</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 620M(a) of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/23/2378d">23 U.S.C. 2378d(a)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>No assistance</quote> and all that follows through <quote>Arms Export Control Act</quote> and inserting <quote>No assistance, including the sale of defense articles or defense services, shall be furnished under this Act, the Arms Export Control Act, or any other provision of law controlling the export or transfer of such articles and services</quote>.</text></section>
<section id="H34D755122EBA456A94916CD55E105679"><enum>8.</enum><header>End-use monitoring of misuse of arms in human rights abuses</header>
<subsection id="H352D6F7069B84BC89E6D0D23F6C0FE6F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>End-Use monitoring</header><text>Section 40A(a)(2)(B) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2785">22 U.S.C. 2785</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HD39CEE9D0B504C77A1C5477EE54698CD"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in clause (i), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H3C62280D6E9D41559FCE425666301BA6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in clause (ii), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDB643624B38B49D392AC5E0E45968904"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new clause:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9853C0D59B1E4445B6A7D65D0AC6B11C">
<clause id="H10A6BEB4166F4797A5D81C5A0DF20688"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>such articles and services are not being used to violate international humanitarian law or internationally recognized human rights.</text></clause><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE10C573085F14D9199A57FBEBDBBD227"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text>The Secretary shall report to the appropriate congressional committees on the measures that will be taken, including any additional resources needed, to conduct an effective end-use monitoring program to fulfill the requirement of clause (iii) of section 40A(a)(2)(B) of the Arms Export Control Act, as added by subsection (a)(3).</text></subsection></section>
<section id="H80171F34F02A4A3E8D29C1DF5D1C44C7"><enum>9.</enum><header>Human rights elements in auxiliary reports</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 36(b)(1) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2776">22 U.S.C. 2776(b)(1)</external-xref>) is amended—</text> <paragraph id="HC6A2DC15073046E4AF0537B8E83C9D0A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>in subparagraph (O), by striking <quote>; and</quote> and inserting a semicolon;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H8059A65B9A464A3089BC2190BC06210F"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (P), by striking the period at the end and inserting <quote>; and</quote>; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H072C4F9921AE4CB580DF9EC34222AB78"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new subparagraph:</text>
<quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0D87D25750C24FE395C7AD171B84D25E">
<subparagraph id="H5ADB3AA1DF4F4A768297E1FC8CF030D4"><enum>(Q)</enum><text>an assessment of the risk that such defense articles or defense services will be used in the commission of violations of international humanitarian law or internationally recognized human rights, and a description of any measures to be taken by the recipient government or by the United States to prevent and monitor any such use.</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section> <section id="H806E05EFA4E14896A89EE1BC77BDD37E"><enum>10.</enum><header>Requirement for certain weapons to be subject to conditions and end-use monitoring as foreign military sales</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Beginning on the date that is 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the following defense articles may be sold, exported, or transferred only pursuant to section 36(b) of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2776">22 U.S.C. 2776(b)</external-xref>):</text>
<paragraph id="HE314E52C4CC64CB5854DCB7EE5B23FC2"><enum>(1)</enum><text>Rockets, space launch vehicles, missiles, bombs (including equipment to enable precision guidance), torpedoes, depth charges, mines, and grenades.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H3DC37876370F403599B57A05BB4181CF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Armored combat ground vehicles, including ground vehicles and trailers that are armed or are specially designed to be used as a firing or launch platform to deliver munitions or otherwise destroy or incapacitate targets, excluding any unarmed ground vehicles, regardless of origin or designation, manufactured prior to 1956 and unmodified since 1955.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H4C46C4B64D424CB0843593353BEC92C3"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Aircraft, whether manned, unmanned, remotely piloted, or optionally piloted, as follows:</text> <subparagraph id="H86DE71AFD1CF4960A7A766B23AA06930"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Bombers.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H78D5E9DA116A4A418C9A6629DA6D94D9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>Fighters, fighter/bombers, and fixed-wing attack aircraft.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H75BCCD6FA08C414BAA15BF8F9F9F653B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Turbofan- or turbojet-powered trainers used to train pilots for fighter, attack, or bomber aircraft.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HD584BBBE01BF4DBCBE8F9121757DEC5D"><enum>(D)</enum><text>Attack helicopters.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1AD76057AEAE4113A39028CCAA1120B9"><enum>(E)</enum><text>Unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) specially designed to incorporate a defense article.</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="H80083C623921496B8404C0094555A631"><enum>(F)</enum><text>Aircraft specially designed to incorporate a defense article for the purpose of performing an intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance function.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEED054F0D30A4356B41C476589F531DA"><enum>(G)</enum><text>Aircraft specially designed to incorporate a defense article for the purpose of performing an electronic warfare function, airborne warning and control aircraft, or aircraft specially designed to incorporate a defense article for the purpose of performing a command, control, and communications function.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></section>
<section id="HB2FEC13FFAC14354AF9DF11176C8D720"><enum>11.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="H4130F853ADCF4024BCD591BBFBB8CC19"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <term>appropriate congressional committees</term> means—</text>
<subparagraph id="HA435315CECE54086A6DA46AA8029AE70"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations and the Committee on Appropriations of the Senate; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H1F87C2E7C0774258B8AB39E452F4B5B6"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs and the Committee on Appropriations of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HD59A026785054B8CA7099100778BC384"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The terms <quote>defense article</quote> and <quote>defense service</quote> have the same meanings given the terms in section 47 of the Arms Export Control Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2794">22 U.S.C. 2794</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section> </legis-body> </bill> 

