<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H21A0F62AF27848408B03ED88838F37AF" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6138 IH: Reform Immigration Through Biometrics Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6138</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231101">November 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000032">Mr. Donalds</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="W000814">Mr. Weber of Texas</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000565">Mr. Gosar</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHM00">Homeland Security</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To evaluate U.S. Customs and Border Protection’s implementation of an integrated biometric entry and exit data system in the United States, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H630BEFAFA3CB43C4BC6F658803D4A9F7" style="OLC"><section id="HBCA15175E6B74629A8F74DF69FD3D082" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Reform Immigration Through Biometrics Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H7758649607394A2FB3AC3FFD796D0CD3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Evaluation of CBP’s implementation of an integrated biometric entry and exit data system</header><subsection id="H346B2E730E0044BCB3874114665AC26D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Evaluation</header><paragraph id="H8EEDDE01D8144458BA842BDDC4E34F4E"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate an evaluation of the status of efforts to implement an integrated entry and exit data system in accordance with section 110 of the Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1365a">8 U.S.C. 1365a</external-xref>; in this section referred to as the <quote>System</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H69B9715E335A465FA42051608290A769"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The evaluation required under paragraph (1) shall include information relating to the following:</text><subparagraph id="HB2DF8B999F2B483D9207518FCD0BEEC6"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of the ongoing efforts to implement the System, including information on pre-existing requirements, design, development, operational, and maintenance costs relating to the System, and other information that takes into account prior reports on such matters issued by the Government Accountability Office and the Department of Homeland Security.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4F0050E8C9B9448D915AD43A5C797DB2"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of cost-effective staffing and personnel requirements of the System that leverages existing resources of the Department and takes into account prior reports on such matters issued by the Government Accountability Office and the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H60F56FC4F86C465681252EF9829AD4A9"><enum>(C)</enum><text>An evaluation of training programs necessary to establish the System that takes into account prior reports on such matters issued by the Government Accountability Office and the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H95D01E439025411B9BFA3303A53A51DA"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of how the System will affect arrival and departure wait times that takes into account prior reports on such matters issued by the Government Accountability Office and the Department.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6D4E334099F47BA84E8289D15C33DA8"><enum>(E)</enum><text>An evaluation of audit capability for systems procured in partnership with the private sector.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCDDBC4E4E2B640DEBA522D772FB0F300"><enum>(F)</enum><text>An evaluation of prior and ongoing consultation with the private sector.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H47DCD9945CE84253B6994B52E8714C4B"><enum>(G)</enum><text>An evaluation how trusted traveler programs in existence as of the date of the enactment of this section may be impacted by, or incorporated into, the System.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H984573FE74894863A78A7697642CFDC3"><enum>(H)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of milestones and metrics of success, if any, that have occurred already, and whether such milestones and metrics should be updated to successfully carry out the congressional directive to establish the System.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HF60CF5C6846945CDA075B7C0F0A1E049"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of risks and mitigation strategies to address such risks.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H08E37BD8D8E048B9941D9B3443D048F3"><enum>(J)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An identification of statutory, regulatory, or administrative authorities, if any, needed to integrate the System into the operations of the Transportation Security Administration, and an evaluation of how the progress made toward any such integration.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAA611C75ED7549C59CF09A6FBCC48347"><enum>(K)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The infrastructure required to implement the System.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE633630DB88343EFB38968D36915BB74"><enum>(L)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The effects of the System on the following:</text><clause id="H3497B52088454F3087ADF99C5E7F06B5"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Legitimate travel and trade.</text></clause><clause id="H29BD039196154E3396A6B504D0F3CE2D"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Combating terrorism.</text></clause><clause id="HB6062843DEA44C6690471C842819BECC"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>Identifying visa holders who violate the terms of their visas.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HCBFFCEF9856B45CFAF6F0B66D6B8F5EA"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Homeland Security shall ensure that the collection of biometric data under the System shall cause the least possible disruption to the movement of people or cargo in air, sea, or land transportation while fulfilling the goals of improving counterterrorism efforts and identifying visa holders who violate the terms of their visas.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAC296A7637AB46C7B2B22A42E81A4F22"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Data matching assessment</header><paragraph id="H4F1740DC450C40BBACDD6B2929F6D56D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>in general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate an assessment of how the System is currently—</text><subparagraph id="H7BBAEB9034D843369378C3CCE361D46D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>matching biometric information for an individual, regardless of nationality, citizenship, or immigration status, who is departing the United States against biometric data previously provided to the United States Government by such individual for the purposes of international travel;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFE9C0E8C44D14C08A19CA209B418E699"><enum>(B)</enum><text>leveraging the infrastructure and databases of the current biometric entry and exit system established pursuant to section 7208 of the Intelligence Reform and Terrorism Prevention Act of 2004 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1365b">8 U.S.C. 1365b</external-xref>) for the purpose described in paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEB4F2EA3AFBB4CA9BAECDB6E51ABFB5D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>being interoperable with, and allow matching against, other Federal databases that—</text><clause id="H21C35E1314314356A906EFADDDD56BC2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>store biometrics of known or suspected terrorists; and</text></clause><clause id="H0D47E8F6FBEF496084F4B5F910AAD503"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify visa holders who violate the terms of their visas.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H87AF0EBD308E4EFC80CABE9B91F183FA"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Prohibition</header><text>The assessment required under paragraph (1) shall not include any information relating to citizens of the United States.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDDFEBCAB07B64116917B0F56252AF2E6" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Exceptions for certain individuals and certain ports of entry</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of whether certain individuals, as described as an individual who exits and then enters the United States on a passenger vessel (as such term is defined in section 2101 of title 46, United States Code) the itinerary of which originates and terminates in the United States, in addition to an evaluation of considerations relating to not collecting biometric information in the case of a United States or Canadian citizen who exits the United States through a land port of entry.</text></subsection><subsection id="H20514C785F9F4F4699CF1B71E4FCEF19"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Further evaluations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this section, the Secretary of Homeland Security shall submit to the Committee on Homeland Security and the Committee on the Judiciary of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs and the Committee on the Judiciary of the Senate the following evaluations:</text><paragraph id="H7BAD0D1767BE413190B8EDFBB82CA2B3"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Multimodal collection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of whether the Secretary has made every effort to collect biometric data using multiple modes of biometrics, and how the Secretary can improve, modernize, and take advantage of innovation relating to using multiple modes of biometrics.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H497DCF83C67F4E0991CFA4999A936C6E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Northern land border</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">With respect to the northern land border, an evaluation of whether the sharing of biometric data provided to the Department of Homeland Security by the Canadian Border Services Agency pursuant to the 2011 Beyond the Border agreement has occurred and the impacts of such data sharing agreement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H940190F84BDE4BBD9599AAA3ADB916C5"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Full and open competition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An evaluation of whether the procurement of goods and services to implement the System has been through full and open competition in accordance with the Federal Acquisition Regulation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42385B834E8548B88DF813050F78EEC9"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Facilities</header><text>An evaluation of whether facilities at which the System is implemented has provided and maintained space for Federal use that is adequate to support biometric data collection and other inspection-related activity.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA8F9457609EC44EE9B392EEF29B6A4BC"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Special rules relating to certain facilities</header><paragraph id="H05091F09EFA742A098B045063580DDB2"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Non-Federal facilities</header><text>With respect to each non-Federal facility at which the System is implemented, the space required for such implementation shall be provided and maintained at no cost to the Federal Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D1372A1E57A48CBAF61FAA6CB1C37B4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Land ports of entry</header><text>With respect to each facility at a land port of entry at which the System is implemented, the space required for such implementation shall be coordinated with the Administrator of General Services.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HDEE7A05A3A3B4448AED37EE11C9B0189"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Other biometric initiatives</header><text>Nothing in this section may be construed as limiting the authority of the Secretary of Homeland Security to collect biometric information in circumstances other than as specified in this section.</text></subsection><subsection id="H688681F7037441BFB9B8E628BD8AD53C"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Savings clause</header><text>Nothing in this section may prohibit the collection of user fees permitted by section 13031 of the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act of 1985 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/19/58c">19 U.S.C. 58c</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

