<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H51FD886B58EF489AA0F862D95C40B0F7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6904 IH: Support Our Afghan Partners Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6904</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231222">December 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001208">Ms. Slotkin</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="W000823">Mr. Waltz</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of State to further surge capacity to better support special immigrant visa applicants who are nationals of Afghanistan, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H10FC7C0E5F8849A8A29C020CD88053F4" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HEF873CBCF4A7431FA120E5612C38AC2A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Support Our Afghan Partners Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></section> <section id="H3830D806C9274444B0EC26811134EE20" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Support for Afghan special immigrant visa and refugee applicants</header> <subsection id="HF8DA0B70C4ED4A28B230E2F791D078FF"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Sense of congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the United States should increase support for nationals of Afghanistan who aided the United States mission in Afghanistan during the past twenty years and are now under threat from the Taliban, specifically special immigrant visa applicants who are nationals of Afghanistan and referrals of nationals of Afghanistan to the United States Refugee Admissions Program, including through the Priority 2 Designation for nationals of Afghanistan, who remain in Afghanistan or are in third countries.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HA6D0440E05F749F3B9598555796F60D2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of State, in coordination with the Secretary of Homeland Security and the heads of other relevant Federal departments and agencies, shall further surge capacity to better support special immigrant visa applicants who are nationals of Afghanistan and referrals of nationals of Afghanistan to the United States Refugee Admissions Program and who have been approved by the chief of mission, including through the Priority 2 Designation for nationals of Afghanistan, and reduce their application processing times, while ensuring strict and necessary security vetting, including, to the extent practicable, enabling refugee referrals to initiate application processes while still in Afghanistan.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H49D290A42CE44D459FF27E6C7684215C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Surge capacity described</header><text>The term <quote>surge capacity</quote> includes increasing consular personnel to any embassy or consulate in the region processing visa applications for nationals of Afghanistan.</text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

