<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Reported-in-House" dms-id="HB6DCCB4FDA07441295543418BD8DCBED" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4667 RH: Returning Erroneous COVID Loans Addressing Illegal and Misappropriated Taxpayer Funds Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">IB</distribution-code><calendar display="yes">Union Calendar No. 147</calendar><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4667</legis-num><associated-doc role="report" display="yes">[Report No. 118–184]</associated-doc><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230717">July 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="M001220">Mr. McGarvey</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Additional sponsor: <cosponsor name-id="L000598">Mr. LaLota</cosponsor></action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Reported from the <committee-name committee-id="HSM00">Committee on Small Business</committee-name>; committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc><action-instruction>Strike out all after the enacting clause and insert the part printed in italic</action-instruction></action><action><action-desc><pagebreak></pagebreak></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Small Business Administration to issue guidance and rules for lenders and the Small Business Administration on handling amounts of Paycheck Protection Loans returned by borrowers, and for other purposes.<pagebreak></pagebreak></official-title></form><legis-body id="H680D9087E9DB4AF89268EFF4457E9A9C" style="OLC"><section id="H5A74694AD0564D0A9BC64210C95C037F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Returning Erroneous COVID Loans Addressing Illegal and Misappropriated Taxpayer Funds Act</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>RECLAIM Taxpayer Funds Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H39B2EC7605024FD0945CDC8CE02599CD" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Paycheck Protection Loan return guidance</header><subsection id="HE28CCBAA25044899AD1EB2AE1EAA7EE3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Small Business Administration shall issue guidance for borrowers and lenders on returning any unused amounts of PPP loans made to the borrower.</text></subsection><subsection id="HA7A2ED2C90154CF8B3E84D71372F0DA7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance requirements</header><text>The guidance required by subsection (a) shall include—</text><paragraph id="H6B3927B25ED44369B4FF92C67D11FE90"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">detailed guidance for borrowers on how to return to the lender that made a PPP loan to the borrower the unused amounts of such PPP loan;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF4E444C1FF3E41D9A8ED4477B1458726"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">detailed guidance for lenders regarding the responsibilities of lenders, including that a lender must—</text><subparagraph id="H1A41843F4B2048D29E53DBAC242E6AEF"><enum>(A)</enum><text>accept the return of any unused amounts of any PPP loan from a borrower or any other source (including law enforcement) if the lender made such PPP loan;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA1F889B43E894CF6A16391F83C99E2F3"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">document the reason for the return of such unused amounts, the identification number of the PPP loan, the name of the borrower of the PPP loan, and the name of the person returning such unused amounts if different than the borrower;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H46BFE444FC9149AD8347CA0F0E92B64B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>remit such unused amounts to the Administration;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA7D9BD8F005944C2B16A193C32D1BC5F"><enum>(D)</enum><text>make the guidance described in paragraph (1) available to borrowers described in such paragraph; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC35AB2AE93294E4388CEA3B745042E33"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">if the lender made a PPP loan, periodically certify that the lender has reported and returned to the Administration all unused amounts of PPP loans returned to the lender;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE0E4796A287475A8A4B292012143964"><enum>(3)</enum><text>detailed guidance for financial institutions holding funds from a PPP loan on the procedure for returning such funds to the Administration if the financial institution suspects the borrower may be committing fraud with respect to the PPP loan or any other issue for which the financial institution should return the funds the Administration; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD20046F22FBE4A45922D8A6AD1A8DD6B"><enum>(4)</enum><text>detailed guidance for borrowers and lenders of PPP loans, financial institutions described in paragraph (3), and other relevant individuals and entities on complying with the requirement to report to the Office of the Inspector General for the Small Business Administration any information indicating the occurrence of fraud with respect to a PPP loan.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H8C4980B73048477A907D50401F31109D"><enum>3.</enum><header>Returns handling process</header><subsection id="HFDBBF9642A6642C78738843E8856D7FD"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Small Business Administration shall issue guidance establishing a process for the Small Business Administration to track amounts of PPP loans returned to mitigate the risk of financial loss to the Federal Government.</text></subsection><subsection id="H8E7B245BD5184EC69418E03ACAD02D57"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Returns handling process requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The process established under subsection (a) shall require—</text><paragraph id="H04CFC899146E49EDBF6E62296BC802C6"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Administration to accept returns of unused amounts of PPP loans; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8F39A2D12278432F92C1690D267AE0C8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the Administrator to deposit in the general fund of the Treasury the unused amounts of PPP loans returned to the Administration.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HDD896DBA77D444B5B3E05799B272D2AD"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H0D4F6C0994614543860E9C8C7C3F4D35"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administration</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Administration</term> means the Small Business Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HBFEA91C9E86A4AAC887F1D3E41F9B24F"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Administrator</term> means the Administration of the Small Business Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H104D3D3C2FA6452F90B47CABE0A87BFC"><enum>(3)</enum><header>PPP loan</header><text>The term <term>PPP loan</term> means a loan made under paragraph (36) or (37) of section 7(a) of the Small Business Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/636">15 U.S.C. 636(a)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="H1C3F0C9902EE427DA4E1A11EFAB2D8C5"><enum>5.</enum><header>Compliance with CUTGO</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">No additional amounts are authorized to be appropriated to carry out this Act. Such Act shall be carried out using amounts otherwise appropriated to the Administrator of the Small Business Administration.</text></section></legis-body><endorsement display="yes"><action-date date="20230901">September 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc> Committed to the Committee of the Whole House on the State of the Union and ordered to be printed</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

