<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD0A58F265857488D82D4331DB1FDE4E4" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 334 IH: Significant Transnational Criminal Organization Designation Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-01-12</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 334</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230112">January 12, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000579">Mr. Gallagher</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="G000578">Mr. Gaetz</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="C001087">Mr. Crawford</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001248">Mr. Burgess</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">Committee on the Judiciary</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committees on <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Financial Services</committee-name>, and <committee-name committee-id="HRU00">Rules</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Immigration and Nationality Act to add membership in a significant transnational criminal organization to the list of grounds of inadmissibility and to prohibit the provision of material support or resources to such organizations.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H17F5D420BEE1479E9CBEFE942ED23491" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="H7E5831BB43E943D1A31E92CAED20FA91"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Significant Transnational Criminal Organization Designation Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="HA635DBB4390D4FD5BFD737F2EFFF64FA"><enum>2.</enum><header>Inadmissibility of members of significant transnational criminal organizations</header><subsection id="HCF311F9763D04CD4A94591E00982974F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 212(a)(2)(F) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1182">8 U.S.C. 1182(a)(2)(F)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4B0811533A034827A2E0BF17261B3FDD"><subparagraph id="H965F81CB31CF40F08A0EA111BE2B6B49"><enum>(F)</enum><header>Membership in a significant transnational criminal organization</header><clause id="HBE51051ACDEF43AEAA9D24C884BABD6C"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Any alien who—</text><subclause id="H0EDB72DFF62848DEB18F25501D346BB0"><enum>(I)</enum><text>is a member of a significant transnational criminal organization; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HB89F562305E3435699B648927B46AC0E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is the spouse or child of an alien described in subclause (I),</text></subclause><continuation-text continuation-text-level="clause">is inadmissible. </continuation-text></clause><clause id="HC1FA602D28844C878F88012A7D843F7A"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Exception</header><text>Clause (i)(II) shall not apply to a spouse or child—</text><subclause id="HBB94EF1812AD40478A3926527A6E235D"><enum>(I)</enum><text>who did not know, or should not reasonably have known, that his or her spouse or parent was a member of a significant transnational criminal organization; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H7EB917A6C52646D9B0298B7443B4FE66"><enum>(II)</enum><text>whom the consular officer or Attorney General has reasonable grounds to believe has renounced the significant transnational criminal organization to which his or her spouse or parent belongs.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H910B7EA95C0F49FBBC63161308ED8667"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Designation of significant transnational criminal organizations</header><paragraph id="HB9CA6EB0152E43D59C6FE3D073C6FFB0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Chapter 2 of title II of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1181">8 U.S.C. 1181 et seq.</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HC8EA4ABA0A3C4B90A156F7D3F962AEF3"><section id="H790E231A7C7E4D1CAADBDD9FB062C9A1"><enum>219A.</enum><header>Designation of significant transnational criminal organizations</header><subsection id="H58EA060B2560405D998C4CC003ACBBAB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Designation</header><paragraph id="HFF670AB03C5F407C84AD1A59D7857C78"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General is authorized to designate an organization as a significant transnational criminal organization in accordance with this subsection if the Attorney General, after consultation with the Secretary of State, the Secretary of the Treasury, and the Secretary of Homeland Security, determines that—</text><subparagraph id="HA2C63647E06F497F86E99C8C461E1558"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the organization is a foreign organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H331BDB554A3041C99E4E90CE2D278AC0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the organization—</text><clause id="HA7B60D9296B745269C5B2F8068FDA6F5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>engages in criminal activity that involves or affects commerce in the United States; or </text></clause><clause id="H56426F9A31D041DF94A366BB8EAD03F0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>retains the ability and intent to engage in such criminal activity; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H83DFE795B9004ACAAEA5A1FC8C311164"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the criminal activity of the organization threatens the security of United States nationals or the national security of the United States.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H3ED623797A9E4EF499D5CF2978FEE1CD"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Procedure</header><subparagraph id="H290467B8864F4CBC8B3D3911E5C1D93E"><enum>(A)</enum><header>Notice</header><clause id="HB55BA6C4DB094D739A1C378AA8A733B1"><enum>(i)</enum><header>To congressional leaders</header><text>Not later than 7 days before making a designation under this subsection, the Attorney General shall, by classified communication, notify the Speaker and minority leader of the House of Representatives, the President pro tempore, majority leader, and minority leader of the Senate, and the members of the relevant committees of the House of Representatives and the Senate, in writing, of—</text><subclause id="H56CB2A954F8C4CA6831B53CEC1E1C57A"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the intent to designate an organization under this subsection; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H866A9D6A096044B6B6AA8D002CB6098E"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the findings made under paragraph (1) with respect to that organization, including the factual basis for such determination.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="HB3D43765489443C08CD16E9B421BCD60"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Publication in Federal Register</header><text>The Attorney General shall publish the designation in the Federal Register not later than 7 days after providing the notification under clause (i).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H26294B5CBE9041ED86C812B40CB3B1CD"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Effect of designation</header><text>A designation under this subsection—</text><clause id="HD72E48993AF04A8AAEEEAB892210A045"><enum>(i)</enum><text>shall take effect upon publication under subparagraph (A)(ii), for purposes of section 212(a)(2)(F) of this Act and section 2339B of title 18, United States Code; and</text></clause><clause id="H191AFC67757D428BB80B8914C25A1362"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall cease to have effect upon an Act of Congress disapproving such designation.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H43BFE24912C74207B15765D5BB43B8D5"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Freezing of assets</header><text>Upon notification under paragraph (2)(A)(i), the Secretary of the Treasury may require United States financial institutions possessing or controlling any assets of any foreign organization included in the notification to block all financial transactions involving those assets until further directive from the Secretary of the Treasury, an Act of Congress, or a court order.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HC435D229374948FB83A5D482418D4B55"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Record</header><subparagraph id="H2D1282D84AEC435DB1032C66A8F75728"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In making a designation under this subsection, the Attorney General shall create an administrative record.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H15F6398FA68342B6BDEA6D9DBD9B7F91"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The Attorney General may consider classified information in making a designation under this subsection. Classified information shall not be subject to disclosure for such time as it remains classified, except that such information may be disclosed to a court ex parte and in camera for purposes of judicial review under subsection (c).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0FD7890DD26442FEB1BE80278691D54F"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Period of designation</header><subparagraph id="HD5BD4E6F46054BE9BD2DB06601BC651A"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>A designation under this subsection shall be effective for all purposes until revoked under paragraph (5) or (6) or set aside pursuant to subsection (c).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBD273258D256441595478567EC76B805"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Review of designation upon petition</header><clause id="HC4AF2BC879AE467C8620083738A1E9E4"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General shall review the designation of a significant transnational criminal organization under the procedures set forth in clauses (iii) and (iv) if the designated organization files a petition for revocation within the petition period described in clause (ii).</text></clause><clause id="H0305B29E3BD84C9FBC571F1D7AD90435"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Petition period</header><text>For purposes of clause (i)—</text><subclause id="H7E2BD409DE6B4EB3A921E9DA847F3FC1"><enum>(I)</enum><text>if the designated organization has not previously filed a petition for revocation under this subparagraph, the petition period begins 2 years after the date on which the designation was made; or</text></subclause><subclause id="HC3F4553E722A4F73B9F108CDA7B7F0D6"><enum>(II)</enum><text>if the designated organization has previously filed a petition for revocation under this subparagraph, the petition period begins 2 years after the date of the determination made under clause (iv) on that petition.</text></subclause></clause><clause id="H425D0BBE10B2466DAEA68DE2257E939E"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>Any significant transnational criminal organization that submits a petition for revocation under this subparagraph shall provide evidence in that petition that the relevant circumstances described in paragraph (1) are sufficiently different from the circumstances that were the basis for the designation such that a revocation with respect to the organization is warranted.</text></clause><clause id="H084D98ABA2EE4FA0AE1E84D12941482D"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>Determination</header><subclause id="H87039EF900E54F138BC99E94936A3466"><enum>(I)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 180 days after receiving a petition for revocation submitted under this subparagraph, the Attorney General shall make a determination regarding such petition.</text></subclause><subclause id="H14F6349FE4FD417B9CD43D6E3B29C28D"><enum>(II)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The Attorney General may consider classified information in making a determination in response to a petition for revocation. Classified information shall not be subject to disclosure for such time as it remains classified, except that such information may be disclosed to a court ex parte and in camera for purposes of judicial review under subsection (c).</text></subclause><subclause id="H2AAD8D13156F44C784F194578901B330"><enum>(III)</enum><header>Publication of determination</header><text>A determination made by the Attorney General under this clause shall be published in the Federal Register.</text></subclause><subclause id="H7CF869D967B8444FAA2182D1D4D0F146"><enum>(IV)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>Any revocation by the Attorney General shall be made in accordance with paragraph (6).</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H51430E57C37447F3822E67FBC16F33F0"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Other review of designation</header><clause id="HF107319DE8DB42A4A5CDE6CE71AC3EDE"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>If no review is conducted pursuant to subparagraph (B) during the 5-year period beginning on the date on which a designation under this subsection takes effect, the Attorney General shall review the designation of the significant transnational criminal organization in order to determine whether such designation should be revoked pursuant to paragraph (6).</text></clause><clause id="H880CE43C7B6B486684D6968AD938E209"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Procedures</header><text>If a review does not take place pursuant to subparagraph (B) in response to a petition for revocation that is filed in accordance with that subparagraph, then the review shall be conducted pursuant to procedures established by the Attorney General. The results of such review and the applicable procedures shall not be reviewable in any court.</text></clause><clause id="H0713F82551804C0EA38C5F8BB2BB7E4A"><enum>(iii)</enum><header>Publication of results of review</header><text>The Attorney General shall publish any determination made pursuant to this subparagraph in the Federal Register.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB87B7F3D0EA248E98B6B564897C15B12"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Revocation by Act of Congress</header><subparagraph id="H5228494C43064DA98B4A68C2882047D5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Except as provided by subparagraph (B), Congress, by an Act of Congress, may block or revoke a designation made under paragraph (1) through the congressional disapproval procedure set forth in section 802 of title 5, United States Code. </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HBC2273FDBA1D4B12BBD231D5B45E2F55"><enum>(B)</enum><header>References to rule</header><text>In applying the procedure, references to the term <term>rule</term> in such section 802 shall be deemed to refer to a designation made under paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC04FE94FA93C44A5AF0BB53206C4FB32"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Effective date</header><text>A joint resolution to block or revoke a designation made under paragraph (1) shall not be subject to the procedure set forth in such section 802 unless it is introduced in either House of Congress during the 60-day period beginning on the date on which the Attorney General notifies Congress pursuant to paragraph (2)(A)(i).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H71AA056C5D754D1AB4370093316E9F45"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Revocation based on change in circumstances</header><subparagraph id="H77ABB19DD75B47598B065CD6F7B75DCE"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General—</text><clause id="H4F88A437E3A349379D209D9F59F2F2E2"><enum>(i)</enum><text>may revoke a designation made under paragraph (1) at any time; and </text></clause><clause id="H50247ECCDF2A4DBD8ECDB56DC09AB74B"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>shall revoke a designation upon completion of a review conducted pursuant to subparagraphs (B) and (C) of paragraph (4) if the Attorney General determines that—</text><subclause id="H403B2FB487E74688AF993860286E8733"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the circumstances that were the basis for the designation have changed in such a manner as to warrant revocation; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H08C7A89B32B04399979526461181EDE5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the national security of the United States warrants a revocation.</text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H147AF30D0A25410FABCC8928CD0F1627"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>The procedural requirements under paragraphs (2) and (3) shall apply to a revocation under this paragraph. Any revocation shall take effect on the date specified in the revocation or upon publication in the Federal Register if no effective date is specified.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H514F504826A5412BB5600632048AEB98"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Effect of revocation</header><text>The revocation of a designation under paragraph (5) or (6) shall not affect any action or proceeding based on conduct committed before the effective date of such revocation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1970E0C156B94B54A2D7BFD4BC2FF2BE"><enum>(8)</enum><header>Use of designation in trial or hearing</header><text>If a designation under this subsection has become effective pursuant to paragraph (2)(B), a defendant in a criminal action or an alien in a removal proceeding shall not be permitted to raise any question concerning the validity of the issuance of such designation as a defense or an objection at any trial or hearing.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF1A79F0486114E0F8CFB287FDFA32876"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Amendments to a designation</header><paragraph id="H410509CF1085438CA9E042288C860B3F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Attorney General may amend a designation under this subsection if the Attorney General discovers that the organization has changed its name, adopted a new alias, dissolved and then reconstituted itself under a different name or names, or merged with another organization.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H175C4B432AB94052966D4B50ED71C4A6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Procedure</header><text>Amendments made to a designation in accordance with paragraph (1) shall be effective upon publication in the Federal Register. Subparagraphs (B) and (C) of subsection (a)(2) shall apply to an amended designation upon such publication. Paragraphs (2)(A)(i), (4), (5), (6), (7), and (8) of subsection (a) shall apply to an amended designation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H19E2BCC55CC94A0D99BC062210386D93"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Administrative record</header><text>The administrative record shall be corrected to include the amendments and any additional relevant information that supports such amendments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE1885326E794EAA95A069229898F42E"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Classified information</header><text>The Attorney General may consider classified information in amending a designation in accordance with this subsection. Classified information shall not be subject to disclosure for such time as it remains classified, except that such information may be disclosed to a court ex parte and in camera for purposes of judicial review under subsection (c).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFAA0B3169C8A45F995ADCDBF6798D263"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Judicial review of designation</header><paragraph id="HF6503E6402584DE8A6FB85CBB54DE5F7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 30 days after publication in the Federal Register of a designation, an amended designation, or a determination in response to a petition for revocation, the designated organization may seek judicial review in the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC410DC2E7D94F1AA9CD06964968D137"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Basis of review</header><text>Review under this subsection shall be based solely upon the administrative record, except that the Government may submit, for ex parte and in camera review, classified information used in making the designation, amended designation, or determination in response to a petition for revocation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE5927BFA0C394260863A818EA8F1320D"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Scope of review</header><text>The Court shall hold unlawful and set aside a designation, amended designation, or determination in response to a petition for revocation the court finds to be—</text><subparagraph id="HD5C10DD4032C4E1ABC3483A5901C7E00"><enum>(A)</enum><text>arbitrary, capricious, an abuse of discretion, or otherwise not in accordance with law;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA908B1E4B4F54278A07E604FA6F04F35"><enum>(B)</enum><text>contrary to constitutional right, power, privilege, or immunity;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F78769B981F48DBA07C0008927D5715"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in excess of statutory jurisdiction, authority, or limitation, or short of statutory right;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H23B89F5D331A4AFEABD46338795F98F7"><enum>(D)</enum><text>lacking substantial support in the administrative record taken as a whole or in classified information submitted to the court under paragraph (2); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10C6B29F91CD4DFE8E217F31196ACC82"><enum>(E)</enum><text>not in accord with the procedures required by law.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5395CA93DF5A40578EFB6AB766BFD4F8"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Judicial review invoked</header><text>The pendency of an action for judicial review of a designation, amended designation, or determination in response to a petition for revocation shall not affect the application of this section, unless the court issues a final order setting aside the designation, amended designation, or determination in response to a petition for revocation.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H95F1BB590A4C4FB48652FBF6B56425B8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The table of contents of the Immigration and Nationality Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/8/1101">8 U.S.C. 1101</external-xref> note) is amended by inserting after the item relating to section 219 the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H31BB0743EB15466BB0063DC23BB462A6"><toc><toc-entry level="section" idref="H790E231A7C7E4D1CAADBDD9FB062C9A1">Sec. 219A. Designation of significant transnational criminal organizations.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H84C831D7A6BF4406ACC14FACE7D00CA4"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Providing material support or resources to significant transnational criminal organizations</header><text>Section 2339B of title 18, United States Code, is amended—</text><paragraph id="H29B75C4A02A74287AF3516727FCE248E"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or a significant transnational criminal organization</quote> after <quote>foreign terrorist organization</quote> each place such term appears; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFEC2CDFB00204A459CA756EDECA398E5"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subsection (a)(1), by striking the second sentence and inserting the following: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H260BE6EBA0DB4DFCA858852D102BC9ED"><text>A person may not be prosecuted for violating this paragraph unless the person has knowledge that the organization referred to in the previous sentence—</text><subparagraph id="H452D08CD88594C8C873B55C3D570C64F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is a designated terrorist organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H252DED84C0F044D987263AD10A3AF9DD"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is a significant transnational criminal organization;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H230A6EA90E7043369C0F507653516925"><enum>(C)</enum><text>has engaged or engages in terrorist activity (as defined in section 212(a)(3)(B) of the Immigration and Nationality Act); or </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6E62D9FD7C1248B1809BF406C7AB48B1"><enum>(D)</enum><text>has engaged or engages in terrorism (as defined in section 140(d)(2) of the Foreign Relations Authorization Act, Fiscal Years 1988 and 1989).</text></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HE545959EDBA74EC0886FA371FB2100E2"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subsection (g)—</text><subparagraph id="HBF2C40FC7AE94D9885878985533BDB8D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>in paragraph (5), by striking <quote>and</quote> at the end;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDDA08EFD2EF74538A756731FA1DCE7B3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by redesignating paragraph (6) as paragraph (7); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6A5E8AE64D0A476C9014968C38B14331"><enum>(C)</enum><text>by inserting after paragraph (5) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H263F5822BAF24522A70D79FA5263567E"><paragraph id="HFD877848F567476999107F37DD907741"><enum>(6)</enum><text>the term <term>significant transnational criminal organization</term> means an organization so designated under section 219A of the Immigration and Nationality Act; and</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

