<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB7F3ED5EC00D4A8DB477CF89621A1C0B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3878 IH: To require a report on Puerto Rico’s progress toward rebuilding the electric grid and detailing the efforts the Federal Government is undertaking to expedite such rebuilding, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3878</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230606">June 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000486">Mr. Torres of New York</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="G000582">Mrs. Gonz&#225;lez-Col&#243;n</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To require a report on Puerto Rico&#8217;s progress toward rebuilding the electric grid and detailing the efforts the Federal Government is undertaking to expedite such rebuilding, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H552A0FDE6E1F4322B04DC76B77BABFEA" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HA45471BC35044C95A61A3E4ED03C0A9D" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Report on Puerto Rico’s electric grid</header> 
<subsection id="HA3DC1E26DA054E6AA66C415F9B0D7B00"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Energy, in consultation with the Administrator of the Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA), the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, and appropriate representatives of the Government of Puerto Rico, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees a report on Puerto Rico’s progress toward rebuilding the electric grid and that details the efforts the Federal Government is undertaking to expedite such rebuilding. The report shall contain the following:</text> <paragraph id="H8EFAE06C1EE048C78E5E30079EF9F78B"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An analysis of the state of Puerto Rico’s electric grid, including the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="H95DE2E7E392B45BE970679451702581F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>A list of projects in order of priority, estimated cost, and estimated time necessary for completion.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HFACDD88EA23949658E9B9798E36FBFE2"><enum>(B)</enum><text>An analysis of the measures taken by the Federal Government and the Government of Puerto Rico to expedite such rebuilding and the effectiveness of such measures.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H21361F74F9584559848C29CD04B3CFC5"><enum>(C)</enum><text>Information relating to the amount of funds that have been allocated and the amount of funds that have been disbursed.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HA44FD0AAC1D849E39F677BE84C9925AD"><enum>(D)</enum><text>An analysis of how the Federal Government can provide further assistance in expediting such rebuilding.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H12A7B6EE850D4F2987A449804BAE8BF4"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information on accountability measures the Federal Government is implementing or planning to implement to oversee the work that the Government of Puerto Rico, the Puerto Rico Electric Power Authority, and private sector entities are carrying out in the rebuilding of the electric grid.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HE5DF1270330F4BE7A318ED62911D0FA9"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An analysis of the role of the Financial Oversight and Management Board for Puerto Rico in the rebuilding of Puerto Rico’s electric grid. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H72D3784DE9CF40F4865EDFB940676258"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Recommendations, as appropriate, for private sector entities and governments to reduce the number of outages and blackouts.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HF16A22827E45468EA96AA4EE6C70A74D"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Proposals, as appropriate, for legislative actions and funding needed to improve the process of fund disbursement for critical projects related to electric grids.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA51BC8132C4F47A680ACCAFBBF87D2A4"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A plan for expediting such rebuilding by not later than three months after the report is so submitted.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H049502D8949F4EA9BB2AEEC460ED7CBA"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section, the term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the Committee on Energy and Commerce, the Committee on Natural Resources, and the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate. </text></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

