<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H02AE102D95334316B03638747E38EFC9" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4116 IH: Systemic Risk Authority Transparency Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4116</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230614">June 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="G000553">Mr. Green of Texas</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S000344">Mr. Sherman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="B001281">Mrs. Beatty</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Federal Deposit Insurance Act to require reports on the use of the systemic risk authority applicable to winding up a failed insured depository institution, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0B6F97F3961541BA8B84F1C8BC4B4DD5" style="OLC"><section id="HD8D36909DCBA495BB93088304D3A024F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Systemic Risk Authority Transparency Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H6971FB83A22F44399CE7EF95E122AB68"><enum>2.</enum><header>Systemic risk provisions</header><subsection id="H38CE37413D884900B7A962135A21269D"><enum>(a)</enum><header>GAO review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 13(c)(4)(G)(iv) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1823">12 U.S.C. 1823(c)(4)(G)(iv)</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="HBC8D367A6B3F4A3CB22B9CCC518F342D" display-inline="no-display-inline"><clause id="H9DB0799187D3447786B51792CF606030"><enum>(iv)</enum><header>GAO Review</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Comptroller General of the United States shall, not later than later than 60 days after a determination is made under clause (i), and again 180 days thereafter, review and report to the Congress on the determination under clause (i), including—</text><subclause id="H9EE058B8CB304D569E1105E8DCC8AAD2"><enum>(I)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the basis for the determination;</text></subclause><subclause id="H962F8F73719E4BBE95F9ADFD61A927C5"><enum>(II)</enum><text>the purpose for which any action was taken pursuant to such clause; </text></subclause><subclause id="H2C77D2AC3C82483B888BD538C0637FEB"><enum>(III)</enum><text>the likely effect of the determination and such action on the incentives and conduct of insured depository institutions and uninsured depositors;</text></subclause><subclause id="H99E56BD39D30401C9FC46B68A44A3EF8"><enum>(IV)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any mismanagement by the executives and board of the insured depository institution that contributed to the failure of the insured depository institution; </text></subclause><subclause id="HBCC6CA22184345738831AA65A971FC7C"><enum>(V)</enum><text>a review of the compensation practices of the insured depository institution;</text></subclause><subclause id="H65797851BDDA420EB165250CC5A4F6DD"><enum>(VI)</enum><text>any supervisory or regulatory shortcomings with respect to the primary Federal banking regulators of the insured depository institution;</text></subclause><subclause id="H039339E2EEAC4E70AE8DFB54378070D9"><enum>(VII)</enum><text>any actions taken by the Federal banking regulators, Financial Stability Oversight Council, Treasury Department, and other relevant financial regulators in relation to the bank’s failure; and</text></subclause><subclause id="H4BD53490655049E78CD5429D079D11DD"><enum>(VIII)</enum><text>any additional relevant entities or activities that may have contributed to the failure of the insured depository institution, including with respect to auditing, accounting, credit rating agencies, investment bank underwriters, and emergency liquidity options such as loans from the Federal Reserve or advances through the Federal Home Loan Bank system.</text></subclause></clause><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H9A82BC6B251A4024872DB4C915F502CB"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Primary Federal regulator report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 13(c) of the Federal Deposit Insurance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/12/1823">12 U.S.C. 1823(c)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H7BEA5736AAB2425DA32C593C435F5287" display-inline="no-display-inline"><paragraph id="H46513C436A2A445DB5E6FBCC9F096312"><enum>(12)</enum><header>Primary Federal Regulator report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The primary Federal regulator of an insured depository institution about which a determination is made under clause (i) shall, not later than 60 days after the date of such determination, and again 180 days thereafter, submit a report to the Congress that—</text><subparagraph id="H57631C2D1FDF49ABADA42ABB1251B711"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">discloses all confidential supervisory information held by such primary Federal regulator that relates to the failed insured depository institution;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C2B7E3D54574D52B21191C4D6F63C4A"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">examines any mismanagement by the executives and board of the insured depository institution that contributed to the failure of the insured depository institution;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB425A8C5B994ACDA3EF56D836F25B6D"><enum>(C)</enum><text>discloses any supervisory or regulatory shortcomings by such primary Federal regulator with respect to the insured depository institution;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6EDEBCA5D52043978EDE2C4E36BF8D7A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>describes any dynamics that the primary Federal regulator determines may have contributed to the failure of the insured depository institution; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC0B2C82307234C7DB3F44EDEB003F727"><enum>(E)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes any supervisory, regulatory, and legislative recommendations such primary Federal regulator may have to improve the safety and soundness of similarly situated insured depository institutions, the banking system, and financial stability.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

