<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HC7C7CBF7E0FB4302B3ADB8AA2AA970F8" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 2622 IH: To amend the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 to codify certain Securities and Exchange Commission no-action letters that exclude brokers and dealers compensated for certain research services from the definition of investment adviser, and for other purposes.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-04-13</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 2622</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230413">April 13, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000250">Mr. Sessions</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="W000812">Mrs. Wagner</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 to codify certain Securities and Exchange Commission no-action letters that exclude brokers and dealers compensated for certain research services from the definition of investment adviser, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDF283695F8D44BFDA07C8B87F316B9BE" style="OLC"><section id="H3A7AB5745ADF41D0BED37D27C90FB0E9" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Definition of investment adviser amended to exclude brokers and dealers compensated for certain research services</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 202(a)(11) of the Investment Advisers Act of 1940 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/15/80b-2">15 U.S.C. 80b–2(a)(11)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following: <quote>In subparagraph (C), the term <quote>special compensation</quote> does not include compensation provided by any person who is an investment adviser, who would be an investment advisor but for subparagraph (A), (C), (E), (F) or (G), or is an insurance company, for research services, as described in section 28(e) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, whether paid from the resources of such person or the resources of a client of such person (including client commissions).</quote>.</text></section></legis-body></bill> 

