<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H70D52448AAB34D0BACCCC3EE594D6E43" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6656 IH: Stuck On Hold Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-07</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6656</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231207">December 7, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="C000059">Mr. Calvert</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="C001063">Mr. Cuellar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Committee on Ways and Means</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Veterans' Affairs</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs and the Commissioner of Social Security to implement automated systems with callback functionality for each customer service telephone line of the Department of Veterans Affairs and the Social Security Administration, respectively, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H6E80197EF10543268FF09F5336A0C4C7" style="OLC"><section id="H0E756A7021724A48B60C8414ECB760D6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Stuck On Hold Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H48A9AA3C828248469C2B9E536FB55669"><enum>2.</enum><header>Improvements regarding wait times of callers to customer service telephone lines of certain agencies</header><subsection id="HED10FE40D47941089852E0F86A45F602"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Customer service telephone lines of the Department of Veterans Affairs</header><paragraph id="H25C8F4EE13A74A79AC025146B1C7382F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Automated system</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary of Veterans Affairs shall implement for each customer service telephone line of the Department of Veterans Affairs an automated system that—</text><subparagraph id="HDF479DCBF25B4F83855E8BBF50760CC3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>informs any caller to such a telephone line about the anticipated wait time, if any; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD022B2DE4F9E4EA5A5458F868CEA5504"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">automatically offers a callback to any such caller with an anticipated wait time of more than 15 minutes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F9BEDE93ED543978A7E4B2F41AC1A2A"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidance regarding caller wait times</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall issue such guidance as is necessary to reduce the average wait time of callers to a customer service telephone line of the Department to not more than 15 minutes. All calls will be answered in the order in which they are received.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H508EF314B74D4E1FB5C0C7CC510E16CC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Customer service telephone lines of the Social Security Administration</header><paragraph id="HBAD9667963364194929F316A7765D1FD"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Automated system</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Commissioner of Social Security shall implement for each customer service telephone line of the Social Security Administration an automated system that—</text><subparagraph id="H947808AACED74AFF91456AB07B10C93A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">informs any caller to such a telephone line about the anticipated wait time, if any; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC6A5253E9AF6465A96FE7C00E74ED7FF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">automatically offers a callback to any such caller with an anticipated wait time of more than 15 minutes. All calls will be answered in the order in which they are received.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H94F313BC0721490C9218A4031AC424A6"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Guidance regarding caller wait times</header><text>The Commissioner shall issue such guidance as is necessary to reduce the average wait time of callers to a customer service telephone line of the Social Security Administration to not more than 15 minutes.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

