<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H23344237A3534B56AAD7474678636D8F" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 4228 IH: Fostering Opportunities for Resources and Education Spending through Timber Sales Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-20</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 4228</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230620">June 20, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001159">Mrs. Rodgers of Washington</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HII00">Natural Resources</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To restore employment and educational opportunities in, and improve the economic stability of, counties containing National Forest System land, while also reducing Forest Service management costs, by ensuring that such counties have a dependable source of revenue from timber sales conducted on National Forest System land, to reduce payments under the Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 to reflect such counties' receipt of timber sale revenues, to strengthen stewardship end result contracting, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H437EA74DB9884A6091315070F6104FA4" style="OLC"><section id="H749C8E88C2674D8E91C71C2A4DA8947E" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title; table of contents</header><subsection id="H532360E60C934C1FBD8C4DFF246AAF5B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Fostering Opportunities for Resources and Education Spending through Timber Sales Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>FORESTS Act of 2023</short-title></quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H6988240B94A84052A8300CDEB666314C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Table of contents</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of contents of this Act is as follows:</text><toc container-level="legis-body-container" lowest-bolded-level="division-lowest-bolded" lowest-level="section" quoted-block="no-quoted-block" regeneration="yes-regeneration"><toc-entry idref="H749C8E88C2674D8E91C71C2A4DA8947E" level="section">Sec. 1. Short title; table of contents.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H04D4FC82EB764697B68D32B4C8F9DB49" level="section">Sec. 2. Purposes.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDD4ADFED03A241E2816696D94815FC41" level="title">Title I—Forest Active Management Areas </toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H158F12FA91D0458399FB23329B8FBE3A" level="section">Sec. 101. Definitions.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBA6EBE3D8202483385A539E13FBD371C" level="section">Sec. 102. Establishment of Forest Active Management Areas and annual volume requirements.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H7727A7DB8752455685133EF597721461" level="section">Sec. 103. Management of Forest Active Management Areas.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H2E3D09ECA18D44D8A573970D96840E28" level="section">Sec. 104. Environmental analysis process for covered active management projects.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HA370E195A19D425A9ED6A9758F084F1E" level="section">Sec. 105. Expedited compliance with Endangered Species Act.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H0AE9C3D7F769407185F81D115DEF127F" level="section">Sec. 106. Administrative review.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HBE10C955FF4549C1A29C74790B47C11D" level="section">Sec. 107. Use of arbitration instead of litigation to address challenge to covered active management project developed through collaborative process.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HDD09C2D632A44CCDAF2E89B7B3285DCF" level="section">Sec. 108. Distribution of forest active management revenues.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HEA44FEADC36E49A99F30406B6B3B7ACF" level="section">Sec. 109. Annual report.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H20594EB12832449D9E8284AB18904020" level="title">Title II—Transition of Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 and 25-percent payments</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H388AFB892C0E40B88124E2CFC4753D55" level="section">Sec. 201. Prohibition on State retention of portion of 25-percent payments made on behalf of beneficiary counties.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HF0C4C3A4A4A94A26ABF9C23AA493ED62" level="title">Title III—Stewardship end result contracting authority </toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H8C1A5E95BC3245A9AC44A7FCE60EA538" level="section">Sec. 301. Maximum authorized duration of stewardship end result contracts.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HD0B71238946147AE8DD20D1E59F92ADD" level="section">Sec. 302. Payment of portion of stewardship project revenues to county in which stewardship project occurs.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HAB4D5DD6C166475883FFE8E13B4FB15D" level="section">Sec. 303. Use of contractors to perform environmental analysis in connection with stewardship end result contracting projects.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H9BB8F2CE603441A781FB9586599D86EA" level="title">Title IV—Other Matters</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H4D88F29EC7874AF1B8C1791519302676" level="section">Sec. 401. Treatment as supplemental funding.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="H722E73C7D6F946CCAA04ADF9137FD94D" level="section">Sec. 402. Definition of fire suppression to include certain related activities.</toc-entry><toc-entry idref="HB9B4AD35A8DC4D01B763B81EEB3B4A75" level="section">Sec. 403. Prohibition on certain actions regarding Forest Service roads and trails.</toc-entry></toc></subsection></section><section id="H04D4FC82EB764697B68D32B4C8F9DB49"><enum>2.</enum><header>Purposes</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The purposes of this Act are as follows:</text><paragraph id="HFDF6A307F08A4D47815FBED173C61144"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To restore employment and educational opportunities in, and improve the economic stability of, counties containing National Forest System land.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H11E56695FFEC437AB445D4A8A5FCF83D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>To ensure that such counties have a dependable source of revenue from National Forest System land.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17A10A60724442F5B59BE7B03631A07A"><enum>(3)</enum><text>To reduce Forest Service management costs while also ensuring the protection of United States forest resources.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A255BC93E9540FAABC342CE68BDCD97"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To reduce the frequency and severity of catastrophic wildfires on Federal lands.</text></paragraph></section><title id="HDD4ADFED03A241E2816696D94815FC41"><enum>I</enum><header>Forest Active Management Areas </header><section id="H158F12FA91D0458399FB23329B8FBE3A"><enum>101.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this title:</text><paragraph id="HDBDFCD9766B641959F1B9C5BB8F56A59"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Annual volume requirement</header><subparagraph id="H2B107C1A86554480BB476D7814267597" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>annual volume requirement</term>, with respect to a Forest Active Management Area, means, the annual volume of national forest materials from such Forest Active Management Area that, subject to an adjustment pursuant to section 102(e)(2), is equal to or greater than—</text><clause id="HC32E3BA8091A4977A48A499899802E9F"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the allowable sale quantity established in the applicable forest plan for such Area,</text></clause><clause id="HA6E9D0D702704A8AB534AAF1075F0331"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>divided by 10.</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H00E5B36668A042E486D58B6352AAC824"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In determining the volume of national forest materials or the sustained yield of a Forest Active Management Area, the Secretary may not include non-commercial post and pole sales and personal use firewood. </text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H5FBEC02008B044CC8D3C9928D1118780"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Beneficiary county</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>beneficiary county</term> means a political subdivision of a State that, on account of containing National Forest System land, was eligible to receive payments for any of the fiscal years 2001 through 2015 through the State under title I of the Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7111">16 U.S.C. 7111 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8396E0DE514B4F4C90EEF240BE5CE81A"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Collaborative process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>collaborative process</term> refers to a planning, decisionmaking, and management process that, as determined by the forest manager of the unit of the National Forest System for which the process will occur and as confirmed by the Regional Forester—</text><subparagraph id="HB2C31868C7E94599A99EEF683C246701"><enum>(A)</enum><text>includes multiple interested persons representing diverse interests; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB559805AC6F144CCBAB42FCAAD3BBCEE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>is transparent and nonexclusive or meets the requirements for a resource advisory committee under subsections (c) through (f) of section 205 of the Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7125">16 U.S.C. 7125</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA48E69D18CF24F91813288E1A7C8BF8B"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Covered active management project</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <term>covered active management project</term> and <term>covered project</term> mean a project involving the management or sale of national forest materials within a Forest Active Management Area to generate forest active management revenues and achieve the annual volume requirement for the Forest Active Management Area.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDAB867080E7342789A3000CB335439ED"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Forest Active Management area</header><subparagraph id="H89CFA60F8C1A457E9C060D8B26976CDD"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Forest Active Management Area</term> means National Forest System land in a unit of the National Forest System that has been identified in the 5-year period preceding the date of such identification as being overstocked based off of basal area or at risk of wildfire and suitable for timber production.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFCFCA5D2633545D587B5E7B7EE61DE14"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Exclusions</header><text>A Forest Active Management Area may not include National Forest System land—</text><clause id="H4999AEFA00474475BB2E725B698EE28A"><enum>(i)</enum><text>that is a component of the National Wilderness Preservation System;</text></clause><clause id="HC65405181ECE4EFB8256914A7AB3414F"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>on which the removal of vegetation is specifically prohibited by Federal statute; or</text></clause><clause id="H928F998FE43D45098E9783478F29F260"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>that is included within a National Monument as of the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H727FCAA562FD48D2B7A5FE339C8598E7"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Forest active management revenues</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>forest active management revenues</term> means revenues derived from the sale of national forest materials in a Forest Active Management Area.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H48DF6A40030B40959A2D20DEA35EECED"><enum>(7)</enum><header>National forest materials</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>national forest materials</term> has the meaning given that term in section 14(e)(1) of the National Forest Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/472a">16 U.S.C. 472a(e)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C43C408D8044520A87CD407ED09C573"><enum>(8)</enum><header>National forest system</header><text>The term <term>National Forest System</term> has the meaning given that term in section 11(a) of the Forest and Rangeland Renewable Resources Planning Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1609">16 U.S.C. 1609(a)</external-xref>), except that the term does not include the National Grasslands and land utilization projects designated as National Grasslands administered pursuant to the Act of July 22, 1937 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1010">7 U.S.C. 1010–1012</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H39250595935C43C29016148CC0A96FD3"><enum>(9)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text>The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Agriculture.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H25DA31250F594EB0A6A95500150129D6"><enum>(10)</enum><header>Sustained yield</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>sustained yield</term> means the maximum annual growth potential of a forest calculated on the basis of the culmination of mean annual increment using cubic measurement.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE2CB81BF850A437F984CEA2A69BFDD4F"><enum>(11)</enum><header>State</header><text>The term <term>State</term> includes the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3FBA48D80BEE4C678BD9E80EF35F4179"><enum>(12)</enum><header>25-percent payment</header><text>The term <term>25-percent payment</term> means the payment to States required by the sixth paragraph under the heading of <quote>FOREST SERVICE</quote> in the Act of May 23, 1908 (35 Stat. 260; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/500">16 U.S.C. 500</external-xref>), and section 13 of the Act of March 1, 1911 (36 Stat. 963; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/500">16 U.S.C. 500</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></section><section id="HBA6EBE3D8202483385A539E13FBD371C"><enum>102.</enum><header>Establishment of Forest Active Management Areas and annual volume requirements</header><subsection id="H19FA9CF659EE4DF59BA03E88E157C753"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment of Forest Active Management Areas</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary shall establish one or more Forest Active Management Areas within each unit of the National Forest System.</text></subsection><subsection id="HBFAFC556C5CD416AAF161B0A131C01D4"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Deadline for establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall complete the establishment of Forest Active Management Areas not later than 60 days after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB000836189BE4A36AA5BDF2D898F3DB0"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Purpose</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The purpose of a Forest Active Management Area is to provide a dependable source of 25-percent payments and economic activity through sustainable forest management for each beneficiary county containing National Forest System land included within that Forest Active Management Area.</text></subsection><subsection id="HDF5CA7E151DF430AAC18AD64EC358501"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Fiduciary responsibility</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall have a fiduciary responsibility to beneficiary counties to manage a Forest Active Management Area to satisfy the annual volume requirement established for that Forest Active Management Area.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0B609ABE5A244558BF08FDA87400F058"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Annual volume requirement</header><paragraph id="H4715E1F60E864D8DB323498BCB7FE6E0"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Deadline for establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after the date of the establishment of a Forest Active Management Area, the Secretary shall establish the annual volume requirement for that Forest Active Management Area.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D882037A9604E5A864F776A163289F7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Collaborative adjustment authority</header><subparagraph id="HBE513EE114934DD8958F40A6A6EC07AA" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall make publicly available the annual volume requirement for a Forest Active Management Area.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H506565E3476A4F979F1D74ED43AE1840" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Petition for adjustment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 30 days after an annual volume requirement for a Forest Management Area is made publicly available under subparagraph (A), a forest management collaborative located in the same Forest Service region as the Forest Active Management Area may petition the Secretary to adjust such annual volume requirement.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3BEA04F7C80343778D92D094E42CC965" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Determination</header><text>In the case of a petition under subparagraph (B), the Secretary shall make a determination on such petition not later than 60 days after receiving such petition. </text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H13819AB34AC746ECB63C81C992656A6C"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Size of forest Active Management area</header><paragraph id="H56B5861B58BA44078EFC835DC8F83BD8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Minimum size</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (3), the Forest Active Management Areas established within a unit of the National Forest System shall include not less than 50 percent of the National Forest System lands in that unit identified as commercial forest land capable of producing twenty cubic feet of timber per acre.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEBC3C33BF98A46B0B71A8F7148625AD5"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reduction prohibited</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except as provided in paragraph (3), once a Forest Active Management Area is established, the Secretary may not reduce the number of acres of National Forest System land included in that Forest Active Management Area.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0E1D42391F8C4BF184D66E346B2A6D2F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Collaborative adjustment authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may reduce the number of acres of National Forest System land included in a Forest Active Management Area, including an acreage reduction resulting in the inclusion of a quantity of commercial forest land below the percentage required by paragraph (1) and section 101(5)(B), if the reduction is developed and agreed upon through a collaborative process.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC103F1E6166D44F4BC8D4E1EE567CEA1"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Map</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall submit a map of all Forest Active Management Areas established under subsection (a) and a map of any Forest Active Management Area whose acreage is adjusted made pursuant to subsection (f)(3)—</text><paragraph id="H99301F4BA3B84FF59902F669C0250F34"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to the Committee on Agriculture and the Committee on Natural Resources of the House of Representatives; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5F25F119F6D749C0B1B5352A218CFF79"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry and the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources of the Senate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1A215B1232434FEB88F97E344875C926"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Recognition of Valid and Existing Rights</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Neither the establishment of Forest Active Management Areas under subsection (a) nor any other provision of this title shall be construed to limit or restrict—</text><paragraph id="H0486C24F6FA143FC9B27BD499C960BCA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>access to National Forest System land for hunting, fishing, recreation, and other related purposes; or</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3927522FE41F46D68C6E056C4DB4422C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>valid and existing rights regarding National Forest System land, including rights of any federally recognized Indian tribe.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H7727A7DB8752455685133EF597721461"><enum>103.</enum><header>Management of Forest Active Management Areas</header><subsection id="HE76E0F1387054A9FBFF978FBE298C428"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement To achieve annual volume requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Immediately upon the establishment of a Forest Active Management Area, the Secretary shall manage the Forest Active Management Area in the manner necessary to achieve the annual volume requirement for the Forest Active Management Area. Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Secretary shall commence covered active management projects to begin generating forest active management revenues.</text></subsection><subsection id="HC92A487353F54B148912D90083A57B84"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Standards for projects within forest Active Management areas</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall conduct covered active management projects within Forest Active Management Areas in accordance with this section and sections 104 and 105, which shall serve as the sole means by which the Secretary will comply with the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4331">42 U.S.C. 4331 et seq.</external-xref>) and other laws applicable to the covered projects.</text></subsection><subsection id="HAB332E4AAE3C4D2CBF45476F53E081B2"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Use of collaborative process</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary is authorized and encouraged to develop covered active management projects for a Forest Active Management Area through a collaborative process. The decision notice for a covered active management project shall describe the collaborative process by which the project was developed, including a description of—</text><paragraph id="H9F75D80355D442BBAF0845F338DA20F1"><enum>(1)</enum><text>participation by or consultation with State, local, and tribal governments; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H84193B052A6A42659CFB02A67CF844BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text>any established record of successful collaborative planning and implementation of forest management projects by the collaborators.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC69E7352D4474719B985780ABD8AA1BB"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Use of contractors To perform environmental analysis</header><paragraph id="HFB9D4BFD47FD473180D2B51E5175B3DE"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of a covered active management project, or as a separate agreement or contract in connection with one or more covered active management projects, the Secretary may procure the services of persons who are not Federal employees to perform activities necessary to ensure project for compliance with the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4331">42 U.S.C. 4331 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8EA705AADD04474DBAC4AB328E832133"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Approval requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Services performed under this subsection are subject to approval by the Chief of the Forest Service or other responsible official of the Forest Service.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H0BFEE6D4A8BA4CF8B42A7CD3F3584477"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Funding source</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As provided in section 108(c)(2), the Secretary shall use forest active management revenues to cover the cost of services procured under this subsection.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF49DC7CBF1504638A5E2DC49A39D10F2"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Application of land and resource management plan</header><paragraph id="HEAF28B78C8564BEEB96AF25EF49E51C7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Modification authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may modify the standards and guidelines contained in the land and resource management plan for the unit of the National Forest System in which the covered active management project will be carried out as necessary to achieve the requirements of this Act.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD46412A5939946C2B73DE72A2D5F8B8C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Harvesting system</header><text>Section 6(g)(3)(E)(iv) of the Forest and Rangeland Renewable Resources Planning Act of 1974 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1604">16 U.S.C. 1604(g)(3)(E)(iv)</external-xref>) shall not apply to a covered active management project.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H90C645BFE0C645B4A4924469738A46A5"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of all-Terrain vehicles for management activities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary may allow the use of all-terrain vehicles within the Forest Active Management Areas for the purpose of activities associated with the sale of national forest materials in a Forest Active Management Area.</text></subsection></section><section id="H2E3D09ECA18D44D8A573970D96840E28"><enum>104.</enum><header>Environmental analysis process for covered active management projects</header><subsection id="H4C4562548FE145C88C85E139B0F488CA"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Environmental Assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Except in the case of a covered active management project for which a categorical exclusion is available under subsection (e) or a Forest Active Management Area for which a programmatic environmental impact statement is in effect under subsection (f), the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="HF6ED91A4175B4FA7BB3B34015FEDEC03"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">publish advance notice of each covered active management project proposed to be conducted within a Forest Active Management Area; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD46B61BEDD8F4E41AB1A27EBBD3625AD"><enum>(2)</enum><text>complete an environmental assessment pursuant to section 102(2) of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4332">42 U.S.C. 4332(2)</external-xref>) for the proposed covered active management project.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H3D5428B5F391408F930B80F07F662E28"><enum>(b)</enum><header>No alternative version</header><text>The Secretary is not required to study, develop, or describe any alternative to the proposed agency action.</text></subsection><subsection id="HEDB3D1EB606344B1B9B12CAC00FBF102"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Cumulative effects</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall consider cumulative effects solely by evaluating the impacts of a proposed covered active management project combined with the impacts of any other projects that were approved with a Decision Notice or Record of Decision before the date on which the Secretary published notice of the proposed covered project. The cumulative effects of past projects may be considered in the environmental assessment by using a description of the current environmental conditions.</text></subsection><subsection id="HB9E5C7B535B44BDA94296F0E5B4600C0"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Treatment of decision notice</header><text>The decision notice for a covered active management project shall be considered a final agency action and no additional analysis under the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4331">42 U.S.C. 4331 et seq.</external-xref>) shall be required to implement any portion of the covered project.</text></subsection><subsection id="H74C6CC63217B499CB994432CEFE5CA30" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Applicability of NEPA</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The designation and management of a Forest Active Management Area under this Act shall not be subject to the requirements of the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4331">42 U.S.C. 4331 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="HA370E195A19D425A9ED6A9758F084F1E"><enum>105.</enum><header>Expedited compliance with Endangered Species Act</header><subsection id="HD350B278D81D40EE9DE7476BDDD34AB3"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Non-Jeopardy assessment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary makes a determination that a proposed covered active management project is not likely to jeopardize the continued existence of any species listed as endangered or threatened under section 4 of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1533">16 U.S.C. 1533</external-xref>), the Secretary shall—</text><paragraph id="H4C8EA7C6C0BF4C2EB568A307B2BE3131"><enum>(1)</enum><text>prepare an explanation of the basis for the determination; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8730C509FC574884B56DAA0729760486"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">submit the determination and explanation to the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Commerce, as appropriate.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HEFB05A5DE5CD4CB2A1ED33EA5E14E6E5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Review and response</header><paragraph id="HD7515576A2A64724927681BCF7167B9F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Within 30 days after receiving a determination made by the Secretary under subsection (a), the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Commerce, as appropriate, shall provide a written response to the Secretary concurring in or rejecting the Secretary’s determination.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9610E2B898094945827943C965442B54"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Effect of rejection</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Commerce rejects the determination made by the Secretary under subsection (a), the written response of the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Commerce under paragraph (1) shall include recommendations for measures that—</text><subparagraph id="H6C0896ADFC2B4225996B1EE5D63546CD"><enum>(A)</enum><text>will avoid the likelihood of jeopardy to an endangered or threatened species;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HADDBABD1E4BA431FBFF8CE761C673A5D"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">can be implemented in a manner consistent with the intended purpose of the covered active management project;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB27382D012E4653AD7063BB87859E5B"><enum>(C)</enum><text>can be implemented consistent with the scope of the Secretary’s legal authority and jurisdiction; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HE806A52B874E41EB9A70745496855A3A"><enum>(D)</enum><text>are economically and technologically feasible.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5779D95EE3F6400EAF0B0D4E66B6B0CB"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Formal consultation</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In addition to recommendations made under subsection (b)(2) when the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Commerce rejects a determination issued by the Secretary under subsection (a), the Secretary of the Interior or the Secretary of Commerce, as the case may be, shall engage in formal consultation with the Secretary pursuant to section 7 of the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1536">16 U.S.C. 1536</external-xref>). The Secretaries shall complete such consultation within 90 days after the submission of the written response under subsection (b).</text></subsection></section><section id="H0AE9C3D7F769407185F81D115DEF127F"><enum>106.</enum><header>Administrative review</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Administrative review of a covered active management project shall occur only in accordance with the special administrative review process and requirements established under section 105 of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6515">16 U.S.C. 6515</external-xref>), including the project-level predecisional administrative review process established in part 218 of title 36, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></section><section id="HBE10C955FF4549C1A29C74790B47C11D"><enum>107.</enum><header>Use of arbitration instead of litigation to address challenge to covered active management project developed through collaborative process</header><subsection id="H13327F19A251418D8AE81A8D809F5814"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Arbitration process</header><paragraph id="H5C89504E81F04D46A3FDF1B7AC3E2CE1"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a covered active management project that was developed through a collaborative process, any challenge to the covered project made after the special administrative review process required by section 106 shall be addressed using arbitration consistent with this section instead of through judicial review.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE36BFD3AB77B4EC5B56617FE005E14E4"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Who may seek</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person who sought administrative review for the covered project described in paragraph (1) and who is not satisfied with the decision made under the administrative review process may file a demand for arbitration regarding the covered project in accordance with <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/9/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of title 9, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HA39DA99F1A284BF3A5C4C6E102FAE95B"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Requirements for demand</header><text>The demand for arbitration under subsection (a)(2) shall—</text><paragraph id="HA0BD59EAD1A14E94A6C95A1DFE5C90A0"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be filed not more than 30 days after the date on which the administrative review decision was issued; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFC9B708A7FA041469AD1912B36F14CAD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">include a proposal describing the modifications sought to the covered project.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H21959B2F09F64774A4D965068A9672D8"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Intervening parties</header><paragraph id="H3936F866B9D849F4845E38524B5E74FF"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person that submitted a public comment on the covered active management project subject to arbitration may intervene in the arbitration—</text><subparagraph id="H5A67F140C77B435AB5734BED379A2A0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by endorsing the covered project or the modification proposal submitted under subsection (b)(2); or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6527E827719046C88E9ED3C2B8D25600"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by submitting a proposal to further modify the covered project.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB3B54E891B33487BA75BD5FDF2C2FF35"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Deadline for submission</header><text>A request to intervene in an arbitration must be submitted not later than the date that is 30 days after the date on which the demand for arbitration was filed.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H414736EFABE246AFB7B1877582880826"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Multiple parties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Multiple objectors or intervening parties may submit a joint proposal so long as each objector or intervening party meets the eligibility requirements of subsection (a)(2) or paragraph (1), whichever applies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HC2BC1088ADDE4BB8A01C1EDA915CE2BF"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Appointment of arbitrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States District Court in the district in which the covered active management project is located shall appoint the arbitrator to conduct the arbitration proceedings in accordance with this section and <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/9/1">chapter 1</external-xref> of title 9, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H445EAEF8EB3C486AB1B7215C151065D6"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Selection of proposals</header><paragraph id="H88F282E545ED4FF68BFF36167BA9C87D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The arbitrator appointed under subsection (d)—</text><subparagraph id="H5316E4D635B7447080557567CF3E6D68"><enum>(A)</enum><text>may not modify any of the proposals submitted with the demand for arbitration or a request to intervene; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC076B402B6744FE9857313D7C8D6033"><enum>(B)</enum><text>shall select to be conducted—</text><clause id="HA91617077F69470B9EA546A358CFDF40"><enum>(i)</enum><text>a proposal submitted by an objector or an intervening party; or</text></clause><clause id="HB5467AF9BAC243B7B7DC2311E0E2BFE0"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the covered active management project, as approved by the Secretary.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H9BC14BBA2DE14E1FBF81FE5D906EA1CE"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Selection criteria</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An arbitrator shall select the proposal that best meets the purpose and needs described in the environmental analysis conducted for the covered project.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H441F68F5A0C04BF79AD81F0DDE2DC130"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Effect of decision</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The decision of an arbitrator with respect to the covered active management project—</text><paragraph id="HF22FAA0AE62148689450CBE1CECDC0F9"><enum>(1)</enum><text>shall not be considered a major Federal action;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H18188D8107324A119500D2C2647E11A4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>shall be binding; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3D9E5B1A20C8449ABC1C95D89989FA2C"><enum>(3)</enum><text>shall not be subject to judicial review.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H5CC2BC7EBE594C7690671104CA874306"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Deadline for completion</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 90 days after the date on which the demand for arbitration is filed with respect to the covered active management project, the arbitration process shall be completed.</text></subsection></section><section id="HDD09C2D632A44CCDAF2E89B7B3285DCF"><enum>108.</enum><header>Distribution of forest active management revenues</header><subsection id="H38782B099AC8405586870AD0E6F45B7F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Use To make 25-Percent Payments</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary shall use forest active management revenues generated by covered active management projects to make 25-percent payments to States for payment to beneficiary counties.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2813C2D885F94C66B7F186D41786EB0C"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Relation to payments under Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Subject to the offset required by subsection (f) of section 102 of the Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7112">16 U.S.C. 7112</external-xref>), a beneficiary county may receive both—</text><paragraph id="HF800FB7FE6FB45FEB71938E42352E0C7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a share of the 25-percent payments made to a State under subsection (a); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC58642376C09487A82F631C657E6D858"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a share of the payment for the State (known as the State payment) calculated under section 101(a) of the Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7111">16 U.S.C. 7111(a)</external-xref>) for which the beneficiary county made an election (or was deemed to make an election) under section 102(b)(1) of such Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/7112">16 U.S.C. 7112(b)(1)</external-xref>).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB7FF0EAD8F134F43B9473607B32EEC5B"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Other uses of revenues</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After compliance with subsection (a), the Secretary shall use forest active management revenues—</text><paragraph id="H2841E666023240B3BC3BEE2FE7CF12E7"><enum>(1)</enum><text>to make deposits into the fund established under section 3 of the Act of June 9, 1930 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/576b">16 U.S.C. 576b</external-xref>; commonly known as the Knutson-Vandenberg Fund), and the fund established under section 14(h) of the National Forest Management Act of 1976 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/472a">16 U.S.C. 472a(h)</external-xref>; commonly known as the salvage sale fund) in contributions equal to the monies otherwise collected under those Acts for projects conducted on National Forest System land; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5240A11B8CD84A5BAEEF8739E6ED6AB8"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to cover the cost of project services procured under section 103(d).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4C5CA6F65B744943BD7A370928056B43"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Deposit in general fund of the Treasury</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">After compliance with subsections (a) and (c), the Secretary shall deposit remaining forest active management revenues into the general fund of the Treasury.</text></subsection></section><section id="HEA44FEADC36E49A99F30406B6B3B7ACF"><enum>109.</enum><header>Annual report</header><subsection id="H708F054962234B3290421A3DD0E31018"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 60 days after the end of each fiscal year, the Secretary shall submit to Congress an annual report specifying the following:</text><paragraph id="H1BA898CD829D4BBBA913738B883A92D6"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The annual volume requirement in effect for that fiscal year for each Forest Active Management Area.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H42EE95888F5642B49E904D8F9E52A94B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The volume of board feet actually harvested for each Forest Active Management Area during that fiscal year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC937A1C98A9D456AB557A6A25B94B561"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The average cost of preparation for timber sales for each Forest Active Management Area during that fiscal year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5CB60E578F924A14945263CEE68FD3C5"><enum>(4)</enum><text>The forest active management revenues generated from such sales.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H369536F8068641CDB43AF656320CDA25"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The total amount of 25-percent payments made to States under section 108(a) during that fiscal year for the benefit of beneficiary counties and the amount of forest active management revenues distributed to each beneficiary county.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H4F330587D93F4CA990D3704B6805A40D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Form of report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The information required by subsection (a) to be provided with respect to a Forest Active Management Area shall be presented on a single page.</text></subsection><subsection id="H0F409B88037E41509E1FB192E3681687"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Public availability</header><text>The Secretary shall make each annual report available on the website of the Forest Service.</text></subsection></section></title><title id="H20594EB12832449D9E8284AB18904020"><enum>II</enum><header>Transition of Secure Rural Schools and Community Self-Determination Act of 2000 and 25-percent payments</header><section id="H388AFB892C0E40B88124E2CFC4753D55" commented="no"><enum>201.</enum><header>Prohibition on State retention of portion of 25-percent payments made on behalf of beneficiary counties</header><subsection id="HB6BDEF774A974D38A82FA5464F80C9B9" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment of Act of may 23, 1908</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The sixth paragraph under the heading <quote>FOREST SERVICE</quote> in the Act of May 23, 1908 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/500">16 U.S.C. 500</external-xref>), is amended in the first sentence by striking <quote>situated: <italic>Provided,</italic> That when</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>situated. Beginning on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>FORESTS Act of 2023</short-title>, the State or Territorial legislature may not withhold any of the amount paid under this paragraph from distribution to the county or counties in which the national forest is situated. When</quote>. </text></subsection><subsection id="H53490ED84E644849B65CE91C6A17891D" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Conforming amendment to weeks law</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 13 of the Act of March 1, 1911 (commonly known as the Weeks Law; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/500">16 U.S.C. 500</external-xref>), is amended in the first sentence by striking <quote>situated: <italic>Provided,</italic> That when</quote> and inserting the following: <quote>situated. Beginning on the date of the enactment of the <short-title>FORESTS Act of 2023</short-title>, the State legislature may not withhold any of the amount paid under this section from distribution to the county or counties in which such national forest is situated. When</quote>. </text></subsection></section></title><title id="HF0C4C3A4A4A94A26ABF9C23AA493ED62"><enum>III</enum><header>Stewardship end result contracting authority </header><section id="H8C1A5E95BC3245A9AC44A7FCE60EA538"><enum>301.</enum><header>Maximum authorized duration of stewardship end result contracts</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 604(d)(3)(B) of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591c">16 U.S.C. 6591c(d)(3)(B)</external-xref>) is amended by striking <quote>10 years</quote> and inserting <quote>20 years</quote>.</text></section><section id="HD0B71238946147AE8DD20D1E59F92ADD"><enum>302.</enum><header>Payment of portion of stewardship project revenues to county in which stewardship project occurs</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 604(e) of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591c">16 U.S.C. 6591c(e)</external-xref>) is amended by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HD1599E0FD74244CDB5240D7B1ACCE6D8" style="OLC"><paragraph id="H14453566E06F4ECDB483994C236239C7"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Payment of portion of stewardship project revenues to counties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Of the monies retained under paragraph (2) from an agreement or contract under subsection (b), the Chief or the Director, as the case may be, shall pay 25 percent of the retained monies to the county or counties in which the project site is situated.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="HAB4D5DD6C166475883FFE8E13B4FB15D"><enum>303.</enum><header>Use of contractors to perform environmental analysis in connection with stewardship end result contracting projects</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 604(b) of the Healthy Forests Restoration Act of 2003 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/6591c">16 U.S.C. 6591c(b)</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HC4C4C23A6BAF4BA8826FA77604CAEF92"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by striking <quote>The Chief</quote> and inserting the following:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H3103F10617BC4C7B8ED3754459B2CA80" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HE60ED138844047589D4F9501AD8E0329"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Project authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chief</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HD3900C08CE13419DA7FE842E3C67BA2D"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by adding at the end the following new paragraph:</text><quoted-block display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H4AC1279AA84440CF85206C0B71EB6936" style="OLC"><paragraph id="HFFD0FF52AEA54D659E4825F6A2226FE8"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Related project preparation authority</header><subparagraph id="H16A640F154C643D4ACB9972C93F9B9A5"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">As part of an agreement or contract under paragraph (1) for a stewardship contracting project, or as a separate agreement or contract in connection with one or more stewardship contracting projects, the Chief or Director may procure the services of persons who are not Federal employees to perform activities necessary to ensure project for compliance with the National Environmental Policy Act of 1969 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/4331">42 U.S.C. 4331 et seq.</external-xref>) and the Endangered Species Act of 1973 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/16/1531">16 U.S.C. 1531 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCC12774CA19F43B189E8E8F8DCB87FB0"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Approval requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Services performed under this paragraph are subject to approval by the Chief, Director, or other responsible official of the Forest Service or Bureau of Land Management.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HCB156F49280D4039902CC23AD28BCE6C"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Funding sources</header><text>The offset authority provided by subsection (d)(4)(A) and receipts available for expenditure under subsection (e)(2)(B) may be used to cover the cost of services procured under this paragraph.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></title><title id="H9BB8F2CE603441A781FB9586599D86EA"><enum>IV</enum><header>Other Matters</header><section id="H4D88F29EC7874AF1B8C1791519302676"><enum>401.</enum><header>Treatment as supplemental funding</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">None of the funds made available to a beneficiary county (as defined in section 101(2) of this Act) or other political subdivision of a State under this Act shall be used in lieu of or to otherwise offset State funding sources for local schools, facilities, or educational purposes.</text></section><section id="H722E73C7D6F946CCAA04ADF9137FD94D"><enum>402.</enum><header>Definition of fire suppression to include certain related activities</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">For purposes of utilizing amounts made available to the Secretary of Agriculture or the Secretary of the Interior for fire suppression activities, including funds made available from the FLAME Fund, the term <term>fire suppression</term> includes reforestation, site rehabilitation, salvage operations, and replanting occurring following fire damage on lands under the jurisdiction of the Secretary concerned or following fire suppression efforts on such lands by the Secretary concerned.</text></section><section id="HB9B4AD35A8DC4D01B763B81EEB3B4A75"><enum>403.</enum><header>Prohibition on certain actions regarding Forest Service roads and trails</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Forest Service shall not remove or otherwise eliminate or obliterate any legally created road or trail unless there has been a specific decision, which included adequate and appropriate public involvement, to decommission the specific road or trail in question. The fact that any road or trail is not a Forest System road or trail, or does not appear on a Motor Vehicle Use Map, shall not constitute a decision.</text></section></title></legis-body></bill> 

