<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H2F85606B7809436DB176138D21692759" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3592 IH: Donut Dollies Congressional Gold Medal Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3592</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230522">May 22, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S001207">Ms. Sherrill</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="D000631">Ms. Dean of Pennsylvania</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="T000460">Mr. Thompson of California</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000305">Ms. Ross</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="R000606">Mr. Raskin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="P000616">Mr. Phillips</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000596">Mrs. Luna</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001301">Mr. Bergman</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="P000620">Ms. Pettersen</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HBA00">Committee on Financial Services</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HHA00">House Administration</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To award a Congressional Gold Medal to members of the Red Cross Supplemental Recreational Activities Overseas (SRAO) program, also known as the <quote>Donut Dollies</quote>, who served honorably during the Vietnam conflict.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HD8333DF0370046C8A7DAB55832369DD3" style="OLC"><section id="HAC2AFCF76B374157B13359D612C8BD0F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as <quote><short-title>Donut Dollies Congressional Gold Medal Act</short-title></quote>. </text></section><section id="H42806C98FCA74E61B21509F217B90B9F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HD35C39FAE4F54F238A59ED806CE85257"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The Vietnam War, (1954–1975), a conflict that pitted the communist Government of North Vietnam and its allies in South Vietnam, known as the Viet Cong, against the Government of South Vietnam, involved thousands of U.S. servicemembers and volunteers over its course. U.S. military advisers, present in small numbers throughout the 1950s, were introduced on a large scale beginning in 1961, and active combat units were introduced in 1965. As early as February 1962, the number of American military forces in Vietnam warranted the assignment of American Red Cross field directors.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2B1B121140074DB785418D7DA0230CA4"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Women were not subject to the Vietnam-era draft, but thousands volunteered. The first American Red Cross Field Directors were sent to South Vietnam in February 1962. The last Red Cross staff members to serve in-country departed in March 1973. Official records indicate that a total of 1,120 women served with the Red Cross in Vietnam during that 11-year period. Of that number, 627 were young women who were part of the organization’s Supplemental Recreation Activities Overseas (SRAO) program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA61FCBDAFEA445719E5EB185FAF55407"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Based on Red Cross estimates, around 280,500 servicemen took part in these recreation programs and the women, affectionately known as <quote>Donut Dollies</quote>, traveled 27,000 miles by jeep, truck, airplane, and helicopter every month. Red Cross officials estimate that, during the seven years the program was in operation, the women logged over 2,125,000 miles. The first SRAO unit opened at Danang in September 1965. Others quickly followed at Bien Hoa, Nha Trang, Cam Ranh Air Force and Army bases, Dian, Quang Tri, Phu Bai, Lai Khe, Dong Tam, Qui Nhon, Xuan Loc, and more. In all, there were 28 SRAO unit locations throughout the country.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H730BAC9760B54F7096AA37A1B5B29C33"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Military commanders expressed high praise for the Red Cross volunteers, calling the services of the organization <quote>indispensable</quote> and <quote>prime factors</quote> in their efforts to maintain the high morale of their men and to look after their welfare. Writing to Red Cross national headquarters in 1968, General William Westmoreland, then commander of the U.S. forces in Southeast Asia, stated, <quote>Serving our men on the battlefields here in Vietnam, the American Red Cross is a hotline to the folks back home, an oasis in the heat of battle, and a comfort during hospitalization.</quote>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E6B70ACCA724F12BA30742B10B76302"><enum>(5)</enum><text>These Red Cross volunteers shared with military personnel the hardship and privation of life in a war zone and were subject to the dangers of war. Many staff were injured. Five American Red Cross workers died in-country. Three of those were women, Hanna E. Crews, Virginia E. Kirsch, and Lucinda J. Richter, all of whom were members of the SRAO program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9F7487E932F4DE7BD4DAD6FC910B45F"><enum>(6)</enum><text>The Donut Dollies volunteered to be sent to the frontlines to support servicemembers directly engaged with the enemy during the Vietnam conflict. The extraordinary efforts of these volunteers throughout the extent of America’s involvement in the Vietnam conflict is deserving of official recognition.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HFFDC4398D7B040AAA662FD0F6E84FF29"><enum>3.</enum><header>Congressional gold medal</header><subsection id="HBA3EC517A8A8443784B8490937587E7B"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Presentation authorization</header><text>The Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President pro tempore of the Senate shall make appropriate arrangements for the presentation, on behalf of the Congress, of a gold medal of appropriate design in commemoration to members of the Red Cross Supplemental Recreational Activities Overseas (SRAO) program, also known as the <quote>Donut Dollies</quote>, who served honorably during the Vietnam conflict.</text></subsection><subsection id="H87BFAB1ADD6F40288F517ECC434AD7CD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Design and striking</header><text>For the purposes of the award referred to in subsection (a), the Secretary of the Treasury (hereafter in this Act referred to as the <quote>Secretary</quote>) shall strike a gold medal with suitable emblems, devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary.</text></subsection><subsection id="H78C73411C86E43099041DE80DF468791"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Smithsonian Institution</header><paragraph id="H8304F08CBB11439BA088857104E62FC7"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Following the award of the gold medal under subsection (a), the gold medal shall be given to the Smithsonian Institution, where it shall be available for display as appropriate and made available for research.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3CC96E6FA08E49B2A610F40CB215BAAF"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is the sense of Congress that the Smithsonian Institution should make the gold medal received under paragraph (1) available for display elsewhere, particularly at other appropriate locations associated with the <quote>Donut Dollies</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H042B920EB58D480CA21DC7D137F953C6" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Sense of Congress</header><text>It is the sense of the Congress that the United States Mint should expedite production of the gold medal under this Act, so that the service and sacrifice of <quote>Donut Dollies</quote> volunteers can be recognized and honored in a timely manner.</text></subsection></section><section id="H637CA1D1136C4B8BAF8FB2CD111CBE16"><enum>4.</enum><header>Duplicate medals</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">The Secretary may strike and sell duplicates in bronze of the gold medal struck pursuant to section 3, at a price sufficient to cover the cost thereof, including labor, materials, dies, use of machinery, and overhead expenses.</text></section><section id="HCECB67C7C1E2406FB9014015C94EF65F"><enum>5.</enum><header>Status of medals</header><subsection id="H7DB37152752E453DBCAB88D5C6D6BA1F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>National medals</header><text>The medals struck pursuant to this Act are national medals for purposes of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/31/51">chapter 51</external-xref> of title 31, United States Code.</text></subsection><subsection id="H2C237DAA07B74DDD94FF141A46A20691"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Numismatic items</header><text>For purposes of section 5134 of title 31, United States Code, all medals struck under this Act shall be considered to be numismatic items.</text></subsection></section><section id="H387C140A1BB444CBB3D5CF89C11BD6A4" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>6.</enum><header>Authority to use fund amounts; proceeds of sale</header><subsection id="H7226811726D6488BB5DE7B3971654149"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Authority To use fund amounts</header><text>There is authorized to be charged against the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund such amounts as may be necessary to pay for the costs of the medals struck under this Act.</text></subsection><subsection id="H4DACCFD095C645929A3A5AA12AA7DFE6"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Proceeds of sale</header><text>Amounts received from the sale of duplicate bronze medals authorized under section 4 shall be deposited into the United States Mint Public Enterprise Fund.</text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

