<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HB7552646D2DB462594021B492843EA79" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3870 IH: Food Security for All Veterans Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-06-06</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3870</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230606">June 6, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="P000619">Mrs. Peltola</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HVR00">Committee on Veterans' Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 38, United States Code, to direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to submit an annual report on food insecurity among veterans to certain congressional committees, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HF5768C0E4BA2452389AFE5958967BD3B" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H1FB32CC114184873938576CD38A9428A" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Food Security for All Veterans Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H777FDB43DB074C8E8AA91348F3442A2F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Annual report on food insecurity among veterans</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Subchapter II of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/38/5">chapter 5</external-xref> of title 38, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section (and conforming the table of sections at the beginning of such chapter accordingly):</text> 
<quoted-block style="USC" id="HC01D81CB5AA948418C6B74BEBC30F448" display-inline="no-display-inline"> 
<section id="H4BAE8B30BBDC49F98308FDB82E5F65C8"><enum>534.</enum><header>Annual report on food insecurity among veterans</header> 
<subsection id="HB102A88A7E4D47639472286A1712ACE4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Annual report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary, in coordination with the Secretary of Agriculture, shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees an annual report on veteran food insecurity. Each such report shall include data on the following:</text> <paragraph id="HDB1560B4A5F848B289F62B51ABCBC889"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The socioeconomic and racial characteristics of veterans experiencing food insecurity, disaggregated by State in which the veteran is located, Indian tribe (if applicable), age, service-connected disability rating, racial or ethnic group, gender, gender identity, and sexual orientation.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H9FEC8925DAC041369E679907286D85B9"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Native American veterans experiencing food insecurity.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H02120EA58D354386A0EF28D7F3E5AC0D"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Specific interventions for veterans who screen positive for food insecurity, including the number of—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H696D30E3BC004FD0995FEB463C3C58AE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>personnel from the Department who have received specific training in screening veterans for food insecurity;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4715AA7684474C09B2CC7ADCC7C0D944" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>referrals completed by a social worker, nutritionist, dietician, or other personnel of the Department for veterans who screen positive as food insecure, disaggregated by facility of the Department from which such veterans were referred; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9A9242491B534BC6AFA635CE44138F1E"><enum>(C)</enum><text>veterans who screen positive as food insecure who were provided information regarding the supplemental nutrition assistance program and other Federal nutrition assistance programs.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H63E6E08BBB93496B9040D32F786BBC00"><enum>(4)</enum><text>Each referral described in paragraph (3)(B), including the number of such referrals that were completed.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF5032D7118034AB9BFD6CF081A177B4F"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Eligibility screenings for participation in the supplemental nutrition assistance program completed by personnel of the Department. </text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2F8B402C48BB42C9B8D1A2FD92D8D295"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The number of applications for participation in the supplemental nutrition assistance program completed with assistance from personnel of the Department. </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H697592650A8544A9922F7E0371D30FA3" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Measurable outcomes for veterans who participate in the supplemental nutrition assistance program or other Federal nutrition assistance programs, including food security status, health outcomes, and other measures of well-being.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H481C797ACA4F4B318C09992C829DA130"><enum>(8)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Coordination efforts between State agencies, facilities of the Department and the Department of Agriculture located in that State, and veteran service organizations regarding outreach to veterans to participate in the supplemental nutrition assistance program.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H4A36C32AAD3341E39E1B94AF80F23C13"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text> <paragraph id="H41AFB08E3FF442FF8BF59E2C678B89DB"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means the following:</text> 
<subparagraph id="HBDEEAB9EAA5E4B5882FD2A447AB9B168"><enum>(A)</enum><text>The Committee on Agriculture of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HCE07A5BF25AB4224912B8A9574E927BC"><enum>(B)</enum><text>The Committee on Agriculture, Nutrition, and Forestry of the Senate.</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H9314B1E525534BF999BE667BE8D8A33D"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the House of Representatives.</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H58D9C40BA13E4AE7B216A7C36F0A4C4B"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Committee on Veterans’ Affairs of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HC3E81B1B0A344B5AA652D2AF65513DF7" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Indian tribe</quote> has the meaning given such term in section 4 of the Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/25/5304">25 U.S.C. 5304</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HB0D1C57C13694CE1A41860884629B07F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>The terms <quote>Native American</quote> and <quote>Native American veteran</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 3765 of this title.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H126464A659D54C489256A6F3AE97A336" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The terms <quote>State agency</quote> and <quote>supplemental nutrition assistance program</quote> have the meanings given those terms in section 3 of the Food and Nutrition Act of 2008 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/2012">7 U.S.C. 2012</external-xref>). </text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section> </legis-body></bill>

