<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H4022B587696D48E8AD6CFB6F49E9BC5C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>85 HR 1791 IH: Classified Documents Accountability Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-03-24</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1791</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230324">March 24, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="Q000023">Mr. Quigley</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="L000585">Mr. LaHood</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Accountability</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HJU00">the Judiciary</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 18, United States Code, to provide civil penalties for unauthorized removal and retention of classified documents or material, to amend <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, to include a certification process for Presidential records, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H2CEB6571083645939CDD0B3125AB76BC" style="OLC"><section id="HC040211DBC224BD3A17895CA504B2BBE" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Classified Documents Accountability Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H2260680F6D934BCBA32EB26B3863C6FC"><enum>2.</enum><header>Civil penalties for unauthorized removal and retention of classified documents or material</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 1924 of title 18, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HFA7126DC453E47D48C3BD1DD04DD34CE" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subsection id="H0EB3C84682C3442A99D2D23B3C6AC0BF"><enum>(d)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Attorney General may bring a civil action in the appropriate United States district court against any person who violates this section and, upon proof of such violation by a preponderance of the evidence, such person shall be subject to pay a civil penalty in an amount not to exceed $500,000 for each such violation. The imposition of a civil penalty under this subsection does not preclude any other criminal or civil statutory, common law, or administrative remedy, which is available by law to the United States or any other person.</text></subsection><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></section><section id="H75FEFE262EAB4A79922C333937995E8C"><enum>3.</enum><header>Certification requirement</header><subsection id="H787DF3F9884C433B9698A9DEEA0BF8BC"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">Chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new section:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H763B48045AEF40C19848CC703A875FFB"><section id="H8E0872D889754C83B24C59D1F5D81E05"><enum>2210.</enum><header>Certification of Presidential records</header><subsection id="H1DE0722EA03248CCA0A01CAFF69822F2"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Requirement for Archives representative</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There shall be an officer or employee from the National Archives and Records Administration present in the Executive Office of the President and the Office of the Vice President to ensure proper logging and handling of Presidential records and Vice-Presidential records, as applicable.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9789D061090448ACB98C4E219B925D5D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Certification process</header><paragraph id="HFE243BE55B9C475881453161A27ACD1D"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Screening by Archives</header><text>Any record of the President and Vice President shall be screened for classified material by the National Archives and Records Administration during the Presidential transition and shall be retained by the National Archives and Records Administration.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDBD0E2E92FD84DCA9DE2DADC8168E51D" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Certification required</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than the first day of a term of office of an incoming Presidential administration, the outgoing President and the Vice President, or a designee of the President and the Vice President, shall certify to the Archivist and the Attorney General whether outgoing President and Vice President have retained any classified records. This paragraph does not apply to a second consecutive term of a President.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HF3BDD73EEE6B4EA7BEEA1ACD97C00B7C" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Penalties for noncompliance</header><text>Beginning on such first day and ending on the date the certification under subsection (b)(2) is so submitted, an outgoing President or Vice President, or a designee of the outgoing President or Vice President, who fails to submit the certification shall be subject to the following, as determined by the Archivist:</text><paragraph id="HFC8135E98B8F450B8BEAF0557C41379D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>No Federal funds may be obligated or expended for office space, staff, or the travel of such outgoing President or Vice President, including any funds authorized under the Former Presidents Act of 1958 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/85/745">Public Law 85–745</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H193241BD9F7B454EBDC5843CC8E2AB4C"><enum>(2)</enum><text>A reduction of up to 50 percent in the monthly payment of any pension payment dispersed to such outgoing President or Vice President under such Act or chapter 83 or 84 of title 5 (as the case may be).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H0F8499AE331247EA81C2DCA3C6133AE8"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H4D44C496514C460B83F0E0E567DE1F7A" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Federal agency</header><text>The term <term>Federal agency</term> has the meaning given that term in section 2901. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H4B0A0AA7D0E94324B32318FE32C5A782"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Presidential transition</header><text>The term <term>Presidential transition</term> means the period of time that begins on the day on which the Administrator of General Services declares an apparent winner of the Presidential election and ends on the day on which the winner of the Presidential election is inaugurated as President.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H205057D9FAA54AF0A8F7D8E6F2B18543"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Records</header><text>The term <term>records</term>—</text><subparagraph id="HC16D0A624F1C421AA3D7E983EEC38C7A"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes all recorded information, regardless of form or characteristics, made or received by a Federal agency under Federal law or in connection with the transaction of public business and preserved or appropriate for preservation by that agency or its legitimate successor as evidence of the organization, functions, policies, decisions, procedures, operations, or other activities of the United States Government or because of the informational value of data in them; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB0FE05A9C58E450E9F1B5ABB0478AF5E"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">does not include library and museum material made or acquired and preserved solely for reference or exhibition purposes.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="HFBEDAA933F9748E0BD31AE719408F2A2"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/44/22">chapter 22</external-xref> of title 44, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following new item:</text><quoted-block style="USC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H9F928729BA1043E8A98C696828A309D9"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="item">2210. Certification of presidential records.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="H9A37EF44AB0A4238B7C357D22923857C"><enum>4.</enum><header>Clarification</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Nothing in this Act, or any amendment made by this Act, shall be construed to effect or otherwise alter any whistleblower protections afforded individuals under title 5, United States Code, or any other provision of law. </text></section></legis-body></bill> 

