<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H56F10B90F1A042CD8D2B46B869DC5CD7" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 1004 IH: Promoting Public Health Information Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-02-14</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 1004</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230214">February 14, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="D000197">Ms. DeGette</sponsor> (for herself and <cosponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To establish the Public Health Information and Communications Advisory Committee for purposes of providing recommendations and reports, and to support educational initiatives on communication and dissemination of information during public health emergencies.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H722B95AF245044AA80DDC595505C9B7D" style="OLC"><section section-type="section-one" id="HC2B04E6792F7458B93C15AD319E6F386"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Promoting Public Health Information Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section section-type="subsequent-section" id="H45F734C6D8D740F6A4B3282721A6CF8A"><enum>2.</enum><header>Strengthening public health communication</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 319F of the Public Health Service Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/42/247d-6">42 U.S.C. 247d–6</external-xref>) is amended—</text><paragraph id="HD0B86B1707BF4FC0B7831AB0A03F0FBC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">in subsection (b), to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H8987F54A34524645AD3BB37653B4CA14"><subsection id="H6F18FAB382D44C32993BB2AFF7485D94"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Public health information and communications advisory committee</header><paragraph id="H1EEB37D54646448F9BDC7B318AAB7142"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall establish an advisory committee to be known as the Public Health Information and Communications Advisory Committee (referred to in this subsection as the <quote>Advisory Committee</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7484AA0BDA274FD199013C77B371D860"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall make recommendations to the Secretary and report on—</text><subparagraph id="HB41DD0AFAB164D8C94D649729E785D0A"><enum>(A)</enum><text>critical aspects of communication and dissemination of scientific and evidence-based public health information during public health emergencies, including—</text><clause id="H5E993E5F3EA6450FB8D3D171446C7C90"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the role and impact of misinformation on the response to such public health emergencies;</text></clause><clause id="HE85F460BA95A4FD7A3A08CE3012C83B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>the role of risk communication before and during such public health emergencies; and</text></clause><clause id="H84E30574193545CCA548A7D8720800C5"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>other relevant factors, as the Secretary determines appropriate;</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H150C141E9C03420988909CFDF2EF34F0"><enum>(B)</enum><text>information from academic institutions, community-based organizations, and other nongovernmental organizations related to evidence-based or evidence-informed strategies and best practices to effectively communicate and disseminate such information; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H5BAA94BE01C945C69212AD7920CB15E6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>strategies to improve communication and dissemination of scientific and evidence-based public health information to the public, and, as appropriate, to address misinformation during public health emergencies, including strategies to—</text><clause id="H59F2BB96D5504311A777B5BE4E0AF659"><enum>(i)</enum><text>identify the most effective methods for the dissemination of information during a public health emergency; </text></clause><clause id="HFD760F78B92045D7BB7D156922068CFA"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>determine best practices and communicate information to populations that may be impacted by such misinformation; and </text></clause><clause id="H06F9B0A7A1B8437E9D936EE5DD1FA247"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>adapt approaches for the dissemination of information, as appropriate, to address emerging trends related to misinformation.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H0318317E5B08448D8DD8A6EEE6E6E586"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Composition</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall be composed of—</text><subparagraph id="HA645DCBC367B493F9E2640CD386E2358"><enum>(A)</enum><text>appropriate Federal officials, appointed by the Secretary, who shall serve as nonvoting members; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H30A41B52452E4092BECFA3960BB28376"><enum>(B)</enum><text>individuals, appointed by the Secretary, with expertise in public health, medicine, communications, related technology, psychology, national security, and other areas, as the Secretary determines appropriate, who shall serve as voting members.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HB7770B744AE44C0AAFEFE9FD2DFFBCE1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Dissemination</header><text>The Secretary shall review the recommendations of the Advisory Committee and, not later than 180 days after receipt of the report under paragraph (2), shall submit to the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate and the Committee on Energy and Commerce of the House of Representatives a report describing any actions planned by the Secretary related to the communication and dissemination of scientific and evidence-based public health information, including addressing misinformation, as appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE58EC313593438095B141D01FAD242D"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>The Advisory Committee shall terminate 4 years after the date of enactment of the <short-title>Promoting Public Health Information Act</short-title>.</text></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H6BB771890A244101A11B7E0AA4BA04BE"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by redesignating subsection (f) as subsection (g);</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFE4C520EE6034EB29A1369CFC2240904"><enum>(3)</enum><text>by inserting after subsection (e) the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H66F1C39FF53C4CB3A104C86324461CA0"><subsection id="HB49662EC614D49CA814BB6F3EC49DEB2"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Educational initiatives</header><paragraph id="HC4E5C8821D5F45288D5B960EA7662E2B"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary shall award assistance for the development of evidence-based initiatives to promote fact-based public health and medical science information to the public and educate the public on how to identify misinformation, disinformation, and credible information.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9A2604FAD5344A45B973DFA0F89E9E95"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>In developing the initiatives under this subsection, the Secretary shall consult with—</text><subparagraph id="H16E58A18B8384AF89393E3416911B9A3"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Public Health Information and Communications Advisory Committee established under subsection (b);</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HACA7015BDE0B4DB3A4162AB132B48181"><enum>(B)</enum><text>experts in the fields of public health and medicine, communication, technology, behavioral science, and other relevant disciplines as appropriate; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAD44A3833DEA4F8D9D4650F5DE9182AE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>relevant Federal agencies, as appropriate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HE322BE244705404D9E6E032144955B9F"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>The initiatives established under this subsection shall—</text><subparagraph id="H509FB145CCA44804AB3807314D760E47"><enum>(A)</enum><text>be an evidence-based or evidence-informed media and public engagement initiative that includes partnerships with national and local organizations;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HAB99E2DF37F14E279EE0F051F409B7C5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>ensure that official scientific and public health guidance is accessible and communicated effectively to the public with specific focus on populations that are underserved or with low health literacy; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H02436F53C67B48C9A78E044F7574D44A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>ensure that activities are tailored towards subgroups that are being targeted for health misinformation and disinformation, or are especially susceptible to health misinformation and disinformation, in a culturally and linguistically appropriate manner.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><after-quoted-block>; and</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="H8147365581074411AAD1C3125771F65F"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by adding at the end of subsection (g), as so redesignated, the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H1CCD280857A844479C7F50F23C52DC71"><paragraph id="H04A1CC95E7D54C06B9803A95A54ED3C4"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Funding for Advisory Committee and educational initiatives</header><text>There are authorized to be appropriated $45,000,000 for each of fiscal years 2023 through 2027 for purposes of carrying out subsections (b) and (f).</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

