<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" public-private="public" dms-id="HF2BE99608E214A30A92D814BB5D63876">
<metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 3218 IH: Air Traffic Control Tower Replacement Process Report Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-05-11</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code>
<congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session>
<legis-num display="yes">H. R. 3218</legis-num>
<current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber>
<action display="yes">
<action-date date="20230511">May 11, 2023</action-date>
<action-desc><sponsor name-id="C001066">Ms. Castor of Florida</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="F000472">Mr. C. Scott Franklin of Florida</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B001257">Mr. Bilirakis</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001214">Mr. Steube</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001221">Ms. Scholten</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HPW00">Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure</committee-name></action-desc>
</action>
<legis-type>A BILL</legis-type>
<official-title display="yes">To require the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration to report to Congress on the process by which air traffic control tower facilities are chosen for replacement, and for other purposes.</official-title>
</form>
<legis-body id="H9B529275BDC24A499CFBA1868ED2277B">
<section id="HC6ECDC16C6654086AD04A35849E0835F" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Air Traffic Control Tower Replacement Process Report Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HAE71A75BE57046CCB57E35E4A652C17C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Air traffic control tower replacement process report</header> <subsection id="HAB902AFF5E1845889768D4EBA09918E4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report required</header><text>Not later than 120 days after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall submit to Congress a report on the process by which air traffic control tower facilities are chosen for replacement.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="H064F8BD5E0AC42098BB0890A5F0C9E27"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The report required under subsection (a) shall contain—</text> <paragraph id="H3997331C843B4A7DAEAC516F6F6BD8FA"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the process by which air traffic control tower facilities are chosen for replacement, including which divisions of the Administration control or are involved in the replacement decision-making process;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H305387421F0642808863A2C8AF224100"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the criteria the Administrator uses to determine which air traffic control tower facilities to replace, including—</text> <subparagraph id="H494890B297D44D0BAA5F4F54FFF2EC01"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the relative importance of each such criteria;</text></subparagraph>
<subparagraph id="HECAAC4A46FB34F03BCE674E00E608C73"><enum>(B)</enum><text>why the Administrator uses each such criteria; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2319818175B04F24A7F0904307801EB6"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the reasons for the relative importance of each such criteria;</text></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H36116FA0D17848F3A150E1BD1A5F1C0F"><enum>(3)</enum><text>what types of investigation the Administrator carries out to determine if an air traffic control tower facility should be replaced;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H28DF4805FECC46E6876B1439ECFBBFB1"><enum>(4)</enum><text>a timeline of the replacement process for an individual air traffic control tower facility replacement;</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H055CF682748E4745A7AA7DF54B08AB99"><enum>(5)</enum><text>the list of facilities established under subsection (c), including the reason for selecting each such facility; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H824938EC5F594CE5B6AA544BF6EE7BFC"><enum>(6)</enum><text>any other information the Administrator considers relevant.</text></paragraph></subsection>
<subsection id="H7AFB686158C94091AF322A0378B423DF"><enum>(c)</enum><header>List of replaced air traffic control tower facilities</header><text>The Administrator shall establish, maintain, and publish on the website of the Federal Aviation Administration a list of the following:</text> <paragraph id="H5AB15B606A384AFC891647CFCFF33D9D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>All air traffic control tower facilities replaced within the previous 10-year period.</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="H42E637FF6DD7458897B01BE04ED5CE77"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Any such facilities in the process of being replaced.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H2A6AD423BF434E5BB56B9C4D516B6DCB"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Any such facilities under consideration for replacement.</text></paragraph></subsection></section>
</legis-body>
</bill> 


