<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H10E41E503DF7476C975335202CC2E10A" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 6557 IH: To direct the Under Secretary of Defense for Personnel and Readiness to conduct a study on certain grace periods under the Transition Assistance Program of the Department of Defense.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-12-01</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6557</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231201">December 1, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000191">Mr. Neguse</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAS00">Committee on Armed Services</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Under Secretary of Defense for Personnel and Readiness to conduct a study on certain grace periods under the Transition Assistance Program of the Department of Defense.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H09C834B8361143AA9EF0B4224019ABC6" style="OLC"><section id="HC6C7363190574B04A24384DD4212CADB" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Study and report on grace periods under Transition Assistance Program of the Department of Defense</header><subsection id="HF23361A11DFF49EE9571909C2E8FAAAB"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Study</header><text>The Under Secretary of Defense for Personnel and Readiness, in coordination with the heads of other Federal agencies the Under Secretary determines appropriate, shall conduct a comprehensive study on reforms to grace periods under TAP. Such study shall include the following:</text><paragraph id="HFA3ACF5E9B93435BB01F2FE1A0805E87"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">An assessment of the impact of unit tasking on the ability of a covered member to transition to civilian life.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA14B82F63CCA446DB23F2E3D9789733B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A review, disaggregated by military department, of current practices regarding unit tasking during TAP.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8CA5DD12E7E44057BC3215272D845821"><enum>(3)</enum><text>An analysis of each challenge a covered member faces when balancing duty assignments with the requirements to participate in TAP.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC9D4D2528F4C481480E9DD1BB28F4298"><enum>(4)</enum><text>An assessment of such grace periods that allow for unplanned periods of leave, temporary duty, deployments, or other periods when a covered member is unavailable to participate in TAP.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HB85B2D993F334853AA12F26176021000"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Report</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than one year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Under Secretary shall submit to the Committees on Armed Services of the House of Representatives and the Senate a report that includes the following:</text><paragraph id="HE4DD34CB61BC4C2E8D9FBEE0BEE01501"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The findings and conclusions of the Under Secretary based on the study under subsection (a).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H438EB7AC5F834EFE9CCAAD7F6EF126B2"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The recommendations of the Under Secretary whether to reform such grace periods.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H611A656D853D48FDB553D42A67A7BC5C"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The recommendation of the Under Secretary whether a member of an Armed Force, while a covered member, may receive orders only from the command post or headquarters of the unit to which such member is assigned.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2F28C455620B4E89A931095171686CDD"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A comprehensive plan, including proposed timelines, milestones, and resources the Under Secretary determines necessary, to implement such recommendations.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9E2DE6DEFCA946F9BD1D6CABE45104D9"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Any other information or recommendation the Under Secretary determines—</text><subparagraph id="HB4DB8A46651642D285C24B4FF6E348E6"><enum>(A)</enum><text>appropriate; </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4208ABA3C5AA40869BFE43B28B4D5E3E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>would improve TAP; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC5CE63DEA014C82B5F1157C915FED99"><enum>(C)</enum><text>would facilitate a successful transition to civilian life for a covered member.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H463C5E7BC17C4D838CDDA81901743186"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this section:</text><paragraph id="HD0465E3EE6004970810876124C0EFB70"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The term <quote>covered member</quote> means a member of the Armed Forces participating in TAP.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9790F7DFDB9C49029BAE831A2C1767CB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>TAP</quote> means the Transition Assistance Program of the Department of Defense under sections 1142 and 1144, of title 10, United States Code.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H90217448349042A68D6380D3EE0A4F7B" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>unit tasking</quote> means a defined and measurable activity assigned to a unit of an Armed Force by the command post or headquarters of such unit.</text></paragraph></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

