<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HD25BC0821C8045D9ABC6849F694CFD7B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5966 IH: Off-Chain Digital Commodity Transaction Reporting Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-25</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5966</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231017">October 17, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="B001292">Mr. Beyer</sponsor> introduced the following bill</action-desc></action><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231025">October 25, 2023</action-date><action-desc>Referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAG00">Committee on Agriculture</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend the Commodity Exchange Act with respect to reporting digital commodity transactions.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HA9A11C8C15F44D9B81A49EDE34DA1192" style="OLC"><section id="HF554CAEFED7C4FB497A87D445CD351B6" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Off-Chain Digital Commodity Transaction Reporting Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H58BE3A12E01B477C8F73CA82EE913E0B" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Reporting of swaps and digital commodity transactions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Section 2(a)(13) of the Commodity Exchange Act is amended—</text><paragraph id="H1998D273E7F94270B363F3F7EDF979D0" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by amending the paragraph heading to read as follows: <quote><header-in-text level="paragraph" style="OLC">Reporting and public availability of swap and digital commodity transaction data</header-in-text></quote>;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1472D5D4744C4439875B3E0D77016870"><enum>(2)</enum><text>in subparagraph (A), by inserting <quote>or digital commodity</quote> after <quote>swap</quote> both places it appears; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE7602AFEA20C4D209B83FE3976AC4F12"><enum>(3)</enum><text>in subparagraph (B)—</text><subparagraph id="HDAB38E32ADAF4C809488A4B20360F58F"><enum>(A)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>or digital commodity</quote> after <quote>swap</quote>; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H9316FA2E310B4D299FFC7194FF872770"><enum>(B)</enum><text>by inserting <quote>and investor protection</quote> before the period at the end;</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7063A8F7E52440B4ABA1329DAA951812"><enum>(4)</enum><text>by amending subparagraph (G) to read as follows: </text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H87A0A754516B4B388F02648C116EE058" display-inline="no-display-inline"><subparagraph id="H9769588505D0486B87FF64A70C2794F1"><enum>(G)</enum><header>Reporting of swaps and digital commodity transactions to registered repositories</header><clause id="HFE177B4816F04162A887E68FCFE877C6"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Swaps</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each swap (whether cleared or uncleared) shall be reported to a registered swap data repository.</text></clause><clause id="H4827DEA8F7BE413AAC11645ACB83A2F5"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Digital commodities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each contract of sale of a digital commodity in interstate commerce (whether on-chain or off-chain) shall be reported to a registered digital asset repository for transactions.</text></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>;</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph><paragraph id="HB319F00D2C8A45D7B8F2A7AE95CBA529" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="HFECB6D64E94043D5BA9CD4826858C3AB" style="OLC"><subparagraph id="H36EFBD22B97C4139B71F6E07E5AFEA2D" commented="no"><enum>(H)</enum><header>Reporting of digital commodity transactions</header><clause id="HBFAC8D3FFD0D4302A2C984976BC2FB2F"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text>With respect to contracts of sale of digital commodities in interstate commerce that are not executed on or through a trading platform, such transactions shall be reported by the purchaser in real-time to a registered digital asset repository for transactions as soon as technologically practicable after execution of the transaction.</text></clause><clause id="H0E242792F58242159AC95A79E3CB4B84"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Rule for trading platforms</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Trading platforms which facilitate contracts of sale of digital commodities in interstate commerce transactions shall be responsible for reporting all such transactions to a registered digital asset repository of transactions as soon as technically practicable after the execution of each such transaction. </text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA935DF4F7E3645EB87A6308C863DE82D"><enum>(I)</enum><header>Actual delivery of digital commodity transactions</header><clause id="H9A2DA5E4BFFB45D3A7EF9204D254BB45"><enum>(i)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In the case of a contract of sale of a digital commodity in interstate commerce, the seller of such digital commodity shall actually deliver the digital commodity into the exclusive control of the purchaser not less than 24 hours after the transaction is executed. </text></clause><clause id="H9632E95A462240CBBD54D1EC207CE9B4"><enum>(ii)</enum><header>Actual delivery</header><text>For purposes of clause (i), actual delivery shall have occurred only if—</text><subclause id="HFCADCC49CC0A405B962BC313D7D58FCE"><enum>(I)</enum><text>the transfer of the digital commodity from the seller to the purchaser’s address is recorded on the public distributed ledger for the digital commodity; or</text></subclause><subclause id="H1DDA6820E9F9443787C23745AC1EFFC4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>with respect to off-chain digital commodity transactions on a trading platform, the trading platform reports the off-chain digital commodity transaction, which must be held in a customer segregated account, to a registered digital asset repository of transactions. </text></subclause></clause></subparagraph><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></section><section id="H307E38601EFB44B3A7FD8DAABA0C2A3F" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>3.</enum><header>Swap data repositories and digital asset repositories of transactions</header><subsection id="HE2C34EEC866A4CA1ADF2467C9EC54732"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Commodity Exchange Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 21 of the Commodity Exchange Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/24a">7 U.S.C. 24a</external-xref>) is amended to read as follows:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H3672F4059C6D490B8AC3E2C690FB826B"><section id="HAEEDDA6AE9C44FCEA1F13A5E8D9CA394" commented="no"><enum>21.</enum><header>Swap data repositories and digital asset repositories of transactions</header><subsection id="HEF37398A07574A4C9AF82B14116678E3" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Registration requirement</header><paragraph id="HBCD45811016D407C90F0E69BEF6D6176" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Requirement; authority of derivatives clearing organization</header><subparagraph id="H3F72664CE5014408B0F5F52E93A5E722" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>It shall be unlawful for any person, unless registered with the Commission, directly or indirectly to make use of the mails or any means or instrumentality of interstate commerce to perform the functions of a swap data repository or a digital asset repository of transactions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F1240AD6113411589FD4178EF5DA461" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Registration of derivatives clearing organizations</header><text>A derivatives clearing organization may register as a swap data repository.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF435392EA75F4BDF986405091779EEEE" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Inspection and examination</header><text>Each registered swap data repository and digital asset repository of transactions shall be subject to inspection and examination by any representative of the Commission.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HFBDECD495AEE41DA9BC92CE56250312A" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Compliance with core principles</header><subparagraph id="HF9952114CD6C4C56A1EFA680184DA857" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>To be registered, and maintain registration, as a swap data repository or a digital asset repository of transactions, the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions shall comply with—</text><clause id="H2C9968229A394D799211F3F4373C784B" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the requirements and core principles described in this section; and</text></clause><clause id="HE6812AAE017947898C15B1A7BAAC9FC4" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any requirement that the Commission may impose by rule or regulation pursuant to section 8a(5).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H27763B082DC34C7CA90312FA80E06FE8" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Reasonable discretion of repository</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Unless otherwise determined by the Commission by rule or regulation, a swap data repository or a digital asset repository of transactions described in subparagraph (A) shall have reasonable discretion in establishing the manner in which the swap data repository or the digital asset repository of transactions complies with the core principles described in this section.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H8F908CA6E7A942D491623C9440A37754" commented="no"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Standard setting</header><paragraph id="H4E63F68B13C04F59A45227CA1844D5A1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Data identification</header><subparagraph id="HDBA8A2C3285D44A7938CD10C0F406A8A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In accordance with subparagraph (B), the Commission shall prescribe standards that specify the data elements for each swap or digital commodity, digital asset, or digital collectible (as determined a collectible under section 408(m) of the Internal Revenue Code) that shall be collected and maintained by each registered swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions, respectively.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H6BC036BC79494A0388125B5A237F9B6F" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In carrying out subparagraph (A), the Commission shall prescribe consistent data element standards applicable to registered entities and reporting counterparties.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H70E5CA527AF540F59DC5A3FBA1923BCC" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Data collection and maintenance</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall prescribe data collection and data maintenance standards for swap data repositories and digital asset repositories of transactions.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H133F57E93D49415F8BB30CADA8742D3C" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Comparability</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The standards prescribed by the Commission under this subsection shall be comparable to the data standards imposed by the Commission on derivatives clearing organizations in connection with the clearing of swaps or digital commodities, digital assets, or digital collectibles, as appropriate.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA11D1AEF151F436589E16A2A46CD37EE"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consistent standards</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">If a digital asset repository of transactions is jointly registered with the Commission and Securities and Exchange Commission and receives digital commodity, digital asset, and digital collectible transaction data, the Commission shall coordinate with the Securities and Exchange Commission and the Commissioner of the Internal Revenue Service to ensure that the data standards and elements are appropriate and consistent for use by both Commissions and the Internal Revenue Service. </text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H1F87D1C0EF1B43948CEEFBAAC2525B64" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A swap data repository or a digital asset repository of transactions shall—</text><paragraph id="H85F776D4EE0449E68256BF1B29FD61E4" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">accept data prescribed by the Commission for each swap or digital commodity, digital asset, or digital collectible transaction under subsection (b), respectively;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF3CDE368BA8A415ABD14019B4B891C06" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">confirm with both counterparties to the swap or digital commodity, digital asset, or digital collectible transaction the accuracy of the data that was submitted;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H788F5332A4144BB4B918EA01E641BC13" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><text>maintain the data described in paragraph (1) in such form, in such manner, and for such period as may be required by the Commission;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEA64233FE9E04F238A0BE80A6CB61EF3" commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline"><enum>(4)</enum><subparagraph commented="no" display-inline="yes-display-inline" id="H7185DA2FCEB34CABA9BFDBB92F8EF178"><enum>(A)</enum><text>provide direct electronic access to the Commission (or any designee of the Commission, including another registered entity); and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H65785C8A2398454DA94FF9F4922193CB" indent="up1" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>provide the information described in paragraph (1) in such form and at such frequency as the Commission may require to comply with the public reporting requirements contained in section 2(a)(13);</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HA1D8C4DE69D546118AD012BB055C80F5" commented="no"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">at the direction of the Commission, establish automated systems for monitoring, screening, and analyzing swap or digital commodity, digital asset, or digital collectible data, including compliance and frequency of end user clearing exemption claims by individual and affiliated entities;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H24AF1495F9D944D997F258AC8CC1E224" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">maintain the privacy of any and all swap or digital commodity, digital asset, or digital collectible transaction information that the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions, respectively, receives from a swap dealer, counterparty, or any other registered entity;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H700873A259454A75AE68ECC907582951" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">on a confidential basis pursuant to section 8, upon request, and after notifying the Commission of the request, make available each swap or digital commodity, digital asset, or digital collectible data obtained by the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions, respectively, including individual counterparty trade and position data, to—</text><subparagraph id="H17E625BF26E14CF5BEA1D3CA195CC790" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each appropriate prudential regulator;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0285397AF9C14DAA8FB0B332106C84C4" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Financial Stability Oversight Council;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDA31A09C63D9408DA0EACEEBCAA19921" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the Securities and Exchange Commission;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEC5BE959169446ACB6730A756B8C9BB3" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>the Department of Justice; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4DB754BF8BB54684867DFF55E09C5CD5" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>any other person that the Commission determines to be appropriate, including—</text><clause id="H773FE4CF704E4D4E8D75DC831D4D4855" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>foreign financial supervisors (including foreign futures authorities);</text></clause><clause id="H68B6C45B460649F8A7B4724F636785CD" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>foreign central banks;</text></clause><clause id="H5FB398B1BE954A4C9EFE7AA2B291E0A3" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>foreign ministries; and</text></clause><clause id="H2F6D9349941D4ADE88F76E10C805206F" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>other foreign authorities; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H87AB7DE7B47748948C506B3189E3B98F" commented="no"><enum>(8)</enum><text>establish and maintain emergency procedures, backup facilities, and a plan for disaster recovery that allows timely recovery and resumption of operations and the fulfillment of the responsibilities and obligations of the organization.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H214C943E8F9B468B82BE4DB310D6D339" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Confidentiality agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Before the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions may share information with any entity described in subsection (c)(7), the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions shall receive a written agreement from each entity stating that the entity shall abide by the confidentiality requirements described in section 12 of this title relating to information on swap or digital commodity, digital asset, or digital collectible (as determined a collectible under section 408(m) of the Internal Revenue Code), respectively, that is provided.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE2FD0F0DD69F4F489FD2803611B8303E" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Designation of chief compliance officer</header><paragraph id="HB88C47881A534BE1B111385D7C3A0EDF" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Each swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions shall designate an individual to serve as a chief compliance officer.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H26D643198CB04129BBDFDCDE504D228F" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The chief compliance officer shall—</text><subparagraph id="H059AD0FE69944646B1682F9A4CD7665A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>report directly to the board or to the senior officer of the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H0F8AD4FD32D34FA7A7C4222FA2C36CC5" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>review the compliance of the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions with respect to requirements and core principles described in this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB5516AE718884A6A911EC0F1A3794C3A" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>in consultation with the board of the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions, a body performing a function similar to the board of the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions, or senior officer of the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions resolve any conflicts of interest that may arise;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HFADE1A56CBA64AE2BC44EFBC12E6707B" commented="no"><enum>(D)</enum><text>be responsible for administering each policy and procedure that is required to be established pursuant to this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H03DA18651A92452B92AE6F5FC7460990" commented="no"><enum>(E)</enum><text>ensure compliance with this Act (including regulations) relating to agreements, contracts, or transactions, including each rule prescribed by the Commission under this section;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H7D3E475CB5BC44D39D3FD068DA614567" commented="no"><enum>(F)</enum><text>establish procedures for the remediation of noncompliance issues identified by the chief compliance officer through any—</text><clause id="HB210D14C6196408597E9D10724A572BF" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>compliance office review;</text></clause><clause id="H1DD3990307C3454C96E5F12A340042BA" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>look-back;</text></clause><clause id="H5263E805FDC24CACB00901DF5B224A05" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>internal or external audit finding;</text></clause><clause id="H6C62FAE9FE2140418E7951AB878561CB" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>self-reported error; or</text></clause><clause id="H07A73EB410A24D8CB09BB379EA5BD354" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>validated complaint; and</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1FE807D48FC046AEBE5DDEA9E7F84AF6" commented="no"><enum>(G)</enum><text>establish and follow appropriate procedures for handling, management response, remediation, retesting, and closing of noncompliance issues.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C06228AED3E40D499466D2D9512DDF6" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Annual Reports</header><subparagraph id="H47C89C3905ED482F960D4ECDD49EBCBB" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>In accordance with rules prescribed by the Commission, the chief compliance officer shall annually prepare and sign a report that contains a description of—</text><clause id="H4113683F4E0D4BB69293F942E402C8B0" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>the compliance of the swap data repository or the digital asset repository of transactions, as appropriate, of the chief compliance office with respect to this Act (including regulations); and</text></clause><clause id="H49AB1A3A41BA401CB71DBF078C3E468D" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>each policy and procedure of the swap data repository or the digital asset repository of transactions, as appropriate, of the chief compliance officer (including the code of ethics and conflict of interest policies of the swap data repository or the digital asset repository of transactions, as appropriate).</text></clause></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC17307EDF00F4F20B0AABC6E3182E83A" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Requirements</header><text>A compliance report under subparagraph (A) shall—</text><clause id="HE9A2BFB683294D3BA1AE7BE160418296" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>accompany each appropriate financial report of the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions that is required to be furnished to the Commission pursuant to this section; and</text></clause><clause id="HEF1FE92142294F19B2E20B3571DE9C90" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>include a certification that, under penalty of law, the compliance report is accurate and complete.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H6B94A89099BD4D3AA30D525163BA77E5" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Core principles applicable to swap data repositories and digital asset repositories of transactions</header><paragraph id="H295AE3A1D93543619397BB1D69042AF4" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Antitrust considerations</header><text>Unless necessary or appropriate to achieve the purposes of this Act, a swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions shall not—</text><subparagraph id="HF7AFC8098A83404883F911C8ED2A0FE9" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>adopt any rule or take any actions that result in any unreasonable restraint of trade; or</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB7F61AF14859463D91D7C24122372E0D" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>impose any material anticompetitive burden on the trading, clearing, or reporting of transactions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H1EADBBDDCDF14F249DA73CA62B50BBD1" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Governance arrangements</header><text>Each swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions shall establish governance arrangements that are transparent—</text><subparagraph id="HA9942046E1864DCE8FB1C87EAAD56757" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>to fulfill public interest requirements; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H3F04D528913548E1B1E3D3B663F8178E" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to support the objectives of the Federal Government, owners, and participants.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HF818A1862CB94BC49B8F0DD22DD80934" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Conflicts of interest</header><text>Each swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions shall—</text><subparagraph id="HCCE049861B67455099B25FFED8A72200" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text>establish and enforce rules to minimize conflicts of interest in the decision-making process of the swap data repository or the digital asset repository of transactions; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HC740813DC6C7475B9EE7AB3436FBF879" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>establish a process for resolving conflicts of interest described in subparagraph (A).</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H86E128C55EC14055B6614C9E14DE1E41" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Additional duties developed by the Commission</header><subparagraph id="H5EC2ABA303474B0DAD43338D31B38593" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Commission may develop 1 or more additional duties applicable to swap data repositories or digital asset repositories of transactions.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DB02CC983DA47348903644CFB669724" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Consideration of evolving standards</header><text>In developing additional duties under subparagraph (A), the Commission may take into consideration any evolving standard of the United States or the international community.</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H11348E3FE99C4B94B188DE36CF643D7F" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><header>Additional duties for Commission designees</header><text>The Commission shall establish additional duties for any registered swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions in order to minimize conflicts of interest, protect data, ensure compliance, and guarantee safety and security of the swap data repository or digital asset repository of transactions.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H64D15851877742998B9E2A4F97E24C8B" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Required registration of swap data repositories and digital asset repositories of transactions</header><text>Any person that is required to be registered as a swap data repository or a digital asset repository of transactions under this section shall register with the Commission regardless of whether that person is also licensed as a bank, trust company, money services business, or registered with the Securities and Exchange Commission as a security-based swap data repository, broker-dealer, qualified custodian, or transfer agent.</text></subsection><subsection id="H95D2F9BAF8A6437289B4B89FC0A08B3A"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Dual SEC and CFTC Registration of Digital Asset Repository of Transactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Any person that seeks to act as a digital asset repository for transactions for digital commodities, digital assets, digital collectibles (as determined a collectible under section 408(m) of the Internal Revenue Code) shall register with the Commission and Securities and Exchange Commission subject to joint regulation by such Commissions, but only with respect to the digital commodities and digital assets subject to their respective jurisdictions.</text></subsection><subsection id="H5E7D8D216C7A465E82152084E68B9ADC" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Rules</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Commission shall adopt rules governing persons that are registered under this section.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section><section id="HF4EB69C11251439CB8F19357DF9C2A06"><enum>4.</enum><header>Definitions</header><subsection id="HD92B9487A4E74D9BA39806B5F549C295"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1a of the Commodity Exchange Act (7 U.S.C 1a) is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block style="OLC" id="H0D76A800F096448C8DD2143009401AF7"><paragraph id="HE3051D05EA2D4D08AD3E399DAE01F3AE" commented="no"><enum>(52)</enum><header>Digital asset repository of transactions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>digital asset repository of transactions</term> or <term>DART</term> means any person that collects and maintains information or records with respect to transactions or positions in, or the terms and conditions of digital commodities, digital assets, or digital collectibles (as determined a collectibles under section 408(m) of the Internal Revenue Code) entered into by third parties for the purpose of providing a centralized recordkeeping facility for digital commodities, digital assets, or digital collectibles.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HB181C1A00DBC4E07B66B3C76F6431B7B"><enum>(53)</enum><header>Off-chain digital commodity transaction</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>off-chain digital commodity transaction</term> means any contract of sale of a digital commodity in interstate commerce which is not mined or validated and recorded on the appropriate public distributed ledger for such digital commodity within 24 hours of the transaction being entered into.</text></paragraph><after-quoted-block>. </after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H1C5F26242B6B4554BB1E925A716A4BF5"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Definition of registered entity</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Section 1a(40)(E) of the Commodity Exchange Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/7/1a">7 U.S.C. 1a(40)(E)</external-xref>) is amended by inserting <quote>or a digital asset repository of transactions</quote> after <quote>section 21</quote>. </text></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

