<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H9CB7091E257F4A9884822858BE6CB309" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5555 IH: DMEPOS Relief Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-09-19</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5555</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20230919">September 19, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</sponsor> (for herself, <cosponsor name-id="T000469">Mr. Tonko</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="H001091">Mrs. Hinson</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HIF00">Committee on Energy and Commerce</committee-name>, and in addition to the Committee on <committee-name committee-id="HWM00">Ways and Means</committee-name>, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services to provide for certain adjustments to Medicare payment for items of durable medical equipment that were formerly included in round 2021 of the DMEPOS competitive bidding program.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H20B9C571A8564704A496E394B57CF2B8" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4CEC4B22B3404715B61CC1C8FE2BF021" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>DMEPOS Relief Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>DRA of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H7866FFA81842468CA63BA75EDA1BDC79"><enum>2.</enum><header>Adjustments to medicare payment for items of durable medical equipment formerly included in round 2021 of the DMEPOS competitive bidding program</header> <subsection id="H08969C856B96457CA5C339B512903790"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The Secretary of Health and Human Services shall implement section 414.210 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations, such that the fee schedule amounts determined pursuant to such section for covered items furnished during the period beginning on January 1, 2024, and ending on December 31, 2024, shall be applied as if the transition rules under paragraph (g)(9) of such section provided that for such covered items so furnished, the fee schedule amount for the area involved is equal to 90 percent of the adjusted payment amount established under such section and 10 percent of the unadjusted fee schedule amount established under such section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H97FF991DED7C4D2FAF29D50921615713"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Covered item defined</header><text>For purposes of subsection (a), the term <quote>covered item</quote> means any item—</text> <paragraph id="H6488C66783FF4CB89D079CC4E098C78C"><enum>(1)</enum><text>that were competed under the Round 2021 DMEPOS Competitive Bidding Program;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HA658A4AE6EFA42E286DD1606FC1CA4B1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>for which contracts were not executed for such round of bidding; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H54720199851143E6BC89FBD427302FBE"><enum>(3)</enum><text>which did not, as of January 1, 2021, revert to the unadjusted fee schedule amount established under section 414.210 of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="H1D312ACFF0AC42EE8696B6DD6D623532"><enum>3.</enum><header>Payment rates for durable medical equipment in DMEPOS non-competative bidding areas under the medicare program</header> 
<subsection id="H88117706B8164EE8B928D377BA0F95ED"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Areas other than rural and noncontiguous areas</header><text>The Secretary shall implement section 414.210(g)(9)(v) of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation), to apply the transition rule described in the first sentence of such section to all applicable items and services furnished in areas other than rural or noncontiguous areas (as such terms are defined for purposes of such section) through December 31, 2024.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H8ADAB9D01DC14EDCBF916DCEAE383989"><enum>(b)</enum><header>All areas</header><text>The Secretary shall not implement section 414.210(g)(9)(vi) of title 42, Code of Federal Regulations (or any successor regulation) until January 1, 2025.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7B3B47ED029F4787B8399513FE392996"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Implementation</header><text>Notwithstanding any other provision of law, the Secretary may implement the provisions of this section by program instruction or otherwise.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

