<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H11221C40B391410A9E272C0175C68E0C" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>118 HR 5879 IH: Drone Research and Innovation for Law Enforcement Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-10-03</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5879</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231003">October 3, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="N000026">Mr. Nehls</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H001095">Mr. Hunt</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="F000475">Mr. Finstad</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="G000591">Mr. Guest</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="D000230">Mr. Davis of North Carolina</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="H001077">Mr. Higgins of Louisiana</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S001212">Mr. Stauber</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HSY00">Committee on Science, Space, and Technology</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To amend title 49, United States Code, to permit small, unmanned aircraft pilot research for public safety, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H18DA35EF85064BB6BC039233DD7B7D52" style="OLC"><section id="HDBDA4425104A44CE95013F7BB1313E76" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Drone Research and Innovation for Law Enforcement Act of 2023</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H0CB27C1E286B4CB39F26E006A26FE1EF" section-type="subsequent-section"><enum>2.</enum><header>Small unmanned aircraft pilot research for public safety</header><subsection id="H1B629792876442C5AAC322DB0E9F8981"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/448">Chapter 448</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following:</text><quoted-block id="H1D883E590FF44B08BEE276A19BBD654B" style="USC"><section id="H5E6B39CF076242FAB10B3A4E756D16CB"><enum>44811.</enum><header>Small unmanned aircraft pilot research for public safety</header><subsection id="HD5FA0578C5B64EF09F0A706E9FD10373"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Prohibition regarding weapons</header><text>The prohibition regarding unmanned aircraft armed with dangerous weapons under section 363 of the FAA Reauthorization Act of 2018 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/49/44802">49 U.S.C. 44802</external-xref> note) is reaffirmed.</text></subsection><subsection id="H9904D363CED0464FAD13A90443E7CE70"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Pilot research program</header><paragraph id="HA7056DF4FE5E4FA282EC467D497A8EEC"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 3 months after the date of enactment of this section, the Administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration shall initiate a pilot research program to study the potential use of non-lethal de-escalation unmanned aircraft by law enforcement agencies.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28B52FFCECDA45889DAA818FB0DCAF2C"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Contents</header><text>The study required under subsection (b) shall address—</text><subparagraph id="H1614E5E0BD7A41A0860CB520C47F8B0E"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the process of assessing and validating conducted energy devices or other non-lethal de-escalation equipment that may be attached to unmanned aircraft;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H10BB4395771C484EBFE8DF64CC50E70E"><enum>(B)</enum><text>training protocols for law enforcement and agents of the Administration; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB00A4E2B778E40E4B2084A6B35E5516C"><enum>(C)</enum><text>operational and safety protocols for operators of non-lethal de-escalation unmanned aircraft and agencies directly overseeing the operation of such unmanned aircraft.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H40E8744461C44ED0A9A9DD82EBB9993B"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Partnerships</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall enter into interagency agreements with the Departments of Justice, Department of Homeland Security, and State large metropolitan and rural law enforcement agencies with regard to the pilot research program established under this subsection. The Administrator shall designate the Center of Excellence for Unmanned Aerial Systems designated under section 44814, in collaboration with Federal, State, and large metropolitan law enforcement as well as rural law enforcement training facilities, as the location for such program.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H1136F34D03A346C2AEE099ECEDF18F9C"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Consultation</header><text>The Administrator shall solicit input from, and coordinate with, relevant stakeholders as appropriate in carrying out the pilot research program established under this subsection.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC84FA8C31CA84EDDAF69683B0B87420E"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Report</header><text>Not later than 2 years after the date of enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation a report on the results of the pilot research program that includes a plan outlining a proposed process through which a law enforcement applicant to such program may seek permission from the Administrator to operate non-lethal de-escalation unmanned aircraft.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HAD7FFD09EAC048E18B622C913DEFBA72"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Rulemaking</header><text>Not later than 90 days after submitting the report set required under subsection (b)(5), the Administrator shall initiate a rulemaking to create a process through which the Administrator may provide approval to operate non-lethal de-escalation unmanned aircraft.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD7B1EB4E50634D758146836C266419D7"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Manufacturing requirement</header><text>Any non-lethal de-escalation unmanned aircraft used under the pilot research program may be manufactured in the United States, as defined by the Federal Trade Commission under part 323 of title 16, Code of Federal Regulations.</text></subsection><subsection id="H78968AE574C34DD7B7A7B9FA5B3B8F87"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Definitions of non-Lethal de-Escalation unmanned aircraft</header><text>In this section:</text><paragraph id="H75BC97BDC43C48928F0250EAB1A89A38"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Non-lethal de-escalation unmanned aircraft</header><text>The term <quote>non-lethal de-escalation un- manned aircraft</quote> means an unmanned aircraft equipped with 1 or more non-lethal weapons or devices that is—</text><subparagraph id="H26CCE3A27287466DA09EB9AB7E6C737D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>used by law enforcement personnel in scenarios that present significant risk to human life, including the life of law enforcement personnel, captives, uninvolved individuals, the public, or a suspected criminal; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HA90571B5DD48443E9AD5E149C20C164B"><enum>(B)</enum><text>in which the suspected criminal is in an position through which he or she could potentially escalate the situation and expose human life to a high level of risk.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H70E923FF03FE4E81AB9EDF54A68966C1"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Non-lethal weapon</header><text>The term <quote>non-lethal weapon</quote> has the meaning given the term in used in DOD Directive Number 300.03E, issued on August 31, 2018, by the Department of Defense.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection><subsection id="H91417D2FF69843998D356E1D5B6160A1"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Clerical amendment</header><text>The analysis for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/448">chapter 448</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code, is amended by adding at the end the following: </text><quoted-block style="USC" id="HD2C4BFA761004ADAB91ECA07E24EFB02" display-inline="no-display-inline"><toc regeneration="no-regeneration"><toc-entry level="section">‘44811. Small unmanned aircraft pilot research for public safety.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></subsection></section></legis-body></bill> 

