<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H3C39B101DFF74D5CA44B63870943F62D" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>117 HR 6424 IH: Supporting Innovative Global Health Technologies Act of 2023</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2023-11-15</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">118th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 6424</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20231115">November 15, 2023</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="F000466">Mr. Fitzpatrick</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="H001085">Ms. Houlahan</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S000168">Ms. Salazar</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HFA00">Committee on Foreign Affairs</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide additional authorities for the leadership of the United States Agency for International Development in health technology innovation for global health in low-resource settings, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H0EAD2C30A6194DD9AAB6AF86F375886A" style="OLC"><section id="H871731DF607E470DBFD01CEC31E219FA" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Supporting Innovative Global Health Technologies Act of 2023</short-title></quote> or the <quote><short-title>SIGHT Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="H154D22DA047D4F3CBC37C98FA435AEE3"><enum>2.</enum><header>Findings</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Congress finds the following:</text><paragraph id="HC2EB2999E29E42D7AC7D153959A558E8"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Agency for International Development has a unique role in the research and development of health technologies for global health that complements the work of other departments and agencies of the United States Government, having both an advantage and unique mandate for development of health technologies for use in low-resource settings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H599EEFA80D2D4A5FBE603727070403BB"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">It is in the national interest of the United States to build greater country capacity for research and development of new health technologies in low and middle-income countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H265EE092D1244221A9A597135F68950B"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Investments by the United States Government in global health research and development should be coordinated with and leverage investments from partner country governments, other government donors, and the private sector. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD8D2BC1869C84373A119D8499A89A34E"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Human immunodeficiency virus, tuberculosis, malaria, neglected tropical diseases, emerging infectious diseases (such as COVID–19, Ebola, and Zika), and many other health conditions (such as complications in pregnancy) have a disproportionate public health burden in low- and middle-income countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3F43B30B21394DF0B6951BB174E2E7E5"><enum>(5)</enum><text>Health technologies that were developed for use in high-income countries often cannot be implemented in low-resource settings in low- and middle-income countries or require adaptation to be effective.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H466DB0029E4A41508289D73CA4A03B72"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Due to poverty or to low incidence, many neglected tropical diseases and emerging infectious diseases either lack or have limited commercial markets to drive health technology innovation.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H28980A1F08784D72B4FE23141DF1AB15"><enum>(7)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Achieving the ambitious goals set through initiatives such as the President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief (commonly referred to as <quote>PEPFAR)</quote> and the President’s Malaria Initiative (commonly referred to as <quote>PMI</quote>) will not be possible without the development and scale-up of new health technologies designed for use in low-resource settings, which are needed to address both long-standing endemic diseases and prepare for potential pandemic threats.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59B41AA7E7E64A4D829116BEC0A03FD9"><enum>(8)</enum><text>Public funding has proven highly successful at incentivizing the development of health technologies for global health that are high-impact, accessible, and cost-saving.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H21C21220C2E640909047658104F9744C"><enum>(9)</enum><text>COVID–19 has demonstrated the importance of global access to health technologies designed for low-resource settings.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H92B08589EFE14A89918449D26B7FC059"><enum>(10)</enum><text>Support for the development of accessible health technologies for low-resource settings can have reciprocal value and produce tools that reduce health care costs, improve public health, and strengthen health security for the United States.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H17D295B5261340458741875C35F5F687"><enum>(11)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">For decades, the United States Agency for International Development has been a catalyst in the global health innovation ecosystem. While other Federal departments and agencies, including the National Institutes of Health, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, and the Department of Defense, provide support for global health technologies, the United States Agency for International Development is the only Federal agency that provides broad support for the late-stage development of new health technologies to combat neglected tropical diseases and emerging infectious diseases and other health conditions for low-resource settings specifically. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6F9C23A9FE5C4198A38DB830DFB6C556"><enum>(12)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">While the need for new tools to tackle disease threats has grown, in recent years, investments by the United States Agency for International Development in research and development have shrunk as a proportion of its overall global health spending, squeezed by both stagnant budgets and growing needs. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2BBDA290F597411B983E6ED1B77BFA01"><enum>(13)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Innovation at the United States Agency for International Development is primarily supported from siloed disease- and population-specific appropriations accounts, resulting in the limitation of its ability to seek shared value across health sectors or health threats.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7C8E1CF87F30484EB06AB43A11773EB1"><enum>(14)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The United States Agency for International Development is compelled to prioritize support for immediate program needs with imperfect tools at the expense of support for technologies that can improve clinical effectiveness, increase access to care, save costs, and build capacity and ownership by partner countries.</text></paragraph></section><section id="H4A87543CD56F49CB862052980EE83C91"><enum>3.</enum><header>Statement of policy</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">It is the policy of the United States that—</text><paragraph id="H1A5E65296B9747CCB23700E4D11373C5"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">research and development for new health technologies is essential for the success of the global health programs of the United States Government, by providing for the improved effectiveness, cost-effectiveness, and sustainability of such programs; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7F9A613D6E6E48728108C05069B8D80B"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">funding and other support for global health research and development under this Act shall be additional and complementary to, and may not replace, displace, or otherwise compromise, funding otherwise provided for existing and ongoing global health research and development of the United States Government or activities relating to the implementation of the global health programs of the United States Government.</text></paragraph></section><section id="HE43FEAD28FFD401BB867BB62BE019CFA"><enum>4.</enum><header>Chief Innovation Officer for Health</header><subsection id="H643A88D00F9C49ADA7B8E902ACA99FA4"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There is established within the Bureau for Global Health of the Agency the position of Chief Innovation Officer for Health. Such position is at the level of Deputy Assistant Administrator or equivalent.</text></subsection><subsection id="H7A4769FA4CFD4ACEA8A2994B34167530"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appointment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall appoint the Chief Innovation Officer for Health from among such individuals as the Administrator determines have relevant experience within private sector industry and an expert understanding of health finance and of the research, development, testing, evaluation, deployment, and implementation of new health technology.</text></subsection><subsection id="H29CB66F602774A87847BA36648147864"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Relationship to Assistant Administrator for Global Health</header><text>The Chief Innovation Officer for Health shall—</text><paragraph id="HFCD93A3A24724F01B22D54B34394534A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">serve as the principal advisor to the Assistant Administrator for Global Health on global health research and development necessary to meet the requirements of the United States Government and the governments of partner countries for improving global health; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H981691142EE14FBEB374EDDA7A37A22F"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">report directly to the Assistant Administrator for Global Health.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H11240C8881BD471C9D1424C32A7E751C"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Duties</header><text>The Chief Innovation Officer for Health shall be responsible for the following:</text><paragraph id="HADD0D11236E54911AF32A94228BC4073"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Ensuring cross-sector, Agency-wide cooperation, support, and programming for global health research and development, for the purpose of increasing the effectiveness of international development programs of the Agency and supporting the foreign policy and development goals of the United States Government.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H3A3647A579674D37AD7E507A49ABAC86"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Drawing on the expertise of other departments and agencies of the United States Government and of nongovernmental organizations (including affected communities and institutions in low- or middle-income countries, businesses, health and science research organizations, and institutions of higher education) that pursue global health-related research and development, to identify the most pressing requirements for the development of health technologies to improve global health and programs of the Agency relating to global health. </text></paragraph><paragraph id="HF238719D10B64041BD47BBC85F12C813"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Leveraging research and investments by other elements of the Agency, other departments and agencies of the United States Government, and nongovernmental organizations (including businesses, health and science research organizations, institutions of higher education, and governments or other institutions of partner countries) to support the research and development of new health technologies by the Chief Innovation Officer of Health.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5A87DEA5DD05429A94F3F379F2E4D196"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Administering the processes for the award of grants, entry into partnerships, and joint establishment of other arrangements, to support global health research and development (including by administering the grant program under <internal-xref idref="H2D48FEC794E74227A23A95D563663CAB" legis-path="7.">section 7</internal-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H7732DC262CCF4570A1BC1962305C5835"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Serving as the Chairperson of the Global Health Research and Development Advisory Council established under <internal-xref idref="H60B6AA43DC5A462C9BB003F8D393D31E" legis-path="5.">section 5</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD604EAC1826C48DF8C834FD542CDB05F"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Authorities</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Assistant Administrator for Global Health shall take such steps as may be necessary to ensure that the Chief Innovation Officer for Health has sufficient authority within the Bureau for Global Health to carry out the duties under subsection (d).</text></subsection></section><section id="H60B6AA43DC5A462C9BB003F8D393D31E"><enum>5.</enum><header>Global Health Research and Development Advisory Council</header><subsection id="H3B25DE1653124A0C8A0AFA79EAC9A89E"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Establishment</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall establish an advisory council to be known as the <quote>Global Health Research and Development Advisory Council</quote> (in this section referred to as the <quote>Council</quote>).</text></subsection><subsection id="H998CC4A3F803497DA6AB420CC1625FEC"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Membership</header><text>The Council shall be composed of the following:</text><paragraph id="HC4CB0835D0E74FDCA1088AB0B790C617"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Chief Innovation Officer for Health of the Agency under <internal-xref idref="HE43FEAD28FFD401BB867BB62BE019CFA" legis-path="4.">section 4</internal-xref>, who shall serve as the Chairperson of the Council (in this section referred to as the <quote>Chairperson</quote>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HE17BBD946B084CCB94E2863CF611EDE3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Not more than 8 other members appointed by the Administrator from among individuals—</text><subparagraph id="H7436CBE365DD4B3ABAAE7FF56A74C802"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">recommended for such appointment by the Chairperson; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HEDD5EAD28CE04E23A356B4E1090032AE"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">who are scientists or other experts with experience in global health research and development through or on behalf of—</text><clause id="HCE1D58785F4644A58A136874E9822A51"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Agency;</text></clause><clause id="H132E09C540604A15816A54CC44C43ADE"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>any other department or agency of the United States Government;</text></clause><clause id="HC587D534F6B740A88086D029DE140114"><enum>(iii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">affected communities in low- or middle-income countries; and</text></clause><clause id="H3A2C3D1B3D374C2B96341DEBB5D5FF4B"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>nongovernmental organizations, including nonprofit organizations, businesses, and institutes of higher education.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE4B55390A38848C6A9714AE9B8D0ED69"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Terms</header><paragraph id="HFF2D025726E84ABFBCDFBD88DCD621E5"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each member other than the Chairperson shall be appointed for a term of 6 years.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD24C397DAE3049589DF5F1557421DF4E"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Vacancies</header><text>Any member appointed to fill a vacancy occurring before the expiration of the term for which the predecessor of the member was appointed shall be appointed only for the remainder of that term. A vacancy in the Council shall be filled in the manner in which the original appointment was made.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HBDE4F52425E44A3C86F8D47834475955"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Compensation</header><paragraph id="HCF821F07D795406CB814F92CC529BBE8"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Prohibition of compensation of Federal employees</header><text>Except as provided in paragraph (2), members of the Council who are full-time officers or employees of the United States may not receive additional pay, allowances, or benefits by reason of their service on the Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H6C3F092CF0A143EDA28F90D47F674275"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Travel expenses</header><text>Each member of the Council shall receive travel expenses, including per diem in lieu of subsistence, in accordance with applicable provisions under subchapter I of <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/57">chapter 57</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H87607F1E0C2E4A9FB81021091A199194"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Meetings</header><text>The Council shall meet at the call of the Chairperson.</text></subsection><subsection id="HE219A5A6E7014014A790D214208ECE19"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Duties</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Council shall be responsible for advising the Administrator regarding the priorities and objectives for the Agency with respect to global health research and development, including by providing such advice on an individual member basis or as a collective Council, as the Chairperson may direct.</text></subsection><subsection id="HD05646A54BA1463CBB0DF0E14F7CA12E" commented="no"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Nonapplicability of Federal Advisory Committee Act</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline"><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/10">Chapter 10</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, shall not apply to the Council.</text></subsection></section><section id="H590F80F51B324F5C88E735843DD73BDB"><enum>6.</enum><header>Global Health Research and Development program area activities and budget</header><subsection id="HFCA598836CF14E7F81F863DD9A12E083"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall carry out global health research and development activities with respect to new health technologies with the potential to advance the effectiveness and sustainability of the global health programs of the Agency, including the potential to advance—</text><paragraph id="H10B5F6B8280B4E6F81EB7F7E8ECA79AF"><enum>(1)</enum><text>health technologies with characteristics identified or otherwise prioritized by affected communities and partner countries;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H611EC5B2343B43D797EDBDDD4830F91E"><enum>(2)</enum><text>health technologies with characteristics that facilitate introduction and access of the respective technology, to ensure use by those in need; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD93D44053BEF4A84B498399B5512C6F7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>support for capacity-building within partner countries and the transition by such countries to greater country-level ownership, responsibility, and decision-making with respect to global health.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HFDEC21EBFE79432D9704E3E2CC7BFEB7"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Budget</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator shall—</text><paragraph id="HF8421DD0D7F442AA80A54E443B24A546"><enum>(1)</enum><text>not later than 90 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, establish a single, separate budget line for the activities under subsection (a), under which funds authorized to be appropriated or otherwise made available to the Administrator for the purpose of carrying out such activities shall be categorized; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDF66F38B6F714B169E9A19B349E7DAA0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>include information regarding amounts expended and requested to be expended under such budget line in the budget justification materials submitted in support of the budget of the President for any fiscal year beginning on or after the date of such establishment.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="H2D48FEC794E74227A23A95D563663CAB"><enum>7.</enum><header>Grant program for expanded use of global health research and development</header><subsection id="H370265BC08AC4ECDBD829AA8184DA186"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Grant program</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator, acting through the Chief Innovation Officer for Health under section 4, shall carry out a grant program under which the Administrator may award grants on a competitive basis to nongovernmental organizations that are determined eligible by the Administrator.</text></subsection><subsection id="HECAE66AB6FFE44A5890FE551169C75BD"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Use of amounts</header><text>Grant amounts awarded under this section may only be used for the following purposes:</text><paragraph id="H685E8814E777411C8046308387549BE9"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Developing new health technologies designed for use in low-resource settings to improve global health.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H59F84E9BE185480684A3B8AB82750815"><enum>(2)</enum><text>Evaluating and improving the implementation, production, and scale-up of health technologies in low-resource settings in partner countries.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HA6C288F2CEC54A19957E2E194E1E69C8"><enum>(3)</enum><text>Investing in the research capacity of institutions in low- and middle-income partner countries to lead and contribute to the development of health technologies.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HD2E0FAFE4E1C4D9B846EDAB54B1960C1"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Conditions on grant award</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Administrator may not award a grant to an entity under this section unless—</text><paragraph id="H72BBC7995FDE4669988E2C9EAFEF5A4D"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the entity submits to the Administrator a proposal demonstrating sufficient technical standards, as determined by the Administrator, for any of the purposes listed in paragraphs (1) through (3) of subsection (b) for which the entity intends to use such grant amounts;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H41C4603C07504D4CADD60C6C9BFC890A"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the entity agrees, as a condition of such award, to report to the Administrator regarding the use of such grant amounts on a basis that is not less frequent than annually for the duration of the grant period; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HDFD9748324B246FE9F3DB390373F79CF"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the Administrator certifies to the appropriate congressional committees that such award is in compliance with section 3(2) of this Act.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="H48F9DBADDF3E4AD2AFB9A8530717A835"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Additional nature of authority</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The authority to award grants under this section is in addition to, and not in lieu of, any other authority of the Administrator, including any such authority under part I or II of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/22/2151">22 U.S.C. 2151 et seq.</external-xref>).</text></subsection></section><section id="HD48DE8B64DDB47CC9C9CDAF559B0EB8E"><enum>8.</enum><header>Strategy and reports</header><subsection id="H82B3D92CA9894931A27A84C8D8F3872C"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Report on progress</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 180 days after the date of the enactment of this Act, and prior to the submission of the budget justification materials in support of the budget of the President for the first fiscal year following the date of the enactment of this Act, the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees, and publish on a publicly available website of the Agency, a report that contains the following:</text><paragraph id="H7FD452A3A2A34427A21B17A65EA1E9BC"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed description of the status of the Global Health Research and Development Advisory Council under <internal-xref idref="H60B6AA43DC5A462C9BB003F8D393D31E" legis-path="5.">section 5</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5206DB036E0F4C3BB9FDF93940F1E930"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Recommendations by such Global Health Research and Development Advisory Council.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HEF32CBF48AE4400A928DE9A504D410C2"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Solicitations for grant awards under <internal-xref idref="H2D48FEC794E74227A23A95D563663CAB" legis-path="7.">section 7</internal-xref>.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H8A019BE7E3A444B7B061F47C19B0CC13"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Comprehensive accounting of awards and objectives to be included within the annual report to Congress on the health-related research and development strategy of the Agency required pursuant to the Department of State, Foreign Operations, and Related Programs Appropriations Act (or the report accompanying such appropriations bill reported by the Committees on Appropriations of the House or Representatives or Senate) for the respective fiscal year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC137BFCE9E67413D8BB2502A85604250"><enum>(5)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed description of how the planned investments by the Agency in the activities under <internal-xref idref="H0EAD2C30A6194DD9AAB6AF86F375886A" legis-path="6.(a)">section 6(a)</internal-xref> align with the multiyear strategy of the Agency titled <quote>Global Health Research and Development Strategy 2023–2028</quote> and developed pursuant to section 7019(e) of division K of the Consolidated Appropriations Act, 2022 (<external-xref legal-doc="public-law" parsable-cite="pl/117/103">Public Law 117–103</external-xref>).</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H877F6DB6954847DF8C8CB511B5BDC6AE"><enum>(6)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A detailed description of how investments made by the Agency in such activities advance the other health-related programming goals of the Agency.</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="HE43FFA50F50F40E1B4BD4D532F520A0D"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Annual reports</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter for the next 5 years as part of the annual report specified in subsection (a)(4), the Administrator shall submit to the appropriate congressional committees, and publish on a publicly available website of the Agency, a report that contains, with respect to the year covered by the report, the following:</text><paragraph id="H6785CD95C9BB455CA50EA83510857817"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Information on any grants awarded, or other assistance provided, by the Administrator during such year pursuant to an authority under this Act or any other relevant provision of law for the support of global health research and development in support of programs of the Agency.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HC6BEA0BB25D1412F803178E1737633AF"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The primary, secondary, and tertiary purposes of—</text><subparagraph id="H18DE3E8AAED64ED0A3A77C085FABAB8D"><enum>(A)</enum><text>any such grants awarded; and </text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H936B8EA8FDB5480F88AA7AF35CFCEC27"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">any investments in the activities under <internal-xref idref="H0EAD2C30A6194DD9AAB6AF86F375886A" legis-path="6.(a)">section 6(a)</internal-xref> made or proposed by the Administrator during such year.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H2D77F0D362BD49EC9E75FC316F4EF576"><enum>(3)</enum><text>A summary of how affected communities and researchers based in partner countries have been consulted with respect to any such investments.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H2CFDC9CEF5D34D79B61ECCB03D42B7C6"><enum>(4)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">A description of the outcomes and status of the activities under <internal-xref idref="H0EAD2C30A6194DD9AAB6AF86F375886A" legis-path="6.(a)">section 6(a)</internal-xref> carried out or otherwise supported by the Administrator during such year.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H5E93CBDFB57A40A99F76A85D88B4D39B"><enum>(5)</enum><text>An identification of any amounts obligated or expended during such year by the Administrator, from any appropriations account, to support global health research and development. Such information shall be presented both as a summary and in a table delineated by—</text><subparagraph id="H45B538FF7DEE4D489D525A7020984CBB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>health area;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HDB540A5E8CC24CA9A6441A0A762F23DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text>type of research or development activity; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HB791A52403DC40C7B2A734806235C5AE"><enum>(C)</enum><text>appropriations account.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H4D914AA33AC543B7BB0DEB7077B0B897"><enum>(6)</enum><text>A description of relevant objectives and expected outcomes for the subsequent year.</text></paragraph></subsection></section><section id="HD8B18CC9D0784C0BA8359E95BE8E0EE8"><enum>9.</enum><header>Definitions</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">In this Act:</text><paragraph id="H5E2BAB99B5F74C9190D00A2CBA80C1D9"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Administrator</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Administrator</quote> means the Administrator for the United States Agency for International Development.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="HD2C74641BCA945FEAC4CF95DDB7D2D1D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Agency</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>Agency</quote> means the United States Agency for International Development.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H9964084B71C448C89A56DE151C3173DF"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Appropriate congressional committees</header><text>The term <quote>appropriate congressional committees</quote> means—</text><subparagraph id="H2F20A08FA98348F698FAC33E58ABC402"><enum>(A)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Affairs of the House of Representatives; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="HD44BFF788FEB498E9E141B07BE1820A3"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the Committee on Foreign Relations of the Senate.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H263D2C0FC89D412186EFB345CD12CBD1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Global health</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>global health</quote> includes efforts to combat and prepare for—</text><subparagraph id="H8A79FE1A83944C9BBB758B5869B7A322"><enum>(A)</enum><text>neglected tropical diseases;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1A6549C180CE410D87D814B6B7BDA832"><enum>(B)</enum><text>emerging infectious diseases;</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H4C8580B4B08646CB82F239A4242B9837"><enum>(C)</enum><text>antimicrobial resistance; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H1DC58B85A885410094D929C6CC6D40B8"><enum>(D)</enum><text>any other condition that may not be easily treated, diagnosed, or prevented in low-resource settings.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="HBCCD3E7BA8A54B9FAAD620EDA32542FB"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Global health research and development</header><text>The term <quote>global health research and development</quote> includes an activity, or the support for such an activity, related to research, development, testing, evaluation, deployment, or implementation of any new health technology.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="H849F25AB74434417894516CFF82843C3"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Health technology</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>health technology</quote>—</text><subparagraph id="H9CDF8574C209410C873A095AF35F34CB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means a vaccine, therapeutic, diagnostic, device, or other tool designed, modified, or adapted for use in low-resource settings to improve global health; and</text></subparagraph><subparagraph id="H24C3D07BF35E4DBFA87E4CD18C7FE2DF"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes personal protective equipment and insecticide so used.</text></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph id="H7B069AAB2C6C4FC39A55336D8CBA962A"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Low-resource setting</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <quote>low-resource setting</quote> means a location with limited or inconsistent access to running water, electricity, refrigeration, supply chains, lab services, medical equipment, trained health care personnel, or other resources important for global health.</text></paragraph></section></legis-body></bill> 

